Vertue betray'd : or, Anna Bullen. A tragedy. Acted at His Royal Highness the Duke's theatre. Written by John Banks .., . | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
Vertue betray'd : or, Anna Bullen. A tragedy. Acted at His Royal Highness the Duke's theatre. Written by John Banks .., .
Published
London :Printed for R. Bentley and M. Magnes, in Russel-Street in Covent-Garden.1692.
Rights
Public Domain, Google-digitized.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/osu.32435017631565

Table of Contents

    Front Cover
    Title Page
    Section 1 on page number 1
    Section 2 on page number 3
    Section 3

Book Text
Front Cover
Page Scan 1

Blank page
Page Scan 2

WS2 S-23S-2S2s2NS2'S2 SS-2S2XS2S25C2% --- ** - K T (The feast is $preab,33raú up a Jbair, ; § or Books are foot begomb coupart ## - = 2+= Elſº - 2: -

Page Scan 3

-, * - - - . . . . . - : * > º g - º * - * | - . . ſ º . * ; t § º * q * - ; : ** *- i. ſt ºf tº LIB RARY of the OHIO STATE UNIVERS ITY A 03238

Page Scan 4

Blank page

End of Front Cover. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Title Page
Page Scan 5

Vertue Betray'd: ANNABULLEN. ACTED at His Royal Highneſs - - THE t . - - D U KES Theatre. —— Written by 70 HN Banks, . . . Creſcit ſal Pondere Virtus. ~ º Lo ND6 N, Printed for R. Bentley, in Ruſſel street in Covent-Garden. tº- - - -

Page Scan 6

|-|-！ ）;*, ， ,*！},"… . . |-|- |-|- |- {|× -* |-*…º{|- →·|- - ae |- ·t---- • º-}·-！€- /*|-|- !----·~\·|- … " ~|- , ！（~）. . .‘ “ ’，” •• • •••••••••• •|- ·· · · -|- |-|-• · ~|×{, ，**|-• ***）· |-·1 |-|-|- , ！|*·… ►►***1-º-,·|- · , ！|-|-！* ！·· |-|- |- • ]！, |-|-|- · |- ----·· • ×|-*}|-*.* * |-***）|- - * · "… --- |-！”, |--_- -（）* - … ~~~~ ~~~~） • • - -！ … *· -· |-· * *|- - * -ae.|- ~|- |-！ ！ ·！|- ·· |-v |- |- |- |- } |-·|- · |-·----|- |-|• •|-- - ·**,|- · |-|- · ----|-|-----*|-· |- |--- |-ſ.~e • **|-••••• •|- ， ， ） – |-•* |- |-- |-|-|- |- |-·----|-* ***--（°|--- - - -（~~~~ |-|- ·----！»！|-！~~|-…"，！*|-|-« … ~~|- A·|-!·*|-|- |-·-- - -|-|- |-• •|-*----* · ----|-* |-|- ·|-· •|-|- - →|-*→ ·|-?|- |-**…-·· ----|- wº… **** º º… *· ·*** - *! |- |-|-- -------- |- |-|- |-|- · |-··*· · •|-·---- ·|- · |- -••,|-***-， * * ·|- ！ ±-”.|-ae~）;|-|-· |- … * *: ~~）.\， ,|- «.… - ~~|-|-- wae.··ae *!}~ ！* , |- - - -· ·…*·---- ·… *·|- |-|-^）. ***---- ！|-· · · · · ·…º.|- |-•*..*→ ·* -- ：）- -|- |- ·|- |---------~ ***+！• • •****·|- |×-------- |-|-|-----*- - - - ----*/ *· · ~•^. . .|- ·|-}~* …）» |-----* |-|- |- →|- |- · （, ， ， ， ,/?----Tºº （， ， ; **· • × ± •---- |-|- }*---- ·„… ***！|-··|-- |-|-|- |-|-·----|- |-•|- · -******， ,*-|- |-|-****|-|-·- ·• • •••|-* - |-|-|-* ！|-- -~* :|-- *• • • • • |- · ….… "|- |-！^|--- №|- · |- |-*----- |-|-* … *---- ----· }&ſ*, -- ··· *}. . .*|-· |- |-· |- |- - -|-· |-|- |- |- · |- |-！ |- ！|-}|-|×|-· · ·· ·|--' * *--）;×;.* ſ;* * * · • *{*******}·\，----·•·---- |-*---- -- .|- |-|- ， ，…º·· ··*•---- * ***• ·|-|- e|-|- *„…****- ： - - - |- |- …· ··|- · ·****…）- - |- ſae ， ſ.º ----- |-*|-? ！*…|-* |-• ^ • • • |' …«*·„* ·*|- |- ！ -º.. ，，，- - --->**…-------- ' .|-|-~~·· ---- - -|- |-|- …·（~~~~ * --·· ， , , , , ！·|-·****… *\ , ！**. • . {, ， !# !' '. , .; ： ！*---- - -|- ***,|-* * * * |-··|-|-|- |-|- · • .|- |- *---- -|- · „¢ £ © i****, , ， ， ， ， ，* *· · · · · · *----·#----|-< ***|- .* *· , ！+|------- … |-*…|-|-|- ---- ·|- …·！ -|- · ----** -->·* -· |-.* ----|-|- |-·~•,-----}*|- {;:*|-*·• |-|- - |-|- |-•••• |------|- ----}}.rº*·*• ·|- ::：:-：\*#• • • ** * **: -|- · --•*· ·<！--~~|-* <！*, ***· ----·*·---- *·------- ~~ ·|- ----• • • •» ----· |- . --|-|- - ----- |- |- …- º ！·*…， ， ， ， ，•|-|- &|- • •~~----*į„-s“|-|-: |--- ： *~^ |- *rººs; |- - - |-'~, ， ··… |- |-·***---- |-|- |-…** *· |-：::：：::::：:：：：ſæ~~~~ |-|- ·• ！!± ------|- |-|- w• ººre）,·••••----|- ... •· · ·- |- ， ！|×********* ----* · · · ·|×{~*----·****，* --> :-）.|- |-----|- |-·|- --****----*---- |-*----/ ****-- -- ·----*|-：|- *|- … -- *·***** |-----, ！， ,|-*|- …*..* *… … ----*· ·！ - ---- ---- ·|-t.* 4. （#|-|-·· |-∞-------- -- »|- |------|-*,º|- |- ： •|----- |-*… |-|--|-··---- ！ |- - ·-- --* „*… -- |- ---- |-• … ***** .*·---- > ----*· ••••••••••••••• ---- |-|-|- |- ----*|- |- ;· ：-…---- «- -·|-→ ·· -* #* .***→: '',·|- ----- * ----|- · * ---- *+ （|-*|- |-- - |-- - - *- （)|-.*· |-- -|----- ••• |- |-·|- #|-*.·ș |-…*…*…（~~~~|-|-* - ，----|- ~*|-|- *|-gº*№.**， …· · *** ***•••• ·~- - ·|-… + - ****** ， ！ 5|-*--------！ »|-·· |-|-****\ ------+ …****3*.*|-<！”，|- |-|-|-~ · ·* .- º •}·&|-**•-， |-|----- |- ！ -|- |-→ · |-••.*· º ,· |-*, ！---- · ----*·---- |-|- ! »|- |- |- * **， … |- ··|-|- ·|-*： - ***--- … *... ** |- __ -- ·|-; ： ！… （"… - |- |-|-}|-• ,…） º* *：,： ， ,· · · · -<！-, -： " ·`-|- *· ---- - ***|-|- · |-* ·|-|- *** •|- · - |-|- →|-|--* |- - - - - |- |-#|- ·|--！ |- - -·|-· ----· |- |- |- |- ---- ）*----！ 1|- -*|- |-|-！ - • |-----·|- |-· ----|-|- |- |- ſ \，， ，|- ſ.~ ~ ~ ~）\| – |-|- *~ L→ |- |-- *… ******* ·* · **! ~---- • • • • • • •|-` ~|- - |-|-----|-. -- |- · |-·** ----… … *|-• . |-. | |----- }: ！|-:- |- |- |- *|- |-- ） ·•*|-！！|-··| – |----- º • • • ----|- →·\,* |-|- ！-}|- |- |-\ ·· - ， ，|-{*- -----·|-··• *~*- ·→ ·|-|- * |- |-·^， ，~· |- |- \ |- | |-|- |- |- |- ||-|×_■ *----- – —−） |-



Page Scan 7

- - º Dutches of S OM ERSET. -- - º - * . . To the Illuſtrious Princeſ, LIZABETH w º ºv. *** * y MADAM, . . . . . . . . . . . . Aving met with Succeſ; in a Poem of this Nature, I was in: - couragd to proceed, and lay the Scene again in a country, ... that, perhaps, hath nºt been, nor is now inferior for #; z- em’d, it fonages to any part of the World; and if it is not ſº ". . has been thrºugh the dalmeſ of our #orians, ºr the figratitude or Deſigns of our Poets, who may think it an eafter courſ to write 7, the Improbable and Romantick Aëtions of Princes remote, both y diffance of Time and Place, than to be confind at home, where ev'ry School-Boy has a right to be a critick, and ev'ry Gentleman. an Intereſt to ſtand the Champion of his Family, ºff } raſh and inconſiderate Author. I ſay not this to derogate from thoſe excel. lent Perſons, who, fought to believe, have written more to pleaſe their Audiences, than themſelves; but to perſuade them, as Homer, and our Shakeſpear did, to Immortalize the Places where they were Born; and then, perhaps, I will fit down, and leave it to much li abler Pens. - - - - * ‘. . . . . * , When I was reſolvd to do my country this juſtice, where could 1 pitch upon an Hero more conſiderable, than out of Tour Grace's Family: What chronicle cou’d I conſult, that would have inform'd me ºf a Greater 2, ſhe very Crown it,ſ: oblig'd by ſº many gal- lant Supporters, wou'd have told me a iercy—Piercy whoſe Illuſtrious Name and Blood, having for a long Series of fears ran #: the Perſons of ſo many Earls of sºft, i; And if that ineffimable chain was almoſt broken, in the unfortunate Death. of your Father, it were rever enough to be {eplºd, had a #ich Treaſive and £ºyhal &ream fall, wertues lenhordini, º: s a Noble fº. 4ve &# Čº ºff...ºft. ſpring as many Princes more, and you'reſtore whii he had like to have loft. There is ſººnsh of Divinity and Wiſdom in: your choice, that none ºur theyţānighty ever did the like ; and that o, . was, when to the Sºiſſary Firſt of Men he gave a Wife, and with her, the World and Eedn for a Dower: England adores you for it; • * * * * * * f * * A. a: - the great ſočelin º -







Page Scan 8

- The DEDICATION. - - - -- - - * - *-* * * - * * * * * * - the Proteſtant Religion bleſſes you; the Saints above ſing loud yoar Pºiſe; and the Chief of all, young Edward, its great Eſtabliſher #º, jo ſº º: ; in i. Aº. This great Day % #. how douº has it made Me I Since this exalted Piece, which I deſign'd for a ºf Offerin may prºve : ... Lon: *::::::: º º: ſand Tears, e're envious Deat ſhall part you; for eºry Day of ſch Illuſtrious Lovers is more wºrth than whºl. Tears ºf ſºrdid-Life ºffſe. Buºy dº I ſºft that you ſhould ºft a thouſandºarms, and ºth iºniº gainſt Peº Bºkeries tº jº tº: tº happy is to ſee your incom: #º r, Ajd hºnºſed ºf Bejºy ſhe has to come, tºº. }}}/{th}} % º º e; but aliayi bloom: Tºu look as ºff you had noffinº Mortal in you; four Guardian. An % more a Deityºſanſhe ºright Planet that ſhird ºith ſuch amaz- - r - . - - eavens, than you on Earth. ..." \,\ , , , - *** yº - ei *** > •º * x - ...” " . * * - - *::::: º -- *When Y idºchºice of ſo, excellent a Sulješi, I was not to ſeek for a Dedication; I was commanded in it, even by the good Fite of the Play: For before what Patroheſ, ſhou'd I kneel, but Her, the charaćier of phoſé great Anceſtor was the chiefeſt Stroak and Linea- ment that made it # table to the World? And it is as much your Grace's due, as Firſt-Fruits are to Monarchs. For Anna Bullen, - º drew her in all the miceſ. Ideas that ever my Pen or Fancy be capable of; yet, I confeſs, ſhe comes ſhort ºf the Excellency of your real Perfeitions; and though her Merits rais'd her to a crown, and ſhe was Queen, her Portunes were leſ, Miraculous than yours. For Heav'n, without a Diadem; never ſhowr’d down ſo many admi- * * * * ~ 1. a --~~ ". . . ; };" 2. * * * : * * * * • sº - r * ---…- : *- : - rable Bleſſings of Kirtue, Beaut , Birth, Wit, and Fortune, upon tº: is * . . . º, i. ‘. with that, and in any One ºf yºur Sex before... I dare no further attempt their De- ſcription # ny Ignorance, left"I ſpeak too. Meanly or irreverently of 'em ; *:::::::::::::: #; Subjeti to ſome more Glorious. Pen *}. ºf a Cºlº º. write of you: My mean ſtile has nº otherórnament than Truth; and * -- a tº a 2 - - - % #miliº return Thanks for your moff Gra- ;#####. ºr a h tº . º an it given a more s'to the Author, who is, Madam, --- #: af your Birth, makes not more gloriºus Figure in the ** º ... * * * ... * * * * : -, - * * *******2 ºt, . É. **** * * *** ***** * vºº, º º ºrºwººnikºwº , º, º sº *** **t, * *** *** \,\, \sus vºwtºbeſientiºw tº ºn vº ºf \º ºt, a sº sº sº. \mºtºvºlta Sºvanº gº tºº ...º . * | &; : ... . - - * ~ * - - --- -- - -- ºr - *** - - - *** **, ºvºi, pasſ; # wºrk, t, tº ºf sº, ºr nk. -, *, *, *. * - - . • J. Ban S. - ... * * * - -, * e. A







Page Scan 9

P RO LOG UE Spoken to Anna Bullen, written by a Perſon of Quality. - Tº all Impartial judges in the Pit, ... . . . . . *: . . . . - And ev'ry beauteous Patroneſ; oftāfi; ; ; ; ; , , * † I'm ſent to plead the Poets cauſe, andſay, - - Af # - ſº tºlander in his mod:#fff; ) → * He brings before your Eyes a modern Story, Tet meddles not with either Whig, or Tory. swº . . . . " Was’t nºt enough, vain Men of either ſide, º yº . . . Zvo Roſes once the Nation did dividé? - -- But mºſt it be in danger, now agen, ºxº Betwixt our Scarlet, and Green-Ribbon Men? Who made this diff'rence, were not England's Friends; º' Be not their Zools to ſerve their Plotting End. º º * - Damn the State-Fop, who here his 2eal %. Andore the Stage, like our ill Geniuſ, hovers: . { • * * give ºf a Pit of Drunkard, and of Lºvers, S Good Sanguine Men, who mind no State. 4ffair, - But bid a baſe World of it ſelf take Care, i. * . . . We hope there lives not ſo abhorr'd a 7.hing, . . . . £at ºver his Country, and wou'd ſerve bis fing, s , ; ; ; ; But in your Parties, why ſhould we engage, Or meddle with the Plots of a mad Age P : . . . ." § ... : * . We loſe enough by thoſe upon the Stage. -- ~. Sº Welcome Mark-Teazer, Páeviſ, Gamſter, Huffer; 4'l Fools, but Politicians, we can ſuffer ; tr 4 Gºd's name, let each keep to his Pocation; º Our Trade is to mend Tou, and not the Nation, – Beſides, our Author has this further End, - - Tis not enough if but One side's his rºad ; § - - Jºže needs you. All, bis weakneſ; to defends.” rº ** to obligº you tºº, hopes he has ſhown . * - . Nº Country has Men braver than your own. , - His Herº's all to England are coff,'a," - – ’ 7° yºu,” Fathers (ſure) you will be kind. – - - He brings no Foreigners tº move yºur Pity, . . . . But ſend them to a jury of the city.’”. 8. * - *** , , º, . " – Perſons
Page Scan 10

- Northumberland. Piery. . . . Rothfra - Anna Bullen. - Diana Talbot. - Lady Eliz. Blunt. Toung Princeſ; Elizabet - . - - w - Ladies, Gentlemen, Attendants, an - - - - - * - - -- - - ---- - - - - - . . PE R - - º- - - - - **. Cardinal. - - - - - - - - * - - | - . - - - - - - - - \ ... N, - - + º -º- - - -- - - - º …’ - - -- ** - * - - - * - r:- -, * -- ,º º - * - - r - º - *** * - ~ 3. - - w - - - - - w J - º _ - - - ~~~ - * - - - : - - - - - - s, * . . w - w - s º - - - - * - - - - ſ - - - - . -- - - *: - - - - - t - -- - - - -







Page 1

- - * - * * - - - - - - º $ * , -- \ . . /* , - . . '- - s' * º - & a F. . . . . . . - o R, Anna Bullen. A c T 1 s c E N E L – ent, Northumberland". Rodfºrd North, is is the Day ſhall Crown your Paºntºniſhes. - . And long expettinghops: The king intends To F. reight his Marriage with your Siſter, - And make her known by th’Title of his Queens The reaſon why it was ſo longkept ſºººº... - , -º - was our great cardinai's Delays, and Tºškº of r., which Harry has with frowns diſcover'd : But ſince, in ſpite of Wºolſ, and the Sonclav, - . . . By Reverend Cranmer has the cauſe been try’d; And ºtherine is this day proclaim'd divºrºd. . . . . j. Haºn be my witneſs, brave Northumber” It joys not me, but that it is hi: Pleaſure, . . . . . . . . º, whoſe happineſs we all are bound to pray for; . . . . . º And may my Siſter's Crown ſit lighter on ... . . . . . ... . . . Her grºw, than does the Honour upºn mine : . . . . . * S v something of boding whiſpers to my ºl. º And telline, Oh! this Marriage will be fatal- . . . . Methinks I ſee a sword ty'd to a Thread, Small as a hair, hang o'er our Pºgºant Greatneſs: . . . . Believeme, friend. Thrones are ſºvºreſ: Touch-ſtones; . . . . . Ai, ii. the Emblem of their Guard, the Lyon, All but of Royal Blood they will deſtrºy... ... . . . . "N. Mºori, this is ſevere to all that love you ... And you reflect unkindly on your Fortunº, * Triº. Fortuneſ whyºſhihy hºlº on her . . . . . A load, I ſay, to quiet Mindsºr-ſhºſhould nº Hiſ . . . *, *, *. wº N. - W -

Page 2

- - : as * 5 2. - V E R T Z/E Betray'd: 0r, ... Have caſt it upon one that was ambitious : . . M} Lord, it had been kindly dane of Fortune, " : Thaye ſeen my Siſter wedded to her Vows; *-*. Your 'º'; and nöt at one * hade her." #. Both Cruel to the Queen, and Falſe tº him: `- North. You know, my Lord, we all are Witneſks. That ſate upon her like a heavy Armour * * * *-* On a Child’s back; ſhe º: Weight. Koch. Oh! may it not be fatal to us, Heav'n' For at the very time ſhe gave her Hand To th” eager King to faſten’t with a Pledge, The Ring fell off, and could no more be found. . . ; & * -º North. Meer Chance, my Lord. *-*... . . ; Roch. And then immediately, : - When the glad Ceremonies were perform’d, “…---- The amorous King bending to Kiſs, her Hand, O A ſhower of Pearls broke paſſage from her Eyes, ' '. And all-bedev'd his Head with ominous Tears. - - North. The common uſe of every baſhful Bride. . . . . Roch. What will ſhe do when ſhe ſhall underſtand Our foul Deſigns, and Piercy's Innocence ; ; ; ; ; ; ; H- ..º.º. His Letters to her that you intercepted, go ºf And counterfeited others to deceive her,' & 'ſº #. To make her once believe that he was marry'd? - - - But what a mortal Grief will ſeize your Son, . . . . . . . . When he ſhall find his Miſtreſs was betray’d; tº . . . . . . . And forc’d to marry one ſhe cannot love? * , º, . . . . . . North. To prevent that: Soon as he's come to Court; . juſt but to ſee ſhe's marry’d, and no more, º ºxº, (Not giving him the time for ſecond thoughts) . . . . . I’ll make a Match between him and the Heireſs, tº Of Shrewsbury. • *- : " . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - w .* - Roch. A very gallant Lady. It º º . . As Virtuous, Beautiful, and Richer får ºr " - i – , , , , Than all our Generation of that Sex. "º", ºr Brings her this day on purpoſe from the Country: But the Queen thinks already they are marry’d. . . . . º Roch. And are you ſure to gain your Sen's conſent, . . . . . . To what he has been ſtill ſo obſtinate ºf . . . . . . Will make him raſhly change to any ſtate; ºr icº ſº. ... : And, thinking to be miſerable, will plunge 2 ºr . . . . • * * * Into the dreadful Sea of Matrimony;… a ... ſºu º º, ºn tº And make himſelf; The happieſt man that *- `- ** - * --- r - - - - - , * . . . . n tº * . . . ; it. “ North, You wrong your ſelf to flatter me. Her Father, : ºf . , i.e. . North, Rage and Deſpair, when he ſhall find her falſe, though much againſt his Will, a -lºnoa º §::::::::::" isiuſ on tº i tº 4, \f-- • ** with what remorſe ſhe took the Regal Burthen, f : - “;" * : *. * : - ; º' * * * * * * * * * * * tº ºr º “... . . - - * * * * ‘. . . " # * - * - - .."--- **** ~ - Enter

Page 3

; > ANNA BULLEN. 3 s As if the World’s four Winds were pent within º Enter cardinal Woolſey mnſing. Behold the proud imperious Cardinal, with ſuch a furious Tempeſt on his Brow, His bluſtering Carkaſs. He has heard the News, And comes to argue with his Friend the Devil, The Reaſon of his No-lntelligence. Roch. The Popedom now, and all the Wealth in Rome, Can ſcarcely recompence him for the fright . . - This News has put him in-See how he ſtaggers, Giddy with th’ height his Pride has rais'd him to. *Tis then moſt fatal to unhappy England , … When ſuch Church Blazing-Stars appear in it. [Ex, North, and Roth. * . card. Marry'd in private, and declar'd his queen! N - Katherine divorc'd, and Anna Bullen marry'd] . Now, by our Holy Father’s Triple-Grown It muſt not, cannot, nay, it ſhall not be. . . . . . . Where was your aid, that time, you ſlothful Saints, You whom falſe Zeal created in more numbers - - Thane're the Heathen made and worſhipp'd Gods? A Lutheran Queen upon the Throne of England l . - w She to lye in the Boſom of our Prince . . . . . . . . A Buxom King, that for a wanton Smile ºf . . . . . . . Will pawn his Faith, and turn an Heretick! . . . . - Enter the Lady Elizabeth Blunt. ºr nium. Awake thou wretched dreaming Prieſ, lookupi Can you behold your proud Saint Peter ſhake? . . . . . The mighty Pillar of that ſpreading Church.… . . . . . . . . . That holds the great Religion of the World … . . . . . . ; To ſtagger, and beſtow no help, no aid . . . . . . . . . From mighty Woolſey's Shoulders to ſupport it P ". . . . Is this the great King-Cardinal, who late . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . From ſmalleſt Root began to ſhade the Land, . . . . And ſtood the talleſt Cedar of the Church? … . . . . . . Shame to thy Prieſt-hood, and thy Scarlet Robe, … . . . . . . . Ev’n thou to whom the liberal See of Rome . . . . . . . . . . . . . Has given all, next giving of her ſelf: ... s. . . . . . . . . . unworthy Servant of ſo kind a Miſtreſs: ... . . . . . . . . . card. What does the Faireſt meanſ . . . . . . . . . . . . Blunt. Ha! muſt I teach thee fºg. . . . . . . . . . . . . tº: Art thou the Thing that from ; Chaff of Matkind, sº .. , is C From the baſe ſcurrilous Rubbi • of the World, ... . . . . . . . ... ºn A Firſt found thy ſelf a way to thrive by Wit? - Then edging it with ſharpeſt Villanies,
Page 4

* The News not ſtirs your Wonder . Hell and Furies' - 4. V E R / O E. Betray d: Or, - - - Mow’d thee a paſſage to thy Princes Breaſt, - And cut down all the Virtuous from his ſight, . v Who choſe thee for the Champion of his Vices; Whilſt thou with labour let looſe all their Sluces, And pour’d them like a Torrent in his Boſom * This you did once confeſs to me, and more, When you declar'd how hot you were in Love * - Bullen is Queen, the Crown you promis'd me - º Now wreaths her Head Are theſe the hopes you gave me, When once you ſaid my Son ſhould be a King - Card. What wou'd you I ſhould do to ſerve you? > Blunt. Forgive me, tender Woolſey, pious Cardinal - Shall I then teach your Scarlet Prieſthood Blood? . I would have done as Alexander did, “ . . . The Sixth, and the moſt merciful ſo nam'd : . . . Are there no Conſecrated Weapons left? . . . . . . . . Or have you loſt the Power to make 'em ſo? . . . . Give me Saint Dagger or Saint Poiſon ſtraight, And I will do that Meritorious Aët: . . . . . . . . . . . " Diſpatch her ſtreight to Hell, from whence ſhe fetch'd . Thoſe Looks that robb'd me of the King and Crown. . . Cara. Have patience, Madam... . . . . . . . . . . Blunt, Preach it to the Damn'd, º 'º To thoſe that feel the Rack or Inquiſition— . . . * Curſe on your Gown Apologies: but more º 'º " Be curſt the time of Bullen's fatal Birth, º 'º'; -ºº º Wrinkles like Age anticipate her Youth; - - Mildews and Blaſts devour her wanton Beauties, Small-Pox and Leproſies rough-caſt her o're; Dig up her Charms and Features by the Roots, And bury 'em in Pits as deep as Graves. . . . . . . . . _Card. Study ſome Aét that may revenge this Fury, This hurts no more than Barks of Coward Curs; * * * . . She lives, and is as beautiful as ever: º, . . . . . . . . Be rul’d by me, who like a dreadful Piece, - Am ſure to kill, where-e’re I take my Aim, “ . . . . Before they hear the Noiſe or ſee the Flame. . . . . . . . . Blant. Oh tell me how to quench this Fire within'! ”, -- - That burns me up with thoughtful Injury. . * : * ~ * * * - * - - - ... nº Card. An eaſie way I’le chalk to your Revenge, … " . . . . . . A Road not ſteep, nor dangerous, but ſmooth; ' ' ' ' ' So unſuſpeded, and ſo fatal too, , . . . . . . . . That the Queens Fancy and deluded Genius; º' . . . Shall tempt her in the ſame diſſembled Path; ; ; ; ; …} =:: * : Taking her by the other hand with us, ... º.º.º. And lead her in the Pit prepard for her. " º _* * * * * * * - 5, Ağı" . . . . - * * * '--- . . . . J. : . . . . . . . . . . . ~ * * * * * * ºn 1 º' . . . . . … - , , , . . . . . . . . . Blunt, - - - ~ . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - - l
Page 5

A N N A BU L L E N. Blunt. Go on my Woolſey, Charming as the young, And more melodious than a Quire of Angels. - - Card. This then it is: The King you know’s inconſtant, As jealous and as teaſty as old Age, So covetous of the pleaſure he poſſeſſes, That he who does but look upon’t muſt dye, With her, whoſe innocent Charms did force him toºl. Blant. But how ſhall we be backt with a pretence card. 'Tis eaſie to give fire to that fond Breaſt That is already charg’d with jealous Sulphur : . The Queen loves Piercy, that may be a means; And Spies may be laid every where to watch Their Private Meetings, and their very looks, And then acquaint the Hot-brain’d King with it: So ſtreight their joyful Deſtinies are ſeal’d. . . . Blunt. Moſt admirable! . . . Card. If we fail in this, - Some cry’d-up Beauty, ne’re yet ſeen at Court, Muſt be found out, to put her in his way, And take the Amorous King: 'Twill certain do; For then no greedy Falcon, when he ſees the Lure, - Will flye down ſwifter to be catch'd and hooded, Than he into the Fetters of her Charms. Blunt. O come to my Embrace, thou Godlike Prieſt Balm to my wounded and my tortur’d Boſom. Card. Go ſtreight, and haſte about the Intelligence. Blunt. I will. Good Fortune has been ſo propitious, To make young Rochford, Anna Bullen's Brother, - Enamour’d of my Beauty; him I’le mould, Sound ev’ry thought of his unguarded Soul, Linking him cloſe in amorous Intrigues, *Till 1 have diſcover'd from him our Deſign Of Piercy’s Love, and of his Siſters Condućt. Card. An Accident, the luckieſt that could º !. s,'— Behold the Queen in her firſt State and Greatne But yet ſhe bears it with no welcome meen: Piercy hangs heavy on her Heart, and in her Eyes; It works, it manages as we would have it : And in her heedleſs Innocence ſhe ſails, Shunning no Rocks, no Quick-ſands, nor no Danger, But runs into her Ruine faſter than We wiſh. - Blunt. Her Crown is hideous to my ſight, - - - Its Jewels fatal as the Eyes of Baſilisks: - O Cardinall This Rival-Queen and I . . . That weigh all Morials even and alike. ... *- : - B 2 Should never meet but in the Scales of Death, - º sº . • *, * > . .
Page 6

For I receive 'em with as little joy, As a ſuſpicion of its Faith to you. . . . . . . . . . º 6 W E R Tºy E. Betray'd: or, Queen Anne appears ſtated upon a Throne. Northumberland, Rochford, Lords, Ladies, Attendants and Guard, about her. - - - : º – Omnes. Long live King Henry, and Queen Anne of England. ' North. Immortal live Great Queen of England, France, 4 And Ireland, and for ever rule the Heart - * Of Conquering Henry, as he Reigns o're us And all his faithful Subjećts— I ſpeak it as the Wiſhes and the Wolte' Of your moſt Loyal Kingdoms; to confirm it, Sound ſtraight your loudeſt Inſtruments of Joy, And ſhout as I do, all that Love their Queen. Queen riſes from her Throne, [Shout, and Trumpets within. Queen. Theſe Sounds might lift another to the Heav'ns ! But what is Muſick to the Ear that’s deaf; - Gr Crowns and Scepters to a dying Wretch?: . Deſpair turns all alike that comes to me, Blind to the Pomp that gladsall Eyes but mine, - Deaf to its Charms, and dead to all its Glories. : . - [Trumpets and Shouts again. Ceaſe you more empty Flatterers than Winds; - * Be ſilent as the Sorrows in my Breaſt: If you will give me eaſe, forbear ſuch Flatteries: As ev’n thoſe ſilly Wretches utter them, . . . . . . . Having no other Reaſon but vile Cuſtom. . . . . . . . My Noble Lords! * * - ') º: - I know you all are Loyal to the King, , , -- And for his ſake you are thus kind to me; • , º, ; But for the Rabble, who can read that Sphinx? Their very Breath that now Proclaims, with joy, - . . . . . . . Sad Katherine to be no longer Queen, . . . . sº ...And my unwelcome Coronation, gº º * . . . Would the ſame moment, ſhould my Stars permit, " … Shout louder at the Sentence of my Death. - # Card. Moſt gloriqus and beloved ef England's Queens #3 O lay not on our Nation ſuch a Curſe, - I dare be bold, and ſay it as a Prieſt, As Confeſſour to all my Country’s Guilt, ... . . . …; There's none, how mean ſoever with my ſelf, . . . . . . . . ; But loves you more than life, or darling Riches, . . Wiſhing to feel ſevereſt Penance here, - . . . . . . .” - And Hell hereafter, rather than behold tº . . . . . . . . You leſs a Queen, or leſs ador?d than now. " - - * . . . . . . Queen. They have my thanks, next kind good natur'd Wºofty;..... . . * - - --. … -



Page 7

A N N A BUL LEN. 7 Who cannot but be real, 'cauſe he ſays it. . . . . . . . . Card, Oh that your Majeſty would think ſo ever, . . . . . . . And that my proud endeavours, with ſucceſs, “. . . . . . . . w Firſt whiſper'd in the Boſom of the King . . . . . . . . . . . The ſecret Wonders of your Mind and Perſon, º' And made him ſoon diſcover all your Beauties, Thoſe rare Perfections, that above your Sex. Have merited his Paſſion and his Crown.” . . . . - Queen. O Reverend, pious, beſt of Cardinals tº Who too well knows . . . . . . . . - " - By whoſe high hand I climb'd this malic'd Greatneſs, "sº º And wear this envy’d Crown. Card, May Heav'n and Stars . . . . . . s Pour their juſt hatred on— 3 -, *, *, - Queen. Ceaſe Execrations: . . . . . . . . -- For ſhould they come to paſs, as Heav'n forbid, . . . . . . What wou'd the miſerable Nation do? . . . . . * - 1 Beſides 'twere pity to the King and me, . . . . . - That we ſhould loſe ſo exquiſite a Head, - And ſuch a Prelate ſhoutd. be damn?d ſo ſoon. . . . . . . . Card. Ten thouſand Saints, more than my Royal Maſter, . . . T Are Witneſſes to th’ #: what I ſay. b . a - ls . . . . . . . ueen. As many Saints and Myriads of bright Angels . . . . . . . . . cº of the sº Soul, rig are: That canker'd firſt the Conſcience of thy Maſter, , . . . . . Miſleading him with hopes to purge a ſin, ". . . . . . . . To act the worſt, ev’n a Religious Guilt— . . . . . . . . . . * . . . . . . ." > card. The wiſe and juſt Omnipotence—", - ueen. No more : . . . . . . . . . . . . . Hell's not ſo full of Torments, as thy Seal, '' . . . . . , Has Blaſphemies to be rewarded in it—º , give me ſome eaſe, juſt Heav'n" if there beany—º . - * My Lords! if there's no more for you to at . . . . " ** To perfeót or unmake this Ceremony, . . . . . . . . . . (Oh that it cou’d be done!) retire a while, " " , "º And leave me with my Women for ſome Moment What am I then a Priſoner to be guarded? ~ Has then a Throne coſt meſo dear a Price, sº *--- º - - - . * -º, tº . * * *. - \ - As forfeit of my Liberty of Thinking? . . . . . Do Princes barter for their Crowns their Freedoms?’ - * * * Good Heav'n' not think?"nor pray if I have need— . If I am Queen, why am I not obey'd? º . . . . . . . . . . . . . t Card. We'll all perſorm your Majeſties Command. - 6 - gºin. Am I got looſe, looſe from this worryingScene of diſmal State, that always loads a Monarch, And racks him with diſſembling Tortures?: . . . . - - o wretched
Page Scan 18

ºr (ſhe feast is S-2S2-S-2:S^S2^S2 SZSZ-S2S25.2% spread. 33raw up a (Jbair, i - - º - ºsiº Nº-S º Hºs --- -- E 5: 5:... ºn tº intº it mes 39. 3. §mitt, - - S-2S2S2'S 25.2S2'S 2S | - t º }; - % 3|a













Page Scan 19

Ø\ - UNIVERSITY LIBRARY Of the OHIO STATE WTO32:38

Page Scan 20

- - - - - - ---- - - ------ ~~~~ ----+----
Page Scan 21

Vertue Betrayd: ANNABULLEN. TRAGEDY. ACTED at His Royal Highneſs D U KES Theatre. - - Twº º 77-7 wº, Y. - -- Creſcit ſai Poure Virtu. ~ : Printed for R. Bently, in Rºſal street in Covent-Garden. MDCXCII.

Page Scan 22

- - - -, - º - - - * - rº * - + - - - - • * * , - - ----- º - - - º - - . . . * * ~, º .# + -- - - - - - - - - ºrº º * - * 3. * * * : * * * * *...* : * : * : * º - - º - - - * * - k - - * *-> --- - - * * - - - º - - - - * --- º - - - º *- - -- -- - -- -- - * -,-- - * * ***** ------------ -- ------ ***** --------- - - --- - - --- - - a . - - - - -- -- ~! - ** * , - - -- º - +- - . * - º vº º --- * - - - * - -- º - - - - - - - -----, * * * * * *- * * * * * > . - - - - ~ - i = - * , w: *3 , i .* ** - ***". - * * * * - - - - - - - - * **** * ** --- * * * * -- , * * * - `-- * -- - *. - - - w - - - - º -------------------- **** - - - ------------ --------. - - --------------- *-**** -------- --- - * - - - - - \ - - " - - A r - - - * - - - - - - - - ** º - - ~ -: - * * - - - - - - * * * * > . . . . . --> - - - - * - - - - - - r - - - - - - - - * - * - ... • ** * * - - , - - -- - - - -,- r - -- - - - -- - - - - ‘. ...º-** **, *, * : ***** *...*.*.* ſii Nº. ºf , . . . . . . . . . ; º, # *** * - *.* ** * … -- *…* ** * → º * * * V. ** * * * - ** - - * ---. - - - - - *.* ------ - - **- - - ~ . - - T - - -- - - - - . w ii 2 }{{ ; º - - º * }. -** - * 4. - - - - tº ~ -- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - *> * -- -- - --- º - - º , , - * * *- - - * , - " - - - - - - - -- - t - - - - . - - - ------ - - - º - ** - º -- ** -: - - - - *- - - - - - - - - - - - - -- -- - - * x . . ** - -- º - - - , - º -- - - - - - - - - º - -- - - - -- * - -- - - - * - - - -- * - - - - - - - - z \ - - * - -- - - º - - w º -- - - *: º - \ - - - * - - - s - - / - - - --- - --- - - - - --- - --- --- --> ºf .. # 3. *::= ºr º -- -- - : -- - #. - º - - --- f - - - *- *** i - - -- -- --- - - - º * - - +. - -" -- * - - "… : - * - - : - ! --> - - * 2: . * - t .* - - * * * -- * --- : , ; ; ; - * --- -- -- - º r --- : º-a * - " - - - - - * --" - - º'- º - - -- º - - - - º - - - .* - - - --, - - -- º - - --- - - r *-* * * - - * -- " - - --- * -a- * *, * ** - sº - . -- *. - * ---- * - - - - - - - - - w - - - - - * - * T - -- - - - / t - - * * - - - } - - - -- - - - - - - -- - - - - - - - - - - -- - ** --- ** - - - -- - tº -- - * * -- º; ºf **- - º - - --- " . .** --- . - : - - * -- - - - -, * - - - - - * * - - - - .# - 3. - º -- -- - - - - * - ---- º - - - - -: * - … • - º #. - “. - -, *. - - - - -- sº - -- * . - - - - - - -- - - - - - ** - - - -- - - - - * - --- -- --- ---- * - -----> * .*. - - - - - / • - - --- -- *** - - - -- . " - - • * - - - - - - - - º - - . . - h - - - - - - - -- - - - ----- * -- - --> --- - *- -- - --- - - - / - - - - * - - - - - - - - - - - - - - * -ºr- - - - --- - - - - *:: *: * - - º - - * - - - .* º - - - - - - - - * * - - - - - - * º . *, * : * * * * * *- : - - * *** * * * --" - --- * - - * * - f . . - * , : º º: *: * - - - s - * t º -- - -- #. .* - --- º * * -- -- * . -- - * * * - - º - - - - & - º - -- - - - * * º w. - * * - *..., -* * * . . - - * , º - - - - - - -- - - - - -- --- * * - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - w - - \ ** - * - - - - - - \ - - - - - - - - - - - - - - **** - - - - * : } * # -- - * --> --- * - - - - * * * - - *-*- e- - - *- - - - - * - - - - - - * - - # * *- : - \ . -----, - 'º- - -- - - -- * - ----- - - - - - - -- ºr . • - ---, * : … - re- º *: - - - - - * - *- --- - --- 2. - --- --- - --- - r - º - ſ - - - -- - --- - - - - - - - - - -—e - * * * ------- º º º - - . . fº . . --> *: < . . n - - -- - - - - - - - - - - -- ---, * -: - ----> * * - - - - - -- - - º .*. * - - - - -- - - - - - * - ºf * - - `-- - º - -- -- --- - - *: - - * - - -- -- - - - - - - ** - - - - º ºr - - - - - º -º- - - ------- –4 - - ----------- ------ ------ ------------- -- ------------------------------ --- ***** ------------



Page Scan 23

- - To the Illuſtrious Princes * - MAD AM, * - - - - - - - -- - - Aving met with Succeſs in a Poem of this Nature, I was in: couragd to proceed, and lay the Scene again in a country, - that, perhaps, hath nºt been, nor is now inferior for Heroick Per. fonages to any part of the World; and if it is not ſº el tem’d, it º: through the dulneſs of or fiftºn, ºr the Ingratitude ELIZABETH, Dutcheſs of SOMERSET. or Deſigns of our Poets, who may think it an eafter tourſe to write of the Improbable and Romantick Aëtions of Princes remote, both by diffance of Time and Place, than to be confind at home, where ev'ry School-Boy has a right to be a critick, and ev'ry Gentleman. an Interºff to ſtand the Champion of his Family, againſ; a raſh and inconſiderate Author. I ſay not this to derogate from thoſe excel. lent Perſons, who, fought to believe, have written more to pleaſe their Audiences, than themſelves; but to perſivade them, as Homer, and our Shakeſpear did, to Immortalize the Places where they were Born; and then, perhaps, I will fit down, and leave it to much abler Pens. - - * . . . . . . . . . When I was reſolvd to do my country this juſtice, where cou’d I pitch upon an Hero more conſiderable, than out of Tour Grace's Family: What chronicle cou’d T conſult, that would have inform'd me ºf a Greater 2, 1.he very Crown it {{ oblig'd by ſº many gal- iant Supporters, wou'd have told me a iercy—Piercy whoſe I/affrious Name and Blood, having for a long Series of fears ran #: the Perſons of ſo many ###. Kºjić'. And# that ineffinale chain was almoſt broken, in the unfºrtunate Death. of your Father, it were rever enough to be ºpſ. 3. º got the Rich Treſºre and Cºal &ream diſlºyees Fred:#ffºrt Blendaid Pertues lenhordini º, which (nºjºkºvº. ābhiited to take a Noble Partner, as Angels have & º: verſe with % may prove the ſecond and more lifting Fountain, from whence ſhall ſpring as many Princes more, and you reſtore whii he Great Jocelin had like to have loft. There is ſº ºwth of Divinity and Wiſdom in: your choice, that none ºur theyţāºrighty ever did the like ; and that was, when to the Sºiſſary firſt of Men he gave a Wife, and with: --- flie. ºn whence ſha f º her, the World and Eedn for a Dower: England adores you for it; - .* : f : * A. a. -

Page Scan 24

º * * * º ºff. The DE DI CA T IO N. the Proteſtant Religion ble es you ; the Sints above fing loudyoar ź. and the chief ºf all, young Edward, its great Aſtabliſher, - Joaks down with joy tº ſee his happy Succeſſor lye in your Arms. This great Day | #. how º %. ſº Me! Since this exalted Piece, whichº 'd for #ſºft may prºve : amidmº! Lon: *:::::: }}#}}º a º: ſand Tears, e're envious Deat ſhal' part you; for eºry Day of ſich Illuſtrious Lovers is more wºrth than whole T.ears ºffraid. Life ºftde. Buºy dº Iſºpoſe that you ſhould everº # a thouſand§: and ſºuth impregnable againſt Death, Bºkeries - º Rºßhappy is tº ſee your incom: this many. º * -- * ---- - º, Aſh hºnºſed ºf Bejºy ſhe has to come, ºil. hink that yºutlºfide, but allºy; ſloom: Tu look as ºf you had nºthing Mortal. in you; four Guardian. An elſ…ircely is more a Deity iñº and #. Bright Planet that ſhird § amaz- ing ſiſtence at your Birth, make not a more gloriousfigure in the Feavens, f anyon on Earth. * yº sº *** º -- º º . - , , º *** "When midéºthpies of ſo excelºt a Sulješl. I was not to ſeek for a Dedication; T was commanded to it, even by the good Fite of The Play: For before what Patroneſ ſhou'd I kneel, but Her, the charaćier of phoſé § Anceſtor was the chiefeſt Stroak and Linea- write'ſ yºu;, º; ºff. with that, anã in all #milit ment that made it acceptable to the World? And it is as much your Grace's due, as Firſt-Fruits are to Monarchs. For Anna Bullen, though I drew her in all the niceſ: Ideas that ever my Pen or Fancy º be capable of; yet, I confeſs, ſhe comes ſhort of the Excellency ofyour real Perfeitions; and though her Merit; rais'd her to a crown, and ſhe was Queen, her fortunes were leſ, Miraculous than yours. For Heav'n, without a Diadem; never ſhowr’d down ſo manty admi- rail Blºft.gºfºriºuſy, Birth, Wii, and Fortuñº, upon any One of#. Sex before..." dare no further attempt their De- º:#;..... of 'em ; *::::: r §: hty sº more Glorious" Pen º but a º or º: of Lauréats, ought to write of: ..". .* lé has nº other Gr o ºf return Thanks for your moff Gra- cious Acceptance ºff poor a ſºle; which has ſtarce given a more tº Liftº: lay, than it has to the Author, who is, Madam, º sº; sº sº, º ºsºvº º 'º *...* º ºsº ºwn (ºrae's mºnikºvº º Aº, sº as sº º – ***** : *** ***, *, ºftopsitti sãº tº sº, wº ~ ºf ºwn ºn sº º sº \mſtºwed savam, is a tº º **** **.*, basſgºi, zwºi i. º. ººg sº, º I. Bank.” * * * • A nament than Truth; and . ” – ><-- -

Page Scan 25

* º s PROLOGUE §. 24mill, written by a Perſon of Quality. ' Tº all Impartial judges in the Pit, , , , "º, º - And ev'ry beauteous Patroneſ; oftāfi; " ", , .# * I'm ſent to plead the Poets cauſe, and ſay, Af # . There's not ºne Sander in his modeft Play, ' , * * He brings before your Eyes a modern story, i Tet meddles not with either Whig, or Tory. . . . . . . . . 2, Was't not enough. vain Men of ºther ſº. A \º Was't nºt enough, vain Men of ither ſide, º, . . . Zwo Roſes once the Nation did dividé? . . . . . . . .” - But muſt it be in danger app. agen, . - - ºn Betwixt our Scarlet, and Green-Ribbon Men? - Be not their Zools to ſerve their plot; Ends. " º- Paºlº the State-Pºp, who here his 2eal diſcover, 2 And o're the Stage, like our ill Geniuſ, hovers: . . { give us a Pit of Drunkard, and of Lovers; - * * * * ~ Good Sanguine Men, who mind no State Affair, --> We hope there lives not ſo abhorr'd a 7.hing, - ------- - - - £ut lºves his Country, and wou'd ferve his fing, s , ; ; ; ; ; - But in your Parties, why ſhould we engage, - - - But bid a baſe World of it ſelf take care.” - - t We loſe enough by thoſe upon the Stage. --> - S - Welcome Maik-Teazer, Peeviſh Gamſter, Huffer; 4'l Fools, but Politicians, we can Juffer ; . 4.9% ºlet eaſh keep to his fºcatiºn; *…) ºs Or meddle with the Plots of a mad.Age P : . . . . . S º º * - s 24. Trade is to mend Tou, and notºrbºn ºn , " " ' " --~~ Beſides, our Author has this further End, Złº not enough if but One side's his rºad ; § - - He needs, you. All, his weakneſ; to defends.” S rºº And to oblige you tºt, hopes? has ſhown #: No cº, Men 3. than year own. … ." His Hero's all to England 4fe conſin'd; - - 7° yºu,” Fathers (ſure) you will be kind. #######jº, ity, But ſend them to a jury of tº .**** , , * : *- : * , - Perſons x 2- . . . z Who made this diff'rence, were not England's Friends; ºn c. . . v * - *::::: --"
Page Scan 26

Northumberland. --- º, - - - - t - - w - s -- - - w -* f - - -. - - - * . - - - - - - Fº - - - - - - - - - t º - ". * I - - - - - - - - - : - - " . - -- - - - - - - - - e t - o .* - • U 47 (Aſia! . . . - OW - - - - - - © - f - O - - - - - - - - - e - * - Wi il tſhi - -- - - ~ - - - * - * -- Piercy. . . . - - - - - - - - - Rochford. Anna Bullen. - - , 3. - - - . . . . . . . . . -- * - Lady Eliz. Blunt. Lady Eliz. Blunt. . . . Toung Princeſ; Elizabeth. - oung Princeſ; Elizabeth. * S * - . -- * . . . .” - * - * . . . . . . . . - - -* * - - - * - - - Ladies, Gentlemen, Attendants. and L4446.ſ, Gºſtleſſiºn. *** A - - - - - - 's . . . 2. fn, Atten - iſlij, and - - | -* . - * * * * * n - sº - - - /* -- w g - s - • - 4. - - º - * zºº * !











End of Title Page. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 1

- - - - - - 's- - - - * º , - - - - --- . - - - , \ // . .” - - - - - - * . . . . . , - - - - † - - *\ - - - 2. - on, Anna Bullen. s A c T L sce N E L Emir Northumberland". Rodfºrd . . . . North, is is the Day ſhall Crown your Parents wiſhes, - . A.º.º. The king intends * - To publiſh freight his Marriage with your Siſter, - And make her known by th? Title of his Queen: The reaſon why it was ſo long kept ſecret, - was our great Cardinal's Delays, and Tricks * * > . . . of Rome, which Harry has with Frowns diſcover'd : . - but ſince, in ſpite of Wolſey and the Sonclavº, By Reverend Cranmer has the cauſe been try’d; And Katherine is this day proclaim'd divºrºd. - rº. Hayºmbe my witneſs, brave Northumberland." - It joys not me, but that it is hi: Pleaſure, - whoſe happineſs we all are bound to pray for; . . . . . . . And may my Siſter's Crown ſit lighter on ... - - . . . . . . ~ Her grow, than does the Honour upºn mine : . . . - Something of boding whiſpers to my Soul, . . . . . . A. tiline, oh! this Marriage will be fatal- * * * * . . . Methinks I ſee a sword ty'd to a Thread, . . . . Small as a hair, hang o'er our Pageant Greatneſs: jºine. Friend. Thrones are ſevereſt Touchſtones; . . . . . And, like the Emblem of their Guard, the Lyon, Anºtherwillº... ... . . . . - North. My Lord, this is ſevere to all that love you? . . . . . . . And you reflect unkindly on your Fortúnº; Tº -- rºb fortune! whyāid ſhe lay hº i. on her 2 . . . . A load, I ſay, to quiet Minda-rſhº, ... " . . . . . . . . Hir. wº \ Have -
Page 2

. Have caſt it upon one that was ambitious: 2} V E R T v E Betrayd: Or, . QWs; * it Your Piercy’s Wife; and nºt at one time made her." - - Both Cruel 3. the Queen, º: Falſe jº: *T*. North. You know, my Lord, we all are Witneſſes. With what remorſe ſhe took the Regal Burthen, ; * : . That ſate upon her like a heavy Armour * * * On a Child’s back; ſhe º: Weight. Koch. Oh! may it not be fatal to us, Heav'n' For at the very time ſhe gave her Hand - - - > To th” eager King to faſten’t with a Pledge, * The Ring fell cff, and could no more be fºund: ; ; ; ; , North. Meer Chance, my Lord. 3- . . . . . - My Lord, it had been :* of Fortune, * * -- ºg •" ‘I have ſeen my Siſter wedded to her Vows; º: \f tº - : 5. Roch. And then immediately, --- ~~ When the glad Ceremonies were perform’d, `-- * *---------- The amorous King bending to Kiſs, her Hand, Y : A ſhower of Pearls broke paſſage from her Eyes, ' ' - - And all-bedev'd his Head with ominous Tears. . - North. The common uſe of every baſhful Bride. . . º \; will ſhe do when ſhe ſhall underſtand Qur foul Deſigns, and Piercy's Innocence ; ; ; ; ; ; ; ; }-15-1 ºr His Letters ; that you intercepted, a goſ ºf § - - And counterfeited others to deceive her,' ... ''{{q : . . . . . To make her once believe that he was marry’d 2 - - - - But what a mortal Grief will ſeize your Son, , . . . . When he ſhall find his Miſtreſs was betray’d; : … . . . . . . . . . . . . And forc’d to marry one ſhe cannot love? A tº . . . . . . . . . . . North. To prevent that: Soon as he's come to Court; . . . . . . Juſt but to ſee ſhe's marry’d, and no more, º ºxº, , . . . . . (Not giving him the time for ſecond thoughts) I’ll make a Match between him and the Heireſs, . Of Shrewsbury. - - - . … , : Roch. A very gallant Lady, º . . . . . . . . . . . . . . As Virtuous, Beautiful, and Richer far . . . . . . . . . . . tº | Than all our Generation of that Sex. " '' … . . . . . . . . . . . . North, You wrong your ſelf to flatter me. Her Father , , . . . . Brings her this day on purpoſe from the Country : . . . . . . . But the Queen thinks already they are marry’d. º.º. . ... tº: Roch. And are you ſure to gain your Sen’s conſent, . . . . . . . . ºr To what he has been ſtill ſo obſtinate ºf . , , , , it ºf , , , , , North, Rage and Deſpair, when he ſhall find her falſe, a ..., Will make him raſhly change to any ſtate; , i.e., " . . . . . . tº And, thinking to be miſèrable, will plunge … . . . . . . . …, , Into the dreadful Sea of Matrimony, . . . . º, ºr tº: And make himſelf; though much againſt his Will, a -lºod sº, The happieſt man that ever was on Earth. ºf ei º I ºf 4. *- - - - **

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 3

ANNA BULLEN. 3 s As if the World’s four Winds were pent within - Enter Cardinal Woolſey mnſing. Behold the proud imperious Cardinal, - With ſuch a furious Tempeſt on his Brow, . . . His bluſtering Carkaſs. He has heard the News, And comes to argue with his Friend the Devil, - - The Reaſon of his No-lntelligence. + = Roch. The Popedom now, and all the Wealth in Rome, , - Can ſcarcely recompence him for the fright This News has put him in-See how he ſtaggers, Giddy with th’ height his Pride has rais'd him to. *Tis then moſt fatal to unhappy England , lº - - When ſuch Church Blazing-Stars appear in it. [Ex, North, and Roth. Card. Marry’d in private, and declar'd his Queen! t - Katherine divorc'd, and Anna Bullen marry'd] : s Now, by our Holy Father’s Triple-Crown It muſt not, cannot, nay, it ſhall not be. . - a Where was your aid, that time, you ſlothful Saints, You whom falſe Zeal created in more numbers Thane're the Heathen made and worſhipp'd Gods? . . . . . A Lutheran Queen upon the Throne of England I . She to lye in the Boſom of our Prince!, T : . . . . . . A Buxom King, that for a wanton Smile . . . . . . . . . . . . Will pawn his Faith, and turn an Heretick! . . . . . . . . Enter the Lady Elizabeth Blunt. - Blunt. Awake thou wretched dreaming Prieſt, look upt a Can you behold your proud Saint Peter ſhake?... . . . . . . . . . . The mighty Pillar of that ſpreading Church... . . . . . . . . . . That holds the great Religion of the World … … . . . . . . . To ſtagger, and beſtow no help, no aid . . . . . . . . . . From mighty Woolſey's Shoulders to ſupport it P. ". . . Is this the great King-Cardinal, who late . . . . . . . . . . . From ſmalleſt Root began to ſhade the Land, . . And ſtood the talleſt Cedar of the Church? … sº - Shame to thy Prieſt-hood, and thy Scarlet Robe, , … . . . . . . . Ev’n thou to whom the liberal See of Rome . . . . . . . . . . . . . Has given all, next giving of her ſelf: . . . . . . . . . . . . unworthy Servant of ſo kind a Miſtreſs; , , , , . . . . . . . gard. What does the Faireſt mean . . . . . . . . . --- Blunt. Ha! muſt 1 teach thee Pºu. . . . . . . . . . . . . iii.; Art thou the Thing that from the Chaff of Matkind, . , is ſº From the baſe ſcurrilous Rubbi of the World, . . . . . . . . . . ºn A Firſt found thy ſelf a way to thrive by Wit? Then edging it with ſharpeſt Villanies,
Page 4

4. V E R / U E Betray'd : Or, - Mow'd thee a paſſage to thy Princes Breaſt, And cut down all the Virtuous from his ſight, - Who choſe thee for the Champion of his Vices; * Whilſt thou with labour let looſe all their Sluces, And pour’d them like a Torrent in his Boſom * This you did once confeſs to me, and more, When you declar’d how hot you were in Love— Bullen is Queen, the Crown you promis'd me Now wreaths her Head Are theſe the hopes you gave me, When once you ſaid my Son ſhould be a King? The News not ſtirs your Wonder . Hell and Furies : - s Card. What wou'd you l ſhould do to ſerve you ? > Blunt. Forgive me, tender Woolſey, pious Cardinal ' ' . . . Shall I then teach your Scarlet Prieſthood Blood? . . . . . . I would have done as Alexander did, " , , ; ; ; - The Sixth, and the moſt merciful ſo nam'd : . . . Are there no Conſecrated Weapons left 2 . . Or have you loſt the Power to make 'em ſo? Give me Saint Dagger or Saint Poiſon ſtraight, ' ' ' . ." And I will do that Meritorious Aët: . . . ". . . . Diſpatch her ſtreight to Hell, from whence ſhe fetch'd Thoſe Looks that robb'd me of the King and Crown. Card. Have patience, Madam... . . . . . . . . . Blunt. Preach it to the Damn'd, - º ºs To thoſe that feel the Rack or Inquiſition . . . . . Curſe on your Gown Apologies: but more . . . . . . ." . ." Be curſt the time of Bullen’s fatal Birth, - - - - - - - - - - Wrinkles like Age anticipate her Youth; . . Mildews and Blaſts devour her wanton Beauties, Small-Pox and Leproſies rough-caſt her o're; • * Dig up her Charms and Features by the Roots, -- And bury 'em in Pits as deep as Graves. - Card. Study ſome Aét that may revenge this Fury, This hurts no more than Barks of Coward Curs; . . . . . . . . . . " She lives, and is as beautiful as ever:", - . . . . Be rul’d by me, who like a dreadful Piece, Am ſure to kill, where-e’re I take my Aim, “ . . . . Before they hear the Noiſe or ſee the Flame. . . . . . . . . . . . Blant. Oh tell me how to quench this Fire within'! . . . . That burns me up with thoughtful Injury. . . . Card. An eaſie way I’le chalk to your Revenge, A Road not ſteep, nor dangerous, but ſmooth; So unſuſpeded, and ſo fatal too, , , , - ... • That the Queens Fancy, and deluded Genius, , , , , . . . Shall tempt her in the ſame diſſembled Path, . . . . . . Taking her by the other hand with us, . . . . º. And lead her in the Pit prepar'd for her. * * * * * * * * * : . . . . ; ; ; ; ; ; ; ; ; ; ; ; *-º: py...... . . . . . . . Blunt, t : . . . . . . . " " " : * ~ *- y*- *- + • - -: * : …”
Page 5

A N N A BU L L E N. 5 . Blunt. Go on my Woolſey, Charming as the young, And more melodious than a Quire of Angels. - Card. This then it is: The King you know's inconſtants As jealous and as teaſty as old Age, - So covetous of the pleaſure he poſſeſſes, N - That he who does but look upon’t muſt dye, * * , With her, whoſe innocent Charms did force him to't. Blant. But how ſhall we be backt with a pretence 2 Card. 'Tis eaſie to give fire to that fond Breaſt That is already charg’d with jealous Sulphur : . The Queen loves Piercy, that may be a means; And Spies may be laid every where to watch Their Private Meetings, and their very looks, And then acquaint the Hot-brain’d King with it: - - So ſtreight their joyful Deſtinies are ſeal’d. . . . . . . Blunt. Moſt admirable! . . - … Card. If we fail in this, . . - - - Some cry’d-up Beauty, ne’re yet ſeen at Court, Muſt be found out, to put her in his way, And take the Amorous King: 'Twill certain do; For then no greedy Falcon, when he ſees the Lure, Will flye down ſwifter to be catch'd and hooded, Than he into the Fetters of her Charms. Blunt. O come to my Embrace, thou Godlike Prieſt - * - Balm to my wounded and my tortur’d Boſom. Card. Go ſtreight, and haſte about the Intelligence. Blunt. I will. Good Fortune has been ſo propitious, To make young Rochford, Anna Bullen's Brother, . . . . Enamour’d of my Beauty; him I’le mould, Sound ev'ry thought of his unguarded Soul, Linking him cloſe in amorous Intrigues, *Till 1 have diſcover'd from him our Deſign Of Piercy's Love, and of his Siſters Condućt. * , Card. An Accident, the luckieſt that could happen! Behold the Queen in her firſt State and :* But yet ſhe bears it with no welcome meen: Piercy hangs heavy on her Heart, and in her Eyes; It works, it manages as we would have it : And in her heedleſs Innocence ſhe ſails, Shunning no Rocks, no Quick-ſands, nor no Danger, But runs into her Ruine faſter than We wiſh. * , - - - Blunt. Her Crown is hideous to my ſight, - . . Its Jewels fatal as the Eyes of Baſilisks; … . . " O Cardinall This Rival-Queen and I * Should never meet but in the Scales of Death, . . . . . . . . That weigh all Mortals even and alike. . . . . . . ... --> - - B 2 Øº.
Page 6

6 y E R Tz & Baraya; or, Queen Anne appears ſtated upon a Throne. Northumberland, Rochford, Lords, Ladies, Attendants and Guard, about her. . . . Omnes. Long live King Henry, and Queen Anne of England. ' North. Immortal live Great Queen of England, France, And Ireland, and for ever rule the Heart - of Conquering Henry, as he Reigns o're us And all his faithful Subjećts— . . . I ſpeak it as the Wiſhes and the Wolter --- Of your moſt Loyal Kingdoms; to confirm it, Sound ſtraight your loudeſt Inſtruments of Joy, And ſhout as I do, all that Love their Queen. - Queen riſes from her Throne, [Shout, and Trumpets within. Queen. Theſe Sounds might lift another to the Heav'ns ! But what is Muſick to the Ear that’s deaf; - Or Crowns and Scepters to a dying Wretch?: . Deſpair turns all-alike that comes to me, Blind to the Pomp that gladsall Eyes but mine, Deaf to its Charms, and dead to all its Glories. : [Trumpets and Shout again. Ceaſe you more empty Flatterers than Winds; - Be ſilent as the Sorrows in my Breaſt: º If you will give me eaſe, forbear ſuch Flatteries: - For I receive 'em with as little joy, . . . . . . . . . As ev’n thoſe ſilly Wretches utter them, . . . . . . . " Having no other Reaſon but vile Cuſtom. . . . . . . . . . . . My Noble Lords! . . . . - . . . . ºf . I know you all are Loyal to the King, , , -- And for his ſake you are thus kind to me 3- • , º, . But for the Rabble, who can read that Sphinx? Their very Breath that now Proclaims, with joy, -, … Sad Katherine to be no longer Queen, . . . . . * * * ...And my unwelcome Coronation, Would the ſame moment, ſhould my Stars permit, Shout louder at the Sentence of my Death. - Card. Moſt glorious and beloved ef England's Queens? O lay not on our Nation ſuch a Curſe, - * As a ſuſpicion of its Faith to you. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . I dare be bold, and ſay it as a Prieſt, * * * * As Confeſſour to all my Country’s Guilt, * * * * * : There's none, how mean ſoever with my ſelf, . . . . . . . . . ; But loves you more than life, or darling Riches, . . . . Wiſhing to feel ſevereſt Penance here, . . . . . . .” - And Hell hereafter, rather than behold . . . . . . . . . You leſs a Queen, or leſs adorºd than now... ." . . . . . . . . . Queen. They have my thanks, next kind good natur'd Wºofty;.... . . * - - --. - * -

Page 7

. . . . . A N N A BUL LEN. 7- Who cannot but be real, 'cauſe he ſays it. . . . . . . . , Card, Oh that your Majeſty would think ſo ever, And that my proud endeavours, with ſucceſs, . . . . . Firſt whiſper'd in the Boſom of the King The ſecret Wonders of your Mind and Perſon, º And made him ſoon diſcover all your Beauties, Thoſe rare Perfections, that above your sex. Have merited his Paſſion and his Crown.” . . . . . . Queen. O'Reverend, pious, beſt of Cardinals tº Who toº well knows, , , ,, ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . By whoſe high hand I climb'd this malic'd Greatneſs, " sº - And wear this envy’d Crown. Card. May Heav'n and Stars- . - Pour their juſt hatred on — 3 * : - Queen. Ceaſe Execrations: . - * - | * * For ſhould they come to paſs, as Heav'n forbid, What wou'd the miſerable Nation do? . . . . Beſides 'twere pity to the King and me, " " ' ' ' ' That we ſhºuld lºſſo ºxquiſite a Head. And ſuch a Prelate ſhoutd. be damn?d ſo ſoon. . . . . Card. Ten thouſand Saints; more than my Royal Maſter, . . . Are Witneſſes to th’ truth of what I ſay. t º ls ueen. As many Saints and Myriads of bright Angels. . . . . cíº...? of the blackneſs of thy Soul, argº ". . . . . . . That canker'd firſt the Conſcience of thy Maſter, , , . . . . Miſleading him with hopes to purge a ſin, ... " To act the worſt, ev’n a Religious Guilt— . . . . . . . . . Card. The wiſe and juſt Omnipotence—- º, Queen. No more : ºf . . . . . . Hell's not ſo full of Torments, as thy Seal ºr . . . . . . Has Blaſphemies to be rewarded in it—º . . . . Give me ſome eaſe, juſt Heav'n" if there beany - w My Lords! if there's no more for you to at To perfeót OT unmake this Ceremony, . . . . . . . . . . . . º º º º º (Oh that it cou’d be done!) retire a while, “ . . . . . . . . . And leave me with my Women for fºoments—º what am I then a Priſoner to be guarded?" Has then a Throne coſt meſo dear a Price, sº . . . . . . As forfeit of my Liberty of Thinking? . . . . . . Do Princes barter for their Crowns their Freedoms? - c. §ood Heav'n' nºt think nor pray if I have need— - If I am § * º I not obey'd? . Comm a ; : . . . Card. We'll all perſorm your Majeſties Command. Queen. Am I got looſe, looſe from this worrying Scene . . . of diſmal State... that always loads a Monarch, - And racks him with diſſembling Tortures 2: * º º,
Page 8

8 V E.R Tºy E. Betray'd: Or, - O wretched ſtate of Prince; I that want nothing But a Retreat from Buſineſs and from Crowds: “ . . . . . . . Yet wanting that, want every thing that's happy, . . . . . . . A Soul at eaſe-–-O ſacred Solitude : : - « . . . . . . . How aiery and delightful are thy Walks fºr . . . . . . No ſtinging Serpent, nor worſe Inſeół Man, ...... . . . * Diſturb thy fragrant and enamell’d Paths; -- . . . . No Winter-Blaſts, nor Autumn Winds moleſt; ºthº . . . . . . . . . . Thy ſacred Grotto's, all around is Summer ; ; ; ; sº º " . . Nothing broods there but an Eternal Spring, º . . .'; cº, ºr Mild as all May, and Beautiful as Eden: , , ;", i ! . . . . . . tº . Thou charitable Good! that from th’ afflićted … . . . . . . . . . . llnloads the heavy Burdens that oppreſs them, ... . . . . . . . And plants Repoſe in every Breaſt in ſtead! . . . . . . . . . . . . : 3. * : *, *, * > -- . . . . ºnter a Lady. …, c. … . . . . . . . . . . . • , - * - - - - - - º * . . . ; Lady. The Lady Diana Talbot begs admittance, - To pay her Duty to your Majeſty. - Queen. What ſay'ſt! Thou'ſtrous’d a Dragon in my Breaſt, Which I had thought for ever to have huſht: ; ; ; , . . . . . . . . . That Name ſets every Pulſe again at work. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Within me—--Talbot! how art thou miſtaken? . . . . . . . . . . . She's Piercy's now ; And Piercy all his hers. • Lady. Shall ſhe be brought to your Preſence? . . . . . Queen. Ay—No—Yes— , , , º, . . . . . . . . . . . Do any thing, ſo 'twill be ſure to kill me: ; ; ; ; , , , , , , , , O Piercy! Piercy! would thou ne're hadſt been ... . . . . . º.º. llnfaithful, or at leaſt in being ſo, : - ; ºº Hadſt never taught me how to be reveng'd : " " . . . . . . But oh the diſmal Pain is all my own, . . . . . . . . . And like an Arrow from an o'rebent Bow, ºr tº . . . . . . The haſty Dart turn’d back and hurt my ſelf, sº . . . . . ºo Wounding that Breaſt where 1 leaſt meant my aim. º. º. º. How ſoft and tender were our mutual Vows, . . . . . . . . Which ſince another’s Charms, like Lightning, blaſted; 2 ºr Whilſt Parents Threats and King's Authority, - Rent me, like Thunder, from my fixt Reſolves: . . . . Th’ art marry'd now, and all thoſe amorous ſighs, . . . . . . . . And paſſionate Tears, with thouſand Extaſies, :* . . . . . . - Which we both learnt and taught to one another, ºr Like innocent Children in the School of Loyº, º, º ºf , ; , Are now the Arts with which, falſe Man! th’ haſt caught ... . . Anothers fond believing Heart, they are. - - - º - ^ - " - - . . -, -, * *.* ... ." . . º f * * tº - . - * - " - -, * . . .” . g . . . . . . . .'; 's Fienter. ºth ºf . * : * : * ~ * * * * . . . . . ... º. º f :: *- : * * : * 28. *** . - - * *

Page 9

~ * AN N A BULLEN 9 Enter Lady Diana Talbot. cº º - : . . . . yuana : albot. ! #183 tº biº - - - ... ... -...- … • * : * ºr “º ºr * * She comes, Triumphant in her Eyes the joyº tºº “º ºf That once like Tides o're-flow'd my fruitful Breaſt, ſº How proud ſhe bears her ſelf to ſee my pain! . . . . . . . . . . Whilſt I look up to her; and ſigh in vain *** : **** *** But I will hide it, and forgive me Heav'n, }. .. ºt. [Diana Kneels. For ’tis the firſt time that Ie're diſſembled—ºº" " ` “Riſe dear Diana, you have been a Stranger; 12 º' Could nothing but a Queen drag you to Court 2, "' ... ". . . . I owe this Kindneſs to my Royalty, : - … . . . . . . And not your Friendſhip - “ . . . . . . . . . . . . . Dian. Pardon, mighty Princeſs! º flºº I had been bleſt for ever in your Preſence, º zºº tº Yº Charming in all Eſtates as well as now, * * * * * * ****, Had I been Miſtreſs of my Inclinations. * * * * * * * But . . - - tº . . . . . . ºº:: … : - Queen. PTis no matter, I’le allow your Reaſon, lºº I ºccº A Cauſe ſo indiſpenſible and juſt, º'º ſº.º. That’twere a fault in me to blame ſuch Virtue...”. * * tº: Dian. Indeed a Parents Willought ſtill to be ºs tº "º ºf: Obey'd, next Duty to your Majeſty.º. º.º. ---- Queen. And ſomething yet more binding—Do not bluſh—sº Come I’le unriddle all, and ſpare your Tongue " ' " ' " " '' . The trouble, and your baſhful Cheeks the Fire,”, “ . . º.º.º. Dian. what firéf what bluſhes do you tax me with?' ſº- I feel not any but what wonder raiſes, º, . . . . . . And bluſh becauſe I cannot comprehend, tº ººº- º Queen. You are unkind, why make it you a ſecret 2 tº sº ... And but to me, when all the World reports it. . . . . . . . Dian. There is no ſecret; nothing I would hide From ſo ador'd a Friendſhip as my jūeen's, " " ' ... . .” - sº - - - * * * * * - -- - - - - - - - - _Queen, Why d'you ſuſpešt me then?' [Aſide. #How loth ſhe is.", To tell it me? As loth as I to hear it: * * * * * * * Sure ſhe ſuſpects how fatal twill be to me; *... . . . . . . . And the proud Man has triumph'd o're my weakneſs! : "... And told her all my Paſſion with a ſcorn-. º, 'Tis ſo; whilſt poor, regardleſs, innocent F : * : * : ***. was ali the while their Cenſure and their Paſtime, * * * - - " - The Fool, whoſe Story ačićd madé'em ſport, ...". And gave new edge to all their ſated Joyes; * * * * * Nay and perhaps drew Pity from their Pride? : " . . . . . . Pity good Gods ! muſt I endure their Pity ? ". . . . . . “Yon will not own it then?' But 'tis no matter. iii., i. º When ſaw you Piercy? ºr º, . . . . . . . . . . Dian. Piercy, Madambandº Yº Si tº -- tº . * [she ſtartſ. sº







Page 10

*1 O VER Tºy E. Betray'd : Or, Queen. Yes, - Why did you ſtart I has he a Name ſo horrid? But now you ſpoke as tho’ there were not ſuch - - - - A Man i'th’ World, and wonder'd at my meaning; ~ * But yet have all the Agonies to hear him nam'd : Him you would hide, but cannot hide your Bluſhes. . . . . . Dian. Good Heav'n' by what ſtrange Miracle have you [Aſide. Reveal’d my ſecret Paſſion to the Queen 2. - - I never told my Grievance but to you, . . . . ... . And that but ſilently in broken Sighs . . . . . . . And ſtifled Tears— . . . . . Queen. 'Tis plain ſhe is diſturb’d l— . . . . . . . . . . . What can this mean? Sure one of us is madi . . . . . . . . . [Aſide. Why all this Care to hide a Truth from me, . . . . . . . * That is the common talk of all the Wor...? … . . . . . . . There's ſomething in it more than yet i know, . . . . . Which I muſt ſearch into by other means. - - Madam, I thought when I had condeſcended..., , , , , ... [To Diana. To open my Breaſt, and mingle friendſhips with you,…, " : º, . You would not then deny ſo ſmall, a Secret 3 iſ . . . . . . ºf And now when I am Queen and may, cºnnaad if-t-t-sº vº Therefore begone. Leave me without Reply, y Henceforth I’le know the Perſons betteſ, out y : , , of whom I mean to chuſe a Friend—farewell— . Tº Piercy no doubt is not ſo fondly niče, ) iſ a , , ... . . . . . But brags, and tells the World of his proud Conqueſt, ſº Diam. Forgive me firſt; then give m. leave. té sell you-------- How 'twas diſclos'd to you, the Wonder ſigns me; g . . . . . . . . But Piercy knows not yet, nor ſhall from mº, - * . This ſecret which I thought ſcarce Heav'd found out. … . . . . Queen. Racks and worſe Tortures! Frenzies of the mind! . . Hence; take her from my ſight: She will diſtract me..., , , , , , Pian. O hear mafirſt; Yºur Fury's not ſo dreadful, ºf a As is my pain to tell: Yet I’le confeſs : . . . . . . . . . IEKnelli. A fatal Truth it is, Piercy I Love—- º . . . . . . . Now pity me, aniquené mºrning bluſhes: For Heav’n ºº: you for no ill º - - Queen. I am amaz'd: Still worſe and rń. **- * - * . And they’re Abuſ i -ingr º **. ºr Wouldſt have me think thy lawful Paſſign ſuch a wonderſ ... . . . . Is it a Crime for thee to Love thy Husband? Tº Pian. Ha! what is that you ſay? my Husband ſaid you! . !Meant you to mock th’unfortunate Diana? " tº c z - #. No. I will ſay's again; thy perjur’d Husband ºn tº ºf . tan. Ah! Royal Madam. Piercy is more bleſt; , ; ; ºr -º w .."; Marry'd, he is not my Husband. €tº, Ha - - . . - - -- 4. ra º * - ... DAſide. . Dian. v

Page 11

ANNA BULL EN. . . . . . Dian. That were to me too great a Happineſs! * Queen, Should this be true, what would become of me? [Aſide. Diana riſe: Are you not Marry'd, ſaid you! Dian. So far from that, his Perſon I’ve not ſeen In twelve long Months, this laſt long tedious year. Queen. Art not his Wife --- - Dian. By all your precious Hopes And mine, I'm not. . Qgeen. Is Piercy then not marry'd : , , Support me Heaven! and with a wonder ſave me; [Aſide, Call all thy Virtue and thy Courage ſtreight To help thee now, or thou art loſt for ever. Am I then cheated 1 and is Piercy faithful! If I can bear all this, I challenge Atlas To live under a Load ſo vaſt as mine. Ah Piercy! injur’d Piercy! injur’d Bullen But hold, there's yet a greater task behind, And that is to Diſſemble well.—Diana : . Dian. Madam - - Queen. Thou wonder'ſt at my Curioſity, As tho’ 1 were concern’d at this falſe Story. . - I'll tell thee why: It has been long reported, That you and Piercy were in private Marry’d. Dian. Such a report came likewiſe to my hearing; But how ’twas rais'd, by whom, or why, I know not. - Queen. Too well the dreadful cauſe of it I know. [Aſide. This, when I heard, I took unkindly from you: I was your Friend, you ought no more to ſteal A Marriage from a Friend, than from a Father. And when you aggravated, as I thought, By your unkind denial, it enrag’d me; For which I hope, Diana, you’ll forgive me—- - Methinks I do it rarely— * - [Aſide. Dian. Beſt of Queens ! - - Thus on my Knees, I ought to beg that Pardon: I only did offend, my Gracious Miſtreſs. Queen. Riſe to my Arms This Kiſs now Seals thee mine For ever. - - Diana. Oh moſt admirable Goodneſs! - Queen. This tenderneſs betrays me, melts my Soul | [Aſia. A fatal Engine that draws all my Griefs . . up to my Eyes and Lips, juſt ready to unload And pour’em in at once into her Breaſt, - Whom I, of all the World, ſhould hide’em from. Oh for ſome Wild, ſome Deſart to complain in, Some vaſt and uninhabitable place; - – Or elſ: ſome Precipice that butts g-oan, - Th s - € - --
Page 12

Come rolling on apace, and, Katherine, now Puniſh not me, I ſought not to be Queen; . . . H2 VERT Z/ E Betrayd: Or, The wide, and never to be fathom'd Ocean, - That I might tell the ecchoing Rocks my Wogs, And count my Sorrows to the Winds and Seas, More pitiful, and more relenting far, . Than falſe and cruel Mankind is to me. - Dian, You ſeem diſturb’d Ah! what inhumane Grief Dares ſeize your Royal Breaſt? Queen. Come, dear Diana; Go to my Cloſet with me ; there, perhaps, Some reſt may quell this melancholly Monſter ; And there it may not be amiſ; ſometimes To talk of Piercy, will it? Dian. Sacred Queen, ‘. . . . *Twill not; and oh! I wiſh that the Diſcourſe Would ſooth your Soul with as much Joy as mine. Queen. Theſe are the firſt of Miſeries, the reſt Thou art Reveng’d Juſt Heav'n, whoſe is the Sin But Henry's Guilt amidſt my Pomp is weigh’d, ! And makes my Crown ſit heavy on my Head, To baniſh from his Bed, the chaſteſt Bride, That twenty years lay loving by his ſide! How can I give it, without Tears, a Name, When I refle&t my Caſe may be the ſame * And I, perhaps, as Slaves are by the Prieſt, Thus gay and fine for Sacrifice am dreſt. Ah! Katherine, do not envy me thy Throne, For thou art far more happy that has none. A CT II. S C E N E L Enter Northumberland and Rochford. - - ſexeumt. - *Tºg News is trange you tell me of the King, He came juſt now from Hunting as his uſe, a North. Moſt wonderful, nor can I gueſs the meaning, Where at Sir Thomas Seymour’s Houſe he was Moſt ſplendidly and kindly entertain’d At a Repaſt. - … . . . . . . . . Roch. Took he there any thing . . . Morth. No : quite contrary, ſo good humour’d, # never ſaw him in my life more pleaſant: • But now, inſtead of going to the Queen, . . . . ºf . . . . . . With words that ſhew'd more diſcontent than rage, . . . . He order'd all about him to regire, * • * | ~) -

Page 13

w A N N A BU L L E N. . . .3 And, which is ſtill more ſtrange, enquir'd for Woolſey, . . Woolſey, whom all Men thought quite out of favour; Then ſhut himſelf within his Bed-Chamber, And there remains; nor durſt the boldeſt venture • To follow him, and ask him what he ails— . . . . May not the Queen your Siſter, think you, be . . . . The innocent Occaſion ? - . . . . ... Koch. That's impoſſible ſº . . . . . . " For but laſt Night he came to her Apartment, - . . . . with all the heat and love that could inſpire . . . . . . . A Bridegroom, ſcarcely of an Hour's making : • • With haſte he ran, and where he ſhould have ſate - He kneel'd down by her as his Deity; * . . . . , Printing ſoft Kiſſes on her lovely Hand, , , , - * * And ſigh’d as if he had been ſtill a Woeing. ". . . . . - __North. Right Harry ſtill: For by this Flood of Paſſion The nearer he's to Ebb and Change. . \,: Koch. Seel the King. * ~ * \ . A sº - North. You are Brother to his Wife, and may be bold, But Ple not venture. , - [Ex, North. - Enter King Harry. - - King. Who are you that durſt preſs on my Retirement f - [Ex. Roch. Ha! Bullen Get thee from my ſight—Begone Who waits there? Why am I thus troubled P ^ - Let none but Woolſey dare to be admitted. [To the Attendants. Who can withſtand ſo vaſt a ſhock of Beauties, [He ſits down. , So many Wonders in ſo bright a Form 2 - - When Heav'n deſigns to make a perfeót Face, A Beauty for a Monarch to enjoy, - * , as * Tis feign'd that the moſt skilful Spirits are all * - Imploy'd, and juſt before their Eyes is plac’d Th’axadteſt, lovelieſt Angel for a Pattern; - If it be true; this only muſt be ſhe, - And muſt be mine- Who's there f the Cardinal . . . Enter Woolſey. Card. The humbleſt Vaſſal of his God-like Maſter. ... | King. Come hither, Sir—I ſent for thee, my Woolſey? And doſt not wonder; when but yeſterday - . . . . . I took from thee the Seal and Chancellour's Place 2 But 'tis no matter: Do not care, I ſay: \ I love you ſtill in ſpight of all your Foes—- You have malicious Enemies at Court; Beſides the Queen, my Lord, *: good Friend sº '. .. --- *-
Page 14

* and to thy Mitre adding humble crºwn." . . . . 14 - V E R Tºy E. Betrayd: Or, Of yours. . . . . • - Card. Wretched am I that have incurr'd My Kings Diſpleaſure, and my Queens dire Hatred' But m”Innocence when I am dead, perhaps May to my Royal Maſter, tho’ too late Appear. - j- King. Talk not of Death, good Cardinal, For I have Buſineſs with thee firſt—By Heav'h He that dares mutter Woolſey is a Traitor, Shall dye for a worſ: Trator as he is: Keep thy own ſtill, the Biſhopricks of Tork. And Wincheſter, and Cardinal, that is - Above my Grant; and when I give thee leave, º Go to thy Dioceſs, and live to ſpite 'em. - Card. Immortal Wreathes, and Diadems of Saints, Crown you in Heav'n for this Royal Goodneſs. I am grown old, too weak to guard me from My Foes, but for your Majeſties Protećtion. King, O Woolſey! be to me but half ſo kind, As I ſhall be to thee. Seymour, my Father The lovely Seymour, whom thou toldſt me of, I did devour her Beauties from thy Lips, And fed my Ears with the delicious Feaſt ; But ſince I’ve ſeen this Wonder of her Sex! - - The Charming'ſt Creature e're adorn'd the World; And find her all as far above thy Praiſes, - As Heav'n can be beyond Man's frail deſcription. ... Card. Have you then ſeen her, Sir 2 King. O, yes, my Woolſey? And having ſeen lier, gueſs, 1 needs muſt be But wretched without her, or thy aſſiſtance, - Card. This goes as I expected. King. Help thy Prince 1 - 2 Why art ſo ſlow P. Has Woolſey loſt his Courage 2: . That Wit that Emperours and Popes has ſway’d— So, let thy Brain begin to travel now; - Bring forth thou more than King; thou more than Man #. Thou haſt a Mine within that ſubtle Breaſt, º The Stone which dull Philoſophy has toyl'd In vain for Make me Maſter of thy Indies——- kend me thy Wit to purchaſe Seymour for me. - ; Card. You have the Means already in your hands, Power is the greateſt Charmer of that Sex. King. Command my Power, my Kingdoms tothy aid, * Join to thy Foxes Tail my Lions Skin;" Take thou my Scepter, bind it to thy Croft, j
Page 15

* A N N A B U L L E N 'Tis all my Woolſey’s. Woolſey ſhall be King. . I ask but only Seymour in Exchange. Card. You bid too much : Send for her ſtreight to Court s - - Make her a Marchioneſs, or elſe a Dutcheſs; There's hardly now a Woman but will ſell - 15 - - - - - - - - - º “… .”. A fooliſh Honour that none ſees, for that which makes a Noiſe and ſplendour in the World. . . . . - § 1. Sº . . . . . - ~ - - - - King. How thou deceiv'ſt my eager Expediation This I have done without ſuch rare Advice: ' ' But oh ſhe is inflexible to all ! . . . Deaf to the ſounds of Vanity and Pomp ! And more remorſeleſs than a Saint or Hermite. Her Chaſtity cold as the Frozen Stream, And then as hard, and never to be thaw’d, As Cryſtal Rocks, or Adamantine Quarries: . . . . . . That oh I fear, had I but what I covet, . . . . . * * * The Crown from Bullen's Head, to offer her, *Twould ſcarcely tempt her to thy Prince's Bed. card. Then, Sir, I doubt 'tis hardly in my Power To help you. - - King. Ha! falſe and ungrateful Man!, * Is that then all the hope your Brain can give me?' " Card. It is impoſſible; if ſhe be Virtuous, That e're ſhe ſhou’d be had by Force or Cunning. Therefore apply this Remedy a while, º Have but a little Patience ’till 'tis Lawful." King Traitor and Poiſoner of thy Maſter's Reſt, Muſt ſideſpair 2 Is that thy precious Council - Did I deſcend to ask Advice from Hell? Conſult thy Wicked Oracle for this? . To tell me what is Lawful ?: -- * Card, llnderſtand me. King. Give me ſome hopes, or, by thy damn'd And make thee leſs and more dejećted far . Card. Hear me but is . - King. Why didſt thou infect my Breaſt, , ~ And with thy venomous Tongue deceive me, worſe. Than the old Serpent that in Paradiſe . . . . . . . . . .” Betray'd the firſt of Mankind with a Bait 2 - So thou, lurking and hid amidſt the Charms, Of .. rare and unſuſpected Beauties, Sungſt me her Praiſes in ſuch tempting Words, That I with raviſht Ears ſwallow'd the ſound,” And never ſaw the Sting 1 ſuckt in after. . . . £ard. You will not give me leave t'explain my º, i. * - - - -- * * Than the baſe Fellow that begot thee, Prieſt. . . . -----> *** --> -- -- " . . . . . - - - - . . . . . . . ; * . * - 1 –- - * * * * * * * . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ºº Riº Nor- - Ambition; . . . * . º 1’le crumble thee to duſt, puff thee to nothing: "º

Page 16

¥ 5 V & R / U E. Betray d: ur, - Nor yet to give you Remedy. . . . . . -- ... I King. Tell me; - - . . . . . ; ; For Remedy I’le have from Heav'n or Hell, * . . . . . Or I will take thy Blood, thy Scorpions Blood, And lay it to my Grief till I have eaſe. . . . . . - Card. Your Fury will not let you underſtand me: . -- When I advis’d to ſtay till it was Lawful, - - - - At the ſame time I meant to let you know : - A. 'Twas not a thing ſo hard to bring to paſs. . . . . . . King. Ha! ſaid again like Woolſey ! tell me ſtreight, - , , º, My Soul waits at the Portal of thy Breaſt, - " To raviſh from thy Lips the welcome News, - . . . . . . . s * E’re they have minted into Words thy Thoughts— -, * : * ~ * Quick, what can lawfully make Seymour mine f . . " Card. Make her your Queen. , - º King. Make her my Queen Card. Yes, Sir. . . . . . . . . . . .". King. Sure I but dream; what doſt thou mean? or how? . . . . Card. Inveſt her Head with Anna Bullen's Crown. - ... " King, Sure thou art mad, and would make me ſo too— . . What, whilſt ſhe lives? . . . . . . Card. Ay, whilſt ſhe lives I ſaid: -- - º Is that ſo ſtrange a thing that ne're was done? . . . . . . . . Divorce her. 4. - - King. Ha! . . . . . . Card. What is't that makes you ſtart 2 - Divorce her, and take Seymour to your Bed. . . . . . . . . . . . . - King. How ! take good heed what 'tis thou pull'ſt upon . . . . . 2 - - Thy ſelf—Divorce my lawful i.º. - - Without a Cauſe ! . , , *- : - Card. There is a Cauſe. King. What is’t 2 . . … . . . . . Card. Pretend Remorſe of Conſcience. . . . . . . . King. Gods ! tº . . . . . ... . . . . . Card. Ne’re wonder: - . . . . . . . . . . ." Say you are troubled and diſturb’d within. . . . . . - - I King. Eternal Villain Lucifer the Damn'd. I4ſide. Traitor, at what 2 - . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Card. At that which ſeiz'd your Mind, gº. … . - * When Katherine you divorc’d for Anna Bullen. . . . . . . . … ; Conſcience Conſcience * - - - . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Kind. Horrid tormenting Fiend! - . . . . . . Thou know'ſt ſhe was my Brother’s Wife, and Bullen -- On no ſuch juſt pretence I can diſclaim. . . . . . . . . . Card. No matter; on the like diſtruſt of Conſcience . . . . . That made you do the one, you may the other, a lºº, , , . . . . Give out that ſhe's not lawfully your Wife, ſº º ~ f

Page 17

AN N A BULLEN. ºr The firſt alive, and that you never had . . .” - - A Diſpenſation from his Holineſs. . . . . . . * * * King. His Holineſs! I'm blaſted with the thoughts: º, . . . Pernicious Traitor . How can this be done? º Card, Leave it to me; Conſent you, 'tis enough: And I’le engage, on forfeit of my life, - To get a Licence from our Holy Father - . . . . . . To diſanul this Marriage, and to take … . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Into your lawful Bed the Beauteous Seymour. . . . . ºf ºr . . " King. But then I ſtill remain unfreed from Katherine. 2: … a . - Card. The Church ſhall grant a Diſpenſation too º . For that: . - * . - / ` King. What Horrour’s this I hear? Cap,this be true? . * In all my wanton and luxurious Youth, . . . . . . . . . . . . . ; Or in my blackeſt thoughts of Luſt and Rage, . . . . . [Aftie. I ne're yet found one Wiſh amongſt them aii, º, . . . . .”.” Of ſuch a deep Infernal hue. The Horrour . . . . . Has kindled my whole Blood into a Flame, , , - And made me bluſh a deeper Scarlet than This Villain's Robe. Diſloyal wicked Monſter 1. But I will ſtrive to hide my juſt Reſentments. . . . . º Divorce my ſecond Wife without a Cauſe ! . . . . [To him, Could it be done, what would the Nation ſay ? What would the Aëtion look like, but a Hell? To warn ſucceedings Princes from the like, - * , , And blot me from the Sºrole of Pious Kings: . . . . ." w Could it be lawful Woolſey, I would hearken. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Card. Then lawful it ſhall be in ſpight of Scruples: . . . . I ſee your Conſcience is an Infant grown, . . . . . ." - A Child again, and wants to be inſtructed— . . . . . . Come, let me lead you by the hand, and point º * - A way, for you to walk on even ground; . . . So ſafe, the Miceſt Conſcience ſhall commen - tº . . . And chooſe it. - - : . . . . º King. Now thou doſt rejoice thy Prince. | * * Card. What if ſhe be unfaithful to your Bed, . . . *- And prov’d ſo? - a King, Ha! there's Thunder in that word, * . The Bolt ran through, and ſhiver'd me to pieces. . . . . . . . . . . Diſloyal to my Bed & Adultrous ! -Hah! - º! … . . Saidſt thou not ſo Yet hold, if this be true, ... . . . . . . . There hangs a Shower of Cordial in my reach , To cure this horrid Fit. Woolſey, beware . . . . . . . . . How thou doſt daily with my hopes and fears; . . . . . . . .” Look to't, and ſee you wrong her not ; for if … . . .” - . . . Thou doſt, by all the Plagues thy Soul deſerves, ºcłº All Hell ſhall be too little for thy Carkaſs; º' ºr a . . . * - . . . . . . - - e New .* . - * x * * - * * * * * -- - - * - º º . . . . . . .
Page 18

18 VERT v E Betrayd: Or, New Hells ſhall be created, and more hot. - º-, "it Than what’s prepar’d for Traitors, Parracides, . . . . . . . . For Raviſhers of Mothers, luſtful Nuns, . . . For Lucifer himſelf t'endure; nay more . . . . Than Villain, Pope, or Cardinal ever felt, . . . . . . " Speak how thou know'ſt it. Qpick. - - - Card. Alas! my Lord, - . . . . - -- c. I never meant it enter'd in my own - . . . . . . . . . . . . Particular Knowledge: but it is Reported. . . . - : . King. Reported, ſaid'ſt thou ! is not that enough f : " : Report why ſhe is damn'd, if ſhe's but thought - A Whore, much more reported to be ſo. 'Tis not the aët alone that Wrongs thy King; Each Smile, each Glance, and every wanton Look, That’s meant t'another, if I leave unpuniſh'd, Shall brand me with the ignomińious Name . . . . Of Wittal, which is worſe—make me but ſure . . . . . . . That the leaſt Breath has utter'd ſuch a ſound, - Or whiſper’d to the Air that ſhe's unchaſt, a By all the horrid Fiends that puniſh Luſt, .. 'And by the black Concupiſcence of Hell, l'le tumble her from the Throne into a Dungeon— Name me the Man that is ſuſpećted. * . - Card. Piercy. ~ King. Piercy! - Card. Yes, Sir: He is the Man ſhe dotes on; - 'Tis he lies deeper in her Breaſt than ever; For him ſhe ſighs, and hoards up all her wiſhes; . -" Gives him her Perſon warm, inſpir’d with Paſſion, : . Whilſt for your ſelf ſhe only treats you with - The cold dead Body of departed Love. King. Is Piercy then at Court 2 . Card. He is this day . . ; ‘. . . º . . . . . . . Arrriv'd. - - . . . . . ; : King. Hough! Come without my leave ſay’ſt thou?… . . . Card. He is, no doubt to conſummate their Joyes, , , ; Their Signs and Tokens to compare, which the - By Letters and Devices in their abſence Have hourly plotted to deceive you, Sir; . . . º And put in practice when the time is ripe, , , , … Í. ! King. Hell and tormenting Furies—l believe thee. - - Card. Nay in your Bed and in her Dreams ſhe thinks on't ; r When Pleaſures made you dull, it whetted her— . . . . King. Hold, I can hear no more. By all my wrongs . . . . . . . . And cheated Hopes, thoubringſt to my Remembrance, a . . . . How all Complaiſances to me were dragg’d a zºº iſ . . . . . ; And forc’d from her, like Mirth from one in Torture! sº gº ºn ; : - ...”i. Sometimes
Page 19

AN N A BUL LEN. 19 Sometimes I found her Face all drown'd in Tears, - With Gales of Sighs juſt blowing off thoſe Storms, . . . . . In fear away: Sometimes again in Bluſhes, As if them all the wanton Heat of Love - . Were darting through her Eyes to meet my Flame ; * - - But when with eager haſte I catch'd her in - Theſe Arms and preſt her Lips, alack I found inſtead of Summer there no Ice ſo cold 3 º' Inſtead of breath that would revive the dead, No Air ſo chill, nor Winter Blaſts ſo keen. - - Card. Thus all her actions ſtill will be to you: The Roſes of her Bloom ſhe keeps for him, - The Thorns for you—Had you been Piercy then King. Let me embrace the Saver of his Prince, The dear Preſerver of my Life and Honour! What ſhall I do for thee, my Friend ? " . . . - - - * Re-enter Rochford. card. Here’s Rochford! . . . . . . . .” Pray ſmooth your Brow, and hide your Diſcontent: . . And now y’are going to the Queen ſmile on her. Mean while ſhe’ll ſtumble, like a haſty Child, - * * And ačt more plain and open to your Juſtice; . . . . º And when you find her tripping, on the ſudden . . , Strike like the Hand of Heav'n, a ſure Revenge, And never let her riſe again. 22 ° * -- - - 1 - King. I will- † : ; ; ; ; ;... tº . . .” “: … º , - My Lord, you may come near: Where is the Queen? [To Roch. Koch. I left her in the Drawing Room. Tº King. Ah Woolſey ! . . . * . . . . . . What Angele’re ſo bright as Woman was, . . . . . . . Had not the firſt ſcorn’d her Creator's Laws;" . .'; For neareſt his own likeneſs they were made, " ' " * * * , -*Till they by falſeneſs did their Sex degrade. [Extunt K. and Card. - ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . [Manet Rochford. Roch. What means this ſudden alteration! - - - - - - - - , ºº iſ º, º iſ cºsº – if ºf . , tºº ſº. .*.*.*, *: iſ . . . . . . ; ; ; ., 3 tº . ‘. . . - - * - … - - - - is not that Piry: Oh! too true he comestº ... . Not like a joyful Bridgfoom, as was told thee, - - - - - poor cheated siſteri but like one, alasi " . . - º That knows already, the baſe wrongs our Friends - -- ºr ºf jº, Enter Piercy: ". f: Have heap'd upon him! where ſhallſ avoid him? Ah! why muſt I of all the Plot be Curſt P , . . To look upon a Face ſo full of horror; . . . . . . * * * - - D < * - That . ...--> <-
Page 20

º VERT W. E. Betray'd: Or, That like a Hell, at once upbraids my Guilt, . . . ºr º And laſhes me with the Remembrance : , . . . . . . . . . . . Pier. Methinks I walk like one that’s in a Dream, . " : " ..."-1" A horrid Dream, and fain would be awake! - . . . . . Theſe Rooms of State look not at they were wont, - - | - When Anna Bullen oft has run to meet me;- - * ~ * ~ But ſeem like Fairy-Land, a Wilderneſs. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . My Friends, like Beaſts that never yet ſaw Man, . Start at my fight; and ſhun me worſe than Fire. : ....… . . . . . What mean you Heav'ns ! what mean thoſe boding Viſions! . . . . . O that ſome Friend, ſome Friend indeed would meet me ! . . And wake me out of it—-Behold; ’tis gººd— - Is not that Rochford there my Deareſt Brotherſ—, , , , º, . - - Roch. My Lord, my Piercy! . . . . a 24; ... º. º. 3: a . Pier. Come thou to my. Arms.--—hi,j ... ; ; ; ; * * * * º, ſº | Methinks th’ art not concern'd to ſee thy Friend: . . . . . . . . . When I embrace thee, ’tis a pain I find, Thy Friendſhip is as cold as Winter Blaſts, - Or as chill Age is to a tender Virgin! - - * What ails my Friend?" ſay quickly. "...º.º. "… . .” Roch. Nothing ails me, tº t. i. º. ºit tº tº Pier. Nothing! why look'ſt thou then ſo full of horroir 2: . . . Thy down-caſt Eyes call to my ſad remembrance... . . ...... How paſſing by yon Gallery of Pićtures, i.e : i..., That happy Gallery that was once the Scenes: ºd oº Of many a joyful meeting with thy Siſterſ. is tº a Looking with wonder on thoſe famous Perſons,... . . . . . . . . . Whom the rare Painter had with ſo much Art ------ " . . . . . Deſcrib'd, to make Poſterity amends, . . º. . . . For their bright Forms now moulder'd in their lirns; . . . With their Immortal Shapes of Beauty here; ſº, A - - There as we us’d to walk, nonee’re foſkind, sº ſº rº With loving Arms and tender wiſhes joynºd, ; ; ; , . . . . . . g : Aglad remembrance in their looks we ſpy’d, ºad tº ºf . Qf what their Bodies had on Earth enjoy’d; ºn. . . . . . . . . . . . - - - With ſtedfaſt Eyes they watch'd us all the while, And when we ſimil'd, they would be ſure to ſimiſe: ; 3. . . . . . . Or if we chanc'd to weep and ſigh our woe, - - They ſeem'd to pity us, and do ſo, tao: , Such ſympathy they drew from all our Fears, - . . . Our very Griefs, and every Look was theirs. . . . . . Gº", * * * * - - - - - *- - | Roch. The over-flowing of your Love-ſick Fancy, ºr -º Pier. But mark me now, my Kochford; mind the ſad? … ºº ... Cataſtrophe. They looking; now like Friends, ºbsºsº.' . Of Comfort, but like hading Sybilstrathergiº tº acqſ' lºgs. . . . . Their Smiles converted all tº dairing Frowns, , ; ; ; ; ; ; ; ; ; ; ; , Whilſt with their ſeeming Voice and Hands, methought, " :- ? .). T - ----- ºr-. 2 * - • * ~-----------wº / ſ Liº y: • * * * * - - - - - s 2.



Page 21

A N N A BULLEN. : an They chid and beckon'd me to ſhun the place, . . . . As if they did intend to ſay aloud, . . . - -: , Ah Piercy! 'tis not now as heretofore, . " , - . . . . . . ; Piercy begone, for thou ſhalt happy be no more. . . . . . - Roch. Ah, my Lord! Sº! Tº ‘º º' º' - -- Pier. Ha! what ſay'ſt thou? 'tis enough, , , , , There hangs a dreadful Tale upon thy Brow, … . . . . . And there’s ſome horrid meaning in that word—— . . . . Let thy dire Looks ſpeak all the reſt, I prithee; - Th’ haſt pierc’d quite through me like an Agué-Fit, - . Stopt every circling paſſage of my Blood, - And made me ſweat big drops as cold as ſte--" " , - - Say quick J. How fares thy Siſter? is ſhe well? . . . . . . . . . . My Love I my, Wife I Did I not call her Wife? . . . . . tº . Speak, Is ſhe living? Is ſhe dead? If ſo, . . . . . . . ~~. . . . And thou dar’ſ utter it! Plant thy dread Voice ºf , ºf . . . . . . . Juſt like a Cannon to thy Piercy's Breaſt, ºr 3 ºr ºf . , . " And ſhiver me to pieces. . . . . . . . . . . . -- Roch. By theſe words . . . . . . . . . , - “... . . . . ; º I find he knows not of my Siſter’s Marriage! LAſide. Still worſe and worſe!—Alas! my Lord, ſhe lives! ... [To Pier. Pier. Lives! oh the joy. But is ſhe ought than well? . . . . Tell it with ſpeed why didſt thou ſay, alas?-- . . . . . . a Kºch. Well ſhe is tºo... ...... . . . . . . . . . . . . . Pier. Then bleſſed be that Voice; . . . . . . . . . But why thou ſpeak'ſt it with ſuch cold reſerve, ~ I cannot gueſs. ... Oh tell it out with joy! . . . . . . . . . . Tell it aloud with ſhouting to the Spheres; º ºr That they may eccho with glad Harmony: “. . . . . Thy Siſter lives: my Bullen is in health. . . . . . . A Roch. She is in health: but . . . . . . . . * * Pier. Ha! but what? ſpeak out: . . . . . . . Why doſt thou torture me with dire ſuſpence?' ' ' ' '. If there be any thing can now be call’d Misfortune, . . . . . When thy dear Siſter is in health, out with it; Let it be worſe than Thunder, I can bear it. . . . . . . . . . . Roch. Alas! kind Pierey force not me to tell you, * * * * * Too ſoon you’l hear the News from one perhaps : That can relate it, Rocky as he is, - Without a Sigh or Tearin pity of you.' . . . . ; -- . Pier. You Heav'nly Pow’rs! What does my Rochford mean? . . . Methinks the joyful Tidings in my Breaſt, . . . . . . s That ſhe's in health, does thide me for my Fears; . . . . " ! - But then again a fatal heavineſs - - -º is . . . Streight intercepts this dawn of Comfort there, And like a Cloud hides all thoſe new-born Beams . . . . . . Of Hope, and bids me dread Î know not what, “ . . . *... --> →
Page 22

22 V E R 77) E. Betray'd: Or, I am in Hell, in Torments, worſe, in Doubt— . . . is there no Balſom that can cure this Sting? . . . . . . . . No Oedipus that can unfold this Riddle 2 " … . . . . . . . . ; 1 prithee, gentle Rochford, do not rack me : . . . - - - - - , . . . Take off this heavy Weight that ſinks thy Brother. . . . . . . Come, flatter me, if thou’rt affraid to tell The Truth, and ſay that all theſe killing words - Were not in Earneſt. .* - * -- - - - º Enter Northumberland. Koch. See, your Father's here, … . . . . . . Pier. He will take pity, and releaſe me ſure. North. Harry, thou art moſt welcome to thy Father; - r Welcome to all, and welcome to the King. - - Rejoice, my Son, and deck thy Face with Smiles: There’s Love and Fortune coming towards thee. - - Pier. Pardon me, beſt of Fathers ſpare my Anſwer: [Kneels. Oh tell me firſt what News is from my Love? - - - How does my Miſtreſs fare 2 and what’s become Öf Beauteous Anna Bullen f. quickly, Sir. ----, *, *, * : * , Nºrth. Why, what’s become of her ? She's very well. . . . . What ſhould become of her? She's Marry'd, Son. :: * Pier. Marry'd : - - - North. Marry’d l ay Marry'd, that ſhe is - * A Q-ſeen ſhe’s too, a joyful Queen, I tell thee. , ~ - Pier. Marry’d and to the King! by all my hopes, By all our chaſt, Eternal Vows of Love a It cannot be, although my Father ſays it;, You, whom l’le credit ſooner than an Angel. Marry’d my Anna Bullen falſe, and Marry’d Pei ſwade me that the Sun has loſt its Virtue, The Earth, the teeming Earth, forgot to bear, – That Nature ſhall be Nature now no more; . . . . . . . That all the Elements ſhall vaniſh ſtreight, (, , , Turn to Confuſion, into Chaos ſhrink, - . . . . . . And you, and I, and all the living World, . . Are what we were before we were begot; . . . All this muſt be, when Anna Bullen’s falſe. . . . • * * * North. I tell thee, raſh and diſobedient Boy, , , , . . . . . Marry'd ſhe is without ſuch Miracles. . . . . . . . . . . . . Pier. Ah, deareſt Father, on my Knees I beg you, ºr a Repeat that horrid, diſmal word no more; º To be obedient, and at once to hear . MI Miſtreſs wrong’d, is not in Piercy's power. . . Here, cruſh this inſºt, pound me into Duſt, , , l'in at your Foot! oh lay it on my Neck, , . * , º f--- ºs-L. - - - --------- º 3 * : . - - . And
Page 23

A N N A B U L L E N. And puniſh me with death, ten thouſand deaths; For whilſt I live I muſt be guilty ſtill, And near can think that Amna Bullen's falſe: O Sir, be inerciful and juſt at once, And ſay you did it but to try your Piercy. North. Riſe, and repent, and do not tempt my Anger, Which thou ſhould'ſt feel, but that I pity thee, And think thy Folly Puniſhment enough. Pier. See, Sir, her Brother’s more concern’d than I. To hear ſuch words. . Come, tell 'em, deareſt Rochford, Proclaim her Virtue loud as Cherubins, Tell 'em, theſe Rocks, they may in time relent, And hear the ſad Complaints of injur’d Honour: Is ſhe not Chaſt! Chaſt as the Virgin light, -$ 25 And conſtant as the Turtle to its Mate, - Her Perſon ſacred ſtill to all Mankind, And Beauties leſs corrupted, leſs defil’d, Than is the lovely Blew that fragrant hangs. . On Autumn Fruit, or Morning Dew on Roſes. - • North. Tell him, my Lord. - . Pier. Oh hear the Charming ſound; Tell’em, and undeceive 'em, Friend; tell 'em How thou wert by, when firſt we plighted Troths, And ſwore Eternal Faith, Eternal Love, By every Saint, and every Star that ſhone,: Who then look’d down as joyful Witneſſes, And darted forth in all their bright Array, To ſee our Loves that ſhin'd more bright than they. Gent. My Lord, the King and Queen are paſſing by. North. Look you, Romantick Sir, behold your Miſtreſs, Whoſe Bride ſhe is. [King and Queen, Lords and Ladies paſs over the Stage. Northumberland follows the King, Pier. By the Immortal:Powers that gave me life, And Eyes and Senſes to believe, ’tis ſhe - It is the King, and Anna Bullen Crown'd? Why Father, Rochford, Friends is it not ſo? And did ſhe not like haughty june walk P. - Who, as ſhe held the Thundeter by the hand, - Lookt down with ſcorn on the low World, from whence She came; ſo did ſhe caſt a loathing Eye - - ** upon the place where humble Piercy ſtands— Now you are mute, dumb as thoſe Conjurations You hir’d juſt now from Hell to be my Ruine; Ha! is't not ſo? Confeſs that it is ſo, - And I am bleſt; own it, and make poor Piercy happy. Rºck. Alas! my Lord; afflict your mind no more,
Page 24

- - * > A 24 V & R Tw E Betrayd: Or, 'Tis torment to your Friend to ſee you thus, Pier. Friend, ſay’ſ thou? I diſclaim that Name in all, In Father, Brother, Siſter, and Companion; - Nature her ſelf abhors it, like the Plague, And baniſhes that Gueſt from all her Creatures—- Falſe Brother to the falſeſt Woman living! . Was it for this that I was ſent from Court . . . Was it for this the ſubtleſt of her Sex - Sent me a Letter with ten thouſand Charms, , , To let me know that I ſhould write, and ſhould - Be written to no more till my return ? \ . * , ” x Tº avoid ſuſpicion, as ſhe ſaid; but 'twas To flatter me that I ſhould not miſtruſt her. * - Röch. By Heav'n, and all that's true, ſhe’s not to blame. Pier. Here, Rochford, rip, and tear her from my Heart, ‘Faſt rooted as ſhe is: The Poiſon ſwells, - - O lance it with thy Sword, and give me eaſe: - * * She's Hell! ſhe's worſe! ſhe's Madneſs to the Brain; I am poſſeſt, and carry an Hoſt of Devils: - For he that wears a perjur’d Woman here, Has in his Breaſt ten thouſand Fiends to ſcourge him. — ` . . Re-enter Northumberland. . . . : - North. Come, my beſt Son, the King Salutes thee, Piercy; Come, ſee the Bride he has prepar'd for thee, - And think no more of Anna Bullen now. - . . . . Pier. Ha! bring me to her ſtreight ! Is ſhe a Woman? . . . . A bright diſſembling and proteſting Woman . . * Smooth as the ſmiling pitileſs Ocean is by fits; . . . But then Her Heart as Rocky, deep, and fathomleſs: Has ſhe a Face as tempting as the fair Deceitful Fruit of Sodom, but when taſted, . . . . . . * Is rottenneſs and horröur to the Core ? . . . . Is ſhe ſo kind, that nothing can be kinder? Nay were ſhe Anna Bullen all without, And Bullen all within, I'd marry her - To be reveng’d r - North. Thou doſt rejoice thy Father : . . . . . . She is as good and beautiful as Angels, º And has ten thouſand Pounds a year; which added - To thy Eſtate, will make you far more happy han Harry with his Crown, or Auna Bullen. . . . . . . . . . Pier. Come, bring me to her : when ſhall we be marry'd? . . . . . . North. When my Son pleaſes: if thou wilt, to Morrow. . . . . . . ... Pier. To Morrow! Now: To Morrow is too late: . . . . . . what muſt 1 waſte a Day, and loſt a Smile ! . . . . . . - The
Page 25

A N N A BUL LEN. 25. The King with Bullen revels all this while, Haſte, thou ſlow Sun! when wilt thou bring the Morn? . . . . And when 1 oh when ſhall the long Day be worn 1 That theſe triumphant Arms may ſeize my Bride, . . . . . . . And claſp her gently like a wanton Tide. In Floods of Extaſies I’le drown; and ſay, Thus Harry and his Queen live all the day; Thus he embraces her all o're, and o're ; Whilſt for each Kiſs I’le reap a thouſand more: . . . And for each Pleaſure they ſhall act that Night . . . . . . I'le pattern then, and double with delight: . . . . . . But for that rareſt Bliſs we bluſh to own, - Spite and Revenge much more my Joys ſhall Crown. [Exeupt., ſ - - - - * . * - . . . , , , - - A CT III. SC E N E L . - - - Enter cardinal and Blunt ſeverally. A - - - _--" . . . card. IA II, to the Sacred Queen of Wit and Beauty; . . . . . . Ji Hail to the Empreſs of the World that ſhould be Blunt. What News? what Song of Comfort brings my Woolſey?: Methinks your Looks ſhine like the Sun of Joy, ". ". . . And Smiles, more glittering than your Robes appear: . . . . . . . . Come, for I long to be partaker of it— . . . . . . . - Say, is it Great f Shall Bullen ſink to Hell? . . . . . . . . . . . . . Shall this proud Exhalation vaniſh ſtreight ! . . . . . . . . . . . . Or, ſhall ſhe ſtill be Queen taffront my Woolſey'? … . . . . . . . Card. No - I'd firſt pawn both Body and Soul to Hell, . . . • Forºit a Dram of Poyſon that would kill : . . . . . - . . . . -- - Blunt. Oh famous Cardinall - - ‘. . . . . . . Rome’s Sacred Champion, and the Saints of Rome! What can reward thee but the Mytre here, And when th'art dead, a mighty Throne, as high As was great Lucifer's before his fall 2, . . . . . . . . - Card. Have I not liv'd more ſplendid than the King fº, More aw’d and famous than was Harry ſtill P. . . . . . . - * Have I not ſcatter?d with a Liberal Hand, - *- : * And ſow'd more Seed to Charity, than all . . . . ; ; ; , º The Kingdom elſe? Built ſuch waſt Palaces, . . . ; º' - tº sº. Tº As ºf either. Italy nor Rome can pattern? . . . . . . . . .''...' [...'. .*- : - tº Which England's Monarchs have been proud to dwell in... : :ºx Blunt. And but for thee, the Nation had been ſcorn’d, Card. Who fram’d ſuch ſumptuous Embaſſies, as I, With ſuch a Glorious Train of Servants deck'd, - - . As Germany and France both wonder'd as, 5 , , , ; :::... à ' '. And thought that all the Nation follow'd mesº. 9 : sº wi w * . . . º a - 1 Hºº'. - -------- --- : º
Page 26

26 VERTZ E Betray'd : Or, Whilſt Tudor here, as a leſs King than I, Was ſerv’d, but with the gleanings of my Pomp 2 - Blunt. 'Twas Woolſey, our Great Maſter’s greater Servi º ºr Who, as he rode to meet the Emperour, E’re he approach'd, firſt check'd his pamper'd Steed, . . . . And ſtood at diſtance to receive that Monarch; . . . . . . . Whilſt Maximilian, as became him beſt, - - Firſt did unlight, and firſt embrac'd my Woolſey. Card. And have not I rul’d Harry and the Nation Shall then this ſtrong Foundation of my Greatneſs : - Be undermin’d by ſuch a Wretch as Bullen - - - By the weak ptačtice of a ſpleenful Woman - A thing, that I have made ; a Poppet Queen, Dreſt up by me, to Aét her Scene of Greatneſs, And all her Motions guided by this Hand! . . . . . Blunt. Shall ſhe then Mount the Fame to ruine Woolſey? Card. No; by my Self, that moment ſhe attempts it, - She pulls a dreadful Tower upon her Head; - - When I begin to totter, if I muſt, . . . - *Like a huge Oak, that's leaning o're a Wall, I’le take my Aim, and cruſh her with my fall— Piercy's arriv'd, there's Aid for your Revenge. .* Blunt, I heard ſo, and perceiv'd it by the Queen. Card. By that ſhe has diſcover'd the deceit, a - And finds him Innocent, now ’tis too late; - . t This makes her careleſs, to her own undoing; . . . . For when the Amorous King comes, loaded with . . . Big hopes, and thinks to take his fill of Joys, . . . . . . . . . Streight, like the ſenſitive, nice Plant that ſhrinks, . . . . . And on a ſudden gathers up its Leaves, - " . . . When 'tis but touch'd, ſhe will contračther Charms, , , - And ſhut 'em from him in her ſullen Boſom, . . . . . . . . . As cold as Winter to his warm Embraces: This, when the vext and paſſionate King perceives, . . . . . . . . . He'll hate, and caſt her from him in a Rage. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Blunt. Seel yonders Rochford coming towards us, Big with glad Looks, I hope, to be deliver'd : . . . . . . . . . . Of ſomething that will forward our Deſign, . . . . . . .'; an " . . . Card. I will retire, and leave him to your Care, , , ; ; , , To mannage him with all the Art of Woman; ... . . . . . . . s. 1. And Hell, if Heav'n wont, inſpire your Wit. . . . . . * And Malice. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . [Ex. $.4 - * : . . - ; ; . * - . " * - - Enter Rochford. . . . . . . . . . . - Roch. Brighteſt of thy dailing sex, º º … ..., T. ...That wears the Charms of all the world about thee; ; ; ;... • * *** * *-* : * - - ~~ How

Page 27

ºr - A N N A BUL LEN., 27. How have 1 been this long, long hour in pain, ºcº jºd tº ºn ; ; In Torments and in Darkneſs all the while ! . . .s ºf'; Sun of my Joy, to waſte the tedious Bay, ſº, … ', ºf . , And Star to gaze the live-long-night away. : {3, tº ºivºd ºf ‘’’ Blunt. O, you are grown a Courtier now indeed, - a My Lord; but 'tis no wonder now, you are . . . . . . . . . . . Exalted, and are Brother to the Queen: , ; ; ; ; , º, … . . . .32 'Tis hard for one to gain a look from you, . . . . . Without the purchaſe of ++-I will not tell you-- ",".. . . . . Roch. Ha! Brother to the Queen! to jupiter. tº . . . . . . And if my raviſh'd Senſe deceives me not, . . . . . . . . I will not change my State to ſhine in Heaven! : . . . . . . . . . . To be the darling Brother of the Sun, tº cººl is gº ºf . Or one of Leda’s Twins that deck the Sky:::::: ... ºr ºf & No, Caſtor I defie thee. g.º.º. ººz. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Blunt. Hold, my Lord ; , , tº 3 s , , , , , , . . . . . . . . . I will not chide you, though you have deſerv’d it: . . . . . - For all thoſe Raptures are but ſtarts in Love, . . . . . . . . And ſeldom hold out to the Races end;3 . . * Or elſe like Straw that gives a ſudden blaze, sº . . . . . . . ºf And ſoon is Oute º tº tº o; sº, b : " : : sº tº sº. ºr º . ; Roch. Oh ſay not ſo, my Goddeſs!, so ºf tº gº i ! ... The Negro, neareſt Neighbour to the Sun, . . . . That lives under the torrid burning Line, ºr . . . . . . . . . . . Feels not the warmth that does poſſeſs my Breaſt. - * * - And, oh forgive the vaſt Compariſon, 2 ... . . . - Hell's flame is not ſo vehement or laſting. g.º.º. ºf . . . . . . . Blunt. Enough, my Lord: I’le put you to your Trial: º, . . ; Prepare, and ſee how well you can obey; sº . ~ * . . ." But that you may not ſtrive without all hope, - - Like Slaves condemn’d for ever to the Gallies; . . . . . . . . . Here is my Hand, an Earneſt of my Promiſe, . . . . . . . . . . . • That as I find you Faithful, Ple Reward you... . . tº º, . .'; , , Koch. Your Hand! where ami-letell me, I God of Love!, sº Blunt. But mark me: Hear, as from a Prophet, this: ' ' '. Be ſure you merit well this firſt of Favours, . . . . . - -- And keep the Oath you vow upon this Hand, . . . . . . Elſe I'le denounce a worſe than Hell ſhall follow º sº tº tº º, . . **'. -- * * * . . . . . . - - - tº - --, --> º 'º - . . …' . . * - -, -- Your Sacrilegious Crime. …sº ºn ºf , º, . . . . . Sº, Roch. Lo, here I ſwear guidi was ſº. a . . . * **** - - - - But tellime, Heav'n '...what ſignifies an Oath? . . . ºil c. …sº When 'tis impoſſible I ſhould be falſe f : . . . . . . . . . . . . I ſwear upon this Altar, breathing Incenſe! . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Eternal Love! Eternal Conſtancy— ; c. c. tº : y : * : Divineſt, ſofteſt—Sweeteſt——t tº 13, CKiſether Hand. , Blunt, Go my Lord... cºg ºs; , ; ; ; ; sº ºf ºf And now you have it, brag to my undoing; . . . . . . º. º. -- ...; e For

Page 28

Z To ſell it for a falſe and glittering Trifle: ... º. ºf ." . Miſtruſt of her you Love:oi long to hear : 5.9 ſ ºn tº - * , «- - 28 VERT!?/ E. Betray'd:0r; - For never any but your King can boaſts ºf , ºf 2:1 moºd i ºf wººl The like. :::::::: ºº ii. 2; ii., tºi i Ens 2: Haig tº at Roch, And he, th’ º: Mänkind; ºr:w ci rºot tº 3 nire Who having ſuch a Jewel in s Breaft, ºi-ºji º ºsº ºn ºf:g ºf h The Crown not half ſo Sacred, were it mine, , , , , , tº . . - º * , * . . . . . . . So ſilly Indians barter Gold and:Pearls itſ ºf ºilº ºth Þjº º iſºx: For Baubles. tº ºf 3291 i is ºf ºc gº tº 2: Blunt. What your Siſter, treach’rous Man #33 ºf fººtº ºil gººd: #7 You do not mean it; nor can I endure itſ ºf 63 ºf icºi sº sº. To hear her ſo degraded; if 'twere real: º, º º Sh’ has Goodneſs, and has Beauties more than I,’ ºr a sº And much the more, becauſe.ſht foughtºntt formit; I tº 3. … 19 Which is the cauſe, 1 fear, that ſhe's unhappy-i-kº I tºº ºr ºf You viſit her, not only as a Brother, ; # ºf ºd tº H. º.º. But as a Friend, and Partner of her Councils; ºn iſ ºf . , ; You Love like Twins, like Lowers, or indeed is tº ' ' is tº As a fond Brother, and kind Siſter, ſhould 3ſix of Jºo his rºll ºf A, How bears ſhe this unwelcome $tateſºur rathers ::: y : 138 : i. 3 tº 30 Hoſt does ſhe brook the wrong that’s done to Piercy *.iſio zi ſco Bºº. Roch. All her Reflections on it'ſfreight willivaniſt; º; tº "…. A King and Crown are Charms invincible;','º', ºn ... º. º." No Storms, nor Diſcontents can long abide; 2 tº efix -º ºf sº tº Where Love and Empire plead: but ſapn-will flye; in sº gº ºf . . . Scatter'd like Miſts before the Sunrofiñower fº'oſi. 9;iº tº ... it, Blunt. You ſpeak indifferently, näy 9and likdom ºf stºri, a tº º! .º.º. The more what you would fain diſguiſe from me— , , , º, . " Have you ſo ſoon forgot the Oath you took?” ºn wººl ºv, , , , ,º And merits what ſhe does poſſeſs, acCrown ºvati giºiºsº. 253 cºg w Or isºt ſo lately, that you think’tis ſcarce : ; ; bº.cºod 2 sit ºf Reach'd down to Hell, to claimiyou Perjur’d there? bus ºf 2: … tº Or think you that I e're can hate the Siſter, ºil.i..', tº hiſ ºf . , ; When with a bluſh I own, I love the Brother?..iº, ºbſt. 1.9'ſ tº Falſe and ungrateful Man #ifarewelli. 25 ºf : an iſºerſ, sº tºº, Koch, O ſtay ! ... gº- d … ii 4.... ſ.v. 2.; tº . . . . .3 And read what e're you thinkis written there, how is ºne ºf 33 Had I no Tongue to ſpeak, I’d ſuffer that, .orgiº aſſºliº & Tuo'ſ Rather than once deny you any thing. ——nsavā i &ix: 0.1 º' Blunt. He ſoftens, turns; and sºlº <taff iſeſi. His waxen Soul begins to melt apades. 2. LI.e., f : . . . *** . . . ii... c...' ... º. ºv Oh that I had but Harry ſo to torture bus:ticſ: 's is:# :2y:3 said: but ºrévénéºny ſelf on this-ſoft-Foči;23, 2–-ſºld floſiivići Qn Ballen, and on all their Race at once .º. I vºn co.º. that were the Curſed cauſe of injundoing gºd ºiºsidoº won f:A w . -- - - º - -- You: Rip open my Boſom to my naked Heart, wººl ºf fiz-C ºn tº it. A He is my Slave, my Chain’d and Gally Slave...º. 3 ºf dog, sº I -







Page 29

/ . . . . ANNA, B.J L LEN, 29 , - ~ 2. You hear he's come to Court, and what you learn * -- - Y. * - ºr a You find my Paſſion and good Nature quickly,'... . . [To Roth. That makes you uſe me thus.... . . . .” *** - gº is º ºs. 3. --- :#3 jº ‘. * - * * - - iºſ º-'--~ … : : - - - - Roch. Ten thouſand Pär ășiiliº: "º ºvº º Blunt. No more; ſcan forgive, if you deſerve it; ºniº, bºx I charge you, as a Sign of your *:::::::::: - Go viſit ſtreight the Queen, and Piercy too; From them, that ought copcerns their §. love -- " sº From time to time, acquaint me with the Story, ºr ºf And you ſhall lock the ſºrtimãº º sº jºº ºf Asſaf, as in your ºwpº hº # º ** tº gº - Roch. 'Twere Blaſphemy, “’” º: º *i;ºvº But to ſuſpect it. . his c t; º, º - Blunt. I require thi }}]; ...: '..." ": “”, - -º Not that I . the º "the ſeen," *:::: ºil ºf ºf But know, that, worſe thai Hell, f hate th Miſſ , º ºſcº º (To which juſt hatred 'tis jºš 3}º 11 ºil 1 .º.º. - - - - - - -- - - - - - - * - - *** **---------> wi... . . . . . , º, … . .” -> * > . . . . . . . . - *-*... its tº º, . . . . . º, . . . . ; s - - - * * **** ºf • r \;\, * And wiſh your Siſter, and all Humane kind,” sº tº Would hate him too. º 'º - ºr ºf Roch. I’le inſtantly obey you.’’ ‘’’,º º 'º' cº ºr. * , ---, * * * , , ºº i ! . . . * * ***s----> --- * - Blunt. Come back, my Lord; t º: eſs has Char 'd me: 3. now I can’t but give you # - * - ou may have leave to viſit me herea r. rº ºth ºf ºil iſ ºr And talk of love, perhaps I’le take it kindly: *** cº won tº Koch. Bleſt Harmony! Happieſt of Mankind, I.' ' ' - - Blunt. And you may write tº me, and beſt by Proxy: , , , - . For tho’ the King hôt viſits mê; as he was wont, sº Yet he is Jealous *** * is of tºtal ºils tº A Let all your Amorous Letters be diſguis'd, º ! iºniº - - - under the borrow'd Name of Brother ſtili," " ' " º Direéled to me by the ſtile of Siſter, ' ". . . . . . . . . . . . s Roch. In all things I’ll obey my lovely Goddeſs! . . . . . w - Blunt. Theſe Papers once ſhall be of *Conſequence, [Aſide. See, the Queen comes, her Soul in º * * * * *ETo Roch. and longs to be disbärtfiend: t I}, i #. ‘dºwſki's you—º A fit occaſion’s offer'd, flow. *ś, nºi ... " " " -- - The Rack, to eaſe her by a fond Confeſſion. . . [Ex, Blunt. ºf sº tº º - - - * Enteroicºn and Ladieſ. nter Queen and Ladies: “ . . . . . . . . . a trº § :*:: dº ... r.; … ... . . . : My Brother? Is it you; , ; *::: ,23:9. rºº aſſº º, . . . ; Queen. Where am I now ºf I hear that Piercy’s come to * === - . . . . Roch. He is. ºº: º, .º - Queen. Where ſhall I hide my gº ilty Face from hi * * * : . . . And ſhut me where he ne'er may £eme more? & . . . . . . For now, I ſtart at every §§ Shape, --- vº 3. … • And think I meet wrong’d ### - à º º º fº * * - sº. . - " **Y*##1 bºº! …", "tº gº. Like Sº º 3 ºf l - * *







Page 30

30, VERTUE Betray'd : or, Like one eſcap'd for Murther, in his Flight "... . . Shuns every Beaſt, and Trembles at the Wind, º ºr: And thinkach Buha Mantºpfriend him. Hº. * * * ***.....!---- w ic ºf . . . .” * -: , ; Enter Diana.' * * * * * ºn - - - - - - * - " - 2. --- * : *. - * ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ** * * ~ * - - - - - - I ſent thee to the Queen, Diana, ſay, º - How fares ſhe in her hopeleſs, loſt Eſtate . . . . . . . . . . . . What Anſwer bring'ſt thou, that is Death to hear? . . º. Come talk of Miſery, andfill my breaſt tº cº º With Woe; Ple lay my Ears to the ſad ſound, " " " ' ". . . . And thence Extračt it as the Bees do Hony, " ' ". . . ." . . - º is * Food º: the afflićted live #T.T. º, 'alk anything; there's naught ſo dreadful as:"... ', " : * * . . . The thoughts É injur'd #: T. º º I afi, 7 ºf - Diam. The Princeſs Doma ris, d: id..... ." & " - iſ, ºº:: º eſs Rºdgiris dead..." ". . . . . . Queen. What Princeſs? ... '" ºf … * * * * * : ) Art thou a temporizing falſe one too?” jº And haſt ſo ſoon forgot ſº was thy Queen? ... "... " º . ...” #in. Oueen Kathering's ... . . . . .” Nº ºr 9 - wº. #. §. ! § ... ºf º 3 * Then ſhe has got the ſtart of Ahma Bulleh-, * * º bº A Came you too late to pay my pity to her?...º.º. º. ºf Diaſ. No: for ſººnjoyā her senſes to the laſt,” ſº tº it 7, -- 3: . . . . * . . And then not ſeem'd to dye, but fall aſleep." ' " " " . 2ueen. So bold is Innocence, it conquers Death, And after makes amends for all the wröngs " " …" ". . . . . ; Suſtain’d in Life. “. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Dian. When I began totelſ her, " . . . . . . . ." I came by your command, to make a tender Of your moſt humble Duty, and Condole Her Majeſties Misfortune and Diſtemper; . - She check'd me at that word, and as you have ſeen . . . a A clear Sky, with a travelling Cloud o'retook, 2. And quickly gone, ſo ſhe put on a Frown, ..." . . . . . . . Which did not laſt, and anſwer'd with a Smile: " ' ". . . Why did you ſay, your Majeſty to me," . . . . .” ----- - - - She ſaid, a name I loath? Go, tell your Queen, Let her º: Ori ...: be happy, "' - - - But take a ſad. Example:hese by me: ; , , , , , , ..... I, who was j §:###: º.º. ºJ tºº, To three great Émperours, and Wife, alas f*** ***, * : To the moſt potent Prince in Chriſtendom, . . . . . . . . Muſt Dye more wretched than the meanºgreatºr. º In a ſtrange Country, 'midſt my Enemiès." * ºf w arm ºf Li A. Not one of all my great âtio shere. º: airfi wºn toº 2:30 pity me, nor ſº. * Bedoja *::::: ; 3 ºi: t: . . ; * * * 4 -** ~ *
Page 31

- ANNA BUL LEN. 35 And then ſhe wept, and turn'd her gentle Face º - † : . . . The other way, and quickly after dy’d. . . . . . . . . Queen. Go on; why doſt thou ceaſe this Melody ? . . . . . . . . Thy voice exceeds the mourning Philomel; ; * The dying Swan takes not that pleaſure in . . . . . . . Her note, as I in ſuch Celeſtial Muſick : Haſt thou no more of it 2 . . . . . - . Come play the Artiſt : Shew thou to my Fancy, ºr ºr Th’ Infernal Paths that lead to infinite Horror; . . . . . . . . . s. . Op'n all the Charnel Houſes of the Dead, ... . . . . . . . And fright away, if it be poſſible, . . . . . . . The ſad remains of injur’d Piercy here. . . . . . . . . . "tºp--aa. e - - - - - [Exeunt Diana and Rochford. King. Yonder ſhe is, in Tears amidſt her Glories! º You laviſh Stars, what will content this Scorner P. . . . . . . . . . . From a mean Spring l took this ſhining Pebble, And plac'd her in my Heart, and in my, Crown, , , , , The faireſt and the beſt lov’d Jewel there: . . . . . . . And ſate her on my Throne to be ador’d.: . . . . . . . . Yet ſhe contemns all this, and would do more, º, . º The Heavens are all too narrow for her Soul . . . ." Gods, you muſt flatter and deſcend to her, , , Or ſhe’ll not ſtir one jot to you - *.- She is. - - - - So very proud. - - ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . - guern. My Lord.... . . . . . . . . . . . . - King. Sit down again, - a I but diſturb you; therefore l’ll return; . . . For ſure they muſt be tender thoughts, for which . . . . . . You pay ſuch laviſh Tribute from your Eyes. Queen. Sir, I was thinking of th’ uncertain State . . . . . . . . - Of Greatneſs, and amongſt its ſad Misfortunes, , , , , , What wº. of me, alas! if you . . . . . . . . . . . . (Which I’ve no reaſon to ſuſpect) “ . . . . . . . Should change your Love ; and that produc’d theſe Tears. . . . . King. Y'are in the right, if that ſhould ever happen;––– But what begets ſuch doubts within your breaſt 2," You have done nothing to deſerve ſuch fears: . . You love me, and as long as that ſhall laſt, , , , , , - Miſtruſt not Harry. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - * -- - Q4een, by my hopes 1 do. . … . . * : King, Bléſt ſound. I will hear nothing but my. Bullen : - Woolſy and Devil tempt me now no more | . . . . [4ſide. Then ſhake theſe Clouds of ſorrow from thy Eyes. . . . . . And dart thy brighter beams, like Arrºl Sun-ſhine, . . . . -- - * . . . . . . . . Inte.
Page 32

- 32 y E Frv E Betraya; or, into thy Boſom, and thus lock me ever— º ºſ. º Oh, now I nought remember but thy Charms, * * * * * * ~ * And quite forget what-e’er I was before..." . . . . . . . . . . ) One word of Bliſs, one word of Softneſs from thee, 3. * : : To baniſh hence Suſpitions, like the Plague, ; ; ; ; ; , . ." And clear our Breaſts from jealouſies for ever— is What, not a ſyllable do I deſerve 2 ‘. . . - . . . . . . ---- Theſe Kiſs, faint Embrace, and theſe odours, sº ºn 3 Are raviſh'd, not beſtow'd upon me—ha! º, º ſº, ſº ºf . Queen. What means my Lord *"...º. ºf ſº, : 1 is tºo King. What means the Traiterous Bullen?.... ºrs : * ~ * By Heav'n ſhe wants the tunning Trick and Skill; … . . . . . . . ; The eaſie quick Deluſion of her Sex, `- To hide her falſeneſs—By’all Hell ſhe's damn'd. º gueen. O-Gracious Sir. Nay in the very Moment of Enjºyment; King. Too grations not to kin thee—gº tº º But guard your fatal Hony with a Sting a 2, ... g . . . . . of acy 'Gainſt thoſe you hate Your Perſon you reſign, . . . . .ifſ. But as to Priſon ; my Arms are but the Grates . . . . . . . . Through which your mind is longing ſtill to be abroad ; ; . . . ." . . . . And who would think but then P ſhould be happy? . . . . nº A 3 * * * * . There's ſtill another's Piétèreiniyeur heart, "" ; , just pla * On which you look and fanſie, I am he, For whom, for whoff, are your kind looks reſerv'd?: 2 pºsſ ºf Hide you your Minion; for his ſafeguard, do. . . . . sº sº... I For were he’mongſt his happy Stars, I’d reach him. . . . . . . . I’m frightful as a Ghoſt, or à Diſeaſe: to ads ºf lºsi ºr For when I think to hold her in theſe Arms, ... tº iºd sº brå She ſtruggles like the Quarry in the Toll º' ºr tº gº nº gº And yields her ſelf unto my leath’d embraces, . . . … . . …T. With ſuch a forc'd and awker'd willingneſs, . . . …, As men, when they are paſt all hopes of life, . . . . . . . . Reſign themſelves into the power of Death. . . . . . . . c2 Queen. What Fiend has put ſuch thoughts into your Breaſt Pº. When did I wrong you? How have 1 been falſe fºr 12 º' Yet I will not complain againſt my Lord.” . . . . . . . . ºf 4. Since ’tis your Will—Sir, have I not obey'd you? . . . ; No Slave ſo humbly faithful to your Pleaſures, . . . . . And in your Bed, with bluſhing paid thoſe Duties . . . ). That modeſt Virgin, or chaſt Wife could do: º, … 's ºf it? . And if I was not wanton,"pray forgive me. . . . . .'; w ºff ºf King. Yes, yes, I have your outſide; but Hell knows, ºriº) And thy falſe ſelf, who 'tis enjoys thy Soul! 9 ºº You yield to meindeed, °tis true: but moſt e. Y ~ * llnwillingly you part with your dear Sweets, ºn a tº llnleſs it be to him that has your Hoard, º iſ . . . . . ºved tº - And |

Page 33

| , Are come to paſs, ºr gººd ºf ºf - *- My Fears by Day, and horrid Dreams by Night; …, ; : C And tell her Face to Face the Perjuries ºf roº, sº And Falſeneſs that ſh’ has heap'd upon her Soul, ... gy What ſhall I do !--—Begone, this place . . . . ANN A BUL LEN. 33. And all the while I'm ſporting for another. : y : ºv. … sºft. º. 2ueen. Can Heatºo hear this! O cruel, faithleſs Lord. ... º. King. No: to thy Syren's Voice. I’ll ſtop my ears;.… s iſ , , , ; A thouſand times, liks; them, th’haft cheated me, ºn 323 wº, Laid my juſt Paſſion to a gentle Calm, wºº tº -º Whilſt Storms behind were ready to devour me. º . . . . . . . . On thy falſe dangerous Charms I'll wrack no more, sº . . . . . ; But ſeek for ſhelter on ſome kinder Shore; ; ; , , º º' aii ºº, A grateful Beauty here ſhall Reign alone, ºr tº "… w And chace thee from my Heart, and from thy Throne, ſº º oſſi º A Ha! who comes there 2: My gentle Woolſey come, . . . . . . . ºn ºf And with thy Counſel ſtreight defend my Breaſt. Nº . . . . ~. A [The King meets Woolſey, and goes out leaning on him. Queen. Did not my Lord flye from me in a rage, tº 3: Tº ſº; Arm'd with a Frown, and darted it quite through me?...sº tº gº ºn.’, And Woolſey in his Favourites place again? ... ſº tº a tº dº ſº, I' Nay, then the Wonder is expir’d; that proud, 1.33 ± gº i.i./ That great bad man, and Lucifer ne'er meant , - Me nor my Virtue well—The Kings inconſtancy - * Begins to ſhews its janus Face again: * * And all the Doubts of an unhappy Wretch, ºr tº - - _* < * * * * * 8 : º3 .º. 26ſ; gºi iº * , fººt ºf Eºf. * - - * - - . . . ." -, * -- - - - * -- * - ** -- - - - - --~ :"... . - t ... gº ºr . . .--> * 3 : . . sº -- s º . Enter Piercy, -- . . . . - l , ! & - - - - - - -- - -- . . • *- - * Pier. What ſhall I fear to ſee her tº ºils: i Iſ gºs . . . . . " Yº! # . . . . . . º. is 3.0 ºil ºf ... º.º. And ruin’d mine?——Lo, where the falſº one is ºr In counterfeited Grief? By Heav’n in Tears! . . . . . .31% º , - a : . . . . . . .” - ºr tº . ~ * - - - - - - - - - - - - * * . . . . . . . As if her ſins already did upbraid her! . . gº tº sº, sº Juſt Pow’rs can you behold at Form ſo fair, , ; ; ; ; ; cº sº. And ſuffer falſeneſs to inhabit there 2 --~~1.3 : His lºgº; ; The Morning Sun riſen from its watry Bed, tº gotº ºvºst' to: Leſs precious drops does on Arabia ſhed: ' ' ' tº sº sº.” tº And ſacred Viols of rich April-Showers; , ; ; ; ; ; sº tº: When he alternate Rain and Sun-ſhiné pours; g-fººd tº ºf ſ. Nor is he half ſo Beautiful and Gay, ºu º ºsº ºil: o, º As ſhe a wiping of thoſe Tears away-ºff: gài is ejºo ºr Queen. Ha, Piercy! I’m betray’d. Adviſe—me-Heav’ālºt º' is Hell jejo ‘i ºff ºf Vipers and Adders lurking under ſmiles, tºº. 9, º 'º And flatt’ring Cloths of State: Oh! dondt ſtreadiheit yiºs og acrº llnder this Mask of Gallantry and Beauty, fººt sº I ºf C. Is a rude Wild; nay, 'worſe, a dangerous ºcean; jºuſt you; to Into whoſe Jaws, Love, like a Cºlgatūrºl. 2d 10ſ. Isſa I is...; ** as - - - - - *.*.*.*--- Will. "…” z - * * *



Page 34

34 V & RTZ/ E - Betray'd: Or, will tempt us, where we both muſt ſink and periſh. y : 1 I. : :º Pier. What, can ſo mean a Creature fright a Queen tº C vº. Sº, Behold a wretched thing of your undoing. . . . . . ºf iſ . A Queen. See where he ſtands, the mark of pity, Heav'n't * A --- Shut, ſhut thy eyes, and fly with ſpeed away; . . . t Or view the Rocks and Quick-ſands, if thou ſtay, * = . . . . . . . Ç Left this rough Helliſpont I, venture on, , ; 2 and like Leander tempt my Fate, and drown—º . [Ex gºd - Pier. Ha! ſhe's ſurpriz'd ſhuns me! and flies from me !? - ". And more affrighted. is at Piercy’s wrongs, gº … e. . º.º.º. A Than guilty Ghoſts, that have ſcap'd to Earth, ºn ! Hear the Čock crow to ſummon 'em away, . . ºº, And ſtart and tremble at the fight of day. . . . . . . But yet ſhe look’d not like a Foe upon me; * : * : * : *º And as ſhe parted, told me with her Eyes, . . . . . . º. ii. . . . . . That there was ſomething in thoſe ſpeaking Tears, sº ºrá . . ; Which might Excuſe her, and Condemn her Piercy. … . Emir Northumberland. . . . -- -- * } - -- - - - - - , iſ * 1: {}T : . . . . --- Nor. Son, I am come to tell you joyful News, -> ** * * . . . . f - **- : * * * **** The King has Charm'd the fair Diana to thee, ºf , º, . . . . . . . . . . And is reſolv’d to Marry her to Morrow, . . . . . . . . . . . .” And Celebrate the Nuptials with a Pomp, Pier. The King! the King is marry’d, Sir. North. He is. - - But thou art not : H’intends to give her to thee I. Aſ º' Himſelf: Why doſt thou ſtart: 'Twas but this day ºf it. Eup. * You ſwore and vow'd, with all the ſigns of Joy, sº º ºf bºº, And Duty to your Father, you'd obey, me. . . . . . . ; - * . . . ----- - - - . . . . - - Pier, Alas! I did; but cannot Heavºn, nor you 9, * * Forgive a raſh, unhappy Man his Wow 2 ºf jº. ºf ºil, ºil ſºil fi : * > North. No.: by the blood that honours-Piercy's Veins, ... cº ſº. I ſwear, I will not—— ºf: -, i..... For Marry'd thou ſhalt be, and that to her, tº 4, 2 gº tºº ºf . Or live a Vagabond, baniſh’d from Wealth, , , . . . . . . From Friends, and Pity; whilſt I will advance . . . . . And ſee thee ſtarve; nay, more, and loaded with c. tº ºf iºniſ. The Curſes of thy Father—as tº ºf ºc gº.º. 3 ºil ºf Pier. Hold, Sir?----, tº -ºº::... tº tº . , six .ſº * * * * * * * > . . . What Miſery, or Death can do to me; . . . tº A L., & Nor to avoid the hungry:Lyon's Den, ; i.e. . . . . Jºr. 3: Or Dragon's Teeth, juſt ready to devour me; is a ºil: º, . For know, I plungfinto azState more dreadful. . . ; ºf 9... zi But that l may not be thºnhappy Cauſe... . . . . . g., ..., Gilii ſº of { ... Thy Younger Brother to thy loſt Eſtate, is , : A º º * * * * * I'll ſtrive tº obey you; not becauſe I fear 2 -- 0: , ; " it.... . . . . . . . ºf biº A



Page 35

ANNA BULLEN. 35 Of dragging wrongful Curſes from a Father, Which rather turn upon his Head that aims, Than hurt the Boſom of the Innocent. Enter Diana. / . North. Seel ſhe is coming, brighter than a Goddeſs— 2. - I’le leave you, and commit you to her Cure. [Ex. North. Dian. Yonder’s the dear-lov’d Man, whom all muſt love, - That loves another too. What ſhall I ſay? . [Aſide. Spite of my Stars, I dote upon a Perſon, .* • Who has no Heart, no Eyes that are his own; Nor yet one look that ever can be mine. ſ Pier. Madam I d'you hear the news? My Father tells A-. W’are to be Marty'd. - Dian. So the King will have it. Pier. The King! what would the Tyrant be a God? To take upon him to diſpoſe of Hearts! And joyn unequal Souls with one another l O Beautiful Diana: Y’are all Goodneſs, A ſtore of Virtues in as bright a Perſon, - - As Heav'n e're treaſur’d in a Form Divine: . . . . . . . If ſo, what can your Eyes behold in me? What ſee in ſuch a wretched thing as I, - To Marry me 2 - - Diam. How Charming is his Perſon! - - And much more Charming is his Grief! Andoh — * . . How can ſhee're receive a Wound more deadly, - [Aſide. Than I, tormented with the double Dart - Of Love and Pity— Some kind Deity . . . . . . . . z Aſſiſt me now, leſt I ſhould ſhew I love him, * * s -- And teach my Tongue how to bely my Heart. . . Pier. You ſeem to ſtudy for ſo plain an Anſwer. - - : Come tell me ſtreight my faults, and what you think; For here I ſtand, the Mark of Truth to aim at. What is there, in this miſèrable Shape, -- To look on without Scorn ? Dian. Now kind Heav'n, - Lend me the Cunning now of all my Sex! - [Aſide. I like you juſt as well as you like me; [To Piercy. Our Perſons might, for all you ſaid of mine, Be anended both, and both receive Additions: And for your Nature, Ple be plain, and tell you, I could have wiſh’d a Man of better humour; But 'tis no matter, ſince ware both ſo bad, We are the fitter then for one another.' ' - Regal what miſèrable Thisºns: º : [4: \- . .
Page 36

-- > We'll moan, we’ll ſigh, we’ll weep; we’ll a ... You that y’are Marry’d—— / To make us happy both againſt our Wills; 36 ... WE R Tºy E. Betrayd: Or, Oh! when ſhall we attain that bleſt abode, . . . . Where we may never fear to ſpeak aloud, , , , , What's Juſt, and is no Sin? " . . . . . . . Pier. What, do you hate me?" " ' " Then y’are happier one Degree than I; - For ſhºuld you love me, you are truly wretched. * * * * | º --- , - - - , * - > * * * * * * - - - - - e , - ºn . . .* : - - - - - - - -- * * * * * * Din Indeed he little thinks I am that Wretch. . . . . [4ſide. - Tell me wherefore ? Pier. Becauſe the Cruel God . . . . . . ; Has rub'd me of my whole Eſtate of Love, And leſt me naked, deſolate, and poor ; - t Not worth one Sigh, nor Wiſh, if that could pay The Slebt I owe: Nay, ſhould you come a begging, . Cold, and half ſtarv'd, for Sutcour to my door, * . You would not find, in all this rifled Cottage, . . . One Spark, one Charitable Spark, to warm you. [To Piercy, -- - - º - * * * Dian. Hºar, Heav'n hear, Cruel One who-e’re thou art He loves, tho’ I am ſlighted, ſcorn'd, nay hated, , , , Wou'd thou hadſt my Kind Eyes, my Breaſt, my Soul, Would all my Vital Blood were Balm to Cure him. Yet will our Cruel Parents have us Marry'd : . . [To Piercy. Then, ſince we muſt, how know we but our Bodies,. . . . And yet more Careleſs and Deſpairing Souls, - in time may grow to ſuch Indifference, As quite forgetting of what Sex we are, We may like faithful and condoling Friends, lf not like Lowers, live together. . . . . . . . Pier, Ay; -- - , , , -- - - - - - º, - - - And when y'are ſad, I'lº Kiſs you like a Brother; And if you ſigh, cr chance to ſhed a Tear, I will weep too, and ask you why you grieve; And you ſhall do the like to me, and ſtreight £nbrace me like a Siſter, ſtill remembring . . . . The Sabjećt of our juſt Complaints ſhall be, Diaw. You for Marrying me. Pier. O rarely thought ! "twill be the only Means laſtead of loving, pity one another. . Dian. And who can tell but Pily ma By gentle, ſoft Degrees, grow up to Love. . . . . . Pier. Come, let’s away then, ſince they’ll have it ſo; * , Meet theſe glad Rites to all Mankind but us, : - *... " . * - *** * * * * * ** ... 2 tº Where the malicious Charm ſhall joyn our Curſes, , … º. Ard not our Perſons, but our Woes together : ..." - . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - ll but love--- . . . . . . y at laſt, . . º … . . ... [Afte, . - * * * ºn trius iſ likºtºcºmº writis; - * * * * A - - ~ --- *, * * w º ! * : * > * * * * - - - * > . . ~~ - :: * > . . . . . *- - - * , - * : b. Q is Baniſht

Page 37

- - A N PV fl 15 U L L E N. . . . , Baniſht from Earth, no Creature but our ſºlves, . . . . . In an old Bark on wide and Deſart Seas, . . . . . . . . . " .. In Storms by Night and Day, unſeen by all, unpity'd toſt, not one dear Morſel with us . . . . . . . . • To eaſe our Hunger, nor one drop of Drink To quench our raging Thirſt, and which is worſe, Without one jot of Rigging, Sail, or Steer to guide us. -- Dian. Forgive me, Heav'n? Forgive me all my Sex, . . . . [Affat. That ever lov’d, or ºre was ſtorm'd like me! Tho' 'tis my Fate for ever to be hated, . . . . . Tho' we are doom'd to dwell, like wandring Wretches, In worſe than what his worſt of Sorrow paints; . . . . - | Yet I muſt love him, and reſolve to Marry him ; º ~ And now 1 challenge all the wondring World, . . . . . And more admiring Angels, if they can, , , . . . . . . . . . . To find who moſt is to be pity’d. He . . . . . . . . . Or I—Quick, let us launch then with a Courage, ... [To Piercy. Since ’tis our King and Cruel Parents Wills. . . . . - Pier. And give a rare Example to the Marry'd, Of Conſtancy: For that which ſevers them, - - --~ * ~ *-*. Poſſeſſion of their pall'd and loathºd Enjoyments, Our faithful Woes ſhall joyn our Lives the faſter. Dian. And having each of us ſo mean a Stock Of love, I in your Breaſt, and you in mine; . . . * - We need not fear that Thieves ſhould come to rob us.. . . . . . . . . . Pier, Nor Jealoufie to partus. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Dian. Well then, Pierry: . . . . . . . . - When our expečted Sentence is perform’d, , , . . . . . . . . . .” - Where ſhall we take our welcome Baniſhment? . . . . . . . . . . - Pier. To the World's End?. Far from all fruitful Grounds, . . . . . - From Corn, and Wine, or any wanton Spring, , , , , . . . . . In ſome dead Soil, ſo barren and ſo curſº, º , , . . . . . . . . . . - Where neither loathſom Weeds, nor Thiſtles:grow. . . . . . . . . . . . Dian. Or ſome deep Cave, Where Winds are all ſo ſtill, .."; 1 c : > * .. * * : * - I - - - * . . . * * * > . . . . ~ * ~ * - - - And Biaſts ſo far remote, that we ſhall hear . . . , , . . . . . . No Howls, nor Groans, but what we make our ſºlves. . . ." ºs Pier. No: on ſome dreadful Rack we'll chuſe to lye, s. 5. Whoſe diſmal Top ſeems faſten’d to the Skye; , , , , , , , Thence we can look on all the World below, So full of Vanity, ſo full of Woe! ! sº, And ſometimes on the Wrack devouring Seas, The Emblem of our preſent Miſeries: " " . . . . . . . . . . Sigh for the Creatures, think the Storms weſte . . . . . . . . . . Our Cruel Parents, and the Wretches We, . . . . . . . . . Dian. Or waſte our Days in wandring to and fro, a 1. . . ; , - . And make our Lives one Harmony of Woe..…; ; ; ; , ... . . . . w Pier. Till Heav'n ſhall rain down pity on us—- ..º.º. - - - - F 2 – - Diºni * : , ; ; ; ; ; , , º, ºr 3. -- ... - - - " " - - * : *, * : * : * : *, *.* * -
Page 38

- - - - - - -ver w “... wº, - Dian. No. - - . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .'' we'll not be pity’d. Pity's half a Cure; , , , , . . . . . That will bring Comfort, which we’ll ne’re endure. . , - . ; Pier. O my Virago Partner. ; : . . . . . . . ... ." 1)ian. Nay, I dare you. - - - º, St. Pier. Then here we'll take an Oath, and with this Kiſs Let’s ſtrike a League with woe, adieu to Bliſs! - And now I challenge the All-ſeeing Sun, - . . . . . . From his proud Proſpect, his high Seat at Noon; . . . . . . . *Mongſt all the wonders of the World, to ſpy . . . . . . . . A Couple half ſo kind as thee and l; Or all the Matches that e're Love decreed, . . . . . . . If ever Man and Wife ſo well agree’d. .. - Love oft-times flies from Miſery and Pain; , , , . . . . . . . But we reſolve the cloſer to remain. . . . . . . . * *. What though we Wed in Hatred, we may mend; .. - * - WWe but begin where others ſurely end, - º - And each of you that Marry firſt for love, , . . . . . . WWe are but ſooner, what at laſt you'll prove. [Ex. Ambo. A CT IV. SC E N E L Enter Blunt with Lettr, Rochford. Flunt. My Lord, you aſt the cunning Lover well, | - Paint a rare Paſſion under all Diſguiſes; Yet oh! I wiſh this Art had not been learnt, But Nature in you, and true Love the Teacher; Yets will prize and hoard your Letters ſafe, As I would fragrant Flowers within my Boſom. Roch, O my prodigious and exalted Soul, And my more precious Stars!' I bleſs you all. - ls there a Man 'mongſt all your Favourites, . . . So rich, ſo happy, and ſo lov’d as I? - - - . . . . . . . . Methinks, for my dear Anna Bullen's ſake, ' , . . . . . . . . . H poſſible, I love you better now, . . . . . . . . . . Since H dare call you by the Name of Siſter. . . . . . " - Blunt. And I much more now I can call you Brother. . . . . . Koch, O my too weighty Joys! Immortal State . . . . . . . And more Immortal love! . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Blunt. No more: I’le chide you. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - - - - * - , , . " - - This is too great, too violent to laſt— ' ' ' Hold! give your Paſſion Breath, leave ſome for next, , , , , , , And love not all your wiſhes out at once— , , ..., Gº, wVhere is the Queen?” Sº º'º". " . . . . . . º Kash. I left her diſcontent: ". * -º-º-º-º: ºf P **** - . • * " . . * - ... vºet, ſº tºº ºlid tº r. º. º. -- ~ *- -- ~~ : . . . . . . * , , , , -s. tº fºsi it iſ , , § {^!“ -, A. ... . . . \ & i < *... ---> - - *** * - —
Page 39

A N N A BUL LEN. " Plumt. why, where is Piercyf Has ſhe ſeen him yet?'." - Roch. Seen him ſhe has; but would not ſpeak to him, ſº º tº. what crime in the ſevereſt Virtue once, , º, . " ' ". . * * * him. Not ſpeak to him! Oh cruel, mºſt inhumane! " + Had ſhe but ſeen him in that ſtate as: did, g º 'º' “” roch. No; not a word: but quite cºercame her Pity, º 'º x - -- tº do . . . . . " }*** * * * - *** * * : * , she would have ſpoke to him, and dy’d for him. . . . . : kºi, Alast her cruelty drew Pity from . . . . . . . . Her eyes and mine .......... ... , -- , º, piºns, would ſhe not ſpeak tº him then 2 . . * lº And went away reſolv’d ne'er more to ſee him. . . . . . . !º Blunt. The reaſon. ~ 3 - . . . . . . . º º * . . . . . Roch. She'd not tell—but 1 moſt doubt tº Her ſcrupulous Virtue is the cauſe. º, Blunt. Impoſſible 1 ," :: . . . . . 2: ..." ... .. -º- virtue can never lodge with Cruelty. . . . . . . . . º. what ſtain were it to th” whiteſt Innocence.” " … tº ºr ºf In her condition, but to hear him ſpeak? . . . ...tº Come! ſhe muſt ſee him - . . . . * * Roch. Would my Life and Fortune, ! It ºf, ºft: A ºr Coºld purchaſe her conſent tº ſee him one, " ' Pardon the Sallies of moſt mighty Friendſhip, * So well I wiſh him, I would hazard all - . . . Nay, all my Rights of Love, and Hºpes in thee," … ºr ºf lº º: * * : * , - --- ** …, “º : Blunt, Go tell, as from your ſelf, the ſad condition Her horrid Cruelty has brought him to.º. º tº ºvº my Apartment, ºl." º, within this hour he enter’. Nºte the Great, the Brave, and Charming Pierº,i, Whoſe Perſon none could fee without adoring: " . . . Bºike a dreadful Ghoſt, or horrid Shadows. ºº: ºº ... .". Far worſe than what dead, melancholly Midnight, “. . . … * To frighted Man º'er painted in a Dream; . . . . . ; The evil Genius of his Family gº ºf *.*.*..." Ne'er look’d ſo mad, nor. threaten’d half the woe, sº **** As he did to himſelf. . . - --- - Roch. llnhappy Piercy.” . . . . . . .” - sº Aunt. At firſt his ſight was pointed to the Earth: ". * - - - ( *. * - * - -, * * * ...' ... ? - - Then with a Groan, charg’d with a Volley of Sighs, He lifted up his fatal Eyes on me, which I . . . . .” - could ſcarce behold with mine, they were ſo full º' Of pitying Tears— and flats it witha Guill, … . . . . * - º Againſt our sexes loath’d ſnconſtancy, " " ' ºf fºr 5.5 s : . . . . .31% º riº. " t - - - - r ** Then ran into ſuch bitter, ſad Complaints: º º a . That I was forc’d to chide him- " " ' tº º . . . . * * --- - Roch. Oh, no more! . . . . . . . .” ! :º), -º-; 2 ºz. .. it wakes my drowfie Conſcience from its rºº, `" ºf P : - :: * * D tº . . cº - - º - ~ * - #3 ºi (, ºli; ::::: a 2 - Blunt;.



Page 40

| 2. º sº - º | 1. ºn - tº º º And beg the Queen, but once to ſee her. Piaºyi ji " … ... º. º. Which I, rack'd with Compaſſion, promis'd him. . . . . . . . . . . . "...t And when ſh' has got her Hay'a, and I my aims: #4 ºn fºr 3: i ào y & R 1 v.1, petraya;, wr, Blunt. But then at laſt . . . . . *\ . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . " From railings into Bieſings ſºreight he fell, . . . . . . . . . . . . . And on his Knees beſeech'd the that I’d plead, º' -- . . . . . . . . . * Alas! I fear more than I can perform : " . . . . . . . . . . . * A This ſaid, I riſe, and Piercy follow'd me; - He ſaid that you had vow'd to bring't to paſs. tº "º º Roch. I’ll do it inſtantly; abdºirºſhe will not, ſº tº . … . . . I'll bear her Body in theſe Arms by, force; . . . . . . .'; ... ". . . . . Her mind, I’m ſure, is willing to be with bim. . . . .'dººr. … .". Blunt. She’s coming ſtreight this way; gºiguickly; you; ºr, iſ (The miſerable Wretch is yet, without.).ºw ºf ºria.” & - * * And give him notice, now's the time to ſpeakitºhtr, ºf Then ſtreight return to holdsber, in diſcourſe . . . . . . . . . . . . Till Piercy comes. –----' . . . . . . . . . . . … Roch. So kind and pitiful! 2-ºxº~7 big ºf , º, . . . v . . . s : . . . . . . . . "Therefore I charge you by the Power df. Friendſhip, ... ." . . . . . . . By Piercy's Woes, and all she Love you owe ºf , , ; c. tº ºf .º. To me! go and prevail that:htºmayofre her thº, ſo, it (, ; ; ; ; ; ; ; *. May all thyºl sex bººkſ for the ... ºn 1. . . [Fr. Roch. #limt, Sólº this has provina Rºky Tale, and now ºf * s This rare Intelligence goggito, my Woºlfº ºn is . . . . . Who'll ſend th’Alarm to theiwatchful King, ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Streight to ſurpriſe him with his Wife, like jaſon, sº . . . . . . . . . Juſt ſtealing of his Golden Fleece: away---, ºf , º, …') : . . . . . . . She comes, ſhe comes; this Player-Qaeen; but know, ºf , ; 1 ºf f/ This is the laſt proud Aćt of all thy, ſhow 3: , , º, ...if yº 's 24, ºt This is a bait, kind Stars, āfīyeu'lºot frown, , ºes nº º 'º',' With which i'll take Revenge, or catch a Crown tº ºth a . . . .”. Who then dares tell me that 4 was ºto blamed tº gº tº ºr of For who contemns a proſp’rous Wickedneſs, gij is ºn 3 tº 24'ſ Or thinks that ill, that's Saluted with Succeſ, ºn tº GE4, Blunt.: \ . - .#}º, c. º. ºf 25. - Enter Queen with a Letter.º.º. ºf . . . . . . … - º - - - - -- - - * - , º - 2.1; º 0.25 ivi º ºil 3, 4 ºf 38 ºr “. gºn what ſhalliº wiers ºf my ºbling Festiºn tº Their way ! was ever Virtue; ſºm'dºikeimias.bi Isºs, ºr q; ; , ; 25 Within, without, I am haunted, all alikeja is ºſcº ºsºbiugº Without, tormented with a jealous King, ------sºº gº ºn 30 Within, my Fears ſuggeſt a thouſand-Plaguei, i. e.t.cº. 1 ºr Bid me remember injur’d Piercy's Wrongs, ... ...... c.4:3 tº ºn; aſ: ...And brand me wtih the name of Cruel to him; , ; ; * : *s ºf iſ Then on a ſudden a more dreadful thought ºut ºf .40 º upbraids me with a Guits; cig; fl. 3...ijº dº º ºsº aſ And tells me that kind Pity is a Sin. .iii.9 g (.iº, Ji edii, with .*.*.*. • * . . . . . . witneſs, . . .

Page 41

- Say anything; but let me not behold him; is . . . tº , For oh! my Weakneſs he ſa fierce aſſaults, zºº rººt *-*. *Twili ſpoil—"Twill wrack my Conduct--Ste, the comes tº N ** - - - - º - - - * > * wº ~ ... A N N A BULLEN 44. Witneſs, and blame not me, y'immortal Powers tº hai: … tº a When you expoſe.'two diff'rent Paths, one good, lºſt ºf 2 tº . . The other bad, and tell not which to take: tº 3rd isiº q lf to obey you is my Aim, juſt Heav'n', ºr C- ºr ºr 'Tis not my fault if I ſhou'd thuſ: the wrong, sº tº - ºf s... . . . º. - *-* - ---. ; :-- ** t \ . . . Enter Rochford... . . .'; ºf ºxº-. . . ; *_- - - . . . . . . . … º.º.º. is ----- - - - --> --~ : *- : * ~ * Roch. Siſter! moſt Royal, Merciful; Fair," gº ºf w. § And beſt below'd of Heav'n, and all Mankind, ºr . . . Let your dear Brother make it his Requeſt, . . . . . . . Thus on his Knees, as Deities are Charm’d, . . . . . . . . . . That you would hear th’ unhappy Pierry ſpeak, ºr ºf 2. This once, and but this once Piercy's without; +----it-º- Shall my beſt Friend take but his lait farewell? ... H ... . * - ºr Grant it, or never more let Rochford ſee you.' ... "... . . . . . Queen. Oh Brother; plead no more, 'tis all in vain; - Do not betray thy Siſter to a Guilt, ". . . . . . . . . . . . . . And ſtain the Cryſtal Virtue of a Soul, ºn , , º, … . . i.º. Which ſtill ſhe helds far dearer than a Crown; L ºr º Seek not by vile Enchantments to deſtroyº a sº, . . . . . . . That Innocence, which yet is all my Force, º 'º fººt. All the Defence poor Ballen has againſt ... v. ºf . * . t * : * * --> -- A jealous Husband, cruel Foes, and worſe, . . . tº * . . . . . tº --- Againſt the Malice of inveterate Hell. … . . . . . . . . . . . Koch. What danger can there be ºvywhat guilt in you ?, ? -- To hear the Wretched, and the Injur’d pray? ...º. • Come; for you will, you ſhall, you muſt now hear him. tº is Queen. No more 1 no more. There’s yet a fubtler Orator º: Than you, or Pity, pleads for Pierry here, - º Here in my firm couragious Soul, and ſtronger. . . . . . . . . . . . Than Father, Mother, or ten thouſand Brothers, < *; ºr tº Yet I can that deny, A., , , ; ; ; ; –---º' sº dº. Roch. What ſhall I tell him f : . . . . . ºth tº , º, jº w Queen. Tell him we are undone; I muſt not ſee him # * ..." : ". - And what's far worſt, the King is jealous; tell him is . . . . . . \ I love him—Tell him what is falſe, I hate him; ºº * . , i. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . º. 2: . . . . . . -- 2 : . . . . . . t - - --- - - , - . : Enter Piercy. tº sº ºf , ºf --~ - * - - - - .. *...* : *... - ... r - . . . . . ; ; cº-º', sº º ºf-sº : J Moſt cruel Piro–Cruel Brother rather—s ºf Help—Take, and bear me ſwiftly-free the dangerºzº; aid: ; . &och. Caſt but one Look, and you muſt needsir leat, 3-Y ~ * , £ºth. What ſhall 4 do? which Paſſage ſhalpychuſ…} : [Aſide. . . - " Tº sº. tº - Arms ----- - * . -
Page 42

42 VERTUE Betrayd: Or, - Arm me, kind Heav'n' againſt my Foe of Pity. , , º, . . . . . . . . . Pier. Still, ſtill ſhe turns, and hides her treach’rous Eyes-5. . Is’t poſſible that ſhe can feel remorſe f : . . . . . tº sº. T.’...." Or Pity after all 2 O no ; ſhe loves too well ; ; ; The fatal cauſe that purchas'd all this Pomp— . . . . . . . . - - Stay, Anna Bullen Stay; my Queen It is expected 1 ſhould call you, Queen: . . Behold your hatred -- 24een. Fly, good Piercy, fly: ... ." … ', iſ . . . .” -º There's Nets preparing for your life and mine—- "... h. There's nought but Snares and Quick-ſands where we tread, sº llafathom'd Pits hid under painted Grounds : . . . . . . . . . Where vaſt Deſtrućtion watches to devour us: - , , , tº . . . . Farewell—º. º.º. ---, -, zºº º 'º - iº Pier. Hear me but firſt, and ſhew thy Face, tº . . . . . ... 2 Thy falſe, diſſembling Beauties— * > . . . . . Many when wrack'd, have been by Dolphins born, And ſafely landed on the welcome Shore: And in the Foreſts, nay, the Monſters Dens, The Paſſenger, half ſtarv'd for want of Food, . . . . . . Has by the Lyons oft been ſpar'd and fed : . . . . . . . : - But cruel Ballen, cruel Beauty kills; , . . . . . . . . . . . All whom it fetters, moſt on whom it ſmiles. Nor can the Elements, nor gentler Brutes, perhaps > * > . -- “ , ºº ...' Teach Woman to be pitiful or good... g . . us Queen. Now, now juſt Heav'n' y'are ſhowring all your plag At once upon my Head, and I will bear 2em; - Bear'em like one of you, and bleſs the Weight; . . - Hear, my ſelf falſe upbraided, call'd moſt perjur’d, - . . . . . Deceitful, and the Monſter of my Sex; . - Ev’n I, (who, you Revengeful Pewers above . . . . . ‘Know) love this cruel chider to a fault. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Ah Piercy, Piercy Fly ; for life begone; . . . . . . . . . Each minute that you ſtay brings death to both. . . . . . . . . . Pier. Ah, holdſ if not for Love, for Pity ſtay. . . . ." And if no juſt complaint can pierce your hearing, . . . Then Blellings ſhall: Ten thouſand Bleſſings on you, . If you will hear the curſt of Mankind ſpeak. ſº tº , Koch. Now, Siſter, heard you that I by Heav'n it melts me, . Sure I’m turn’d all the Woman, you the Man. ---ſºº iſ Queen. Give me your hand, kind Brother, and ſupport me; Help, ſor I ſtagger with the treble Weight - Of Grief, Deſpair, and Pity - - - - - - My Sences all are charm’d, and Feet faſt ty’d - ºf To this inchanted Floors—Quick, or I’m loſt. . . ; – - cº- Pier. Yet turn; if there’s one jot of pity in you; ; *o º If Piercy exºr was worth one Thought, I tharge you, º 'º By the lov’d name of Anna Fullen, ſtay— What
Page 43

/ A N N A BU L L E N. 43 what then, will nothing move o inexorable: No not a Look! not Piercy worth one Look! . . Yet, Rochford, hold Canſt thou too be ſo Cruel! Fell and obdurate both ! . . . Is there no hope? but will you; will you then Begone? * -- - I - É. Fly, Brother, e're it be too late, For ſhou'd I liſten but a Moment more, . . . . " - The ſtrength of Hercules were not enough . . . . .” To draw me hence, ſo unruly is my Body, - And my unwilling Soul ſo loth ſo part. \ Pier. Then with my Knees, thus faſtning to the ground Your Robe, and thus with my extended Arms . [Piercy kneel; upon her I’le force and charm you, 'till y’have heard my laſt [Kobe. Complaint: And then forbear to pity if you can. - Queen. Why doſt thou hold? Why do I hold my ſelf? Pier. Ten thouſand Curſes light upon her Soul - In Hell; and worſe, what mine on Earth endures, That firſt taught Woman Falſehood— If for a Crown ſhe's falſe! Oh may that Crown Sit loathſom on her Forehead as her Crimes, May Adders neſt within th' Ambitious Round, And into Stings the fatal Ermins turn. When dead, may all the Miſeries ſhe feels w - Be through the World recorded as a Mark . . . For faithful Lovers to beware, and ne’re Be nam'd without a Curſe. Queen. Ah Cruel Piercy! . . . - . . . . . ... ... Pier. But for my Queen, let Heav'n and Angels guard her; Her I except from any bitter Fate: * Let Anna Bullen's Breaſt be ne’re diſturb’d, Nor Soul upbraided with the Wrongs of Piercy: And oh, kind Heav'n" if there be any Sorrow - . (As ſure none e're can be) ordain’d for her, . . . Falſe as ſhe is, I beg that it may fall Only on wretched Piercy's Head—-May Hers . . Be all the Pleaſure ſtill, and mine the Pain. . . . . . . . Queen. O Gods! obdurate Heav’ns! Cruel Honour! . [Aſide, And yet more Cruel Vertue, hear and ſee * - ... Pier. And when I ſhall for ever be recluſe, As now I go to part with all Mankind, - 'Twill be my Joy, ſometimes to think of you, -- And make me live, perhaps one Day the longer, When in my Melancholly Cell I hear . . . . . That the Crown flouriſhes on Bullen's Head. . . . . . . . Queen. Ha! I'm or’ewhelm’d, the Sluces all are broke, [Aſide. And Pity, like a Torrent, pours me down; , - - * - - G -
Page 44

V tº IC 1 C 1: Derray a . Ur, Now I am drowning, all within's a Deluge; Wiſdom nor Strength can ſtem the Tide no more, And Nature in my Sex ne’re felt the like Help Rochford, e're I’m rooted to this Earth. Away, away! the leaſt word more undoes me. Pier. Yet turn one Look upon me, e're you go, Queen. There take it, with my life, perhaps the purchaſe • T Take that too, Piercy, thou haſt been betray’d. [Gives him a Learn there th’ unhappy Bullen's Fate—Farewell. Letter. Pier. Yet ſtay—the Soul ne’re parted with ſuch pangs, From the pale Body, as you fly from me. - Queen. Piercy adieu-1 can–I will—I muſt: No more. - [Ex, Qu, and Roch. Pier. What, never ſee you more? She's gone, - I - She’s gone, more lov’d and beautiful than ever: And now methought, juſt as ſhe parted from me, She ſhot a Look quite through my gory Heart, - - - And left it Gaſping, Dying, and Deſpairing. - What’s here, a Letter 1 and the Charaćter— - . . . That I ſo oft have been acquainted with ? If theſe Eternal Kiſſes give me leave, - I’le break it open with as great a Joy, As I had leap'd into our Marriage-Bed, - And rifled all the Sweets and Pleaſures there- - . Whats this I read || - - - Reads. . . - - | By Wicked Woolſey, Harry, and our Parents Lºa, betray'd, and fore’d to Wed the King : Who intercepted all thy Letters, Swearin With Sacramental Oaths, that thou wert falſe, 4nd Marry'd Firſ—Piercy adieu, and credit me, 4nd that I lov’d thee better than my Life. Burn this raſh Paper, left the Fiend; diſcloſe it. - - B E) L. F. E. W. She's Innocent! Oh! you Immortal Powers! . . - º She’s Innocent! And then ſhe loves me ſtill, - Sound, ſound my Joy, till my Exalted Soul is wound up to th” extreameſt pitch of Bliſs: - Let Piercy never after this be fad— Yet hold-What dawn of Comfort can'ſ thou ſpy la this-Oh none—This Gloworm-spark, - This Glimps of Hope is vaniſht, and I’m ſºft ' . in deeper Parkneſs, Horrour and Deſpair, s Thane're I was before- - -

Page 45

... A N N A BULL EN. Qh Anna Bullen? Curſt in being true ! And I more Curſt in knowing it too late. º Re-enter Queen and Rochford. Ha! ſhe returns! The mourning Angel comes Again! Sure Heav'ns in Love with both our Miſeries, They look with ſuch a Pomp and Train in me; . . . And are ſo beautiful in her - - - Queen. Well, Brother, And thou far ſtronger and Immortal Pity And more Immortal Love, y' have brought me back—— Ye have. What? what will you do with me now * Koch. Could anything on Earth! Tyger, or Panther, Much leſs a Creature form'd by Heav'n like it: Could you, I ſay, refrain at ſuch an Obj-6t: At the laſt words of the *happy Wretch, And not forbear to balm him o're in Tears, Or elſe but hear him ſpeak; - Queen. Now I'm inclos'd again! The Combat now grows fierce and ſtrong, and oh! How weak an Armour Reſolution is, Againſt our Paſſions, or the Man belov’d: . Virtue and Honour, hence be proud no more; Nor brag of your Dominion o'er Mankind; Leſt Love, moſt fatal Love, too ſoon ſhould tell you, And make you feel, h’ has mightier Chains than you See where he is look Heav'n with tender eyes; Give Council to my juſt deſpairing Soul, - And tell me, Pity is no Sin Ah Piercy! , , Pier. My charming Queen! my Anna Bullen once Am 1 ſo bleſt, and yet ſo wretched too, As what is written here contains; and tell me! May 1 believe that you can love me ſtill 2 Queen. Oh Piercy! Piercy! urge me not to tell you What Heav'ns Auſterity will not permit, Nor force me to declare— What the Eternal Sees already written . . . In two broad Charaćters within my Breaſt; How large, how deep thy Story’s graven here, . And what 1 dare not, never muſt unfold— Oh! I have ſaid too much. Pier, What f ſaid too much Can you repent of one kind thought of Piercy? And ſpitefully call back your tender Mercy? Nay, worſe; can you behold the almoſt Naked, ... . And ſtarv'd beſeeching WWretch, and ſtrive to pull The totter'd Remnants from his quivering Joynts, G s
Page 46

46 y E R 1 v E. Betraya: o And daſh the Pitcher from the greedy Lips - Of one juſt ready to expire with Thirſt 2 - * * Oh Cruel Queen 2 For Anna Bullen would not, She would not, would not uſe her Piercy thus. - Queen. Ceaſe, ceaſe ſuch ſounds——— And turn thy ſad, reſiſtleſs Eyes away; For if I once behold thoſe Tears, and hear Thy juſt Complaints, I can no longer hold, But break I muſt through all the bonds of Virtue. Nay, ſtood the Jealous Harry by With all his Guards of Devils, Woolſey's, Cardinals; º In ſpight of all, in ſpight of more my ſelf I muſt both ſee, hear thee, and ſpeak to thee, And pity thee. Now are you ſatisfied? Pier. It is enough, bright Daughter of the Sky: Y”have conquer'd me, my Deity, you have Here on my Knees, but yet at diſtance too, The Poſture of a Soul in Extacy, I beg a thouſand Pardons of my Queen. A Look, a Sigh, a Tear, from Anna Bullen, , ) ls far more worth than all the trifling Wrongs; Nay, than the Life and very Soul of Piercy. - Queen. Help me juſt Heav'n, who ſees how I’m beſieged, And what a weak Reſiſtleſs Wretch I am 1. Why d'ye impoſe on us ſo hard a Task Os poor Mankind, ſo feeble and ſo frail, Making us here Commiſſioners of Virtue, Yet put by Drams and Scruples in the Ballance, To Counter-poiſe and weigh down Fleſh and Blood. How weaks my Will to draw my Body hence; And oh! how loath my Eyes are to depart, But wiſh for ever to be faſten’d on thee, And look one Look to vaſt Eternity; - Yet we muſt part, Ah, Piercy! part for ever—— Pier. Ah ſay not ſo! muſt we ſo ſoon, my Queen! Is then this Moments Bliſs ſo Criminal, That it muſt forfeit all my precious Hopes - Of an Aſſurance once to meet again Queen. My mind now bodes to me, that’tis our laſt; Yet i muſt bid thee go: There is no Joy for us; The World's a Deluge all to thes and me—— There is no reſt, my Piercy, in this World, . No Sanétuary to lay the weary Head - Of the undone, th’ unpitty'd; and betray’d. Farewell: There's ſomewhat riſes o're my Soul, And covers it as with, a fatal Cloud of Horror, Death, and Fear. It cannot be; - -- . . - - * * **H3-------- (The
Page 47

ANNA BULL EN. - 47 The Sting of parting cannot do all this; , Farewell, farewell. - - - - - Pier. Stay; muſt we part for ever ? . What never ! never meet again! . . Queen. Never till we are Clay, and then perhaps, Neglečted as we were in Life, thrown out in Death Some charitable Man may be ſo kind, To give our poor forſaken Bodies Burial, Laying 'em both together in one Bed Of Earth- - - Hah! the time's come ! my Fatal Doom's at hand! - Three drops of Blood falls from her Noſe, - and £ains her Handkerchief. Behold, the Heav'ns in Charaćters of Blood, -- In three inevitable Drops, - -- ~~ Have ſeal’d it, and decreed that it is now ! Ah Piercy J fly, and leave me here alone - - To ſtem this mighty Torrent of my Fate, - - Be gone, while I have life to bid thee go :. For now Death ſtops my Tongue Pier. My Lord She faints—my Life my Anna Bullen ſtay 5 Or your Commands ſhall fetter me no more. . But break I will through all the Bars of diſtance, And catch thee thus, thus hold thee in my Arms— Rochford 1 O help to call her back again. Hold, ſtop thy flight; thou precious Air return!. Y Far richer than that rare immaculate Breath, Which Natures God breath'd in the firſt of Mankind I *. Roch. Wake Siſter, wake! behold no danger’s night Quern. Ah Piercy now I wake, with Courage now , - - To meet my Fate; and ſee where it approaches. . . - [She Swoºn. - … Enter Cardinal, Northumberland, and Guard. Pier. Ha! Woolſey, and my Father with the Guards ! . Card. My Lord, e'er we diſcover our Commiſſion, Pray, let your Son be parted from the Queen, . . . . . Leſt the wrong’d King ſhould ſee him in his rage, . -- And execute his worſt of Fury on him. . . . . . . North. Son! tho’ you have committed, in the Court, , , The greateſt Crime, againſt your Royal Maſter, That e'er a Subjećt can be guilty of;. - - Yet in reſpect of theſe gray Hairs and Tears, . . . . - He has been pleas'd to ſpare your forfeit Life: . . . . . . . . . Therefore be gone: a minutes ſtay is fatal— . . . . . . . - Guards, force him, if he goes not willingly, . . . . . - tº - - • . . . .
Page 48

* * - 46 y E R Tºy E. Betray'd: Ór, And carry him ſtreight, by Barge, to Suffolk-Houſe - Without reply. - Pier. Obediently I’ll go, - If you will promiſe me that you have nought - - Againſt the ſacred Perſon of the Queen, And will not touch her: for ’tis greater Sacriledge, , - Then 'tis to hurt an Angel, cou’d it be, - ^- She is ſo linnocent, ſo Chaſt, and Pure. - Elſe I’m reſolv’d to ſtand, no Rock ſo firmſ Fixt like the Center to the Maſſey Globe, - | You ſhould as ſoon remove ſtrong Hercules, With his hands graſping both the Poles of Heaven, - As force me from this Footing, where I ſtand, -, And ſee the Queen but threatned, or in danger. Card. My Lord, on both our Honours, the Queen’s Perſon Shall be inviolate and ſacred always; - Nor know we ought againſt her—but the King Is coming ſtreight to viſit her, as kindly, As he was wont: Therefore you muſt be gone— \ We have no other reaſon but your ſafety. Pier. I fear ! for ah! what truth can come from thee? - Thou ſpeak'ſt but at the ſecond hand from Hell——— - Kind Sir, may I believe what Woolſey ſays 2 Card. Confirm it, good my Lord, or you'l delay. --> North. 'Tis true, what the great Cardinal has told you. Queen. Go, Piercy; and miſtruſt not more than I; Be gone, if I have Power left to command; - Leave me to Innocence, and Heav'n that will not Permit a Soul that never did any ill, To fear it. - - Pier. Then I’ll go——but oh juſt Heav'n? And all you Angels, Cherubims, and Thrones: All you bright Guards to the moſt High Imperial, . . . . . . " You kindeſt, gentleſt, mildeſt Planets, -- You leſſer Stars, you fair innumerable, And all you bright Inhabitants above, . . - Protećt the Sacred Perſon of the Queen; And ſhed your balefull'ſt Venom on their heads, That think to ſtain a Whiteneſs like your ſelves. Farewell * . . . . - - - {Ex. Pier. Queen. Farewell! - - ** . . . . - * Card, john Viſcount Rochford, by the King's Command, W’ arreſt you here, of Capital, High Treaſon. - Queen. Hear Heav'n' my Brother faln into the Snare : Card. And 'tis his pleaſure that you ſtreight be ſent Cloſe Priſoner to the Tower, with the Lord Norris, , , , ; Who is ſuſpected with you to be Guilty” " ' " " ' ' ' ' " ºf
Page 49

A N N A BUL LEN. 47° Of the ſame hainous crime. Guards ' ſieze his Perſon. Roch. Baſe Villain! Traitor : Woolſey I ſay, for what? Queen. No matter. Let a Woman teach thee Courage: Ne'er ask for what, ſince ’tis his wiſe Decree a Above, who gave us with a liberal hand, - - - - And ſate us on the higheſt ſpoke of Greatneſs, No longer than he pleas'd to call us down Well, whoſe turn's next 2 Come, dart your worſt, my Lords, - And meet a temper’d breaſt, that knows to bear. - - By my bright hopes, y’are more afraid than I; . -- I did exped you would begin with me ! - Card. Moſt Royal Madam, oh I wiſh the King Had choſen ſome leſs unwilling than our ſelves, . To Execute this moſt deteſted Office. . - In Witneſs of it, on our Knees with Tears, IKneeli. And Sorrow, we our ſad Commiſſion tell: It is the Kings moſt fatal Pleaſure too, That you be ſent a Priſoner to the Tower, - And thence immediately to both your Tryals. - [Rºſes. Koch. Tryal 1 oh her wrong’d Innocence 1 for what? Queen. No more, dear Brother; let us both ſubmit, - And give Heav'n Thanks, and our moſt Gracious King For I’m not ſo preſumptuous of my Virtue; y But think, Dear Rochford, that both you and 1 Have once committed, in our erring Lives, - - Something, for which we juſtly merit Death. - " * - ~ Though not, perhaps, the thing we are accuſed of - -- ~ Enter the King in a Fury, with Letters in his hand. Attendants - and Guardt. - Card. The King is here ! Queen. Then he is Merciful. - King. Where is this Woman this moſt abhorr'd of Wives | This ſcandal to her Sex, my Crown and Life! What by your Minion? oh good natur'd Husband!' Down on your Knees, and thank me for the favour— See—here are Letters faln into my hands, - Where your dear Brother ſays he has enjoy'd you. - º [Gives the Letters to the Queen, Oh thou more damn'd, and more inſatiate far, Than Meſſalina She was chaſt, to thee. Her, half the Men and Slaves of Rome, Could ſatisfie; but thou, not all Mankind, - - With Husband, Brother, Kindred in the Number. EShe gives Queen. Oh Heav'nly Pow’rst oh Guard of Innocence 1 [em Roch. What do l ſce and hear: O Sacred Sir! . Y - - Qū;
Page 50

'Tis yours; but do not rob me of my Fame, In his behalf’s a Traitor, worſe than he— [To North. who kneels, º – 5o V E R T & E. Betray'd: Or, You took me to your Royal Bed, a Hand-maid, - -- The moſt unworthy of the mighty Favour; - . Oh throw me into Dungeons ſtreight, or take . . . . . . . Away my Life, that ne'er offended you: - -- Take all in recompence from Anna-Bullen Nor ſtain my Virtue with ſo foul a Guilt. ... " Roch. What's here 2 my amorous Letters ſent to Blunt 1 Has ſhe betray’d me ! * > - King. I will hear no more--- [To the Queen. Roch. Ah, Royal Sir, theſe Letters I confeſs—— King, Damn thy hot luſtful breath; thy Poyſoncus tongue! Here, take 'em hence, to Tortures, Racks, to Death. Queen. O Sir! I am prepar'd for any Death; For worſe than Death, a thouſand, thouſand Torments; And if you think 'em all not pain enough, Here take advice of Woolſey; he’ll inſtrućt you; -- Tell you, how you may plague this hated body; But do not think that I’m ſo loath’d a Creature. -" King. Quick; take away thy hands, or I will force thee— - Queen. You ſhall not, cannot, till l’ve ſworn the truth: For by th’ unſpotted Babe within the Womb, That yet lies wrapt in Innocence, unborn; - - By injur’d Truth, by Souls of Martyr'd Saints, By you, Iny Lord, my Husband, and my King! And by the King of Kings, the King of Heav'n, I’m wrong’d Ah Royal, Gracious Sir, I’m wrong’d. King, llnhand me; or I'll ſpurn thee from thy hold Seize, ſeize on Piercy—by my Life, who begs [To the Guards. Here is another Letter too, it is from Norris, Who much commends your darling, ſecret Beauties, And ſweetneſs of your Lips; Yet you are wrong’d 1– Here's Notes of your Muſician too, that charm'd you. Eternal Hell / where’s ſuch another Monſter? I have more Horns than any Forreſt yields. * - Than Finsbury, or all the City Muſters upon a Training, or a Lord Mayors day. - Riſe and be gone, thou Fiend, thou Sorcereſs; - Thy Power, thy Charms, like Witchcraft, all have left thee, Go you inceſtuous Twins, make haſte and mingle - Your foul, adulterate Blood in Death together— - Oh, they’re too long aſunder. Why, doſt weep? " Go to thy Death, and what’s a greater pain, * - - - May Heav'n, like me, ſee all thoſe Tears in vain - . . . . - - LEx. King, Attendans. Roth. Ah Siſter what dire Fiends muſt puniſh #. - - wº i - What - *
Page 51

* N N A D U. L. L. L., TN. What will become of me, the Cauſe of all 2 - - Queen. Fear not. Heav'n knows thy Innocence, and mine ! What tho? we ſuffer here a little ſhame ! - 'Tis to reward our Souls above, and with Immortal Reſtitution Crown 'em there We two liv'd in one Mother’s ſpotleſs Womb; . . And then we ſcarce had purer Thoughts than now! . And ſhortly we ſhall meet together in - - One Grave. ~ 2. Roch. O ſay not ſo: Death dare not be ſo Cruel. - uten, Ceaſe Brother, ceaſe; ſay not a word in anſwer; But lead me, like a Valiant Man, to Chains, * Come, let's prepare—But firſt my Pomp adieu!” [Kneels, and lays down her Crown, From Heav'n I did my Crown and Life receive, And back to Heav'n both Crown and Life I’le give; And thus, in humble poſture, lay it down .. - With greater Joy than firſt I put it on. . * - [Riſes. And now I tread more light, and ſee from far - A Beamy Crown, each Diamond a Star. But oh, you Royal Martyrs! Ceaſe a while Your Crying Blood, that elſe muſt curſe this Iſle; Of the Imperial ask it with my Pray’r; For you are ſtill the neareſt Angels there; Then Richard, Edwards, Henry, all make room, The firſt of ñº. I come: . . - Let me amongſt your glorious, happy Train, ~ Free from this hated World, and Traitors Reign. [Ex. Ambe. A C T V. S C E N E I. - -> . 2 Enter Cardinal and Blunt ſeverally. Gard. llckieſt of Omens ! do I meet my juno My Fair, llluſtrious Partner in Revenge : Come, tell the News that your glad Eyes proclaim: Speak, by thy Looks, I know it muſt be well. ls ſhe Condemn'd? Shall Rome be Abſolute 2 Shall Woolſey Reign, and ſhall my Blunt be Queen 2 Blunt. 'Tis as thou ſay'ſt, moſt mighty of thy Funètion; Greateſt that e're adorn’d this Robe, it is. Theſe Eyes ſaw the bright Engliſh Sun Eclips'd, / ; ... . . . And what is more, Eclips’d by Thee and Me, - - - - , . . . . Caſt by her aweful Judges from her Height, Guilty and ſham’d, as Lucifer from Heav'n, And forc’d to beg it, as the mildeſt Sentence, - To loſe her Head. - - º H Card
Page 52

infernal Darkneſs, ſuch as vºgypt felt, S2 V E R T & E Betrayd: Or, - | Card. Then there’s an end of Bullen. Blunt. And what to ſee, gave me the greater Joy Thoſe Letters counterfeited by the Fool - Her Brother, were the ſtrongeſt Proofs againſt her; . . - - - So the ſame Papers which by your Advice - I got convey’d into her Cabinet, - - Were the ſubſtantiall'ſt Circumſtances found - For which ſhe dies. - - Card. O Juſt and Sacred Rage, * - - Revenge! Thou greateſt Deity on Earth! - - And Woman’s Wit the greateſt of thy Council. - Blunt. We ought to veil before your Prieſtly Robe; My Crown of Wit ſhall ne’re ſtand Candidate With yours; and yet l dare be bold to ſay, This I, and Malice would have done alone, Without the mighty Aid of Woolſey's Brain. - - Card. Then nothings to be done by Fate, nor Woolſey, - But take the vanquiſht Crown from Bullen's Head, - And place it ſuddenly on yours. Blunt. For which, My gracious Woolſey, 1 will ſo reward you.' Enter to them Piercy. . . . . Pier. Blackneſs Eternal cover all the World ! When the Great Patriarch curs’d the fatted Land, , ...And with a Word extinguiſht all the light. - Blunt. See, Piercy's here ! More mad than we are joyful: Does’t not make young the Blood about thy Heart, Tº ſee that our Revenge not ſingly hits, But, like a Chain-ſhot carries all before it? . Card. Let us avoid him—You intend to ſee The Queen receive her Death : But I, to hide . . The Pleaſure that perhaps the ſight would give me, - Will paſs this Day at Eſher, like a Mourner. - . . . Pier. Behold, the Sun ſhines ſtill ; inſtead of Darkneſs, * . Yon Azure Blue’s unſpeckled with a Cloud; The Face of Heav'n ſmiles on her as a Bride, . The Day, the Sun ſits mounted on his Chariot, . . . . . . . And darts his ſpiteful Beams in ſcorn of Pity; . *Bates not a jot of the Illuſtrious Pomp, . . . . . . . . . . " He ſhould have furniſh’d on her Wedding-Day: : . . . . . Heav'n looks like Heav'n ſtill, Nature as ’twas, Men, Beaſts, and Devils; every thing that lives,..., Conſpires, as pleas'd at Anna Bullen's Fall. . Behold, juſt Powers! the Curſes of the Land t ) . . . . . . . Stay you Amphibious Monſters, Prieſt, and Devil | ET, the Card, And Strumpet, if it can be, worſe than both and B. - - - * - - - . You * * * ~.

Page 53

A N N A B U L L E N. You far more dreadful Pair than thoſe that firſt Betray’d poor eaſie Man, and all Mankind : Thou fatal Woman Thou! and Serpent Thou! By whoſe ſole Malice (oh that Heav'n ſhould let it !) - A greater Innocence this Day is fallen, Than ever bleſt the Walks of Paradiſe. - Card. My Lord, I ſhall acquaint the King with this, a And thoſe juſt Lords the Judges of her Cauſe, . / Whom your baſe Malice wrongs Farewell. - - Pier. Bold Traytors! Hell-hounds! hear me firſt; Stay you infeftious Dragons; do you flye! - Does Anna Ballen's Chaſtity and Virtue. Writ in this Angry Fore-head, make you ſtart Enter Diana to him. What, the fair, wrong'd Diana's Face in Tears 1 Can him. Bullen’s Miſeries Attract The nobleſt of Compaſſion, Pity from A Rivals Breaſt ! thou Wonder of my Sex! How far, more Wretched mak’ſt thou Piercy ſtill, When I behold how much thou doſt deſerve, - And I, ſo very little have to pay ! - Dian. What Rocky-heart could have refrain’d from Pity, To ſee the Sight that I did! any thing, But Man, moſt Cruel Mankind, would have griev'd; Tygers and Panthers would have wept to ſee her; . - And her baſe Judges, had they not been Men, a Would have bemoan’d her like departing Babes. - . Pier. Is Rochford too Condemn'd? Dian. Alas! he is. - Rochford and Norris both, receiv'd their Sentence, And both behav'd themſelves like Gallant Men— But for the Queen! Ah Piercy, ſuch bright Courage, No thought can Dićtate, nor no Tongue Relate, When ſhe was tax’d with that unnatural Crime, Adultery with her Brother; ('Tis a Sin That e”re it ſhould be nam’d.) At firſt ſhe ſtarted, \ And ſoon an Innocent, not Guilty, Red . . . Adorn’d her Face, and Sainted it with Tears; But ſtreight conceiving it a Fault, ſhe Smil'd, i. ', º r Pier, When I am Dead, may my ſad Tale be bleſt, ...And have no other Tongue, but thine, to tell it, Dian. Then with the meekneſs of a Saint ſhe ſtood; With ſuch amazing Oratory dazled, And like the Sun, darted quite through her Judges, And ſham'd their Guilt, that none durſt look upon her; ... ſº H 2 But I’m above it— - LEx. Card, and Blunt. Wip'd off . : and chid the Bluſh away, sº sº, sº º - 53 [Exeum. * But
Page 54

- V E R T W E Betray d: Or, - But oh! what's deſtin’d in the blackeſt Pit - - - of Hell; what Innocence can n'ere withſtand. Whate’re ſhe ſaid, that Angels cou’d not finer, And ſhew’d a Soul, no Cryſtal nigh ſo clear; Tho' all appear'd to be the Plot of Devils; - Yet was ſhe guilty found, and, oh, ſad Piercy! (May all Eyes weep at it, like thine and mine) Condemn’d to loſe her Head. Pier. Hell dare not think it. Dian. The Cruel Duke of Norfolk, her Relation, As Steward for the Day, pronounc'd the Sentence. - Pier. And my hard hearted Father too was there. . . * = . Diam, My Lord ' What ſaid you? Your hard hearted Father f Oh blotted let it be from all Records, - * And never be in England’s Annals read, What I’m about to tell you. Her own Father, The Earl of Wiltſhire, ſate amongſt her Judges. Pier. O Monſter damn'd? than Cruel Titan worſe, - That eat up his own Iſlug as he got 'em. sº Dian. Behold, the King! All Knees, are bent, all Hands, All good Mens Eyes lift up to Heav'n and him, . " " ' ". . To beg the Life of Her that glads the World. - - - - - | - Pier. Make uſe of all thy VVomans art to win him; Let all Petition him that ſhare her Blood, - Matrons, VVives, Virgins, all the Charming Sex. Dian. Do you withdraw. You but incenſe the King Iv’e yet a ſoft Experiment to try, - Shall pierce his ſtubborn Nature to the Quick. - Pier. That Angel, th’art inſpir’d with proſper thee. . [Ex. - Enter King and Attendants. - º King. Piercy! did l not charge he ſhould be ſeiz'd? - [To the Guards who go out to ſeize Piercy Now by the Sacred Crown of England’s Monarchs, Let none entreat me upon pain of Death 2 [To Petitioners. WWhat’s here 2. A Liſt of baſe Petitioners, - For Norris Life & Hell and Confuſion ſeize 'em Have I not like a Rock againſt the Seas, And Mountain 'gainſt the VVinds ſtood thus unſh Nay more, this heart, that pleads with mortal pangs " . For my dear Anna Bullen's life?. And ſhall I - tº Pardon a Slave before I would my Queen 2 Enter Northumberland, who kneels. . . . . King. v.vhy doſt kneel?" "º tº º . . - -- - - -- : . . . :-- * -- f º, .*, *, * *s Morth. I met my Son this moſt unlucky moment;ºº", *. Juſt as the Guards were ready to obey, tºº, º 'º And Execute your fatal orders on him, sº tºº º' ----- - yºu- * - - aken, º º - Deny'd all England's Prayers, and Tears of Angels? . . . . . . . . .
Page 55

- N. - - . The World, juſt like the Piâure of the Pope, º' • * ~ * 2 A N N A BU L L E N. 55 Who in deſpair, or rather in obedince, 2 º' ' ' ' ' ' ' . Making a faint reſemblance to reſiſt; º, º As they were ſtriving to put by his Sword, º He on a ſudden open'd wide his Arms, And on his Breaſt receiv'd a wilful wound. . . . . . . . I kneel with humble Prayers, that his diſaſter . . . . Would mitigate your preſent and juſt Fury. . . . . . . . - And grant my Son his freedom, till his hurt ºf º' Is cur'd, which is not mortal. King. Be it ſo. . . . . - . . . . . .” - Enter Diana, leading the Toung Princeſ; Elizabeth, with Women, Dian. Pardon this bold Intruſion in your Preſence. Your Daughter, Sir, this little Princeſs here, - - - - - - Poſſeſt with Womans Rage, and far above . . . tº . . . . . The little ſparkling Reaſon of a Child, - - . . . . . . Scream'd for her Father; where’s my Father, ſaid ſhe 3. Aud as we brought her to you, ſtill ſhe cry’d, " - llnleſs ſhe ſaw her Father, ſhe wou’d die. King. What wouldſt thou have, my little Betty, ſay? . Child. But will you promiſe me that you'l not frown, And cry aloud, Hough? and then indeed I'll tell you, King. I do. Come, let me take thee in my Arms—- , child. No : but I’ll kneel: for I muſt be a Beggar, And l have learnt, that all who beg of you, Muſt do it kneeling. *... tº --- North, Prettieſt Innocence { * * * * * * King. Well then, what is't my little Pratler, ſay?: - Child. I’m told that ſtreight my Mother is to die, ºr Yet I have heard you ſay, you lov’d her dearly : And will you let her die, and me die too? as King. She muſt die, Child; there is no harm in Death; , Beſides the Law has ſaid it, and ſhe muſt. . . . . . ,”, * . . . . . . . . . - * * = * Child. Muſt 4 is the Law a greater King than you?” ſº King; O-yes. But do not cry, my pretty Betty: " . . . . . For ſhe’l be happier when ſhe’s dead, and go … ºº To Heaven. - . 3. . . . . . . Child. Nay, I’m ſure ſhe'll go to Heav'n. ºf . . . . King. How art thou ſure ?', ſº tº sº tº Child. Some body told me ſo . . . . . . . . . . . Laſt night when I was in my ſleep.-: * : . . . . vº King. Who was it 2 º, a ºn Child. A fine old man like my Godfather Cranmer. . . . . Card, Ay, there's the Egg that hatcht this Cocaktrice. Child. Pray Father, what’s that huge, tall, Bloody man **** * 1 ne'er ſaw him but once in all my life, . . . . . . . . . And then he frighted me. ... He looks for all s , . " ºf . * . ** * * ---, * * * * * * - - - - - - - Ring
Page 56

\ V A. R. I O C, Delray u : vſ, - | King. Why, don’t you love the Pope? . . . . . Child. No indeed don’t I, - Nor never will. - * , - King. Ay, but you muſt, my Dear ; – He is a fine old Man too, if you ſaw him. . . . . - - Card. Go, y’are a little Heretick. - - Child. A Heretick 1 * - - ‘. . . .” Pray Father, what does that bold Fellow call me? * * What’s that 2 - * * * *, , , King. Why, that’s one that forſakes the right, And turns to a new, wrong Religion. Child. Then I’m no Heretick: For I ne'er turn’d In all my life. But you forget your Child. . . . . . . . . - Dear Father, will you ſave my Mother's life f : . . . . . . . . . º King. You muſt not call me Father: For they ſay, Y’are not my Daughter. Child. Who’s am I then 2 - Who told you ſo f that ugly old, bald Prieſt? He tells untruth. I’m ſure you are my Father ? King. How art? . . . . . . . . . Child. Cauſe I love none ſo well as you - . * But oh you'l never hear mewhat I have to ſay, - As long as he, that Devil there, ſtands by Your Elbow. - . . . . . King. Ha! what Devil - Child. That Red Thing there. ‘. . . - - King. Oh Child; he is no Devil, he's a Cardinal. - - Child. Why does he wear that huge, long Coat then 2 unleſs it be to hide his Cloven feet. * . . . . - Card. Sir, all’s deſign’d by Cranmer for the Queen, . Of whom ſh'has learn'd this Leſſon like a Parrot, King. Take her away, I were a Fool indeed, . . . . . . . If Womens Tears, and Childrens idle Prattle, ... . . . Should change my fixt Reſolves, and cheat my Juſtice- Away with her. - *** -- . . Child. Oh, but they dare not: . . . . . Father, will you not let your Betty kiſs you ? . . . Why do you let 'em pull me from you ſo 2 tº . . . . . . . I ne'er did anger you: ºc, , . . . ." . Pray ſave my Mother, dear King-Father do ; , º, . . . . . . . . . . . And if you hate her, we will promiſe both, . . . . . . . . That ſhe and I will go a great huge way, . . . . . . . . . . And never ſee you more. - - * . - . . . . N. ,s - King. Unlooſe her; hough 1. º. . . . ... " . - Hence with her ſtraight: I will not hear her prate . . . . . . . . Another word. Go, y’are a naughty Girl. . . . . . . . Child. Well," l’m reſoly’d when I am grown a Woman, wº º i - I?I l / . . . . . - - - - —-
Page 57

A N N A B U L L E N. 57 I’ll be reveng’d, and cry, Hough too. w [Ex. Diana, Princeſs, Women. King, Ha! Spirit, - Mount all the Draw-Bridges, and guard the Gates, - Then bring the Priſoners forth to Execution :- Norris, and Rochford firſt, and then the Queen: My Lord Northumberland, be it your Task; Diſpatch my Orders ſtraight, and fetch the Traytors— What's this that gives my Soul a ſudden Twitch?, . . . . . . And bids me not proceed. Ha! is't Compaſſion 3 . . . Shall Pity ever fond the Breaſt of Harry! “ . . . . . . . 'Tis but a ſlip of Nature, and I’ll on. . . Think on thy Wrongs; the Wrongs her Luſt has done thee, And ſweep away this loath’d inceſtuous Brood, - * - As Heav'n would drive a Plague from off the Land: ' ' ' ". . Think thou ſhalt have thy Seymer in thy Arms, . ! . . . . . Who ſhall reſtore thy loſs with double Charms: - - And though my Bullen ſets this night, and dies, Seymor, next Morn, like a new Sun ſhall riſe. [Ex, King, Attendants. North. With an unwilling heart, I take this Office, - And Heav'n, if Anna Bullen's Innocent, - • Forgive me, ſince it is my King’s Command. My Breaſt is ſad, and tender for her, all; . . º Tho' Piercy ne'er can riſe, but by her Fall-– Enter to him Rochford, Lieutenant, and Guards. - Roch. Wil’t not be granted, that I here may ſee . - - - My Siſter e'er 1 dye, to part with her? - - . - - - Lieut. There is my Lord Northumberland, he'll tell you... Roch. My Lord y’are come to ſee a wretched Pair . Of Ormonds Iſſue leave this fatal World. - - Shall we not meet, and take our laſt Farewell : Nor, Norris, my Lord, is now upon the Scaffold, Then your turn follows; but before that time, ... . . .” - - - I gueſs the Queen will be prepar’d, and come, Koch. Forgive me, Heav'n, my Paſſion, and my Crime, . . . - For Natures choice of a wrong; fatal Objećl, ºn * > . . . . . . Loving too well, what in effect was ill. . . . . . . . O all you ſtrićt Idolaters of Beauty - -- * , . You fond, ſevere Adorers of that Sex, . . . . . . . Who think that all their Vices cannot Center . . . . . . . In one vile Womans Breaſt; ſee, and repent 1 I cºlº 'º - º Behold 'em all together * * * : * : tº tº . . . . . . . . . In the Infernal Blunt, in her they’re fix’d. " . . . . . . - Thus have they all been curſt, and thus they all . . . . . . . Have been betray'd, that loy'd ſo well as I. . . . . . . - - - - “... . . * . . . ºs . . . º ** = . . . . . . . . . . Effier, 2 . "... ... -- ------> - x -: * ~~~ • *. -- . -
Page 58

- º 58 VER / U E Betray'd : Or, Enter Queen going to Execution all in white : Diana, Women in Mourning; Guards. Queen. Come, where are thoſe muſt lead me to my Fate? To a more Glorious, Happy Marriage-Bed, - And my Eternal Coronation-day What, Piercy’s Father l muſt he do the Office 2 Still 1 can bear it all, and bear it bravely. Nor, Madam it is the Kings ſevere Command, That I attend your Majeſty to th’ Scaffold. . . . . - Queen. Enough, my Lord, you might have ſpar'd that Title Alas! I wiſh it ever had been ſpar’d - * ***, I ſhould have been, if Malice had not reign'd, Your Piercy's Wife, the Scope of my Ambition: I ne'er had then been mounted to a Throne; Then this unhappy-hour had never been. Koch. Mind this you Rocky World, and mourn in Chaos. Such words as theſe the Heav'ns muſt weep to hear, - And make yon Marble Roof diſſolve in Tears. - Queen. What! do you weep to ſee your Miſtreſs glory ! That ſhe ſhall ſtreight wipe off the ſtain on Earth She bears, with an unſpotted Fame in Heav'n? 1 charge you, by my hopes, and by your hopes, . When, you are going where I ſoon ſhall go; By the Illuſtrious Pomp I long to meet, - The Sacred, juſt Rewards of injur’d fruth; Acquaint this Noble Lord, and all here preſent, If e'er you ſaw in all my Nights or Days, Or in my looſer hours of Mirth or Humour, fhe maileſ: ſign of that moſt horridºi: . . . . That I’m condemn’d for 2–-Why, are you all dumb 2 If you are loth to tell it whilſt I live, Proclaim it when i'm dead, to all the World, . That Heav'n may bar the Gates of Bliſs againſt me, And throw me to the blackeſt of Hells Dungeons, . . . . Where all Diſſemblers at their Death ſhall howl. , , , , _Wom. Alas! moſt Gracious Miſtreſs, none can wiſh . . . . . Themſelves more Innocent for Death than you. . Queen. What doſt thou weep, unhappy Brother too ! Oh ſhew me not ſuſpečted, northy ſelf ... . . . So Guilty, by ſuch ſoftneſs——learn of me! . . . * This Bréaſt that's putrify’d by conſtant Woes? . . . . . By all my Wrongs, m” Injuſtice, and my Cauſe, , , ; ; ; Who ſees me weep, they ſhall be tears of Joy. Who grieves to leave the World, ſhall never come . . . º *- - .* . * * * Where I am going, where all ſorrow’s baniſh'd. . º º º, Roch. Tho’ I am innocent, my Fate is not; *Tis that has been unjuſt to thee and me.
Page 59

-- *. * - 2- º A N N A p U L L E IN. Queen. Tho’ 'tis a Common, 'tis a fatal ſign, we weep when we are born: but it was . More ominous, and much more fatal prov’d, … From theſe prophetick Eyes there guſht a ſhower, when Harry gave his Faithleſs hand to me; And on my Coronation day the like, My bodeing Heart another Tribute rack'd, Méthought there ſate a Mountain on my Head, , , , The Curſes of wrong’d Katherine weigh’d me down; And made my Crown indeed a Maſſey Crown. roch, Deny me not a little tender Grief, For every drop of Blood that's to be ſhed, of that ineſtimable Maſs of thine, My soul muſt rack a thouſand year; in Hell. Queen. Forbear ſuch words—You have not injur'd me: I might as well tax Providence, as you; For Éeav'n, that heard the Perjury of Villains, - Might, if it pleas'd, have chok'd'em with its Thunder, Or ſent 'em with a º blaſt to Hell! But he has bent their Rage another way, And on their Malice we ſhall ſafely mount, As on a Cherubin to Heav'n. North. My Lord, º you muſt prepare; a Meſſenger is come, , , , who brings the News that Norris is beheaded. Queen, Alas! unhappy 'Norris art thou dead? yet why do I ſo much wrong to pity thee Thou'rt hapdier by ſome moments now than I. 1 Now, Anna Bullen, teach me, all thy Courage; Thy innocence, that makes the Heav'ns amaz'd: And the more guilty Angels bluſh to ſee. - - Help me to paſs this Kubicon of Parting: This mid-way Gulph that hangs 'twixt Barth and Sky! Then that bieſt Region, all beyond is mine, And Ceſar was not half ſo great as I. * , - Queen, Go! be a lucky Harbinger for me; Roch, Come! lead me to my reſt, my reſt from Wrongs. * - ' Tell all the Saints, and Cherubins, and Martyrs, . º Tell all the Wrong'd, that now are righted there, - Till it ſhall reach the high, Imperial Ear, ". . . . That Anna Bullen is a coming ſtreight. . . roch, wilt not embrace thy dying Brother firſt * One Father and one Mother gave us Birth; . . . . - - - - And one Chaſt, Innocent Natures Bed inclos'd us-- . . Theſe are our Parents Arms, and ſo are thine. . . . . . . . Then all you Saints above, and Men belºw, Barwin'ſ, and ºwnsºn Death, ºf *. > º z ~ [One Whiffers North, -
Page 60

T e're receiv'd from Anna Bullen's Perſon. I need not fear theſe Eyes ſhould ſee you dye. . For e're that time, juſt Grief ſhall ſtrike me dead; - Or Torrents of theſe Tears will make me blind. " ... Envy of Mankind cannot be ſo Curſt. Nothing could ſhoot Infečtion through my Breaſt, 6o VER TO E. Betrayd: Or, It is the greateſt, firſt, and only favour - - Queen. In ſpite of Scandal, Malice, and the World; Nay, were the King and our vile Judges by, - Since Heav'n is ſatisfi'd it is no Sin; I will embrace thee, think I’ve in my Arms, - . . . Both Father, Mother, Siſter, Brother, all; - - And Envy cannot blame me now for this. - Roch. Thus, let thy Soul into my Boſom fly; - - That I may feel the ſtroke of Death for thee; And when the fatal Ax hangs o're thy Head, O' may it lull Thee, and not ſtrike thee dead; Softer than Infants Dreams, or with leſs pain, - - Than 'tis to ſleep, or to be born again [Ex. Roch. to: 2ueen. So, this is paſt and vanquiſht! but behold Executions, A greater yet Now 1 begin to dread - - Enter Diana, with the young Princeſs, and Women. - Ah kind Diana, wonderful and good | - The pity that thou ſhew'ſt thy dying Friend, - —tº - This little one, I hope, will live to pay. - - - Dian. Ah Royal Miſtreſs England’s falling Star ! Beſt Pattern that e're Earth receiv'd from Heav'n- --> Queen. Come, lift her to my Arms, and let me Kiſ her, For *.is the laſt kind Office you will do me. . . . . Now let me preſs thy little Coral Lips * . With my dead pale ones now!" and oh let me. - - lnfuſe ſome of thy Mothers lateſt Breath, -- . . . . in Bleſſings on thy tender, blooming Soul— ‘. . . . What's this that tempts me with a Mothers Fondneſs tº * A To break my Reſolution, and upbraids me, - . . . . . That I muſt leave thee to a Fathers Rage, N. - And yet more Cruel Enemies to both 2 - - - Leave thee a Lamb, 'mongſt Wolves; for all who’ve been Thy Mothers Foes will certainly be thine. Dian. Tygers, nor Devils' or what's more inhumane; Queen. See, ſºe Diana by my Wrongs it weeps, Weeps like a thing of Senſe, and not a Child; - Like one well underſtood in Grief; the Tears, Drop ſenſibly in order down its Cheeks; And drowns its pretty Speech in thoughtful Sorrow. But this ; and this has done it——— - Why weeps my Child? Ah, what a Queſtion's that!
Page 61

. . A N N A B U L L E N. 6 I- Pian. Behold I how’t ſtrives; and betwixt Tears and Throbs, If it could form a Language, it would ſpeak. & Queen, Strive not for Words, my Child; theſe little drops Are far more Eloquent than Speech can be— Be pitiful, my Lord; and thou, my kind Diana, ever faithful to thy Queen; When I am dead, as ſhortly I ſhall be, - - Take this poor Babe, and carry’t to the King ; - - . Its Lips juſt pregnant with its Mother's Fondneſs, ` - / Perhaps he'll take her then into his Arms; * . - And tho’ the favour were to me deny’d; Steal there a Kiſs of mine. - ~ Say, 'tis the laſt Requeſt of Anna Bullen—— North. Remove the little Princeſs * - To her Apartment, where we ſtreight will come, And wait on her, as is the Queen’s Command. Queen. Yet let me hold her but a moment longer, And with this Kiſs, that now muſt be my laſt, - . unlock a Secret, which Heav'n dićtates, to me. If e're there is a Light that does tranſcend . . . - - . . . " - - Dark humane Knowledge in the Breaſt of Man, . . . Fate to foreſee, there is a Light at Death, And that now bids me ſpeak. Thou, little Child, Shalt live to ſee thy Mother’s Wrongs o're-paid - - In many Bleſſings on thy Womans State. From this dark Calumny, in which I ſet, . - As in a Cloud; thou, like a Star, ſhalt riſe, . . . 2 And awe the Southern World: That holy Tyrant, " Who binds all Europe with the Yoak of Conſcience, _- , ºr 2 - - Holding his Feet upon the Necks of Kings; Thou ſhalt deſtroy, and quite unlooſe his Bonds, - And lay the Monſter trembling at thy Feet. - - -When this ſhall come to paſs, the VVorld ſhall ſee - - - º . Thy Mothers Innocence reviv’d in thee, - º - - - L.Ex. Women with the Princeſ; Eliz. * * North. Madam with greater pain to me than Racks, I’m forc'd to let you know your Brother's dead: And that, alas! you muſt prepare. - - Queen. My Lord! - ~ , I thank you, you miſtake your noble Office; - - . It is the Voice of Angels to wrong’d Martyrs; The ſound of Cherubs trumpetting from Heav'n I've heard it ſaid, amongſt our many Ends, - | - Beheading is the mildeſt Death of any. - - | - If it be ſo; I thank my Gracious Lord: For I was never us’d to pain—How ſay you? . . . . . . . . North. We cannot wiſh you lºº y'are to dye, * d - - 2. - I.G., -
Page 62

62 V & R 77) E Betray'd: 0r, And if the Head-man do as he's command. * . 'Twill be no more, than 'tis to drop aſleep. rºº. My Lord. I've but a little Neº: Therefore I hope hel not repeat his Blow; , , • But do it, like an Artiſt, at cne ſtroke. Aorth. There is no fear. He has particular Order, - £ºttº...Then let me go; Heav'n chies my fond delay— ' But tell the King, I ſay it as I juſt - - Am going to dye; I both forgive, and bleſs him, '. And thank him as my kindeſt Benefactor— Firſt from an humble Maid he lifted me • To Honour; then he took me to his Bed, The higheſt State that I could be on Earth; And now, as if he thought he ne’re cºuld do Enough for me, has mounted me 19, Heav'n— North. Mr. Lieutenant On, and lead the way. . . . . . Queen. If 'tis no Sin to skip one moment now - 9f what belongs to Heav'n; let me remember Poor Piercy once— Here, take this Innocent Kiſs, : - A Token to you both 'Tis thine and his— Farewel, Diana. Farewell to you ji. . 3. *ºtºel to all ourseses Glory. £º Wºp not for me; but hearmy dying Sentence. . . . . . Any that ſhall hereafter faii'like me. _- - - - Falſly accus’d by wicked Men and Traytors; - - Tho' in this Wörld y’are §ºat, in Virtue ſtrong; - Never Blaſpheme, and ſay that Heav'n does wrong; Nor think an undeſerv'd Death is Hard; For Innocence is ſtill its own Reward. - - And when th' Almighty makes a Saint, ſometimes He aſts by Contraries, and Villains Crimes, - - Whilſt thus, their Malice, always cheated is, \ - And leads us but the neareſt way to Bliſs. - - - - [Bºit Queen to Execution, nº Northumberland and Guard, - - Enter Piercy alone. - - Fiºr. I dread the horrid deed is done, or now A doing, elſe what means this ſudden Gioom - Qad o're the Morning Sky, and aii Mankind: All paſs with Horror by, with frighted Looks and Vo - . ICC Liſt up to Heav'n, who ſees and hjm vain; £hen ſhake their melancholly head, like Time: A general Conſternation ſtižes ałl, . . . . . ** if the Univerſal Empreſs of the Wºrld, *ature itſelf, were fled with Ama Eni.” . Haſt thou beheld this great Eclipſ of Virtue? ... " * isthiºn Büssiºdłºś. & * * - » * Enter a Gentleman with a Hanckgrºhief ſtain’d with thegum Bloºd. -
Page 63

A N N A BUT LEN 63 As I commanded ? . . . . "Gent. Sir, when the fatal blow I ſaw perºd. - Swift as a W Whirlewird, through the Cºtid i ruſh'd, , - And, as the Blood from their rich Veſſ is drain'd, #. Linen with the Sacred Crimſºn tº . pier. Give’t me! and leave ºn tº ſei: a noment. -- Now Sacred Drops, now Heav'nly Nečar, firſt ºil kiſs, then pledg; you with a dying Thirſt— . . . vº... this I feel my Sºul tea at my Wound, . A. bid me to remember now's the time 3 ~ Now to let out Liº's Navigable Stream, - And mix it with this moſt Čeleſti, Flood, - Thus, as kind Rivers to their Ocean run. Fiji'i'ſ deſcend by juſt degrees to Earth, º' º: , Thus on my Knees, and wing my Soul to Heaven, . . . ." - - - - - - ... [Kneels, where Anna Bullen waits for her Piercy's coming; ºr . . . And with this Bloody ſign the Pow’rs implore, ... . - Like a poor Wretch, Ship-wrack'd on Hºme Lone ſhoar, who ſpies a Sail far off, waves 'em his hand, ~ To come, and waſt him from the Barren Land. . . . . . . . . *” “” Enter Diana. . . . . . * > . . Behold the good Diana- by thoſe Tears, . . . . . . something of horror ’tis thºu haſt to ſay. . . . . . . . Tian. Alas! my Lord, whº have you done 2 * ~ * * Your wound does bleed afreſh. ... . . . . your looks are alter'd] all thoſ Maſculine Beauties, . - That ſhone in your illuſtrious Face, and made . . . . . . . . . H. nºt brave Epitomy of Mankind, Are vaniſh’d on a ſudden, and you hang Like a pale Carcaſs on my trembling Arms— ºr le me run and call for help T-ſº fºch Your Father, fetch the King, Quick, let me go— . . - pier, o bear me to ſome horrid Deſart rather, i. - - - where nought but Tygers, Wºº. and Panthers breed, . . . . They are more merciful thai, King or Parent. - I feel, like the wrong'd patriarch, a deſire - ". . . . To do ſome fatal Miſchief with my end. . . . . . stand by me; and correót me with thy Virtue, ‘. . . . Éire i ſhall loſe the Duty of a Soº * -- º And subject, do a raſhneſs to be famº for, . . Pull down a ſhow’r of Curſes on the Heads of this Philiſtin-King, and Cruel Father. . . . . º * . * * - • * ;º a Dºsion’ſºmeº. tº *.*Gººf, like a fibris Liubeck, by aegists, * º With ſtill diffuſion quite *:::::::::: º * ... sº and ſteals by drops my Blood and Špirits away.”
Page 64

X ---. * - * -º-; * * 44 V E R To E Betrayd: Or, But firſt Diana, I’ll be juſt I doubt if I have ſtrength My Father made me vow If I here die to thee to riſe again—- - - . . [She raiſes him upon his Knees: to be your Husband; ' ' I kneel that you'd forgive me; But if I live, I'll keep my promiſe to you. - Dian. You faint, you fink, you die; ſome Creature help— Pier. Go, ſtrive to lave the Water of the Sea, And quench the burning Arna, ’tis in vain, And ſo are Eſculapius Remedies to me— - Look, ſee'ſt thou this, as long as I have this, [Shem's the Handkerchief. This here, to waft me o'er Deaths dreadful Main, - ‘I need no Sword, no Poiſon, nor no Pain. - Dian. What’s that I ſee? Your Blood? Your vital Blood Pier. Yes I of a Heart far Dearer than my own. - Now, now my Blood, my Crowd of Spirits, all Ruſh to behold, and with their Standard fall. Dian. Why ſtand I here, like Marble made of Woe, ** "And run not for the cure of both our lives 2 For ſhou’d l ſtay, 1 ſhall In dying with him. Pier. Thus when the Generous Lyon ſees the Blood - - betray my Love - *. [Exit Diana running. Of his once Royal Maſter ſhed like this; Taking the Lawn, ſtain’d with Imperial Gore, At firſt he Frowns, and then begins to Roar. Laſhes his Sides; his fiery And with his awful Voice Till finding no Relief, at And weeps, Tears falling Then gently on it, as his Aud with a Groan, breaks Eye-balls rolls, Revenge he calls ; - length he's mute, from the Kingly Brute; , Death-bed lies, - * - his ſtout Heart, and Dies. [Diet. Enter Northumberland, and Gentlemen. - Gentl. He's dead t Alas, he's dead! W’are come too late | North. Here let me fix till my Gray Hairs ſhall rot, Or turn to Snakes, to plague this Aged Head; , 's And never more be look’d on to upbraid me ! - This is a Puniſhment for what my Eyes - Llnpitying ſaw; and now 1 feel, dear Piercy, Thy Father's Curſes on his own head turn, And thou art bleſt, and l alas, forlorn. Enter King, Lords, Attendants, and Guards, King, Whom mourn'ſt North. 'Tis Piercy's: You and all good Men ſhou’d weep, . . . . For you have loſt a faithful Queen, and l a Son. - -- - - - thou over ? Whoſe dead Body’s that? Aorth. Norris and Rochford, and th’ unhappy Queen, . . . . . . . . A * ... : Were all Beheaded in one fatal hour; - - . . ; ; ; ; ; ; /* -º-, . * * * * - . . . . . . - - * --- º: ! Yet - > . . . ki. Tº Tongº tº bºldſ are all the traitors dead? &

Page 65

, Was ſitting to behold that diſmal ſight : - A N N A BUL LEN º - - * --- - * - Yet all the Traitors are not dead. . . . *A sº King. What mean'ſt thou ? Say! who has ſcap'd? . . . . . . . . . . . . North. The haughty Blunt, deck with * Her proudeſt Ornaments of Gold and Jewels, - Came to behold their Ends upon the Scaffold, - . - - . . . . . . . * -º- º * * *-* - . . . º * And ſaw 'em with a Helliſh Cruelty; a Till Anna Bullen's Head lopp'd from her Body; . . . . The brighteſt Ornament of that Perſon fell . . . tlpon that wretched Womans knees, as ſhe - The Trunkleſs Head with darting Eyes beheld her, Making a motion with its Lips to ſpeak, - As if they meant t”upbraid her curſed Treaſon. - . When ſtreight the dreadful Accident ſo ſtruck her, - . . . Swift as a Hind ſhe gave a leap, and with . . . . . . . . . . . . . . A ſudden ſhriek, ſhe ſtarted into Madneſs, . . . . . . . . . So fierce, that juſt and ſpeedy Death muſt follow; Then uttering ſtrange, and horrid Guilty Speeches, ºt In her diſtraćtion ſhe accus’d her ſelf, And Woolſey: Talk'd that the Queen was innocent; . Saying the Letters found within her Cloſet Were falſe, and plac’d by them to ruine her: . . . . . . . . . . - For which her cruel Ghoſt, ſhe ſaid, did haunt her. King. Where is the Traitor Woolſey f º North. Fled to Eſher. . . . - - Ring. Go you in Perſon, and ſecure the Villain! Many foul Cauſes claim his forfeit Life; . . But if 1 find him guilty in the leaſt, . . . . Of a Contrivance with this curſed Woman; ; , , , , (Though the Queen juſtly merited her End). . . . . - I’ll rack his Soul out with a thouſand Tortures. . . . . . . . . . Marth. 'Twill be ſome joy to my Revenge and Piercy's. . . . . King. For thy Son's Death, thy King ſhall be a Mourner—'. " Now Heav'n vouchſafe to pardon till this time, " ' ". . . What 1 by Sycophants advice have done, º º 1 will be Abſolute, and Reign alone: ; . . . . . . For where's a States-man fam'd for juſt and wiſe ; , , But makes our failings, ſtill his aim to iſ " " . . . . . If Subjećts thus their Monarchs Wills reſtrain; , , , . . . . . . *Tis they are Kings; for them we idly Reign: . . . . . . . . Then I'll firſt break the Yoak; this Maxim ſtill. Shall be my Guide (A Prince can do no ill!). In ſpight of Slaves, his Genius let him truſt; - For Heav'n ne'er made a King, but made him juſt. IExeum omni, s . Epi-

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page Scan 92

Zo ſee you 46 what we ſhould Repreſent. " . . . . . . . - EP I Lo G U E. E/, Sirs / Tour kind 0 inion now, I pray: º Of this our neither. Whig nor Tory-Play; . . - To low ſuch coals our Conſcious AMuſe denies; Wit, Sacred Wit, ſuch Subječis ſhould deſpiſe. The Author ſays his Heliconian ſtream, - Is not yet drain'd to ſuch a low extream. . . . . . * - - - To abuſe one Party with a Carſed Play, . . . . . . . . . . . . . . And bribe the other for a large third Day. . . . . . . . Like Gladiators then, you ſtreight reſºrt; And troud to make your Nero-Faëtion ſport. But what's more ſtrange, that Men ºf ſenſe ſhould do it ! : For Worrying one another, pay the Peet ; , . So Butchers at a Baiting, take delight, . . . For him that keeps the Bears, to Roar and Fight; - Both Friends and Foes, ſuch Authors make their Game, Who have your Mony, that was all their Aim ; ; sº No matter for the Play, nor for their Wit; * - - The better Farce is Aéied in the Pit. º ... * - - Both Parties to be cheated, well agree; 7 . . . . And fivallow any Nonſence, ſo it be - With Fatlion fac'd, and guilt with Loyalty. X . . . . Here's ſuch a Rout with Whigging, and with 7.orying, * - That you negleif your dear-lov'd fin of Whoring;" " . . . . The Wiſor-mask, that ventur'd her Half-crown, " ' '. Finding no hopes but here to be undone; . . . . . . . . . Like a Caſt Mi % paſt her dear delight, º, . . . . . . Turns Godly fºreight, and goes to Church inſpight; . . . . " And does not doubt, ſince you are grown ſo fake, nº lºa º To find more Cullies in a Conventitle: . . . . . . . . . . . . We on the Stage ſtand ſt/, and are content, ". . . . . . - - - - --- ---. Tº f; . . . .'; 'fºº', Ton uſe us like the Women that you Woe; º, º ºsºvº Tou make us ſport, and pay us for it too, º iſ . . . . . . . . . . Weſ/, w are reſolv'd that in our next Play-Bill, Lºſ . To Print at large a Tryal of your ski/;º ºf ; ; ; ; And ſº hºndred Monſters are to fight, , , º, Zhen more ºil, run to ſee ſº ſtrange a fight, 9 º' Than the Morocco, or the Muſcovite, ºvº - “. . . - - - - F I N I S.
Page Scan 93

Blank page
Page Scan 94

------ - - ***** - -- - - - - - —ºr -–
Page Scan 95

--------- -- - * * -



Page Scan 96

Blank page

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents

End of text. Return to beginning.
