
Skip to main content

    Internet Archive Logo
    web
    books
    video
    audio
    software
    images
    search

    uploadUPLOAD
    personSIGN IN

    ABOUT
    CONTACT
    BLOG
    PROJECTS
    HELP
    DONATE
    JOBS
    VOLUNTEER
    PEOPLE

Full text of "The elder brother : a comedy as it is now acted at the Theatre Royal, by His Majesties Servants"
See other formats

• *#






























■ f-■ *


THE


Elder



A


C O M E D Y.

As it is now A<5ted at the

THEATRE ROYAL,’

By His M'AJ E.STIES Servants.


/




A


Written by


Francis Beaumont^ 1

Sc ^ Gent.

John Fletcher, ^ y








^LONDON,

Printed by T. N. for D. N. and T. C. and arc to be
fold by George Marriott^ at the Sign of the Temple
aezi the Inner Temple Gate'm Fleetjireet,

M. DC. LX XVIII.






















t •"


\




¥


'i >

S'.'®




•* .^•


;ii




I

{ f ■^'






,-f>


i • ■*>’ ■'« t-♦'' '\ ■^fc i* tv

‘ - ■<■ v:' 'W

f > •' --

■« » ' V .








T

wl.


f


\r

L


r>. i. t

kJ




r - -I

<

J


V'


i - »•


r-.

1^






c . •


/*/


' - . ^ ' ?


/








v'*


' i rr ,’«•*••. r I .- ’■} *^^ ' ti '• '.■{ •♦■' '


'i


_, .. ...

. r'^v'a • J/'l




'i, ■. .


f •^- t

4

' % X


A.%




'^J *_ .


oa


VI n 1


sy w«i.




' 11 • O?


•i 'T 1 ^


r

. r -1 ^
^ i.»j*


» V -'


. > »

1 V f ^

■ ' i ^


'/ O ••■ 1 ^' ‘1"'. ?

• '-^ ''»- I ij t i f -^ ^ 1 ^ *


* / ' - 'i ■ ■

* -* »i ,' i




„■ J^-rV:'.

b *4 • ^


*‘r ^ t 1

;, « 4 V V » i ', t



• ■>: • • »

- . ■ . 4 . :


4 - : . f\*


V- V 5 s ..


*r



~^ ' ’ J

r, ♦^s ?t '» t\ . ■^

^ ) 4 41 I ^ i J ^




Cl ,M












Lewis,

Miramont,

Brifac,

Charles,

Euftace,

Egremont,

Gowfy,

Andrew,

Cook,

Butler,

Prieft.

Notary;.

Servants.

Officers.


Angellina,

Sylvia,

Lilly,

Ladies,


The Spea(ers of the Ttay


a Lord:
a GentUman,

a JnJihey Brother to Mkamont.


Y a Scholary
§ a Courtiery


J Sonsto^n^c:


^tm Conrtkrsyfriends to Euftace..
Servantto Charles*


^Servants ^ Briikc.





_ r

Daughter to Lewis*
her Woman.

Wife to Andrew*


LECTORI

Would’!} thou all Wit^ .aU Comtek. Art furvey ?
Read here and- wonder j Fletcher writ the Play.






B 'Vt that it tvould taJ^e from onr modetiy^
To praife the Writer^ or the Comedy,^

Till yow fair fftfftage crown'it^ I (houldfay,
Tare allmofi welcome to no •vulga^r/f layy ,
Andfo far w are confident: And if he
That made it,ftill lives in your memory,

Tou will expeS what we prefent to night.
Should be judg’d worthy of your ears and fight.
Tou (hall hear Fletcher in it^ his true fir ain.
And neat exprefiions , liying he did gain
Tour good opinions •, but now dead commends
This Orphan to the care of Noble Friends •, ^
And may it raife in you content and mirth, ,
And be receiv d for a legit’mate birth.

Tour grace ereils new Trophies to his fame.
And Jhall, to after^times, preferve his name.




c



' • rr i { O ,■ i , „

^ , .-t •* i i ' 5 f,

f T r

I

f' . ^ •










i





A COMEDY.



ACTUS I, SC^NA I.

Levpjs^ Atrgellina.^ Sylvia.

Lewis,

Ay J walk you farther.

A/^g.lum tir’d. Sir, and ne’er (hall foot it
home.

Lew. Tis for your healthy the want ofex-
ercife takes from your Beauties, and floth dries
up your fvveetnefs: That you are my onely
Daughter and my Heir, is granted 5 and you in


irtT:iau»t

thankfulneft mufl needs acknowledge, you ever find me an indul¬
gent Father, and open-handed.

A?7g. Nor can you tax me, Sir, I hope, for want of duty to de-
ferve thefe favours from you.

Lew. No, my Angellina^ I love and cherifh thy obedience to me.
Which my care to advance thee (hall confirm : all that I aim at, is,
to win thee from the praftife of an idle foolifli ftate, us'd by great
Women, who think any labour (though in thefcrviceofthemfelves)
a blemilh to their fair fortunes.

Ang. Make meunderftand. Sir, what ’tis you point at.

B


I


tew.










































2


THE ELDER BROTHER.

/.OT. At the cuftom, how Virgins of wealthy Families wafce their
youths after a long deep, when you wake, your Woman prefents
your Ereakfoll:, then you fleep again, then rife, andbein^ trimm d
up by others hands, y are led to Dinner, and that ended, either to
Cards or to your Couch, ( as if you were bom without motion )
after this to Supper, and then to Bed: and fo your life runs round
without variety or aftion. Daughter.

Sj/. Here's a learned Lefture!

Lew, From this idlenefs, difcafes, both in body and in mind, grow
ftrongupon you 5 where a ftirring nature, with wholefomeexercife,
guards both from danger: Fd have thee rife with the Sun, walk,
dance, or hunt, vifit the Groves and Springs, and learn the virtue
of Plants and Simples: Do this moderately, and thou (halt not, with
eating Chalk, or Coles, Leather and Oatmeal, and fuch other trafh,
fall into the Green ficknefs.

5 y/. With your pardon ( were you but pleas'd to minifter it ) I
could preferibe a Remedy for my Lady's health, and her delight
too, far tranfcending thofe your Lordlhip but now mention’d.

What is it, Sylvia ?

Syl. What is’t! a noble Husband 5 in that word, a noble Husband,
all content of woman is wholly comprehended : He will roufe her,
as you fay, with the Sun 5 and fo pipe to her, as fhe will dance,
ne'er doubt it 5 and hunt with her, upon occafion, until both be
weary 3 and then the knowledge of your Plants and Simples, as I
take it, were fuperfluous. A loving, and,but add to it, a gamefbme
Bedfellow, being the fure Phyfician.

Lew, Well faid, Wench.

Af 9 g,hiiA who gave you Commiffion to deliver your Verdift,
Minion ?

Syl, I deferve a Fee, and not a Frown, dear Madam : I but fpeak
her thoughts, my Lord, and what her modefty refufesto give voice
to. Shew no mercy to a Maidenhead of fourteen, but off with't:
Let her lofe no time, Sir 5 Fathers that deny their Daughters
lawful pleafure, when ripe for them, in fbme kinds edge their ap¬
petites to tafte of the fruit that is forbidden.

Lew, 'Tis well urg’d, and I approve it: No more bluftiing. Girl,
thy Woman bath fpoke truth, and fo prevented what I meant to
move to thee. There dwells near us a Gentleman ofbloud, Mon-
fieur Brifac^ of a fair Eftate, fix thoufand Crowns per atwitm,, the
happy Father of two hopeful Sons, of different breedings tlie elder,

a meer




3


THE ELDER BROTHER.

a meer Scholar 5 the younger, a quaint Courtier.

Sir, I know them by publick fame, though yet I never (aw
them5 and that oppos’d antipathy between their various dilpofi-
tions, renders them the general difcourfc and argument^ one part
inclining to the Scholar Charles^ the other fide preferring £ufucc^
as a man compleat in Courtlhip.

Lw. And which way fifofthefe twoyouwere tochufe a Huf
band) doth your affedion fivay you ?

Af 7 g. To be plain Sir, ( fince you will teach me boldnefi) as they
are fimply themfelves, to neither: Let a Courtier be never fo ex-
ad, let him be blefi’d with all parts that yield him to a Virgin gra-
tious5 if he depend on others, and ftandnotonhis own bottoms,
though he have the means to bring his Miftris to a Mafque, or by
conveyance from fome great ones lips, to tafte fuch favour from
the King: or grant he purchafe precedency in the Court, to be
fworn a (ervant Extraordinary to the Queen ^ nay, though he live
in expedation of fome huge preferment in reverfion^ if he want a
prefent fortune, at the beft thofe are but glorious dreams, and
onely yield him a happinefs in fojfe^ not in ^ 3 nor can they fetch
him Silks from the Mercer, nor difchaige a Tailors Bill, nor in full
plenty ( which ftill preferves a quiet Bed at home ) maintain a
Family.

Ler^. Aptly confidei’d, and tomy wifti: But whafs thy cenfure
of the Scholar ^

Ang. Troth fif he be nothing ehej as of the Courtier, all his Songs
and Sonnets, his Anagram.s, Acrofticks, Epigrams, his deep and Phi-»
lofbphical Difcourle of Nature s hidden Secrets, makes not up a
perfed Husband 5 he can hardly borrow the Stars of the Celeftial
Crown to make me a Tire for my Head, nor Charles s Wain for a
Coach, nor Gats-ymede for a Page, nor a rich Gown from Jnnas
Wardrobe, nor would Hie in (for Idefpair not once to be a Mother)
under Heaven’s fpangled Canopy,or Banquet my Gueftsand Goffips
with imagin’d Nedary pure Orleans would do better: No, no.
Father, though I could he well pleas’d to have my Husband a
Courtier, and aSchoIar, young, and valiant 5 thefe are but gawdy
nothings, if there be not fomething to make a lubftance.

Lezi?.And what is that?

A^-^. A full Eftate, and that laid. I’ve faidall^ and get me fuch a
one with thefe Additions, farewell Virginity, and welcome Wed¬
lock.

B 2 Leiv.








4 THE ML D E R B R OTH E K.

Zbzv. But where is fiicha one to be met wit, Daughter? A black
Swan, is more common 3 you may wear grey Treffes ere we
find him.

lam not fo pundual in all Ceremonies, I will bate two or
three of thele good parts, before Fll dwell too long upon the
choice.

5 )//. Onely, my Lord, remember, that he be rich and aftive, for
without thefe, the others yield no relifh, but thele perfedl:. You muft
bear with fmall faults, Madam.

LexM. Merry Wench, and it becomes you well 5 Fll to Bnfac^ and
try what may be done ^ fth*mean time home, and feaft thy thoughts
with th’plealures of a Bride.

SjL Thoughts are but airy food, Sir, let her tafte them.

■>

ACTUS I. SCiENAlL

Andrew^ Cook^^ Butler.

Unload part of the Library^ and make room for th’other dozen of
Carts 5 111 ftraight' be with you.

Why, hath he more Books? • *

Ar/d. More than ten Marts lend over. '

Btit. And can he tell their names ?

Their names he has’em as perfeft as \\\s Pater Noiler'-^ but
that’s nothing, ’has read them over leaf by leaf three thouland times,
but here’s the wonder,-though their weight would fink a Spanifh
Carrock, without other Ballaft, he carrieth them all in his head, and
yet he walks upright.

B//t. Surely he has a ftrong brain.

Arid, If all thy Pipes of Wine were fill’d with Books, made of the
Barks of Trees, or Myfteries writ in old moth-eaten Vellam, he
would fip thy Cellar quite dry, and ftill be thirfty; Then for’s
Diet, he eats and digefts more Volumes at ameal,than there would
beL u ks (though the Sky fhoiild fall) devoured in a month \nParis.
Yet fear not Sons o’the Buttery and Kitchin, though his learn’d fto-
mach cannot be appeas’d^ he’ll feldom trouble you, his knowing
ftomach contemns your Black-Jacks, Butler^ and your Flagons ^ and,
Cool{^x\\y Boil’d, thy Roaft, thy Bak’d.

Cool{. How liveth he ?

And, Not as other men do, few Princes fare like him 5 he breaks
his faft with Ariflotle^ dines with takes his Watering with the

Mule,



THE ELDER BROTHER. y

Mufo, (ups with Z./zy', then walks a turn or two in ViaLaSea^ and
(after fix hours eonkrence with the Stars ) fleeps with old JSrr^
Pater,

But, This is admirable.

A?^d,Y\\ teH you more hereafter. Here smy oldMafter, and an¬
other old ignorant Elder 5 111 upon ’em.

Ef2ter Brifac, Lewis.

What, Andrew} welcome5 where’s my Charles} (peak, Andrew^
where did’ft thou leave thy Matter?

And, Contemplating the number of the Sands in the High-way,
and from that, purpoles to make a Judgment of the remainder in
the Sea; he is, Sir, in ferious ^ttudy, and will lole no minute, nor
out of *s pace to knowledge.

Loir. This is ttrange.

And, Yet he hath fent his duty. Sir, before him in this fair Manu-
fcript.

Brif, What have we here ? Pot-hooks and Andirons!

And,\mMc\i pity you, it is the Syrian Charafter, or the Arabick.
Would *eehave it faid, (b great and deep a Scholar as Mr. is,
fliould ask blefling in any Chrittian Language Were it Greek I
could interpret for you, but indeed I’m gone no farther.

Bri. And in Greek you can lie with your fmug Lilly,

And. Ifl keep her from your French Dialed, asl hope I flialI,Sir5
However (he is your Laundrefs, fhe (hall put you to the charge of
no more Soap than ufual for th*wa(hing of your Sheets.

Bri. Take in the Knave, and let him eat.

And. And drink too. Sir.

Bri. And drink too, Sir, and (ee your Matters Chamber ready
for him.

But. Come, Dr. Andrew, without Dilputation thou fhalt Com¬
mence i’th Cellar.

And, I had rather Commence on a cold bak’d meat.

Cow. Thou fhalt ha’t, Boy. [Exit,

Bri. Good Monfieur Lewis^ I etteem my (elf much honour’d in
your clear intent, to joyn our antient Families, and make them one 5
and’twill take from my age and cares to live, and fee what you have
purpos’d but in aft, of which your vifitat thispre(entis a hopeful
Omens I each minute expefting the arrival of my Sons5 I have

not








1


6 THE ELDER BROTHER.

not wrong’d their Birth for want of Means and Education, to (hapc
them to that courfe each was addifted ^ and therefore that we
may proceed difcreetly, fince what’s concluded rafhly feldom pro-
fpers, you firft (hall take a ftrift perulal of them, and then from
your allowance, your fair Daughter may fafbion her afFc-
ftion.

JLeiv. Monfieur Brifac^ you offer fair and nobly, and I’ll meet
you in the lame line of Honour^ and I hope, being bleft but with
one Daughter, I (hall not appear impertinently curious, though
with my utmoft vigilance and ftudy, I labour to beftow her to
her worth : Let others fpeak her form, and future Fortune from me
defcendingto her 5 I in that (it down with filence.

Eru You may, ray Lord, fecurely, fince Fame aloud proclaimeth
her perfeftions, commanding all mensitongues to fing her praifies \
(hould I (ay more, you well might cenlure me (what yet I never
was) a Flatterer. What trampling’s that without of Horles ?'

Enter Entler.

c.

But. Sir, my young Mafters are newly alighted.

Br/. Sir, now ob(erve their feveral di(po(itions.

Enter Charles.

Char.'^^A my Supfiler carry my Hackney to the Butt’ry, and
give him his Bever 5 it is a civil and fober Beaft, and will drink mo¬
derately -y and that done, turn him into the Quadrangle.

Bri. He cannot out of his Univerfity tone.

Euftace, Egremont, Cowfy.

Lackey, take care our Couriers be well rubb’d, and cloath’d 5 they
have out-ftripp’d the Wind in (peed.

Len?. I marry. Sir, there’s metall in this young Fellow ! What a
Sheep s look his elder Brother has!

Char. Yonx ble(Iing,Sir.

Bri. Ri(e, Charles.^ thou haft it.

Eiifi. Sir, though it be unufual in the Court, (fince *tis the Cour¬
tiers garb) I bend my knee, and do expeft what follovrs.

Bri. Courtly begg d. My bleffing, take it.




^ THE ELDER . BKOTHER, 7

Effji. (fo Len?.) Your Lordfhip’s vow’d adorer. What a thing this

Brother is! yet Til vouchfafe him the new Italian Ihrug-—.

How clownilhly the Book-worm does return it >

Char, Tm glad ye are well. {_Reads.

Enji, Pray you be happy in the knowledge of this pair of ac-
complifh’d Monfieurs 5 they are Gallants that have feen both
Tropicks.

Bri, I embrace their love.

Egr, Which we’ll repay with fervulating.

Covp, And will report your bounty in the Court.

Bri. I pray you make deferving ufe on t firfl:. EuflacCy give enter¬
tainment to your Friends 5 whafsin my houfe is theirs.

Enjl. Which we’ll make ufe of5 let’s warm our brains with half
a dozen Healths, and then hang cold difcourfe, for well I^ak Fire¬
works. [Exi.

Lew. What, at his Book already >

Bri, Fie, fie, Charlesy no hour of interruption >

Char . Plato differs from Socrates in this.

Bri, Come, lay them by 5 let them agree at leifiire.

Cy6rfr. Man's life, Sir, being fb (hort, and then the way that leads
unto the knowledge of our felves, fb IcHig and tedious: each mi¬
nute (hould be precious.

Bri. In our care to manage worldly bufinefs, you muft part with
this Bookifh contemplation, and prepare your felf for aftion 5 ta'
thrive , in this Age is held the blame of Learning: You muft ftudy
to know what part of my Land s good for the Plough, and what
for Pafture 5 how to buy and fell to the beft advantage j how to
cure my Oxen when they’re o’er-grown with labour.

Char. I may do this from what I’ve read, Sir 5 for, what cdhcerns
Tillage, who better can deliver it thanin his Georgicl^ ^ and
to cure your Herds, his Bncolicks is a Mafter-piece 5 but when he
does defcribe the Common-wealth of Bees, their induftry, and
knowledge of the Herbs from„ which they gather Honey, with their
care to place it With decorum m the Hive, their Government among
themfelves, their order in going forth, and coming loaden homey
their obedience to their King, and his rewards to fuch as labour,.,
with his punifhments onely inflidfed on the flothful Drone 5 I’m* ra-
vilhed with it, and there reap my Harveft, and there receive the^
gain my Cattle bring me, and there find Wax aid Honey.








8


THE ELDER BROtHER,

Bri. And grow rich in your imagination^ heyday, heyday!
Gtorgickj^ BucoUckj^ and Bees! art mad ?

Char. No, Sir, the knowledge of thefe guards me from it.

Bri But can you find among your bundle of Books (and put in
all your Dittionaries that fpeakall Tongues) what pleafure they
enjoy, that do embrace a welWhapd wealthy Bride? Anfwer me
that.

Char. Tis frequent, Sir, in Story, there I read of all kind of vir¬
tuous and vitious womens the antient Spartan Dames, and Roman
Ladies, their Beauties and Deformities 5 and when I light upon a
Portia or Cormlia^ crown’d with ftill-flouiilBing leaves of truth
andgoodnefs^ with (iich a feeling I perufe their Fortunes, as if I
then had liv'd, and freely tafted their ravifhing fweetnefs 5 at the
preftnt loving the whole Sex*for their goodnefsand example. But
on the contrary, when I look on a Clytemr?eftra^ OEBlCullta 5 the firft
bath’d in her Husbands bloud y the latter, withixit a touch of piety,
driving on her Chariot o’er her Father’s breathlcfs Trunk, hon our
invades my faculties^ and comparing the multitudes o’th’guilty,
with the few that did die Innocents, I deteftand loath ’em as Ig¬
norance or Atheifin.

Bri. You refolve then ne’er to make payment of the debt you
owe me.

Char. What debt, good Sir ?

Bri. A debt I paid my Father when I begat thee, and made him a
Crandfire, which I expeft from you.

Char. The Children, Sir, which I will leave to all pofterity, be¬
got and brought up by my painful Studies, (hall be my living
[flue.

Bri. Very well 5 and I (hall have a general Colleftion of all the
juidditsfrom Adam to this time, to be my Granchild.

Char, And fuch a one, I hope. Sir, as (hall not (hame the Fa¬
nil y.

Bri. Nor will you take care of my Eftate ?

Char. But in my wifhes^ for know. Sir, that the wings on which
ny Soul is mounted, have long Cnee born her too high, to ftoop to
iny Prey that foars not upwards. Sordid and dunghil minds, com-
)Os’d of earth, in that groft Element fix all their happinefi 5 but
)urer Spirits, purg’d and refin'd, (hake off that clog of humane frail-
y j give me leave t’enjoy my felf ^ that place that does contain

my







THE ELDER BROTHER. 9

my Books (the beft Companions) is to me a glorious Court,
where hourly I converfe with the old Sages and Philofophers^
and fometimes for variety, I confer with Kings and Emperors,'
and weigh their Counfels, calling their Victories (.if unjuftly
got) unto a ftiid accompt, and in my phancy, deface their ilj-
pluc'd Statues^ can I then part with fuch conftant plealures,
•to embrace-uncertain vanities? No, be it your care t’augment
your heap of wealth 5 it (hall be mine t* increafe in know¬
ledge—— Lights there for my Study--

Bri. Was ever man that had reafon thus tranlported from all
fenle and feeling of his proper good ^ It vexes me, and if I found
not comfort in my young Eujiace^ I might well conclude my
name v/ere at a period!

Lew, He is indeed, Sir, the furer bafe to build on. ' ,

Ef^ter Euftace, Egremont, Cowfy, a^d Andrew.

, Bri, Etijlace,

Euji, Sir --

Bri, Your ear in private.

Af^d, Ifulpedmy Mafter has found harfh welcome, he s gone
Supperlefs into his Study 5 could I find out the caufe, it may be
borrowing of his Books, or fo, I fhall be latisfied,

Eifji, My duty (hall, Sir, take any form you pleafe 5 and in
your motion to have me married, you cut off all dangers the vi¬
olent heats of youth might bear me to.

Lew, It is well anftvefd

EhJI, Nor fliall you, my Lord, for your fair Daughter ever
find juft caufe to mourn your choice of me 5 the name of Huf
band, nor the authority it carries in it, (hall ever teach me to
forget to be, as I am now, her Servant, and your Lordftiips 5 and
but that modefty forbids, that Iftiould found the Trumpet of
my own deferts, I could fay, my choice manners have been fuch,
as render me lov'd and remarkable to the Princesof the Blood.

Ccw, Nay, to the King.

Egre, Nay to the King and Council.

j 4 //d, Thefeare Court-admirers, and ever eccho him that bears
the Bag. Though I bedull-ey'd, I fee through this jugling. ,

C Efifl,










TO the elder brother.

Then for my hopes.

• Cojv Nay certainties.

They ftand as fair as any mans. '-.What can there fall in
compals of her wiflies, which fhc (hall not be fuddenly pofiefs'd
of? Loves flie Titles ? by the grace and favour of my Princely
Friends, lam what (lie would haverne.

Brr. He (peaks well, and I believe him.

Lew, I could with I did (b. Pray you a word. Sir. He’sa pro¬
per Gentleman, and promife nothing, but what is poflible. So
far I will go with you 5 nay, I add, he hath won much upon
me 5 and were be but one thing that his Brother is, the bargain
were (bouftruc-k up.

Bn, What's that, my Lord ?

Lew. The Heir.. ; -

And. Which he is not, and I trufl: never (hall be.

Bri. Come,thatfliall breed no difference^ youfee Charles has
given o’er the worlds Vll undertake, and with much cafe, to
buy his Birth-right of him for a DryTat of new Books ^ nor
(halt my (fate alone make way for him, but my elder Brothers,
who being ifluelefs, to advance our name, I doubt not will add
his. Your relblution ?

Lew, FlI firft ac^juaint my Daughter with the proceedings 5 on
thefe terms I am yours, as (he(hall be, make you no (cruple. Get
the Writings ready, fhe (hall be tra6hible 5 to morrow we will
hold a (econd conference. Farewell, noble Eujiace -^ and you,,
brave Gallants.

Eujl Full increale of Honour wait ever on your Lordfhip.

And. The Gout rather, and a perpetual Meagrimi

Bri. You fee, EkJlMe^ how I travel to poffels you of a Fortune
you were not born to ^ be you worthy of it: III furnifla you for
^ Suitor ^ vifit her, and profper in't.

Eujl. She s mine. Sir, fear it notin all my travels, I ne'er met
a Virgin that could refift my Courtfhip.

EhJI. rfit'tnkenow^weremadefor ever,and willrevel it. [Ex.

And. In tough WeHh ParOey, which, in our vulgar Tongue, is
(trong-Hempen Halters^ my poor Mafter cozen'd, and I a looker
@n Mf we have fhidfd our Majors and our Minors, Antecedents
jyad Confequent^^ 'to. be concluded Coxcombs, w’have made a







THE ELDER BKOtHER. it

fair hand on"t. I am glad I hav£ found out all their plofl^, and
theiivConfpiracies ^ this (hall t old Monfieur MiramoM^ one, that
though he cannot read a Proclamation, yet dotes on Learning,
and loves my Mafter Charles iot being a Scholar 3 I hear hes
coming hither, I (hall meet him 5 and if he be that old, rough,
teafty blade he always us d to be, Til ring him fuch a peal, as
(hall go near to (hake their Belroom, peradventure beat m, for
he is fire and flax 3 and (a have at him. Exiu

Finis Alius prmu


JBm 11. Selena I.

Miramount^ Brifac.

Ay, Brother, Brother.

p\i Bri, Pray,. Sir, : be not moved, I meddle with no bufi^-
ne(s but mine own, and in mine own *tis realbn I (hould govern.-
But how to govern then, and underftand, Sir, and be as^,
wife as y'are hafty, though you be my Brother, and from pngi:
bloud fprung, I mufttell ye heartily and home too.

What, Sir?

Mir. What I grieve to find, you are a fool, and an old fool,
and that’s two-

Bri. We’ll part ’em, if you pleafe.

M/V: No, they’re entail’d to’em. Seek to deprive an honeft
noble Spirit, youreldeft Son, Sir, and your very Image, ("but he’s
(b like you, that he fares the worfe for’t) becaufe he loves his
Book, and dotes on that, and onely ftudics how to know things
excellent, above the reach of fuch courfe Brains as yours, fuch
muddy Fancies, that never will know farther than when to cut
your Vines, and cozen Merchants, and choak your hide-bound'
Tenants with mufty Harvefts.

Bai, You go too faft.

' Mir. I’am not come to my pace yet, Becaufe h’ has made his '
fhidy all his pleafure, and is retir’d into his Contemplation, not

C 2 medling












12 THE ELDER BROTHEK.

fncdling with the dirt and chaff of Nature, that makes the fpirit
of the mind mud too 5 therefore mlift he be flung from his inhe¬
ritance ? muft he be diipoflefs'd, and Monfieur Gingle-boy his
younger Brother — -

•jBr/. You forget your felf. ,

. Af/>. Becaule h'has been at Court, and learn d new Tongues,
andhowto (peak a tedious piece of nothmg^ tovary hisface as
Sea-men do their compafi, to worfliip Images of gold and filver,
and fall before the She-calvesof the feafon^ therefore muff he
jump intp his Brother’s Land ?

Bri. Have you done yet, and have you (pake enough in praife
of Learning, Sir ?

Mir. Never enough.

jBri.But, Brother, do you knpw what Learning is ?

Mir. It is not to be a Juftice of Peace as you are, and palter
out your time fth’penal Statutes. To hear the curious Tenets
controverted between a Proteftant Conftable, and Jefuite Cob-
ler 5 to pick Natural Philofophy out of BawdryJ, when your
Worfliips pleas’d to correftifie a Lady 5 nor ’tis not the main
Moral of blind Juftice, (which is deep Learning} when your
Worfliips Tenants bring a light caufe, and heavy Hens before ye,
both fat and feeble, a Coofe or Pig ^ and then you 11 fit like
equity with both hands weighing indifferently the ftate o’th’
queftion, Thefe are your Quodlibets, but no Learning, Brother.

Bri. You are fo parloufly in love with Learning, that I’d be
glad to know^ what you underftand. Brother j I’m fure you have
read all Arijlotle.

Mir. Faith no^ but I believe I have a learned faith, Sir, and
that’s it makes a Gentleman of cny fort 5 though I can (peak no
Greek, I love the found of’t, it goes fo thund’ring as it conjur’d
Devils: Charles^ fpeaks it loftily,arid if thou wert a man,or had’ft
but ever heard of Homers Iliads^ Wejiody and the Greek Poets,
thou wouldft run mad, and hang thy felf for joy th’hadft fuch a
Gentleman to be thy Son: O he has read foch things to me!

Bri. And you do underftand ’em, Brother ?

Mir. I tell thee. No, that’s not material 5 the found’s fufficient
fo confirm an honeft man : Good Brother Brifac^ does your
young Courtier, that wears the fine Cloaths, and is the excellent

Gentleman,




THE ELDER BROTHER. u

Gentleman, fthe Traveller, the Soldier, as you think too) nnder-
ftand any other power than his Tailor ? or knows what motion
is more than an Horfe-race ? What the Moon means, but to light
him home from Taverns ? or the comfort of the Sun is, but to
wear flaili'd clothes in? And muft this piece of ignorance be
popt up, becaufe’t can kifi the hand, and cry. Sweet Lady > Say
it had been at andfeen the Reliques, drunk your Ferdea

Wine, and rid at Nuples., brought home a Box of Fe? 77 ce Treacle
with it, to cure young Wenches that- have eaten afhes: Muft this
thing therefore ?-—

Bri. Yes, Sir, this thing muft, I will not truft my Land to one
fo lotted, (b grown like a difealeunto his Study 5 he that will
fling ojfFall occafions and cares, to make him underftand wliat
ftate is, and how to govern it, muft, by that reafon, be flunghim-
lelf afide from managing. My younger Boy is a fine Gentleman.

Mir. He is an Afs, a piece of Ginger-bread, gilt over to pleale
foolifti Girls puppets.

Bri. You are my elder Brother,

Mir. So I had need, and have an elder Wit, thou’dft (hame us
all el(e. Go too, I fay, Charles (hall inherit.

Bri. I (ay, No, unle(s Charles had a Soul to underftand it 3 Can
he manage fix thouiand Crowns a year out of the Metaphyfics ?
or can all his learn’d Aftronomy look to my Vineyards ? Can
the drunken old Poets make up my Vines (I know they can
drink em) or your excellent Humanifts fclTem the Merchants
for my belt advantage? Can Hiftorycut my Hay, or get my
Corn in ? and can Geometry vend it in the Market ? Shall I have
my Sheep kept with a Jacobs-Staffnow ? I wonder you will mag-
nifie this mad-man, you that are old, and (hould underftand.

Aiir, Should, (ai’ft thou? thou monftrous piece of ignorance
in office! thou that haft no more knowledge than thy Cleik in-
fufes, thy dapper Clerk, larded with ends of Latin, and he no
more than cuftom of offences. Thou unreprievable Dunce! that
thy formal Bandftrings, thy Ring, nor Pomander cannot expi¬
ate for, do*ft thou tell me I (hould ? I’ll pofe thy Worfhip in
thine own Library and Almanack, which thou art daily poring
on, to pick out days of iniquity to cozen fools in, and Full Moons
to cut Cattle: doTt thou taint me, that have run over Story,
Poetry, Humanity ? *












14 THE ELDER BROTHER.

Bri. As a cold nipping (hadow does o*r ears of Corn, and leave*
'em blafted, put up your anger, what 1*11 do, I’ll do.

Mir. Thou (halt not do.

Bri. I will.

Mir. Thou art an Als then, a dull old tedious Aft 5 th* art ten
times worfe, and of lefi credit than Dunce HollwgJJjcad the Eng-
lifhman, that writes of Shows and Sheriffs.


E^ter Lewis.


Bri. Well, take your pleafure, here’s one I mufl: talk with.

Lerv. Good-day, Sir.

Br/. Fair to you. Sir.

Lem. May I fpeak w’ye?

Bri. With all my hea t, I was waiting on your goodnefs.

Lem. Good mo/rovv?, ivlunfieur Miramont.

Mir. O fweet Sir, keep your good morrow to cool your. Wor-
(hips pottage 5 a couple of the Worlds Fools met together to
raife up dirt and dunghills. -

Ten:?. Are they drawn ?

Bri. They fliall be ready. Sir, within thefe two hours 3 and
Charles fet his hand.

Lem. ’Tis neceflary , for he being a joint purchafer, though
your Eftate was got by your own indiiltry, unlefs he feal to the
Conveyance, it can be of no validity.

Bri. He (hall be ready, and do it willingly.

Mir. He (hall be hang’d firfl:^

* Bri. I hope your Daughter likes. ^

Lem. She loves him well. Sir 5 young Enflace is a bait to catch ,

a Woman,a budding (pritely Fellow^ y are refolv’d then, that all
(hall pa(s from Charles. Bri. All, all, he’s nothing ^ a bunch of
Books (hall be his Patrimony, and more then he can manage too.

Lem. Will your Brother paft over his Land to your (bn Eufiace ^
you know he has no Heir. ■

Mir. He will be dead fir ft, and Horfe-collars made of’s skin. ^

Bri. Let him alone, a wilful man my Eftate (hall (erve the ;

turn, Sir. And how does your Daughter ? !

Lem. Ready for the hour, and like a blu(hing Role that (lays
the pulling. Bri.








THE ELDER BROTHER: 15

Bn, Tomorrow then^uhe day.

Lerip. Why then to monow Til bring theGirU get you the
Writings ready.

Al/r, But hark you, Monfieur, have you the virtuous con¬
science to ho^ to rob an Heir, an Elder Brother, of that which
Nature and the Law flings on him? You were your Fathers-
eldeft Son, I take it, and had his Land 5 would you had had fiis
wit too, or his difcretion, toconfider nobly, what ’tisto deal un¬
worthily in thefe things 5 you’ll fay he s none of yours, he s his
Son 5 and he will fay, he is no Son to inherit above a (helf of
Books: Why didhegethim ? why was he brought up to write
and read, and know thefe things? why was he not like his Fa¬
ther, a dumb Juftice ? a flat dull piece of phlegm, (hap’d like
man, a reverend Idol in a piece of Arras ? Can you lay difobe--
dience, want of manners,, or any capital crime to his charge ?

Lew. I do not, nor do weigh your words, they bite not me,.
Sir 5 this man muftanfwer

Bri. I have don’t already, and given ftifBcient reafon to^ fecure
me: and fogood morrow. Brother, to your patience..

Lew. Good morrow, Monfieur Miramont,

-M/r. Good night-caps keep brains warm, or Maggots will!
breed in’em. Well, Charles.^ thou (halt not want to buy thee
Books yet, thefaireft in thy Study are my gift, and the Univer--
fity of Lovam^ for thy fake,hath tafted of my bounty >and to vex:
the old doting Fool thy Father, and thy Brother,, they (hall not:
(hare a Solz of mine between them^ nay more, Lll give thee
eight thoufind Crowns a year, in feme high drain to write my,'
Epitaphs

ACTUS IT. SCiENA 11.

EnJiacCj Egre^o^t^ CawJ),

How do I look now, my elder Brother? Nay, ’tis a'handfome-
Suit.

Cowi All Courtly, Courtly.

EyJl.VW aflurc ye. Gentlemen, my Tailor has traveird,.andl
fpeaks as loftyLanguage in his Bills too^ the cover of an old Book
would not (liew thus.. Fie,fie 5 what things thefe Acadesnickstare ?
thefe Book-worms, how they look!: Egrs.







i6 The elder brother.

Egre, Th re meer Images, no gentle motion or behavicnr in'm 3
they’ll prattle'ye oi Vrimiim Mobile^ and tella ftory of the ftate
of Heaven, what Lords and Ladies govern in fuch Houfes, and
what wonders they do when they meet together, andhowthey
Ipit Snow, Fire, and Hail, likea Jugler, and make^^oife when
they are drunk, which we call Thunder.

C< 72 v. They are the fneaking ft things, and the contemptibleft 3
Such Small-beer brains, but ask ’em any thing out of the Ele¬
ment of their underftanding, and they ftand gapinglike a roafted
Pig: do they know what a Court is, or a Councel, or how the
affairs of Chriftendora are manag’d? Do they know any thing
but a tired Hackney ? and they cry abfurd as the Horfe under-
ftood ’em. They have made a fair Youth of your Elder Brother,
apretty piece of flefh.

Eufti I thank’em for’t, long may he ftudy to give me his Eftate.
Saw you my Mtftris ?

Egr. Yes, (he’s a fweet young Woman 3 but be fure you keep
her from Learning.

Euji. Songs ftiemay have, and read a little unbak’d Poetry,
fuch as theDablers of our time contrive, that has no weight nor
wheel to move the mind, nor indeed nothing but an empty found3
{he (hall have cloathes, but not made by Geometry 3 Horfe and
Coach, but of no immortal Race: I will not have a Scholar in
my houfe abovea gentle Reader 3 they corrupt the foolilh Wo¬
men with their fubtle Problems 3 I’ll have my houfe call’d igno¬
rance, to fright prating Philofophers from Entertainment,

It will do well, lovethoie that love good fafhions, good
cloathes, and rich 3 they invite men to admire’em, that (peak
the li(p of Court. Oh ’tis great Learning! to Ride well. Dance
well. Sing well, or Whiftle Courtly, th are rare endowments 3
that they have feen far Countreys, and can (peak ftrange things,
thoughthey(peakno truths, for then they make things common.
When are you marri’d ?

Ef^Ji. To morrow, I think 3 we muft have a Ma(que, Boys, and
of our own making.

Egre, ’Tis not half an hours work, zCnpid^ and a Fiddle, and
the thing’s done: but let’s be handfbme, (halls be Gods or
Nymphs }




THE ELDER bKOTHER.

EuU. What, Nymphs with Beards ?

Cow. That’s true, well be Knights then5 fome wandring
Knights, that light here on a (iidden.

Euji. Let s go, let’s go, I muft go vifit, Gentlemen, and mark
what (weet lips I miift kifi to morrow. [Exeunt.

ACTUS II. SCiENAIIL
Cook^^ Andrew^ Butler.

And how do s my Mafter }

And. He’sat’s Book 5 peace, Coxcomb, thatfuchan unlearned
tongue as thine ftiould ask for him !

Co. Do’s he not ftudy conjuring too ?

And. Have you loft any Plate, Butler .<?

But. No, but I know I (hall to morrow at dinner.

Attd. Then to morrow you fhall be turn’d out of your place
for’t 5 we meddle with no (pirit o’th’ Buttry, they tafte too (mall
for us 5 keep me a Pie in Folio.^ I befceeh thee, and thou (halt fee
how learnedly I’ll tranflate him, . Shal’s h^ve good cheer to
morrow ?

Co. Exc’llent good cheer, Andrew:

And. The fpight on’t is, that much about that time, I (hall be
arguing, or deciding rather, which are the Males or Females of
Red Herrings, and whether they be taken in the Red-Sea bnely 5
a queftion found out by the learned Motion-maker.

Co. I marry, Butler^ here are rare things 5 a man that look’d up¬
on him, would (wear he underftood no morethan we do.

But. Certain, a learned Andrew.

And. I’ve fo much on’t, and am (b loaden with ftrong under-
finding,! fear, they’ll run me mad. Here’s a new Inftrument, a
Mathematical Glifter to purge the M6on with, v^henfhe is laden
with cold phlegmatick humors 5 and here’s another to remove
the Stars, when they grow too thick in the Firmament.

Co. O Heavens! why do I labour out my life in a Beef-pot ?
and onely fearch thefecietRofa Sallad, and know no farther?

And. They are not reVeal’d to all heads 5 thefe are far abovo
your Element of Fire, Cook. I could tell you of Archimedes Glafi,
to fire your Coals with 5 and of the Philofophers Turf^ that ne’er

D goes







mm


,8 THE.ELDEK BR othe r.

goes out: and, G//^er^ r could*ra\^ill thee with two rare

inventions. . ...

B//L What are they, Amlrevp ? ■

And. The one to blanch your Bread from chippings ba(e, and^
in. a moment, as thou wouldft an Almond 5 theSeft of the Epi¬
cureans invented that: The other for thy Trenchers, that’s a
ftrongone, to cleanfe you twenty dozen in a minute, and no
noife heard, which is the vvonder, Gilbert ^ and this was out of
Plato's new Ideas.

But, Why, what a learned Mafterdo'ft thou ferve, Andrew ^

JW.Thefcare butthefcrapings of his underftanding, Gilbert
with gods and goddeffes, andfuch ftrange people he deals, and^
treats with in fo plain a fafhion, as thou do’ft with thy Boy that
draws thy drink, or Ralph there, with his Ritchin-Boys and
Scalders.

C{?. But why fhould he notbefamiliar, and talk fometimes, as
other Chriftians do, of hearty matters, and come into theKitchin,
and there cut his Breakfaft?

And then retire to the Biitt’ry,and there eat it, and drink
a lufty Bowl to my young Mafter, that muft be now the Heir,
he'll do all thefe, I and be drunk too ^ thefe are mortal things.

And. My Mafter ftudies immortality.

Co. Now thou talk’d: of immortality, how do*s thy Wife, An-
drew^ my old Mafter did you no fmall pleafure when he pro¬
cur’d her, and (lock’d you in a Farm. If helhouldlovehcrnow,
as he hath a Colts tooth yet, what (ays your Learning, and. your
ftrangelnftrumentsto that,my Andrew Can any of your learned
Clerks avoid it ^ can ye put by his .Mathematical Engine >

And. Yes, or I’ll break it: /thou awaken’d me, and Ill peep
i’th* Moon this month but Ill watchTor him. My Mafter rings, I
muft go make him a fire, and,conjure o’er his Books.

Co. Adieu, good Andrew^ and fend thee manly patience with
thy learning. , [Exeynt^

ACTUS II. SCiENAlV. .

Charles.

I have forgot to eat and fleep with reading, and all my faculties

turn









THE ELDER BROTHER. 19

turn into ftudy 5 *tis meat and fleep 5 what need I outward
garments, when I can cloath my felf with underftanding .<? The
Stars and glorious Planets have no Tailors, yet ever new they
are, and fhine like Courtiers. The Seafbns of the year find no
fond Parents, yet fome are arm'd in filver Ice that glifters, and
fome in gawdy Green come in like Mafquers. The Silk-worm
(pins her own fuit and lodging, and has no aid nor partner in her
labours. Why(houldwe care for any thing but knowledge, or
look upon the World but to contemn it ?

E^ter Andrew.

Afid, Would you have any thing ?

' Char, I find there is a Hie grown o'er the Eye o’ th*

Bnll^ which will go near to blind the Conftellation.

A?td^ Put a Gold-ring in’s nofe, and that will cure him.

Ch^r, Ariadne s Crown’s away too 5 two main Stars that held
it faft are flipt out

And Send it piefently to Gallatteo^ the Italian Star-wright,
he’l 1 f t it I ight again with little labour.

Char. Thou art a pretty Scholar. '

And. I hope I (liali be 5 have I fwept Books fo often to know
nothing ? ,

Char. 1 hear thou art married.

And. It hath pleas’d your Father to match me to a Maid of his
own chufing^ I doubt her Conftellation’s loofetoo, and wants
nailing, and a fweet Farni he has given us a mile off, Sir.

Char. Marry thy felf to underftanding, Andrew 3 thefe Wo¬
men are Errata in all Authors, they’re fair to fee to, and bound
up in Vellam, (mooth, white and clear, but their contents are
monftrous^ they treat of nothing but dull age and difeafes.
Thou haft not (b much wit in thy head, as there is on thofe
(helves, Andrew.

And. I think I have not, Sir.

Char. No, if thou had’ft, thou’ld’ft ne’er married a Woman in
thy bofome, thy’re Cataplafms made o’th’ deadly fins: I ne’er
(aw any yet but mine own Mother or if I did, I did regard them
but as (hadows thatpafs by of under creatures.

D 2 And.








ao the elder brother.

Af;d, Shall I bring you one? I’ll truft you wichmy own Wife^
I would not have your Brother go beyond ye 3 th are the pi*ct-
tieft Natural Philofophersto play with.

Char, No, no, th’are Opticks to delude mens eyes with. Does
my younger Brother fpeak any Greek yet, Aridrerv ^

"And, No, but he fpeaks High Dutch, and that goes daintily.

Char, Reach me the Books down I read yefterday, and make
a little fire, and get a manchet 3 make clean thofe Inftruments of
Brafi Ifhew’dyou, and fet the great Sphere by 3 then take the
Fox tail, and purge the Books from duft3 laft, take yom Liliy^
and get your part ready.

And, Shall I go home, Sir ? my Wife’s name is Lilly^ there my
befl: part lies, Sir.

Char, I mean your Grammar, O thou Dunderhead! would’ft
thou be ever in thy Wife’s Syntaxes ? Let me have no noife, nor
nothing todifturb me 3 lam to find a fecret.

And, So am I too 3 which if I find, I (hall make fome fmart
fort——— Exeunt.


JBus III. Scana I.

Angellina^ Sylvia,^ Notary. -

T His is the day, my Daughter Angellina the happy, thatmuft
make you a Fortune, a large and full one, my care has
wrought it, and yours muft be as great to entertain it. Young
Eujiace is a Gentleman at all points, and his behaviour affable
and courtly, his perlbn excellent 3 I know you find that, I read
it in your eyes, you like his youth 3 young handfbme people
(hould be match’d together, then follows handfoiiie Children,
handfbme fortunes 3 the mofi: part of his Father s Eftate, my
Wench, is ti’d in a Jointure, that makes up the harmony 3 and
when ye are married, he’s of that foft temper, and fo far will be
chain’d to your obfervance, that you may rule and turn him as
you pleafe. What, are the Writings drawn on your fide, Sir?

Not. They are, and here I have fo fetter’d him, that if the

Elder





THE ELDER BROTHER. 21

Elder Brother fet his hand to, not all the power of Law fhall e er
releafe him.

Leir.Thefe Notaries are notable confident Knaves, and able'
to do more mifehief than Army. Arc all your Claufes fare }

NoL Sure as proportion 5 they may turn Rivers (boner than
thefe Writings.

Lew. Why did you not put all the Lands in. Sir ?

iVi?/.'Twasnot condition’d ^ ifit had been found, it had been
but a fault made in the Writings, if not found, all the Land.

Lew. Thefe are fmall Devils, that care not who has mifehief^
(b they make it 5 they live upon the meer (cent of diflention.
’Tis well, Ws well 5 are you contented, Girl ? for your will
muft be known.

Jffg, A Husband’s welcome, and as an humble Wife I’ll enter¬
tain him 5 no Sovereignty I aim at, ’^tis the man’s. Sir 5 for (he
that (eeks it, kills her Husbands Honqur: The Gentleman I have
feen, and well obferv’d him, yet find not that grac’d excellence
youpromi(e5 a pretty Gentleman, and he may pleafetoo, and
fome few flafhes I have heard come from him, but not to admi¬
ration as to others: He’s young, and may be good, yet he muft
make it, and I may help, and help to thank him al(o. It is your
plcafare I (hould make him mine, and’t has been ftill my duty
to ob(erve you.

Lew Why then let’s go, and I (hall love your modefty. To
Hor(e, and bring the Coach out, AtJgellim 5 to morrow you will
look more womanly.

Ang, So I look honeftly, I fear no eyes. Sir. [ExeurtU

ACTUS III. SCiENA IL
Brifac^ Andrew^ Cool^^ Lilly.

Wait on your Matter, he (hall have that befits him.

And. No Inheritance, Sir ?

J 5 r/. You (peak like a fool, a coxcombs he (liall have am
nual means to buy him Books, and find him cloathes and meat,
what would he more? Trouble him with Land, ’tis flat againft
his nature. I love him too, and honour thofe gifts in him.

And. Shall Matter Enlace have all ?

Brh










22 THE ELDE R .BKO’THER. ' |

Bri. All, all he knows how to ufe it, he’s a man bred in the
world, th other ikh’Heavens. My Mafters, pray be wary, and
fcrviceable 5 mdi Cook.^ fee all your Sawces be (harp and poynant
in the pallat,that they may commend you 5 look to your Roaft
and Bak’d meats handfomely, and what newKicklhaws and de¬
licate made things— — Is th’Mufick come?

But, Yes, Sir, th’are here at Breakfaft^

Bri. There wil|be a Mafrjuctoo, you muft fee this Room
clean, and, Bntler^ your door open to all good-fellows, but
have an eye to your Plate, for there be Furies 5 my li//^, wel¬
come you are for the Linen, fort it, and fee it ready for the Ta¬
ble, and fee the B kic-bed made, and look the cords be not cut
aflunder by the Gallanu too, therebe fach knacksabroad. Hark
hither, Li^, to morrow night at twelve a clock FlI fap w’ye,
yourHusband fliall be (afe. I’ll fend ye meat too 3 before I can¬
not well flip from my company. > J

A^d, Will ye ft), will you fo, Sir ? Ill make one to eat it, I may ■

chance make you flagger too. • , -

Bri. No anfwer, Lil/jf ^

LiL One word about the Linens I’ll be ready, and reft your .
Worfhips flill.

And, And I’ll refl w’ye, you (hall fee what reft ’twill be. Are j
ye fb nimble? a man had need have ten pair of ears to watch you.

Bri, Wait on your Mafler, for I know he wants ye, and keep
him in his Study, that the noife do not molefl him. I will not

fail my Lilly --—■ Come in,fweet-hearts, all to their feveral ^

duties. . [Exeunt.

And. Are you killing ripe, Sir? Double but my Farm, and
kifi her till thy heart ake. Theft Smock-vermine, how eagerly ^
they leap at old menskifles, they lick their lips at profit, not at
pleafure 3 and if’t were not for the feurvy name of Cuckold,
he fhould lie with her. I know (hell labour at length with a
good Lordlhip. If he had a Wife now, but that’s all one, III fit
him. I muft up unto my Matter, hell be mad with Study— [Exit.


ACTUS








THE ELDER BROTHER. 2/

ACTUS Iir. SCiENA III.

Charles, _

What a noifeis in this houfe ? my head is broken, within a Pa-
renthefis, in every coi ner, as if the earth were (haken withibme
ftrange Colleft, there are ftirs and motions. What Planet rules
this houfe?

Enter Andrew.

Who*s there ? , '

And. '"Tis I, Sir, faithful Andrevp,

Char. Come near, and lay thine ear down ^ hear ft no noife ?

And, The Cooks are chopping herbs and nunce-meat to make
Pies, and breaking Marrow-boqes—

Char. Can they fet them again ?

And. Yes, yes, in Broths and Puddings, and they grow ftronger
for the ufe of any man.

Char. What (peaking s that ? fure there s a Maflacre.

And, Of Pigs and Geefe, Sir, andTurkeys, for the (pk. The
Cooks are angry Sirs, and that makes up the medley.

Char. Do they thus at every Dinner? I neer marked them yet,,
nor know who is a Cook.

And. Th’arefometimes fober, and then they beat as gently as a
Tabor.

Char. What loads are the(e > - .

Meat, meat, Sir, for the Kitchen, and (linking Fouls the
Tenants have fent in ^ theyllne’r be found out a a general eat¬
ing 5 and there’s fat VeniCbn, Sir..

Char, What’s that ?

And. Why Deer, thole that men fatten for their private plea-
fores, and let their Tenants ftarve upon the Commons.

I’ve read of Deer, but yet I ne’er eat any any.

And. There’s a Fifhraongers Boy with Caviar, Sir, Anchoves,
and Potargo, to make ye drink.

Char.^xxxt thefeare modern, very modern meats, forlunder-
ftand’emnot..































24 the elder brother.

No more does any man from Caca merda, or a (ubdancc
worfe, till they be greas'd with Oyl, and rubb’d with Onions^
and then fling out of doors, they arerareSallads.

CAar. And why is all this, prethee tell me, Andrew} are there
any Princes to dine here to day ? by this abundance fare there
ftiouldbe Princes 5 IVeread of entertainment for the gods at
half this charge ^ will not fix Difties fcrve'em? I never had but
one, and that a fmall one.

' A^d.Yonx Brothers marrfd this day5 he*s marrfd, your
younger Brother

Char What of that ?

And. AnddW the Friends about are bidden hither 5 there's not
a Dog that knows the houfe, but comes too.

Char. Marri'd! to whom }

And. Why to a dainty Centlewomarh, young, (weet, and
modeft.

Char. Are there modeft women ? how do they look ?

And. O yoxxW blefi your felf to fee them. He parts with's
Book, he ne'er did fo before yet.

. Char. What does my Father for'em ?

‘ And. Gives all his Land, and makes your Brother Heir.

Char, Muft I have nothing ?

And. Yes, you muft ft tidy ftill, and he'll m.aintain you.

Char. I am his eldeft Brother.

And. True, you were(05 but he has leap’d o’er yoUr (houl-
ders,Sir.

CW.’Tiswell5 he’llnot inherit my underftanding too ?

And. I think not 3 he'll fcarce find Tenants to let it out to.

Char. Hark! hark!

And. The Coach that brings the fair Lady.

Enter Lewis, Angellina, Ladies^ Notary^

And. Now you may fe^her.

Char. Sure this flaould bemodeft, but I do not truly know what
women makeof it.^Wreir ^ (he has a face looks like a ftory, the
ftory of the Heavens looks very like her.

And^ She has a v^ide face then.


Char,









THE ELDER BROTHER. 25

She has a Cherubins, cover’d and vail’d with modefl:

blufties. Eujlace^ be happy, whiles poor Charles \s patient. Get me

my Books again, and come in with me ——..i- [Exeunt»

%

Brifac, Euftace, Egremont, Cowcy, IVIiramont^

Er/. Welcome, (weet Daughter^ welcome, noble Brother^ and
you are welcome. Sir, with all your Writings ^ Ladies, moft wel¬
come : What, my angry Brother! you muft be welcome too, the
Feaft is flatelfe.

Mir. I am not come for your welcome, I expeft none ^ I bring
no joys to blefi the Bed withall 5 nor Songs, nor Mafques to
glorifie the Nuptials 5 I bring an angry mind to fee your folly, a
lharponetoo,to reprehend you for it,

Bri. You’ll ftay and dine though.

Mir. All your meat fmells mufty, your Table will fhew no^
thing to content me.

Bri. I’ll anfwer you, here’s good meat.

Mir. But your fauce is fcurvie, it is not feafon’d with the Iharp-
nefi of difcretion.

Eufi. It feems your anger is at me, dear Uncle.

Mir. Thou art not worth my anger, th’art a Boy, a lump o’thy
Father’s lightnefs, made of nothing but antick cloathes ana
cringes 5 look in thy head, and ’twill appear a foot-ball full of
fumes and rotten fmoke. Lady,I pity you^ you are a handfome
and a fweet young Lady, and ought to have a handfom man
yok’d t’ye, an underftanding too 3 this is a Gimcrack, that can
get nothing but new fafhions on you 3 for fey he have a thing
ihap’dlike a child, ’twill either prove a Tumbler ora Tailor.

£///?, Thefe are but harfti words. Uncle.

Mir. So I mean’em. Sir, you play harfher play w’your elder
Brother.

I would be loath to give you.

Mir. Do not venture, I’ll make youi^edding deaths fit clofer
t’yee then 3 I but difturb you. I’ll go fee my Nephew.

Leap. Pray take a piece of Rofemary.

Mir. I’ll wear it, but for the Ladies feke, and none of yours 5
may be I’ll fee your Table too;

E Brr\


E






























26 THE ELDER BROTHER.

Bri, Pray do, Sir.

Ang. A mad old Gentleman.

Bri. Yes faith, fweet Daughter, he has been thus his whole
age,, to my knowledge 5 he has mzdt Charles his Heir, I know
that certainly 5 then why (hould he grudge Enjiace any thing ? -

Artg. I would not have a light head, nor one laden with too
much learning, as, they (ay, this Charles is, that makes his Book
his Miftris: Sure there's fomething hid in this old man’s anger,
that declares him not a meer for.

Bri. Come, (hall we go and (eal, Brother all things are ready,
and the Priefl: is here. When Charles has (et his hand unto the
Writings, as he (hall inftantly, then to the Wedding, andfo to
dinner.

Lerv. Come, let’s feal the Book firft for my Daughters Jointure.

Bri, Let’s be private in’t. Sir. [Exe^wt.

>

ACTUS III. SCiENA IV.

Enter Charles, Miramont, Andrew.

Mir. Nay, y are undone.

Char. Hum.

Mir. Ha’ye no greater feeling ?

And. You were (enfible of the great Book, Sir, when it fell on
your head, and now the houfe is ready to fall. Do you fear
nothing?

Char. Will he have my Books too ?

Mir. No, he has a Book, a fair one too, to read on, and read
^wonders 5 I would thou hadft her in thy Study, Nephew, and
twere but to new ftring her,

Char.Yts^ I law her, and me thought kwas a curious piece of
Learning, handlomely bound, and ofa dainty Letter.

And. He flung away his Book.

Mir. I like that in him 5 would he had flung away his dulne(s
too, and fpaketo her.

Char And muft my Brother have all ?

Mtr. All that your Father has
And that fair woman too ?

Mjr. That womanal(b.


Chan








THE ELDER bKOTHEK. 37

Viar. He has enough then. May I not fee her fometimes, and
call her Sifter ? I will do him no wrong.

M/r. This makes me mad, I could now cry for anger: thefe
old Fools are the moft ftubborn and the wilfulleft Coxcombs 3
Farewell) and fall to your Book, forget your Brother: you are
my Heir, and I’ll provide y a Wife: I’ll look upon this marriage,
though I hate it. £Ex/f.

EtiUr Bril&c»

Where is my Son ? ,

There, Sir, calling a Figure what chopping children his
Brother fhall have.

BrL He does well. How do’ft, Charles ftill at thy Book ?

And. He*s ftudying now, Sir, who fhall be his Father.

Bri. Peace, you rude Knave - Come hither, Charles^ be

merry.

Char, I thank you, I am bufie at my Book, Sir.

Bri. You muft put your hand, my Charles^ as I would have yoii,
unto a little piece of Parchment here ; onely your name 3 you
write a reafbnable hand.

Char. But I may do unreafonably to write it. What is it. Sir ?
Bri.To pafsthe Land I have, Sir, unto your younger Brothete
Char. Is’t no more ? ,

Bri. No, no, ’tis nothing 3 you (hall be provided for, and new
Books you fhall have ftill, and new Studies, and have your means
brought in without thy care. Boy, and one ftill to attend you.
Char, This (hews your love, Father.

Bri. Fm tender to you.

And, Like a (lone, I take it.

Char. WhyFather,rilgo down, an’t pleafeyou let me,becaufe
rd fee the thing they call the Gentlewoman 3 I fee no woman but
through contemplation, and there I’ll do’t before the company,
and wifh my Brother fortune.

Bri. Do, I prethee.

Char. I mu(l not ftay,fbr I have things above require my ftudy.
Bri. No, thou (halt not (lay 3 thou (halt have a brave dinner
too.

E 2 Andt






















28 THE ELDER BROTHER.

And. Now has he overthrown himfelf for ever 3 I will down
into the Cellar, and beftark drnnk for anger, [Exeimt^

ACTUS III. SC^NA V.

Enter Lewis, Angellina, Enftace,Pr/e/?, Ladies^Covfcy^

Notarj/j Miramont.

*

Not. Come, let him bring his Sons hand,and alls done. Is
youf s ready ?

Pr Yes, Ill dilpatch ye prefently, immediately, for in truth I
am a hungry.

Euji. Do, (peak apace, for we believe exaftly: do not we ftay
long, Miftris?

Ang. I find no fault, better things well done, than want time
to do them. Uncle, why are you lad ?

Mjr Sweet fmelling bloflom, would I were thine Uncle to
thine own content, Td make thy Husband's ftate a thouland
better, a yearly thoufind. Thou haftmift a man, ( but that he is
addifted to his ftudy, and knows no other Miftris than his mind)
would weigh down bundles of thefe empty kexes,

Ang. Can he Ipeak, Sir >

Mir, Faith yes, but not to women ^ his language is to Heaven,,

- and heavenly wonder 5 to Nature, and her dark andfecretcaufes.
And does he fpeak well there?

Mir, O admirably 5 but he's too bafhful to behold a woman,
there's none that fees him, and he troubles none.

Ang. Heis a man.

Mir. Faith yes, and a clear fweet fpirit.

Ang. Then converfation me-thinks-

Mir. So think 1 5 but it is his rugged Fate, and fo I leave you.

' Ang. I like thy noblenels.

EuJi. See ray mad Uncle is courting my fair Miftrefe.

Lew. Let him alone ^ there's nothing that allays an angry
mind foibon as a fweet Beauty : hell come to us.

Eater Briiac, Charles.

My "Father’s here, my Brother too I that’s a wonder,
broke like a Spirit from his Cell. Bri.










THE ELDER BROTHER. 29

jBr/. Come hither, come nearer, 5 ’twas your defire to

fee my noble Daughter, and the company^ and give your Bro¬
ther joy, and then to Seal, Boy, you do like a good Brother.

Lerv. Marry does he, and he ihall have my love for ever for’t.
Put to your hand now.

Not. Here’s the Deed, Sir, ready.

CW.No, you muft pardon me a while, I tell ye, I am in con¬
templation, do not trouble me.

Bri. Come, leave thy Study, Charles:

Char.V\S, leave my lifefirft, I ftudy now to be a man. I’ve
found it. Before what Man was, was but my Argument.

Mir. IliketWsbeft of all, he has taken fire, his dull mift flies
away.

Enjl. Will you write, Brother >

Char. No, Brother, no, I have no time for poor things, Vmt
taking the height of that bright Conflellation.

Bri. I fay you trifle time. Son.

Char. Iwillnot feal. Sir 5 1 am your Eldeft, and Fll keep my
Birth-right, for Heaven forbid I ftiould become example: Had
yonely fhew’d me Land, I had dtfiver’d it, and been a proud
man to have parted with it y*tis dirt, and labour. Do. I fpeak.
right, Uncle? .

Mir. Bravely, my Boy, and blefi thy tongue.

Char, ril forward; but you haveopen d tome fuch a treafiirej
I find my mind free 5 Heaven direft my fortune.

Mir. Can he (peak now ? Is this a Son to facrifice ?

Char. Such an inimitable piece of Beauty, that I have ftudied
long, and now found onely, that Ill part fboner with my foul
of Reafon, and be a Plant, a Beaft, a Fifh,,a Flie, and onely make
the number of things up, than yield to one foot of Land, if (he
be ti’d to’t.

’Levp. He (peaks unhappily.

Ang. And methinks bravely. This the meer Scholar ?

You but vex your felf, Brother, and vex your Study too^

Char, Go you and Study, for ’tis time, young Bujlace-, you
want both man and manners^ rveftudy’d both, althoughIma.de
no (hew ont. Co turn the Volumes over I have read, eat and
digeft them,that they may grow in thee; wear out the tedious

night
























T


5 ^


THE ELDER BROTHEK.


flight with thy dim Lamp, and fooner lofe the day, than leave a
^ doubt. Diftill the fweetnefi from the Poets Spring, and learn to
love 5 thou know’ll: not what fair is: Traverfe the ftories of the
great Heroes, the wife anddvil lives of good men walk through 5
thou haft ften nothing but the face of Countreys, and brought
home nothing but their empty words: why ftiouldft thou wear
a Jewel of this worth, that haft no worth within thee to pre-
ierveher.>


Beautji cJe^ and faif^
where the air


Rather like a perfume dwells^
Where the Violet and the Roje
The blue Veins in blufi difclofe^
And come to honour nothing elfe.


Where to live near^

And planted there^

Is to live^ and Jiill live new ^
Where to gain a favour is
More than lights perpetual blifs^
Make me live by ferving yon.


Dear again bach^ recall
To this lights

A /Iranger to himfelf and all 5
Both the wonder and the fiory
Shall be yours^ and ek§ the glory 5
I am your fervant and your thrall.


Mir Speak fuch another Ode, and take all yet. What fay ye
to the Scholar now ?

Ang, I wonder ^ is he your Brother, Sir ?

Yes, would he were buried 5 I fear hell make an Afs of
me a younger. v , .

Ang Speak not fo foftly. Sir, ’tis very likely.

Bri, Come, leave your finical talk, and let’s difpatch,

Char, Dilpatch, what ?


I

j


Bri.






gi


THE ELDER BROTHER.

Bri. Why the Land.

Ciiar. You ait deceived. Sir. Now I perceive what ’tis that
woes a woman, and whift maintains her when fties woo'd : I'll
ftophere. A wilful poverty ne'er madea Beauty, nor want of
means maintain’d it virtuoufly: Though land and moneys be
no happinefs, yet they are counted good additions. That ufe
rilmake^ hethat negledis a bleffing, though he want a prefent '
knowledge howto ufe it, neglefts himfelf . May be 1 have done
you wrong, Lady, whofe love and hope went hand in hand to-
gether 3 may be my Brother, that has long expefted the happy
hour, and blefs’d my ignorance ^ pray give me leave. Sir, I (hall
clear all doubts 3 Why did they (hew me you ? pray tell me
that ?

(M/r. He’ll talk thee into a penfion for thy knavery.)

Char. You, happy you, why did you break unto me ? The
Rofie fugred morn ne’er broke (b fweetly: I am a man, and .
have defires within me, affeftions too, though they were drown'd
a while, and lay dead, till the Spring of Beauty rais'd them 5
till I law thofe eyes, I was but a lump, a chaos of confufednefe
dwelt in me 5 then from thofe eyes (hot Love, and he diftin-
guifli'd, and into form he drew my faculties 5 and now I know
my Land, and now I love too.

Bri. We had beft remove the Maid.

Char, It is too late. Sir. I have her figure here. Nay frown not,
Bufiace^ there are left worthy Soulsfor younger Brothers ^ this
is no form of Silk, but Sandity, which wild lafcivious hearts can
never dignifie. Remove her where you will, I walk alongftilJ^
for, like the light, we make no feparation 5 you may fooner part
the Billows of the Sea, and put a barr betwixt their fellowfliips,
than blot out my remembrance 5 fooner (hut old Time into a
Den, and ftay his motion, wa(h off the fwift hours from his
downy wings, or fteal Eternity to flop his glafs, than fhut the
fweet Idea I have in me. Room for an elder Brother, pray give
place, Sir.

Mir. H'as ftudied duel too ^ take heed, he'll beat thee. H'as
frighted the old Juftice into aFeaver^ I hope he'll difinherit

him too for an Afs 3 for though he be grave with years, he's a
great Baby. ^


Chati.






















52 the elder brother.

Do not you think me mad > ®

No certain. Sir, I have heard nothing from you but things
excellent;

You look upon my cloathes, and laugh at me, myfcurvjr
cloathes!

J/fg. They have rich linings, Sir. I would your Brother——

CAar* His are gold and gawdie.

A^g, But touch’em inwardly, they finell of Copper.

CAar. Can ye love me? I am an Heir, fweet Lady, however I
appear a poor dependent 5 love you with honour, I ftiall love fo
ever. Is your eye ambitious? I may be a great man, is’t wealth
or lands you covet ? my Father muft die.

Mir. That was well put in, I hope he*Il take it deeply.

CA^r. Old men are not immortal, as I take it 5 is it, you look
for, youth and handfomnefi ? I do confefs my Brother s a hand- j

fome Gentleman, but he (hall give me leave to lead the way, J

Lady. Can you love for love, and make that the reward ? The '

old man (hall not love his heaps of Gold with a more doting fu-
perftition, than Til love you. The young man his delights, the ^
Merchant, when he ploughs the angry Sea up, and fees the moun¬
tain-billows falling on him, as if all the Elements, and all their ^
angers, were turn’d into one vow’d deftrudtion 5 (hall not with
greater joy embrace hisfafety. Well live together like two wan¬
ton Vines, circling our fouls and loves in one another, well
fpring together, and we’ll bear one fruit 5 one joy (hall make us |

fmile, and one grief mourn 5 one age go with us, and one hour j

of death (hall (hut our eyes, and one grave make us happy.

A//g. And one hand foal the Match, I’m yours for ever.

Lew. Nay, ftay, ftay, ftay.

A^g. Nay certainly, ’tis done. Sir.

Bri. There wa s a contrad.

-^v^.Onely conditional, that if he had the Land, he had my
love too 5 this Gentleman’s the Heir, and he’ll maintain it. Pray
be not angry. Sir, at what I fay 5 or if you be, ’tis at your own
adventure. You have the out-fide of a pretty Gentleman, but
by my troth your infide is but barren 5 ’tis not a face lonely am
in love with, nor will I fay your face is excellent, a reafonable
hunting face to court the wind with 5 nor th’are not words,

unlefs






THE ELDER BROTHER. 55

Tirilefi they be well plac’d too, nor your fweet Dam*rnes, no^
your hired Verfrs, nor telling me of Clothes, nor Coach an<i
Horfes, no nor your vifits each day in new Suits, nor your black
Patches you wear varioufly, fome cut like Stars, fome in Half-
moons, fome Lozenges, ( all which but (hew you ftill a younger
Brother. )

M/>. Gramercy, Wench, thou haft a noble Soul too.

j 4 //g. Nor your long travels, nor your little knowledge, can
make me doat upon you. Faith goftudy, and glean fome good-
nefi, that you may (hew manly 5 your Brother at my fuit Fm (ure
will teach you^ or onel'y ftudy how to get a Wife, Sir. Y’are
caft far behind, ’tis good you fhould be melancholly, it fhews
likea Gamefter that had loft his money 5 andkis the faChion to
wear your arm inaskarf. Sir, for you have had a ftirewd cut o’er
the fingers.

Lew. But are y’in earneft ?

Yes, believe me, Father, you (hall ne’er choofe for me 5
y are old and dim, Sir, and th’fhaddowof the earth eclips’d your
judgment. Y’havehad your time without control, dear Father,
and you muft give me leave to take mine now, Sir.

Bri. This is the laft time of asking. Will you (et your hand to ?

Char. This is the laft time of anfwering, I will never.

Bri. Out of my doors.

Char. Moft willingly.

Mir. He (hall, Jew, thou of the Tribe Man-y-ajfes^ Coxcomb,

and never trouble thee more till thy chops be cold, fool.

Arjg. Mufti be gone too?

Lew. I will never know thee.

Ang. Then this man will 5 what Fortune he fhall run. Father,
be’t good or bad, I muft partake it with him.

Enter Egremont.

When (hall the Malque begin ?

Euji. ’Tis done already 3 all, all is broken off, I am undone,
Friend, my Brother’s wife again, and has (poil’d all, will not re-
leafethe Land, has won the Wench too.

Egre. Could henotftay till the Mafque waspaft.<? ware ready.

F What
























elder brother.

What a skirvy trick's this?

Mz>. O you may vanifh, perform it at fome Hall, where the
Citizens Wives may fee’t for Six-pence a piece, and a cold Sup¬
per; Come, let’s go, Charles. And now, my noble Daughter, Til
fell the Tiles of myHoufe, ere thou (halt want. Wench. Rate
up your dinner. Sir, and fell it, cheap 5 fome younger Brother
will take t up in Commodities. Send you joy, Nephew Eujiace y
if youftudy theLaw, keep your great Pippin-pies, they 11 go
far with ye.

Char, fd have your blefCng.

jBr/.No, no, meet me no more. Farewel, thou wilt blaft mine
eyeselfe. .

Char. I will not.

Levp. Nor fend not you for Gowns.

Ang. Ill wear courfe Flannel firft.

Bri. Come, let s go take fome counfel.

Bew. 'Tistoo late.

Brl. Then ftay and dine 3 it may be we (hall vex em.

[Exeunk.


JHus IV, Sc ana L.

Enter Brifac, Euftace, Egremont, Cowfy.

^^"jEfer talk to me, you are no men but Malquers 5 fliapes,
ftiadows, and the figns of men, Court bubbles, that every
breath or breaks or blows away. You have no fouls, no metall
in your bloods, no heat to ftir ye when ye have occafion : fro¬
zen dull things, that muft be turn'd with Leavers. Are you the
Courtiers,and the travelfd Gallants ? the fpritely Fellows that the
people talk of. Ye have no more fpirit than three Oeepy fopes.

Eufi. What would ye have me do, Sir?

Bri. Follow your Brother, and get ye out of doors, and feek
your Fortune. Stand ftill becalm'd, and let an aged Dotard, a
hair-brain’d Puppy, and a Bookitli Boy, that never knew a Blade
above a Pen-knife, and how to cut his meat in Char afters, crofe

my




THE ELDER BROTHER. 35

tny dcfign, and take thine own Wench from thee, in mine own
houfe too ? Thou defpis d poor fellow!

Efdh The reverence that I ever bare to you, Sir, then to my
Uncle, with whom T had been but fawcinefs t’ have been fo
rough-—

Egre. And we not feeing him drive in his own caufe, that was
principal, and (hould have led us on, thought it ill manner^ to
begin a quarrel here.

Bru You dare do nothing. Do you make your care, the ex:-
cufe of your cowardlinefi ^ Three Boys on Hobby-horfes, with
three penny Halberds, would beat you all.

Cow, You muft not lay lb,

Bri, Yes, and ling it too.

Cow, You are a man of peace, therefore we muft give way.

Bri. ril make my way, and therefore quickly leave me, or III
force you 5 and having firft torn off your flanting feathers. Hi
trample on em 5 and if that cannot teach you to quit my houle.
Ill kick ye out of my gates 5 you .gawdy Glow-worms, carry¬
ing feeming fire, yet have no heat within ye.

Obleft travel! how much we owe thee for our power
tofuffer?

Egre, fome Iplenative Youths now, that had never feen more
than thy Country fmoak, will grow in cholera it would ftiew
fine in us.

Euji. Yes marry would it, that are prime Courtiers, and muft
know no angers, but give thanks for our injuries, if wepurpofe
to hold our places.

Bri. Will you find the door i? and find it fuddenly 5 you ftiall
lead the way, Sir, with your perfum’d retinue, and cover the
now loft Af?geUina^ or build on it ^ I will adopt fome beggar’s
doubtful iffue, before thou ftial inherit.

Euji, Well to counfe], and what may be done by man’s wit or
valour, well put in execution.

Bri. Do, or never hope I (hall know thee. • {Exeunt,

Bitter Lewis.

hew^ O Sir, have I found you

F 2 Bri,















36; THE ELDER BROTHER.

BrL I never hid my (elf^ whence flows this fury, with which^
as it a ppears, you come ta fright me ?

Lem, I Imell a plot, meer eonfpiracy among ye all to defeat me
of my Daughter 5 and ifftie be not fuddenly deliver’d, untainted
in her reputation too^ the beft of France (hall know how I am
jugled with. She is my Heir, and if (he may be ravifh’d thus
from my care, farewell Nobility , Honour and Blood ai*e meer
negleded nothings.

Bri. Nay then, my Lord, you go too far, and tax him,-'^o(e
innocency undeiftands not what fear is. If your unconftant
Daughter will not d well on certainties, muft you thenceforth
conclude that I am fickle.what have! omitted, to make good
my integrity and truth ? nor can her lightnefs, nor your liippo-
Con, caft an afperfion on me.

tew. I am wounded in faff, nor can words cure it: do not
trifle, but fpeedily, once more I do repeat it, reftore my Daugh¬
ter as I brought her hither, or you (hall hear from me in fuch a
kind, as you will blu(h to anfwer.

Bri. All the world, I think, confpires to vex me, yet I will
not torment my felf: (bme (prightful mirth muft banifli the rage
and' melancholly which hath almoft choak’d me^ t’a knowing
man ’tis Phyfick, and ’tis thought on 5 one merry hour I’ll have
in (pight of Fortune,to chear my heart,and this is that appointed 5
this night Til hug my Lilly in mine arms, provocatives are fent
before to chear me, we old men need ’em, and though we pay
dear for our ftoln pleafures, (bit be done fecurely, the charge,
much like a (harp fouce, gives ’em relifli. Well, honeft Andrew:,
I gave you a Fai m, and it (hall have a Beacon, to give warning
tamy other Tenants when the Foe approaches 5 and prefently,
you being beftowed el(e-where, I’ll graft it with dexterity on
your forehead 5 indeed I Lilly,\ ccme,poor Andrew. [Exit.

ACTUS IV. SC^N A H.

Enter. Miramont, Andrew.

Do they chafer roundly .<?

And. As they were rubb’d with Soap, Sir, and now they fwear
aloud, now calm again j like a Ring of Bells, whofe found the

wind




THE ELDER BROTHER. 37

Wind ftill alters, and then they fit incouncel what to do, and
then they jar agaihwhat fhall be done 3 they talk of Warrants
from the Parliament, Complaints to the King, and Forces from
the Province Sv^hey have a thoufand heads in a thoufand mi-
nutes,.yet neepa one head worth a head of Carlick.

M/r, Long may , they chafe, and long m‘ay we laugh at ’em 3 a
couple of pure Puppies yok’d together. But what fays theyoiing:
Courtier Bujiace^ and his two warlike Friends ?

Affd. They (ay but little, how much they think I know not 5
they look ruefully, as if they had newly come from a vaulting-
houie, and had been quite (hot through ’tween wind and water
by a (lie Du^kirk^ and had (prunga Leakj^Sir. Certain my Maftcr
was to blame.

Mrr. Why, A/idrew

Ar^d. To take away the Wench oTh’fudden from him, and
give him no lawful warning 5 he is tender, and of a young Girls >
conftitution, Sir, ready to get the Green ficknefi with conceit;
Had he but tane his leave in travailing Language, or bought an
Elegy of his condolement, that the world might have tane notice,
he had been an Afs, ’t had been fome favour.

M/r, Thou (ay ’ft true, wife Andrew 3 but thefe Scholars are:
filch things, when they can prattle.

And. And very parlous things, Sir.

M/r. And when gain the liberty to diftinguifh the difference
’twixt a Father and a Fool, to look below, and (pie a younger
Brother pruning up, and drefling up hkexpedlations in a rare
gla(s of beauty, too good for him 5 thofedreaming Scholars then^
turn Tyrants, Andrew.^ and (hew no mercy.

And. The more’s the pity, Sir.

M/r. Thou told’ft me of a trick to catch my Brother, and an-*
ger hima little farther, Andrew. Itfliall be onely anger, V aOurCv
thee, and little (hame.

And. And I can fit you, Sir. Hark in your ear.

M/r. Thy Wife ?

And. So I affure ye 3 this night at twelve a clock. .

iW/r.’Tis neat andhand(bme3 there are twenty Crowns due*
to thy projeft, Andrew 3 I’ve time to vifit Charles^ and. fee. whatt

LeSur®.:




















the elder brother. j

Lefture he reads to his Miftris, That done. Til not fail to be
with you.

Nor Lto watch my Mafter— ^ {Exeunt,

ACTUS IV. SCiENA IIL
Angellina, Sylyia, a. Taper,

Fm worfe than e’er I was 5 for now I fear, that that I love, that
that I onely dote on 5 he follows me through every room I pals,
and with a ftrong fet eye he gazes on me, as if his fpark of inno¬
cence were blown into a flame ofluft. Virtue defend me. His
Uncle too isabfent, and ’tis nighty and what thefe opportuni¬
ties may teach him-— What fear and endlels care ’tis to be

honeft! to be a Maid what mifery, what mifehief! V/ould I
were rid of it, fo it were fairly. ;

SyLYon need not fear that, will you be a child ftill > He fol- I

lows you, but ftill to look upon you, or if he did defire to lie
with ye, ’tis but your own defire, you love for that end 3 I’ll
lay my life, if he were now a bed w ye, he is fo modeft, he would
fall afleep ftraight.

Ang, Dare you venture that ?

Sjil, Let him confent,and have at ye 5 I fear him not, he knows
not what a woman is, nor how to find the myftery men aim at.

Are you afraid of your own (hadow, Madam ?

Ang, He follows ftill, yet with a Ibber face^ would I might
Jinow the worft, and then I were fatisfied. :

SjL Ye may both, and let him but go with ye.

Char. Why do you flie me? what have I Co ill about me, or
within me, to deferve it ?

Aug. I am going to bed, Sir.

Char. And I am come to light ye 5 I am a Maid, and ’tis a
Maidens office.

Aug. You may have me to bed, Sir, without a fcruple, and yet
I am chary too who comes about me. Two Innocents fhould not
fear one another.

Syl. The Gentleman fays true. Pluck up your heart, Madam.

Char. The glorious Sun both rifing and declining we boldly
look upon 5 even then, fweet Lady, when, like a modeft Bride,

he






THE ELDER BROTHER crp

he draws nights curtains, even then he bluflies, that men fhould^
behold him»,

I fear he will perlwade me to miftake him.

SjL Tiseafily done, if you will give your mind to’t.

J//g. Pray ye to ' your bed,

CAar, Why not to yours, dear Miftris ? , one heart and one
bed.

True, Sir, when’tis lawful: but yet you know—^

Char. I would not know, forget it ^ thofe are but fickiy loves-
that hang on Ceremonies, nurs*d up with doubts and fears 5 ours
high and healthful, full of belief, and fit to teach the Prieftr.
Love (hall (eal firft, then hands confirm the bargain,

J^fg. I (hall be an Heretick if this continue. What would you-^:
do a bed ? you make me blufb, Sir.

Char, rd fee you fleep, for fure your fleeps are excellent, you-
that are waking (iich a noted wonder,muft in your (lumber prove
an admiration. I would behold your dreams too, if't were pof*-
fible 3 thole were rich (howes.

Ar;g, I am becoming Traitor.

Then likeblewMj?/;//;^ courting of an Ifland, where alP
the perfumes and the precious things that wait upon great Na¬
ture are laid up, rdclip it in my arms, and chaftly ki(s it, dwells
in your bofome like your deareft thoughts, and figh and weep.

Af 7 g, Tve too much woman inme.

Char. And thole true tears falling on your pure Ghryfl:a%.
(hould turn to Armelets for great Queens t*adorc.

Af 7 g, I muft be gone.

Char. Do hot, I will not hurt ye 3 this is to let you know, my
worthieft Lady, y’have clear’d my mind, and I can fpeak of love
too: Fear not my manners, though I never knew, before thefe
few hours, what a Beauty was, and fuch a one that fires all hearts-
that feel it 3 yet I have read of vertuous Temperance, andftu-
dy’d it among my other Secrets 3 and fooncr would I force a .
reparation betwixt this fpirit and the cafe of flefii, than but con-i
ceiveone rudene(s againft Ghaftity.

Ang. Then we may walk.

Char, And talk ofany thipg, any fit for your ears, and my Ian--
^guage 3 though I was bred up dull, I was ever civil 3 kistrue, P

hav©.















40 The elder brother.

have found it hard to look on you, and. not defire, kwill prove
a wife mans ta'sk 5 yet thole defires I have fo mingled ftili, and
tempered with the quality of honour, that if you Ihould yield,
I fhould hate you fork. lam noCourtierof a light condition,
apt to take fire at every beauteous face 5 that onely ferves his
will and wantonnefi, and lets the ferious part run by as thin ne-
glefted fand. Whitenefiof name, you muft be mine 5 why fhould
I rob my felf of that that lawfully muft make me happy? why
ftiould I ftek to cuckold my delights, and widow all thofe
fv/eets I aim at in you ? Well lofe our felves in Ferns Groves of
Myrtle, where every little Bird fhall be a Cnpid^ and fing of
love, and youth, each wind that blows, and curls the velvet-
leaves, (hall breed delights, the wanton Springs (hall call us to
their banks, and on the perfum'd flowers we'U feaft our (enfes 5
yet well walk by untainted of their pleafures, and as they were
pure Temples well talk in them,

Ang, To bed, and pray then, we may have a fair end of our
fair loves ^ would I were worthy of you,oroffuch parents that
might give you thanks: But I am poor in all but in your love.
Once more, good night.

A good night fye, and may the dew of fleep fall gent-
ly.on you,fweetone,and lock up thofe fair lights in pleafing num¬
bers^ no dreams but chafte and clear attempt your fancy, and
break betimes fweet morn, IVe loft my light elfe.

Afig. Let it be ever night when I lofe you.

Sj/L This Scholar never went to a Free-School, he sfb Ample,

Enter a Servant.

ServYom Brother, with two Gallants, is at door, Sir and
they're fo violent, they 11 take no denial.

Ang, This is no fit time of night.

Char. Let 'em in, Miftris.

Serv. They ftay no leave 5 fhall I raife the houfe on em ?

f^>6^r.^Nota man, nor make no murmur oft, I charge ye.


Enter



THE ELDER BROTHER.

Bnter EuftacejEgremontjCowfy.


41


The’are here, my Uncle abfent, ftand clofe tome* How do you.
Brother, with your curious ftory ? have you not read her yet
fufficiently ?

Char, No, Brother, no 5 I ftay yet in the Preface; the ftyle s
too hard for you,

Eujl, I muft entreat her 5 (he’s parcel of my goods.

Char, She’s all when you have her,

Ang. Hold off your hands, unmannerly, rude Sir 5 nor I, nor
what I have depend on you.

Char. Do, let her alone, fhe gives good counfel 5 do not trou¬
ble your felf with Ladies, they are too light: Let out your
Land,andget a provident Steward. '

Ang, I cannot love ye, let that fatisfie you 5 fuch vanities as
you, are to be laugh’d at.

Eufi. Nay, then you muft go ^ I muft claim mine own.

Bath, Away, away with her.

Char. Let her alone, pray let her alone, and
take your Coxcomb up : Let me talk civilly
a while with you. Brother. It may be on fome
terms I may part with her.

Euji. O, is your heart come down ? what are SSnatches away
your terms, Sir ? Put up, put up. ( his fword.

Char. This is the firft and chiefeft ^ let's walk a
turn. Now ftand off, fools, I advife ye, ftand as far off as you
would hope for mercy: this is the firft fword yet I ever handled,
and a fword’s a beauteous thing to look upon 5 and if it hold, I
fhall fo hunt your infblence: ’tis (harp. I’m fure, and if I put it
home,’tis ten to one I fhall new pink your Sattins 5 I find I have
fpirit enough to difpofe of it, and will enough to make ye all
examples 5 let me tofs it round, I have the full command on’^
Fetch me a native Fencer, I defie him 5 I feel the fire of ten ftrong
fpirits in me. Do you watch me when my Uncle is abfent ? this
is my grief, I (hall be flefti’d on Cowards 5 teach me to fight,
I willing am to learn. Are ye all gilded flies, nothing but (hew
in ye ? why ftand ye gaping ? who now touches her ? who

G calls


^She Jlrikes off
^Euftace’j* hat.


















42 THE ELDER BROTHER.

calls herhiSjOrwho dares name her to mes^but name her ashiv;
own5 who dares look on her? that (hall be mortal too5 but
think, kis dangerous. Art thou a fit man to inherit Land, and
haft no wit nor fpirit to maintain it? Stand ftill, thoufignof a
man, and pray for thy friends 5 pray heartily, good prayers may
reftore ye.

Affg. But do not kill ’em. Sir.

You fpeak too late. Dear 5 itismy firft fight, and I muft
do bravely, I muft not look with partial eyes on any ^ I cannot
Q>are a button of thefe Gentlemen, did life lie in their heel,
Achillas like. I’d fboot my anger at thole parts, and kill ’em. Who
waits within ?

Str. Sir.

Char. View all thefe, view ’em well, go round about "em, and
ftill view their faces ^ round about yet, fee bow death waits^
upon ’em, for thou (halt never view ’em more.

Pray hold. Sir.

CharA cannot hold, you ftand lb fair before me y I muft not
hold 5 ’twill darken all my glories. Co to my Uncle, bid hin^
poft to the Ring, and get my pardon inftantly, I have need on’u

Are you lb unnatural?

Ch^Y, You (liall die laft, Sir, I’ll take thee dead, thou art nomati
to fight with. Come, will ye come ? Me-thinks I’ve fought
whole Battels.

Cow, We have no quarrel to you that we know on, Sir.

Egre. We’ll quit the houfe, and ask ye mercy too. Good Lady;^,
let no murther be done here5 we came but to parly.

Char. How my fword thirfts after them? Stand away. Sweet.

Euit^ Ptay, Sir, take my fubmiffion, and I difclaim for ever.

Char. Away, ye poof things, ye de^icable creatures! do you.
come pofte to fetch a Lady from me ? from a poor School-boy
that ye feorn’d of late, and grow lame in your hearts when you
(hould execute? Pray take her, take her, I am weary of her :
What did you bring to carry her ?

Egre. A Coach and four Horfes.

Char. But are they good ?

Egre. As good as France can (hew Sir.

Char. Are you willingtokavethofe, and takeyour fafeties?

Speak


THE ELDER BROTHER, 4/

Speak quickly.

Enji. Yes with all our hearts.

Char. Tis done then. Many have got one Horfe, IVe got four
by th'bargain.

E^ter Miramont.

Mir. How now, who s here?

Ser. Nay, now y are gone without bail.

JVfir. What, drawn, my Friends .<? Fetch me my two-hand
Sword 0 I will not leave a head on your (houlders, Wretches,

Eujt. In troth, Sir, I came but to do my duty.

Both. And we to renew our loves.

Mir. Bring me a blanket. What came they for

A^g. To borrow me a while. Sir 3 but one that never fought
yet, has (b curri’d, fo baftinado’d them with manly carriage,
they ftand like things Gorgon had turn’d to ftone: they watch'd
your being abfent, and then thought they might do wonders
here, and they have done fo 5 for by my troth I wonder at their
coldnefi, the nipping North or Froft never came near them 5
St. George upon a Sign would grow more fenfible. If the name
of Honour were for ever to be loft, thefe were the moft fofEcient
men to do it in all the world 5 and yet they are but young, what
will they rife to? They’re as full of fire as a frozen Glow-worm s
Rattle, and ftiine as goodly: Nobility and patience are match’d
rarely in thefe three Gentlemen, they have right ufe orft5
they’ll ftand ftill for an hour and be beaten. Thefe are the Ana¬
grams of three great Worthies.

Mir. They will infeft my houfe with cowardize , if they
breathe longer in it 5 my roof covers no baffl’d Monfieurs, walk
and air your felves 5 as I live they ftay not here. White-liver’d
wretches, without one word to ask a reafon why. Vanifti, ’tis
the laft warning, and with (peed 5 for if I take ye in hand, I
(halldiffeift yon, and read upon your flegmatick dull carcafes.
My Horfe again t(p.ere: I have other bufinels, which you (hall
hear hereafter, and laugh at it. Good-night Charles^ fair good-
nefs to your dear Lady 3 ’tis late, ’tis late.

G 2 Ang.











44 the elder brother .

J//g. Pray, Sir, be careful of us.

Mir. It is enough, my beft care (hall attend ye. [* Exeunt.

ACTUS IV. SCiENA IV.

Enter Andrew.

Are you come, old Mafter? Very good, your Horfe is well let
up 5 but ere ye part, Til ride you, and Ipur your Reverend Ju-
fticefhip luch a queftion, as I (hall make the lides of your Repu¬
tation bleed,, truly I will. Now muft I play at Bo-peep--

A Banquet-- well. Potatoes and Eringoes, and, as I take

it, Cantharides-Excellent, a Priapifm follows, and, as Ell

handle it, it (hall, old lecherous Coat in authority. Now they
begin to Bill 5 how he flavers her! Gramercy hiUy.^ (he (pits his
kifles out, and now he offers to fumble (he falls off, ( that’s a
good Wench) and cries fair play above board. Who are they -
in the corner? As I live, acovy of Fidlers^ I (hall have fome
Mufick yet at my making free o’th’Company of Horners 5

there’s the comfort, and a Song too / He beckons for one--

Sure ’tis no Anthem, nor no borrow’d Rhymes

out of the School of Vertue 5 I will liften- A ^ong.

This was never penn’d oxGemva.^ the Note’s
too (prightly. So, fo, the Mufick’s paid for, and now what
follows ? O that Monfieur Miramont would but keep his word 5
here were a Feaft to make him fat with laughter 5 at the mod
‘tisnot fix minures riding from his houle, nor will he break, I
hope — — O are you come. Sir ? the prey is in the net, and will
break in uponoccafion.

Mir. Thou (lialt rule me, Andrew. O th’infinite fright that will
afiTail this Gentleman! the Quartans, Tertians, and Quotidians
that will hang like Sergeants on his Worfhipsfiioulders! the hu¬
miliation of the flefh of this man 1 this grave, auftere man will
he wondred at. How will thole (blemn looks appear to me 5 and
that fevere face, that fpeaks chains and (hackles ^ Now I take
him in the nick, ere I have done with him, he had better have
(food between two panes of Wainfeot, and made his recantation,
in the Market, then hear me conjure him.


And. •








THE ELDER BROTHER. 45

He muftpafi this way to th’onely Bed I have 3 he comes,
ftandclofe.

Brj. Well done, well done, give me my night-cap. So. Quick,
quick,untru(sme 5 I will trufs and trounce thee. Come, Wench,,
a kifi between each point 5 kifi dole, it is a fweetParenthefis.

~ LiL Y are merry. Sir.

i?r/. Merry I will be anon, and thou (halt feel it, thou (halt,,
my Lill,

LiL Shall I air your Bed, Sir ?

J 5 r/.No, no, ril u(e no Warming-pan but thine, Girl, thats
aH. Come ki(s me again.

LiL Ha ye done yet ?

Bri. No 5 but I will do, and do wonders, Lilly. Shev/ me
the way.

LiL You cannot mif§ it, Sir ^ you (hall have a Cawdle in the
morning for your Worfhip sbreakfaft.

Bri. How, fth’ morning, Lilly ^ th’ artfiich a witty thing to*
draw me on. Leave fooling, L/^, Lam hungry now, andth’haft.
another Kickfhaw, I muft tafte it.

LiL Twill make you furfet, lam tender of you: y’have all
y are like to have.

Arjd. And can this be earneft?

Mir. It feems fo, and (he honefl:.

Bri. Havel not thy promife, Lilly?:

LiL Yes, and I have performed enough to a man of your years^s
this is truths and you (hallfind, Sir, you have ki(s’d and tous*d
me, handl'd my leg and foot 5 what would you more, Sn? As
for the refi, it requires youth and (frength, and the labour ia
an old man would breed Agues, Sciatica's, and Cramps: You>
(hall not curie me for taking from you what you cannot fpare.
Sir. Be good unto your felf, y'have tane already all you can take
with eafe 5 you are paft threfhing, it isa work too boifterous foe
you, leave fiich drudgery to Andrew.

Mir. How (he jeers him ?

LjL Let Andrew alone with his own tillage, he’s tough, and;
can manure in

Bri, Y are a quean, afeoffing, jeering quean.

l7'/.*It may be fo, but Lm (ure 111 nek be yours.


Brh














4 g THE ELDER BROTHER.

Bri. Do not provoke me, if thou do’ft, Til havemy Farm again,
and turn thee out a begging.

LH. Though you have the will, and want of honefty to deny
your deed. Sir 5 yet I Andrew has got fo much learning
from my young Mafter, as to keep his own 5 at the word, I’ll
tell a fhort tale to the Judges, for what grave ends you fignd
your Leafe, and on what terms you would revoke it.

Bri. Whore, thou dafft not. Yield, or 1*11 have thee whiptj
How my bloud boils, as if’t were or a furnace!

Mir. I (hall cool it.

Bri. Yet, gentle Z/Z^, pity and forgive me, HI be a friend t*ye>
foch a loving bountiful friend--—•

Lil. To-avoid Suits in Law, I would grant a little, but (hould
Rgycq Andrew know it, what would become of me }

And. A whore, a whore 1

Bri. Nothing but well Wench, I fhall put fuch a ftrong Bit in
his mouth, as thou (halt ride him how thou wilt, my LiUjfy nay,
he (hall hold the door, as I will work him, and thank thee for the
office,

Mir. Take heed, Andrew^ thefeare fhrewd temptations.

And. Pray you know your Cue, and fecond me. Sir. By your
Wor(hip*s favour.

Bri. Andrew.

And. I come in time to take poffeffion of th’office you aflign
me 5 hold the door, alas, *tis nothing for a fimple man to ftay
without, when a deep underftanding holds conference within,
(ay with his Wife: A trifle. Sir, I know I hold my Farm by Cuck¬
olds Tenure 5 you are Lord o’th* Soil, Sir. Lilly \s a Weft, a
Stray, fhe*s yours to ufe, Sir, I claim no intereft in her.

Bri. Art thou forious ? fpeak, honeft Andrew.^ fince thou haft
o’erheard us, and wink at foall faults, man 3 I’m but a pidler, a
little will ferve my turn 5 thou’t find enough when IVe my
belly full: Wilt thou be private and filent ?

And. By all means, Tllonely have a Ballad made of’t, fung to
fome lewd Tune, and the name of it (hall be JnJlice Trap \ it
will fell rarely with your Worfhips name, and Lilly s on the top.

Bri, Seek not the mine o’ my reputation, Andrew.

Ajid. Tisfor your credit, f^nfieur Brifac, printed in capital

Letters,




4 ?


THE ELDER' BROTHER.

Letters, then pafted upon all the pofts in Park..

Bri. No mercy, Andrew,

And. O, it will proclaim you from the City to the Court, and
prove Sport Royal.

Bri. Thou (halt keep thy Farm.

Mir. He does afflift him rarely.

And. You trouble me. Then his intent arriving,, the vizard of
his hypocrifie pull’d off to the Judge criminal.

Bri. OI am undone.

And. He's put <xit ofCommiflionwuh di^race, and held un-
capable of bearing Office ever hereafter. This is my revenge, and
this I’ll put in pradtife.

5 r?. Do but hear me.

And. To bring me back from my Grammar to ihy Horn-book,
it is unpardonable. -

Bri. Do not play the Tyrant 3 accept ofcompofition.

Lil. Hear him, Andrew.

And. What compofition ?

Bri. I’ll confirm thy Farm,, and add unto’t an hundred acreJ
more,adjoyning to it.

And. Umb, this mollifies 3 but y’are fo fickle, and will again
deny this, there being no witneft by.

Bri. Call any witnefe, I’ll prefentlyaflure it.

And. Say you Ib? troth there’s a friend of mine, Sir, within
hearing, that’s ffimiliar with all that’s paft, his teftimony will be
authenticak

Bri. Will he be fecret >

And,^o\x may tie his tongue up, as you would do your purfc-

Bri. MjrafHOHt, f

Mir. Ha-ha«ha ?

And. This is my witnefe- Lord how you are troubled T fure
you have an Ague, you (hake fo with choler: Here s your lov*-
ing Brother, Sir, and will tell no body but all he meets, that you
have eat a Snake, and are grown young, gamelbme, and ram¬
pant.

jBri.Caught thus?

And^ If he were one that would make of you, or plague












▼


The e ld e r broThek.

ye, with making your Religious gravity ridiculous to your
neighbours, then you had fome caufe to be perplex’d.;

Bri, I (hall become difcourfe for Clowns and Tapfters.

Quick, Li% quick, he s now part killing, between point
, and point. He fwounds, fetch him fome Cordial — Now put
in, Sir.^

M/r. Who may this be ? fure this is fome miftake: let me foe
his face, wears he not a falfo beard It cannot be Brifac that wor¬
thy Gentleman, the Pillar and the Patron of his Countrey 5 he is
too prudent, and too cautelous, experience hath taught him
t avoid thefe fooleries, he is the punifher, and not the doer 5 be-
lides, he’s old and cold, unfit for woman; This is fome counter¬
feit, he (hall be whipt fbr’t, fome bafe abufer of my worthy
Eroth-er.

Bri. Open the doors ^ will yeimprifon me ? are ye my Judges ?

Mir. The man raves! this is not judicious Brifac : yet now I
think on’t, a has a kind of dog look like my Brother, a guilty
hanging face.

Bri. ril fuffer bravely, do your worft, do, do. - '

Mir. Why, it’s manly in you.

Bri. Nor will I rail nor curfe,you (lave, you whore, I will not
meddle with you ^ but all the torments that ere fell on men, that
fed on mifohief, fall heavily on you all. [Exit.

Lil. You have giv n him a heat. Sir.

Mir. He will ride you thebetter, LiUy.

And. We’ll teach him to meddle with SchoHrs.

Mir. He (hall makegood his promifo t’increafo thy Farm, An-
•drew^ or I’ll jeer him to death. Fear nothing, Lilly.^ I am thy
Champion. This jeaft goes to Charles.^ and then I’ll hunt him out,
and Monfieur Eujiace the gallant Courtier, and laugh heartily to
foe’m mourn together.

And. ’Twill be rare. Sir. [ Exeunt.








THE ELDER BKOtHER, 4 ^


JBus V. Scana I.


Eujlace^ Egremont^ Coivj),


T Urnd out of doors and baffled! -

Egre. We (hare with you in the affront.

Corv^ Yet bear it not like you with fiich dejeftion.

Eujl. My Coach and Horfesmade theranfbme of our cowardize*
Len?. Cow. Pifh, thafs nothing, kis dumnum reparabile^ and fbon
recover’d. .

Egre, It is but feeding a Suitor with falfe hopes, and aft€4:
fqueeze him with a dozen of Oaths. You are new rigg d,, and
this no more remembred.

Euji. And does the Court, that (hould be the Example and
Oracle of the Kingdom, read to us no other dod rine !

Egre, None that thrives fb well as that, within my kno\vledge?
Flattery rubs out 5 but fince great men learn to admire
themfelves, Yis fomething creft-faln.

Egre, To be of no Religion, argues a fubtle, moral underftand-
ing, and itis often cherifh’d.

EmJI, Piety then, and valour, nor to do and fuffer wrong, are
they no virtues.^

Rather vices, Eujiace^ Fighting! what’s fighting.^ it
may be in fafhion among Provant fwords, and BufF-)erkin men:
But w’us that fwim in choice of Silks and Tiflues 5 though in de¬
fence of that word Reputation, which is indeed a kind of glo¬
rious nothing, tolofe a dram of blood muft needs appear as coarfe
as tobehoneft.

EuJi, And all this you ferioufly believe.

Cow. It is a faith that we will die in, fince from the black
Guard to the grim Sir in Office, there are few hold other Tenets*
EuJl. Now my eyes are open, and I behold a ftrong necefCtj
that keeps me knave and coward.

Cnny tVip wiier



i


m
















50 The EtDtK brother.

Egre. By no means.

Eujl. Honour is nothing with you ?

Cow. A meet bubble 3 for what's grown common, is no more
regarded.

Eujl. My fword forc’d from me too, and ftill detain’d, you
think 'tis no blemifh.

Egre. Get me a Battoon, 'tis twenty times more Court-like
and lefs trouble.

Eujl. And yet you wear a fword.

Cow. Yes, and a good one, a Millan hilt, and a Damafco blade
for ornament, not ufe, the Court allows it. ’

Eujl. Will’t not fight of it felf?

Cow. I ne’er tri’d this, yet I have worn as fair as any man; I’m-
fure I’ve made my Cutler rich, and paid for feveral weapons
lurkijhmdToledo's, twothoufand Crowns, and yet could never
light upon a fighting one.

JS«^. I’ll borrow this, I like it well.

Cow. Tis at your fervice,Sir, a Lath ki a Velvet Scabbard will
fervemyturn.

Eujl. And now Ihave it, leave me 3 y’are infefiious, theplague
and leprofie of your balenefs (preading on all that do come near
you 3 luch as you render the Throne ofMajefty, the Court,
fufpefted and contemptible 3 you are Scarabee’s' that batten in
her dung, and have no pallatsto tafteher curious Viands 3 and
like Owles, can onely fee her night deformities, but with the
glorious Iplendor of her beauties, youareftruck blind as Moles
that undermine the fumptuous Building that allow’d you (helter :
you ftick like running ulcers on her face, and taint thepurenefs
of her native candor, and being bad Servants, caufe your Ma¬
ilers goodnels to be dilputed of3 you make the Court, that is-
the abftraft of all Academies, to teach and praftife noble under¬
takings, ( where courage fits triumphant crown’d with Lawrel
and wiidom loaded with the weight ofhonour) a School of Vices!

,Eg re. What fiidden raptut^’s thisi?

Eujl. A heavenly one, that raifing me from floth and igno¬
rance, (in which your conveilationlong hath charm’d me) carries
rae up into the air of aftion, and knowledge of my lelf3 even
now I feel, but pleading onely in tjj^e Court’s defence (though











THE ELDER B^dTHER.


for fliort of her merits and bright luftr^) a happy alteration, and
full ftrength to ftand her Champion againft all the world, that
throw alperfions on her.

Cow. Sure hell beat us, I fee it in his eyes.

Egre, A fecond Charles ^ pray look not, Sir,lbfuriouny.

Euli. Recant what you have laid, ye Mungrils, and lick up
the vomit ye have caft upon the Court, where you unworthily
have had warmth and breeding, and fwearthat you, like Spiders,
have made-poifon of that which was a faving Antidote.

Egr^. We will fwear any thing.

Cow. We honour the Court as a moft facred place.

Egre. And will make oath, if you enjoyn us to’t, nor knave,
nor fool, nor coward living in it,

Enji. Except you two, you Rafcals.

Cow. Yes, we are all thefe, and more, if you will have it fb.

Euji. And that until you are again reform’d and grown new
men, you ne’er prelume to name the Court, or prefi into the
Porter’s Lodge but for a penance, to be difciplin’d for your
roguery, and this done with true contrition.

Both, Yes, Sir.

EuJi, You again may eat fcraps, and be thankful.

Cow. Here’s a cold breakfaft after a (harp nights walking. •

Eh§1. Keep your oathes, and without grumbling vanifli.

We are gone, Sir. [Rxeufft.

Euji. May all the poornefi of my fpirit go with you; the fet-**
ters of my thraldom are filed off, and I at liberty to right my
felf^ and though my hope in AngeUtnd% little, my honour ( unto
which compar’d (he’s nothing) (hall, like the Sun, dilperfe thofe
lo’wring Clouds that yet obfcure and dim it 5 not the name of
Brother (hall divert me, but from him, that in the world s opi^
nion ruin’d me, I will (eek reparation, and call him untoaftrift
accompt. Ha! ’tis near day, and if the Mufes friend, R ofe-cheek’d
Aurora^ invite him to this folitary Grove, as I much hope (he will,
hefeldome mifling to pay his vows here to her, I (hall hazard to

hinder his devotions.—-*-The door opens,

’tis he moft certain, and by’slide my Sword, Enter Charles.
Bleft opportunity.

Char. I have o’er^flept my felf, and loft part of the morn, but

H 2 ni











*;i THE ELDER BROTHER.

ril recover it: Before I went to bed, I wrote fome Notes within
rtiy Table-book, which I will now confider, Ha!'what means
this? What do I with a Sword? Learn’d needs not

th’aid of and innocence is to it felf a guards yet fince

Arms ever proteft Arts, I may juftly wear and ufe it 5 for fince
Iwas made my prize, I know not how Tm grown in love wither,
and cannot eat nor ftudyc, and much left walk without it. But I
trifle,* matters of more weight ask my judgment.

Ef/Ji. Now, Sir, treat of no other Theme, Til keep you to it,,
and fee y’expound it well

Char. Eujiace l - .

Euji. The feme. Sir, your younger Brother, who, as duty binds
him, hath all this night (turn'd out of door J attended, to bid
Good-morrow t’ye.

> This not in (corn, commands me tareturn it. Would

you ought el(e ?

Efiji. O much. Sir, here I end not, but begin 5 I muft (^ak to
you in another ftrain than yet I ever us’d 5 and if the language
appear in the delivery rough and harfh, you ('being my Tutor
tnuft condemn your (elf, from whom I learn'd it.

Char, when I underftand (be’t in what ftyle you plea(e) what s
your demand, I (hall endeavour, in the (elf-fame phra(c, to make
ah an'fwer to the point.

I come not to lay claim to your birth-right, ’tis your own,
and ’tis fit you enjoy it 3 nor ask I from you your learning and
deep knowledge^ (though I am not a Scholar as you are) t
know them Diamonds by your(ble induftry, patience and la¬
bour, forc’d from fteep Rocks, and with much toil attended, and
but to few that prize their value granted, and therefore without
Rival freely wear themi.

The(e not repin’d at (asyoufeem f inform me) the mo¬
tion muff be of a ftrange condition, if I refufe to yield to’t,
therefore, Eujiace^ without thistempeft in your looks, propound
k, and fear not a denial.

Euji. I require then ( as from’an Enemy, and not 2l Brother)
the reputation of a man, the Honour, not by a fair War won
when I was waking, but in my fleep of folly ravifh’d from me^
wkh thefe, thereftitutionof my Sword, with large acknowledg¬
ment.










THE ELDER BROTHER. 53

merit of ratisfa€lion, my Coach, my Horfes 5 I will part with lift,
ere lofe one hair of them 3 and, what concludes all,my Miftris Ju-
gellina^ as (he was before the mufical Ma.gick of thy tongue in-
chanted and feduc'd her. Thefe perform'd, and with fubmiffion,
and done publickly, at my Father sand my Uncle's interceflion,

(that I put in too) I perhaps may liften to terms of reconcile¬
ment^ but if thefe, in every circumftance, are not fubfcrib’dto^
to the laft gafp I defie thee.

Char- Thefe are ftrift conditions to a Brother.

BhIL My reft is up, nor will I give left.

Char, I'm no Gamefter, Eujiace^ yet I can gheft your refelution
ftands to win or lofe all, I rejoyce to find ye thus tender of your
honour, and that at length you undeiftand what a wretcheci
thing you weje, how deeply wounded by your felf, and made
almoft incurable in your own hopes, the dead flefti of pale
eowardife growing over your fcftred reputation, which no Balm
or gentle Unguent could ever make way to 5 and I am happy,
that I was the Surgeon that did apply thofe burning corrofives,
that render you already fenfible o'th'danger you were plung'd
in, in teaching.you, and by a fair gradation, how far, and with
what curious relped and care the peace and credit of a man with¬
in, (which you ne’er thought till now) fhould be preferr'd be¬
fore a gawdy outfide, pray you fix here,for fo far I go with you;

Ettfi. This difeourfe is from the fubjeft.

Char, ril come to it. Brother 5 but if you think to build upon
my ruines, you'll find afalfe foundation : your high offers,taughu
by the Mafteis ofdependeficies. that by compounding dife-
rences'tween others, fupply their own neceffities, with me will
never carry't; as you arc my Brother, I will difpence a little^
but no more than honour can give way to 5 nor muft I deftroy
that in my felf I love in you, and therefore let not hopes or
threats pei fuade you I will delcend to any compofition for which.
I maybecenlur'd.

Enji. You fhall fight then.

Char, With much unwillingneis with you 5 but if there's* nQ>
cvalion-—

Etiji, None.

CW. Hear yet a word s asfor the Sword and other fripperies^,

^ “ ... .. , in.





:54 the elder brother.

in a fair way fend for them, you (hall have *e^. But rather than
Surrender AngtUim^ or hear it again medtion^d, I oppofe my
' breaft unto loud thunder, caft behind me all ties of Nature*

Eufl. She detain’d, I’m deaf to all perfuafion.

Char. Guard thy felf then, Eujiace 3 I ufe no other Rhetorick.

Enter Miram;

Mfr. Clafhing of fwords fo near my houfe! Brother oppos’d
•to Brother! here’s no fencing at half (word 5 hold, hold,

Euflace.

Euji. Second him, or call in more help. Come not between us,
ril not know nor Ipare you ^ D’ye fight by th’book .<?

Char. ’Tis you that wrong me, off Sir, and fuddenly. I’ll con¬
jure down the Spirit that I have rais’d in him.

EuJi. Never, ’tis thine, and in thy death, be doubled

in me.

Mir. I’m out of breath, yet truft not too much to’t, Boys^ for
if you paufe not fuddenly, and hear reafon, do, kill your Uncle,
do 5 but that I’m patient, and not a cholerick old teafty fool,
like your Father, I’d dance a matachin with you, fhould make
you fweat your beft bloud for’t 5 I would, and it may be I will.
Charles^ I command thee, and Eujiace^ T entreat thee, th’ art a
brave Spark, a true tough-metall’d blade, and I begin to love
thee heartily 5 give me a fighting Courtier, I’ll cherifli him for
^example, incur Age th’arenotborn everyday.

Char.You oflate, Sir, inmelov’d learning.

Mrr. True, but take me w’ye, Charles-^ ’twas when young
Eujiace wore his heart in’s breeches, and fought his Battels in
Complements and Cringes, when’s underftanding wav’d in a
flaming Feather, and his beft contemplation look’d no further
than a new-faftiion'd doublet 5 I confefi then, the lofty noife
your Greek madeonely pleas’d me 5 but now he’s turn’d an Oliver
and a Rowland^ nay, the whole dozen of Peers are bound up in
him: Let me remember, when I was of his years, I did look very
like him 5 and did you fee my Piflure as I was then, you would
fwearthat g2i\\mt Eujiace (\ mean, now he dares fight) was the
true fubftance, and the perfeft figure. Nay, nay, no anger, you
ihall have enough, Charles. Cbar^






THE ELDER BROTH ERl

Char. Sure, Sir,.! (hall not need addition fromhim^,

EhJI. Nor I from any, this (hall decide my intereft 5 though I
am loft to all deferving men, to all that men call good, for fuf.
fering tamely infufferaWe wrongs, and juftly (lighted by yield¬
ing to a minute of delay in my revenge, and from that made a
ftranger unto my Father’s houfe and favour, o’erwhelm’d with
all difgraces^ yet I will mount upward, and force my felf a
fortune, though my birth and breedingdo deny it.

Char. Seek not, Eujiace^ by violence, what will be offer’d tO'^
you on ealier compofition 3 though I was not alli’d unto your
weaknefs, you (hall find me a Brother to your bravery of fpirit,
and one that, notcompell’d to’t byyourfword, ( whichImuft:
never fear) will (hare with you in all but AngeUina.

Nobly (aid, Charles^ and learn from my experience, you<
may hear reafon, and never maim your fighting 3 for your credit^,,
which you think you have loft, (pare, and (winge me, and'

foundly^ three or four walking velvet Cloaks, that wear no^
fwords to guard ’em,yetde(erve it, thou art made up again.

EmJI. Ail this is Lip-(alve.

Mir. It (hall be Hearts-eafe, Eujiac^^ ere! have done5 as for^
thy Father’s anger, now thou dar’ft fight, ne’er fear it, for I’ve
the dowcets of his gravity faft inaftring, I will(b pinch and:
wring him, that, (pight of his authority, thou (halt make thine
own conditions with him.

Euji. ril take leave a little to confider.

Char. Here comes Andrew.

Mir. But without his comical and learned face 3 what (ad dii^^
Andrew?

And. You may read. Sir, a Tragedy in myfacCo

Mir. Art thou in earneft ?

Yes, by my life. Sir 5 and if now you help not, and (pee-
dily, by force, or by perfuafion, my good old Mafteri(for now.
rpity him) is ruin’d for ever.

Char. Ha, my Father!

^;7<^."He,Sir.

Mir. By what means ? (peak.

And. At the fuit of Monfieur Lewk^ his hou(e is (eiz’d'upoiT,
and he in peifon b under guard, (Ifaw it with foefe eyes, Sir)'




the elder brother.

to be convey’d to Park^ and there Sentenc'd.

iVf/r-Nay, then there is no jefting.

Char. Do Hive, and know my Father injur’d ^ '

And. And what’s worfe, Sitjmy Lady Angdlina ™ — i.*..

Enji, What of her ?

And She’s carrfd away too. -
How?

And. While you were abfent, a crew of Monfieur friends-
and kinfmen, by force, brake in at th’back part of the houfe,
and took her away by violence 5 faithful Andrew ( as this can*
witnefi for him) did hisbeft in her defence, but’twould not do.

Mi\ Away, and fee our Horfes fadled, ’tis no time to talk,
but do. Eufiace^ you now are- offer’d a fpatious field, and in a
pious* War to exercife your valour 5 here’s a caufe, and fuch a
one, in which to fall is honourable, your duty and reverence due
to a fathers name commanding it 5 but thefe unnatural jars ari-
fing between Brothers f (hould you profper ) would fhame your
viflory. ,

Euii.l would do much. Sir, butftill my reputation!

' Mir. Charles (hall give you all decent fatisfadion 5 nay, joyn
hands, and heartily 5 why, this is done like Brothers 5 and as
old as I am, in this caufe that concerns the honour of our Family,
Monfieur Lewk (if reafon cannot work) fhall find and feel there’s
hot blood in this arm, I’ll lead you bravely.

Eu^t. And if I follow not, a cowards name be branded on my
forehead.

'' Ch.^r. This fpirit makes you a fharer in my fortunes.

• Mir. And in mine, of which Brifac once freed, and Angellina
again in our pofleffion) you fhall know, my heart (peaks in my
tongue.

Eujl, I dare not doubt it. Sir. [^Exeunt,

ACTUS V. SCiEN A II.

Enter Lewis, Brilac, Angellina, Sylvia, Officers.-

Lew. Tam deaf to all perfvvafions.

Eri. I u(e none, nor doubt I, though a while my innocence fuf-
fers, but when the King fhall underhand how falfe your malice
hatla inform'd him, he in juftice muft fet me right again.

Ang.








THE ELDER BROTHER. 57

Sir, let not pafiion fo &r trani^oit you, as to think in
reafon, this violent courfe repairs, but ruines it j that honour y
you would build up, you deftroy ^ what you would (eem to
nourift,' if refped of my preferment or my pattern* may chal¬
lenge your paternal love and care, why do you, now good for-,
tune has provided a better Husband for me than your hopes
could ever fancy, ftrive to rob me of him .<? In what is my Lord
Clarks ddcdive^ Sir ? unlels deep Learning be a blemi(h in him,
or well proportion’d limbs be mulfts in nature, or, what you
onely aim’d at, large Revenues, are, on the fudden, grown di-
ftaftefulto you. Of what can y ou accufe him ?

len?. Of a Rape done to Honour, which thy ravenous luft
made thee conlent to.

5 //. Her luft i you are her Father.

Lew, And you her Bawd.

Sj/, Were you fen Lords, ’tis falfe^ the purenefi of her chaftc
thoughts entertains not fuch Ipotted inftruments.

J/fg, As I have a Soul, Sir.

Lew, I am not to be alter’d ^ to fit down with this dilgra’ce,
would argue me a Peafant, and not bom Noble: all rigour that
the Law, and that increafe of power by favour yields, ftiall be
with all feverity inflifited^ you have the Kings hand for’t no
Bail will ferve, and therefore at your perils. Officers, away
with’em.

fir/. This is madnels.

Lew. Tell me fo in open Court, and there I’ll anfwer you.
.£;//erMiramont, Charles, Euftace, Andrew.

M/r. Well overtaken.

CAi/r. Ill if they dare refift.

He that advances but oneftep forward dies.

Lew. Shew the King’s Writ.

M/>. Shew your diferetion, ’twill become you better.

Y’a re once more in my power, and if again I part with
you, let me for ever lofe thee,

Ef/Ji. Force will not do’t, nor threats j accept this for vice from
youridefpair’d of Eujiace.

And.


I






the elder brother.

And. And beware your Reverend. Worfhip never more at¬
tempt to learch my Lilly-pt^ you fee what follows.

Is the King s power contemn’d >

Mir. No, but the torrent o your wilful folly ftopp’d. And for
you, good Sir, if you would but be fenfible, what can you wifli,
but the fetisfaftion of an obftinate will, that is not endear’d to
you ? rather than be croft’d in what you purpos’d, you’ll un¬
do your Daughter’s fame, the credit of your judgment, and
your old foolidi Neighbour 5 make your ftates, and in a Suit
not worth a Cardecue, a prey to Advocates, and their buckram
Scribes, and after they have plum’d ye, return homelike a cou¬
ple of naked Fowles without a feather.

Char. This is a moft ftrong truth. Sir.

M/r.No, no, Monfieur, let us be rightFrenchmen, violent to
charge 5 but when our follies arerepell’dby reafbn, ’tisfit that
we retreat, and ne’er come on more: Obferve my learned
Charles^ he’ll get thee a Nephew on Angellina (hall difpute in her
belly, and fuck the Nurfe by Logick: and here’s Eujiace^ he was
an Aft, but now is grown an Awadis , nor fhall he want a Wife,
if all my Land,for a Joynture, can efFed: Y’are a good Lord, and
of a gentle nature, in your looks I fee a kind confent, and it
(hews lovely : and do you hear, old Fool ? but Fll not chide,
hereafter, like me, ever doaton Learning, the meer belief is ex¬
cellent, ’twill fave you 5 and next love Valour, though you dare
not fight your fel^ or fright a foolifh Officer, young Enlace can
doit to a'hair. And, to conclude, let Andrew's Farm b’en-
creas’d, that is your pennance, you know for what, aiut fee you
rut no more ^ you underftand me. So embrace on all fides.

Ill pay thofe Bilmen^ and make large amends^

Provided we preferveyou Jiill our Friend s -- [^Exeunt^


Epilogue.



Epilogue.

y- g M Jj. U0f fig lands^ oror common vea^
of approbation to a rpeU lik’d Flay^

We onely hope-, but that you freely mould.

To th*Author’s memory fofar unfold^

And (hem your loves and libbing to his Wity
Not in your praife, but often feeing it', .

That being the grand ajfurance that can give
The Poet and the Player means to live.


F I N I S,
