Sir Courtly Nice; or, It cannot be. A comedy. As it is acted by His Majesties servants. Written by Mr. Crown., ---. | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
Sir Courtly Nice; or, It cannot be. A comedy. As it is acted by His Majesties servants. Written by Mr. Crown., ---.
Author
Crown, Mr. (John), 1640?-1712.Crown, Mr. (John), 1640?-1712.
Published
London,Printed by H. H. jun. for R. Bently ... and Jos. Hindmarsh ...1685.
Description
4 p. l., 59, [1] p.22 cm.
Rights
Public Domain, Google-digitized.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/nyp.33433112065069

Table of Contents

    Front Cover
    Title Page
    Section 1 on page number 1
    Section 2 on page number 5
    Section 3 on page number 11
    Section 4 on page number 14
    Section 5 on page number 19
    Section 6 on page number 32
    Section 7 on page number 44
    Section 8 on page number 45

Book Text
Front Cover
Page Scan 1

|||||||||||||

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 2

--*） • ！！！！！！！！！！---* - … ► ► ► ► ► ► ► ►► --------------------- - - - -------------------- - - - --------- ----=~=- - - - - - - ---------------------- ------ --------- - - - - - - --------- - ---------- ----
Page Scan 3

-
Page Scan 4

Blank page
Page Scan 5

Blank page
Page Scan 6

Blank page

End of Front Cover. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Title Page
Page Scan 7

| Sir Cou rtly Nice: ** - - - O R, 3ſt tannot ºt. A CO ME DY. * - - - - - - - As it is Aéted by His MAJes T I e s Servants.) !, - - - - - " . . . . . . . 'I - ºf 2:1:::::::, . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . f , ) - * --- - * , - * : **** … . . . ... Written by -- _-- ſº r = . . . . . * * L 0N D 0 N. … " , " " - º . . . Printed by H. H. Jun, for R. Bently, in Ruſſel ſtreet, Covent-Garden, and joſ, Hindmarſh, at the ::::::::: º, Golden-Ball over againſt the Royal Ex- * - - - - - - - change in Cornhill. Mbelxxxv.
Page Scan 8

- - - - - - ---------------- ---------- Ord Belguard. Leonora's Brother, in love with ToR, LENox AND e Wiolant6. TILDEN FOUNDATIONS. - - - - - ly Ni A Fop, overcurious in his Diet and Sir Courtly “Dreſs: Inlove with Leonora. t 5A young Man of Quality and For- Farewel. $º Rival. - - r low; in love with Violinié. tº -*. Surly. § moroſe, ill natur'd negligent Fel. ' s º - ** * * * º' i. ** - ! Crack A young ſubtleintriguing Fellow. - 5A cholerick Zealot againſt Fana- Hakat * ... . § . . . . . . . . º i. Teſtimony. A Canting Hypocritical Fanatick - A Lady of Quality and Fortune, in Violante... -- §: with Belguard. Leonora. #.Iguard's Siſter, in love with Fare- mel. - - - - ------ -- " (Le - ---- ------- ---> --------------- --> Aunt. *onora's Governeſs—an oldAmo- - &rous, envyous Maid. • *, . . .” - ..". \ ū. . . ." . . - Scene Covent-Garden. - * : . . . . ..." : y º gº ºvºv 7: . •º . . . . . . . º. º . . . . . . . . . ) . - - To. - I ! -



Page Scan 9

Tº his Grace the Duke of ORMONI), Lord Stemard of His Majeſties Hoſſhold, Chan- tellor of the Oniverſity of Oxford, Knight of the Moſt Noble Order of the Garter,&c. May it pleaſe your Grace, º His Comedy was Written by the Sacred Command of our late moſt Excellent King, of ever bleſſed and beloved Memory. I had the great good Fortune to pleaſe Him often at His Court in my - Maſque, on the Stage in Tragedies and Comedies, and ſo to advance myſelf in His good opinion; an Honour may render a wiſer Man than Ivain; for I believe he had more equals in extent of Dominions than of underſtanding. The greateſt pleaſure he had from the Stage was in Comedy, and he often Commanded me to Write it, and lately gave me a Spaniſh Play called No Puedeſer: Or, It cannot Be... out of which I took part o' the Name, and deſign o’ this. I received the Employment as a great Honour, becauſe it was difficult; requiring no ordinary skill and pains to build a little Shallop, fit only for the Spaniſh South Seas, into an Engliſh Ship Royal ; but I believe myſelf able for the Work, becauſe he thought ſo, who underſtood me and all Men, better than I only knew my ſelf, en- courag’d by a Royal judgment that never was miſtaken, I have attained a fucceſs I never ſhould have met with, had I only followed my own feeble Genius, which often deceives me. That I may enjoy the little fortune I. have got with the better reputation, and not ramble the World like a bold outlaw, obſerving none but my ſelf, I make this humble Application to your Grace. I am ſure all the World will approve my choice. I cannot be guilty of Flattery if I would; nor ſlander Wit (if I had any) by ful- ſome and wanton Paintings. Here will be no Tryal of skill how I can praiſe, Nature has done it to my Hands, and devis’d and expos'd finer Ideas, than I am able to Tranſlate. A gracefulneſs of Perſon, excellence of un- derſtanding, largeneſs of Heart, a Loyalty, Gallantry, Integrity, Humi- lity, and many Qualities above my deſcription. Fortune alſo has been more wiſe than uſual, She frequently honours and enriches others to her own diſgrace—but here She ſhares in the Praiſe, and Commends her own Wiſdome, in what She beſtows on your Grace. She has advanc'd Honour in Advancing you, Titles, Greatneſs and Command may be prowd, they have attained you. Wealth has a value in your Hands, 'Tis no vile par- don, poor flatterer, ſervile Lacquey, wretched Priſoner; but excellent Mi- niſter of a juſt wiſe and liberal Prince. Shou'd I mention all the Qualities, that have long gained you the higheſt Honours from Prince and People, I ſhould rather ſeem to deſcribe a Province then a Man; for what ſingle Pro- vince can afford what are at once in your Grace, a General, a Stateſman, Courtier, and all in perfeótion; and which is rare in ſuch company, a Martyr. What has your Grace both done and ſuffered, for our Religion, Laws, Liberties and Honour? And not only in the former times of Rebel- lion, but the latter of Confuſion? When the pretended Proteſtants of the times, out of their Zeal againſt all Popiſh Dočtrines, abhorr'd you for ad-
Page Scan 10

The Epiffle Dedicatory. º - As an Engliſh-man, I am bound in juſtice, to pay you all the Honours I ean. You have been an Ornament, and ſupport to the Crown and Church of England, both in your Perſon and Poſterity. Many great Men no doubt have ſprung from your example, but none equalling thoſe deſcended from your ſelf. The late brave Earl of Oſſery, advanced the Honour of our Na- tion, both by Sea and Land. 'Tis hard to ſay in which Element he made us moſt twown'd, and for which vertue. He was no more to be vanquiſhed by fallhood than fear; Loyalty, Fidelity,and Gallantry,are Vertugs inſepara- ble from the Houſe of Ormond; we find e^m in every branch †. and at all ſeaſons. The Earl of Arram, Attacked in the late days of Confuſion, a Bloody, Popular, and Formidable Error in its Camp, Fortified and De- fended by all the ſtrength of England; and for ever ſecur'd his own, and ſo, much of the Publick reputation as was entruſted to him; managing that charge with the ſame Wiſdom, Juſtice, and Fidelity he has done the King- dom of Ireland, and many other great Commands, for the Honour and Ser- vice of the King. In the Young Earl of Oſſery we have great aſſurances, the Grandfather and Father ſhall live in him, and receive the laſt rewards of Vertue Men are capable of in this World, to have their Honour and Happineſs extend beyond their own beings. And herein the Hiſtory of your Grace ſeems a Comment on the Fifth Commandment, you have always Honoured the Father of your Country, and your Days of Honour conti- nue long in the Land, in your own Perſon, and your Illuſtrious Race. A uſeful Preſident to England. That I may approve my ſelf an honeſt and grateful Engliſh-mam, is one reaſon of my Addreſs: I have alſo other obligations on me. Your Grace has been a Princely patron and encourager of Poetry; a Pleaſant but Bar- ren Country where my Genius and inclination has caſt me. I am entan- gled among theſnchantments of it,though it affords nothing but a good Ayre, a little vain reputation, and we muſt climb for it, and ſhall miſs it too, if envy or ill nature can hinder us. There were no living, if ſome great Men elevated not only in Quality but underſtanding above the reſt of the World, did not Protéét us from thoſe Barbarians, becauſe they know us. I beſecch your Grace then give me leave to pay my Duty to you. Many and great are your Revenues in Honour, in the Camp, the Court, the Church, and the whole Common-wealth of Learning. The Poet may be employed as well as the Hiſtorian. I have made but a ſmall Colle&tion, but I have put it in hands that I hope will not ſoon embezie it. This Come- dy has raisid it ſº if ſuch a fortune in the World, I believe it will not ſoon. run away. Give it leave to Honour it ſelf with your great Name, and me: *ith the Title of, - May it pleaſe your Grate, 2öur Graces moſt \ Humble and Obedient Servant. John Crown, --- * f :
Page Scan 11

-- --- * - . The Prologue. W7 Hat are the Charmes, by which theſe happy ! Wy' - - - (Iſles Hence gain'd Heaven's brighteſt and eternal - - - (ſmiles? What Nation upon Earth beſides our own, But by a loſs like ours had been undone? Ten Ages ſcarce ſuch Royal worths diſplay As England loſt, and found in one ſtrange Day. One hour in ſorrow and confuſion hurld, And yet the next the envy of the World. Nay we are bleſt, in ſpite of us 'tis known, . Heavens choice for Us was better than our own. To ſtop the bleſſings that oreflow this day, - What heaps o' Rogues we pild up in the way: We choſe fit tooles againſtall good to ſtrive, The ſawcieſt,lewdeſt, Proteſtants alive. They wou'd have form'd a bleſſed Church indeed, Upon a Turn-coate Doctor's lying Creed. To know if ere he took Degree is hard, 'Tis thought he'lhave one in the Palace Yard, Plot fivallowers ſure will Drink no more ſtuff down; From that foul Pitcher when his Ears are gone. Let us rely on Conſcience, not on Cheats, On Heavens wiſdom, not on Juglers feats. How greatly Heaven has our great loſs ſupplyed? 'Tis no ſmall Weatue heales a Wound ſo wide.
Page Scan 12

The Prologue -- ºrº- Beneatht Theſe are not all the bleſfings of this Iſle, Nay in ſo little time to reer our ! :ºs, To our own wonder, and cººr eighbours dread. They ſee that Valoº C wild with regal Power, They oft have ſeen wila, Lawrels Crown'd before. Verſe is too narrow for ſo Great a Name, Far ſounding Seas hourly repeat His Fame. Our Neighbours vanquiſh’d Fleetsoftwafted o're, His Name to theirs and many à trembling Shore; And we may go by His great Conductled As far in Fame as our Forefathers did. At home he milder ways to Glory choſe, Godlike, by Patience he ſubdued his Foes; Now they and their deſigns are Ruin'd all, i. fallen,accurſt,Excluding Wall. Heaven on our Nation in a Queen does ſmile. Whoſe Vertue's Grace by Beauty ſhine ſobright, All the Fair Sex to Vertue She’l invite ; And all the Clouds turn to a glorious Day, } By that Illuſtrious paire's united ray, - Who both Reform and Grace Us by their ſway. Epilogue.
Page Scan 13

-- - - --- - E pilogue 3. Is a hard Caſe, an Audience now to pleaſe, For every Pallat's ſpoyl'd with ſome Diſeaſe. Poor Plays as faſt as Women now decay, , They’r ſeldom car'd for after the firſt day; How often have I heard true wit call'd ſtuff, By Men with nothing in their Brains but Snuff 2 Each Shante Spark, that can the Faſhion bit, Place his Hat thus, roſe full Forſooths a Wit; And thinks his Cloaths allows him judge of it. The City Gallant, the Exchange being done, Takes Sword at Temple-Bar which Nice ſtuck on. Comes here and paſſes for a Beaugarzoon. Audacious Wizards too, ſo faſt do grow, 7ou hardly can the Virtuous from 'em know. Nay Parents now not likely can endure, Their Childrens faults, but what is worſe procure. Of Old the Mother full of Parent ſway, . . . . Kept Miſs a Vaſal to her work all day; . . . And to the Wooing Spark Miſs was not brought, º But ſome fine Golden thing her wheedle wrought: Wom you ſhall meet young Lady and her Mother, Rambling in Hackny-Coaches maſqu't together; Jes, and to ſay the truth, to j, go, Fine work but ſuch as they will never ſhew... . Z/nleſs ſome Nott to draw a Fool to Wed, And then he finds Miſs rare at work a Bed. But the Grand Randevouz is kept of late, Exači at Aline, hard by ore Chocholate, Sad
Page Scan 14

- —-- º- * - And had throng’d Audiences when we had none. Confound you give your bawdy prating o're, Epilogue. * Sadfate, that all the Chriſtian Youth o'th' Nation, Should be oblig'd to Jews for Procreation. Nay, what is worſe, that's, if reports he fue, Many a Chriſtian Gallant there fºrms ſº wº That is, ſo oft ſome rotter Sirºt fºr, pim, The Chirurgion's forc't a laſt to Circumciſe him. Our Bridges-ſtreet is gron, a Strumpet Fair, Where higling Bawds do Palmb their rotten Ware. There Fowler like the watching Gallant Pores Behind his Glove, to get a ſhot at Whores; And from his tongue lets flye ſuch charºg Hººd's, That ſtrait he carrys off the wounded Birds. Another waits above in the great Room, Till a mem Cargozoon of Strumpets come. There by three Glaſes plac’t the Affe'ied Dance, Aśis you Four Courtly-Nices all at once; Our Gallerys too, mere finely us’d of late, - Where rooſting Maſques ſat cackling for a Mate: They came not to ſee Plays but ači their own, Our Plays it was impoſſible to hear, The homeſ Country Men were forct to firear : > Or Zounds, Fleſling you i'the Pittyou bawling Whors- This Comedy throws all that lewdneſs down, For Virtuous Liberty is pleas'd alone: * ~ *- : Promotes the Stage to'th' ends at firſt de'ſign4. º As well to profit, as delight the Mind.

End of Title Page. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 1

COMED Y Caird sit Courtly £itt: O R, \ It Cannot Be. / A c T. I. w * . Enter at ſeveral Doors Leonora and Violante. º Scene, Lord Bellguard's Houſe. Leo. Y Dear - (they embrace) Vio. My Dear, how is it with thee? What amend- ment in thy Brothers humour, and thy condition? - Leo. None. Vio. Oh I thou break'ſt my heart, for I love him cztreamly, and am, I think,as well belov’d by him ; but whil'ſt he has this Diſeaſe upon him ſo mortal to Liberty, dare venture on him no more, than if he had the Plague, or any other Diſtemper dangerous to Life. For what is life with- out Liberty 2 To be his Wife is worſethan to be a Ghoſt, for that walks and enjoys a little chat ſometimes, but I muſt be laid by a Conjurer call’d a Husband for my whole life, I would not be a Queen on the tearms; no nor on any tearms,becauſe a Queen is confin'd to Forms, ſo fond am I of Liberty; but next to that I love your Brother; I wou'd give all the World to cure him, is there no way? - . . . -, - B * N. Leo, None -- r
Page 2

2 Sir Courtly Nice: *- - TO Oſtle. . Leo. None that I know off. - - . , Wºo. Muſt we then be for ever unhappy, I in the leſs of him, and you in Eternal Slavery? - Leo. I might have Liberty, but on ſuch tearms— Vio. What Tearms?" Leo. Marriage with ſuch a Coxcomb, you know him— Sir Courtly Vio. A tempting Man, he has a vaſt eſtate. ~ - *---> * } Leo. But incumber’d. * { Vio. With what 2 .. ! * - Leo. A Fop, 'tis morgag'd to a thouſand expenſive Follies, if it were not, I wou'd not drink water for the ſake of a fine Bowl chain'd to the Well. The Youth I love has a fair and free Eſtate. Vio. Mr. Farewel is it not - Leo. The ſame. -- . . . . . . . - - - , , Pºo. #: but he's forbidden Fruit. * . Leo. I know it to my ſorrow. - Vio. What's the reaſon? - Leo. Hiſtory muſt tell you. There has been a pique between our Fa- milies ſince the Conqueſt; none were thought truly of our Blood, that had not that Scurvy init; becauſe mine began to ſweeten,my Father almoſt ſuſpected my Legitimacy; and left me no Fortune but on condition I re- tain'd the Ancient mark of our Houſe. - Vio. There ariſes then your Brothers great Authority. He has the diſpoſal of your Fortune, by conſequence of your Perſon; Fortune is all Men ſeek now. They are ſo cow'd from Marriage, they will go Voluntiers into a Battle but muſt be preſt to marriage; and ’tis the Shilling does it. Leo. Too true, But I believe Mr. Farewel of a more generous tem- per, he addreſſes ſtill. Vio. It may be he does not know how it is with you, you have the Fame of Ten thouſand pound. Leo. And the Money too, if I marry with my Brothers conſent, not elſe. Wio. That's hard, but Mr. Parewel has enough for you both. Leo. Ay, if he will venture on me; yet if he will I know not how to come at him, I am ſo watch'd, not only at home but abroad. I never ſtir out but as they ſay the Devil does, with Chains and Torments. She that is my Hell at home, is ſo abroad. . . - - - Vio. A new Woman. - Leo. No, an old Woman, or rather an old Devil ; nay worſe than an old Devil, an old Maid. / - Vic. Oh I there’s no Fiend ſo envious. - Leo. Right, ſhe will no more let young People ſin, than the Devil will. let 'em be ſavid, out of envy to their happineſs. - - Kio. Who is ſhe - tº - - Leo. One of my own Blood, an Aunt. l'io I know her,ſhe of thy bloud 2 ſhe has not had a dr ty Years; the Devil of envy ſuck'd it all out, and left verjuice in the - Ileo. True, . of it,theſe Twen-- t

Page 3

Or it cannot. Be. – 3 t Leo. True, this Aunt hangs on melike a daily Ague; but I had rather endure her,then be cur’d by ſuch a nonſenfical Charm as Sr. Courtlyis, And nothing elſe can be applyed to me; for to affiſt my governing Aunt, there is a whole Army of Spies in the Houſe; and over them two Spies General : And there my Brother thinks he ſhews a Maſter-piece of Policy. . . . . . Vio. Why? what are they - . . .”.” Leo. Two, that will agree in nothing but one anothers confuſion. The one is a poor Kinſman of ours, ſo fierce an Enemy to Fanaticks, that he cou’d eat no other meat; and he need no other Fire than himſelf to roaſt 'em,for he's always in a flame when he comes near 'em,his Name is Hot-head. pºo. And I warrant thee the other is a Fanatick. Leo. Oh lºamoſt Zealous Scrupulous one ; with a conſcience ſwadled ſo hard inks Infancy by ſtrićt Education, and now Thump'd and Cudgel'd ſo ſore with daily'Sermons and Leótures, that the weak ricketty thing can endure nothing. - - Pio. Certainly theſe two, muſt make you ſport. Leo. Oh I their faces, Dreſſes, Names are jeſts. The Fanatick's Name's Teſtimony. - - - / where is my Lord * Where's my Lord? Hot-head Leo. Oh I hear my Cholerick Couſin Hot-head. within. . Enter Hot-head. Hot. Where's my Lord ž Where's my Lord, I ſay? Leo. What wou'd you do with my Lord ž - Hot. Call hitn to an account if he were not my Couſin, cut his pate, it may be Cudgel him. Heaven be thank’d to Cudgel a Lord is noScandalum Magnatum. ... " - i.ee. What's thereaſon of all this anger ? - - . . . ~ Hot. He affront's me, he invitesme to live in his houſe, and then keeps a Fanatick to make a jeſt o' me. He knows I ſweat when I ſee one. Leo. May be he has occaſion for one. - - - Hot. What occaſion? He is not in a Plot, is he Fanaticks. are good for nothing elſe that I know of - Leo. Why not ? Toads are good for ſomething. Hot. Ay, when they are hang'd and dryed, ſo is no Fanatick. He is ſuch a canker'd Rogue, he does miſchief when he's hang'd ; let him ſpread Ink upon Paper and it raiſes bliſters. But here the Rogue is. * . . . Enter Teſtimony. Sirrah ; Sirrah, What's your buſineſs in this Houſe, Sirrah? Teſt. What Authority have you to examine me,Friend? - * Hot. Friend, you Dog! call me Friend, I’le knock you down Sirrah. Tºft. Poor Soul poor Soul— * Hot. You are an Impudent Raſcal to call me poor Soul Sirrah, I have a Loyalty and a good Conſcience, and that's a better Eſtate, than any - . . . E 2. of
Page 4

4 | Sir Courtly Nice: º- ºf your Party have ; and ifyoulive in the Houſe with me, I'le ſettleit on with a Pox to you. - Tºft. Yet, Mr. Hot-head I know you well enough, I know you would hangus all if you could. - Hot. I need not Sirrah, for Heaven be prais’d now you begin to ha yourſelves; I knew when Tyburn was beſtow'dupon §: #: and º: heranaticks and Republicans wou'd not long be without it,for they arevery fond of all Church Lands, come,Sirrah,if you live here, Tſe make you turn over a new leaf, Plemake you go to Church, Sirrah. Zºff. That’s more than you do your ſelf Mr. Hot-head, you go not often to Church. º Hot. What then I’m for the Church, Sirrah. But you are againſt the º and againſt the Miniſters, Sirrah. Tºft. I cannot be Edifyed by’em, they are formal, weak, ignorant, -7 Souls—Lord jº. ". s. gn poor Hot. Ignorant? you're an impudent Raſcal to call Men o’ their Learning Ignorant; there's not one in a hundred of 'em, but has taken all his Degrees at Oxford, and is a Dočtor, you Sot you. Tºft. What ſignifies Oxford f can't we be ſav’d unleſ, we go to Oxford * Hot. Oxford don’t lye out o' the road to Heaven; you Aſs. Zºff. Pray what do they learn at Oxford only to ſtudy Heathens; . they’l talk of Ariſtotle in the publick, they may be aſham'd to name A. riſtotle among civil People. - Hot. Oh you Sot. - Tºft. Our Miniſters are powerful Men. Oh! Forſooth I wiſh ſ to Leo. you were under one of our Miniſters; you wou'd find they wou'd pierce you forſooth; they wou'd go to your inward parts. Hat. This Rogue is talking Bawdy, º Tºft. They would ſhew you the great—great ſinfulneſs of fin, that . ſin is one of the ſinfulleſt things in the whole World. Hº You"enºrº, whº ſhºuld befits, but fin what ſhould be fooliſh but a Fool? " - . . . . . Leo. Are not theſe a ridiculous Couple * - ºf . , - Tºft. Come this is very provoking, and very Prophane; I ſhall have a ſad time on’t in this wicked Family. Hot. Wicked 'Sirrah: What wickedneſs do you ſeein this Family? £eo. Ay, Mr. Tºftimony, now we are all concern'd,what Vices do you find among us? - Tºft. Suppoſe I ſee not many Vices, morality is not the thing; the Hea.' thens had morality, and forſooth would you have your Coachman or your a Footman to be no better Menthan Seneca P Hot. A Coachmana better Man then Seneca 7 - Leo. I wou'd have him be a better Coachman than I believe Seneca ‘Was. - . . . Tºft. Ay, and a better Chriſtian too, or woebe to him. . But truly I ſee greatwautonneſs eveninyourſelf forſooth," the very Cook debauchesyou.-- Hof. How?

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 5

—--— - - - - --- Or, it cannot Be. 5 Hot. How? call the Cook –Cook —Cook'— Leo. The Cook debauch me,8irrah? - -- Teſt. I mean by pampring you, Morning, Noon, and Night with one wanton kickſhaw or another.— . ‘. . . . ; Pºo. You Coxcomb. - Leo. Sot. Hot. Raſcal, I thought the Cook had layn with my Couſin– Sirrah, you deſerve to have your bones broke. Well Sirrah, ſince you find my Lords Table is too luſty, Ple have it guelded ; I'le make you keep Lewt, and faſt Wednesdays and Fridays. Tºft. I will not, I abhor it, 'tis Popery. * Hot. Then you ſhall faſt Tueſdays and Thursdays. Tºft. And then the Family will ſlander me, and ſay I do it out o' con- tradićtion,- I will not do it, I do not love to grieve the weak. Hot. To grieve the ſtrong thou mean'ſt, thy own ſtrong ſtomack. Tºft. You are offenſive. - Hot. I will be more. I will watch you Sirrah, and know why my Lord feeds ſuch Raſcals. . - Tºft. I tarry not for his feeding, the Family is a ſad Family, and I tarry out of pure Bowels. - - Hot. Out of empty Bowels, which you have a mind to fill, and it may be youmay fill other empty bellys, I mean among the Wenches, ſome of you Godly Rogues play ſuch tricks ſome times. I’le watch you Sirrah. (Exit.' Tºft. And I’le watch you, my Spirit riſes at this Man exceedingly. (Exit. Vio. Theſe are a pleaſant Couple. Leo. Is not my Brother politick? Theſe are to ſee no Proviſions forwan- tonneſs be conveigh’d to mc from abroad, and be ſure they will not agree to deceive him. And that I may have none at home, My Brother will not venture a handſome Servant in the houſe ; he ſwears he will not be Brother in Law to ere a Butler or Footman in England; and he has cull'd for his Family, the moſt choicepeices of deformity he cou’d find in the Nation. I believe they are nowaltogether in the Pantry, and my Aunt among 'em -- * diſtributing their Breakfaſts—the Monſters will be worth ſeeing— open the Door. . . . . / Tº sºuri, drawn, and, company of crºwd, mitira, ill-look'd Fellows are at b º, },and Aunt with them. Amt. How now? who open'd the Door without my leave? Neice, this is one o' your Girliſh tricks, will you always be a Child Will you never learn ſtaidneſs andgravity, norwithſtanding the perpetual Counſel you have from me,the perpetual diſpleaſure I ſhew at all ſort of youthful Fol- lies; do not you know how I hate impertinent Youth P - - Leo. Or any ſort o' youth to my knowledge. . . . (aftas.) Au Do not I always tellygühow fine a thing it is to be Grave; that Youth with Gravity is very paſſable, and almoſteſteem'd equal with years? very wiſe Perſons will not be aſham'd to match with Grave Youth; daily experience ſhewsit, and will you never leave? Fye—fye— ſye—i
Page 6

-- - - - - - - - ** º -- learn o’ this Lady ? - & - Sir Courtly Nice: would not for the World any Wiſe Sober Perſon o' Quality that has an In- clination for you, ſhou'd ha’ ſeen this rudeneſs in you, to Expoſe your . Aunt in this manner, in her undreſs; it might ha' created in him an aver- ſion for you. - - - - * - Leo. An averſion to me, to ſee your ill dreſs (aſide.) Au. Madam, I hope you’l pardon the liberty I take in your preſence. -Vio. Oh good Madam. - - - - Au. Oh I Madam pardon me I know I commit a Soleciſm in good Manners, but you are a Lady that has a great deal o' goodneſs, and a great deal o' worth--- Vio. Oh! ſweet Madam : — - Au. Oh! Madam! our Family has found it—you are pleas'd to Ho- nour us with your Friendſhip. . We may venture to expoſe our Frailties before you, Madam, you’l be ſo good to pardon Madam Wío. Oh Madam : Au. Well really Madam—I wonder where my Neice learns her wan- tonneſs, we are the moſt reſerv’d Family in the World. There were Four- teen Siſters of us, and not one of us married. - . Pio. I'ſ poſſible? - Leo. To your great grief—— (aſide. , Au. We were all ſo reſerv’d. Oh J Madam! no Man durſt preſume to think of us ; – I never had three love Letters ſent to me in my whole life. Vio. Oh! ſtrange | Au. Oh! we were very reſerv’d. Well Madam I am very much out o' Countenance to appear thus before you. Vio. Oh J. Madam, everything becomes you Madam. . Au, Oh! you are very obliging Madam. Do you hear Neece— Leo. To flatter you. -- (aſide. Au. Madam I am extream unfortunate, the affairso the Family call me away from your ſweet Converſation. - Vio. the misfortune is mine, Madam. Au. Oh! ſweet Madam your moſt humble Servant. - sº Vio. Your humbler Servant dear Madam. Ha! ha ha / what ſ Exit . ridiculous peice of Antiquity is this Thy Brother has a great Ho-R Aunt, nour for his Family ſince he will keep ſuch a relick of his Anceſtors ** - - - - - - as this. - - . . Leo. All the houſe is of a piece. Vio. Nay if thou learn'ſt lewdneſs, at home, thou haſt, a great Genius to 10 . . . - ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Leo. Well, what do you think of my condition?... . Vio. I like it. . . .. - - - Leo. Like it ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . -- Vio. Ay, for Iperceive your Brother has put the whole force of his Wit into this Form of Government; now if we can baffle it, he will find it is a dream fit for nothing but Utopia ; and never torment himſelf and his Friends with it any more, then he’l be a faultleſ, Creature, and all of us hap. py in our Loves. Here he comes. . . . . . . . - - - - - - - - - - - * * . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ; * Enter
Page 7

0r it camot Be. 7. Enter Lord Bellguard. * Your Servant good my Lord. - - Bell. Your moſthumble Servant Madam. - . Leo. My Lord, why do you call him Lord * he's a Dočtor and curing me o’ the Palpitation o’ the heart, Falling-ſickneſs, Convulſions in the Eyes, and other ſuch Diſtempers. - - - - - - , - Vio, A Dočtor? a Quack by his falſe Medecines; ſhortly we ſhall ſee him mount the Stage, or ſtandat the Old—Exchange and cry a Cure for your Horns, a Cure for your Horns. . . . . . , Ball. I’m glad to ſee you ſo pleaſant Madam. Pio. How can I otherwiſe chuſe my Lord, and ſee your Family and Government 2 - - . . . . . Bell. Faith, Madam he that will have a Garden muſt incloſe it, and cover tender Plants : This is a very blaſting age to Vertue, 'twill not thrive with- out a covering. - - - - - -- Vio. Ay, but my Lord, you force your ground too much, what Horns - \- wou’d not grow in your Soyle? When wou'd not your Forehead ſprout? . Were Iyour Wife and thus kept, Iſhou’d ſpread like a Vine, and all the Walls in England wou'd not hold me. • . . . Bell. I’m not o' that opinion, Madam. - - - Vio. Why ſhou'd youthink better o' me than your Siſter 2 Bell. I judge very well of her, but muſt ſpeak freely I think few Women may be truſted in this life, this World is, and ever was a great brothel; where? or with whom may a Woman be truſted? with ancient Ladies; they are the chief Beauty Merchants, venders of fine Love. . . . - Leo. Ladies o’ that Profeſſion. - - . - Bell. Oh the moſt excellent, and moſt in Employ. Pedling Wo- men cry Scotch Cloath of a groat a yard, ſtuff only fit for Footmen. But wou'd you have fine Beauty, Choice of Beauty, and with eaſe Security and Decency, go to your Lady Merchants ; in Common houſes the work is manag’d as ſlovenly as Religion in Conventicles, enough to put one out of - lag y 3. g p - - conceit with it; but in Brothels o' Quality,. Iniquity is carried on with that venerable order wou'd intice any one to Devotion. - Vio. Fye fye! • * * . . " - - - - - - - Bell. And with that ſecurity. A Man may there enjoy a Lady whilſt her Husband holds her Cards. - Deo, And ſhall the Lady o’ the houſe know o' theſe things Bell. And manage’em too ; break the Lady to the Lovers hands; that’s the advantage o’ Quality, if a young Lady has not a natural amble, a poor Bawd cannot have acceſs to teach her. - Vio. What can a Lady of Quality propound by ſuch doings? Bell. Oh! many things. As Preſents; and Pleaſures. She has her houſe full of good Company, her Ears full of wanton Stories; her Eye full of tempting Sights, and now and then her Lips get a cloſe kiſs. Oh! Madam do you think it does not warm an Elderly Lady's blood, to have a brisk- young Spark always by her ſide 2 heisher Liquour of life, and though ſhe. never gets a full draught, a taſt chears her heart. - - - - Leo, Who
Page 8

8 Sir tourtly Nice: up Leo. Who are theſe Ladies? where do they live - - Bell. Oh you’d feign be acquainted with 'em no ſuch matter ; and , yet I’le tell you where they live. Leo. Where 2 - Bell. Almoſt every where; where there is an Amorous Aunt, or over-in- dulgent Mother. - ... • Leo. Mothers? will Mothers corrupt their Daughters? - Bell, Ay, or iſ they wont Daughters will corrupt their Mothers. Things are ſo inverted, that Ladies who were honeſt all their Youth to be like their Mothers, turnlew’d in their old Age to be like their Daughters. There never was ſuch an open and general War made on Virtue; young ones of Thirteen will pickeere at it, and by that time they are twenty, they are riſen to be Strumpets General, and march in publick with their *#. with Miſs, and Maſs, and Nurſe and Maid, and a whole train o ſinners, expesting the next Cully that falls. . r Wis. You talk of paltry huſſes. Bell. Very good Gentlewomen. Leo. Gentlewomen o' thoſe employments. Bell. Ay, purchaſe 'em. I have known a fairyoung Lady give all her Fortune to attend a Man o' Quality in his Bed-Chamber; be his chief Gen- tlewoman. -- - - Leo. Suppoſe fo, what's all this to me? If they be bad muſt I be ſo Bell. Truly Siſter, a rambling Womanlether be never ſo good a mana- ger, will be apt to bring her Vertue as a Traveller does his Money, from a Broad peice to a braſs É.i. But ſay ſhe does not, is reputation no- thing? and let metell you, Reputation will hang looſe upon a galloping eformade - Lady; you may as well go among high Winds and not be ruffled,as among Men and not have your good Name blown over your Ears. Vio. Thoſe Winds blow where they liſt. A Woman is not ſecue rat home from Cenſure. Bell. But you muſt allow a Jewelis not ſo ſafe in a Crow'd as when lock'd I, Lockd up do youthink to lock me up Bell. I think toſecure thee, my dear Siſter. Women like Cheney ſhou’d be kept with care, º' * One flaw debaſt's her to common Ware. [Exit.j A CT II.
Page 9

Or, it cannot Be. - 9 , - … …' . . . . . . . . " tº - . . . K . . . - - -- • * * - • * : * ~ * ~ *º . . . . A c T II. - ** -- - - - - Scene Violante's houſe. Enter Violante and a \ - Servant. . . . : Vio. TS Mr. Farewelcoming? ‘. . . Ser. Yes Madam, he's juſt at the Door. ...Vio. That's well, if this brisk young Fellow, has but Love enough to undertake this work, and Wit enough to gothrough with it, we ſhall all be happy. • ppy Enter Farewel. ' Fa. Where's your Lady ? Madam, your moſt humble Servant. Vio. Your Servant Mr. Farewel; you are a happy Man, young, rich, and in the Ladies Favours. - Fa. I’m glad to hear that, Madam; who are theſe Ladies Madam, 2 a day, and hour of Youth and good Fortune is precious; and Ladies like Birds muſt be aim'dat whilſt they hop aboutus, miſs that opportunity you nay looſe 'em for ever... Therefore the Ladies, good Madam, quick, quick, for if you deferbut half an hour, they’l bein love with ſome body elſe. Vio. No Mr. Farewel, there is one *: more Conſtant, you’l own it when I name her; my Lord Belgaard's delicate young Siſter. What ſay you to her Fa. I adore her. Pio. And dare you attempt her ? Fa. Dare I? - Vio. Ay, for do not you know you are the only Man forbidden her. - Fa. Do I know of what Race I am, Madam? Never was ſuch a pack of Fops as my Lord Belguard’s Anceſtors and mine. . They lov’d wrangling more than we do ". kept Lawyers inſtead o' Wenches, and begot upon their bodies, a thouſand illegitimate Law Suits, the Terms they ob- ſerv’d as duly as the River does the Tydes, and Land was carried too and frow, as mudis in the Thames. Nor were their quarrels ſo bitter about Land, as place; ſo big were their great hearts, they cou’d not come into one Room together, for fear of looſing place. My Lord Belguard's Father to end the difference, moſt piouſly endeavoursto be a better Man than any of his Anceſtors. That is to ſay a Lord. - , Wio. And then the ſtrife ended ? - -- " Fa, Was more enflam'd. For my Lord was more inſolent, as having Authority under the Broad Seal to be proud, by Conſequence my Father more enrag’d; and both the old Gentlemen contended who ſhou’d have the greateſt "Eſtate in malice, and attain'd to be very conſiderable, and ". - - ‘C they
Page 10

IO Sir €ourtly Nice: - they dyed, endeavourd, to ſettle it allupon us. But truly the young La- dy and I moſt prodigally conſum’d all our Portions at one look,and agreed to cut of the wicked Eatail. . . --- • Wºo. You did well, but how will you accompliſh your deſires 2 her Brother has ſuch guards upon her. - Fa: Oh! 'tis Decreed: nor ſhall thy Fate oh! Brother reſiſt my vow, though Guards were ſeton Guards, till their confounded Coxcombs reach'd the Skies, I'd or'e 'em all— . . . . . Vio. You are in a Rapture. Fa. Ten thouſand when ever I think of her. Jºio. But how will you do this? - - Fa. I have leagu'd with a Witch; at leaſt a young Fellow that has more tricks than a Witch; he was a poor Scholler at Oxford, but expelrd for ſtudying the Black Arts. Vio. For Conjuring 7 Fa. Yes, Madam, not only any Mans Pigs or Poultry, but Wife or Daughterinto his Chamber. Nothing cou’dſcape him, and he ſcap'd every thing. The Proëtors watch'd more diligently for him, then a Benefice, and cou’d never catch him. The Grave Doctors abhor’d him worſe than a Haereſie, and ſtudyed more to keep him out of their Families, but he con- futed their Skill, and they cou’d no more light upon him than on, a , teſt. - - Pio. Ilong to ſehim. Fa, Iordered him to come hither to me. Entera Servant. Sir Here's one Mr crack enquires for you, Sir. Fa. That's he—bring him in. Enter-Cracks. Mr. Crack your Servant. - Cr. Your Servant Sir, your humble Servant, Madam. - - Wio. Your Servant Sir, I am told you ha’ been an Oxford Scholler. Cr. A. Scholler Madam? a Schollers Egg— emptyed by old ſuck- Eggs, of all that Nature gave me, and crumbled full of Eſſences, Hypo- ſtaſes, and other ſtuff o' their baking. º Pio. Why did not you apply yourſelf to Divinity? Cr. Leave Wenches for Pigs, Madam;’tis true Imay Wench then toe, but it muſt be with Fear and Reverence, I hate that. . - - Pio. Why wou'd not you be a Phyſician * - Cr, A Gold-finder Madam? look into Jakes forbits o' money? H. had a Spirit above it. I had an ambition to be of ſome honourable profeſſion; . ſuch as People of Quality undertake. As for inſtance, Pimping. A Pimp is as much above a 'Dočtor, as a Cook is above a Scullion; when a Pimp has foul’d a Diſh, a Dočtor ſcours it. Vio. This is an arch Blade, Čr. Oh! w

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 11

Or, it cannot Be. 11 - r. ch?you are pºwd toſyſ, Madam 'impreyour goºdnºthin my deſert. ...” -- - Fa. Well Mr. Crack, you know what you have undertaken. Cr. Ple do't—The Lady's yours. Give me ſome Mony. Fa. There, there. - Cr. Gold: thou Sono’ the Sun, and Brother o' the Stars, Nutmeg & comfort, and Roſe of delight, as my Friend the King o' Perſia call’s him- ſelf, what can’ſ thou not do great Prince, if I be thy chief Mini- ſter?— - - t (Exit.) Vio. This is a notable Fellow, our next Plot muſt be toſecure your Rival Sr. Courtly Nice. - - Fa. Hang him, he ſecnre's himſelf by his Foppery’s, ſhe deſpiſes him. Vio. Not many Lady’s do ſo. -- Fa. Oh! no, Madam,he's the General Guitarreo’ the Town, inlay'd with every thing Women fancy ; Gaytry, Gallantry , Delicacy, Nicety, Courteſy. - Pio. And pray, put in Gold too. Fa. True Madam, Oh! the Ladies love to have him in their Chambers, and play themſelves aſleep with him. - - * ~ * Vio. Well, I have provided one ſhall thrumble on him. Fa. Who’s that 2 - - Vio. Surley. - - Fa, Oh! Fire and Water are not ſo contrary, Sr. Courtly is ſo civil a Creature, and ſo reſpectful to every thing belongs to a Gentleman, he ſtand's bare to his own Perewig. , Surly uncovers to nothing but his own Night- cap, nor to that if hebedrunk, for he ſleeps in his Hat, Sr. Courtly is ſo #. Creature, he writes a challenge in the file of a Billet-doux. Sur- ley talks to his Miſtreſs, as he wou'd to a Heółor that wins his Mony. Sr. Courtly is ſo pleas'd with his own Perſon, his daily contemplation, may his Salvation is a Lookinglaſs, for there he finds Eternal happyneſs. Surley's Heaven at leaſt, his Prieſt is his Claret Glaſs; for to that he confeſſes all his Sins, and fromit receives Abſolution and Comfort. But his damnation is a Looking glaſs, for there he finds an Eternal fire in his Noſe. In ſhort if you wou'd make a Poſſet for the Devil, mingle theſe two, for there never was ſo ſweet a thing as Sr. Courtley, ſo ſower as Surley. But how will you get ’em together? for nothing has power over Surley, but Claret and the Devil. Pio. Yes I have. Heaven is pleas'd to think the Devil himſelf has not miſchief enough to plague that ill-natur'd Rogue, and joyns me in Com- miſſion with him to torment him with Love; he loves me. Fa. Love? can he love? - Vio. Somuch, he negle&ts his Claret for me; and comes hither hourly to perform his Devotions to me, but in ſuch a ſlovenly manner; 'tis ſuch a Non-Conformiſt to all decent Ceremonics. Surley N.Where's your Miſtreſs within. - L Vio. Ibear him, we'l haſ ſport with him. He abhorshi, Loveworſe than - -C 2. Murder .
Page 12

12 Sir Courtly Nice : - Murder or Treaſon, for thoſe are miſchiefs to others, but Love he accounts : High-Treaſon againſt his own damnable Perſon; and he's more aſham'dofit, than he wou’d be of a Beaſts Taile if it grew out of him. Therefore Ple \conceal, and do you charge him with it, you ſhall hear how he’l renounce , { ! C. ! £ºt, then will I appear like Conſcience to a ſick debauch, and you ſhall ſee - (1 C ºf 3. whatan aukard Penitent Ple make him. --- (Ex.. __--- - - -* - - . . . . . Enter Surly... . Ea. Honeſt Surly, how do'ſ do 2. . . . . . Sur. Prethee look in my Water. . Fa. In thy Water 2: - Sur. Ay, for I don't love to anſwer impertinent queſtions, Fa. Is it impertinent to enquire after the health of a Friend? - Sur. A Friend?-thy talkis more boyiſh than thy Face. Doºſt thouthink . | there are ſuch Friends? thou believ'ſt there are Mair-maids and Centaures a/rº- I warrant; for ſuch Friends. Monſters that grow to ſome other Beaſts, and are the leaſt parto’ themſelves? - - l Fa. Why? haſt thou no concern for any Beaſts but thy ſelf? . Sur. Yes Bird, for manythings formy own ſake; for Witty Men whil’ſ they drink with me, handſome Whores whilºſt, they lye with me, Dogs, ~ Horſes or Cattle whil’ſ they belong to me; after that, I care not if the Wits behang'd, the Whores be pox'd, and all the Cattle bewitch'd. Fa. A very generous temper... - ... " Sur. 'Tis a wiſe and honeſt temper. The pretended good nature is ill nature; it makes a Man an Aſs to others he bears their Burden, a Rogue to - himſelf, he cheats himſelfoſ his quiet and Fortune. I am ſo very honeſt to my ſelf, if the whole World were hang'd it ſhou’d not rob me of a Minutes caſe, I thank Heaven for it. Fa. Was ever ſuch a Barbarian - Sur. Thou'rt an Aſs; which is the Barbarian, he that eats Man, or the Man that's eaten ? The Rogue that grieves away my Fleſh eats me, and is a . Barbarian; ſo is hethat with vexation gnawes himſelf; I am no ſuch Can-- nibal. . . . . . . - - - Fa. Haſt thou no compaſſion? " Sur, I know not what it is. . Fa. Suppoſe you ſee a Man o' Quality in miſery. Sur. Let him bein miſery and be damn'd. Fa. Are you not concern’d for his Quality? . . . ... Sur. The leſs for that, becauſe if he fancies the whimſey, he has it to pleaſe him. - - Fa. To trouble him. - * Sur. Then to comfort him I’le tell him he's the Son of a Whore, and his... Grandfather roſe by Pimping. Fa. Suppoſe you ſaw a Man o' partsumfortunate? Sur. Let his parts look after him. , - !. Fa. They’l afflićt him. - - Sur. Then to quiet him I’le tell him he's an Aſs. - Fá. Have -- -
Page 13

• -- - f - Or, it cannot Be. I 3 Fa. Have you no charity? doyounever give anythingtothe Poor? Sár. As much as any Man. - Fa. What's that P Sur. Nothing. Fa. Does no Man give anything? -- - - - Sur. Not to the Poor; they give it to themſelves; ſome Fools have Di- feaſes in their Natures, they never ſee anyone in pain, but they feel halfon’t, , and ſo they give money to eaſe themſelves. - º Fa, Ha’you no love for anything 3 Sur. I have Appetite. : - Fa. Have you no love for Women? . - - Sur. I ha” Luſt. * - Fa. No Love? ..' - - - - Sur. That's the ſamething, the word Love is a Fig-Leaf to cover the na-- ked ſeace, a faſhion brought up by Eve,the Mother of Jilts,ſhe Cuckolded her . Husband with the Serpent then pretendedto modeſty and fell a making Plác- kets preſently. And her Daughters take up the Trade, you may import what Lewdneſs you will into their Common-wealth, if you will waſhit over with , ſome fine Nmae.You may proclaimeatMercat-croſs,how great an Adorer you. are of ſuch a Womans Charms ? how much you deſire to be admitted into her Service; that is,how luſty a Centaur you are, that the Horſe in youis much the major part,and ſhe ſhall receive all this without a bluſh, whil'ſ the Beaſt trots to her under the Name of Lover; when if ſhe had any Wit ſhe'd know, a Lover is a more impudent Name than. Whoremaſter; for a Whoremaſter throws all his Bombes at a whole City, your Lover waſts, all his upon a fingle Houſe. That when a Woman deſires a Lover, ſhe deſirestohave the whole Brute to her ſelf. . . . - Fa. Ha 1 ha º haſ Sur. What do you laugh at Sir? - - Fa. Only that your Miſtreſs has heard your learned Diſcourſes Sir Pray appear Madam, and own you have loſt your Wager, is hea Lover or no? z r - - Enter Violante. . - Sar. Here's a young Treacherous Rogue. - - Wło. Yes—a Brutal one are theſe your Sentiments of Love Sir 2 was it this you meant when you talk’d of Love 2 when we grow Lovers do we degenerate into Brutes? I thought there was a generous Paſſion, of which a Beaſt cou’d have no more ſence, than he has of Muſick or Poetry. And to ſuch Love you pretended Sir. . . - Sur. I’le whedle her, - • (aftaleto Fa.) : So I do ſtill Madam, but why muſt I let a Boy Catechiſe me? I have that Muſical, Poetical, Fantaſtical love, you ſpeak of, and a pox on me for it; you’l neither be my Slipper, nor my Shooe, my Wench to ſlip on and of at ~ pleaſure, nor my Wife,that is a Whore buckledon. * , w Wid. You are charming in your expreſſions. . . . . > Fa. Mr. Surly, Madam, is a miſtical peice, to be underſtoodlike a Prophe- - cy, where Rams and He-Goats ſtand for Kings and Princes, Mr. Surly's. … …-- w

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 14

ºf 4 ~ Sir courtly Nice: º, No, no, they fignifieśń own filthy meaning.º.º.º.º. "- has no otherſence, in this corrupt Age. Nº" ifa Woman by bluſhes or otherwiſe, confeſſes ſhe thinks a Maº, afine Gentleman, he to requite her ſends her preſently a Libelcall'd a Billet-doux, where hein fine words tells he to her face, he thinks her a Wench, and invites her tolye with him. Thirunsailconverſation, Men are always driving their brutal appetites to the Plays, the Court, to Church, like Drovers their Beaſtstoevery Market; and * no converſing with 'em, unleſs you’ltake their Cattel of their hands. . - - * - - - sur. Madam, Ilove you! in you.” faſhion,admire you, adore you, and the devil and all, what woºd you have? - Now will this ſimple Jade believe me? - - Fa. He calls you ſimple Jade, Madam, and ſay's you’l believe aſide to him. . . . . . ...! - . . . . ... ºli Fare. sur. You Malapert Boy, why do you meddle in my buſineſs? Fa. 'Tis my buſineſs, ſhe's my Friend, and I wont ſee her abus’d. Sur. A Friend to the Woman loves your Enemy, Tom Fool? - Fa. No, ſhe hates him, and has quarrel'd with him, and I wou'd ha’ had you ſtep into his room. tº . . . Sur. Oh! hoſ ºr tº ... Nºw who's the Tom Fool? - sur. I am, look you Madam, that Rogue deſpayr made me talk like an Aſs, and I am ſorry for it: - - - jº. I knowyou are Sir, Iknow yºu! baſe deſire is (for your puniſhment; confind to my Eyes, and Ple uº" as you deſerve. . . Fa. Come, Madam,let me interpoſe; thoughye; will not receive Mr. Sur- ly as a half Horſe, you mayº. whole AG, a Drudge; you know you have $uſineſ; moſt agreeabletohiºl Nature, pray employ him. ~. º: well, He make tryal of him, 79* pretend you love me Genº rouily. - - - - - - - `sºr. Yes, and Damnably. , , , : , - #. Knºw heamy Lorá Belguerº." (as Ihave of late perceiv'd) ſunk withºofine Age, into baſeoPiº of Love and Women, that I am angry lever had a good thought of him. - - * - --- Sur. Good. -- - - rio. Look upon his addreſs to me, as an affront, and will re- Sur. Better andbetter. . . . ." . . . . Pao. Andyou ſhall do it. º ºr " ' ". . . Sur. Beſt of all. . . . . . . . - Vio. Do not you know Sir Courth Nice ? ... - •. - Sur. That you ſhou'd joyn ºteige with ſuch a Foº tish queſtion to be put to a º ? I may know Philoſophy, but tº aska Martif he knows a Horn-Book? for ſuch .# isthis Fop; guilded on theout fide, on the inſide, the CriſsCroſsrow.” always hanging . the Girdle of a Girl. i. ; You have deſcrib'd him right. This Föphasmy Lord Belguarden- tied to accept his siſter with no Fortune, but her Birth and Beauty. Now - - at a –W--L- *Nº. "...º be to me the moſt amiable Creature in the - ºf-___ ºn-
Page 15

- Or, it cannot Be. 15. Sur. Or the moſt damnable, if you filt me. . . Pio. In earneſt of a farther favour here's my hand. I Sur. There's the Devil in it. Tistransforming my ſhape, I am growin a Womans Aſs, I feel the Ears prick out o' my ſkin already; .# I mu hoof it away with her load of Folly upon my back, Well I am thy Aſs at preſent, but if thou Jilts me, I will be thy Devil. - (Exit.) vio. 'Tis the fitteſt Office for thee; thou art ſo like, one already, you may paſs for Twins. Now Mr. Farewellet’s go in and Laugh. (Exit.) Scene Lord Belguards Houſ. Enter Hot-head and Teſtimony. Tºft. He ſhall not ſpeak with her, I dont appfove of it. . Hot. You approve Sirrah what ha” you to do?’ Tºft. I have Authority. - - Hot. You Authority ? Teſt. Yes, from my Lord. º - - - Hot. You had it then out of his Kitchin, Sirrah; the Beefo' the Nation breeds all the Maggots in the Peoples heads. I am ſometimes tempted to throw down their Porridge-pots, and ſpill the Divine ...” Ia ſhort my Lord is a man of honour, and you have belyed him,Sirrah. - Teſt. It is well known I make a Conſcience. : . Hot. Ay, you Rogues making o’Conſciences is a great trade among your Party, and you deſerve to looſe your Ears for it. Teft. I mean I keep a Conſcience. - – - * Hot. Y’ave reaſon Sirrah, it keeps you; but that an honeſt Lord ſhould give money for a Rogues falſe Conſcience.—Oones?— Taft. Well but dont ſwear. - - - Hot. Sirrah, who ſwears Pº – Tºft. Dee hear? don’t ſwear I ſay. Hot. Oones! Sirrah, don't preach to me. Teft. Don’t ſwear then. . . . . . . . . . Hat. Sirrah, if you preach to me, I'le cut your Pate. . - Tºft. Had I a Sword’ºwere more than you cou’d do. . . . . . . . * Hot. How now Sirrah ... (takes Teſt. by the throat.) Tºft. Nay but don't throttle me, don't Godfrey me. . . . Enter Aunt Aunt. What's the noyſe? what's the rudeneſs, Couſin Hot-head? you a Gentleman, and make a Bear-Garden of a Perſons of Honours houſe? Hot. Better make a Bear-garden of it than a Conventicle ; here's a Fana- tick Rogue ordain’d ruling elder o'th. Family by my Lord, as the Rogue ſys, ſo he undertakes to govern and Preach. Au. And you undertake to Govern and correół ż Couſin no body Go- verns here but I ; if he had committed faults, you ſhou’d have brought him Before me.’ - - Hot. Oh+ you’d have him enter'd in yº. Office? Ah, What do you mean?"obſcenely? you are confident You are *. firſt
Page 16

16 Sir Courtly Wice: - - - ; * Gentleman that offer'd to ſay a wanton thing to me. . . . . . . - Hot. To your great ſorrow, .. - , , (aſide. Enter Leonora. * Leo. What's the quarrel here? Hot. There's a Taylor wou'd fain ſpeak with you. Leo. All this noyſe to introduce a Taylor 2 - " . . Hot. He can't get through this Fellows narrow Conſcience, yet there is room for a whole Common-wealth. - Au. Call in the Taylor; there muſt no Cloaths be made without my •r. dets, that I may ſee 'em modeſ. - Leo. A Taylor PI order'd no Taylor. - , , (aftile.) Enter Crack - - Au. How now, Sir f what are you? - Cr. A Taylor, Madam. - Au. Who ſent you? I know you not. Cr. Your own Taylor, Mr. Stitch, Madam. Au. How chance he came not himſelf 2 Cr. He's ſick, Madam. - - Au. And canyou work well, for we are very hard to pleaſe? There's ſcarce a Taylor in Town can make me endure to ſee my ſelf. Leo. The fault lyesin Fifty—Fifty—. (aſide). Cr. Indeed Madam,I muſt needs ſay my Country men are not the beſt Tay. lors in the World. This is a fine Nation, and all ſpoyl'd by the Taylors. Heaven makes the Women Angels, and Taylors make 'em Hedg-hogs; 'tis a ſad fight to ſee 'em, now I’le make an Angel of a crooked Pin. Au. Ay, where did you learn your Skill & - Cr. In France, Madam. - Teſt. In France? then Friend I believe you area Papiſt. Hot. Sirrah, I believe you are a Presbyterian. . . . . . Zeft. Friend, if you be a Papiſtl’ieha' you before a Juſtice. " Hot. Sirrah, if you be a Presbyterian, I’le kick you down Stairs. Teſt. What are you Friend? -- . . . Hot. Ay, what are you Sirrah 3 - Cr. What am I? why, I'm a Taylor, I think the Men are mad. Au, Intolerable; Mr. Tºftimony pray leave us, and Couſin Hot-head, I ſhall deſire the ſame of you, unleſs you’l behave your ſelf like a Gentle- IIIan. - Hot. I will behave my ſelf like a Gentleman, for Ple know of my Lord when he comes home, if he has given this Rogue Authority over me; if he has I’le demand Satisfaction of him; if he be innocent woe be to your prick- ears, Sirrah. , . . . . Teſt. I fear you not. - - . . . (Exit Hot.) Au, Mr. Teſtimony, Ionce more deſire you'l give us liberty. Tºft, Yes, Forſooth, Idare truſt the young Gentlewoman with you, For- ſooth
Page 17

0r, it cannot Be. 17 ſooth—you are a grave—Gentlewoman and in years.--For- ſooth. : . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Au. In years, rude Clown.— . . - --- Taft. And truly ſhe's a very pretty ſweet Woman, and deſerves to have great care taken of her. - Leo. Well Sir, we’l excuſe the care at this time— , - Tºft. Pretty Woman— - - - - - (aſide. . Leo. Pray leave us - - - . Teſt. Sweet Woman I profeſsſhe's ſtrangely alluring, I had beſt retire leaſt Ifall into frailty, and be diſcovered. (Exit. Cr. Now, Madam, before I take meaſure of you, I'l ſhew you ſome Patterns—pleaſe you to look upon ſome Madam, you have judg- ment—. . . . . . . . ' ' tº . . . " (to the Aunt. Au. Let me ſee. “. . . . . . . - - - - Cr. To you, Madam, I wou'd recommend this peice. - - - - Leo. Mr. Farewel's Pićture? oh! I Sirrah! now I gueſ; thee--my Dear--- Dear (kiſſes the Pičiure. T - - - - - Cr. Have a care o' your Aunt Madam. Leo. Give it me—quick quick- Au. Theſe are pretty Silks. Cr. The beſt in France, Mdaam. where's my Siſter? - Leo. My Brother ? I hope he does not know thee. Cr. No, if he does I’m a dead Man. - -- Leo. Haſt thou no diſguiſe for fear he ſhou'd? r. Only this great pair of Spectacles. … . - * * Ihave a Letter too. (Bºard within. * -- z Enter Lord Belguard. Bill what Fellow this . . . . . . . . Leo. A Taylor. . ". . . . . . . . . . --- - - -- * Bell. Notyour Taylor. , , , , , , Au. No, he's ſick and ſent this Fellow in his Room, , ------ Bell. How comes ſuch a young Fellow to wear Spectacles 2 Cr. Young my Lord *I'm above Five and Fifty. Bell. Thou bear'ſt thy age well. Cr. Ay, every where but in my Eyes Ithank Heaven. Bell. This Fellow may be a Bawd for ought I know, Ple watch him. - - - [Exit. T * Aunt views the Patterms, Bell, ſtands behind his Siſter, and watches Cr. Cr. mean while puts his Meaſure before, and delivers her a Letter. - § wa, Madam, I perceive your Ladyſhip likes the Pattern Iſhew’d you nrit. Leo I have ſeenthe whole piece. Cr. And your Ladyſhip likes it f Leo, Oh!
Page 18

18 Sir Courtly Nice: - - Leo. Oh! very well. . . . -- . . . - Cr. I’le aſſure you, Madam, you'llike it mightily when 'tis upon you, and you have a ſweet body to workfor. I donordoubt,Madam, but to get a great 3eal o'credit and a great deal o' Cuſtome by you,among the Ladies, as ſoon as ever they ſee my work. . * - - Leo. Well let'sſee your work, and Ple ſay ſomething. Cr. That you ſhalland ſpeedily, Madam, I'le bring you home as ſweet apeice o’ Work, as ever you had in your Life. You'ſ look upon the Pat- term I ſhew'd you laſt - Zeo. Yes. - cr. That's for the inſide; do you like much Bombaſt, Madam? £eo. No-. - - Cr. Well, Madam—I ha’ taken a Surveigh o' your fine Body- now you ſhall be pleas'd according to your own hearts deſire—your Ser- vant Madam—. - - (Exit.) Bell. Well Siſter-prepare to receive a Viſit from Sr. Courtly Nice, this Afternoon. .. - - Au. Oh dear! then Imuſt dreſs. He’s a great Critick. (Exit 3 Leo. She deſigns him for her ſelf, wou'd ſhe cou’d get him. . . . (aſide. Bell, Sr. Courtly and I have agreed; pray give him your promiſe, Leo. So ſoon f 'twill be fulſome, he’s abſtemious. - Bell. Therefore take him whilºſt he has an edge. , - Leo. You uſe to deſpiſe Fools, how chance you marry amongſt 'em? . Bell. Becauſe none but Fools will marry. Wits are but few and common- ly poor; Fools are numerous and rich. Fortune is as fond of thoſe bits of Men, as Bigots are of Reliques; wraps’em in Silver. -- - Leo, Better they were buryed. A Fool in a Coach is like a Knave in a Pillory, the Objećt of publick deriffon. *. - . . Bell, Oh! there are few to deride’em, many to admire 'em, ſo many, I . have oft admired how one Apple, Shou'd ſuch Diſeaſes in old Adam breed. -- That from his Loyns not Men, but Hºms proceed. (Extumome'. . s

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 19

or, it cannot Be. 19 Act III -> → - tº: Scene, Covent-Garden-Square. Enter Farewel and Crack meeting. - - Fa: Oh! the News the News! art thou an Angelor a Devil bring'ſ thoujoys or Torments 2 - - Cr. ; !joys joys Fa. Angel! Angel ! Angel ! Cr. In the firſt place I deliver'd your Pićture. Fa. Rare. Cr. And ſhe kiſſed it. - Fa. kiſſed it? - - f Cr. Sweetly, wantonly,laſciviouſly. She ſet me ſoon fire, I kiſs'd all the Wenches as I came along, and made their moyſtlips fiz again. Fa: Oh! Rogue! Rogue! delicious Rogue. - Cr. Then I deliver'd the Letter, and before her Brothers face. Fa. Before his face 2 ha / haſ ha! - º M: Prepare this Night to be the happyeſt o' Mortals. Give meſome more On W. Fa. Mony? I'le ſell my Land rather than thou ſhalt want. That one Inheritance will purchaſe me two, onein Love, and another in laughingst this politick Brother. - Cr. No, no, Inheritances as for laughing, I believe you will have an Anui- ty for life; but for Love you'l only have a leaſe for three or four Years. Fa. Pleaſant Rogue! here's Money. - Cr. So, ſo, I wiſh you joy I wiſh youjoy. (Exit.) Fa. SeeSurly going to my Rival; my affair thrivesadmirably. (Exit.) Enter Surly. Knocks, enter a Servant. Sur. Is Nice within - - Ser. Nice Sir 2 ' ' , Sur. Ay, Nice Sir ; is not your Maſters name Nice. - * Ser. 'Tis Sir Courtly Nice. • Sur. Well Sir, if I have a mind to cliphalf his Name, ’tis not Treaſon, is it Sirrah P Ser. I believe not Sir. - Sur. Then get youin, and tellyour Maſter I’d ſpeak with him, . Ser. What ſort o’ domineering Man is this? - – , - . - h a Scene
Page 20

2O - Sir Courtly Nice: Scene, a Chamber—Sir Courly Nice dreſſing, Men and Women ſinging to him. - Sir Co. Very fine extreamly fine. Gentlemen and Ladies, will you do me the favour to walk in, and accept of a ſmall Collation ? I am in ſome haſt to dreſs upon an extraordinary, occaſion. You’l Pardon me? your ve- ry humble Servant—, , ” (Exit Muſick.) Ser. Very fine. . . . . . . .” - Sir Co. You Sot, 'twas very barbarous. Ser. Your honour ſaid 'twas very fine. | Sir Co.. You Clown, don't you know what belongs to a Gentleman? Com- plaiſance is the very thing of a Gentleman, The thing that ſhew's a Gentleman. Wherever I go, all the World cryes that's a Gentleman, my life on’t a Gentleman; and when y’ave ſaid a Gentleman, you have ſaid all. - - Ser. Is there nothingelſe Sr. belongs to a Gentleman º' - Sir Co. Yes, Bon mine, fine Hands, a Mouth well furniſh’d— Ser. With fine Language - - Sir Co., Fine Teeth, you ſot; fine Language belongs to Pedants and poor Fellows that live by their Wits. Men of Quality are above Wit. 'Tis true for our diverſion ſometimes we write, but we ne’r regard Wit. I write but I never writ any Wit. - - Ser. How then Sir P. Sir Co. I write like a Gentleman, ſoft and eaſie. - Ser. Does your Honour write any Plays 2 - | Sir Co. No, that's Mechanick, I beſtow ſome Garniture on Plays, as a Song or a Prologue. * - - - Ser. Then your Honour is only a Haberdaſher o' ſmall Wares? Sir Co. A Haberdaſher, you ſawcy Raſcal ? " - - - - Enter a Servant. 2. Ser. Here's one Mr. Surly to viſit your Honour. , Sir Co. Surly, what the Devil brings him hither ? 2. Ser. He has been walking about the Rooms this quarter of an hour, and would not let me bring him in, till he had fould'em all with his dirty Shoes. - - -- . . . . . . Sir Co. A Nauſeous, Beaſtly, Sloven, Clown, Fool, Sot. . . * . . . . ." Enter Surly. . . - - Dear Mr. Surly your moſthumble Servant. (Sir Co. Bows to receive him. Sur. What, are you unbu—buckling my Shooe? - - - (Sur. is Drunk, ſtammars and belches.) Sir Co. Dear Mr. Surly—he ſtinks horribly— aſide.) aſide.) How camel to enjoy a very Polecat This great happyneſs – pox"' foh you and I have been Z aſide.) long pianee, and I’m amaz'd to ſeevau at my levee. Swº-
Page 21

Or, it cannot Be. - 2 I - Sur. I begin tothink, thou art a good honeſt Fellow, and have a mind “we ſhou’d no longer be two lo—lo—Loggerheads, but one. - Sir Co. Dear Sir, you are always ſo Jºã. ;Well Sir, ſhall I beg a fa- vour of you? . - - . . . . Sur. What's that ? - - Sir Co. Leave to dreſs before you,Sir. I am to meet ſome fine Women to day, one preſently. - - Sur. Prethee dreſs, and be damnd ſhall wedi—dine together? . Sir. Co.. Yes Sir, I ſuppoſe, and Sup too—. *- . . . . . Sur. That's kind, well when? . . . . . . - - - Sir Co. About Five o’clock Sir. . . . , Sur. Where : - . Sir Co. In the Kings Box, Sir. - Sur. Muſt, you and I, dine in the Kings Box? * ** Sir. Co. Oh I deareſt! I beg your Pardon Ten thouſand times, I thought you ask'd me where I ſhou'd meet the Lady. Sur. Pox o'the Lady; I ask where we ſhall Dine * Sir Co. Really Sir I don’t know, I can’t put my head into one o' your beaſtly eating houſes, nor ſwallow the filthy meat you eat there, if you'd give me One hundred pound. … . . . . . . Sur. Filthy Meat P Sir I eat as good Meat as you do. Sir Co. Oh! dear Mr. Surly, no doubt the meat in its own nature may be very innocent ; but when once it has committed familiarity with the beaſtly Fiſts of Cooks and Butchers, ’tis to mean unpardonable Sinner. My Butcher cuts up all his Meat with a Fork, - Sar. Does he cut up an Ox with a Fork? - Sir Co. Ay, and he cuts up an Ox as meatly as a Lady does a Partridge. Sur. Well, then Ple accept o' thy Dinner. - Sir Co. Dear Sir, your moſt humble Servant; pox on him (aftile) I wiſh I be capable o’ the great happyneſs. For I came but laſt Night from my Country houſe, and I queſtion whether I have all things in order or no. Whoſe there? are all thingsbrought from my Country houſe? Ser. No Sir, your Butler has forgot your Salt. -- º Co. Left my Salt 2 careleſs Raſcal. Let him take Horſe imme- 13tely. . . - º Sir he's ridpoſt for it. - - Sur. Rid poſt for Salt 2 whether ? . . -- Sir Co. #. Country houſe. . . . . Sur. How far’s that off? " " ' ". . . . Sir Co. But a little way, not above Forty miles. - * Sur. Send Forty miles out o' London for Salt Is there not Salt enough in London for you? - - - Sir Co.. Ay, ſtuff pawm’d by Butlers and Waiters, they take up the Wen- ches coats, then handle the Salt. . . . . . . . . th Sur. Here's a Rogue—(aſide) well come let's drink a Glaſs o’ Wine €n. - - - - - \ Sir Co. Oh I dear Mr. Surly, if you name Wine, you make me thro tip my Soul. I have abhor'd Wine ever ſince 1 was in France, andº what . . . . . . . . aſ Oğı Q\lº
Page 22

- - - --------- “A i 22 Sir Courtly Nice: - barbarous Education they give that generous Creature. Duce take me, Sir. if the Clowns don't preſs all the Grapes with their filthy naked Feet. Oh; beaſtly naſty Dogs nowonder we are poyſon'd with their Wine. Sur. Prethee what o' that P the Wine purgesbefore it comes over. Sir Co. Oh! Lord Mr.Surly what a Phraſe is there you'l Pardon my Freedom, Sir 2 ; Moſt civil Coxcomb (aftale) well what muſt we drink, for drink I muſt? - Sir Co. I have ſeveral drinks of my own compoſing at your Service, as Mead, Syder, Ale. - " . . Sur. Ale P there's Sauce for a Woodcock. Come let's taſk a Bottle. Sir Co. Fetch a Bottle; This Fellow will Poyſon me—. (ºftd.) Sur. Well I come to requeſt a favour o' thee. - Sir Co. Your moſthumble Servant Sir, how de’c’ like this Cravat? Sur. What's that to my buſineſs f I come to make a requeſt to thee. Sir Co. Tis welltyed too, with a great deal o'humour. Sur. A Pox on thee, mind me. Sir Co. Your moſthumble Servant Sir. Sur. I am going to make Love. Sir Co. Before youdrink Sir Sur. Before I drink Sir–. Sir Co. Well Sir, ſince you’l have it ſo, I'le wait on you down ſtairs. Sur. Is the Devil in the Fellow * I tell thee I’m going to make love. Sir Co. Oh! Lord'Sir, I beg your pardona thouſand times. Sur. And Icome to beg thy aſſiſtance. g. Sir Co. Oh dear Sir. - - - Sur. For thou haſt a knack on't. Thou art the only Court Card Wo- *- up all. - , Sir Co. Oh JSir, youare ſo obliging; – and ſtinking—Pox take him. - - -- ºft.) Sur. And’tis a very pretty Woman I'm in love with ; my Lord Be guard's Siſter Leomora; thou know'ſt her. - Sir Co. The Rogue's my Rival, he was born for my confuſion (aftile.) Ay, Sir, I have the honour of ſome ſmall acquaintance there. Sur. Prethee ſpeak for me. - - Sir Co. Oh dear Sir, you have a great Talent of your own: , , Sur. But thine’s a better. One thing I am ſure thou may'ſtdo,there’s an a- bominable Fop makes Love to her, and I am told is to marry her; prethee tell him he's a Son of a Whore. º - Sir Co. Really Sir I'm unfortunate; I ha no manner o'Genius to that ſort o’ Converſation. Sur. Say my words. Tell him ifhe proceeds, I’le not only Libel him, but tweag him by the Noſe, Kick him, Cudgel him, and run him through the Guts. Prethee tell him this. (bugs Sir Co. Sir Co. Oh J pray Sir give me Ayr. - , Sur. Prethee do. Sir Co. Sir I am ready to— men loveto play with; the very Pam at Lantereloo, the Knave that picks
Page 23

Or it cannot Be. 23 Sur. And thou wilt tell the Puppy this Sir Co. I will upon my Soul. Entera Servant with Wine and Glaſſes. w Sur. Then thouart an honeſt Fellow ſo, is the drink come'? ... fill a Glaſs, why two Glaſſes? do you think I cannot drink after your Maſter? Sir Co. Pox o' your Complyment (aſide.) Sur. flings s− Sur. Here Nice, my Miſtreſſes health. ways § £, &Sir Co. What miſery is this Beaſt impoſing on me? he coughs in the Glaſs too—— w (aſide.) Sur. Poxon't,a whole gulp went the wrong way, come off with it 'Tis my Miſtreſſes health. Sir Co. This Fellows the Devil— (affide.) Sur. Off with it, Man. - - Sir. Co. I never was ſo embaraſs'd ſince I was born. Sur. Oones off with it. Sir Co. I muſt take the beaſtly portion down, but I ſhall be moſt horrible ſick after it. (drinks.) Sur. So, now thouartanhoneſt Fellow, now I’le kiſs thee. Sir Co. The Devil thou wilt? more miſeries? (aftale) may but Mr. Sury. 'Sur. I ſwear I will. Sir Co. Nay but you'l diſorder me. Sur. I ſwear I will. - Sir Co. But Sir I’m going upon your occaſions to your Miſtreſs. her. Sir Co. Oh I Hell. (aſide) may but Mr. Surly. Sur. I ſwear I will. (kiſſes him and belches—) This Bottle Beer is damn'd windy—well honeſt Nice farewell te thee. (Exit.) Sir Co. Who's there? Pmſick to death,--to death!—lead me in- get my bed ready—and a Bath—and ſome Perfumes—I'm ſick to death,--I'm dead. (Exit.) Seine Lºrd Belguard's Houſe. ... Enter Bell, with Farewel's Piłure in his hand. . Bell. Thou horrid Viſion I wou'd I had met with the worſt Fiend in Hell, ºather than thee; in theethereisa Legion exciting me to Blood-blood- Who's there? - - Enter a Servant, Str. My Lord— * My Coach—to blood—blood– * * * £ater º------. Sur. Nay then I’le give thee two kiſſes, one for thy ſelf and another fa º . -
Page 24

24 Sir Courtly Nice: Enter Leonora and Aunt, Leo. To Blood? what means my Brother? Bell. Begone. - - Leo. To whom do you ſpeak 2 . . . Au. Bleſsus ; Nephew what ailes you? - - Leo. Alas my Lord, I fear you area going to quarrel. º “… Bell. Yes, I'm going to puniſh one who Violates my Fatherºy Will w and calls my Mother Whore. - ~ / Leo. What execrable Wretch is that? - Bell. Thyſelf. - - - Leo. Me 2 * . . . . . . - - - Bell. Yes, what doſt thouelſe but proclaim our Mother falſe, when ſhe - conceiv'd a thing ſo oppoſite to allour Fathers race as thou art? Leo. In what? - - Bell. In Infamy; when was there a ſpot in our name, till Heaven for our fins ſent thee among us? and I am going to deſtroy thee in thy lewd undoer Leo. Iknow of no reproach in our Family but your madneſs, deſtroy that. What are your Spycs and Coxcombs, but ſo many Capital Letters, wherein zou write over your Door, My Siſter is a wanton Woman. Bell. "Tis truth, you are not only a wanton, but a wicked Woman; not only Intrigue, but with the Enemy of our Family, Farewel. - Au. How P - Leo. I am betray’d— (aſide. . . . . . . . . . . . , Ball. D6 you bluſh? . . . . . . :: * > Leo. At your Folly. - Bell. Dare you deny it? . . . . - - - Leo. Who dare accuſe me? - - - Bell. This Pićture, which I found in your Chamber. . Au, Horrid Creature : I ſhall ſwoon away. . . . . . . . . . . . Leo. How ſhall I bring off this (aſide) All this noiſe for a Pićture ? if you had found a littlehumane Effigies in ſwadling Clouts, there might haſ been ſome ſquawling. - - - - -- Au. Doyou laugh at your ſhame? " - - - - - - - - - Bell. She ſhall ha’ no cauſe. *-* : " ... --> * *... " --- Leo. Do, kill me, beforeyou know whether he's guilty or no. Bell. I’le know it from himſelf. If he denys it, it will be ſome revenge to make him ſtab his Soul with Lyes. He ſhall ſwear not only that he never did, but never will ſend ſo much as an Imagination . - Leo. Do, if you wou'd force him hither, what charm to a Man of ſpirit, like daring 2 Bell. She ſpeaks ſence in that....., -- *- . ... (affle) Leo. If you wou’d be fighting; fight your own jealouſe, which abuſes you worſe than Mr. Farewel can do, my Honour proteć's you, from him ; but neither Witor Honour, can guard.§. the rude inſolence of your jealouſe, which is now ſending you of an Errant, a Footmano’Spirit wou'd ſcorn, to proclaim the diſhonour of your own Siſter. Fye! Fye! Bell. And €//. All ... - º . . . . . - - - - - - - - -:
Page 25

r Or, it cannot Be. . 25 Bell, And ſo I muſt ſit down tamely with this abuſe Leo. You are not abus'd, the Pićture was found at Church. . * Au. At Church º do you intrigue at Church? . . . . Bell. They do nothing elſe, the Church is almoſt as bad as the Porch. Au. Nay there's ſhameful doings, that's the truth on't, it provokes my Fleſh to ſee how the young Men fling their Eyes about. Leo. And not upon her. (aſide.) - Au. But 'tis no marvail; when Women will encourage 'em. No Fellows dare gape upon me, becauſe Inever encourage Fellows: Leo. A Face of Fifty isſmall encouragement. (aſide) Bell. Nay no wonder the Devils cauſe thrives, he has a numerous Clergy, Heaven has but one Miniſter in the Church, and whil’ſ he is Preaching Divinity, the Devil has a thouſand of both Sexes, byall the Oratory of looks and dreſſes, preaching Fornication and Adultery. Au. Too true, well ſhe's certainly undone.I dare not examine her Breaſts, if there ſhou'd be anything in 'em, I ſhou'd dye. Leo. In my breaſts 2 - Au. Ay, Gentlewoman, do you think I regard your Flim flam ſtory o'the Church 2 - Leo. "Tis not my ſtory, my Woman found it in Weſtminſter Abby, at Prayers, and I knowing what work wou’d be made with it,commanded her to burn it, and ſhe has dar'd to diſſobey me. - Wom. Indeed,Madam, I thought to have preſented it to a Friend o' mine; andlaying it out o' my hand unfortunately in your Honours Chamber, my Lord found it. • , Bell. Oh ſhow nimbly ſhe takes the lye at the firſt rebound 2 Au. Out upon you; I’m extream ſick lead me in not you— you are not fit to touch a Woman o' my Virtue. Theſe things have ſtrange impreſſion upon me. (Exit.) Leo. That you don’t ſhare in 'em (aſide.) Bell. Pray,Siſter, go out o' my ſight, you are an horrour to me. Leo. Your own Dreams are. Y’are as madas a Prophet, you have al- ways before your Eyes a Viſion of Horns and Whores. Bell. All this goes upon the ſcore of Farewel’s heart blood if he be guil- ty, Ple make enquiry preſently, and ſearch at what gap this Treachery entred. - Leo. Oh unfortunate negligence . (aſide.) (Exit.) Enter Hothead. Bell. Who's there, Couſin Hot-head, Tºftimony ? Hot. Oh are you here? . * Bell, Ay, to yourſorrow, if you have play'd me falſe. Hot. You ha” ſerv'd me finely. . Bell. Do you firſt complain Hot. Coupled me with a Dog? E - - - Bell. But {
Page 26

26 Sir Courtly Nice : Bell. But you ha' Coupled my Siſter Sir. - Hot. With a Famatick Rogue. - Bell. No–with a finer Gentleman. Who brought this Pićture? Hot. The common Fire-fork of Rebellion. Bell. A Fire-fork-Fork me no Forks—Who brought this Pićture? Hot. The rotten rump ſhou’d ha’ been burnt when 'twas only- Roaſted. Bell. The rotten Rump Hot. Anſwer you what 2 - Bell. Who brought this Pićture? I found it in my Siſter's Chamber. Hot. Then your Fanatick Rogue conveigh’d it thither to make me ſu- ſpećted, out of his malice to the Common-Prayer. I’le cut the Rogue to peices. Anſwer me, or ille fight thee. - Enter Teſtimony with a great Sword by his ſide. Bell. Tºftimony. Yeft. I am here. Bell. How now, Sworded ? - - - - Teft. To preſerve my Life. My life is threatned by that bloody Papiſt. Hot. How, Sirrah? dare youthink of fighting me? . Teſt. Yes, and hope to do it, through Providence. - Bell. Drawing before me? (Hot. and Teſt.offer to draw) Hot. Will you protećt a Fanatick? I ſee what you are. - wa Sirrah, though I may not cut your Throat, i'le choak you . Sirrah. Tºft. De'e, hear the bloody Papiſt He'l throttle me. Hot. Sirrah, I’le cram the Oaths of Allegiance, and Supremacy into you, and they’lſtick in your Throat, though Treaſon wont, and ſo ille to a Juſtice preſently. - (Exit) - Bell. And ſtay with him, and never plague me more. Now Sir do you . reſolve my queſtion. - Teſt. I do reſolve I will not take the Oaths. Bell. I do not ask you about the Oaths. Tºft. Why, if you ask me Ten thouſand times, I will not take the Oaths. Bell. Didone ever ſee ſuch a Coxcomb 2 Teff, Call me what you pleaſe, I will not take the Oaths worſt. - (Exit.) Bell. A very fine account of my buſineſs. So do your º Enter a Servant. Ser. My Lord a Gentleman deſiresto ſpeak with your Honour. Bell. I’m not to be ſpoke with, i'm a broad—my Soul is— in the heart of Farewel, ripping it up for this Secret: What Gentleman? . Ser. One from th’ Eaſt-Indies, My Lord, he brings a Letter from your llmde-Rich. - Bell. He
Page 27

- 0r, it camot Be. 27 Bell. He comes in a Storm; he will find worſeWeather here, than any he met at Sea. Butile endeavour to compoſe my ſelf admit him. - Enter a Man dreſ like a Merchant. Man. My Lord, your Lordſhips moſt humble Servant. I perceive your Lordſhip has forgot me; you will know me better, when I acquaint you, who I am. My Father had the honour of being a Retainer to your Lord- ſhips Father, of Honourable memory ; and ſent me ſome Years ſince to the Eaſt Indies, in the Service of your Noble uncle, Mr. Rich. My name is Waytexel. Bell. Oh! Mr. Waytenuel, I am glad to ſee you, truly you are ſo chang'd, if you had not told me who you was, I ſhou’d never ha’ known you. Aſam, I believe ſo my Lord for I’m ſure you never ſaw my Face before, but the Pićture of it you have—for Waytexel was my Pi— &ture. (aſide) Time and Travels will alter a Man, but truly iHave loſt nothing by my Travels but my Countenance; and in the room have gotten what's better, a convenient ſmall competency of ſome Seven or Éight thouſand pound 3.Heaven and your uncles love be prais'd. I have brought Your Lordſhip ſome Letters from your Noble uncle, and a ſmall Preſent of ſome Threeſcore thouſand pound. * - * - Bell. How - Man. Only the trouble of it, my Lord. Your uncle contracted in th’ Indies an intimate Friendſhip with Sir Nicholas Calico, Preſident for the Eaſt India Company. Sir Nicholas dyed, and left moſt part of his Eſtate (which was near a Hundred thouſand pound,) to his only Son, Sir Thomas. But poor Sir Thomas happen'd in his Fathers Lifetime to fall into a Diſtem- per, which gave him a ſcurvy flaw in his Brain, that Sir Nicholas left him and all his Eſtate to your uncles Guardianſhip. Now your Noble uncle perceiving his affairs are like to detain him many Years in th’ Indies, and fearing if he ſhou’d dye,poor Sir Thomas might be cheated of all; he has like a Worthy and honeſt Gentleman, ſent Sir Thomas and all his Eſtate to your Lordſhips care, as theſe Letters will teſtifie, I ſuppoſe your Lordſhip is well acquainted with your uncles Hand and Seal. Bel. I am, and this is his Hand and Seal reads-um Um Ulſh – to preſerve him from being cheated here,or beg'd in England,I take the boldneſs to recommend him, to the care of ſo Noble a Perſon as your Lordſhip— um---um---um--.. Weil Sir the Letter expreſſes what you told me. Where is the Gentleman. ** Man. I brought him along with me; he's in the next room, my Lord. Poor Gentleman,he has the oddeſt Phraſes and ways with him. He will needs be attended like a great Indian Mandarine, or Lord. And has brought with him ſeveral Siamites and Bantammers, that ſerve him as his Slaves, in the ridiculous Dreſſes and Modes of their own Countries. we had ſuch a aping Rabble after us, as we came along. - - I Bell. Pray call him in, Ilong to ſee him— Man—Sir Thomaſ—pray come to my Lord. E 2 Enter
Page 28

28 Sir Courtly Nice: Enter Crack ridiculouſly dreſt, attended by Men, in the Habits of Siamites, and Bantammers, Cr. Which is the Peer? * * Mam, This is my Lord. €r. Great Peer, your extream humble Servant. Bell. Your Servant Sir, you are recommended to me, by my uncle. Cr. I knowit my Lord, and am moſtincomparably oblig'd to him—. He is a Perſon, my Lord, that as to the altitudes of Friendſhip, and the moſt- glorious Circumſtances of a Singular Perſon, is not to be caſt up by the Lo- garithmes of Oratory, nor his Latitude to be taken by the quadrangle of Circumlocution. - Bell. So I find I ſhall ha’ ſtore o” Non-ſence. - - Cr. My Lord, I'm a Perſon that asto the Circumſtances of Mony, am not. indifferently contemptible; and as to the circumſtances of Honour, I am by profeſſion a Merchant, by Generation a Knight. Sir Nicholas Calico apply- ‘ing his Perſon tomy Mother, was the Author of, Sir, Your humble Šer- Want, - Bell. So the Letter ſays. Cr. The Letter contains Verity. . . - { - Bell. Pox I ſhall be teaz'd. - Cr. One thing more'Sir, I am a Perſon that as to underſtadning,am under the circumſtances of Witchcraft. I lov’d in th’ Indies, a fair Chriſtian Curio- ſity, and a nauſeous Indian Baggage, had a mind to apply to my Perſon her Tawny Circumſtances; and findingſhe cou’d not obtain her Ambition, ap- plys her ſelf to an Indian Bawd, and Bewitches me. Bell. Pfhaw! Bewitch what ſtuffs here 2 (aſide.) Cr. Bewitches me Sir, what follow's thereupon a loathing in me of Fe- males? I abhor Women; fall into Agonys when I ſee Women. Pray let me. ſee no Women: - - . - - Bell. You ſhall not Sir. - Cr. Pray My Lord,no Women. Bell. I’le warrant you Sir. Cr. But as much Supper as you pleaſe, my Lord. Bell. You ſhall Sir. . --Cr. You are highly civiliz'd. - * - - --Man. I told Your Honour he had ſuch odd ways; well My Lord, as ſoon- as the Ship is come up the River, which will be in few days, I’le bring the Captain to wait upon Your Lordſhip, with the account of Sir Thomas his Eſtate, Aboard; which will amount to Forty thouſand pound, beſides Ten thouſand pound he has brought a ſhore in º Diamonds. So, My Lord, your very humble Servant. Sir Thomas your Servant- I leave you in goods ‘hands. . . . - - Cr. Your Servant, Sir. . . - ~ Bell. Ple order things for you, I muſt diſpoſe this Man quickly, for i'm horribly weary of him, and alſo impatient to go about my Affairs. Le T 0. 1 li º
Page 29

Or, it cannot Be. 29 Leo. Tishe--- I'm ſure’tis he (Lee, peeps) Bell. How now Siſter what’s your buſineſ; here? Leo. Staring at this ſtrange ſorto’ Man. - - . Bell. You were no Woman elſe—pray get from him ſpeedily, Leo. You are not jealous of a Mad-man ſure? he's mad is he not ? Bell. Yes, and impertinently bringsme vexation too from the Indies, at a . time when I’ve enough at home, as every Man has, that keeps a Woman. Pray get from him, he hates to ſee Women. (Exit.) Leo. Hates to ſee Women Pha ſhal Sir Thomas Calico your humble Servant, you are welcome from the Indies; but have a care of being diſco- ver'd, leaſt you be under the circumſtances of a Cudgel. Cr. Truly Madam, I expect to have ſomething ſtick by my ribs pre- ſently, that is to ſay a good Supper; which I have order'd. My Lord and I will ſup together, and you and Mr. Farewel. - Leo. We ſup together f where? in the Grave 2 a fatall accident has hap- ned, will bring us both thither My Brother has found Mr. Farewel’s Pi- Čture in my Chamber. - • Cr. He ſhall not keepit, he ſhall deliver both Pićture and jealouſie. Leo. Then thou art a Maſter. I told him my Woman found it in Weft-, minſter-Abby; may be thou may’ſ make ſomething out o' that Cr. Stay let me conſider Weſtminſter-Abby, or the Abby of Weſtminſter-- um-um-Let me alone begone—he comes, (Exit Leo.) Enter Bell. Bell. Come Sir, let me wait on you to your Chamber. Cr. Hold, my Lord, a word, I have buſineſs of great conſequence, I muſt . humbly apply to your underſtanding. . - Bell. So, I muſt behindred with more Non-ſence, (aſide.) Cr. I’ve in the Indies, a delicatepeice of my Fathers Rib, Ibeg your . Lordſhip to adviſe me in the diſpoſal. - - - º Bell. Oh I diſpoſe it how youpleaſe,Sir. º Cr. 'Tis a Siſter I mean, Sir. * . . . Bell, Oh! that's ſomething. Cr. She's ſweet and ſlender as a Clove, and is worth two Millions o' Cox-- combs---Three hundred of 'em comes to Three Farthings; 'tis a Chineſe Mo- ny. This Mony makes her much ſought in Marriage: The great Hobhom- - moscoes o' the Indies come gallopping upon Elephants, Camels, Rhinoceroſes, and Oxen to ſee her. Now my Father was under the circumſtances of great obligation, to a Gentleman in England; and out o' gratitudeto him, order- ed me on his Deathbed, to beſtow my Siſter on his Son, and Heir, if his aćtions have any ſort of ſmile in 'em to his incompatible. Father, which is the query. Pray reſolve it. Bell. Firſt let me know the Gentleman. . . . . - Cr. You ſhall, I’le #. you a Map of his Face, a Pićture contain’d in my; pocket--haſ-Iha'loſt it, “I haſ loſt it---. • . . . Bell. Tell me his Name, Sir. - s: Cr. Iha'dropt it out o' my pocket. - - Bell. I, ,
Page 30

3o Sir Cour/ly A'ice: Bell. I, but his name. . . . . . Cr. I ha” dropt it out o' my pocket. * Bell. Ha you dropt his Name out o' your pocket 2 his Name Sir Cr. Oh! his Name, I’le cell you both his Name, and Cogname. His Name is Andrew, his Cogname Farewel. - Bell. Farewel? what comes into my head P Sir can you gueſs where you might looſe this Pićture? - Cr. A gueſs may be obtain’d---by the Prayers of Marriners---. Bell. No other way? thoſe Iſeldome hearof.---- Cr I was drawn down be idle has London no place in the Weſt ? Bell. Ay, no doubt. . . Cr. Ay, but ſomething very Weſt? ſomething call’d Weſt? Bell. Yes there's Weſt-Smithfield. - Cr. That's not th' appellative. Is there no Monſter in the Weſt, call’d Weſtmonſter? - Bell, Weſtminſter I believe you mean. Cr. Y’ave nick'dit it. To Hºffminſter I rode, to behold the Glorious circumſtances o' the Dead; and diving into my pocket, to preſent the repre- . ſenter with a Gratification, I am fully confirm’d, I then loſtit; for my Eyes, and the Pićture had never any rencounter ſince. Bell. This exactly agrees with my Siſters ſtory, what a Prodigious thing. is this ; a diſcovery o' my Siſters innocence, ſent to me from th? Indies, in: heap o' Non-ſence? and in ſo Critical a minute; czcellent Providence? Cr. What's an excellent Providence, Sir, that I ha’ loſt my Pićture ? * Bell. No Sir, that I ha’ found your Pićture. Cr. Found my Pićture ? - - Bell. Ay, Sir, 'twas found by a Friend o' mine, in Weſtminſter-Abby— there it is— - Cr. Oh! my Pićture Bell. Oh! my eas'd heart : Cr. Oh my Pićture: my Pićture my pretty Pićture! - My Lord I muſt requite this favour, open that Casket, and give my Lord a handful of Diamonds. º Bell. A handful o' Diamonds. " - y Cr. Ay,my Lord, I beg your Pardon for the inconſiderableneſs o' the Preſent. : Bell. Inconſiderableneſs what a Market wou’d ſome make o’ this Man? -- put up your Diamonds. - Cr. By no means, my Lord. -- - - - Bell. Put 'em up Sir, or you'l diſſoblige me. Cr. You overwhelm me with Favours, I wiſh I had you at my houſe in Bantam. • * . . . . . . Bell. Ithank you, Sir; we are better where we are. - Cr. My Lord, you put me under the circumſtance o’ bluſhing. Bell. Pray let me put you into a Chamber, to reſt your ſelf. Cr. Reſtis good—yours humbly my Pićture —my Pićture . . . t Bell, Yours ſtaylºme ſce—remembrance begins to
Page 31

Or, it cannot Be, 31 Bel. Yours as humbly—What a Fire did I kindlein my houſe, to clear theáir of a Peſtilence, was not in it? my Siſter and all my Family are inno- cent. But what a fantaſtickthing is Womens Honour? - Whilſt She enjoy it, 'tis not ſeen or known, And yet when loft She's utterly undone. . . - - (Exeant Ommes.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 32

/ 32 St Courtly Nice; - Act. IV. The Scene continues. Enter Violante and Leonora laughing. Pºo. A ha!ha what an excellent Fellow is this what Engines he has in his head? not only to wind himſelf into my Lords houſe, but the Pićture out of his hands? Leo. He undertakes to bring Mr. Farewel hither to Night. If he en- §. to bring him in a Church with a Parſon to marry us, I wou'd not doubt it. - - Vio. Certainly my Lord muſt bein a moſt mortified humour; now is the time to ſcarify him, and takeout his Worm. - Leo. Here he comes, now will I carry myſelf with all the inſolence of a Vertuous Woman. * - Enter Lord Belguard. So my Lord, have your Slaves been gathering any more ſcatter'd ſmiles o' mine? what loads o' that Gold Sandhave your Aſſes brought home? " Bell. They have heard all, now I am aſham'd to ſhew my Face. Vio. Come, my Lord, wou'd you confine a Woman of Honour? give her Liberty; wou'd you corrupt her ? confineher. - Leo. "Tis true; were Ia Wife to ſuch a Man, I ſhou’d abuſe him out o' Pride; and think my ſelf not an ill but a great Woman, ſince to puniſh is a mark of Princely Dignity. Bell. This I confeſs is the Engliſh Dialeół ; and when Italk of Governing Women, I talk of a thing not underſtood by our Nation. I admire how it came about, that we who are of all Nations, the moſt wiſe and free in other reſpects, ſhou'd be the only Slaves and Fools to Women. - Vio. Oh! you are the Wiſeſt of all Nations, you know let Men do what they can, Women will do what they pleaſe; and whereas other Nations by their ſpyes and Governantes are at great toyle and charges to be Cuckolds, you have it for nothing. - Leo. Come Brother, do not dreſs me in a Fools Coat, nor hang ſpyes a- bout me, like ſo many gingling Bells, to give notice of all my motions. I can count, and know that one and one, put ſhamefully together, are two lewd :ools, and not one happy pair, as ill Women reckon, and deceive them- lves. Bell. Siſter, I believe you Virtuous, but I wou’d have you not only be Virtuous but thought ſo. And truly a Woman may be Virtuous, but is ſel- - dome *

Page 33

- - - –––. - - 0r, it canngºbe. - 33 dome wiſe in Mens company, Her vain honour will put her on new Con- queſts. And Womens Conqueſs are pretty things; they often end like thoſe of Highway Men, in a ſhamefuſexecution on their one Perſons. And yet all the buſineſs of their lives is muſtering up Forces. To day the Beauty Lyes ambuſh'd in undreſſes, the hairpin’d up in Papers, like Serpents coyl’d to fly on you with greater force; the Garments are looſe and flowing as the Sea, to ſhew a Venus is there. To morrow ſhe's as regularly fortified as a Low Country Town, and oft a party of Charming looks are ſent abroad to put all Speºtators under a contribution. Pio. You Wiſe muſt not dreſs? - - - - Bell. Why ſhou’d ſhe I think Womens Poynts and Embroyderies,but ſo many Billet-doux in Needlework. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . io. She muſt not go abroad or ſee a play. . . . . . . . . Bell. Yes, She may go to Plays, provided ſhe’l ſºc Plays and not Fools, - it may be enter into Converſation with 'em, and inſtead of getting Wit from the Plays, get folly from the Fops; and ſo her Wit being ſpoyl'd in her . Youth, ſhall likea Clock ſet wrong in the Morning, go falſe all the day af. ter. In ſhort, no Wife or Siſter of mine ſhall dabble in converſation with any Man ; I hate a Slattern in her credit. . . . . . (Enter Surly peeping.) Sur. I’my conſcience I think I hear Belguard and his Miſtreſs quarreſ in good earneſt. . (aſide.) . . - - - - Pio. Let no Woman marry a Man o' your humour, but ſhe that for her Crimes is condemn’d to Tranſportation. The Slave that in Virginia, toyls to planther Lord Tobacco, is not more miſèrable, than ſhe that in your bo- ſome Labours to plant a good opinion; both drudge for ſmoke. I ſcorn the ſlavery, nor will marry a King to encreaſe his Dominions, but to ſhare 'em. . . . . . . - Bell. I offer you the entire Dominion o' my ſelf; only deſire you, not to aim at further conqueſts. - Vio. I ſhou’d be a fine Soveraign, where Jealouſe, Pride, Rage, and ſuch a ſawcy Committee ſhall give me Laws; which they wou'd never do to a Prince they lov’d. - . … --- - - - Bell. I think I’ve given convinceing Proofs of Love. Vio. When 2 • * : . . Bell. When I offer'd, Madam, to take you for better and for worſe ; thoſe are Heroical Complements. The form of Matrimony out-does Ovid for paſſionate expreſſions. - - Vio. Ay, my Lord, but that's none o' your. Wit, and I wou'd not have a Man o' your Farts, ſtcal other Mens Phraſes; ſo Your Lordſhips humble Sºrvant. Come away Child - (Exit Vio, and Leo.) Enter Surly. Sur. Rare! they’r parted; once a Woman ſpoke truth. My Lord, your Servant. I’ve overheard your quarrel, and I honour you, you are the only Man in the Nation that underſtandshimſelf. Lock up the Women till they’r muſty, better they ſhou’d have a Hogo, than their Reputations. And their F Honours **.--
Page 34

34 Sir Courtly Nice: Honours are not like their Smocks, whitened by lying abroad. Bell. Nor have their ador'd Faces the more eſteem, for often appearing. Sur, pox on 'em, they varniſh like Copper, and the Women are ſenſible of it,that's thereaſon they forge new faces every time they go abroad; and all the Arts of Paint and dreſs are ſuborn'd to give a Baſtard beauty Title to Reign,becauſe the Legitimate Face is fallen into contempt by familiarity.No more to be ſaid, keep your ground like a Man of honour ; and looſe your Miſtreſs like a Coxcomb-(aſide.) (Exit) Enter a Servant. ser. An’t pleaſe your Honour, Mr. Hothead and Mr. Tºftimony,are re- turn'd, as your Honour gave order. * Easter Teſtimony. Bell. That's well—come Mr. Teſtimony; here has been a miſtake gave me a harſh opinion of you—I’m ſorry for it. Teſt. Oh! My Lord, have a care of cenſuring Profeſſors—— fora Profeſſor. Bell. Nay,prethee don't profeſs too much. I am ſatisfied with thee. Teſt. Truly you would, if you knew of what a tender Spirit I am of I. was only deluded the other day into a Play-houſe, and truly it will bea bur- den to my Spirit whilſt I live. Bell. A lack a day, well I hope you’l be the more tender of my Siſter, your trouble will not belong. I have engag’d her to a Gentleman, whom about this time I expećt. What a clock is it? Teff, Truly I do believe it is about Four, I cannot ſay it poſitively; for I. wou’d not tella Lye for the whole World. - Bell. This is an excellent Fellow, if hebe what he pretends. (knocking. Hark!ſome one at the Door maybe’tishe—ſee— - Enter Hothead. Hot Did you ſend for me, my Lord? Bell. Ay, Couſin, to reconcile my ſelf to thee; I was in a miſtake. Hot. I think you was, when you judg’d a Raſcally Famatick a better Man's than I. Bell. The contrary Couſin—I think thee ſo much the better Man, I keep thee to have an eye over him, becauſe I, don't know if he be a Knave. º Hot. Not know if a Famatick be a Knave? You’r fit to fit in the Houſe o' Peers I faith. Bell. Well, thou art a very honeſt Fellow Couſin let me have thy Company. But what are thoſe Patches on thy Face, for Ornament? Hot, they are for Plaiſters, but they are Ornaments. I have been in a Fanatick Coffee-Houſe,and this is the Beauty they gaveme. Bell. ’Twas
Page 35

Or, it cannot Be. 35 Bell. Twas to reward ſome honourable Names, thou gav'ſ 'em. Hot. I gave 'em no wrong names. I call'd 'em Rogues indeed, but that's their proper Name; and they all ſet their hands to it immediately, and ſub- ſcribed themſelves Rogues upon my Chops, theonly true Narrative they ever writ. Bell. Thou art a mad Fellow-prethee goin. Exit Hot, at one Door. Enter at another Teſtimony. Bell. Well—who's at the Door? Teſt. Alamentable Soul. Bell. A Beggar? Teſt. A more ſad Object; but I conceive he comes rather to rob than beg, for he comes Arm'd with a ſtrong Bow and Arrows. Bell. A Bow and Arrows? what, is he a Tartar * Teſt. A Bow and Arrows made of Ribons, Laces, and other idle Vanities, wherewith he intends to wound your Siſter’s heart. Bell. Oh the canting Coxcomb. Tºft. Nay, why canting Coxcomb? Bell. Be gone you ſenceleſs Aſs; and bring in the Gentleman. Teſt. Nay, why ſenceleſs Aſs? this is unſeemly. Bell. He wont ſtir. * Teſt. I am no ſenceleſ, Perſon I ha'more ſences than your ſelf; I have a ſence o’Vanity, and of the nothingneſs o' the things o' this World--- and a ſence o’ Sin, and aſence o’ the inſinuating nature oºſin— I dare not bring this wanton frothy young Manto your Siſter—for ſhe is frothy alſo--- and fin will get in at a little crany and if ſin once get in his head, he’l get in all his whole body. now your honour has not that ſence o’ theſe things. You ought to have that Your Honour is a ſenceleſs Perſon Bell. How Sirrah—? Tºft. In a ſpiritualſence - Bell. There’s no getting this preachingFellow away—Couſin Hothead. Enter Hothead. Hot. My Lord. Bell. Why do you let this canting Coxcomb plague me? Hot. Why do you keep ſuch a canting Coxcomb let him plague you, Pox you, and Damn you, I don't care. Teſt. Oh! ſad! oh!ſad Î Hot. Oh! ſhad 1 oh! Sot! Bell. So, now I’ve brought 'em both upon me. Hot.He's always tuninghis Noſe,too high too low, like a Sowgelders Horn Bell. Well,Sir,if you pleaſe, tell me who's at my Door? Hot. Forty One is coming indingdong. Bell. Into My Door f who's at my Door, Iſay? Hot. Old Forty One, I'faith. - Bell. I cannot have an anſwer—Sirrah—who's at my Door? - F 2. Tºft. Papery,
Page 36

36 Sir Courtly Nice: Tºft. Popery, Pmſure is coming in. ºi. " : Bell. Intomy Door? I ask you, who ‘sat my Door?" - l º Teſt. Popery I’m ſure. - - . Hot. Roguery I’m ſure. - ". . . . Teſt. Popery I’m ſure. Hot. Roguery I’m ſure. Bell. Confound you both. Hot. And confound you both. (Bell turns them both out.) Bell. You Boy, is there any one at Door f : (to a Page. ) Pa. Yes my Lord. Bell. So, this Boy can anſwer, who isit? Pa. Sir Courtly Nice, My Lord. Bell. O' theſe Rogues, have they made him wait all. this while 2 intro- duce him quickly. He comes moſt ſeaſonably to rid me of my plague, now I’m very ſick of it. Enter Sir Courtly and the Page, bowing to one another. Dear Sir Courtly, my Servants did not tell me who you were, that I have ignorantly made you wait, I am a ſham'd to ſee you. . . . . Sir Co. Your Lordſhips moſthumble Servant. - Bell. Your very humble Servant Page call my Siſter. Enter Aunt and Leonora. - . . . goes to Salute Leo. Sir Co. Madam your moſt— - Aunt #eps firſt. Au. Sir Courtly, your very humble Servant. Sir Co. Oh your Ladyſhips very humble Servant Au. Your moſt humble Servant. Sir Co. Now Madam, your moſt humble Servant. (to Leo.) Au. An incomparable fine Gentleman. - Bell. Well, Sir Courtly, now I've brought you thus far o’your way to my Siſters inclinations; I’le leave you to purſue the reſt o' your journey by your ſelf; you need no guide to Ladies hearts. Sir Co. Oh! your moſt humble Servant. Au. No, Sir Courtly commands all. If my Neice does not receive you, Sir Courtly, in all the obliging manner in the World, 'tis for want of ex- perience and underſtanding merit- Ple aſſure you, Sir Courtly, I who have ſome little more judgment,have had a very particular value for you,Sir, from the firſt Minute I had the honour to ſec you, Sir. Sir Co. Oh! Madam, your moſt humble Servant. Au. A very particular Sir Co. Oh your moſt humble Scrvant. Au. And if my Neice has not, it proceeds from her want of Years to know Deſert. And indeed all Youth is indiſcreet, I wou’d by no means ad- viſe a Gentleman of Merit, to marry any Perſon, that has not ſome Years and ºxperience upon her Bºll. She’s ſººting up for her ſelf I think. Aunt, . Au, Ne- (Salutes Aunt.)
Page 37

Or, it cannot Be, 37 Au. Nephew— - -- ", tº “ . . . . . . . . . . . Bell. Pray leave the Loverstogether. * * * * * * * * Au. Sir Coartly, your moſt humble Servant. - Sir. Co. Madam, your moſt humble Servant. -> - Au. Pray, Neice, behave your ſelf ſo to Sir Courtly, as at leaſt to do me right; and by all your expreſſions and behaviour, he may know how very particular an honour I have for him. - - - Bell. She has for him # Au. Moſt particular.— - - - - – º – “... ." . . . . . . * (aſide.) . . . . . . . . . . . . º - - t Bell. Pray Aunt in particular-—come with me— Au. Very particular— º . . . . . . Sir Co: Oh! Madam—Madam -- . . . * Bell, Aunt—tº . ~ : * : * 'º', ; , , … ...: - - - - Au. Yes Nephew—Sir Courtly, Ham exceeding unwillingtoleave you to to the Qonverſation of a young Lady, whoſe Years I’m afraid will not afford her Wit enough to entertain ſo fine a Gentleman— - • Sir. Co. Oh! Madam J. Madam! Madam 1. Au. But I’le return with all ſpeed poſſible— - 2 º' Bell. But you ſhall not, if I can help it— (aſide). , , , , Au.' And ſo your very humble Servant. , , , Sir Co.' Oh! Madim! your moſthumble Servant. I (Exit Aunt and Bel.) Leo. Now will I manage him, humour him---pretend to admire him. to draw him into love, laugh: at him and revenge my ſelf on him, for plaguing me. - - (aſide). - Śr Co. Now, Madam, is the glorious opportunity come, which my Soul' has ſong wiſh'd, to expreſs how much I admire, adore— , , , , º, . º, Oh! Sir Courtly—º L'vºdº, cº- ſº ſº t ſ º - Sir Co. Extravagantly adorek ºn Leo. Oh Sir Courtly—I cannot receive all this. . . . . Sir Co. Oh! Madam, is there anything on the Earthſ, charming?—I. never ſaw anything ſo fine as your Ladyſhip, ſince I was born. ... . . . Teo. Fye, Sir Cºurtly—-ſ: fºr 32. , , * . '... . . ) ...) Sir Co. Never ſince I was born—iſ a v . . . . . . . . . . - * - - - - - - - - - … . . * * * Leo. You'l kill me with bluſhing. . . . . .” - Sir Co. I ſpeak my Soul—Heavens! what Divine Teeth there are 2 Leo. Fye! fye! I ſhall never open my mouth more. Sir Co. Then you’l undoe all the World.: Oh! there’s nothing ſo charm- ing as admirable Teeth. If a Lady faſtens upon my heart, it muſt be with her Teeth. - : Ico. That’s a pleaſant Raillery—ha!ha ha!” feigns a Fooliſh * Sir Co. Oh! Madam, I hope your Ladyſhip has a tº: laugh. ter opinion o' my good Manners Railly a Lady o' your quality? Leo. Oh! you Wits, turn all things into ridicule. . . - '. Sir Co. Madam, I never was ſo ſerious ſince I was born; therefore I be- ſeech your Ladyſhip have pitty upon me. I ſwear and vow if you do not, I ſhall dye. - - - ico. Dye ha had you Wils will be raillying. Sir Co. Heavcnº, Madam : how ſhall l convince you, I am ſerious. * Leo Really. Sir Colºr:ly,l ſhou’d be very ſorry if you be ſerious, Sr Co.
Page 38

38. Sir Courtly Nice: Sir Co. Oh Heavens ! why ſo Madam Leo. Becauſe tipity ſo fine agentleman ſhou'd loſt all hi. Gallan- try— , - Sir Co. Now you frighten me, Madam. Is it impoſſible for me to attain the Glory of your inclinations? Leo. It will be impoſſible for me to keep the Glory of your inclinations,Sir -Courtly ; ſo Idare not venture on 'em. "- Sir Co. Qh! as to that, Madam, I’le ſwear Eternal conſtancy, eternal ſer- vices,and all thoſe things. Leo. You are not in your own power, Sir Courtly. You fine Gentlemen, 'like fine Countries,are deſir'd and ſought by all, and therefore in a perpetual War. If Iſhou’d place my heart in you, it wou'd not have a minutes quiet. A thouſand Potent Beauties wou'd every day aſſault you, and you'd yield out o’ Complaiſance, your good Breeding wou’d undo me. Sir Co. Oh! Madam, thisis extremity of Gallantry; your Ladyſhip pu- ſhes things to a ſtrange height. Leo. I ſpeak my Soul. Beſidesi’ve another humour, but that's a Foibleſ; will ridicule me. - Sir Co. Oh! Madam. ~ Leo. NY i’le confeſsit. I am ſtrangely curious— extravagantly cu- rious nauſeate a Perfume if itewer ſaluted any Noſe but my one. Sir Co. Ohiº fortunate my owii humour. Lee. Nothing muſt come near me, that was ever once touch'd by another. * Sir Co. Is it poſſible? .* Leo. Notifyou'd give a Hundred pound. Sir Co. My own Phraſe too, i've obſerv’d it in my ſelf, 'meſtrangely for- - * tunate we ſhall be fond to an infinite degree. * (aſide.) Leo. For that reaſon, your fine Gentlemen is my averſion, he'sſo tempt- ed by all Ladies, ſo Complaiſant to all Ladies, that to marry a fine Gentle- man, is to accept the leavings of a Thouſand Ladies. '- - - Sir Go. Oh; Madam : you ha” met with the Creature you deſire; – I never touch'd Woman ſince I was born. Leo. That's pleaſant, I believe you have ruin’d a thouſand. Sir Co. Not one upon my Soul. - Leo. 'Tis impoſſible. Sir Co. Oh! Madam 1 there's not one Lady in a thouſand I can Salute. I only touch the tip o' their ear with my Cheek. - Leo. Fy! ſye? - Sir. Co. Not one Lady in a Million, whoſe breath I can endure. But I - cou’d not go into their Beds, if you'd give me a Thouſand pound. I cou’d not come into the Ayr of any Bed in England but my own, or Your Lady- ſhips, if you'd give me all the World. . Leo. This is all Gallantry, Sir Courtly. You have been told this is my humour. Sir Co. Is it really, Madam * Leo. Oh! above all things. I ſuffer nothing to come near my bed, but my Gentlewoman, Sir Ca.
Page 39

0r, it cannot Be. 39 } —with filthy Aprons on, made by ſluttiſh Women that ſpit as they Sir Co. Nor I, but my Gentleman. He has a delicate hand at making a Bed, he was my Page, Ibred him up to it. Leo. To making Beds? Sir Co. Ay, Madam, and I believe, he’l make a Bed with any Gentle- man in England. - Leo. And my Woman has a great Talent. Sir Co. Is it poſſible? Ladies commonly employ ordinary Chamber Maids ſpin foh - Leo. Foh Sir Co. Your Ladyſhip will pardon me my Linnen is all made in Holland, by neat Women that dip their Fingers in Roſe-water, at my charge. - - £eo. Delicate. - Sir Co. And all waſh’d there. Leo. And ſo is mine at Hearlem. Sir Co. At Hearlem,Ihold a conſtant correſpondence with all the Eminent Waſhers there. Leo. That's delicate, and agrees wonderfully with my humour. Sir Co. Oh happy : we ſhall be fond to an infinite degree. Enter Surly. Leo. Oh! foh! here's that beaſtly rude Clown Mr.Surly. Sir Co. Oh foh what ſhall we do with him? - - Sur. How now P how now ºf you two are intimate Madam. . . - Leo. Oh fob : *- Sir Co. Foh Sur. Foh what’s this fohing at - Sir Co. Nobody Mr. Surly; only at preſent we are accoſted with an ug- grateful ſmell. Sur. Yes, I ſmell an ungrateful ſmell, your Rogury. Madam, I employ'd this Fellow to ſpeak for me, and Ple be hang'd if he be not falſe to heark you, , II].C. Leo. To ſpeak for him? ha haſ Sir Co. Ay, for him, Madam, ha! hal. ' Sur. Ay, for me Nickumpoop. . Sir Co. Your humble Servant Sir, y” are very civil. - Sur. So I am, that I do not execute thee for this theft upon the place; , but thou plead'ſt thy Face, as Whores do their Bellys;’tis big with Fool. Sir Co. Very civik—Sir. ... Sur. Sure, Madam, a Woman o' yourſence, will not chuſe him before me. He has more Land? not more improv'd Land. His Acres run up to one great Weed, I mean himſelf; and there it Bloſſoms in Periwigs and Ribons. Oh! but he has a finer Perſon that's a cheat; a falſe Creed impos'd on you, by a General Council of Taylors, Milleners and Sempſtreſſes; let my hat expound his Face, and youl ſee what a peice o' ſimple ſtuff it is. H Sir Cn. Hnre -
Page 40

4o Sir Courtly Nice: * * Sir Co. Horridº he has put his beaſtly Hat upon my Head—pray Sir dome the favour to remove it, or I ſhall grow very ſick—, , (ta a Scr.) . Sur. Sick; I hope thou wilt eat Ray Hat. Now, Madam, you ſee what a cheat he is, and whether he deſerves any more favours, then to be decently hang'd with the reſt of his Brothers. * Sir Co. My Brothers hang'd,Mr. Surly? . . * - - - * Sur. I mean the Piétures in the Hangings, for they and thou are all but Needle-work; and thou would'ſt ſerve for a peiceo Tapflery, but for a Husband, Lerd,ha’ Mercy on thee. - ... " --- - - Sir. Co. Your Servant, Mr. Surly. You are a very well bred Gentleman, Sir, and pay great Veneration to a Lady o' Quality; and your Miſtreſs— ha ha º - . . . . . . . . . . . - - * - Leo. His Miſtreſs 2 ha haſ - - - " . " º º Sir Co. Let's railly him to death,Madam ha! ha'—H= Sur. Railly does the ridiculous Figure pretend to laugh, at any thing 2 ... ". . . . . . . . . . . . . . Sir Co. Dee' hear, Madam? ; : " . . . . . . . . . . . --> Leo. Sir Courtly, you are a Martyr to good manners, and ſuffer out o' re- ſpečt to the, more thanis fit for a Man to bear. . . . . . . . - Sur. He a Man? I ha'ſeen a Butler make a better thing out of a Diaper Napkin. - * - . - Sir Co. Your moſt obliged humble Servant Sir. Leo. Sir Courtly, l’le withdraw, that you may do your ſelf Juſtice be kick’d … (aſide) . . . . ;: ". . . . . . . . . Sir Co. Your Ladyſhips maſt humble Servant. ºr . . . . . ; tº Leo. I’le no longer protećt ſuch a Coxcomb—as your ſelf. (aſide.) Sir Co. Your very humble Servant, Madam; I'le puſh his Soul out pre- ſently. - - - - }. Oh! don’t do him that favour,Sir, only correót him. . . . Sir Co. Well, Madam, what your Ladyſhip pleaſes.— . . . . . . Your Ladyſhips very humble Servant, 2 . . . (Exit Leo.) .2 Mr.Surly, I have receiv'd ſome favours from you, Sir, and I deſire the and Honour of your Company, Sir, to Morrow morning at Barn-Elms, Sir- pleaſe to name your Weapon, Sir. . . . . . . i . . . cº- Sur. A Squirt. Sir Co. A Squirt? . ſº tº . ~~ Sur. Ay, for that will go tothy heart, I’m ſure, º 'º . . . . Sir Co. Well, Sir, I ſhall kiſs your hands.º. º.º. . . . Sur. Kiſs my Breech— - ºz. . . . . . . (Exit) -º Sir Co. Beaſt, Clown, Fool, Raſcal. Pox take him what ſhall I do with him? it goes againſt my ſtomach horribly to fight ſuch a Beaſt. If his filthy Sword ſhou'd touch me, 'twou'd make me as ſick as a Dog. (Exit.) * * - Scene a Garden. Enter Cr, and Leonora. L. H. that Ple ſcure the Coxcomb—re get him confinid upon the Guard, among Tobacco takers,and that will confine him to his Bed and Ba- gnio's for one Month. Cr. Thar
Page 41

- Or, it cannot Be. 41 Cr. That will do rarely. About this time I expect Mr. Farewel, I ha ſent for your Brother to introduce him. - Leo. My Brother ? Cr. Your Brother I ſay, to ſhew my skill. Retire, and ſtay conceal’d in the Garden. Here your Brother comes. (Exit Leo.) Enter Belguard. Now for lies and nonſence to entertain this jealous Brother till the Lo- ver connes. - Bell. Sir Thomas your Servant, what's your will with me? Cr. Talk—I love talk—begin. .. º Bell. Very pithy. Cr. In what circumſtance are we ? Bell., Circumſtance 2 Cr. Ay, what call you this, where we are? Bell. A Garden. - Cr. A Garden? i've ſeen in the Indies a Melon as big Bell. As all this Garden & - Cr. Bigger. - Bell. Well lyed of a Mad-man. (aſide.) Are all your Fruit ſo large 2 Cr. All. Bell. Your Nutmegs and Pepper are not. Cr. Your Hiſtory is erronious.We have Nutmegs as big as ſmall Fly-boats, I have ſail'd a hundred Leagues in a Nutmeg. Bell. Well lyed. - (ºftde). Cr. Our Oyſters have wonderful conferrence. Bell. Circumference I ſuppoſe you mean. - Cr. Y’ave nick'd it. Three of 'em blockup a Harbour. 'Tis our way of Mortification. - ... - Bell. Fortification. - Cr. You are in the right—Póxon't I have been ſolong abroad, I have almoſt forgot my Mother tongue. - Well—when will this Lover come * 'tis near the hour, and de- s licately dark. (aſide.) Farewel Q Murder! murder 1 murder t claſhing ºf within. - Savor Cr. That's he he's come! (aſide.) murder cryed out. Bell. And at my Coach-houſe Door? - - - Parewel Oh Cowardly Rogues: Four upon one. within. } Bel. A Gentleman aſſaſſinated 2. Cr. Open the Door. Bell. Who's there? , - . G - * - - - Enter
Page 42

42 | Sir Courtly Nice : - Enter a Servant. Ser. My Lord. Bell, Call ſomeo' the Servants to aſſiſt a Gentleman, ſet upon at my Coach-Houſe Door. - Cr. Ay quick—quick—— (draws.) Bell. How, Sir Thomas 2 will you venture among’em Cr. Dee' think I wont ? a Gentleman and not fight? * Bell. I muſt not ſufferit, you may be hurt. Cr. No Sir, I’le fight like a Gentleman; I’le come by no hurt I’le warrant you. Come quick-quick---open the Door— - - Enter Servants. Now Sound a Trumpet, Tivy---tivy-- tan tan---tivy---Tone, --Pox on't 'tis a Horn I don't know a Horn, I ha’ forgot every thing belongs to a Gentleman.-among 'em---helterskelter }: Bel:Cr. and Ser. mean while Farewel, ſteal into the Garden. Enter Leonora and her Woman. Leo. I'my conſcience this is Cracks deſign to let in Mr. Farewel. • Fa. Dear Madam you are in the right. Leo. Mr. Farewel? I know your voice Fa: Oh! Madam, I adore you for this bounty. Leo. And I ſhou’d bluſh for it. . . Fa. Why ſo, Madam? Leo. Should a Woman admit a Lover by night at a Back-Door into the ſame houſe wher ſhe lyes, and converſe privately with him before Mar- 1132(e. - §. Your Brother admitted me. Leo. 'Tis true indeed, you may thank him for the favour, I thought your ſufferings deſerv'd pity, and my Brother wou'd let me ſhew it, no other. way. - Fa. Athouſand Bleſſings on you. - Leo. I doubt not but my honour is very ſafe in your keeping, I wiſh your Perſon, were as ſecure in mine. - - Fa: I am glado’ the danger, ſince tis ſome aſſurance o' my Love. Leo. Your Friend Mr. Crack plays his part very well, and I doubt not but he will ſecure us here, and conveigh us hence, but then other dangers will follow you. - Fa. What are thoſe, Madam? " - Leo. The
Page 43

0r, it cannot Be. 43. • Leo. The danger of marrying without a Fortune, my Ten thouſand pound is at my Brothers diſpoſe. - - - - Fa. I am glad of that too, Madam, 'twill ſhew my love is not mercenary. Leo. The danger of being laught at by the Wits, for marrying at all. Fa. Oh! let the Wits keep the Jilting rotten Wenches, and leave the ſweet Virtuous Ladies tous marrying Fools, I can be as well pleas'd to keep a fine Wife to myſelf, as they can be to maintain five Wenches for all the Town. - Leo. Nay, your keeping Men, Keepers like have commonly but the Of. fals for their Slave.Well the Eveaing Ayr will be unwholſome to you, if you, ſtay longer in it, you’l be in danger of Thunder and Lightning preſently, I mean my Brother--he comes---follow me--- (Ex. Leo, Fa. Wom.) * • Enter Belguard, Crack, &c. 1 Cr. What Cowardly Rogues were theſe ? they ran upon our firſt ſal- ying. Bell. They had a reaſon, you’r a Lyon. Cr. Ius’d to kill Lyons and Tigers in the Indies, as you do Hares and Co- myes here. I kept a Tiger Warren, I kill'd a brace every morning to get me a ſtomack. Bell. It was a good one ſure,you offer'd dear for it. Well I hope you ha' got no hurt? - - Cr. Yes, ſomething very ſharp, went quite through my ſtomack. Bell. How 2 through your ſtomack 2 then you cannot live. - - Cr. Yes, if you noint it preſently with a good diſh o' Jelly-broth, and Tent it with a bone o' Roaſt-beef. - Bell. Is that the wound? it ſhall be heal’d preſently. Cr. Preſently, for my ſtomack is Captious, Bell. It ſhall be done. Go to my Aunt and deſire her to order Sir Tho- mas his Supper - Ser. She's not very well, my Lord, and gone to bed. Bell. Then let the Steward do it. Sir Thomas I am going out and ſhall ſtay late. Pray command my houſe--good Night to you--- (Exit.) Cr. Your Servant Sir---you keep a Woman ---now to the Lovers----- where are they?--- Enter Farewel, Leo, and her Woman. Fa. Here ! here ! thou Divine Fellow. Cr. So, ſo, kiſs' kiſs kiſs :---- Leo. Before Marriage 3 - Cr. Ay, for fear you ſhould not kiſs after marriage--well the houſe is our own, and the Night our own---your Aunts gone to bed, and your Bro- ther abroad, we'l Tory-rory, and 'tis a fine Night, we’l Revelin the Garden—Slaves go bring my Supper----quick---quick--- G 2. Exit. *

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 44

44 Sir Courtly Nice: º Ex, Slaves--and enter with Diſhes : Farewel ,Leo. and Crack ſit down. - * - Enter Siamites and Bantammers. Now a Song and Danceo' your own faſhion— but ſhut the Garden- Gates—andlookto’em well, for Iſle be private in my pleaſures---- - (a Songs and Indian Dance.) -So---now to my Chamber—well—there is no publick Officer like your Pimp---. \ - Pimps manage the great buſineſ; o' the Nation. That is—the Heavenly work o' propagation. - (Exeunt Ommes.) \ *~.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 45

-. Or, it cannot Be. - - 45 Act. V. - Scene Cracks Chamber. Enter Farewel and Crack. Fa, O” ! thou Divine Fellow, what joys haſt thou procured me? Cr. What joys? - Fa. All that Innocence cou’d afford. Cr. Innocence? that's inſipid ſtuff. Fa. No Mr. Crack, there's difference between the Mannah that came, from Heaven, and that out of 'Pothecaries Shops;a touch of Leonora's hand like Mannah from Heaven has all that Man can fancy. Here ſhecomes. - Enter Leonora. This, Madam, is bountiful after an Evenings Converſation, to afford me a Morning too. Leo. We ſhou’d be charitable to Priſoners. - Fa. I am a Priſoner, but ſuch a happy one, as a King is when Lodg’d in a Royal Tower, to prepare for his Coronation. My hour of Coronation draws near, I want only the Church Ceremony and the Oath. * Cr. Madam, how dirſt you venture hither, by day light? - Leo. My Aunt, and Brother, are both gone abroad, and won't come home till Noon. So all thoſe hours are mine, and now Mr. Crack to re- quite your Muſick I ha’ brought ſome o’ mine to entertain you. A Song-----And enter a Woman. Worm. Oh Min-uniº-yo: Brother. Cr. How 2 how 2 - Wom. Juſt coming up ſtairs, to viſit--you Sir Thomas. - Cr. Pox of his civility. Hide, Sir Hide. And do you Momen ſhreike --> - ſhreike! and cry out murder. Q Cr. throws himſelf on the ground and - ſcrambles in diffračied fºre after , the Women. They ſhrei Enter Belguard. - Bell. So, here's my Siſter got into the Madmans Room; and has put him into a frantick fit. Oh the inſatiable curioſity o’ Women. - Cr. You Whores!----you bewitching Whores, do you come to bewitc me? I'le fetch blood from you. - - Bell. Why wou'd you offer to come hither, Siſter Cr. What are you, Sir, the King of Bantam 8 - Bell. No.
Page 46

46 Sir Courtly Wice: Bell. No Sir, no. Cr. Oh! the Mogul. - Bell. Nor the Mogul. • - Cr. What do you then with all theſe Concubines? Oh! I know you now, you’r a fineman, you have put me into brave circumſtances. Did not I deſireyouto let me ſee no Women 2 and here, you keep a company of ramb- ling Whores in your houſe, that have put me into the circumſtances o' di- ſtraćtion... I was a top o'the Staircaſe taking a proſpect o'the Cape of Good- Hope, and theſe Flyboats came ſayling under my Noſe. What do me I ? but leap down to break their Necks? and ha’ broke my own I think. I am certain, I have broke º but what I don't know. Pray take me up, and look over my bones, ſee if none be miſſing; if they be, Bone for Boº: will be demanded. Bell. Poor creature! who's there? - Cr. Who's there? will you truſt me to your ſervants ſo if a Leg or an Arm of mine be broke, they’lleave it behinde’m, and I ſhall looſe it. I ex- pećt all my Limbs and Bones from you, as you received'em. So — come \ and take account of 'em. Bell. I will -I will— (Takes him up.) Cr. Oh! have a care Oh! Bell. Alas! I fear he's hurt; your fooliſh curioſity ha's done this? did you not gape enough upon him before? - , Cr. Oh!gently gently ſo—ſo Fa. Oh! this pleaſant Rogue, ha! haſ Leo. Tis an excellent fellow. Asſoon as we hearmy Brother is returnin g ſlip into that paſſage, 'twill lead you to Crak's Bed-chamber. 2 - (Bell leads him out.) Enter Aunt. Au. How now Gentlewoman? a man wi' you? Nephew—Nephew.-- Nephew. Deo. Begone begone—through that Entry. Ex. Fa. at one Door, at another - Enter Bellguard. Bell. What's the matter 3 * : Au. Our family's diſhonour’d, diſhonour’d here was a fellow, a handſome young fellow wi' my Neice, Oh! my fleſh my fleſh. Leo. Wi’ me? - Au. Will you denyit Confidence? - Bell. Who's there? Hothead, Teſtimony, all of you come hither. . - Enter Hothead, Teſtimony, Exit. * . Tºft. What's your honours pleaſure ? - - - Bell. To
Page 47

Or, it cannot Be. - - - 47 Bell. To cut all your throats, you are all Bauds and Villains, Hot. Leave me out o’ the number you had beſt. - Bell. I will not Sir, For here was a young fellow wi' my Siſter; Leo. My Aunt’s whimſy and jealouſe. Au. I cou’d tread you under my feet. Bell. Which way went he Au. Into that paſſage : He cannot be got further, then Sir Thomas Ca- licoes Bed-chamber. - Bell. Lock all the doors, Arm and beſet Sir Thomas Calicoes lodgings. Leo. This will prove ſuch another wiſe buſineſs as the Pićture." Bell. Hold your peace get you into that room wi' my Aunt: Aunt pray look to her. - (Ex. Bell. Hot. Teſt, &c.) Au. I’le keep her, I warrant her come in gentlewoman. you are a fine gentlewoman. Leo. Oh my heart trembles Heaven inſpire Crack. (aſide) Ex. Aunt and Leonora. Scene changes to another Room. Enter Farewell and Crack. Fa. Oh I curſed fortune. Cr. Well don't trouble your ſelf. I’le bring you off ſafe. - Fa. Not trouble my ſelf, when Leonora's honour is in danger ? ſhe’l be the jeſt of every prating Fop, and malitious beauty. Cr. Her honour ſhall be ſafe too. This bluſtering Brother ſhall entertain you—— - Fa. With a Blunderbuſs?" Cr. Ay, full o’Claret. Away—-away—he comes? Ex. Fa and Enter Bellguard, Hothead, Teſtimony, - ... and the Servants armid. Cr. How? the High and glorious Emperour o'Siam with all his guards? Thou moſt invincible Paducco, Farucco, -nelmoeadin—bobbekin-bow— —wow—ww.—why doſt thou ſeek to deſtroy us Engliſh,ſeated on thy Do- minions by thy own Letters Patents 2 - - Bell. Piſh I take him away. Cr. Take away our Priviledges 2 then this goes to my heart. Draws his Dager, and pretends to ſtab himſelf. Bell. Hold, hold—Sir Thomaſ-Sir Thomas, no hurt is ment to you." Cr. Moſt Great and Glorious Emperour, I humbly thank, and do hum- "bly Implore thee; that thou wou'dſt command thy Invincible guards, to lay. down their arms, and put us out of our frights, and we’l ſubmit our perſºns tothee. This is ſome Interlopers work. (aſide), Bell. Pox o' this impertinent mad—coxcombe? Lay down your wea- pons, ,
Page 48

48 Sir Courtly Alice : Pons, may be if we humour him, he may come to his ſences, and give us leave to ſearch the rooms. (They lay down their Weapons) Cr, My Lord Bellguard, your moſt humble ſervant. Bell. He's come to himſelf; that’s well. Sir Thomas your ſervant, how do you? Cr. A little diſcompos'd, ſomething has frightned me, and put me into the circumſtance of a ſweat. - - Bell. I’me ſorry for that. Shall I beg leave, to ſearch your rooms for a theif that’s got in? Cr. Pardon's beg'd; ſearch muſt not be made; for I have a friend there you muſt not ſee. Wou'd you and your friend were hanged. - (aſide; - A very, honeſt Gentleman, but very much addićted to marriage. 'Tis he that I told you, is to marry my Indian Fubs of a Siſter Mr Farewel. Bell. Mr. Farewel 2 - Cr. Ay, hearing of my arrival, and what circumſtance I was in, hover'd all this morning about the houſe to get a ſight o' me; but car'd not to come in, for it ſeems there isenmity between you. Bell. 'Tis True, and I wonder how he got in without my knowledge. Cr. I made him come in. I was throwing my legs about in the Hall, and the door being open, our eyes knock'd immediately, and gave remembrance ſuch a bang, that we ran full ſpeed into the circumſtances of embracing? Bell. And pray who ſaw this 8 - - Cr. Who ſaw what care I who ſaw? I care not if the whole Townſaw, I’m not aſham'd of owning Mr. Farewel. Bell. No Sir, but I mean which of my family ſaw 3 that I may thank’m for their care. - Cr. What do I care for your family * if I may not bring a friend into your family, a fart for your family. Bell. Nay be not angry Sir Thomas, your friend's welcome. Cr. I doubt it not, for I have found you a very civil perſon. And now recolle&tion is active, I fancy he's the man youtake for a theif. Tisſo—-ha! º excuſe me—ha! ha (—leave is implord—ha! haſ—-brother Fare- 276/. - - - (Fa. within) Brother. Cr. Come out, and participate o’laughter. - - Bell. So, now have I play'd the fool again, vex'd my ſelf, and wrong'd my Siſter with my impertinent jealouſies. - - - * Enter Farewel. ' Cr. Come brother—ha! ha laugh but firſt ſalute. Fa. My Lord, I believe you wonder to ſee me here, and you may; I call myſelf Baſtard, and renounce the blood o' my family, by coming under your roof with any deſign, but to prejudice you, which at preſent I muſt ac- knowledge to my ſhame is not my intention. I viſit my friend here for his OWn
Page 49

Or, it cannot Be. 49 own ſake, and the ſake of a great Beauty, which you ſhall not hinder me of,My Lord. Bell. I will not Mr. Farewel, I ſcorn thoſe effeminate revenges. If I hurt any Man it ſhall be with my Sword. Fa. Your Sword, my Lord? Cr. Hold 2 hold. Bell. Ay any where but here Mr. Farewel, my Houſe is your Sanétua- ry, and here to offer you violence, wou'd prejudice myſelf. Cr. What a quarrelling's here? i my conſcience Ibelieve, my Lord, 'tis becauſe youthink he came to ſteal me, I being under whimſical circumſtan- ces, for I remember you call'd him a Thief. Look you, My Lord don't fear me, I won't be ſ: I know when I'm well Brother I’m very well provided for, I want nothing but my Wits; and what do they ſignifie? if a Man lives like a Gentleman, no matter whether he has Wit or no— . - Fa. Well, my Lord, though I have the misfortune to be your Enemy, I am none to good manners; I am ſorry Iha’ given your houſe this trouble, and the more becauſe my Friend receives ſuch generous uſage in it. Bell. Noram I an Enemy to Love, and the fair Sex. If the Lady you come for loves you, for her ſake I wiſh you ſucceſs. Fa. Now my Lord you vanquiſh me. Cr. He's a brave Man Faith. Fa. I fancy we ſhall live to be better Friends, at preſent Ple take my leave, my Lord your Servant.— - Bell. Your Servant Sir. Cr. Brother Imuſt ſee you down ſtairs. This was a Maſter-peice, ha! ha I (Exit Fa, and Cr. Bell. Now I am cool again. What a flame had your negligence put me into. Here releaſe my Siſter, I’m aſhanu'd to ſee her - #. Servant.) Hot. Sirrah! Sirrah! you did this to make me ſuſpected. Tºft. Ay-ay, I muſt be abus'd, becauſe I’m a Proteſtant. Hot. A Proteſtant? a Dog. But with ſuch Names the Rogues divide the Rabble, and make the Nation go like the Devil, upon Cloven Feet. Bell. Hold your prating, and by your future care make amends for your paſt negligence; your trouble ſhall not be long, within this Eight and forty hours Ple marry her, or ſend her into the Country. Hot. Well-well--Ple look to her, for the Honour of my Family, not your huffing. - (Exit. - ... Teſt. I to diſcharge a Conſcience (Exit.) Enter Leonora. Leo. So---Sir----. so Bell. My Siſter— Leo. Do you run from me? is that the reparation you make for the in- tolerable wrongs you have done me? (pretends to burſt into tears.) ... Bell. Well, I have wrong'd you, I'm ſorry for it, and begyour Pardon- H I
Page 50

- so Sir Courtly Nice: I muſt be gone—about buſineſs—your buſineſs—to fetch Sir Courtly Nice. 1 your Servant, Siſter. (Ex.) Leo. Oh your Servant Sir ha haſ COIIICS- - Enter Crack. ºf Thou admirable Fellow, what haſt thou done with Mr. Farewel? Cr. He's in the Street ſtaying for you. Leo. Staying for me? and can’ſt thou conveigh me to him? Cr. Dee' queſtion it put on a Vizard and ſomething over your Cloaths. Leo. Sweet Rogue. - . > . Cr. Nay, nay be gone. Leo. Delicate Rogue. Cr. Nay, nay he ſtays for you. Leo. Incomparable Rogue. Cr. Pſhaw! put on your Vizard. Leo. Moſt excellent Rogue. Cr. Oones! put on your Vizard. º Leo. I will— I will— haſ haſ toll — loll—derol Crgoes out, and as Leo. is going out ſinging and danceing, She's met by Bell, and Sir Co. Bell. Oh Siſter your tune's alter'd. Sir Co. Oh Madam I’m happy to find your Ladyſhip, in ſo gay a humour. Leo. You'l not find it ſo— (aſide.) - Bell. Sir Courtly I’le betray her to you. I left her in Tears upon an un- happy occaſion, and at parting told her I wou'd bring you. Now you are come, I find her in joy. Nothing elſe cou’d cauſe the change. - Sir Co. Oh : fortunate. - Leo. Oh! Fop — (aſide.) - Bell. Now improve your intereſt, and let us ſee how great a Maſter you are in Courtſhip,by your dextrous diſpatch. I leave you together (Ex.) Sir Co. And upon my Soul I will. Oh! Madam, am I ſo Fortunate, ſo Glorious, to be well in your fine inclinations 2 w Leo. Oh fye, Sir Courtly if I had any ſuch guilt upon me, do you think I wou’d confeſs? - | Sir Co. You do confeſs, Madam your fine Eyes, and your languiſh- ing Ayr, and your charming Bluſhes, and all thoſe things-- Leo. I hope I carry no ſuch falſe things about me; for if they ſay any ſuch thing they infinitely wrongme. Sir Co. Oh! now you are cruel, Madam; you kill me. Leo. Can you hope for my heart Sir § yours. Sir Co. What aſſurance wou'd your Ladyſhip have 2 Leo. All manner—he that pretends to my heart-muſt figh, and wait, - and -- - - he runs--- I may chance - -Sir to run as nimbly from you, if Cracks Wit do not fail him-- here he , till I’ve ſome aſſurance o” .
Page 51

• ... -- - 0r, it cannot Be. 51 and watch—and pant—and fight, and write—and kill himſelf. Sir Co. All this I ha' done, Madam, and Ten thouſand things more. Drove by your Windows,a thouſand times a day, ſought you at the Parks and the Plays. Was a conſtant faithful Attendant at all Tragedys--- for I preſum’dyour Ladyſhip nauſeates Comedys.-- ' Leo. Oh! Foh!--- * - Sir Co. They are ſoill-bred-and ſawcy with Quality, and always cram'd with our odious Sex that have not always the moſt inviting ſmell— "Madam, you'l Pardon me—Now at Tragedies, the Houſe is all lin'd with - Beauty, and then a Gentleman may endure it. And I have gone, found not your Ladyſhip there, drove home, kill'd my ſelf with ſigthing, and then writ a Song. - Leo. Oh! Heavens! Sir Courtly, did you ever write a Song upon me? Sir Co. Above a thouſand. - Leo. Oh! there's nothing charms me like a Song For Heavens ſake the Song! the Song—— ~ Sir Co. I’ve above forty here in a ſweet Bag, Ple ſhew you the firſt I made upon Your Ladiſhip.”Tis thought to be a pretty Fooliſh ſoft Song, moſt Ladies are very kind to it. As I gaz'd unaware, On a Faceſ, fair;----- Leo. Oh! Sir Courtly— Sir Co. Tour cruel Eye, Lay watching by Toſnap my heart, - Which you did wi'ſuch art; That away wi't you ram, º Whilſt I look'd on. To my ruin and grief; Stop Thief—ftop Thief. Leo Oh I fine oh! fine . . . - Sir Co. That ſtop Thief, Madam, is pretty Novel. Leo. Oh! delicate : l’m charm'd : I’m loſt fye what have I ſaid— - Sir Co. What makes me the happyeſt of Creatures. ~ | Leo. I only railly— I renounce all--- Sir Co. Not for the World— º Leo Away------the Song again—---the Song------Ple hear nothing but the Song. Is there no tune to it? - Sir Co. One of my own compoſing: - Leo. That accompliſhment to ? Heavens' how fine a Gentleman is this? Sir Co. Oh, Madam, how prou’d you make me? . - Leo. Oh ' dear, how I betray myſelf? Fooliſh Creature ----no more no more---the Tune, the tune. - Sir Co. I always humour my words with my Ayr. So I make the Voice ſhake at the laſt Line, in imitation of a Man that runs after a Thief. Sto— ho ho—hop Thief (ſings.) - H 2. Leo Oh 1. -
Page 52

52 Sir Courtly Nice: Leo. Oh delicate cannot l learn it ſto—ho ho—ha! ha : ha! (imitates his Fooliſh ſinging and fall into a laugh.) Sir Co. Dear Madam, what makes your Ladyſhip laugh? - Leo. At a Coxcomb, that thought to win me with a Fooliſh Song, this puts it into my head. | Sir Co. Oh! Fooliſh there are abundance of thoſe Fooliſh Fellows, and does the Song pleaſe your Ladyſhip? Leo. Hinfinitely, I did not think you had been ſo fine a Poet. Sir Co. Poetry, Madam, is my great foible, and when I ſee a fine Wo- man I cannot command my foible. Leo. How? dee’makeSongs upon other Ladies unfortunate I’ve given my heart to an inconſtant Man Sir Co. Oh Madam, -only Gallantry. Leo. I’m abus’d— unfortunate—. (pretends to weep.) Sir Co, Oh! Madam, you take it wrong— Leo. I’m abus’d. - - Sir. Co. Oh! Heavens' Leo. But the Songs very fine -—ſto-ho—ho haſ ha : Sir Co. Pleaſant Creature. ‘(ſings and laughs) Leo. Coxcomb. (aſide.) Sir Co. We ſhall be infinitely fond w a pretty Glaſs, this Madam - - (looks in a Glaſs.) Leo. So he's making an aſſignation with his own fooliſh Face, I’le leave him to Court that and ſteal away. (Exit.) Sir Co. Sto—ho ho—hop— - Enter Aunt. Au. Singing, Sir Courtly 3 - Sir Co. At your Service, Madam. Well, Madam, you have ſaid ſo ma- ny fine things to me, that Iaſſure myſelf of your heart, and now I am re- ſolv’d to puſh this opportunity, to an extremity o' happyneſs. (Sir Courtly looks in the Glaſ, while heſpeaks.) Au, Oh! fortunate! this to me? I did make him ſome advances to day I confeſ, and have they had this ſucceſs & my heart pants : I am ſurpris’d. with infinitejoy, and am not able to anſwer (aſide.) Sir Co. Well, Madam, I muſt behappy, and ſoupon my—the Lady gone (turns from the Glaſs.) Au. Sir Courtly you put me in great confuſion Sir Co. The Lady's conſent is very conſiderable—ſhe governs her Neice, and under her condućt may make me happy, with a reſerve to Mo- deſty. (aſide.) Well, Madam, ſhall I have your conſent to my happy- neſs, my glory? y - Au. Oh dear Sir! is it poſſible to anſwer you ſo ſoon Sir Co. So ſoon, Madam 2 you know my paſſion has been long. Au: Is it poſſible 2 I ſwear I never heard of it before. ~ Sir Co. That's ſtrange; wou'd not my Lord, your Nephew acquaint you 2 Au. He never ſaid one word of it to me. Sir Co. That's amazing. Au. 1 - - |
Page 53

0r, it cannot Be. 53 * Au. I find my Nephew has been falſe to me. It ſeems ’tis me the Gentle" man loves,and my Nephew wou'd defrau'd me of him, for his Siſter-—heres fine doings. - (aſide.) - Sir Co. I ſwear I thought your Ladyſhip had known, and granted your conſent you ſaid ſo many fine things . Au. I ſaid no more, Sir Courtly, then what were the reſult o' my thoughts, upon the contemplation of your great deſert Sir Co. Your Ladyſhips moſt humble Servant then I hope, Madam, ſince my paſſion has been long, though you knew not of it, you will not deferr my hapyneſs---'tis in your power I’m certain, noPerſon controuls you--- Aa. Controuls me? that’s pleaſant no Sir. ; (aſide.) Sir Co. She ſays true e can bring her Neice I beſeech you, Madam, take pity of a ſuffering Lover. Au, Oh! Sir, ſhou’d I conſent ſo ſoon, 'twou'd be againſt all Forms — Sir Co. I would not for the World offend againſt any Forms. No Man living more ſtudyes, and adores all manner of Forms but my paſſion has been long. - / Au, I know not what to ſay, Sir, indeed I muſt not. Sir Co. Oh 1 Pardon me! - Au, Oh! Pardon me ! Sir Co. Oh I Madam : Au. You confound me, Sir. - Sir Co. You diſtraćt me, Madam. It muſt be— Au. Well, Sir I yield, but with an extremity o' bluſhing, Sir Co. Your moſt obliged humble Servant. Au. My ſevere temper wou'd never ha’ been wrought on ſo ſoon, but by ſo fine a Gentleman. . - - - Sir Co. Your moſthumble Servant. - Au. And to revenge myſelf on my Nephew, for his falſe play. Sir Co. Well, Madam, we’l in my Coach to the next Church preſently. Au, 'Tis very hard to reſiſt you, Sir Courtly... If you pleaſe I will firſt put on a Diſguiſe; for I deſire it may be manag'd with all ſecrecy, till the Ceremony of Marriage be over. - Sir Co. With all my Soul; for I infinitely love a ſecret Intrigue, eſpe- cially when everybody knows of it. - Au. Leaſt my Nephew lighton us, and prevent it. Sir Co. He's for the Match. - Au. He's very falſe. Sir Co.. Is it poſſible? • . Au: Is it not apparent, when he conceal’d the whole matter from me, leaſt I ſhou’d promote it? . Sir Co. That's unanſwreable, I'm amaz'dat it. Well, Madam, Iſhall not fail of being happy P--- - - • Au. Immediately, Sir. - º Sir Co. And youthink you have power Au, Power P that's pleaſant. - . - . . Sir Co. So ſo--- ſhe’l bring or ſend her--- (aſide.) Well, Madam Your moſt humble Servant. - - Au You:
Page 54

S4 Sir Courtly Nice : Aw, Your very bluſhing Servant— (Ex) - Sir Co. Your humble-ſto-ho-ho-hop-Thief— (Exit.) - Enter Crack and Leonora laughing, - cr. Anhumble Thief indeed, ſteal an old Woman 2--- - - º Leo. This was a pleaſure I cou’d not ha’ thought of. Now to our Affair. Cr. Come--on with your Vizard. (Exeunt.) Scene changes to the Hall. Enter at one Do or, Hothead and Teſtimony, at another Crack. Cr. Barbarity falſehood treachery murder Hot. What’s the matter? . Cr. Did not I ſtipulate upon the ſurrendry of my ſelf to this Houſe, to be kept from Women? and I am devour’d with elm; here's come into my Chamber, a hot burnt Whore, with a black cruſt upon her face—here ſhe is, Avant. - - (Exit.) - * Crack pull's in Leonora vizarded. - - Hot. You damn’d Whore, how came you into this houſe? and what are you? I’le ſee your face. Cr. Then l'le ſee your braines, I ſwear by Gogmagog, and all the ſeven damnable Sinnes. - - Teſt. Oh I ſad oh ſad Cr. Shew me the face of a Woman I had rather ſee forty full moons. . Hot. Stand off Impertinence; I will ſee her face. Cr. Murder murder call my Lord -Lord, Lord murder Lord–Lord–Lord. * - Hot. Hold your bauling, I’le lether go.—For now I think on't, if my Lord ſhou'd find this Whore here when he gave ſuch ſtrickt orders, we ſhou'd let nobody out, or in, he’l make more noiſe than this mad fool--—ſo let us kick her out o' Doors, and ſay nothing. Tefé Hold, letus not uſe violence to her ſhe’s a great temptation to Inc. (aſide) Tle reprove the idle Woman, it may be, I may gain upon her. - - Hot. Gain a Clap Sirrah! for this is ſome of the footmens Whores,pick’d up in the dark. Get you out you Whore. . murder— º Teft. No violence pray. She's a great ſnareto me. (aftile) . . wo- man get you out woman—and dee hear?—-l'le follow you, and we'ldrink a bottle. 2 * - * Leo. Do old godly knave, and thouſhalt be welcome. Teſt. I come! I come! (aſide) . get you out woman. Hot. Get you out—you'Whore. (they thruſt Leo. out.) Cr. Good morrow—up ſo early? Hot. What's the whimſy now Cr. Am
Page 55

0r, it cannot Be. 55 Cr. Am not I i” Bed? Hot. In Bed? . Teſt. Poor ſoul, poor ſoul Cr. I am not i faith. Then I walk in my ſleep: I was faſt a ſleep juſt now, and dream't I ſaw women, and Vizards, and all that Traſh; and the fright put me in a Feaver. I burn; prethee give me a mouth full of ſweet ayr. - - (Exit Cr.) Hot. Prethee take a belly full and be damn'd. A fine time on’t I have ; with Whores, and Fools, and mad Men, and Fanatiºues. (Exit.) Teſt. So, now I’le ſteal after her; for I find in me a very great up- roat. - - (Exit.) 'scene changes to Violante's houſe. Enter Farewel— Leonora vizarded, Teſtimony. Fa. Come in, come in honeſt old Fornicator, though the girle be mine, when I have had my collation, if ſhe'l conſent, faith, thou ſhalt have a bit; I love a Wenching Rogue i' my heart. Teſt. Oh! dear Sir, your very humble ſervant, and truly I am a kind of a wag. I love a pretty bit ſometimes. Fa. And I love thee the better for it, and this is a pretty bit,thou ſhalt ſee her - (Leo. pul’s off her vizard.) Teſt, Oh! dear ! undone! undone - Leo. Nay, nay Mr. Teſtimony won't you be as good as your word * ſhan’t we have a Bottle? Teff, Oh! Madam, don't diſcover me to my Lord, and you ſhall not only have my prayers, but the prayers of all the ſober party for you all days o' my life. - Léo. So, he runs from Whoring to Praying. Fa. Are not you a Rogue Sirrah 3 Tºft. I know I ſhall be called Rogue, by the Popiſh party—they will re- joyce at my fall, but lhope my fall will be ſanétified unto me for my bet- . ter upſtanding— - Fa. Among the Wenches Sirrah come, Sirrah, you ſhall ſtay till my Lord comes, for his mortification, as well as yours. Tºft. Oh! my fleſh, it has undone me. - - - Enter Violante, and Crack. . . " Pio. My dear. - - . > *- Leo. My dear.— - Pio. Excellent Crack; for this great peiceo’ ſervice,I’le ha’ thee knigh- ted under a petticote. Well we muſt ſend for my Lord, to laugh at him. Tºft. Oh! dear ! I tremble! ... ', Vio. Who's there? well my Lord, I deſire to ſpeak with him. • Leo. Pray let him bring Sir Courtly Nice, and his bride with him ; be ſure you ſay nothing o' me, - - - - (Ex, footm.) - * Vio. Are -
Page 56

56 Sir Courtly Nice: Pio. Are you a Bride yet Leo. Not yet. Vio. Get in, and let my Chaplain make you one. Leo. Come Mr. Teſtimony. , Mr. Crack, bring him. - Cr. How now you Rogue? what's your buſineſs? . Teſt. Oh! my reproach will be great. (Ex: Fa. Leo. Cr. Teſt.) Vio. Mr. Surly. - Enter Surly. Sur. Well, what now Vio. Now, you ſhall be my Husband. Sur. Your Jack, to turn and roaſt you for another, whilſt I ha’ no ſhare 1n WOu. ; According to the ſhare I have in you : You men wou'd feign en- groſs all manner o’ Sinnes,by the pretended Prerogative o' your Sex; well if iniquity be your Eſtate, when you ha’ married me, I’le put in for my thirds. Sur. I doubt it not ; within this week, I ſhall ſee in a Fop's hand, a Bil. let Doux, that is a Ticket tolet him into your Play-houſe. Vio. Prethee leave of this doged humour. Sur. I ha'mone; fawning is a Dogs humour. . . Vio. Nay but Sullenneſs; it taxes thy Eſtate, that thou art never the better for it; tis a french Eſtate. Sur. Ay, buttolick a fool's ſhoe, is a Spaniels Eſtate. Vio. Prethee dreſs like a Gentleman. Sur. So I do, ; but I wou'd not dreſs like a Gentleboy, lag at my years among thoſe Children, to play with their Toys; be always followed up like a love letter, with a ſuperſcription, theſe to the next pretty girle. Vio. There’s no altering thee go in a while. - Ex. Surly. Enter Lord Belguard, Sir Courtly, Aunt vizarded. Vio. My Lord, your humble ſervant. I invited you hither, to recon- cile youto your Siſter, ſhe's weary of your Government, and has diſpos'd of her ſelf. - - Bell, Ay, Madam, but according to my own defires, that now I ſuppoſe you will acknowledge the good effečts of my Government; —--Siſter ſalute your friend. - Pio. Do you take that for your Siſter? then Ple ſhew you the good effects of your Government. Open the Door. . . - The Scene is drawn, and Farewel, Leonora, a Parſon, Crack, Teſtimony, appear. . . . - - -- Bell. My Siſter there? call my ſervants. . . . . . . . . * -- Cr. Nay then call mine, the great Mogul, and the King o' Bantam, I’le pepper you. - 1.7 . . . . - Bell. Then you were the Pimp were you—Sirrah—I may chance begin with you, - -- ... ---- - - Vio. How
Page 57

0r, it cannot Be. - . 57 Vio. How 'i' my houſe and preſence? touch him if you dare. Bell. I’m made an Aſs on. Cr. Not far from that circumſtance. Bell. You Raſcal Vio. Again & - Sir Co. But what the Devil am I made? what have I got? Leo. Even my ſtale Aunt. - Au. Sawcy huzzy. Sir Co. The Aunt P what have you put upon me, Madam 2 Au. What have I put upon you, Sir, more than your ſelf deſir’d P Did not you declare you have long had a paſſion for me? Sir Co. A Paſſion for you? Comical that's probable Rot me if ever I had a Paſſion for you in my Life. I meant all to your Neice; a Paſſion for an old Woman 2 - - Au. Ill-bred Fop. Sir Co. Very fine---- - Vio. Now, my Lord, what ſay you of your fine Cotgueen art of Con- ſerving Woman 2 will ſhe keep if not j with Virtue f here is a peice o' dryed Sweet-meat, you ſee cou’d not keep ; and proves" by her example, that the Huffs of either Sex, when they are boldly attacqued in private, ſooneſt deliver their Weapons. Au. This is all ill manners. Vio. Ay, but here's an old Cat will ſuffer no Vermin to come into the Houſe ; but then he has a Liquoriſh tooth, and loves to have a ſweet bit for himſelf; he wou'd fainha' pick’d up your Siſter for a Wench. Bell. How 2 º - Teſt. 'Tis true indeed my Lord ; I will not tell a lye for the whole World. ' - Bell. Oh! Villain beads correótion. Vio. But your faults my Lord I’le take into my correótion, and give my ſelf to Mr. Surly— Mr. Suriy. well Sirrah—I’le leave you to my Couſin Hot- Enter Surly. Sur. Well.— Bell. To Surly Sur. Ay, now Nice thy quarrel and mine is at an end, Ile let thee bean Aſs forty years longer. - - Sir Co. You are a rude fellow and you are all ill----bred----and I’le re- venge myſelf on you all, as far as my Sword and my Wit can go--- & Leo. Wit—ha! ha- (all laugh) - * Sir Co. —Very fine manners this—my Coach—Madam, you may follow your own occaſions I have none with an Old Woman. (to the Aunt.) Au. You are a Coxcomb. - - - - Sir Co. Your Servant -my Coach . . I Leo. Muſt *
Page 58

58 - Sir Courtly Nice : Leo. Muſt Iloſe you Sir Courtly—ſtop Theif–ſtop Theif— Sir Co. Oh! your Servant—my Coach you Dogs (Ex.) Pio, Come my Lord, I ſee Patience in your Face, all may be well yet. Sur. How! Jilting already? - Vio. Promiſe I ſhall enjoy all and ſingular the Privilcdges, Liberties, and immunities of an Engliſh Wife. Bell. All. * . - . . . . Vio. That is to ſay, Ramble, Rant, Game, Dreſs, Viſit, Prate, Ogle, Riſs and— - - . Bell. Hold—hold—whether the Devil is ſhe running: Kiſs, kiſs —and- ſtop for Heavens ſake. Pío. Kiſs, and before your Face; is it not the Prerogative of an Engliſh Wife? Surly, I owe thee a reward for Service, kiſs me." - - Bell. That's not to be borne. * . Jºio. Surly, I am thy Wife. - - - Bell. Hold hold for Heavens ſake do not uſe me thus? Vio. Then do not Rebel but pračtiſe obediently, the poſtures of an Eng- liſh Husband, before you are Liſted; Poiſe your Hat, draw your left Leg, backward, bow with your Body, and look like an Aſs, whileſt I kiſs like a—Wiſe—Surly kiſs me. - * Bell.—If he does (lays his Hand on his Sword). Sur. With all my Heart. If I kiſs thee, let the Devil Marry thee. (he offers to kiſs her, and ſhe gives him a box o'th. Ear.) - Vio. And the Devil kiſs thee, cou’dſt thou think any Woman wou'd ſuſ. ferthy face to come near her, but ſome Dairy Milk, to curdle her Milk? All. Ha! haſ hal -- (all laugh.) Sur. Hoh hoh! What a ſociety o' Gotam's are here, to laugh at Man. for miſſing a Woman? had I Married her, as my Lord Wiſe-acre intends to do, I had deſerv'd to ha’ been laught at, for a Coxcomb, and a Cuckold, as he will be in few Days. - - Pºo. How? - Sur, Ay, you are all Whores, Pox on you, all Whores. . (Ex.) Enter Hothcad and all the Servants. Hot. Did you ſend for us? Bell. Yes, do you ſee where my Siſter is? Hot. By what witchcraft was this? - - Pio. Do not you remember a Vizard you turn'd out o' Doors?" Hot. Was it you? Leo. Even the ſame. Hot. Then you deſerve to be turn’d out o' Doors again. Bell. But what do you deſerve Sir? That not only turn'd my Siſter out o' Doors—but let Mr. Teſtimony—pick her up for a Wench. Hot. Oh! Dog oh Rogue— = * * Tºſº I

Page 59

Or, it cannot Be, . 59 - y Teſ. I am no Rogue a Mán may fall, and be Godly in the main— I am ſatisfied in my Spirit, I am a Godly Man Hof. Here's a Rogue—Sirrah—Sirrah - - (beats and kicks Teſ.) Teſ. Perſecution—Perſecution——Papiſt——do kick the Godly, kick the Proteſtants out o' Kingdom do Papiſt—I ſee what you wou'd be at— Ex.) Bell. So Couſin now I have done with ſpyes—you may follow your own buſineſs, if you have any— Hot. Buſineſs? yes I have buſineſs, and will have buſineſs as long as. there is a Famatick in the Kingdom, and ſo farewell— (Ex.) Bell. I am now convinced, Vertue a Womans only guard. If ſhe be baſe Metal, to think by Chimiſtry, to turn her into Gold, Is a vain dream of what we mever ſee, And I’le proclaim to all—It cannot be. (Excunt Ommes.) F I N I S. -- - -- - - A SONG to be sing in Dialogue between a Man and a Woman in the Third Aét, to Sir Courtly Nice, at his firſt appearance. Man. O” ! be kind, my Dear, be kind, … - Whilſt our Loves and we are Young, We ſhall find, we ſhall find. Time will change the Face or Mind; Both will not continue long. . . . . . . Oh! be kind, my Dear, be kind. Woman. No, I Love, and fear to looſe you, Therefore 'tis Imuſt refuſe you, When I’ve yielded fou my Crown. You’l no more Obedience oxyn. No, I Love, and fear to looſe you Therefore’tis I muſt refuſe you. Man. The Fair by kindneſ, Reign, By cruelty Deſtroy. - If you can Charme with the Pain Of Love, then what can you do with the joy The Fair by kindneſs Reign, * . . . . By cruelty Deſtroy. Woman. Ifear to yield, but cannot deny. * * - . Man. If you do not Iſhall die. - } Woman. So ſhall I. . . " , , " . - Both. . . So ſhall I. - . Chorus Then come to joy—come tº joy, . together. Better Love than we ſhou’d die. - Come to joy, come to joy. **
Page Scan 74

- - r ---------- > t. Man. No, no, my other Females all sº ... • ... - - - - - * * A Dialogue Sung between an Indian Man and woman in th Fourth A&t, . to Farewel, Violante, Crack. Being an imitation of ſome Natives of India, before the late King. Man. The lovel, Indian staf charm, - . . . . - - -I'd envy no Jaw-waw alive - Might I be ſo, bleft to dive a Song, Sung by - . In thy ſºft yielding Armi, , . . . . With a Jimminy, Gomminy, whee-whee, whee. - With a Gomminy, Jimminy-whee. ºr º • ? woman. I wou'difyou'd be true. . . . . . . . But ovhen you 've dome - . . . . . . You’l be gone, ... - - º * And throw me of with a Shooh-ſhooh, ſhooh. . -- ...And a huſh pooh, - - - " - * - And a fuſh whooh, - ... . . And a migotty, magotty, migotty, magotty, - Migotty, magotty, ſhooh. ". - - - - * * * . . . . . - -: - *- fºllow, Fair or Black, & ' ' ' ) Tº thy Charmes ſhall proſtrate fall, . . . . . . . . . As every kind of Fºrd, - … To the White Elephant Buitewacke. l JAnd thou alone ſhall have from me . . . - 2. Jimminy, Gomminy, whee, whee, whee, - The Gomminy Jimminy, whee. - - - - - * . • . . . . . . . ~~ -, * Woman. The great Jaw-waw that Rules our Land, " ' ' ' " ".. And pearly Indian Sea . . . z º. Has not ſº abſolute Command, ... . º, As thou haft over me. . . . . . - With a Jimminy Gomminy, Gomminy " ' " . . . º, Jimminy, Jimminy Gomminy, whee.` º º • . * * * . . . º -*. º Both, Thou alone ſhalt have from me . . . . . . . . ºr . ! Jimminy Gomminy, Gomminy, * . . . . . . Jimminy, Jimminy Gomminy, .. ... "… . ... ', Whee, whee, whee, whee, whee, whee. ſ º | - - - - *** * * * : * ~ “. . . . . . . .” -- * * - - - º
Page Scan 75

Blank page
Page Scan 76

Blank page
Page Scan 77

Blank page
Page Scan 78

Blank page
Page Scan 79

Blank page
Page Scan 80

- THE NEW YORK PUBLIC LIBRARY Reference DePARTMENT This book is under no circumstances to be taken from the Building | fºr tº 4 tº





Page Scan 81

+------- - - - - - - -， ！ ------ ------- ----- ---- ---- _ - _ _ … …………………！！！ -- --------- ----- …
Page Scan 82

Blank page

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents

End of text. Return to beginning.
