Elvira: or, The worst not always true. A comedy. Written by a person of quality., . | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
Elvira: or, The worst not always true. A comedy. Written by a person of quality., .
Author
Bristol, George Digby, Earl of, 1612-1677.Bristol, George Digby, Earl of, 1612-1677.
Published
London,Printed by E. Cotes for Henry Broom,1667.
Description
2 p. l., 88 p.21 cm.
Rights
Public Domain, Google-digitized.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/osu.32435017840844

Table of Contents

    Front Cover
    Title Page
    Section 1 on page number 1
    Section 2 on page number 5
    Section 3 on page number 17
    Section 4 on page number 25
    Section 5 on page number 41
    Section 6 on page number 47
    Section 7 on page number 48
    Section 8 on page number 61
    Section 9 on page number 67
    Section 10 on page number 69
    Section 11 on page number 70
    Section 12 on page number 75
    Section 13 on page number 85

Book Text
Front Cover
Page Scan 1

Blank page
Page Scan 2

- I º sº LIBRARY of the OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY L H









Page Scan 3

Blank page
Page Scan 4

Blank page
Page Scan 5

- ... • g - - - - --- * : - - - - - . - - } . * * * º - . . . - 2. - - - \ , º, . -* Q *: . The worſt not always true.

Page Scan 6

****， * | i #



End of Front Cover. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Title Page
Page Scan 7

r------------r-‘ ‘º - - - O - O R. - . . . ... The worſtnot always true. C O M E D Y 22, 4, 6-2-24.2%2 #4 24, 2…” º . . v. Written by a Perſon of Quality. - —— - * - > * ~ * : *-' \ Liºns d Roger L'Estrange. *...* - - - L 0.5\C D 0 \C, Printed by E. Cotes for Henry Brome in Little-Brittain. 1667. " * * * : * - - - - -- • - -- - - - - - - - -- * * . . . * - N. . . . . . . . ------a * : * ~ :… -- - - - - - - - --- --- - - - - - - - - - - - T- U
Page Scan 8

Blank page
Page Scan 9

P E R S O N S. - J Don Julio Rocca. Don Pedro de Mendoca. - Don FernandoSolis: In love with Donna Elvira. - Don Zancho de Menezes: In love with Donna Blanca. - Fabio: Servant to Don Fernando. Fulvio : Servant to Don Pedro. Chichon: Servant to Don Zancho. APage. wo M E N. , º Donna Elvira : A beautiful Lady, Don Pedro's Daughter. Donna Blanca: A Lady of a high Spirit Don Julio's Siſler. Silvia: Elvira's diſguiſed 5\Came, when ſhe Was put to Wait upon Donna Blanca. - Franciſca: Donna Blancas VVoman. s C E N E v. A L E N C I A.

Page Scan 10

- 2. - - w - ---------- - -- ~~~ r - - - - - - *- ar ri { } º C ~ - - - -- - - - "... rº, -w s' - - } (, -- tº ſ' () !. * * * * > * ~ *- : * > sº ....” -- ſi:. . . . . ; ; ; ; ; ; ; ; º 'º' is . j} s' tº r-, …,’ ſ - ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' | C. C.’ liſt’, ‘y ſk) --> \ * > ---. - ..!, f', ſº - - * . . " r - -- - -r * . . . . ... ºf roſ. - ºriº - …sº ...ſi: ; ; iſ ſiſo, i. • • *- … --- … ~ rº • * - -- º - -- - - - - - - - º -- - - - - - . . . . . º. I ºn tºº. . oidº-. . . . . . . . . . sº . ~~~~ - rºº tº Astº tºº, : {} / I, - * - ... ' - - '. * * * - - -, * * * --> * -- : -F * - * … . . . . . . . . . .''...' . . . . . [ICſí2: ... , or ºf f t \ - * - .92ſ, 3. * - * -> " ; * * * .* - *. ‘. - . . ; * * ºt rº, - - - - • * r * > * ~ * º \, \, : ſºrtſ; fiſſio 1 - - - - -- - *** *** **- - - ºr 1. -- f * - - . . . . \\ 3. * {}i ; : { £f Ok i | - . . . - * - - . . tº ºv. "...º.ºrff • * * *** - *"...ºſ. Sº, ºwl'ſ pivſ;2 * - --~ : * : *-** - a . *- º … ſº º ºſey wººt - .* * * * * * 1 ºffſ ºf ſ.ſiſſC' ſ : fºl; Off," i. ^ - - - t / - º -- s .” I O W. H.ſ A W H M 3, Q 2 . " - - - º - * / - - - - - - ~ - - - - - … - - º - º * y > * - / A. - - º – —- -

End of Title Page. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 1
Page 1

- • - O R, - - - - | The worſt not always True: ACT, I. SCENE. I. The Room in the Inn. Enter Don Fernando, and at another door his ſervant Fabio, both in Riding cloathes, Booted. Don Fer. Sº Ave you been with him Fabio,and given him º The Note? . . . : I found him newly gotout of his bed, (pris" ** He ſeem’d much ſatisfied, though much ſur- With your arrival, and as ſoon as poſſibly He can get ready, heel be with youheer. - - - He ſays,he hopes ſome good occaſion brings you To Walencia, and that he ſhall not be At quiet, till he know it. 'Twas not fit º For me, without your Orders, to give him - Any more light, then what your Ticket did. a Don Fer. "Tis well, go now and ſee if Donna Elvira Be ſtirring yet, for I would gladly have her A witneſs, even at firſt, to what ſhall paſs , Betwixt my friend and me, in her concernments: . lf ſhe be ſtill aſleep Fabio, makebold … . - s - - f *— * --~~~~ - - ——- ~~~~~~ `-

Page 2

2. E L V I R.A. To knock, and wake her, whave no time to looſe. - Ohccr ſhe comes, wait you Don Julio, (Enter Donna Elvira. … . . . . (Exit Fabio. Dºn. Blv. Ah, can you think my cares and fleep conſiſtent Slumber and tears, have ſometimes met in dreams, But hearts with ſuch a weight as mine oppreſt, Find ſtill the heavieſt ſleep too light a Gueſt. . . ºfº. Madam, though ſuch, leaſt pity do deſerve, Who by their own unſteadineſs, have drawn *isfortune 9n themſelves; Yet truly Elvira. Such is my ſenſe of Yours, and my compaſſion, To ſee a Lady of your Quality, "T" ºrought tofuchſadextreams, in what is deareſt, šmakesme eydnforgiºmy own reſentment.” - - Granting to Pity, the whole place of Love * - - - º Andatthat ratéile ſerve you. Yet thusiar ºl ºf . . .." You muſt allow th’eruption of a heart. - $9 highly injur'd, as to tell you franckly, . . . Tiso comply with my own Principles ». Qf Honour, nºw, without the leaſt relation Toformer paſſion, ortoformer favours. ...------- Don. Elv. ~p → a ready way to cancel; * * Your ſullen ſilence, during allout journy, . . . . . . . . . . . . . ; ; . Might well have ſparedyoti theſe ſuperfluous words,” tº #. had ſº. º * º º What power, meer appearances, havehad Without examination to deſtroy tº º, . With an umbragious nature, all that Love . * . . . . . . WVas ever able on the ſolid'ſt grounds". 2 ºu º Tofound and to eſtabliſh, Yeºmethinks, ºn ~ : * * A man that boaſts ſuch principles of Honour, ºr gº And of ſuch force to ſway him in his A&ions . . . . . . . In ſpight of ..º. ºn ". - That Honour does oblige waſ raiſe * \ . . . . . . . . . . A. * * º - ." ~. *~~~~-ºf- ~~~~ - -
Page 3

E L P 1 Ra. **offudgement, when ſurpriſingchances ºf Yet unenquired into, tempt gallant men. º º #. º w To prejudicialthoughts of thoſe, with whom ' ' ' They had ſetled friendſhip, upon vertuous grounds. ºt But 'tis from heaveh I ſee; and not from you, º' ºlº :- - Elvira muſt expe&her vindication; : cºſº. " " …, º; Aaduntil then ſubmit to th' hardeſt fate, rºo ºn * iſ That ever can befalăgenerousſpirit, " . . . - Ofbeing oblig'dby him that injuresher, tº **:Nay,ſpeak Elvira.ſpeak, You have me attentive, (with a It were a wonder worthy of your wit," (kind ºffenſiºn. - rest) . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . * * * * - ** Tomake me truſtimy Ears, before my Eyes: " " ºpen. Elv. Thoſe are the witneſſes indeed, Fernando, To whoſe true teſtimonies falſe Inference, º - You ºwe my moderation, and my filence, i. Andthat Ileave it to the gods and time, º, º To make appear both to the worldland you, Cº. º - - - The Maxime falſe,That ſtill the worſt proves true.(Enter Fabio, Fabio. Dew 3 allois withºut: . **. VVaiton him in, tºº, ºn tº Exi, Fabio. - And mnunflºradº gº º ~ . " . . . . . . If you'l be pleas'd to reſt yourſelf a while tºº-ºººº... ". . . -YWithin that Cloſet, you may hear what paſſes].” ". . . ºffiendańme;until ſuch time º *sſby ſome diſcourſehaving prevented º ... v. Tºo great ſurpriſe you ſhalithink fittappear; c. iſ . . . . . . He is the man, (as I have often told you . . . . . . Puring my happydays)for whomalone ºf º I have floreſerves, and 'tis to his aſſiſtance, ſº º 'º tº tº That I muſt owethe means of ſerving you; º, !º , iſ In the conternments of younſafety and honour; thiº ºf . And therefore, Madamºwiłłbeftoogº.º.º. vº' º! I hope, to truſt him with the trusoccaſibbio; ºth 2 º, º That brings me hither, to employ his friendſhip; . . . . . . . .". fºil. B 2. Qbſerving • r tſ .* % - ---
Page 4

4. E L V 1 RA. , Obſerving that reſpešt in the relation, tº gº. . . . . (Colfer. VVhich Iſhall always pay you..."º (Elvira retiring as into theº Don. Elv. There needs no management in the Relation, I am indifferent what others think, º, . . . . . . . . .” " Since thoſe who ought, t'have thought the beſt, have fail'd me tº Sir, I obey, reſign'd up to your condućt, i. º. 9...sº sº. Till Miſtriſs of my own. . . . … 'ri, º, º 'º li(Exit. Enter Don Julio, and Fernando,and he Embrace. . . . Don. Pul. My joy to have my deat Fernando heer . . . . . . So unexpectedly, as great as 'tis A:...º.º.º. . . . . . . . . . Cannot make fulle unſenſible, º' ºr, . . . . . . .” Of th’ injury you have done him, thawe alighted tº . . . º. º. And paſt a night within Walencia, º, . . . . . . . . . . . . . At any other place than at his houſe, tºo º Aº "." Donna Blanca her ſelf, will ſcarce forgive it; ºn tº , º, . VWhen ſhe ſhall know it. º: fºr tº . . yº! 11... ºf A Don. Fer. I hope ſhe's well, toº, siliº ºf Jºãº º £ul. ! She is ſo, thanks to heaven, ... º. ºº ; : " . T. But I muſt bid you expeºf a chiding from her. . . . . . . " Fer. You both, º: well accuſe me of a failure, . . . .” - Did not th'occaſion of my : ---ºl-2 -- . . . -- Bring with it an excuſe, glaſs toojaſt, new ſº tº º jº As you will quickly find. ... ºd variº, ºf Don ful. Nay, then you raiſe diſquiet,eaſe me quickly,” ºr Bytelling me what 'tis; of this be ſure iſ ºntº tº ſºlº. Heart,hand, and fortune, are entirely yours tº ºth rotº, At all Eſſays. ºn Lio, tºo oved 12.) tº 9; 3 ºf º - Fer. It is not new tee, that Iwasa Lover-ºch (After pawfing a Ingaged in all the paſſion, that ere. Beauty, sº (while. , In heigh of it's perfection, could produce, ºf 2:12'' ºtº iſ . And that confirm'd by feaſon, from her wit, ivº º 5. Her Quality, and moſt ºnblemiſh't condućt;...tº ºbeſ. bi, Nor was there more, to juſtifie my love,' tº º ºf Cº gº! Then to perſwademy happineſs, in herº, º cºlº.’.” º - c : Juſt ++- -

End of Section 1. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 2
Page 5

--- --- Juſt correſpondance to it, by all the ways .. Öf honourable admiſſion, that might ſerve - To make eſteem tranſcend the pitch of Love. f Den £ul. Of all this I have not only had knowledge But great participation in your joys; ' ' '.' . . Than which, I thought nothing more permanent, . . .” -- Since founded on ſuch virtue as Elvira's. . . . . . .” * * * Don Fer. Ah, fulio, how fond a creature is the man, That founds his bliſs, upon a womans firmneſs, Even that Elvira, when I thought myſelf Secureſt in my happineſs, nothing wanting To make her mine,but thoſe exterior forms, VVithout which, men of honour that pretend In way of Marriage, would be loath to find Greater conceſſion, where the love is greateſt. As I was fitting with her, late at night, ol. By uſual admittance to her Chamber, y i. As two whoſe hearts in VVed-lock Bands were joyn'd, - And ſeem'd above all other care but how ---- Beſt to diſguiſe things, to a wayward Father, . . . . * - - - tning yward - Till time, and art, might compaſs his conſent ; ; ; ; * * * * A ſuddain noiſe was heard in thinner Boom º Belonging to her Chamber, ſhe ſtarts up . . . - In manifeſt diſorder, and runs in, . . . . . . . Deſiring me to ſtay, till ſhe had ſeen . . . . . . . What caus'd it ; I impatient,follow,” . . . ºf . As fearing for her, had it been her Father : . . . . . . . . . . . My head no ſooner was within the Room, . . . But ſtraight I ſpied behind a Curtain ſhrinking tº 4%º º º - . A goodly Gallant, but not known to me. . . . . . . . . . . . . ilon. £ul. Heavens what can this be?" i. ºº ºo:: jºb Fer. You will not think that there, and at that hour; ſº I ſtay’d to ask his Name, he; ready as I, -- ºr C ºr diº º - To make his Sword thexpreſſer of his mind, …....a.... -- ... . . . ºſmo? l Y a . w we
Page 6

6 E Lºſ R.A. We ſoon determin'd what weſought; I hurt ºf , º, ø r But ſlightly in the arm, befell asſlain . . . tº 120 Run through the body: What Blvira did, . . . . . My rage allow'dºme not to market; But ſtraight º' wº Igot away, more wounded to the heart, "º . . . º: - Then he I left for dead. ...r.º. 3 ºf . , ºf iºn ºf £ul. Prodigious accident! Where can it endº º Fer. I got ſafe home, where carefully conceal’d, - “. I ſought by Fabio's diligence to learn º *... :: 2; ' ' ' ' … " Who myſlain Rival was, and what became "º * Mºsſ ...Of my unhappy Miſtriſs, and what courſe it tº Yº ſº. Don Pedro de Mendoza took to right :, . zºº.º. iii.; , ; ºn of The honour of his houſe, . . . . * * : º " " " ' Don 3 ul. You long'd not moreto knowit then; thenſ tº º ‘Do now. ------ ºf 2: ." … . . . . . . . . . . . . . Don. Fer. All could be learn’t was this, That my Rival." I tº Whom I thought dead, was likely to recover, tºº tº gº And that he was a ſtranger lately come , ſº tº º º -- uptothe Court, to follow ſome pretenſions, º 'º His name he either learn’t not perfºly, oºlºº ołłº cº-lº Ordid not well retains Asſºire, ºr ºil tº That none knew where ſhe was, and that Don Prairs ºf ºbſ: A #adſet a ſtop to proſecution 21ſt . . . . .” - 2 "º In any publick way, with what reſerves 'tº gº ºn tº , Was not yet known. tºº. 9 tº . . . º ºr . . i. ºf Don ful. More and more Intricate, ºr ribºº º' Don Fer. I muſt now come to that, you leaſt would look for.” I had but few days paſt,in my Concealment º' (Reſentment anáRevengeſtill boyling in me) tº gº. -- When late one evening, as Eburied was º 'ººz - In deepeſt thought, I ſuddainly was rows'd tº tº i \, : , sº By a ſurpriſing Apparition; £alie; if 'tº jºi" ºf ºº Elvira in my Chamber, ſpeaking to me!" dº º 'º' bººf. I With rare aſſurance, Thus--- Don Barnande... ."o". º, 3. • , - I come
Page 7

E L 71 RA. - z Icome not heer to juſtifiemyſelf, . . . That were below Elvira, towards one - Whoſe action in deſerting me hath ſhown - - - - - So diſobligingly, his raſh judgement of me. . . . I come to mind you of Honour, not of Love: - , , , Mine, can protećtion ſeek, from none but yours, I've hitherto been ſhelter'd from the Fury Of my enrag’d Father, by my Couſincanilla, But that's no place you eaſily may judge For longer ſtay, I do expect from you To be convey'd, where free from violence And from new hazards of my wounded Fame, I may attend my righting from the gods. - - Don ful. Can guilt maintain ſuch confidence in a Maid " Yet how to think her Innocent, I know not. Don. Fer. Twere loſs of time to dwell on circumſtances, Either of my wonder, or reply ; In ſhort, - What I found honour dićtated, I did, . . . . Within two hours I put her in a Coach, And favour’d by the night, convey'd her fife - Out of Madrid to Ocana, and thence ºf . . . . . . In three days, hitherto Palencia, . . . . . . . . The only place whereby your generous aide, I could have hopes to ſettle and fecure “ . . . . Her Perſon and her honour: That once done . . . Farewelltospain; I'le to the Wars of Milan: ; , , , And there ſoon put a Noble end to cares. . . . . . . . Don £ul. Letus firſt think how to diſpoſe of Her, Since heer you ſay ſhe is 3. That done which preſſes, You will have time toweighallother things. . . . . . Don Fer. My thoughtscan pitchupon noother way Decent or ſafe for her, but in a Convent, . . . . . . . If you have any Abbeſsheer tofriend. . . Tom £ul. I have an Aunt, ruling theºrſulins, tº { : Y ' With:
Page 8

$ - £ L / I F.A. tº -> £xamin'd, in all it's Circumſtances, Wić, whom I have full power, and ſheiswiſe, In caſe that courſe were to be fix't upon 3 But that's not my opinion. Don Fer. What can your reaſon be? -- Don ful. : Laſt remedies, in my judgement Are not to be uſed, till eaſier have been try'd : Had this ſtrange accident, been thoroughly And that from thence, ſhe were convićted guilty, , . . . . . Nought elſe were to be thought on, but a Cloiſter, 'i But as things ſtand, imperfeółly diſcover'd - - - Although appearances, condemn her ſtrongly, - I cannot yet conclude a perſon guilty . . . . . Of what throughout ſo contradićtory ſeems . ‘. . . To the whole tenor of her former life, : , As well as to her Quality, and VVit, - And therefore lets avoide precipitation. -- Let my houſe be her ſhelter for a while, . . . . You know my ſiſter Blanca is diſcreet, . . . . And may betruſted, ſhe ſhallthere beſerv'd - By her and me, with care and ſecrecy. - Don Fer. ThSOffer's kind but no-wiſe practicable, . And might prove Hazardous to Blanca's honour, , , VWhen it ſhould once break out, (as needs it minſt) From ſervants ſeeing ſuch a Gueſt ſo treated. Don Fal. That I confeſs I know not how to anſwer, But could Elvira's mind, ſubmit unto it, I could propoſe a courſe without objećtion. * Don Fer. That ſhe can ſoonreſolve, VWhat is it?ulio f : . Don £ul. A Gentlewoman who waited on my ſiſter, . . . Hath newly left her ſervice for a husband, - - - - And it is known, ſhe means to take another, * -* * I have a ready way to recommendone, By Violante of whoſe love and mine - Yotſ
Page 9

E L V 1 R A. - 9 You are not ignorant,ſince thate’re this . . . . . . We had been Married, had not kindred forc't us . To wait a Diſpenſation for't from Rome’; Blanca I’me ſure will readily imbrace, Any occaſion of obliging her. - Don Fer. That were a right expedient indeed, Could but Elvira's ſpirit brook it. (Enter Elvira as from Elv. You have ill meaſuresof Elvira's ſpirit, (the Cloſet. !Miſtaken Don Fernando: Till heaven's juſtice Shall her entirely to her ſelf reſtore, . The lowlyer ſhape, her fate ſhall hide her under - The more twill fither humor. (Julio ſtarts back as it were amazed Don Julio, aftde. O heavens can guilt with ſuch perfection And put on ſuch aſſurance It cannot be. (dwell ! (Don Julio addreſsing himſelf to her, and beginning. Don £ul. Madam I (She holding out her hand and interrupting Elv. Spare complements, and let your ačtious ſpeak, (him. Thoſe may oblige both him, and me, your words Cannot comply with both. Julio affae, — Did ever yet Such Majeſty with miſcry combine ! But in this Woman. - To her, ——— Madam, Iobey, And ſince you are pleas'd tapprove what I propoſed, No moment ſhall be loſt in th’execution. (Exit Julio, . (Fernando accompanying him and Fabio. Elvira Sola. O how unkindly have the heavens dealt With Woman kind, above all other creatures 1 Qur pleaſure, and our glory! to have placed All on the brink of Precipices, ſuch, As every breath, can blow the leaſt light of us Headlong into,paſt all hopes of Redemption: Nor can our wit, or vertue, give exemption. 'Tis true Ilov’d; But juſtifi'd therein - C By
Page 10

1 O E L V IRA. By ſpotleſs thoughts, and by the objećts merit;" f tº . . . .”. I doºm'd my ſelf above the reach of malice, ºf . º, when in an inſtant by anothersfolly, " . . . . - I am more loſt then any by her own. Accurſt Don Zancho, what occaſion E’re gave Elvira to thy mad Intruſion? " . . . . ūnleſs diſdain, and ſcorn, Incentives are, " º To make men's paſſions more irregular, Ah, matchleſs Rigor,0f the Powers above; Nót only to ſubmit our honours fate, into the vanity of thoſe we love, . . . . . But to the railineſs even of thoſe we hate. " " (Exit. Enter Donna Blanca at one door reading a paper with great marks of Paſsion and Disſturbance, and her Waiting-wo- man Franciſca at another, obſerving her. Blan. Ah, the Traitor . . . . . . . franciſ Affas, -— What can this mean? Blan, continuing, WVasthis thy ſweet Pretenſion at Madrid, Drawn out in length, and hindring thy return? Thy fair pretence, thou ſhould'ſt have ſaid falſe man..... Fran. For loves ſake Madam, what can move you thus 2 plan. For hates ſake ſay, and for revenge Franciſca, " And ſo thou mai'ſ perſwade me to diſcover My ſhame unto thee; Read, read, that Letter; , , º 'Tis from your favourite Chichon. (Franciſca takes the Letter and - The Letter. - , (reads it. : A Adam, to make goºd my engagements ºf concealing nothing # from you, during this abſence of my Maſter; I am bound to ſell you, that ſome ten days ſince, late at night, he was left for dead, run thrºugh the body by another unkhºn Gallant, in the Chamber of a famº Beauty ºf the Court, Whilſt the danger continued, I thought it not fit to let yºu knºw either the accident,or the occaſion ; whº, now he is recover'd and thinking ºf his return to Valencia Imuſ, no longer forbear, I hºpe you will have a care nºt to unde - ** - 7776 -
Page 11

* - E L VI R.A. me for being more faithful to you, them to the Mafter you gave me, . . . . . . ... a.s.l., tº vi., v. Your Sreature Chichen. * Blän. Have ſhºt tºº, think you ! Fram. Madam, this comes of being over curious, And gaining ſervants to betray their Maſters; How quiet might you have ſlept, and never felt VWhat paſt with your Dam Zancho at Madrid'ſ His palé and § looks, at his return . . . Though caus’d by loſs of blood, in the hot ſervice, Of other Dames, might fairly have been thought , Effects of care, and want of ſleep for you ; - And taken ſo,have paſt for new Indeerments. Whoever pryed into anothers Letter? . Or ſlyly hearkn'd to anothers whiſper ? . . . * - But ſaw, or heard, ſomewhat that did not pleaſe him ; , "Twas Eves curioſity, undid us all. Blan. Away with thy moralities dull Creature, I’le make theeſee, and falſe Don % ncho feel, That Blanca's not a Dame, to be ſo treated. But who are thoſe I hear without, who e're . . . They be, they come at an unwell-come hour. ... (Fran, looks out. Fran. Madam, it is a Page of Vialamtes . . . . . - Ulshering a handſome Maid, . . . . . . . . … Enter 4 Page with:4 Letter and #; preſents the " ... ſetter if Blanca, ſhe adreſſes her ſelf to Elvira, and ſhe - throws up her Wail. . . . . . . . - Blan. This Letter is in your behalf fair Maid, (Having read There's no denying ſuch a Recomender, (the Letter. But ſuch aface as yours is, needed none. - - . Page, tell your Lady as much; And you Silvia (Turning (For ſo ſhe ſays you are call'd) be confident Y’are fallen into the handsofone, that knows - How to be kind, more as your friend then Miſtriſs, s C 2 - If - ſ vº
Page 12

1z E L V 1 RA. - If your demeanour, and good nature, anſwer But what your looks do promiſe. - - Elv. Madam, it is the Noble charity (Bythe name of Silvia, - - r - Of thoſe you caſt upon me, not mine own, ". To which Imuſt acknowledge any advantage . . . . . . I ever can pretend to, more then what , gº Fair Piolates mediation gives me. (to Franciſca Blan.Shee'sſtrangely handſom,andhow wellſheſpeaks.(Aſide Frºn. So, ſo, Methinks, you know new comers, Madam, ... Set ſtill the beſt foot forward. tº - - , , , Blan. And know as well that you'decaying Stagers } Are always jealous of new comers, Young, " . . . . And handſome. . . . . Fran. You may be as ſharp upon me, as you pleaſe, f I know to what tattribute your ill humour. * * * * * * * * * - * - - - - - -- - - ^, * f : Blan. Franciſca entertain her, I'legowrite". ºn To Piolante, and then reſt a while . . . . . . . . . . . . In hopes to caſe the headach that hath ſeized me ; , , , , That done, ſweet Silvia we ſhalltalk at leiſure. (Exit Blanca. Fran. Sweet Silvia, kind Epithites are for newfaces: (Aſide. silv, Now comesthe hard part of my task indeed;" " (Aftale. Toad the fellow Waiting-woman right... . . . . . But fince the Gods already have conform'd "º" º º My mind to my Condition, I do hope . . . . .” .."." … They’lteach me words,andgeſtures ſutable.(Fran.embraces Silv. Fran. Let meembrace theemy ſweet Siſter, and beg you. To be no Nigard of a little kindneſs: ". . . A very little ſerves with ſuch a fice,. . . . . . . . To gain what heart you pleaſe. ... . . . . . . . . . silv. If it can help to gain me yours, I’le take it "... " º For the beſt office, that it ever did me, * ~ * º **, And love it much the better. . . . . . . . . . . . ' ' ' Fran. Make muchon't then, for that’t has done already. " ' silv. If you will have me vain enough to think it; º' Y ' ' -- Oll *
Page 13

E L P 1 RA. - - i3 You muſt confirm it, by the proof of being: My kind Inſtructer how to pleaſe my Lady, - For I am very rawe in ſervice. . . . Frazz. O that - I were ſo too, and had thy Youth texcuſe it 3. . . . But my experience, ſiſter, ſhall be yours, - By free communication. Come, let's in And reſt us in my Chamber, there I’le give you - Firſt handſellofthe frankneſs ofmy Nature.(Extunt Sil.gº Fran, Enter Don Zancho and Chichon his man, in riding habit. Don Zam. Imuſt confeſs chichon the very ſmell Of ſweet Valencia, has even revived my ſpirits. There is no ſuch pleaſure, as to ſuck and breath One’s Native air. . - Chich. Chiefly after being in ſo faira way As you, of never breathing any more. - - Don. Zanc. Prithy no more of that; ſince I have forgot it, . . Methinks thou eaſily may'ſt. Chich. Faith hardly Sir, whilſt ſtill your ghaſtly face. Doth bear, ſuch diſmal Memorandums of it; Apter to raiſe inquiſitiveneſs in thoſe Know nothing of the matter, then tallay Remembrance in Partakers. - - Don Zanc. Heaven ſhield us from Donna Blanca's queries, No matter for the reſt. 2. Chich. You would not wiſh to find her ſounconcern'd, I’me ſure you would not ; Faith, I long to hear - Th’ingenious defeats, I make account: . You are prepared to give to her ſuſpicions. - Don Zanch. Let me alone for that: but on thy life . Be ſure that nothing be ſcrued out of thee, ... . . . . . . . Neither by her, nor by her ſly Franciſca. - Chich. Be you Sir, ſure, that from your true Chichon, . They'l know no more today, then yeſterday, .. w m 2’
Page 14

i4 - E L Yi R.A. They did, nor thence, more to the world; end, tº r ºn Then what they did, before we left Madrid. . . . .'; º' Don zinc. Truly Chichon, we needs muſt find the means ºf Toget a fight of her this very night; ----- . . . . 'A I die if I ſhould miſs it. : " . . . . . . . . . * . . . . . . . Chich, Laſt week left gaſping for Elvira's love, tº º And ſcarce revived, when preſently expiring . . . . For Blanca's again ; I did not think Don Cupid -- Had been a Merchant, of ſuch quick returns. . Den Zanch. Thou art an Aſs, and want'ſt diſtinétiveneſs Twixt love and love; that was a love of ſport, To keep the ſerious one in breath. - - - . . . . . . . Chich. Faith Sir, I muſt confeſs my ignorance, That when I ſaw you groveling in your blood, l thought your Love had been in ſober ſadneſs. ** : Don Zanch. Prithy leave fooling, and let's carefully iſ Gain the back way intomy houſe unſeen, That none may know of my return, till Blanca - - Find meather feet ; and be you induſtrious T'obſerve Domžalio's going forth this evening, Doubtleſs hee'ſ keep his uſual hours abroad At Violantes, ſince not married yet:---- - - ..Chich. I ſhall obſerve your orderspunétually. (Exeunt. Enter Don Julio and knocks as at Blanca's door. Don £ul. What Siſter 1 at your sieffa already ? if ſo You muſt have patience to be wak'dout of it, . . . . . . . . For I have news to tell you. - - (Enter Blanca, Blan. No Brother, I was much more pleaſinglycº Employ'd, inſerving you ; that is, making ---> * My Court to Violantº, by receiving ºf To wait upon meià Lucilla's place, º, . " ... * * - * - - - - * --- A Gentlewoman of her reº6mending." . . . . . . Dam. Pul. Where is ſhe let me ſee her. . . Blam. :Tºwere not ſafe, 9. Cº. ºf . She

Page 15

E L V 1 R A. 15 She is too handſome ; Youthink now Ijeſt; But without Rallery, ſhe is ſo lovely, That were not Violante very aſſured Of her own Beauty, and the ſtrong Ideas - That ſtill upholds within you, one might queſtion Her wit, to have ſet her in her Gallant's way. - But what's the news you mean - ful. That our dear friend and kinſman Don Fermando Is come to Town, and going for Italy: ' , , - - The ſecret of it, doth ſo much import him, ". . . . . It forc'thim to forbear alighting here, And lodging with us asheuſed to do; . . . - But yet he ſays, nothing ſhall hinder him ... From waiting on you in the dusk of th’eyeping : - I hope you'lfind wherewith to *...*. Blhh. As well as you have drain'd my Cabinets, Of late in preſents to your Miſtriſs, ſome - - - - . . . . Perfumes willyet be found, ſuch as atrone * . * It'ſ ºf, ſhall not diſgračeňalencia. - - - - - - Dan ful. I know your humour, and that the beſt preſent . Canbegiven you, is to give you the occaſion - - Of preſenting 5. But I am come in now . Only to advertiſe you, and muſt be gone ; Yet not I hope without a fight of One So recommend, and commended ſo. - - • Blan. I ſhould have thought you ſtrangely chang'd in humour Should you have gone away ſo uncuriouſly. - - -- Fran. Ho. - (she knocks. - . . Enter Franciſca. . - - Fraň. What pleaſe yau Madºm. . Blan. Prithy tell Silvia i wouldºeak with her. (Exit Fran. (to ful.) Well, cleer your Eyes, and ſay I have no skill - If ſhe appears not tye exceeding handſome. - ‘’’ ‘’’. > - - Enter w
Page 16

16 - E L V I (R.A. - Enter Franciſco with Silvia, º, . Julioſalutes her. - D.jul. Welcome fair Maidinto this Family, - . . Where whilſt you take a ſervants name upon you . . . . . . . To do my Siſter honour, you muſt allow - -- It's Maſter to be yours,and that by ſtrongeſt Tyes Knowing who plac't you here, and having Eyes. Silv. I wiſh my ſervice Sir, to her and you, . May merit ſuch a happy Introduction. D. ful. Farewell Siſter, till anon, Accompanied As now you are,I think you'l miſs me little. (Exit Julio. ... Blan. I muſt confeſs I ne'er could better ſpare you (Aſide. Then at this time, but not for any reaſon That you I hope can gueſs at. --- Franciſca,you and Silvia may retire (To them. (Extant Silvia And entertain your ſelves; I’le to my Cloſet (and Franciſca. And try to reſt. - orrahertoven freely My reſtleſs thoughts. O the ſelf-torturing part (Aſide. To force complaiſance from a jealous heart. (Exeunf. - ------------" " A CT. II. SCAENE changestothe Roominthe Inn. Enter Don Julio, and Don Fernando. Don Pul. A Lbricias friend, for the good news 1 bring you, - All has falled out as well as we could wiſh. As to Elvira's ſetling with my Siſter, So lucky a ſucceſs, in our firſt aims - Concerning her, I truſt does boad good fortune - - Beyond

End of Section 2. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 3
Page 17

__------ - - º * * * .* - w r E L V1 r 4. 2 #. our hopes; yet, inthe further progreſs O - - this Affair. , Don Fer. There's no ſuch thing in Nature left as better, £ulie, The worſt proves always always true with me, Yet prithy tell, how does that Noble beauty (Wherein high Quallity is ſo richly ſtamp't) . Comporther #. Metamorphoſis. A. - D. ful. As one, whoſe body, as Divine as 'tis, Seems bound to obey exactly ſuch a mind, And gently take, what cre ſhape that impoſes. D. Fer. Ah, letus mention her no more, my julio Ideas flow upon me too abſtracted - ~ * From her unfaithfulneſs, and may corrupt The firmeſt reaſon; Above all be ſure - t I do not ſee her ſo transform’d, eaſt that - Without ſeeing her. - De £ul. But if you intend the honour Leave that to me Fernando, Transform me too, Ple rather paſs with Blanca, Both for unkind and rude, And leave Valencia \ to my Siſter . . . . It will be time, the night draws on a pacc. Fer, Come let's be gone then, (As they are going out, - Fab. Stay Sir, for heaven's ſake ſtay J (Enter Fabiohaftily. D. Fer. — Why what's the matter Fab. That will ſurpriſe you both, as much me Don Pedro de Mendoca is below . - Newly alighted. D. Fer. — Ha, what ſay'ſt thou Sirrah . . . Elvira's father Fab. - Sir, the very And he had ſcarcely ſet one foot to ground (, * - º - º , ſ ſame, - When he enquired, where lives Don julio Rocca? , P. ful. For my houſe Fabio It cannot be, * I never knew the man. . . . . D D. Fºr, -
Page 18

18 , E L V I R A. D. Fer. The thing does ſpeak it ſelf, and my hard fate What elſe can bring him hither, but purſuite Of me, and of his Daughter, having learn’t The way we took, And what ſo eaſie Fulio Here at Valencia, as to know our friendſhip And then of conſequence, your houſe to be My likelieſt retreat. D. ful. 'Tis ſurely ſo, * Let us apply our thoughts to beſt preventives. D. Fer. Whil'ſt we retire into the inner Room T'adviſe together, Fabio be you ſure - - (Since unknown to him) to obſerve his motions. (Exeunt emnes, Scene changes to the Enter Don Zancho and Chichon as in the Proſpecis of Valencia. ſtreet meer Don Julio's houſe. D. Zanc. — Newly gone out ſay you That is as luckey as we could have wiſhed, And ſee but how invitingly the door Stands open ſtill. - --- chich. An open door may lead to a face of wood, (Aſide (To Don Zancho, - * / But mean you Sir, to go abruptly in Without more ceremony - D. Zane. Surprize redoubles (fool) the joys of Lovers; But ſtay Chichon let's walk aſide a while - * Tillyonder Coach be paſt. (Excunt. Scene changes to the Enter Don Julio and, Room in the Inn. - * - a . Don Fernanda. . . . D. jul. There is noſafiyin any other way, You muſt not ſtir from hence, until whave got Some further light, what courſe he means to ſteer, . . . . --- -
Page 19

* - E L / I R.A. 19 Let Fabio be vigilant, I'le get home, . Down that backſtairs, and take ſuch order there Not to be found, in caſe he come to enguire, As for this Night at leaſt, ſhall break his meaſures, And in the morning weel reſolve together - Whether you ought, to quit Walentia or no. D. Fer. Farewell then for to night, I'le be alerte, - But ſee y'excuſe me fairely to my Cozen. . . . (Exeumt. Scene changes to Blanca's - Enter Donna Blanca and : Antechamber. . . . . Franciſca. D. Blan. As well as Silvia pleaſes me Franciſca, I'megladat preſent that ſhe is not well, - She would conſtraine me elſe, ſhe has wit enough To deſcant on my humour, and from thence To make perhaps diſcoveries, not fit. For ſuch new Comers. - Fran. If ſhe has wit ſhe keeps it to her ſelf, At leaſt from me, of pride, and Melancholly I ſee goodſtore. ** D. Blan. – Still envious and detračting Enter Don Zancho and Chichon. See who comes there Madam, to ſtop your mouth. Donna Blanca caſting an Eye that way, and Chichon clinging up cloſe behind his ºff. and making a mouth. Chic. Shas ſpideus, and it thickens in the cleer, - I fear a ſtorm * Goes not your heart pit a pat? (*To his Maſter. D. Blan. Ah, the bold Traytour ! But Imuſt diſſemble, (Aſide. And give his impudence a little Line, • - The better to confound him. - . . . . : Donna Blanca advancing to him, and as it were em- sº bracing him with an affected cheerfulneſs. P. Blam. Welcome, as unexpeãed, my D. zancho. - - D 2 - D, Zancho ^ * : - - * -
Page 20

2O E L V 1 R A. - 2 * - , - - * D. Zame. Nay, then we are ſafe Chichon. (Aſide to Chichon. Incomparable Maid, heaven bleſs thoſe Eyes, (to Her. From which I find a new life ſpringing in me; Having ſo long been baniſh't, from their Rays, How dark the Court appear'd to me without them Could it have kept me from their Influence, As from their light, I had expired long ſince. D. Blan. Y'expreſs your love now, in ſo courtly a Stile I fear you have ačted it in earneſt there, - And but rehearſe, to me, your Country Miſtreſs. * - Don Zant. Ah, let chichon but tell you, how he hath ſeen me During my abſence from you. – - - Chic. I vow 1 have ſeen him even dead for Love, You might have found it in his very looks, Before you brought the blood into his Cheeks. D. Blan. E’ne deadyou ſay for Love, but ſay of whom * Don Zanc. Can Blanca ask a queſtion ſo Injurious? As well to her own perfections, as my Faith. - - Don. Blan. I can hold no longer." (Aſide to Franciſca. My faithful Lover, then it is not you. (To him ſcornfully. Chic. She changestone I like not faith the Key, (4ſide tº his The muſick will be jarring:----". . . . . . (Maſter. Blan. 'Tis not then you, Don Zancho,who having chang'd Lºontinues.] His ſure at Court, into a love Pretenſion, ; 5 ind his Concurrents,into a Gallant Rival, Fell by his hand, a bloody Sacrifice At his fair Mitreſs feet, Who was it then . . . . . . . . . . Don Zando' Chichon behind his Maſter hºlding up his ſtands a while hand; and making a pitiful face, Franciſca. as amazed with ſteals to him, and holding up her hand - folded Armſ. 's ... threatningh. . . . . Fran. A Blab chichon, a Pickthank, Peaching Varlet (Aftde Nerethink to look mein the face again... ... (To Cliº. . - - ..." - - #6. * . - ~ - -
Page 21

-------- / - . - - . . E L P 1 (RA. 21 , chie. In what part ſhall I look thee,haſt thou a worſe? (Aſide It is the Dive! has diſcover'd it, * - (To Fran. Some Witthdwells here, I’ve long ſuſpected thee. ... --~ Fran. I never more ſhall think thee worth my Charms. . D. Blan. What, ſtruck dumb with guilt? Perfidious Man That, happens moſt, to the moſt impudent º When once detected; Well, getthee hence, And ſee thou nere preſum'ſt to come again Within theſe Walls, or I ſhall let thee ſee - 'Tis not at Court alone,where hands are found, Tolet ſuch mad men blood. - - She turns as going away, and Don Zancho holds her gently by the gown. Don Zanche. Give mebut hearing, Madam, and then if— Don £ul. What ho, no lights below ſtairs? (Alowd as below. Fram. O heavens, Madam, here you not your Brother, Into the Chamber quickly, and let them * - Retire behind that hanging,there's a place, . . . . Where uſually we throw neglected things. * - I’le take the lights, and meet him certainly His ſtay will not be kng from Violante . . . . At this time of the Night;beſides you know, He never was ſuſpicious. - - Don Zancho and Chichongo behind the hanging, and - Donna Blanca retiring to her Chamber ſays. D. Blan. Capricious fate, muſt I who whilſt I lov’d him Nere met with checking Accident, fall now - - Into extreameſt hazards, for a man Whom I begin to hate. - - 2. (Exit. And Franciſca at another durwith the lights, (Franciſca re-enters with Don Julio. . . . D. ful. Where's my Siſter - '' . . . . . . Fran. —- In her Chamber, Sir, - - Not very well, ſhe's taken with a Megrum, ". - - - D. ful.
Page 22

22 - E L VI R A. D. jul. Light me In to her. . . . * ... (Exit Don Julio. * : (Franciſca lighting bin with one of the lights. (Chichon peeping out from behind the hanging. Chic. If this be Cupids Priſon, 'tis no ſweet one, - Here are no chains of Roſes, Yet I think Y’ had rather b'in’t, then in Elvira's chamber As gay, and as perfum’d as 'twas, - D. Zan. Hold your peace Puppy, is this a time for fooling? Enter Franciſca and Chichon ſtart's back. - Franciſca Chichon lookout, you may, the Coaſt is cleer. coming to the hanging. ( Chichon looks 6!/?. Could I my Lady's neer concerns but ſever, From yours in this occaſion, both of you Should dearly pay your falſhood. - Cich. You are jealous too, I ſee, but help us out This once, and if you catch me here again, Lct Chichon pay for all, faithful Chicbon. Fran. Y'are both toolucky, in the likelihood Ofgetting off ſo ſoon, ſtay but a moment Whilſt Igodown to ſet the Wicket open, And ſee that there be nobody in the way. (Exit Franciſca. Chich. It is a cunning Drab, and knows her trade. . (Re-enter Franciſca and comes to the banging. Fran. There's now ſome Witch a wing indeed Chichen, £ulio, that never till this night, forbore To#. to Violantese're he ſlept, . . . . - And paſs ſomehours there, fulio who never . . . . . Inquired after the ſhutting of a door, - . . . Hath lock’t the Gate himſelf, at's coming In, And bid a ſervant waitbelow till midnight, With chargetoſay, to any that ſhould knock And ask for him, that hee's gone ſick to bed 3 . . . . . What it can mean I know not. - - chic, I would I did not, but, I have too true -
Page 23

E L / 1 R A. 23 An Almanack in my bones, foretell's a beating , a. Far ſurer then fowl weather, he has us faith - Faſt in Lobb's Pound; Heaven ſend him a light hand, To whom my fuſtigation ſhall belong, - As for my Maſter, he may have the Honour To be rebuked at ſharp. . - . Fran. May terror rack this Varlit; But for you Sir, Be not diſmay’d, the hazard's not ſo great, Yonder Balcon at further endo'the' Room Opens into the Street, and the deſcent, is Little beyond your height, hung by the Arms: When £ulio is aſleep, Iſhall not fail Tocome and let you out, I keep the Key, In the meanwhile you muſt have patience. º - Chic. It were anaſty hole to ſtay in long, 2. (Aſide. - Did not my fear correót it's evil ſavour. T Dame, you ſay well for him, with whom Ithink . . (To her. Yºhave meaſur'd length, you ſpeak ſo punétually Of his dimenſions; But I ſee no care For me, your prity, not your proper man, Who does abhor feats of activity. Fran. I'le help, you, with a halter. (Exit Franciſca and , - (Chichon retires. Scene changes to Blanca's Bed-Chamber. - Enter Blanca, Silvia,and ſoon after Franciſca as in Blanca's Chamber ſhe ſitting at her Toylet undreſſing. - Blan. My Brother told me I ſhould ſee him again, , Before he went to reſt. - - Fram. I think, I hear him coming. - - - Blanca to Hee’l not ſtay long I hope, for I amonthorns Franciſca, Till I know they are out, I’th’ mean while We muſt perſwade silvia to go to bed, - • - - Leaſt
Page 24

14 E L V IRA. Leaſt ſome odd chance ſhould raiſe ſuſpicion in her Before I know her fitneſs for ſuch truſts. - - - f -- Enter Don Julio. ~ . - . . . . . (Silvia ºffers to umpin her Gorget. D Blan. I prithy Silvia, leave, and get thee gone º To Bed, you ha’nt been well, nor are not yet 3 Your heavy Eyes betray indiſpoſition: D. Sil, Good Madam, ſuffer me, twill make me well To do you ſervice. - - Blam. Brother, I ask your help, [º P. fºliº] Take Silvia hence, and ſee her in her Chamber, This night ſhe muſt be treated as a ſtranger, ... And you muſt do the honour of your houſe. - - (Julio goes to Silvia, and taking her by:- . the hand leads her away. Sil. [nating Since you'l not yet let me begin to ſerve, a lºw ºffel I will begin to obey. - Fran. [bridling.] Quaint in good faith. * - D. Ful. [to silvia My Siſter's kinder then ſhe thinks,to give me * * hººds her.] This opportunity of telling Silvia. s How abſolutely Miſtriſs in this place - Elvira is. - w * - (Franciſca whiſpers all this while with Blanca. Silv. Good Sir, forget that Name. . . . . - - - (Exeunt Julio and Silvia. D. Blan. If that be ſo, what ſhall we do Franciſca - What way to get them out 2 - Fran. It is a thing ſo unuſual with him, - It raiſes ominous thoughts, Elſe I make ſure . . . . . . . To get them off, as well as you can wiſh, . . . But if already awaken'd by ſuſpition, - Nothing can then be ſure. . . . . D. Blan. O fear not that what you have ſeen him do of \ .

End of Section 3. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 4
Page 25

E Evi R2 is Of unaccuſtom’d, I dareſay relates . . . . . . . . . . To quite another buſineſs. . . . . . - ** . * - . . ; H ºf: - tº º ~" - ... ... is Fran, Then ſet your heart at reſt, from all diſturbance. * a “... as " " : • e - Ariſing from this accident. egº. Aléºlºr--- If you are certain, To get them tº ſo clear, from obſervation, 'Twill out of doubt be beſt, I tell my Brother Don Zancho is return'd, and had call'd here This evening to have ſeen him, For my fears. Sprange only from the hour, and the ſurprize, Warm'd as he then had found me, ſince you know How little apt he is to jealouſie. - Fran. Madam, Yºhave reaſon, that will make all ſure, In caſe he ſhould be told of's being here -The time of's ſtay, can hardly have been noted. - - Enter Don Julio. . D. ful. As an obedient Brother I have perform'd What you commanded me. . D. Blan. A hard Injunétion from a cruel Siſter, To wait upon a handſome Maid to her Chamber. D. ful. You ſee I’ve not abuſed your Indulgence By ſtaying long, nor can I ſtay indeed - Wihyou, I muſt be abroad ſo early . . . . Tomorrow morning, therefore Dear good night. Donna Blanca Stay Brother, ſtay, I had forgot to tell you . . [* he is going] Don Zancho de Menezes is return'd And call'd this evening here, t'have kiſs'ſ your hands, Franciſca ſpake with him. - - D. ful. I hope he's come ſucceſsful in his ſute, To morrow I’le goſee him, (Exit D. Julio. D. Blan. You ſee he'sfree from Ombrageon that Subject. Fran. Iſee all's well, and may he ſleep profoundly, The ſooner Madam, you areabed, the better. D. Blan. Would once my fears were over, that my Rage Might have it's courſe. . * , . * * - E. - Fram,
Page 26

26 - E L VI (R.A. * - Fran. . I ſhall not ſtop it, "...”. I , tººlſ; , ºn 1C: But after it hashad it'sfull Careere,. . . . º, Twill pawſe I hope,and reaſon findan Bar, (extant. Scene changes to the Enter Don Ferhande Room in the Inn. andrºio. " - . . . . . . . . . . . . . . JJ ! i i" ' ". D. Fer. Ishe gone out 2 … . . . . . . s Fab. — No Sir, not as yet, " " " ' " " ' But ſeeing the ſervant he had ſent abroad tº ". . . . . . . . Newly return'd, I liſten’d at his door, . . .” - " " ' " -: And heard him plainly give him this account. * * * * * That he had found Don Julio Rocca's houſe, . . . . . . And having knock'd a good while at the door, Anſwer was made him without opening it, . . . . Don Julio's not at home, where at Doa Pedro Impatient roſe, and calling for his Cloak -- And Sword, he ſwore he'd rather wait himſelf . Till midnight at his door, then looſe a night - In ſuch a preſſing buſineſs; This I thought Fit to acquaint you with, and that he ſpake . . . . . . Doubtfully of his returning to lodge here. . . - D. Fer. You have done well, but muſt do better yet In following him, and being ſure to looſe - * , No circumſtance of what he does. . . . . . Fab. To dog him, poſſibly mightbe obſerv'd * . This Moon light, by his ſervant, but ſince Sir, s W’are certain whether he goes, my beſt courſe - I think will be to go out the back way, And place myſelf before hand in ſome Porch, Near fulio's houſe, where I may ſee and hear . . . . . What paſſes, and then do as I ſhallſee cauſe. . . . * * * D. Fer. 'Tis not ill thoughton, but how late ſoever Your return be, I ſhall expect to ſee you - Before we goto bed. . - t - . . . . - , Fab,
Page 27

E. L. P. I (R-4. 2× 2 Fab. - I ſhall not fail. º: triº Jº (Exeunt. - * , , , , •º-ºº. … L'...' . * - * - ' Scene alºngeſ tº º * \} Enter Franciſca and goes to the | Donna Blanca's .2ſ 9 hanging where Don Zancho } Ante-Chamber. " . . . and Chichon are hid. Pran. Ho, truſty ſervant with his faithful Maſter, ~ Some out, the Baléone's open, looſe notime, £ulio's abed, and faſt a ſleepe're this, • * There's nobody in the ſtreet, it is ſo light , One may diſcover a mile, therefore bé quick. Scene changes to the pro- Don Zancho and Chichon come ſ” ºf Valencia. out frºm behind the hanging and s - follow her as leading them to the “ , . . . . Balcone. - (Exeunt. ** Fabio 4 in the And ſoon after Don Zancho and ſtreet, and ſetling Chichon appear as in the Balcone, *ſelf in a Forch, and Franáſcasi.ad as peeping out of the door into it. Fab. Here is a Porch as if 'twere builton purpoſe. - - (Fabio looking up perceives them in the Balcone. Ha, here's a viſion that I little dream't of, , " ` Stand cloſe Fabio,and Mumm. * Donžanchoget's over the Balcone,andletting himſelf down *** *nd, leaps gently into the street, Chichon offers ºr at the like, but takes a fall as he lights, and riſing cohn- terfeits lameneſs. | - - - * : * > . - ** * , , º * > . . . º (Franciſca retires and locks the Balcone. *. Curſe on the Drab, I think I've brokemy leg. . E 2 " " Fat.
Page 28

28 E L7, I (R.A." Fab. The Moon has turn'd my brains, or I've ſeen . .”.” That perſon ſome where, and that very lately. (He #. ſcratching his head." But ſure I'me mad,tothink it can be he. - . . . . . . T Exeunt Don Zancho and Enter Don Pedro and Fulvio. Chichon as turning down the next Sreet. - Fabio Cretiring into the Porch..] O now I ſee my mem. D. Ped. This is the Street you ſay; which is the houſe: Fulv. That fair one over againſt the Monaſtery 5. - - - Shall I go knock - iſ D. Ped. What clſe? (Fulvio knocks as at Don Julio's door,and no body anſwers. D. P. Knock harder. (He knocks again,and one asks as from within who's there. D. Ped. A ſtranger, who muſt needs ſpeak with Don £ulio. Although unknown to him, my buſineſs preſſes. *Whoe're you be, and whatſoe're your buſineſs, [*From You muſt have patience till to morrow Sir, (within. Don julio went ſick to bed, and I dare not Wake him. - --" D. Ped. Fortune takes pleaſure ſure, in diſappointing, when men are preſt with moſt impatience, But ſince there is no remedy, guide Fulvio, Unto the lodging y'have provided for me, I hope 'tis nere at hand. - Fulv. Not above three doors from Don £ulio's * There where it makes the corner of the Street. I*Pointing. Fabio Here I muſt follow till I’ve harbour'd them. [ſtealing after them J. . . . - (Exeant. Scene changes to the Enter Don Fernando alone as in Raom in the Imm. his Chamber. - - _ D. Fer. It cannot now belong, ere Fabio come, - - ...And
Page 29

§§§ {^ 4 39 And twere in vaine to go to bed before, ſº . . . . . . .” Forreſt I’me ſure I ſhould not. º bout th. º oft . . . .iv. (He walks about the Room penſively. Ah, my Elvira, I Mijº oſt . o ºil ºn 1 - || ". My very words with falſhood when I name thée: , , , , , , , , Did ever Miſtreſs make a Lover pay to ſº, , , , .º. So dear as I,for the ſhort bliſs ſhe gave? . . . . . . . . What now I ſuffer in exchange of that, . . . . . May make mankind, a fear'd of joyes exceſſive . . . But here he comes. . . . . . . . . [.,..., , (Enter Fabio. . . . . . . . . . . . (* To Fabio. * Have you learn't anything, a That's worth the knowing . . . . . . . . . . - , Fab. Two things, Ithink conſiderable Sir ; The one, that?aliohath found meanstogain . . . This night to caſt your buſineſs in, without Admitting of Don Pedro, whoſe preſſures . . . . Might have been troubleſome, And urged you To haſty reſolutions, whereas now - Y'have time to take your meaſures. The other Sir, v 1. Is, that Don Pedro lodges here no more, … . . . . . And conſequently hath eaſed you of conſtraint Whilſt you reſthere, and left the way more free, For intercourſe betwixt Don fulio and you, , . . . . This more I muſt obſerve t'ee, that Don Pedra . . . . . Took foecial care to have his lodging nereº ~ : Don £ulio's houſe, whereby 'tis evident, That there he makes account his buſineſs lies. - D. Fer. The news you bring me, hath been worth your pains And thanks t'ee for't, Iſuppoſe that is all. - - Fer. Say Fabio, what is't Fab. Pray, Sir, allow me A This night to think, whether it be fit or no To tellit you, ſince 'tis a thing relates not As I conceive to you, nor to your buſineſs, And - - - \ ... • X - v - " ", ! * * * *- - - -- - r - - • * * - - -
Page 30

3o a £º ſº. tº A And yet in the concernments of ano ićr'. . . º 1. May trouble you. A- dº * *11, i ºn "... * Fºr. *Renéroverwiſe ºrithee, }}. know *::\º ºrn." A What 'tis, ſinceydūhavérºiſéïcurk fity". º ºn tº By ſuch Grimaſſes; * I fixiº, º º º: . . ." Fab. You muſt be obey'd, but pray remember Sir, ' ' '. If afterwards l'am call'd fool, for my pains, , , . " Who made meſo, but ſince I do not onely iſ Expect the fool, but ready to be thought" " ' ". . . . . A madmañ too, e're I have done my ſtory “ . . . . . . . . In this I will be wilful, not to tellit - Tilly’are a bed, that 1 may run away So if you long to here it haſten thither. , - º 'º (Exit Fabio as to the Chamber within. I). Fer. Contentifiéyòuskić greatcompliance. (Extant. w . ºf . .r Scene changes to the Room: , Enter Don Zancho, And Chi. in Don Zancho'shouſe. ... chon as a home halting. . D. zan. W’are well come off from danger, would we were it But half as well, from Blanca's jealouſie.” ---- chic. Speak for your ſelf, I never came off worſe, Apox upon your Venery, it has made me . . . . . . . . Another Vulcan. . . . . . . (He halts about grumbling. D. Zarc. Go reſt, to night, or grumble, as you pleaſe, But do not think, limping ſhall ſerve your turn Tomorrow, faith I’le make you ſtir your ſtumps, , . . . . Think you a Lover of my temper likely } ^* To fit down by it ſo . . . . . . . . . . . . . Chiº. I’me ſure I am only fit to ſit down by it, "... Since Icanhardly ſtand. . . . . . - - (He makes as if he would ſit down, and Don Zancho. giving him a kick in the britch. -1. D. Zane. Coxcomb come away. . . . . . . . . Chic. Tonight's, to night, to morrow's a flew day. ( *::::: - ... . . CT. - - - - - - - - - - - - - /
Page 31

B L * FRA # . . . . . . . Enter Don Fernando and Fabio, ºn !.2 As in the Room in the Inn. J. - 3: ... º. : , :9%;"C", ſº ºliſ, ºo, ºniº & • *A*: All things ready Tabić, iigaſeº cH .º. Danjulie when he comes conclude with me.’ ‘, ‘ That I ſhould begon preſently. ... *...ſi: . . . . . . . c. tº Tab. Horſes ſtand ready for you at the poſtoſ. º t ... Fer. 'Tis well, attend without, toº synobiy. (Éxitºſabig, - ..º.º. Enteriſ)onikulio.º ic tº gº ºn. To ful. I ſee you ſleep not in your friends concerns, s You are ſo early, and ſince ſo, the ſoonero ºr ſº tº 2, We fix a Reſolution, certainly, nº iſ . . . . . nº . . . . . 'Twill be thebetter, 'Twas no ſmall Point gained, ſº ſº. To fruſtrate for a night Don Pedrº's aims,º ſº . ſº As Fabio tellsme you have done, for he ſº Nere quitted him an inch laſt night, until . . . . . . . . . He had harboured him. . . nº f ... " ºw - £ut, What, has he left his lodging Pºº ſº....., , , , o - 4- . F. : ºrrºrſ to sº. - \ A C T.O." III. ºfoſſ ºf . . . . . . . . . . . . . º' tºi"; sº ºf . , , * -- r is ** * * - -- -- Fer: --— That he has, ſº ſº. a 2, ... . . . . Andwhich is more conſiderable taken one g : . . . . Cloſe by your houſe, which evidences cleerly tº . . . . Where his ſuſpicions lie ; That being ſo, º . . . . . . I’me confident, you'l be of my opinion ºf , ºr 1, .. For my diſlodging from Valentia - a ºn . . . Immediately, For Elvira being . . . Already ſo well ſetled, nothing can So much indanger her diſcovery, . . . . . . . . As my remaining longer in theſe parts. ...<r: º, . jul, Were Ibut free as yeſterday Fernando, alº º : º . º To think of nothing but Elvira and your Concernments, I muſt confeſs your abſence - Frºm hence were to be wiſhed, but Couſin, tº ... . . . {{ 3. . - - - : ; S.
Page 32

# B L V 18.4. Ther's fallen out this very night, a thing, . Which ſhews how little Ibeholding am . . To fortune, That having ſo newly lent me The means of ſerviúghandſonhly my friendſ assº Calls back the debt already; and ſnak's mé N. As needing of your aide, as you of mine. - - Fer. Hö, Fäbioforbid the horſes preſently. 'I (Fabio looks in. Tº Jul: The ſcaſt appearance Julie of my being, ſº uſeful to you, by ſtaying, puts an end. …. .o. ºlioſ, ºr To all deliberation; for myſelf, tº of Say, what'sthe accident? You have me ready. Hºw iſ , , , ful. Such, and of ſuch a fiature, my Fernando, That as to be communicated to hone. ..., sº Put you, anotherſelf, ſo Iamſure: º, ø, º]. Tº a 3-5 ºr “” It will aſtoniſh you with the Surpriſal. 2: … ºolº'ſ a xi, ºr Ah! could you think it poſſible? that Blanca, º cº, sº II ºf Should raiſe diſturbance in the heart of julio, a tº " As tothe honour of his Family. * . . . . . . . . . Fer. Heavens forbid. . . . . . . . . . . . Jºiºsº...” £ul. Never was Brother ſo ſecure as I, , ; ; , III, Or ſo unalterable in his perſwaſion ºf , º, º 'º - Of having a Siſter, of unmatch't diſcretion; : G - ...A., Nor e're, could leſs, then evidence itſelf, . . . . . . Have ſhaken ſuch a confidence. . . . . . . . . . . ." Fer. For Gods ſakejulio, . . . . . . . . Hold meno longer in ſuch pain of mind; . . . tº º *_--- * - - - - I] . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . " - - - - - - - > ------ - - -- -- -- But ſure we ſhall be better there withi (Exit Julio, Free from the noiſe of the Street. . . . . . ful. You ſay well. º Fernando This is what Fabio told me he ſaw laſt night, a [*b*tolowshim Aſide..] Diſcovered by ſome accident to £ulie, ſº It can be nothing elſe, Owomen! Women I (Exit Fernando. Enter Don Pedro and Fulvio, 2. As in their new lodgingſ. Don Ped. I am glad you have lighted on ſofit space, . r - Or
Page 33

- ... E.H. K. R.A. 3, For all I intend, as this is, Fulvio, sº * . . -- . Iſhall repair the laſt nightsdiſappointment . . . . . . By early care this morning, In the meanwhile, ' ' '. " t Tail not of your partin the diſcovery . . . . . Wheremy Enemy dwells, and i'th obſervation, , Of all his motion's, That'sth' important part. , Ful. Relie, Sir, on my care and Vigilance. . (Extunt Don Pedro and Fulvio. * Enter Don Julio and Don Fernando, . . . As in the outward Room ºf the Inn. #ul. — It is a Quarter, , , Always reſerv'd to my own privacy, ' ". . . . - There lying unſuſpected, if whil'ſt I rº Continue late abroad under pretence . . . . . . . . . . of being atºplantes, You keepwatch " ' ". -- Carefuſly within, he cannot ſcapeus ' ' ' ' ' ' " , So you be ſure t'obſerve punctually . . " ", The ſign agreed, and boulting of the doors, *, '' . . . When he is once within, " . . . . . . . . . . . . . Fer. Since youhaveforeſolvdand laid your buſineſs, - , - is tº a * ; : ---- r- Diſpoſe of me, and leadthe way, whilſt I" ºf “º Give Fabio his inſtructions what to do . . . . During my abſence. (Exeunt Fernando and Julio. Enter Dona Blanca and Franciſ a As in Blanca's Ante Chamber. Fran. Since the black Cloud;that threatn'd you laſt night With ſuch a ſtorm, is luckely blown over, - - Without a ſprinkling; I hope Madam, you Will imitate the ſates,and grow Serene, ... . . . . . . From all thoſe Clouds whigh ſº much threath'd others. . . Blan. Ah! Franciſca caästthou– " ". . . . ... ." ..." (she ſtºps ſeeing Silvia coming. Enter Silvia with a fine Baſin ºf Flowers. º - Aſide — Buthere's silvia, O the ſharp thorns, ſhe bringsme gº time - - - * - - - - - - - - - - . . . . . . . .T.V. º.º. is * - ** 3 ith
Page 34

34 "E L y 182. L} . .'; , ; Tº rº with Flowers in her hand, by the Conſtrait ºn , !!! ... º. ºf Her preſence gives me. . . . . . . -- . . . . . " - º, tº , ſ: , . . . . - - - --------e. theſ Flow ... . . . "tº º tncle Flowers, ºr . talaſsiſcar. - - - - * - ***, *, *, ºne ºf 9-9., sil. Madam, I wiſh the ranging May be to your mind; w - I am too dull for works of fºrciúi iſ is ºr ºilſ. th Blan. 'Tis me you find to l tor; them, .." (D, 5. Anon they may be wellcomer. " rºliſh them, (Dºğ. sil. I’le wait that §. ºt'ſ ºyº Y º . . . ~~ **"... • hum *- : . i - * * * * * *- x-, -- — 3's in ºn ~ * { uſupº, ; , , ), . (Aſide. ..., a tºp 2 is ... (Exit Silvia. Blan. But tell me now, didſt ever ſee Franciſca, nº..., a Sofalſe and bould a Creature?. The Impudence... . º º He had to cloath his Treachery with new Courtſhips, * º Provokes me moſt of all. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ." dio Fran. Laſt night indeed, incens' as you wºre, Madam, . > J ſain would know what air ſo ſoft and Gentle ſ º º 2 He could have breath'd, would not have blown the flame. ..., Higher and Higher! but me thinks your Pillow , , , , Should in ſo many jºić. º, sº ... " Tallay and mollifie; I then complyed . . . . . . ºt -(He preſent) with your an º, Madam, ; : , , 3 You muſt allow me to ſpeak reaſon t'ee, " ' '...' In his behalf, before you go too far, , , - - - - - - - And put things, in your paſſion, paſt Recall, . Whichthat once over, you would give your life, ; , , - To have again. . . . . . . . . . Blam. Pray think me not ſo tame. Fran. Sotame ſay you? I think you wild Iſwear. Totake ſo much to heart, what at the moſt O . . … 2 : ; ; (Yºº. *** -- Deſerves but ſome ſuch ſparklingbrisk reſentment, "... As once flaſh't out, in a few Cholerick words, " ' " " ' Ought to expire, in a next Viſits Coyneſs. . . . - s Blan. Makeyouſoſlight of Infidelity " . . . . * Fran. Cupid forbid; I'de have men true foLove... ſº i. º º º And - ---- But, I'de have women too, true to themſelves,



Page 35

B L V I R.A. º 35; And not rebuke their Gallants, by requiring , sº fly! ... . . . More than the nature of frail fleſh will bear. ... onºt, I'de have men true asſteel; but ſteel you know … ,-, -, - . . . (The pureſt and beſt polliſh't ſteel) willply, , , , . . . . - § : .. Rećtitude, §: But then , , , , , , With a ſmart ſpring, come to it's place agen. . . . . . . . . . - Blan.' :. peakſoberly. Fran. Why then in ſober ſadneſs, y'are in the wrong, I do not ſay, in being angry with him, . . . . . And netl'd at the thing, That's Natural, . . . . . . . . . . We love no Partners, even in what we know . We cannot keep all to our ſelves; But, Madam, …" , -º Tothink the worſe of him for it, or reſolve . . . A breach of friendſhip for a ſlight excurſion, , , , , , That were a greater fault then his, whohas, , , , . . . . For one excuſe, long abſence; And in truth Another, you'd be ſorry he wanted, youth. . . . . . Blan. You talk as y — (Franciſca interrupting her. . Fran. Stay Madam I beſeech you. . . . - And let me make an end, I have not yet . . . . . . Touch'd the main point in his excuſe, A Sute . . . . . . At Court, enough I trow for any dog trick. tº * . . . . . . Blam. How like a Gooſe you talk, A Court protenſion, “ . Whathas that to do one way or other ºv, , , , - . VVith his faith to me 2 - 1:1 tº º * * . - º: - º Fran. So, one diſpleaſed to find his Crafiſhes, Shrivel'd within, and empty, ſaid to his Cook, 's - - (Who layd the fault upon the Wane o'th' Moon,) What has the Moon, to do with Crafiſhes . . . . . . . Marry ſhe has, tisſhe that governs ſhell Fiſh, . . . . And t'is as true, in Courts, that love rules buſineſs . . . . By as Prepoſterousan Influence. . . . Blan. I prithy make an end, or come to the Point. º - Fram. Whythen I'letell you, and you may believeme, , , (Having been train'dup in nº you know, ... O ‘. . * . In \
Page 36

3& B L P. fºr A: In the beſt School, to learn Çourt Miſteries; ºn of º - An Aunt of mine being Mother of the Maids.) . º º, Love holds the Rudder, ahd Steersallig Courts; * * * * : * How oft, when great Affairs perplex'tthe Brains, 4 º' Of mighty Politicians,t}éoéjećture; 2 º' tº ºt From whenceſprung ſuch deſigns, ſuch revolutions, ** º f , Such Exaltations, º ſuch depreſſions, 2 - . . . . . . Againſt the Rulés of their Miſterious'Art,” ºr And when, as in ſupriſing works of Natureº, . . ." | Reaſon confounded, Men crythoſe are ſecrets” º tº Of the high Powers above, that governalſ, ſº º º, Grave lookers on, ſtroking their beards would ſay, tº º ſ What a tranſcendant fetch of State is this ; ; , " " ' " " " . Theſe are the things, that wiſdom hides and hatches, "... . . . under black Cap of weighty jobbernole º 'º " " ' ". I mean Count olivarez, All the while "º º 'º We female Macchiavels, would ſmile to think, ' ' " ' * “ How cloſely lurking lay the Nick of all, . . . . . . . .” - under our Daughter Dell's white Petticoat. . . . Blan. All this I grant you; may be true; And yet . . . . . N'ere make a jot, for his excuſe ; Franciſcº " " ' His ſute, had no Relation to ſuch matters. " " ' ". ... º.o. Fran. Whate’re the thing be, 'tis all one, D'ee think, Sutes be they what they will, can be obtain'd By ſuch as paſs for Fopps, as all young men º' ' ' ' ' ' Without a Miſtriſsor a Confidence 7. Are ſure to do there; A ſharp pointed Hat, , , , (Now that you ſee the Gallants all Flat headed,): Appears not ſo ridiculous, as Yonker, Without a love Intreegue,to Introduce, ! . . . - And ſparkefy him there; Madam, in ſhort." Allow me once to be Sententious; !' -- It is a thing, that always was, and is, Ahd ever will be, true, to the worldsend; That, as in Courts of Juſtice, none can Carry” -- -- - On -- - - - - - . . . . . . . . -----, * , , --
Page 37

- E L P 1 RA. 37 On buſineſs well, without a Procurator, | So none in Princes Courts, their Sutes make ſurer, Then thoſe that work them, by the beſt Procurer. . . . . Blanca Well, haſt; adone Franciſcar Isrin aliull -- - Fraň. - Madam, I have. * - - I). Blan. —- Then letting paſs, º - ! - - Thy fine reflections Politique now vented, . To ſhew thy skill in Courts, I'letellthee freely, I’me not tranſported in my jealouſie • ‘7 So far, beyond the bounds of Reaſon, as Not to know well, the difference, betwixt . . . . Such Eſcapades of youth, as only ſpring . . . From warmth of blood, or Gales of Vanity, And ſuch engagements, as do carry with them Diſhonour unto thoſe, whoſe quality, - And ſove have little to the ſerious Part, Once Embark'd by them, in a Gallentry. -- - . . . Fran. I ſee the Cloudsdiſperſe, ther's no ſuch Art, (Aſide. Ofcompaſsing ones ends, with thoſe above us, As that of working them into good humour, - - - - By things brought in by the by, " . . . . . Why ſurely, Madam, unleſs anger lend you [To her. It's ſpectacles, to ſee things, I cannot think - : • You judge Don Zancho's fault to be any other, Then of the firſt kind; ſo well ſtated by you. - - Blan. Franciſca, were I otherwiſe perſwaded; I am not of an humor that could ſuffer Such Parlies for him, much leſs Interceſſion; But ſince upon refle&tion, I find cauſe Tothinkwhat he has done A ſally only, . . . . . . Of Youth and Vanity, when I ſhall find him . . . . Sufficiently mortify’d, I may pardon him. . . . . . . . . . . ... Fran. Heavens bleſs ſo ſweet a temper, But Madam; I Have a care I beſeech you of one thing. * - - - - Blan. What's that ... C - 2 º i. -, - . . * * * * * * * * - M º ** - . . º * -- . 2 - Fran.
Page 38

38 E L V 1 ºr A. - Fram. That whilſt your pride of heart Prolongs his readmiſſion, his diſpair urge him not to ſome precipitate attempt, That may expoſe your honour, ſafe as yet 3 You ſee what danger the laſt nights diſtemper - Had like t'have brought you into 3 Tranſported Lovers, Like Angels fallen from their bliſs grow Devils. . . . . . D. Blam. What would you have me appear ſo flexible? - – I'ſt not enough - - I tell you I may pardon him in due time? Fram. Good Madam, be advis'd I do not preſs you ? For his ſake, but your own, Truſt my experience, To women nought's ſo fatal as ſuſpence; Whoſe ſmarteſt ačtions, ne’re did caſt ſuch Blot, On honor, as this, ſhall I ? ſhall I not? - . . . . -- * - - * * D. Blan. I'de rather die, then have him think me Eaſie. Fran. Your ſpirit, never can be liable To that ſuſpicion, Madam leave to me . . . . . . The condućt of this matter, I beſeech you, . . . " If ere you ſleep, you do not ſee the Gallant . . . . . Sufficiently humbled at your feet, - - Ne're truſt Franciſca more. . . . * D. Blan. You are ſo tro bleſome do what you will. Fraw.” What gone away? . . . . , I'le do what ſhe would have, but dares not ſay. Enter Don Julio and Silvia as in Blanca's Chamber. -, * * * - - --- - (Blanca turns away and Exit as into her cloſet. . . . " ** * * Dom Pulie Where is my Siſter Silvia? . . . . . . . [looking about him.] Silv. — As yet not ready. 2 - - - ful. —— And wher's Franciſca? . . . . . inter Cloſet, Sir, v. Silv. She's with her, dreſſing her. sº º D. jul. -- Why then Elvira, Let me not Looſe this opportunity, Oftelling you, how ſad a man I am. ** - ... * * *

Page 39

º E L 7 17 A. 39 To ſee youin this poſture, and to aſſureyou - How gladly I would lay down life, and fortune, To ſerve you in Don Fernando's abſence. silv. Your generoſity I make no doubt of : But is Fernando gone? D. ful. — I cannot ſay, ... " That he is gon, for he was not himſelf, With the thought of leaving you, And yet leſs Himſelf, whene're he thought of ſtaying near you, Tortur’d by two ſuch contrary paſſions, " . As love, and ſharp reſentment. . . . . . . . . . . . . Silv. He is gone then? (she pawſes. —— Ah! generous Don £ulio 2 - - ſº hiſ flººd; You needs muſt be Indulgent, to a weakneſs *****] which whilſt that he was preſent indignation, And a juſt Sence of what I am, had power Tokeep within my ſelf, but now I find That check remov’d, Nature will have it's tribute, - And you muſt pardon my withdrawing, where [she weeps. Such grief, may pay it, with unwitneſs’t tears. . . . (Exit Silvia. , £ul. Can a demeanour, ſo compoſed, ſo Noble, - And yet ſo tender, want true Innocence? It cannot be, It grieves my heart Iſwear, - - Thave given her new afflićtion, but the Secret . . . . Of Don Fernando's cloſe concealment here Is ſo important, it neceſſitated” Myſaying what I did, ſince ſecrets are . . . . . . B’ver kept beſt, by thoſe that know them leaſt. Eater j Franciſca. . . . . ful. Now high diſfimulation, play thy Part. . . . . . . [Tº her] Good Morrow Siſter have you reſted well? . . . And do you riſe Serene, as does the Sun, '' Free from diſtemper, as the day from Clouds, Your loºks perſwade it me, they are ſo clear, . . . . And freſh this morning. - ºn tº .***** . , - Blåms. ... ( 2 s - -
Page 40

40 E L V I R.A. Blan. The pleaſure of ſeeing you, puts life intothem, , , Elſe they'd be dull enough, this ugly Head-ache - Havingtormented me all night, you might Have heard me call Franciſca up at midnight, Fran. That was wellthoughton, for 'tis poſſible (Aſide. He may have heard ſome Noiſe. . . - - - . . . £ul. How cunning ſhe's I - (Aſide. Faith now you put me in mind of it I think Twixt ſleep and waking, Ionce heardſome ſtirring. Blan. The worſt of my indiſpotion is, That t'will I fear hinder me again, today, From viſiting Violante, to thankher' - FCr Silvia. * - - - - - - - - * ful. I charge myſelf with allyour Complements, For this whole after-noon till late at night - I needs muſt paſs with her, to make amends' ; : For yeſterdays failings, caus'd as you know By Don Fernando's being in Town. Blan. Imuſt not hope to ſee youthen again º tº Today, when once gone out. … - * : - - - - - £ul. Hardly, unleſs to wait on ºioſante, º - º * * In caſe ſhe come to ſee you, as 'tislikely, ". . . . . . . When I ſhall tell her, you are indiſpoſed ; , , , , , , , And ſo farewell. . . . (Exit Julio Blan. All's well Iſee Franciſca as to him, . . . . I wiſh my heart, were but as much at reſt . . . . . . . . In what concerns Don Zancho. . . . . . . Fram. It ſhall be - - . Your own fault, if it be not quickly ſo, As I'le order the matter. . . . . . . . . . . … * Blan. Take heed, you make him not grow inſolent, By diſcovering to him my facillity. . . . . . . . Fram. I'me too well vers’t, to need inſtrućtions. . . . . . . . . Blam. I leave all tee, But how does Silvia . . . . . . . . This morning? . . . . . . . . - - * * . . . . . . . . . . ] iſ tº . . . ." Fram.

End of Section 4. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 5
Page 41

E L V1 ra. 4. ~ * Fran. I think ſhe has been crying She looks ſo dull and moped. . . . . - Blan. I'le in and ſee her. - [Exeunt. Scene Changes to Don Enter Don Zancho and Zancho's houſe. - Chichon limping. Dan Zan. What not yet gone,thou lazy trifling Raſcal P ... Chic. What juſter excuſe Sir, for not going Then is a broken Legg . . " - D. Zant. If you find not your own Legg quickly Sirrah, I ſhall find you a wooden one. - - Chic. Be as angry as you will Sir, I’le not go Till I have maid my conditions; The true time For ſervants to ſtand upon points, is when Their Maſters ſtand upon Thorns. . * . " D. Zanc. What are they, Owls face - Chic. Aſſurance Sir, but of free air within, - With fair retreat, upon an even Floor, And that it ſhall not be in a ſluts power, After having kept me in a naſty place, , - - To empt me out at window. - Don Zan. — Prithychichon . . . . Adone and miſs not th'oppertunity # * . . Byfooling, unleſs you take Franciſca - Juſt as ſhe comes from Maſs, this day is loſt, And I loſt with it. , - Chic. Come, I’le hobble to her, - Expect a ſorry account,but yet a true one ; Truth always comes, by the lame Meſſenger. (Exeant. . . . - - - - - - - - - - Emirdjúlio and knocks as at the Scene changes to a fine . . . . Door of his private Apartment : pleaſant Apartment. " . Fernando ºpens the doer and lets him in. , * - Fer. Yºhave given me here a very pleaſant Priſon : . . . . But what news my julio: Are things diſpoſed - . . . . For clearing of your doubts? *gown concerns' . . . º - - - ºf J2 ‘’’. I can
Page 42

42 E L W I R.A. I cannot think on, during your diſquiet. - £ul. And I come now ſo ſtrangely moved with yours, I ſcarce have ſence or memory of my own, A heart of Adamant could not behindred I think, from liquifaction into tears: I'have ſeen, and heard Elvira as I have done, upon th'occaſion of my telling her - That you were gone, Aſence ſogallant, and ſo tender both, I never ſaw in Woman. • Fer. Can that high heart, deſcend to tenderneſs? - £ul. Not, (whilſt you preſent) Noble pride upheld it ; But Nature once ſet free from that conſtrăint, . . . . " O how pathetique was her very ſilence And the reſtraint of tears, in her ſwolen Eyes, More eloquent in grief, then others torrents: If ſhe be guilty, all her Sex are Devils. Fer. O ſay no more, For were there Room but left For ſelf deceit, I might be happy yet; Ah Evidence, too cruell, to deny me that. [A noiſe without. £ul. But what can be the noiſe, I hear without In the next Room. - - - - - - - (Fernando peºp; through the K 9-hole. * , - . - Fer. S’life I ſee Don Pedro Elvira's father, ther's no avoding him, - - H'eed not a come up ſo, without being ſure You are within, ... . . . . . . . . . . . . .” - - - ful. Further put off, would be of ſtile uſe, * * * Since firſt or laſt, he muſt be ſatisfy'd, , , Being come hither upon ſuch an Arrant,” The ſooner now we ſee what 'tis, he drives at, The ſooner we ſhall take from thence our meaſures; I'le therefore go out to him, and be ſure . . . . . . . . To entertain him ſtill, ſo near the door ºf º 3: . ~ Fr. I ſhall sy f : * *, *, * * * * ~. * . . ºv, 3. ., & 5 J - - - That you may hear what paſſes. N/
Page 43

E L / I R.A. 43 Fer. I ſhall be attentive, and expect the Iſſue . . . . . With much impatience. . . . . . (Exit Julio. And the Scene changes to Enter Don Pedro and his #!. Don Julio's Ante-Chamber. and Don Julio and a Page. Don Ped. My buſineſs, Sir, is to Don julio Racca, fairſ, biº- If you be he I ſhall deſire the favour (ºftop juio 1. Of ſome few words with you in Private. - . . . . . Don £ul. Sir, I am he to ſerve you, Page ſet Chairs. He points to the Page, and makes him ſet the chairs by the - door where Don Fernando is, and then the Page and \ Don Pedro's man retire. . . [They ſit down.] D. Ped. Having not the honour to be knownt'ee Sir, 'Tis fit this Letter make my Introdućtion 3 'Tis from the Duke of Medina. He gives Don Julio the letter, which he receives with great reſpetſ; And going a little aſide read; it. - T H E L E TTER. º On Pedro de Mendoca my Kinſman, and moſt particular Friend goes to Valencia, in purſute of one who hath highly Injur'd his family, whoſe righting I am ſo much cºncern'd in, as could it have been done without too much publication of the thing, I would have accompanied him my ſelf, but my preſence will be needleſ, in a place where you have power ; I do therefore conjure you, and expect from your regard and kindneſs to me, that you emi- ploy it throughly in his behalf, and what ſervice you ſhall do him, put it upon my account, whom you ſhall always find, Toºr moſt affectionate Couſin to ſerve you - \ The Duke of Medina. (Don Julio giving the Letter to Don Pedro and he taking it, Don £ul, Sir, it is fit you ſee how heartily - The Duke hath recommended your concernments, Whoſe will's a Law to me. - (Don Pedro having read it, and reſtoring it. Don Ped. He told me indeed how very ſure he was Of your Friendſhip and dependance. - G 2 — I am * -
Page 44

44 E L / I ſR A. - - I am proud to find he makes, So obliging uſe of it to my advantage. - D. ful. I do avow my ſelf his Creature Sir Therefore the ſooner you ſhall let me know In what I may be uſeful tee, the ſooner You'l ſee my readineſs to ſerve you. room Pedro, Your perſonal reputation Sir, as well As your relation to the Duke,aſſured me - Before hand, of what I find, and therefore As hard a part as it is for a Gentleman Of my blood and temper, to become Relator of his own ſhame, unreveng'd On the Authour of it, I ſhall tell you in ſhort; I live under an affront of th' higheſt Nature To the Honour of my Family; And the Perſon Who did it, makes Valencia his retreat, 'Tis againſt him, Don julio, - That your aſſiſtance muſt ſupport me here, I have already got ſome notice of him, And when I ſhall be acertain'd, I’le repair Again unto you for your friendly aide, And for the preſent trouble you no farther. - - (Don Pedro offers to riſe as going away. Den ful. A little patience I beſeech you Sir, - - I have expreſs'd my readineſs, and be ſure I am a man never to fail, where once . I have engaged my word ; but Sir, withall, You muſt muſt conſider with a fair reflexion. …” - That in this place are all my chief Relations, . . . . Of blood and friendſhip ; and though neither ſhall - Have power t'exempt me from the ſerving you .. In any juſt pretenſion; yet you know, - That men of Honour, ever ought to ſeek, How to comply with one duty, without . Violating another. 2. - . - º - Boa-2
Page 45

E L P 1 RA. Don Ped. I underſtand you Sir, and as 'tis that | Which well becomes a perſon of your worth, To have reflected on ; ſo it becomes me, To ſatisfie before I engage you further, Then give me leave to ask you, whither or no Don Zancho de Menezes be of the number . . . . .” Of thoſe, towards whom y'are under obligation, Either of blood, or friendſhip? LDon Julioſhewing ſome little ſurpriſe but preſently recovering, Don ful, ion Zancho de Meneſes ſay you? Dos Ped. — Sir, the ſame, He ſtartled at his Name. D. :Pul. He is a perſon I have always liv'd. In friendly correſpondance with, without Any ſuch tye upon me towards him, . As ought to hinder my frank ſerving you. [aft. - Don Ped. You havé reviv'd me; and ſince I have now nam'd My Enemy, I can conceal no longer The Grounds on which he is ſo; That pm Zancho - About a fourtnight ſince, was late at night - Found in myhouſe, run newly through the body, And weltring in his blood, ready to expire; ' ' , I by the outcry brought upon the place, Surpriz'da/you may imagine, and enraged, Was yet ſo far Maſter of my paſſion, As to diſdain the owing my revenge. To an unknown hand, perhaps as guilty Towards me, as was the ſufferer; I made Him ſtraight be carried to a Surgeon, where, I thought it generous to give him life Then dead, that living Imight give him death ; , Recover'd ſooner then I thought,he Fled, And with him, as I have reaſon to believe, \ My only Daughter, who the very night - Of the accident was miſſing ; O the Curſe . Of
Page 46

=- Of men to have their Honours Subjected, is º' To the extravagance of ſuch vile Creatures! - " … . £ul. [ſighing.] 'Tis our bard fate indeed. 3: D. Ped. I preſently employ'd all diligence ºf , , , To know what way he took, and having Learn't nº ſwastowards thisplace, hither Ihave purſued him; s > Confirm'd in my purſuit, by information . . . . . . . . . A long the Road, that an unknown Gallant tº Had with his Servant, guarded all the way . . . . A conceal’d Lady in a Coach: And thus Sir, . . . . . You have the ſtory of my injury, . - . Whereof I doubt not but your generous heart, . . . . Willwed the juſt revenge. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ful. You may rely on't Sir, without reſerves, . . . . . . Toth'utmoſt of my power. - - - - - - - - - - Tan Ped. Mayihegods reward you, . . . " The life that you Renue to theſe gray heirs; . . . . . . . * * 5. 5 - - - - . . . . . * * lle take my leave at preſent, and return tee . . . . . . . . . . As ſoon as from the diligences uſed I ſhall have Clearer lights, - - - - Don ful. Here you ſhall find me waiting your Commands. [Exit Don Pedro,and Don Julio waiting on him out. Scene changes, and Enter Don #. and Don Fernando as in the private Apartment. Don ful. I hope you over heard us. Fer. — All diſtinčtly, º And with ſurprizing joy at his miſtake; Did ever blood-hound, in a hotpurſute, , . Run on ſo readyly upon the change - ful. I hope it boads good fortune in the Reſt. - Fer. Were e're two friends engag’d in an adventure So intricate as we, and ſo Capricious? ‘Ful. Sure never in this world, methinks it merits A ſpecial recapitulation. . . . . . r - - - - 3 You at the height of all your happineſs . - . - - - w Sup-

End of Section 5. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 6
Page 47

E L * 17 A. 47 Supplanted with your Miſtriſsby a Rival, - - v You neither knew nor dream't of ; Evidence Anticipating jealouſie. Fer. And when that Rival, fallenby mySword In her own preſance, is by miracle - Revived, and fitter to ſerve her then I, , That faithleſs Miſtriſs, with the ſame aſſurance She could have done, had ſhe been true, as fair, And for my ſake expoſed to fatall hazards, Flystomy Arms for her Protećtion. - - ful. And whilſt that you, refining point of Honour, In ſpite of Rageexpoſeyour ſelf to ſerve her, She asks,and takes, with a vowed indignation, To be beholding t'ee, new obligations, Fer. I have recourſe unto my only Friend, To help me in protećting my falſe Miſtreſs, - And he, at the ſame time, by heigheſt Powers . . . Impos'd upon, to be her perſecutor.” . . . . . . - ful. Whil'ſt the ſame friend, and by the ſelf-ſame Powers, Isurg'd to Aćt, in their revenge, againſt " ' ' ' The man, on whom you moſt deſire to take it; And then, to heighten all beyond invention, That very friend, is forſt, even in that inſtant, tº . To a dependance on your only Aide,” tº . . In his Honours neareſt and moſt nice concerns. Fer. Heavenſuredelights tinvolve usin a kind Of Laberinth,willpoſe itſelf to unwind. , | - * * * tº Q. i., v. ". . . . . . . º. - Scene changes to the Room Emir D.Zancho,and Chichon at an- at Don Zancho’s.. . . . . . other door,halling ſtill with a ſtaff. ;V V; here again already? have you ſpead? - *- (Extunt. !--- ~ - €hichon * - ~ * . •. - - - + Lambasſam,you ſeeihave made goodſ*: _-_*—º-º-º-º-º:

End of Section 6. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 7
Page 48

That neither In my return, what e're I have had in my Arrant. D. Zan. Leave fool your quibling, and deliver me From the diſquiet of uncertainly. - Chich. That's quickly done, ſet Sir your heart at reſt From the vain hopes of ever ſeeing Blanca: Now you are at eaſe I trow. - Don Zane. You'l be at little, unleſs you leave your jeſting With ſuch edg'd tools; Is baniſhment from her Matter of Rallery ſay Sirrah, and ſay Quickly, what hopes? * - Prithy if thou lov'ſt me . . [kindly. Hold me no longer in ſuſpence chichon. Chich. Why, then for fear, the Divel a bit for love, I’le tell you Sir, That luckely I met . - The Drab Franciſca at the Capuchins Lodging, behind her Lady, I think on purpoſe, For I perceiv'd, her eager Sparrow-Hawks eye . With her veil down (near ſtirs a twinckling while, From it's flypeeping hole) had found me ſtraight, I took mytime in th’nick, but ſhe out nick’t me; For trudging on, her face an other way, , , , , With ſuch a voice, as ſome you have ſeen, have had The trick to draw, from Caverns of their Belly, And make one think it came from a mile off; She made meheartheſe words about twilight, Fail not to paſsby our door, and ask no more At this time }. And thus Sir, you ſee, enor I, have been prolixe, - For this is all; You have leave to make your Comment On a brief text. Don Zanc. Asſweetme-thinks as ſhort, ſuch words imply Little leſs then a demy Aſſignation. - D. Zane. All puddings have two ends, and moſt ſhort ſayings Two handles to their meaning. . . . . . . . . Don Zan. I'meſure I'le ſtill layhold upon the pleaſing'ſt T. ~ - - I * , .
Page 49

--> ºr - E L VI R A. 49 ' Till it be wreſted from me; i'th' mean while If any viſitants come this afternoon, Be ſure to tell them I am gone abroad, That nothing elſe embarque us at the time; You ſhall not go alone. - - - - Chic. I thank you for it (Holding up his ſtaff. , I cannot go alone. . [Exeunt Chichon halting. Scene changes to Don Julio's Enter Don Fernando and Julio - private Apartment. | as in the private Apartment. Don £ul. All things are rightly laid, for Wiolante Will paſs the afternoon with Blanca, and then - v I waiting on her home in th’evening, Blanca * Will be ſecure from me, till late at night, - I ſhall be where I told you, in full view Of thoſe two windows: If the Gallant come Up the great Stairs, he muſt paſs through that Room And cannot ſcape your knowledge: If up the back one, You needs muſt here him paſſing through the Entry Cloſe by that door. If this latter way, Be ſureto ſet the Candle in that window: (Pointing. If up the other, in that ; and in either caſe As ſoon as he's within, fail not to bolt . On th’inſide th’Entry door, that ſo he may Find no retreat that way, I coming up The other. IJon Ferm. As you direct. (Exeunt. Scene changes to Don Enter Don Pedro, and his Pedro's Lodging. ſervant Fulvio. Don Ped. Are you ſure of what you ſay * Ful. —— As ſure, Sir, - . As my own Eyes can make me of what Iſaw, - You cannot doubt my knowing him, ſince tº was I (You may remember) fetcht the Surgeon to him, And ſaw his wounds dreſt more then once, or twice ; . * - H - The - . Be aſſured I ſhall be punāual
Page 50

5o E L VI R.A. The Tavern where I was, looks into his Garden, And there I left him walking, to come tell you. - D. Ped. We are well advanc’t then,towards my juſt Revenge I found Don julio as ready to comply With all the Dukes deſires, as I could wiſh, And my great fear is over, That Don Zancho Might poſſibly have been ſome near Relation . Of his own ; ſo that now Fulvio, if you Keep but a careful Eye upon his motions, Andgive me notice, he can hardly ſcape us. - Ful. Doubt not my diligence. (Exeant, Scene changes to Enter Blanca and Franciſca as in a fine Gar- th" Garden. den with orange-trees and Fountains. Don. Blan. You muſt have your will, but know Franciſca If you expoſe me to his vanity, I never ſhall forgive you. - Fran. Itell you, Madam, I will bring him t'ee So mortifyed, he ſhall an object be For pity, not for anger, you’l need employ Kindneſs to erect the poor dejećted Knight. Don. Blan. It fellout luckely that Violante Came hither, for my Brother now engaged With her, ware ſafe till ten a Clock at leaſt. Fran. But how ſhall we diſpoſe of Silvia? It will be hard to ſcape her obſervation, For ſhe has wit, and of the dangerous kind, Amelancholy wit: O the unlucky Star - ºf . That leads a É. engaged in love intrigues º To take a new Attendant near her Perſon . . . . . . . . Don. Blan. 'Twas an unluckineſs, but Wielante. , Could not be deny’d, I having told her So often that I wanted one; beſides - Who could have thought, ſh'had one ready athand, But we muſt make the beſton't for this night : . . . Twill not behard to buſieher, till 't be late • In / w - - - in z - - - - * - - - w - * - f - - º – - - ...” -
Page 51

In the perfuming Room. This near occaſion Well o're, I think it will not be amiſs . . . . . . Againſt another, to ſay ſome what to her , sº That may in caſe ſhe have perceiv'd anything . . . Perſwade her ſhe is not diſtruſted. -- . Fran. Madam take heed of that, whene're you find It neceſſary to ſay any thing, Be ſure to ſay that, that ſhe may think all ; Take one Rule more from my experience, Nothing ſo fatal as a Confidence By halves in amorous tranſactions; - But here ſhe comes. . . - - D. Blan. Come silvia,and take your part of thisſweet Place; This is a day indeed, to taſt it's freſhneſs. Sil. Madam I needs muſt ſay, within a Town I never ſaw ſo fine a one. , ºr 150m. Blan. In truth - I think not many ſweeter. Thoſe Fountains - Playing among thoſe Orange trees and Mirtles, Have a fine mix’t effect on all the ſenſes; But think not silvia to enjoy the pleaſure Without contributing to make it more. £il. How can I be ſo happy? . . - - D. Blan. Franciſca tellsme ſhe has over-heard you Warbling alone ſuch Notes unto your ſelf, Ashave not only a good voice betray'd, But skill to manage it. . Sil. It is Franciſca That has betray'd, a very ill one Madam, Don. Blan, under yon Palm tree's ſhade, there is a ſeat That yields to none in the advantages -- - It lends to Muſick, let's go ſit down there, . . . For this firſt time, one Song ſhall ſatisfie. . . . ... Silv. When youhave heard that one, I ſhall not fear Your asking meanother, (They go and ſet down under the Palm- * * * - tree and Silvia ſings. H 2 THE - 'i º - >
Page 52

52 - E L V I R A. - T H E SONG. See, o ſee 1 & Hear, obear ! How every Tree, How ſweet, and clear. Every Bower, The Nightingal, - Every Flower, And watersfall, A new life gives to others joys, In conſert joyn for others Eart, Whilſt that I, - Whilſt to me Grief ſtrucken lie, For 4armony, Nor can meet - Every Air . . With any ſweet, - Eccho's deſpair, Bat what faſter mine deſtroys. And every drop provokes 4 tear. What are all the ſenſes pleaſures, What are all the ſenſes pleaſures, When the mind has loſt all mea- When the mind bas loſt all mea- (ſures f (ſures f Don. Blan. I thank you Silvia, but I’le not allow - One of your youth, to nouriſh melancholly By tunes and words ſo flattering to that paſſion. Silv. The happineſs of ſerving you may fit me In time, for gayer things. Don. Blam. I will not ask another for the preſent, Not for your reaſon, but becauſe I'lebe More moderate in my pleaſures; Now Silvia I have a task to give you. silv. Whate’re it be, twill be a pleaſing one - Of your impoſing. - - - Don. Blan. 'Tis to gather ſtore of Freſh Orange Flowers, and then carefully To ſhift the Oyls in the perſuming Room, As in the ſeveral ranges you ſhall ſee . . . . The old begin to wither; Todo it well º . . . . . Will take you up ſomehours; But 'tis a work . . . Ioft perform my ſelf; And that you may º: - . Be ſure not to miſtake, I'lego thither . . . . . . . . . . With you, and ſhew youthe manner of it. . . . . .” Sil. I hope I ſhall not failſo well inſtrućted. - (Extumi. Scene
Page 53

* - You are ſo proud o'th'ſervice you have done ; -v----. E L P 1 RA. 53 / Scene changes to the Room Enter Don Zancho at Don Zancho's. and Chichon. Chic. Y'are ſo impatient Sir, you will mar all, - I tell you that 'tis yet too light by half, º - * The Sun is hardly ſet 3 pray fetch a turn Or two more in the Garden, ear you go. D. Zan. You muſt be Governour, I ſee, to night, º (Exeumt. - Silvia appears in the Garden as gathering Scene changes to the flowers from the orange Trees, and them Garden again. with her Apron full going away ſays, Silv. The task enjoyn'd me is a ſweet one truly, But I ſmell ſomewhat more in the impoſall ; So far I am happy yet in my misfortune That I am lighted into a Lady's ſervice . Of an obliging humour; But moſt of all, --- One that askind as ſhe is, I ſee's as glad, - * : * To leave me alone as I to be it, ſomewhat * . There is, miſterious in her looks, and conduct:- Such motions juſt, ſuch inequalities, -. Such flatteries to thoſe I truſted leaſt, Such pretty employments found, to buſie thoſe I would beridof; And ſuch arts as theſe : To fingle outher Confident unnoted, - I well remember would Elvira uſe, - - * Whil'ſt the unquiet joys of Love, poſſeſt her, . . . . . . . How innocent ſoever; And beſides, . . . . . Franciſca's ſitting up ſolate laſt night, And going up and down ſowarily, . . . . . Whilſt others ſlept, is evidence enough - Come away. whº God raigns here, as well as at the Court, . . . . - But I forget myſelf: Let deſcants ceaſe, ... . . . . . . . . . Whoſerves though ſhe obſerves, muſt hold her peace. . . . . . . - , ſº ºf oººo Yº (Exit Silvia; ; **
Page 54

54 E L V 1 (R.A. . . Scene changes to the Pro- Enter Don Zancho with his cloak ſpeč of Valencia. o're his face, and Chíchon. Don Zant. Advance Ghichon, I’le follow at a diſtance: 'Tis the right time, juſt light enough, you ſee, For warn’d Expedors to know one another; – I hope ſhe will rºot fail you. - - Chic. — She failus * . . . . . . . No Centinel perdu is half ſo alerte o 'º' Asſheintheſe occaſions. - 3 Enter Franciſca wailed peeping, as cut of the portal of Don Julio's houſe. - Fran. There comes the Varlet, and I’me much deceiv'd, Or that's his Maſter lagging at a diſtance, \ I'legive them a go by, cover'd with my wail. - - [she paſſes by them heedlºſſy. Chic. By that light as little as 'tis, 'Tis ſhe, . . . . . . I'le to her. . . . . Døm Z4nc. And I’le ſtand cloſe the while, . . When you have broken the Ice, I’le take my time. . . . . . . . . . [Chichongºing to Franciſca lays hald ºf her wail, and ſhe turns about. ; , ; ; ; ; ; ; ; Chic. What ſignifies a Vail to hide my Doxyer When every motion of a leg or wing ºº sº º Darts round perfuming, and informing Airs, ºr Thou art the very Colly-flower of Women, ºr Fram. And thouthe very Cabbidge-ſtalk of Men, That never ſtunk to me, as does . cº-inºſiſ: , , Chic. Curſe on thee, hold thy tongue; Doſt thou not ſee H. Whoſtands againſt that wall. - " " tº gº tºº. 2 º' - Fran. Away, ſawce-Box. ... [she thruſting him off goes em. [Don Zancho ſets himſelfiuſ in her way, and º, makes as if herwould lie down in it. … sº D. Zanc. Paſs, trample on me, doytrample; Buthere me. *. Fran, Theſe ſhoo's have been my Ladies,and ſhe'd ne’reſſ. Forgive it,ſhould they do you ſo much Honour. º . . --, - - * 'Tis - * - - - - - * - *
Page 55

- E L V 1 R A. 55 * "Tis thou haſt caus'd all this. [*Aſide turning tº Chichon. . Chic. Fire on thy tongue. , - - - Don Zane. Ah! my Franciſca, if their be nohopes Of pardon, nor of pity; Yet at leaſt y - - - Let Blanca for her own ſake, beſo juſt a As not to give me cruel death unheard: Do you your part at leaſt, and do but give her - This letter from me. [He offers her a Letter,and ſhe ſtarting back. Fran. — Guarda. That's a thing She has forbidden, with ſuch Menaces, I dare as well become another Porcia, And eat red burning coales. I had much rather Conſent, that now ſhe's all alone at home, You ſhould tranſportedly ruſh in upon her As following me ſo poſſibly you might Attain your end, without expoſing me 3 Who in that caſe, know how to Aét my Part So ſmartly againſt you, as ſhall keep her clear Fröm all ſupition; But I am to blame Thus to forget my duty, I'le ſtay no longer. - [He ſtops her and pulling out a Purſe of money, pur's it - unto her hand. - Don Zant. Spoak like an Angel. - - - [Franciſca offers to reſtºre the Purſe but jet - holding it faſt. Fran. This is you know ſuperfluous with me, And ſhock's my humour; But anything from you : Be ſure you follow boiſterouſly. ,- [she trudges away, and goes in haftily as to Julio's houſe and Don Zancho follows her in. Chichon ſtops at the door. Chic. I’le bring you no ill luck a ſecond time; If for ſports ſake, you have projećted me Another Somerſet, from the Balcone, " Make your account, that 'tis already done, -- Here you will find me halting in the ſtreet, (Exit Cº.; - - cene. ' * ~ * ---.
Page 56

Scene changes to Donna Enter, Donna Blanca as in Blanca's Ante Chamber. her Ante Chamber. Don Blan. How true it is, that Nature cheats mankind, , , And makes us thinkourſelves the onely Taſters - Of pure delight, and bliſs ; when as indeed, Oppreſſing us with pains, and griefs, ſhe inakes Deliverance from them, paſs for ſolid pleaſure: Witneſs in methoſe Images of joy Wherewith ſhe flatters now my expectation : What will it's higheſt ſatisfaction be, At moſt, but eaſe from what tormented me? Enter Franciſca haſtily. Fram. It now imports, you have affected Rage, Asready at hand as uſually you have Anger, in earneſt ; But above all, be ſure - - You diſcharge it ſmartly upon me, for here He preſſes at my heels. - Enter Don Zancho, and goes to caſt himſelf at Donna Blanca's feet, and ſhe ſtarting back from him. - Don. Blan. What inſolence is this? -— Think not Franciſca That I am to be fool’d; This is your work, - g » You ſhall not ſtay an hour within theſe walls ; - By all that's good you ſhall not. - Fran. For heavens ſake Madam, be not ſounjuſt [Whining. To an old ſervant, always full of duty; But can I govern mad men, would y' have had me - Make all the Street take notice? There he attacqued me With ſuch tranſportment, the whole Town had rung on't Had I not run away 3 Could I imagine - A man ſo wilde asto purſue me hither Into your preſence P . . . . . . . . . . Dºn. Blan. — “It is well Don Zancho [* severely and ſcornfully.] Blanca may be thus uſed; But he that does it . . Shall find–Ishe turns away as going out he hold her by the ſleeve. ‘. - * - * . . . ." - Don * -
Page 57

~. E L VI (R.A. 57 1jon zane. Pardon this rudeneſs Madam; But a man . Made deſperate, hath nothing more to menage. ... Hither Icome, to give youſatisfaction, And if my reaſons can't, my heartblood ſhall ; But you muſt hear me, or here ſee me dead. . . . . . . . . . D. Blan. Since to be ridof him Franciſca, I ſee [. ...; I muſt the pennance undergo of hearing him, º Keep careful watch, to prevent accidents. . . . . . . . . Fran. Madam, your Clofit will be much more proper For ſuch a Conference; For in caſe your Brother Should come, Don Zancho has a ſafe retreat From thence, down the back Stairs. I ſhall be ſure - To give you timely notice. . . - Don Zanc. And I know perfeótly the paſſage thorough Th’Entry, I've come up more then once that way, During my happy days. - - - - - - - - - D. Blan. Ithink y'have reaſon, ſince I muſt have patience Lightus in thither. . . . . [Franciſca takes the lights, and going - (before them, Exeunt omnes.j Scene changes to the Pro-. Enter Don Julio as in the . ſpect ºf Valencia. . . . . … Portal of his own houſe. D.; al. The light was in the further window, therefore He went up this way: Now if Fernando. . ... ', Have not forgot to bolt the Entry Door, . . . . . He cannot ſcapeusſure, who earhebe. . . . . . . 'Tis the only Comfort, ... . . . . . . . . . In ſuch misfortunes, when a manhath means . . tº q: , , , , To right his Honour, without other help . . . . . . . . Then ſuch a friend,asis anotherſelf," . . . . . . And that the ſhame'seven from Domeſtiqueshid until it berevenged. tº gº of [Exit Don Julio 4 going - • (into his own houſe. … Enter Ghichon arcming autºf the Forch befºre Julio's hasſe. Chic. §. 'tis :::::::: if Iſaw goin,º My Maſter's like to paſs histime burilſ,..., , , .*.*. :^. . - I -- le - "I ºn Gºvt. º. "p *
Page 58

58 E L V J R A I'le ſtealin after, and obſerve, although , , , ºº My courage cannot fleedhim;ºyºvit may, , º, ...º.º. As things may poſſibly fallout ºf Exit & hithon as ſtealing afts : "...ſo dº" (Don Julio intº his houſe." Scene changes to Donna º Enter Dón Zancho and Donna Blanca's cloſet. tº Blanca its in her cloſet. - ºur ºr ºf tº D. Blan. As fine aſtory as may be 3 No1}on Zanthe,” I Blanca Rocca, am not Carta Blanca, º 'º - Fit to receive whate're impreſſion . . . . . . . . . . Your Art - º - º S. º … troº tº - * . . . . Enter Franciſca haftily. ºf º, ºri º .N. * Your Brother's in the Hall already; - - Fram. - Quick, Quick, and let him find you in your Chamber Before your Glaſs, I have ſet it ready there º *Whilſt he retiresthe way that was reſolv’d. [*Pointing . . . . . . .”, “ . . . . . . (to Don Zancho. Scene changes to Donna. Franciſca takes the Candle, and Blanca's Bed chamber." Exeunt ſhe, and Donna Blanca. - and D.7,ancho another way. Re-enter Donna Blanca and Franciſca 4 in Blanca's - chamber, and fºe newly ſeated at her Toilet, and beginning to umpin. . . . . . . Enters Don Julio. Don £ul. Blanca I thought you had been abed ear this, Have you had company to entertain you, - - And keep you up beyond your uſual hour? . . . .” - D. Blan. What Company can I have, you abroad, º As this time of the night . . . . . . . . . D. ful. I fain would find outſomefuch as might pleaſe you: [*] Franciſcatake a Candle and light me in º To Blanca's Cloſet, , , , - . . . . D. Blan." — Good Brother what's the matter?' “. . . . . . . . . . . . ," - - * * * : - - - You were not wont to be focurious 4 tº . -, i. 2 i , ". . As thus to pryinto my Privacies.” 2 ºf * : - . º ~ : * , -- - * - P. ful.
Page 59

- Butletus follow him in, that we may mark His whole demeanour. , º, . iſ . . . ELºvć is p: ful. That you ſhall know anon: Possibidyou - Franciſca, ... Franciſca takes ºne of the Candles, and going be- . . . . . , fore him ſtumbles and falling puts out the light. ºr § Don Julio taking it up, lights it again at the . . . . other on the Table, and going with it himſelf . . . . . . towards Donna Blanca's Cloſer, - D. £al. Theſe Tropes are loſt on me. tº [Exit. Fran. Let him go, now we have gain'd time enough. D. Blan. Thanks to thy timely fall. V, i. Fran. — Perſons employ'd - In ſuch truſts, muſt have their wits about them; . 'Tis clear that he ſuſpećts, but know he cannot, whenºitten impºyon To play the Tyrant over him, with reproaches . - , For this his jealouſie. - r - - w D. Blam. Let me alone for that, , , , . . . . . . . . . . . [Extunt." Enter Don Zancho in diſorder. . . : P. Zane. Curſeon't the Entry door's bolted within, . What ſhall I do * . . . . . . . . . . . . . * : * > EHe pawſer. - I muſt ſeek away gº ºn … . . . . . . . (. . . . . . Through the Perfuming Room, into the Garden. . . . . [Exit. D. ful. Hºuſtºmethiºthere isnoother, The Entry:dborºwas bolted. . . . . c. ". . . . Enter Don Julio with a Cahdle in his hand, and paſ- ſing haftily over the Stage. . . . . . . . . - * -º . . . . . . . . - the stage as ſtealing after Don Julio, º ºſcº Fram. All's ſafeghetakes that way, let him a God'shame : " . Follow his Noſe, to the Perſuming Room..., \, . Pºlan. Heel fright poor silvia out of her wits, But I'le come to her ſuccòur, with a peafº.º. A f I'lering him. ºvºi. tº Dominatiºn: Scene w
Page 60

66: B L / 1 (R.A., -- Scene changer to the Laberatory. Mº ſº. º. iſ .º.º. ºº , Here is to open a curious Scene of a Laberatory in perffes. * > * 'tºve, with a Fºuntain in it, ſome Stills, many shelves .*.*.*, withºts ºf Parcelane, and glaſſes, with Pictures above tº them, the Rºom paved with black and white Marble * *** with a Proſpečf through Pillars, at the end diſcovering - the full Moon, and by it's light a perſpečfive of orange . . . ] . Trees, and taiwards that further end Silvia ſpears $45 a Tableſhifting Flowers; herback turned. 19.1 : * Enter Don Zancho haſtily, and Silvia, that is, Elvira turn- ing about they both ſtartle, and ſtand 4 while as it were : amazed. ºz. ºº is 1. . . .'; 'Lººſ. ſº D. Zan. O heavens! what iſ Iſee , 'Tis meer Illuſion, a Or 'tis the Devil in that Angels form, ſº ºn 2 º' cºcº. '.' Come here to finiſh, by another handi ºf . . . ." . . The fatall work that ſhe begun upon me tº . . . . . . By Don Fernando's. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Silvia Good gods Don Zanchohere! it carinet be, ſº ſº I [*] Or 'tis his Goſt come to revenge his death ºv. On it's occaſioner; For were he alive, He could not but have more humanity . . . . . . . . . . Then (having been my ruine at Madrid, ‘. . . . . . . . . . . / And robb'd me of my home, and honour there) To envy me an obſcure ſhelter here. * : * : . . . . Whilſt they amazed ſtep back from one another. Enter Don Julio who ſeeing Don Zancho with his back to- wards him drawing his Sword ſays. . . . . . . . . . D. ful. Think not (who ear thou art), by flying thus, - . From Room to Room, to ſcape my juſt Revenges. - | - Should'ft thou retire to th’Center of the Earth, - . . . This Sword ſhould find thee there, and pierce thy heart. . [Throwing down the Candle he makes tºward, Don. Zancho, but upon his turning about towards him, - - he makes a little ſtop and ſays. ~ : x ~ : D, ful. Nay, then if it be you, I'ma happy yet … lº i. i it

End of Section 7. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 8
Page 61

º * ! ~ - 5 L V 184 6. In my my misfortune, ſince the gods thus give me The means at once, and by the ſelf ſame ſtroak, To right my honour, and revenge my friend; And by that ačtion, fully to comply - - With what the Duke requires in the behalf Of wrong'd Don Pedro. - Don Julio makes at Don Zancho, he draws and they begin to fight, Silvia, that is, Elvira crying out help, help, rums to part them, and they ſtop upon her interpoſing. Entor Don Fernando baſtily over the stage, as coming from the private Apartment. Don Fer. I hear an out-cry, and clattering of Swords ; My friend engagd, muſt find me by his ſide. - - . . . [Exit and re-enters at another door. As Fernando comes as to the door of the Per- fuming Room, ſeeing them at a ſtand, he - ſtops and ſtands cloſe. - Don Fer. They are Parlying, let's hear. (Aſide. [Donna Blanca and Franciſca paſſing over the Stage. , D. Blan.'Twas Silvia's voice,my heart miſgives me ſomewhat, Fram. Tis ſome new accident, or ſome miſtake, Den Zancho cannot but be ſafe long ſince. Tom Blan. However let us in and ſee. [Exeumt Donna Blanca and Franciſca, and re- enter as at another door of the Perfuming Room, and make a ſtand as ſurpris’d wité . . . . what they ſee. . . Don Blan. We are all undone I fear. Fram: A little patience. [Chichon ſtealing over the Stage. chic. The noiſe is towards the Perfuming Room, Iknow, the back way to it through the Garden. - [Exit Chichon, and re-enters at the further end of - the Labºratory and ſtands cloſe... . . . - Ben Zan. Wit muſt repair the disadvantages. . .(4: - - . . . . . . . ºr - 'me.
Page 62

( * As to remove miſtakes; Know then Don Pulie, | - - - 62 a tº 182. I’me under here, and ſave my Blanca's honour, That once ſecured, there will be time enough To ſalve Elvira's. - - - (Whilſt this paſſes Elvira holds Julio by the arm, he ſtriving to get from her. zancho to £uliol Since by this Ladies interpoſing thus, You have thought fit, our Swords ſhould pawſe a while, It may Ithink conſiſt enough with Honour, So far to ſeek your ſatisfaction Sir, That though I have preſum’d upon your houſe, I have not wrong'd your honour; It is ſhe .." With whom you find me, that hath brought me hither, Her I have long adored, and having got Intelligence, that ſhe was here conceal’d, My Paſſion I confeſs tranſported me Bºyond that circumſpection and regard, .* which men of quality uſe and ought t'obſerve, - Towards one another's dwellings. D. ful. Good gods what an identure's here? Yet all (Aſide. Is well, ſo Blanca's honour be but ſafe. . . . . Sir, you ſurpriſe me much, can this be true *, *. (To D. Zancho Blan. Franciſca heard'ſt thou that, Had everman Aſide.) So ready a wit, in ſuch an Exigent? . . . . - Don Pulio to Elvira.) What ſay you Madam? - Fran, Ware ſurer loſt thenever, unleſs ſhe (Aſide. Have wit, and heart, to take the thing upon her. - - Madam, make ſigns to her, and earneſtly. . . (To Blan, Blanca makes earneſt ſigns. . . Silvia. 2 " ' " . . . - To Elvira. § . .” Franciſca. She looks this way, as if ſhe comprehended [Afide to Blanca.] Your meaning - Flv. Iºnderſtandher, and I knowaswell . . . (Aſſº. What miſchief I may draw upon myſelf, . . . _ But
Page 63

z - 1 * E L * 17 A. - - 63 But let Elvira ſtill dogenerouſly - And leave the reſt to fate. - - Sir, ſince you preſs me, (To julio • My humour ne're could diſavow a truth, Don Zambo's paſſion, and tranſportments for me Beyond all Rules of temper, and diſcreſſion, Have been the cauſe of all my fad misfortunes, And ſtill I ſee muſt be the cauſe of more. - £ul. Unhappy Creature, how thou haſt deceiv'd My prone perſwaſion of thy Innocence... . - Don Zancho If that ſuffice not Sir, you have this ready [***bisºrd. To give you ſatisfaction. . . . D. Fer. Hell and Furies, but I will yet contain . (Aſide. My ſelf, and ſee how far my friend will drive it. 120m ful. Stay Don Zancho, And anſwer me one queſtion, is this Night - - The firſt of your preſuming thus to enter - My houſe by ſtealth? - - Zam. — The quere is malicious, (Aſide. run, and But I muſt thorough, as I have begun. - - Fº There was a . makes me #seal. * . . " ...D. Zancho No Sir, it is not I'le keep nothing from you; , , , ... [to fulis.J Laſt Night upon the ſame occaſion. . . . . ful. — Hold it ſuffices. . - ". - Franciſca All's ſafe, you ſee, for Godſake lets away. Laflashaſtily tº Blanta] E're fºlio perceive us, , , , , Your preſence here, can ſerve for nothing Madam, But to beget new chances, and ſuſpicions. . . . . . . - . . . . [Exeunt Blanca and Franciſcº [Fernando ruſhes out drawing his Sword. Fer. Yes, it ſuffices julio to make º tº This hand ſtrike ſurer then it did before. ' - - Elv. Nothing was wanting to my miſery, (4ſide. Buthis being here to over-hear; But yet : '... . . . . . . Imuſt not ſuffer the ſame hand to kill him " . . . --- - - . . . *-
Page 64

64 E L V 1AA. A ſecond time, upon a greater errour Then was the firſt. (Don Fernandomaking at Don Zancho,Elvira ſteps be- tween, and Julio alſo offers to ſtay him. Fer. Ariving Strive to protećt your Gallant from me, do, tº cousatzucºl Strive, but in vain; The gods themſelves cannot: What you Don julio too? - - (Chichon running out from the place where he lurck’t, ſtrikes out both the lights with his hat. chi. I have loved to ſee fighting, but at preſent, I love to hinder ſeeing how to fight. Knights brandiſh now your blades, 'twill make fine work [Alºud. Among the Gallipots. - -č You have me by your ſide Sir, Let them come (As to his Maffer. They are but two to two. [Aſide to hi. Mans Sir follow me, I’le bring you to the Door. and pulling him.] Don Zanc. There’s no diſhonour in a wiſe Retreat From diſadvantages to meet again Ones Enemy upon a fairer ſcore. [Chichon puſhing his Maſter before him out of the poor. Chichon . There 'tis, advance Sir, I’le make good the Rear. [aſide to his maſter.] [Exeunt Don Zancho and Chichon. Don £el. Ho, who's without 2 bring lights. [He ſtamps. - They cannot hear us, - The Room is ſo remote from all the reſt, - - What a confuſion's this? Recall Fernando, . . . (To Fernando. Your uſualltemper, and let's leave this place, ... . . . . . . . . . And that unhappy Maid, untoit's darkneſs, º żº . . . To hide her bluſhes, ſince her ſhame it cannot. - - . . … (Exit Don Juliogroping, - - - - - Elvira ſola. . . . . . and drawing Fernando - - - with him, . . . - Darkneſs and horrour wellcome, ſince the gods . . . . . . Live in the dark themſelves; For had they light Of what's done here below; They would afford: ; , , , Some - -
Page 65

E L VI (R.A. * , 65 • Some Ray to ſhine on injur'd Innocence, And not inſtead thereof, thus multiply, Obſcuring Clouds upon it, ſuch as the Sun, - - Should he with all his Beams illuminate . . . . . ‘Mens underſtandings ſcarce could diſſipate; I now begin to pardon thee Fernando, Since what thou haſt heard, in this inchanted Place, Carries convićtion inſt againſt my firmaneſs, Above the power of Nature to ſuſpend My condemnation: unleſs wrong’d vertue might Expedt in thee, a juſtice ſo refin'd Asne're was found in man to woman kind. 'Tis now I muſt confeſs, the loſt Elvira, Fit only for a Cloiſter, where ſecure In her own ſpotleſs mind, ſhe may defie All cenſures; And without Impietie Reproach her Fate, evento the Deitie. [Exit grouping her way. ~ A C T. V. Enter Don Julio talking to himſelf, and at another door Fernando, who perceiving it, ſtands cloſe. - Don. #ul, B'. be the gods, that yet my Honour's ſafe, .. - D Amidſt ſuch ſtrange perplexities, from which Fortune, and wit, I think, together joyn'd With all their ſtrength, could hardly an iſſue find. . . . To temper, comfort, or to ſerve my friends. . . . . . . What argument? What means? how to aſſiſt Don Pedro in his aims, and to comply > With what Iowethe Duke, I ſee as little, , … . .” - - - . . . . . . . . . . . . . And leſs conceive, how tobehave my ſelf a of . , , , , As ought a Gentleman towards a Lady, tº 'º'; . . . . . With whoſe Protećtion he hath charg’d himſelf, And brought her to his houſe on that aſſurance, * \"" K whom
Page 66

66 E L V 1 RA. t Whom to expoſe, cannot conſiſt with honour, . . . . . ." However ſhe may have expos'd her own, " And leaſt of all, how to repair to Blanca ºf . The injury I have done her, whoſe high ſpirit . I fear will be implacable. O Heavens ! . . . . . | What a condition's mine * * . . . : - - - - - - - [ Heffands pawfing, Enter Fernando. . . . . . . and ſtartlesſeeing l - . . . . . . . . . . Fernando. . . D. Fer. Pardon dear Couſin, if to avoid one rudenſs ºf I have another unawares committed. ºº Whilſt fearing to interrupt, I have overheard, . . . . . . Yet nothing Couſin, but the ſelf ſame things, 3 º'." My thoughts have been revolving all this night, 2 303 Concern'd for you, much more then for myſelf, ` ºf For I upon reflexion, find I am - • 2 tº Much eaſier then I was 3 By certainty . . . . . . . . . . . . . ." Frce'd from the ſoreſt weight, Perplexity. . . In the firſt place, You muſt forgive your friend, The high diſtemper of laſt Nights tranſportments, I hope you'l find me well recover'd from them, . And that my morning reſolutions are . . . . . . . Such, as will make amends. . . . . . . . . . . . . . D. ful. Make no excuſe dear friend, ſuch provocations.º Surpriſing, are above Philoſophy, `... . And 'tis no ſmall experiment of yours, ... . . . . . ºf . , If after them, you can have brought your ſelf ºººººº... So ſoon, to fix a judgement what to do. . . . . ." º'º. Don Fer. I have fix’t on that, which I am ſure wilfſerve.” All Intereſts but my own, as heretofore . . . . . . I underſtoodmy happineſs, but now , , , , ; Iſhall no longer place it in anythingº vi º º bº. Dependanton the wild Caprichoofothers. . o ºgº. - No fulio.º. º 'º º 'º. 310:v, dii º Iwill be happy eveninſpight offate, ‘’” : Jºid ºr *~

End of Section 8. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 9
Page 67

E L V 1 Ra. & By carrying generoſity upto the height. . . . . . . . . . Elvira ſhall her deat bliſs, owe to me, - . . . . . . " Not only by deſiſting, but by making . . . . ºf Her lov'd Don Zancho marry her, his refuſal . . . " Alone, can make mekill him o're again. - Don ful. Since that unhappy Maid, withall herbeauty And that high Quality, hath made her ſelf . . . . . . . . unworthy of your Marriage, certainly ºf . . . . ... None but Fernando, ever could have pitch’t . . . - - Uponſo Noble a thought, but think withal . . . . What difficulties are likely to obſtrućt it, tº . . . . . D. Fer. Say what occur's to you. ºvºi º ... D. ful. Don Zanche is a man of wit, and courage, And though his paſſion out of doubt be great, . Since it hath made him do ſo wild an action, As that of coming twice into my houſe ... ºr After ſoſtrange a manner 3 Yet Fernando . . . . . . . . . . You cannot but imagine, ſuch a one, º Likely to have quite different reflexions, :O . . . . llpon Elvira's condućt for a wife, * - - - - - From what he has, upoh it for a Miſtreſs, " . . . . . . . . . . They are two notions very differing tº . . . . . . . . . . . . Beſides ſhould the propoſal but appear. º. º. º. . . . . . In the leaſt kind, to ſpring from your deſire, . . . . . . . . . . . . . Whoſe former commerče with her shot unknown, . . . . . It were the only way to drive him offiº. A to tº gº º, ... . . . Paſt all recall, I think few have accepted o * (i) 5. -(, º .. * ...; . Wifºrečommended to them by their Rival. ... N. : ; ; ; DºFer. In that y'have ſeaſon I confeſs ; But julio-, Think of the way, for marry her he muſt . . . . . . . Or die, and by HBotheftālūbut mine. *** ... .º.º. I amthinking of it, and 150petol poſºpam#ulipawing, What Interpoſer can b{{Sºnd tº 222 to sº, no º flºº in this buſineſs? ſince-iſſan Zanche., iii, c. . . . - r - e -- a- in- a gi ºf ... - *gg been her prair gºmers r; fo º ºil. 'Anâ" - - - . . - * , -
Page 68

68, E L 7 I R.A.” And what can be more Natural, then for her To take to heart, Elvira's chief concernment ... nº ſº. * . . . whom he finds here retired inher misfortune. . . . . . . . Astoher ſureſ friends. . . . . . . . . . º D. Fer. Yºhave lighted Couſin on the only way, A. And loſe no time I beg you. . . . . . . . . . \, . D. ful. The leaſt that maybe; but you muſt conſidered; In what a predicament Iam likely . . . . . ~ To be with Blanca, at preſent. . . . . . . . . . D. Fer. I underſtand you (ſince the jealouſic - - - - - - - *** You cypreſt of her.) But 'tistobehoped . . . . . The peace will not belong a making. . . . . . . . . " pºli. You'littleknºwherſpirit, once inflamed, , ** . . . * * , - - - - - - But asi'leloſe no time, ſo I’le omit … . . . . . . . . .” -: , , , , ..." so Art to bring her to a temper, fit . . . . . . . . . . To hear and to advance the Propºſition: " . . . . D. Fr. Heavengive you good ſucceſs. , , , ….sº (* Julio turning back to Fernando. . D. ful. * I had forgot to tell you, that I think ºr It will be neceſſary,that asſoon As I have weather'd Blanca's ſtorm, I make tº so. Aviſit to Don Pedro, to prevent rº, º ºſcº º º … His coming hither,to diſorder us, ſº Beforewe haveſet things Right. . . . . . . p. F. ºrwas notill thoughton; And till your return Iſhaikeep cloſein your Apartment; º ... . . . For Blanca has not ſeen me, and Elvira . . . . . . . . . . . Has too great cares upon her to be curious..…. ... (Extant. Eme, Blanca and Franciſca, Blanca with 4 g4J air, º As in her Ante-Chamber. . . . . T ... D. Blam. Say my Franciſca, can Romancescqual . . . . . t Our laſt night's adventure? was there ºve, a toº such a comeoff our Sex has uſed to boaſt tº gº tº Preſence of mind in Exigents of Love, º ºſ tº | Butibelieve none of usever matcht- tº tº na' *. . ------- -- - -- - , - T}on, ** - * - --/

End of Section 9. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 10
Page 69

Don Zanchº's readineſs in an occaſion, , . . . . . . . . . So ſudden and ſo Critical. ". . . . . . . . . . . - - - " ... in tº * . . . ." Fran. Ever give me the man of ready Parts. . . . . . . . D. Blan. But prithy, whil'ſt we give ion Zanthohis dues, | Let us be juſt too, to poor Silvia's merit ś , - Was ever anything ſo generous? . . . . . . . . . . . or ſo obliging to a Miſtreſs? . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Fran. So it appears Madam, I muſt confeſsºr, But the exceſsofitmakes it ſuſpicious. . . . . . Don, Blan..Fye, eave this humour of detračing ſtill, And call her to me,that I may embrace ..., , , , , , And thank her 3. That done conſider how . . . . . . . . To bring her off,who has brought us o ſo well:(0 ºrs to go ºut. . . . . . ." (Entº Don Julio, Fran. Stay I befeech you, and compoſe your ſelf To act a part quite of another Nature; ". . . . Here comes Don fulie, towards whom I hop You'l tune your ſelf, to a far differing Key From that of thanks and kindneſs. ..." - t * Don Flam. Let mealone for that, I'le playthe Dragon, . . - s ... . . . r tº - 5-; " , ; ; ; ; ; ; , . A e * º, . …” ºffſ. Uſi, ºf ſº I - ºf locº ºt - - - C-" 3 s. frºm hin … d iſ - . . . . . . . v. G. G ſ. º * Jºhnsºn . . . . with a furious cºunt;#; and flyer out #:::::::::::::::" ' ' tº twº º ºvº t; , , --> * D. ful. Dearsifierſtay,andhearms...º.º.º.º. 1). #. j. º tº D. #ul. Hear me but Blanca, and then vent your paſſion. Againſt a Brother, that condemns himſelf. . . . º As much as yºu cando; Bºhèar me ſpeak..., , , , , a D. Blan. Yöuraćtions fulis, have fpokéloudenough. º To Ecchothrough the world.your ſhame and mine; . Has all the tenour of my lifebeen ſuch, ... . . . . v" -- - - - - - J. ºſt . . . . . . . . . -- - + - • * * * : * * * - 1. º. - -

End of Section 10. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 11
Page 70

--- - —” º : - - º 7e E L 71 Rä. . . . . . That malice might have ſtain'd the noon day Sun º º ‘. . . º More eaſily, then tarniſh't Blanca's honour, . . º º And muſt that Ho Öur, now be proſtitute, . . . . ." By the Capricho of an unworthy Brother, - - - Should any other have invaded it, , , . . . . . . . . . . Had not you righted her, She has a heart, , º, ... . . . . . . - - ºr . . º.º.º. ºf . 2 º’ is. Would have foundwa s to right herſelf5: Büf you, , , º, . Th’Agreſſor, Wiitre tºyº tRagé, ". . . . . to a . . . ... [she fling from him, and Exit. ºf rººf...,’s' ". . ſº-, * , , - . . .” - Fran: Slic 3&s it rarely." - - - [Aſide. - ----" - - - ºf 1 + º-, j : %. , , ! . . . . - i. 1-- ?–1" * > . D. Pul. Was ever maſſ º ,[To Franciſca, I muſt confeſs # has reaſºšānd the ſenſe . . . . . . . . *** * Nº ty.” Sºlº ºne, ºn, ºf ol She thus ; Čáčkofſhyfält, becomes j, - - tº Q Put it muſt beyotir work, my dear Franciſca; ; , . . . . . To pacific : When onceyétiſhall but know ..., , . . . . All that his paſt ... hts, I am certainº. 3. ' You'ſ ſay, no humatid cº §§§ould cárà * … … "…’ - *śºka ºt tºo, e.g. Irº, Be proof againſt ſuch &#&#i iášči", " ºut ºz. : Fran. Alaſ ; offices;an ſignific But little.” But I'i • *- -- ~...~", "oº" tº * * * * *** - i [Asif ſhe were trying. ëſure the 6&iſion" [4. … . . . . Gives meaſº heaſt, 90 y dº Lás - “by §: Çiğ § itfiy leave - Ahlºomićh w; º: Tinyieſthee all. [Exeunt. Emºjö §§ ; and Fulvio as in his lodging. -- Don Ped. A God's nameſºvić, whāthāsheenthy meaning, tº: Expeding thee, when ſºliń. #### Thºuwert §§diº fö ñégºgº ºn...: ..….g. In things offègreat weight". ..., ºf ſing: Fulv. Nor have I§ º#; as fººd 43. Of your commands;hā ğ £, . 59mºſ 3&ºi .G. You know the 6f § - . f; myśl isºq . - -,------- rº \lºy ºriidation:horio-3 o'T Łºś, .* I ſate all day in my obſerviſ; ilā tº 3.5 ºzo ºff ji W/ #.;#2 ** * - * * - Ste ºi: a" º, ºt, Q, 2 , º, ..., 1** -
Page 71

E L K I R A. z1 Steal as it were abroad; I as warily, - - Dogg'd them from Street to Street, till Sir, at length He made a ſtand up cloſe againſt a Wall, . . . . . Whilſt that his Servant entertain’d a Woman Cloſe Vail'd, who was come out I think on purpoſe ; From an adjacent houſe; ſoon after he . - Accoſted her himſelf, their Conference - Laſted but little, ſhe made haſt away. . . . . . . . . To th’houſe from whence ſhe came, and he as much . To follow her in. ' ' ' ' ' ... . . . . . . . . . Don Ptd. Where waſt; and why cam'ſt thounot preſently To give me notice as you were direéted. . . . . . . . Fulv. At that you will not wonder, when you know, Whoſe houſe he enter'd; But at this you'l wonder, ... It was Don fulio’s ' ' " ' " ' ". . . .” - D. Pedro ſtartling.] Ha! Dºn julio's ſay'ſt thou? [He pawſer. But now I think on't 'tis no marvel Fulvio, . . . . . . . . . Since newly come to Town, For I remember. * . . . . . pen fulio told me, that Denzansha and he , , º, . . . Had always lived in friendly correſpondence. Fulv. Viſits Sir, only of fair civility - * After long abſence, are not uſually . . . . . . . . Begun by º: §autious mainer; . . . . . Nor uſher'd in, by Femalevail'd condućters: "... . . But pray Sir, hear the reſt. . . . . (*To Fulvio. D. Ped. What can this be?,” ſay on then quickly, (Aſide. Ful. I preſently concluded with myſelf. . . . . . . . That fince Domžalia. ... friend on whoſe . * * * º * p Aſſiſtance you relyed againſt Bin Zancho, ... . . . . . . You near would think Sir, attacquing him “- As he came out from thence, ju gºd it therefore º -- ****** * : *- My wiſeſt courſe to ſtay, and mark 9, 3... s , , ; , , *:::::::::::::::::::: * About which time, . §§ º, That I mightſee both Iſſu's # houſe, , 'o'; ' ' i. º - . - … ------- * ----- - --> * * * * * * * ti -
Page 72

71 ° E L V 1 RA. * It being as lightalmoſt asday, I ſaw The Gallant and his man leap from the wall , - Of julio's Garden, and from thence in haſt " ". . . * Make home. . . . . . . . . . . . . . (£ulio's D. Ped. S'death man thou dream'ſt | Don Zancho from Don In that manner; Awake fool and ſpeak ſenſe. Fulv. I ſay but what I ſaw, as I ſee you. D. Ped. Othe Devil, What the ſame Villain Found the affronter of my friend too, here . In the ſame kind? Give me my Cloak and Sword, 1 muſt know the bottom of this. . . [Exeumt. ... Enter Blanca and Franciſca, as in her Ante-Chamber. D. Blan. I come from ſeeing and carefing'Silvia, But with moſt ſtrange ſurpriſe, ather Comportment Towards me. . . - - Fram. How ! Madam, . . - D. Blan. My words, and Aëtions both, expreſſing to her Not only higheſt gratitude and kindneſs, But a ſolicitude in the concerns . . . . . Of her honor, equal to what ſhe had ſhown In mine; They were receiv'd with ſuch a coldneſs, With ſuch an air of Melancholly pride, . . . . . . . . . . . With half replys, and thoſe not half to th'purpoſe, tº . As make me with amazment to conclude, " . . . . . . º. That either ſhe has loſt her underſtanding, *... Or that there's ſomewhat in't we underſtand not. Fran. She's a Maid of an odd compoſition; -- * * And beſides that, I needs muſt tell you Madam, - That having had my obſervation freer, Then you perhaps during laſt nights adventure, -º I remark'd ſomewhat both in her demeanour, . . And in Don Zanche's, makes me confident . . . . They met not there ſtrangers to one another, As you imagine; But there's time enough Tothink and talk of that: What preſſes now
Page 73

} • ‘Tis time to tack about, to reconcilement. B L V 1 RZ, 73 Is your rightordering of Den julio: You have begun, aswell as can be wiſh't. D. Blam. Say did I not do my part 2 Fran. — Beyond imagination, But take heed now, of over doing it, W. And thought of drawing thoſe advantages From the Embroilment, as may for the future Secure you from like accidents. - 1). Blan. — You ſay well, but how - Fran. The firſt ſtep muſt attonement be between you, Of which he hath ſo earneſtly conjured me - To be an Inſtrument, that you conſenting . To give him a hearing, through my mediation, I am made for ever, an ſetled in the power Of ſerving you, by better cozenning him: ~ :44*.* Beſides he tell's me, he hath that to ſay, And to propoſe unt'ee, as ſhall not only Excuſe him with you, but prevent all danger Of prejudicial rumors, which might riſe From laſt night's accident. D. Blam. — Agreed, let's in (jellily. * And play the ſecond part. . (Exeunt. Enter Don Zancho and Chichona in his own houſe. D. zan. Were we not born with Cauls upon our heads (??-?). Think'ſt thou Chichon 2 to come off twice a row Thus rarely, from ſuch dangerous Adventures. . - Chich. Rather I think with Combs, ſo oftto venture. I). Zan. Thou Coxcomb ſay, had I not my witsabout me? . Chich. 'Twere too uncomplaizant to deny that, You know I love not to talk ſeriouſly; But tell me now in earneſt, are you fift. To have come off ſo, is there no qualm remaining Upon your gentle heart, for leaving ith ſuds Apoor diſtreſſed Virgin, whoſhe is - L I neither
Page 74

74 B L VI R4. I neither know nor care, but I am ſure Had generous Chichon, to ſave his life Play’d a ſweet Innocent Lady ſuch atrick, He would have paſt but for a Recreant Knight, And much the more, ſhe having ſhown herſelf Sogallant, as to ſave her Ladies honour T'expoſe her own : Say true Don Galor, ſay, Were your part found in a Romance or Play, Whoſe Charaćter would it not diſluſter? - D. Zane. How ſoon a fool's bolt's ſhot, without diſtinčtion Of what's the mark. Thou cenſureſt without knowing Who th’expoſed Lady is. Khow then Chichon And wonder,’tis Elvira, that Elvira For whom I fighed, like to have ſigh'd my laſt On her ſcore at Madrid: Don Pedro's Daughter. Chich. You raiſe enchanted Caſtles in the Air, But were it as you ſay, that makes the thing , . More inexcuſable ; You had been too blame. . . . . . ; To have uſed a ſtranger ſo; But ſo thave ſerv'd - - - A Lady whom you had once profeſt to love, - Raiſes the fault above all heightning. ... . . - D. Zanc. Nay, then I ſee I º once play the fool, In anſwering a fool ſeriouſly, . - The things thouſay'ſ are heightnings indeed, Not of my fault, but merit in the Aétion - - Towards my Blanca, ſince to ſave her honour, I did not only ſacrifice Elvira's, - - - " . . . But thus expoſemineown: Time may recover c. Elvira's fame, and mine this quickly ſhall. º - - - - (Claping his hand on his sword- Here take thisletter, and employ your wit - - In finding out the means with ſecrecy To give it Don Fernando unobſerv'd, - Iſhall not ſtir from home, till I have his anſwer. chie. You found him Sir, a man of quick diſpatch * - - - -

End of Section 11. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 12
Page 75

- N - B L * 1 Ra. 75 In your laſtbuſineſs with him at Madrid. [Exit Don Zancho, How honorable 'tis to ſerve a Don. What Petit Baſque on t'other ſide the Mountains, Durſt have aſpired to the high dignity Of carrying a Cartal? A Monſieur Would ſooner have put up a twinge by the Noſe, Then ſent a challenge by a ſerving man. [Exit. Enter Blanca furiouſly, and running to a Cabinet, takes out thence & Stiletto, and Franciſca earneſtly after , her as in Blanca's Cleſet. - Don. Blan. Villains ſhall find, I am not unprovided Wrongs to revenge, that cannot be forgiven. Fran. I thought the ſtrange conſtraint upon her ſelf (Aſide. Wherewith ſhe heard her Brother, would ſerve in the end But to make rage, break out with greater fury; Yet it is well ſhe kept it in ſo long, As toget rid of him. GoodMadam, moderate your ſelf a little. (To Blanca. D. Blan. Preach temper to the damned ſouls in hell, "That they may teach the Traitor moderation, When I have ſent him thither with his Devil. Fram. I do confeſs the provation ſuch, - > As more then juſtifies all #: tranſportments 5 And therefore I beſeech you think not, Madam, In what I ſay, I can the leaſt aim have º Ofſaving him; from the extreameſt fury Of your reſentment; or preſerving her, Who has had the impudence to abuſe you ſo llnderpretence of ſerving; May they periſh, Butlet it be in ſuch away, as may not. I)raw a more diſmal ruine on your ſelf; Let ſwift deſtrućtion ſeaze them; Yet let not Madam your hand, but head diſpence their fate, What can the Iſſue be, offuch an ačtion . . . . . As that of which I ſee that ſhining ſteel . . . . * . * * * ~ L 2 And
Page 76

76 B L 71 RZ. And flaming Eyes of yours? The threatning Comets, I beg but the reflexion of a moment. Blanca walking upon the stage with enraged jeffure; paſſes, at length ſheathing, and puling her stilette in her ſleeve with a ſºber compoſed ine.” Don. Blan.* Franciſca I thank you, for recalling me - Thus to myſelf, I will be temperate: [Aſide. But it ſhall be to make revenge the ſurer. - Fran. Her tone, nor jeſtures cannot cozen me, [Aſide. They both ſeem to diſguiſe a black deſign, But I ſhall watch you, 'tis a halfgain'd cauſe In furie's courſe, to have begot a pawſe. D. Blan. Do what Ibid you preſently Franciſca, Send to Don Zancho, and let him know from me, I earneſtly deſire to ſpeak with him. Fram. Lord Madam, what d'ee mean? D. Blan. To make the pleaſing propoſition to him, As I told my Brother I would. - º Say, am I not moderate? But do without reply, what I command. Fran. Madam, Iſhall obey. . But obſerve you ſo withall, [Aſide. As to prevent the miſchief if I can. [Exit Franciſca. D. Blam. Ye Gods aſſiſt me in my juſt revenge, Or you will make an Athiſt; My firſt work Muſt be before Don Zancho cometoſpeak • With his ſweet Miſtreſs, and with words and looks, As falſe asher's have been, ſo to delude her - With hopes of what ſhe wiſhes,that they both May joyntly fall my Honour's ſacrifice. . . [Exit. - Enter Don Fernando * in Don Julio's private Apartment, D. Fer. Sincegenerofity hath ſo far got The maſtery, as to have made me fix upon a reſolution ſounheard of, llong to ſee it executed. J :
Page 77

- B L 2 I MA. Ży — But ſtay, . I think, I hear Elvira's voice without. . . . . And Blanca's too, here curioſity [He makes as if he harkn'd, to over here, is pardonable. (and then d - [Exit as to go where he may better hear. - Silvia , - Eſºter # and Blanca as in the Ante- ! - chamber, and Fernando peeping * from * - behind a door. ,” D. Fer. Here not a word can ſcape me. Silvia - - #.; Madāmyou wrong my zeal, in ſerving You, Whilſt you attribute to any other motive My yeſterdaysbehaviour. - p. xian.” Such niceties Elvira are out of ſeaſºn, ... . Eºin a tone that may ſhew what ſhe ſays to *farº't. I ſeek your ſatisfaction in a Love, - - Wherein it ſeemsyou have been long engaged. - Donna Elviralooking round, and Fernandoſtarting back. 15, Fer. I hope ſhe did not ſee me. [Aſide. D. Elv. My ſatisfaction ſay you, in my Love, of whom for heaven'sſake; if you mean Don Zanchº, Y’are very far from gueſſing at my thought...N. - D. Fer. By heaven Shas ſeen me,and plays the Devil ſtill.[Aſide. D. Elº. By all that’sgood, I am far from loving him: . . *Iſay not worſe becauſe I know ſhe loveshim: [*Aſide. p. Fr. Ah Elviral this is too much, yet not enough Tochange in me, a Noble reſolution. - - [A noiſe is heard 4 ofpeople coming up ſtairs. D. Blan. Ihearſome coming upſtairs, ſhould it be (Aſide. Don Zancho, I am not yet ready for him, ºffee wearelikely tobě interruptedhere I ſºlvira. Eijira, we ſhallbé better in my Cloſet. (Exit Planca. p. Élv. Madam, I’le follow you. . . . . . . What can ſhe mean? ſincethat ſhe needs muſt think, Ik - –’ , -kilow' . - - - - . -- * - w
Page 78

78 B L V 1 R Z. -- Iknow the paſſionſheherſelfhas for him. -x Elvira having ſtay’d a while **ind, a ſhe is going to fl. low .#Enter her Father Don j º É. Vio, ſhe ſtarts and #and, confounded ; He ſeeing her - dºw out his Dagger and mate, 4, ber. D. Ped. Vile ſtainer of my blood, have Iherefound thee? Elvira perceiving the door a lui, ºpen where Don Fer: landº *, flies thither and geisºn. P. fer. This makes it clear ſhe ſaw me. [Affae as Elvira thruſt; in. Don Pedro ſeizes the door befºrei, i. quite ſhut, and they ſtruggle, he to pull it *P* *d Don Fernando to ſhut it. *** *fter ſome conteff, Don Fernand, gets it cloſe, and *altº it within: Don Íedro, , enraged perſon pulls and bounces at the door. - P. Peć. In vain ſhould Mountains interpoſe, between Her and her puniſhment. [He bounces ſtill as to break down the door. Enter Donna Blanca. * *. What Bedlam have wehere; and where's Elvira 2 P: Pº. You have one here, will knowhow. revenge Conſpiracies to affront him ; And you Lady hoere you are,that ſeem to take upon you, - X had beſt produce the wicked thing you have named 2 . . . Or by this Steel --- [Donna Blanca cry; out. P". Blan. Ho! brother, brother, help againſt a madman. Enter Don Julio. - P. jul. Peace, Blanca, Peace,you know not what you ſay, Pom Pedro is Maſter here. - - . . . P. ºlam. I know not your Don Pedro, but I’me ſure 9° tº be tyde in Chains, could donomº - Then he has done. - - - - P. Pul. Have patience Siſter; 'Tis Elvira's Father, Withºares enough upon him to juſtifie - Any diſtemper. - - . . . - Blan. —— Precious Elvira's Father; - - - Nay, then I leave you. [Blanca flings out of the Room. £ul.
Page 79

. . E L V 1 T. A. . 29 jul. Othe unluckineſs of his coming . (Aſide. Sounſeaſonably; 'Twas to prevent that, - I went abroad to ſeek him. 12. Ped. What's this Don £ulio 2 can a Gentleman Of Blood, and Honour,uſe another thus * What after ſuch engagements to the Duke, • * : And to my ſelf, to be my friend and helper, . To prove the ſhelterer of my ſhame's chief Authour; I do not wonder now, Don Zancho himſelf, Should have been here at midnight. - D. #ul. I am hard put to't, help wit to bring us off. [Aſide. * Be as diſtemper'd as you pleaſe Don Pedro, [*To him. It ſhall not alter me. But yet me-thinks It would not ill become your gravity, - To think a while, before you make a judgement, And raſhly frame injurious concluſions, From things wherein a friend has merited from you: Do but conſider, and then ſay, what £ulio Could do of more advance to what you wiſh, Then having found your Daughter, to have brought her To his own houſe, where ſhe might be with honour Accompanied, and ſerv'd as ſuch, by Blanca, until ſuch time, as things maturely weigh'd, You ſhould a final reſolution take. w s And ſince Don Zancho's being here laſt night, I ſee's no ſecrett'ee, me-thinks you ought Tº have been ſo juſt to me, as to believe , . That ſince I admitted him within theſe walls, It was in order to the ſerving you. . . . D. Ped. Noble Don Julio, you muſt pity have Of an old man's diſtemper in afflićtion, - I ſee I was in the wrong pray pardon it. . . - D. jul, O this is more then needs, and now good Sir, • If you’l be pleas'd to walk a turn or two f - . . . . r - I'th'Garden, I'le there give you a full account, tº - - w - - - º * - - - - - - - º : -
Page 80

8o - B L / 1 RA. How I have laid things for your ſatisfaction. D. Ped. I’le wait on you. D. Pul. — Go Sir, there lies your way: (*Turning * And you boy fail not when Don Zancho comes (to the Page. To give me notice of it in the Garden. . [Exeant. Enter Don Zancho and paſſes over the Stage with Chichon af. ter him,and Enter Franciſca,and pulling Chichon ſtays him. Fran. Stay, ſtay, Chichon, a word w'e, it imports. [Shºhiſtºrs Chic. I hope you are not in earneſt. (with him. Fram. - By my ſoul I am; There is no other way, but for us both To get up the backway, and there to watch The time to interpoſe. - - Chic. Can ſhe be ſucha Fury? her looks are All milk and honey. - - Fran. You cannot fancy anything ſo Tragique, But ſhe is capable of executing, " . When once provok'd in point of Love and Honour, - Beyond her bounds of temper. * Chic. Lead the way. . . . [* Aſide * I'le have the pleaſure to hold up the fright She's in, ſince Iamſure there is no danger, Knowing as Idomy Maſter's mind towards Blanca : Beſides’tis to be hoped, that theſe diſorders May produce ſomewhat that may put an end To my Maſters Quarrel, or afford me means - To give Fernando his Letter. [Exeant. Enter D. Fer. Elvira lying upon the Couch in the private A- D. Fer. This laſt diſfimulation moves memore (partment. Then all the reſt, but yet it muſt not alter What honour hath inſpired, ſee how ſhe lies And how ſcarce brought to life from her diſmay, She reſumes ſcorn, to have been ſav’d by me; But multiply what injuries thou wilt, Perfidious Maid, thou ſhall't not diſappoint Fer-
Page 81

Come along with me, I'le bring you to a place . . . B L VI (RJ4. 81. Fernando of the glory that he aims at, - - Of making thy proud heart Elvira, owe It's happineſs to him. - — But I hear again A noiſe without - • ‘Tis Don Zancho, ſ And Iſee Blanca coming towards him; This falls out luckely, that Imay hear What paſſes, for certainly their meeting Avowedly thus, can be no other Subjećt, \ But what Don £ulio has propos'd to Blanca.[Exit as to go harken. Enter Don Julio and Don Pedro as in the Garden. - D. ful. That's all the remedy, that in theſe caſes The wiſeſt can propoſe unto themſelves, His fortun's ſtrait ’tis true. - - D. Ped. That's what I leaſt regard, in this occaſion, - So honour be but ſafe, the leſs they have, , , - The more will be her pennance for her folly; But ſhould Don Zanche upon any Umbrage, From what has paſt between them, prove ſo Inſolent. As to rejećt the marriage, Then I truſt— - £ul. O ſay no more of that, Rely upon't, Should he be guilty of that horrid Outrage, This Sword ſhould pierce his heart, tho' th' only friend I have i'th'world,ſhould interpoſe his own; And Sir, to let you ſeemy franck proceeding, . [He peeps. * - * - Where joyntly over hearing all that paſſes - - - 'Twixt him and Blanca, ſhould he play the Villain, ... . . . His life may pay for’t, ear he ſtir from thence. . . - P.Ped.May heaven repay ſuchgenerousadisoffriendſhip. Esº - Enter Don Zanchº,and Fernando appears tº behind the deer. D. zºne. For her ſo ſuddenly, and ſo avow'dly "... . Toſend for me hither, is very ſtrange, . . . . . . . . . . . . - *** *** **5-3. tº uſ; to is tº What can it mean? . . . . . . . . . * - - º - ‘M’. *** - - - * 'tºº sº...?' - - *** * Enter º:Oy i
Page 82

3. B L V 1 RA. Enter Blanca. * . . . D. Blan.Now lend me temper heaven,but for a moment, tºfº” Till calmly I have drawn him to pronouace , - - The ſentence of his own too noble death For ſuch a Traytor. - - . . . . * I think you come not without ſome ſurprize [*To him with an Ponzanihe, at my ſending for you ſo, (affected cheerfulneſs. ſº i. But let's ſit down for I have much to ſay tee. - / She takes him by the hand, and ſeats him in one chair, and ſhe ſets her ſelf in the ºther clºſe tº him on his right hand, and fumbles in her ſleeve. . . . . D. Blan. I’me ſo well plac't I cannot miſs the mark. [Aſide. D. zinc. Good Madam, what's the matter for I ſce - Diſorder in you, put me out of pain. - * -- - - - - D. Blan. That I ſhall quickly do., “ . . . . . . . Know then Don Zancho, ‘’’ ‘‘‘, ‘I º In the firſt place, you muſt not interrupt me, ’’ º º What cycryou ſhall hear; I'le take it ill elſe . . . º - When I have done, then ſpeak your mind at leaſure, I come not to argue, but conclude. P. Zanc. Your will's a Law to me, . . . . . . . —- * But whether tend’s all this? . * [* Aſide. D. Blan. I do for once, allow you to remember, - All that has paſt between us, º The folly of my Love, The falſhood of yours; That done, And never to be thought on more, D. Zanc. For heavens ſake Madam — D. Blan. Break not the Rule was ſet. Know I inſtrućted amin all your ſtory, And am ſo far grown Miſtreſsof myſelf, - That I who th'other day, could ſcarce o're come The ſenſe of a ſlight failour at Madrid, Canhere at home ſuffer Indignities: - And tell you calmly, and with unconcern'dneſs, , , , , , Be you Elvira's, and Elvira yours, " " * 1: .” -- . 1 a - w ...+ - w -
Page 83

x E. L. P.I. R. A. - - 8; I come to do a partyou little look’t for From Blanca's ſpirit, I muſt make the marriage, . . . All things are ready, and her Father here, - - Now you may ſpeak Pan Zancho, but the thing Admit's of no delay. . . . - - * D.Zame."But can this beinearneſtºſure it cannot ; [*Pawſing What need theſe trials of ſo firm a faith? . . ." (a while. D. Blan. Leave triflng, 'tis no longer time for tricks, , , It is not in the power of fate to alter - … The reſolutions taken. - (Don Zanchopauſes. D. Fer. — She has put it home. . . . . . . . (Aſide. D. zam. Madam, you uſe me hardly, this demeanour Paſſes my skill, to judge #: whenceitſprings; You ſay it is not in the power of fate, . . . . . . . To change your reſolutions; but I’me ſure If they be ſuch, 'twill leſs be in it's power . . . . ~ * To alter mine; but yet before I die . . . . . . . You muſt be left without excuſe, by knowing , , , . " The truth of all. . . . . . . . . . ſº - D. Fer. Here it imports indeed to be attentive. . . . (Aſide. . . D. Zanc. Madam, 'tis true, that abſent at Madrid, . - The cuſtom of the Court, and Vanity, - Embarqued melightly in a Gallantry, ºi nº a -- With . moſt famed of beauties there Elvira; - Thoſe, and no other, the true Motives were, To all my firſt adreſſes, till her ſcorns; ſº a . . . . Which ſhould have ſtop’t them, had engag'd memore d ... . And made a Love injeſt, a point.gfhangūr; ºc ºf : … e. . . Iboat allhot diſdaipā, without tranſportment, , , - "Till having gain’d her waiting Woman's kindneſs, º is ºw. I learn’t from her, that all Elvira's ſlightings -o º - *:::::::: thought, had ſprung from ſevere Maxims,” ºr and prec 9ſ deep engagementin another Love, gº tºol ºn tº ºf With a young Gallant Dom Fernande fºliº: tº lºw wa - 2 1t * . -- -- *- *:::t . ~ * -- - --- w - - - - - . . . - - - - . . . *-*- - - _* , - ~ \ -- - - uſneſs of humour, were the effe′s lºop ºn 1 ºr 3: .
Page 84

- "- - * - - - - 34 B L 71 RA. With whom the cruel Dame, was ſo far gone; . . . . . . As to admit him almoſt every night 'T' '.' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' Into her Chamber. . . . . . . . . º. D. Fer. — Bleſt gods what do I hear? '' (Aſide. D. Zancho I ſcarce believing the thing poſſible, ' ' ' ' 2 ſºlinº]: Ulrged my Intelligencer, todoformé º . That which her Lidy ſofanbther did, ‘ºf 1-, -º And to admitmetoher Chamber, where ºf . tº ". tº By being Eyewitneſsof her Lady's actions ºn . . . . {{ I might transfer my entire love to her ſelf. . . . * * : * * , She granted my requeſt, and late one Night - . . . . . Somewhat before the Gallant's uſual hour, . . .'; º '. She brought me a back way up into her Chamber; sº ***** {r Within Elvira's ; my ſtay had not been long, v . When having found the truth of what ſhe had told me... . . . ." º s --- * * * * * - - - - - : * * * Converting rage into appearing kindneſs . . . . i. To my informer, and expreſſing it. . . . . . . ºf uncautiouſly, we made a ſudden noiſe, ſº º | 2:3 º With which Elvira alarm’d, and coming in, . . . . . . . . . Followed by Don Fernando; That fellout, * Which you have heard before. - . . .” --, - . . . . – - -- *-* 12- : *** -- - - Don Julio beckwing Don Pedro after him; paſ; ſing over a corner ºf the stage. . . . . . . . . D. :Pul. By this time, I ſuppoſe, ſhe will have made • The propoſition to the full, and we - - - - - “… Shall come at the juſt time to hear his anſwer. --" Ty . . . . [Exeum Don Pedro and Don Julio: Don Zancho If fince that hour, I have ever ſeen . . . . [*] Orthought upon her, till laſt night's ſurpriſe; May Ifor ever periſh ; And me-thinks - The uſe I made of that; to your advantage; tº Might challenge from you, a more juſt conſtruction. ‘º ſº ãon, Blan. Itold you at firſt, I came nothere to argue s : ; ; ; , • Ult . f % -

End of Section 12. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 13
Page 85

. But to conclude ſay, will you marry her; - - Or fall by his ſide. B L 2 I r2, 8; ‘’’ ‘Don Julio and Don Pedro peep out as from behind the hanging. . . . . . . Don ful. W’are come you ſee, juſt as we could have wiſh't. Dºn Ped. His fate hangs on his Lips. . . . . . . - . . . . . . . . . . I To Blanca. Don Zanc.You are Miſtreſs of your words,and ačtionsMadam, And may uſe me as you pleaſe ; But this hand Shall ſooner pierce this heart, then ene be given In marriage to Elvira, - { . . . . . . . . . . . - Don Pedro and Don Julio ruſh in with - ‘. . . their ſwords and daggers drawn, and ºf 9", . . . Don Zancho draws too. - D. Ped. Then Villain die, heaven is too weak to ſave thee By any other means. . . . . . . . . . . . - (Fernando draws and ruſhing out, But here is one that ſhall, - Don Fer. D. ped. — O'heaven's what's this? . . . . 100m Fernando Solis protećting him, " . . . . . . Nay, then the whole world conſpires againſt my Honour. ion. Blan. For heavens ſake Gentlemen (Donna Blanca . . . . . . , (runs in between. Chic.Now by my Grandam's Pantable’tis pritty, (From behind. I’le bruſh their Coats if once it come to fighting, Fernando's of our ſide. . . . . . . . - - - - , : * ~ * -- - t - * - i. - - - - - - is ... 1 w sº Franciſca and Chidon with a long Broom run. *** * - º º' . . . out alſo from behind the hanging. ‘. . . . . [...” - . . . . . . " - ; Dam #wl. What frenſie's this Fernandof was not you ... . Engaged me to effectthemarriage? ſure ware alſº , - Bewitch't. - sº -- . . . . . . º ºs. • ... 3 º' - D. Fer.
Page 86

86 E L VI R A. - D. Fer. - Stay my Don Julio,ſtay, - i. And let Dow Pedro have patience but to hear me; " 'Tis true, but you know well upon what grounds Thoſe are quite changed, by my having over heard All that hath paſt 3 For my Elvira, £ulie, Proves ſpotleſs in her faith, as in her Beauty, And I the only guilty, to have doubted: ; , , , , ; , ; What have I then to do, but here to proſtrate My ſelf at her offended Father's feet, And beg his pardon 2 That obtain'd, t'implore His help, to gain me hers, as to a perſon In whom reſpect for him, hathalways held Proportion with my paſſion for his Daughter. D. Ped. You know Don julio, when Iſpake with you, The terms of eſtimation, and reſpect - - Wherewith I mention'd tee this Gentleman, - - - - ‘. . .\, , .<! And therefore ſince in his adreſs t'Elvira ºn , tº º, ºr ºl There was no other fault, but making it - Unknown to me; And that I ſee his thoughts . . . . . . . . . Are truly Noble 3, Honour thus engaged, … . . . . . . () That ought to be forgot, and I to think . . . . . . . . . . . Myſelf moſt happy, in ſuch a Son-in-law §1 ºz. . a woº ºf But where's Elvira P--- ". . . . . . . , , , , , , , º, º A D. Fer. She's there within, where Idare not appear . . . Before her, knowing now ſuch guilt upon me, If Blanca would employ her Intereſt . . . . . . . . . . And eloquence, perhaps ſhe might prevail – º ºſº | Togetherhither, when ſhe ſhall have told herº, , , , º, What changes a few minutes time hath wrought. D. Blam. I never went on a more pleaſing Arrant. . (Exit Don Blanca and Franciſca, Fram. * I am ſtruck dumb with wonder. - tº . . ... ', (44; ſhe goes out. P. Fer. Now Blanca is away, I'letake this time ºf 5-gº To ſpare her bluſhes?ulio, and tell you ... . . . - Though N ~ --> LZſ--
Page Scan 97

B L * 17 A. tº Though I have broak one marriage for Don Zanhe, ºf * You needs muſt give me leave to make another, ºf To which unleſs I’me very much deceiv'd, You'l find on neither part repugnancy.... . . . . . . . . . D. #ul. I underſtand you, and Ithankthe gods . . . They did not make me underſtand the wrong, ". . . . . . . Till they have made it none, ſince lobſerve ". . . . . . Don Zancho's looks joyning in your deſires. .* D. Zane. A heart ſo full of love as mine for Blanca, Doº expreſsitſelf, when it ſpeaks leaſt. Enter Donna Blanca, Donna Elvira and Franciſca. (Elvira ºff. herſelf at her Fathers feet, D. Elv. Now that the juſtice of the gods, at length Hath cleer'd me from ſuſpicions, derogatory To th’honour of your blood, I hope a Cloiſter May expiate my fault as to ãfiº. " * , - . . . (Raiſing her. D. Ped. Riſe Child, The Incloſure I condemn you to Is Don Fernando's Arms,give him your hand. - D. Elv. 'Tis yours Sir, to diſpoſe of I confeſs, And if it be your will, I muſt ſubmit ; - Butlet him know, who could ſuſpect Elvira, She never could be his, but by obedience. D. Fer. I am Thunder ſtruck. - (Elvira giving him her hand. D. Elv. Be not diſmay’d Fernando. - Since I profeſs this a meer ačt of duty, - Another duty may Elvira move, To re-inflame on better grounds her Love. D. #al. Blanca I fear you'l hardly be perſwaded [*] To give yours to Don Zancho; Buta Brother For ~
Page Scan 98

º - ... < *- : *-* * - * - - ... tº -º - * A : $8 # * B ºf 18.4. For once may play the Tyranº Give it him; . . . . . . It muſt be ſo, ; : zºº - *. . . .”.::. . . ( They joyn hands, D. Fer. I now renounce old Maxims, having you Elvira, Iamſure, The very beſt provestrue; chis. Hold thereibeg you Sir, That will appear By that time you have Married been a Year. . -- - * - - * - * - - -º - . . . . . . - . . . . . - * - ** .* : … • * ~ * - - - -- - -- - -- -- - - - - - - * , - - - - * . . . - - - - - - - - - - º - - - *-*.** º • .*** • 4. - - * . - t - -- - - -- - - - - - * * 's - - - - -- **. -- - - - * - - - - - - - : - - y - t * , - - -- l - - {<. - ſ - ! - * * - w ! * - y º - - - - - -" º - * - - - - - - - - - - - - * - * - - - ,------ - - - - --- - 2. - * - - - --- - - - -- * !. - - - - - - - y - r − y - - - - - - º - : - {J. J. º --- * - - ar y - -- * : - \ - - * * * * 2. ::ſ - - 1. - - - -- - º + - - - - - - º w - - --- - - -- - ~ - - -* * - - - - - - - . . . . º * . - --- f. * : * -- - - * * º - - -- * - r - - ''. t .." -- a ~ --- - - - - \ºf - J - ** - - -- - - -- ---- - - * - -- * - - - - - - - - * - - 24, 1: . . . . . ) i Q. - º - -- * * - - * * --- - - • * - -- - - - - - - --- - º z - - - w w - .. º / - - - º w - - t --- -.
Page Scan 99

Blank page
Page Scan 100

Blank page
Page Scan 101

Blank page
Page Scan 102

Blank page

End of Section 13. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents

End of text. Return to beginning.
