Don Sebastian, King of Portugal : a tragedy acted at the Theatre Royal / Written by Mr. Dryden, . | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
Don Sebastian, King of Portugal : a tragedy acted at the Theatre Royal / Written by Mr. Dryden, .
Author
Dryden, John, 1631-1700Dryden, John, 1631-1700
Published
London :Printed for Jo. Hindmarsh, at the Golden Ball in Cornhil,1690
Description
[16], 132, [4] pages ;22 cm
Rights
Public Domain, Google-digitized.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc1.31822043036292

Table of Contents

    Front Cover
    Title Page
    Section 1 on page number 1
    Section 2 on page number 20
    Section 3 on page number 41
    Section 4 on page number 42
    Section 5 on page number 43
    Section 6 on page number 54
    Section 7 on page number 69
    Section 8
    Section 9
    Section 10

Book Text
Front Cover
Page Scan 1

Blank page

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 2

Blank page
Page Scan 3

Blank page
Page Scan 4

•••• ••••• • • • | ----- *****---- « ±
Page Scan 5

º º •'. A. - aſ - - 2 : A * A “. - . . - *~ cº-e - - º - - --> * º -- º
Page Scan 6

Blank page

End of Front Cover. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Title Page
Page Scan 7

--- - 2. D ON - SEBASTIAN, 3'sing of 330rtugal: T R A G E D Y Aćted at the - Theatre Royal. Written by Mr. T R Y T E MC. —Nec tarda Senečius Debilitat vires animi, mutatáue vigorem. Virgil. Lo W D ox: Printed for jo. Hindmarſh, at the Golden Ball in Cornhil M DC XC. -
Page Scan 8

Don Sebaſiian King of Portugal. A Tragedy. Terſons Repreſented I Don Sebaſtian King of Portugal, By Mr. Williams. 2 Müley-Moluch Emperor of Bàrbary, Mr. Kynaſton. 3 Dorax, a Noble Portugueſe now a Renegade, for- merly Don Alonzo de Sylvera Alcalde, or Governor of Alcazar, Mr. Betterton. Benducar; Chief Miniſter and Favourite to the Emperor, - — Mr.Sandford. The Mufti Abdalla, —Mr. linderhill. Muley-Zeydan Brother to the Emperor, Mr. Powell.jun. Don Antonio, a Young Noble amorous Portugueſe, now a Slave, Mr. Betterton. Don Alvarez, an old Counſellor to Don Sebaſtian, now a Slave alſo, - Mr. Bowenan. 9 Muſtapha Captain of the Rabble- Mr. Leigh. lo. Almeyda a Captive Queen of Barbary, Mrs. Barry. 1.1 Morayma, Daughter to the Mufti, Mrs. Montfort. 12 Johayma, Chief Wife to the Mufti, - Mrs. Leigh. Two Merchants. Rabble, - A Servant to Benducar. A Servant to the Mufti. Scene in the Caſtle of Alcazar. 4. :
Page Scan 9

T O T H E - Right Honourable Phili Earl of Leyceſſer, &c. AR be it from me, (My moſt Noble Lord) to think, that any thing which my meanneſs can produce, ſhou'd be wor- thy to be offer'd to your Patronage 5 or that ought which I can ſay of you ſhou'd recommend you farther, to the eſteem of good men in this preſent Age, or to the veneration which will cer. tainly be paid you by Poſterity. On the other ſide, I muſt acknowledg it a great preſumption in me, to make you this Ad. dreſs 5 and ſo much the greater, becauſe by the common ſuſ. frage even of contrary parties, you have been always regarded, as one of the firſt Perſons of the Age,and yet no one Writer has dar'd to tell you ſo: Whether we have been all conſcious to our ſelvesthat it was a needleſs labour to give this notice to Mankind, as all men are aſham'd to tell ſtale news, or that we were juſtly diffident of our own performances, as even Cicero is obſerv'd to be in awe when he writes to Atticus 5 where knowing himſelf overmatch'd in good ſenſe, and truth of knowledg, he drops the gawdy train of words, and is no longer the vain-glorious Ora- tor. From whatever reaſon it may be, I am the firſt bold offen- der of this kind : I have broken down the fence, and ventur'd into the Holy Grove ; how I may be puniſh'd for my profane attempt, I know not; but I wiſh it may not be of ill Omen to your Lordſhip; and that a crowd of bad Writers, do not ruſh into the quiet of your receſſes after me. Every manin all chang. es of Government, which have been, or may poſſibly arrive, will agree, that I cou’d not have offer'd my Incenſe, where it cou’d be ſo well deſerv'd. For you, My Lord, are ſecure in your own merit; and all Parties, as they riſe uppermoſt, are ſure to court you in their turns 5 'tis a tribute which has ever been paid your vertue: The leading men ſtill bring their bul- lion to your mint, to receive the ſtamp of their intrinſick value, that they may afterwards hope to paſs with human kind. They - º riſc
Page Scan 10

The Epiſtle Dedicatory. riſe and fall in the variety of Revolutions ; and are ſometimes great, and therefore wiſe in mens opinions, who muſt court them for their intereſt: . But the reputation of their parts moſt com- monly follows their ſucceſs 5 few of 'em are wiſe, but as they are in power : Becauſe indeed,they have no ſphere of their own, but like the Moon in the Copernican Syſteme of the World, are whirl’d about by the motion of a greater Planet. This it is to be ever buſie; neither to give reſt to their Fellow creatures, nor, which is more wretchedly ridiculous, to themſelves: Tho truly, the latter is a kind of juſtice, and giving Mankind a due revenge, that they will not permit their own hearts to be at qui- et, who diſturb the repoſe of all beſide them. Ambitious Me- teors how willing they are to ſet themſelves upon the Wing; and taking every occaſion of drawing upward to the Sun: Not conſidering that they have no more time allow'd them for their mounting, than the ſhort revolution of a dav : and that when the light goes from them, they are of neceſſity to fall. How much happier is he, (and who he is I need not ſay, for there is but one Phoenix in an Age,) who centring on himſelf, remains immovable, and ſmiles at the madneſs of the dance about him. He poſſeſſes the midſt, which is the portion of ſafety and con- tent : He will not be higher, becauſe he needs it not 5 but by the prudence of that choice, he puts it out of Fortunes power to throw him down. 'Tis confeſt, that if he had not ſo been born, he might have been too high for happineſs; but not en- deavoring to aſcend, he ſecures the native height of his ſtation from envy 5 and cannot deſcend from what he is, becauſe he depends not on another. What a glorious Charašter was this once in Rome; I ſhou'd ſiy in Athens, when in the diſturbances of a State as mad as ours, the wiſe Pomponius tranſported all the remaining wiſdom and vertue of his Country, into the San- &uary of Peace and Learning. But, I wou'd ask the World, (for you, My Lord, are too nearly concern'd to judge this Cauſe) whether there may not yet be found, a Character of a Noblé Engliſhman,equally ſhining with that illuſtrious Roman 2 Whether I need to name a ſecond Atticus 5 or whether the World. has not already prevented me, and ſix’d it there without my naming. Not a ſecond with a longo ſºd Proximus intervalſº, not - - - a Young
Page Scan 11

The Epiſtle Dedicatory. a Young Marcellur, flatter'd by a Poet, into a reſemblance of the firſt, with a frons lata parum, & deješio lumina vultu, and the reſt that follows, ſº qua fata aſpera rumpas Tu Marcellus eris: But a Perſon of the ſame ſtamp and magnitude; who owes nothing. to the former, beſides the Word Roman, and the Superſtition, of reverence, devolving on him by the precedency of eighteen hundred years. One who walks by him with equal paces, and ſhares the eyes of beholders with him: One, who had been firſt, had he firſt liv'd; and in ſpight of doating veneration is ſtill his equal. Both of them born of Noble Families in unhappy Ages, of change and tumult: ; both of them retiring from Affairs of State: Yet, not leaving the Common-wealth, till it had left it. ſelf; but never returning to publick buſineſs, when they had once quitted it; thocourted by the Heads of either Party. But who wou'd truſt the quiet of their lives, with the extravagan- cies of their Countrymen, when they were juſt in the giddineſs. of their turning; when the ground was tottering under them at every moment 5 and none cou’d gueſs whether the next heave of the Earthquake, wou'd ſettle them on the firſt Foundation, or ſwallow it? Both of them knew Mankind exactly well; for both of them began that ſtudy, in themſelves; and there they, found the beſt part of humane compoſition, the worſt they learn'd by long experience of the folly, ignorance, and immo- rality of moſt beſide them. Their Philoſophy on both ſides, was not wholly ſpeculative, for that is barren, and produces nothing but vain Ideas of things which cannot poſſibly be known; or if they cou’d, yet wou'd only terminate in the un- derſtanding; but it was a noble, vigorous, and pračtical Philo- ſophy, which exerted it ſelf in all the offices of pity, to thoſe who were unfortunate, and deſerv'd not ſo to be. The Friend was always more conſider'd by them than the cauſe: And an Oğavius, or an Anthony in diſtreſs, were reliev'd by them, as well as a Brutus or a Caſſius. For the lowermoſt party to a noble mind, is ever the fitteſt obječt of good will. The eldeſt . of them, I will ſuppoſe for his honour, to have been of the Academick Sečt, neither Dogmatiſt nor Stoick; if he were not, . ..I am ſure he qught in common juſtice, to yield the precedency to his younger Brother. For ſtiffneſs of Opinion is the diº, - - A 3 of .
Page Scan 12

w The Epiſtle Dedicatory. of Pride, and not of Philoſophy: 'Tis a miſèrable Preſump- tion of that knowledg which humane Nature is too narrow to contain. And the ruggedneſs of a Stoick is only a ſilly affe&tation of being a God: To wind himſelf up by Pulleys, to an inſen- ſibility of ſuffering 5 and at the ſame time to give the lye to his own Experience, by ſaying heſuffers not, what he knows he feels. True, Philoſophy is certainly of a more pliant Nature, and more accommodated to human uſe ; Homo ſhºw, human; 3 me mihil alienum puto. A wiſe man will never attempt an impoſſi- bility; and ſuch it is to ſtrain himſelf beyond the nature of his Being; either to become a Deity, by being above ſuffering, or to debaſe himſelf into a Stock or Stone, by pretending not to feel it. To find in our ſclves the Weakneſſes and Imperfeółions of our wretched Kind, is ſurely the moſt reaſonable ſtep we can make towards the Compaſſion of our fellow Creatures. I cou’d give Examples of this kind in the ſecond Atticus. In every turn of State, without meddling on either ſide, he has always been favorable and aſſiſting to oppreſt Merit. The Praiſes which were given by a great Poct to the late Queen Mother on her re- building Somerſet Palace, one part of which was fronting to the mean Houſes on the other ſide of the Water, are as juſtly his: For, the diſtreſt, and the afflićied lye . . Moſt in his Thoughts, and always in his Eye. Neither has he ſo far forgotten a poor Inhabitant of his Suburbs, whoſe beſt proſpect is on the Garden of Leiceſter-Houſe; but that more than once he has been offering him his Patronage, to reconcile him to a World, of which his Misfortunes have made him weary. There is another Sidney ſtill remaining, tho there can never be another Spencer to deſerve the Favor. But one Sidney gave his Patronage to the applications of a Poet; the other offer'd it unask'd. Thus, whether as a ſecond Atticus, or a ſecond Sir Philip Sidney, the latter, in all reſpects, will not have the worſe of the compariſon; and if he will take up with the ſecond place, the World will not ſo far flatter his Modeſty, as to ſeat him there, unleſs it be out of a deference of Manners, that he may place himſelf where he pleaſes at his own Table. - * - - I may
Page Scan 13

The Epiſtle Dedicatory. I may therefore ſafely conclude, that he, who by the con- ſent of all men, bears ſo eminent a Charaćter, will out of his inborn Nobleneſs, forgive the Preſumption of this Addreſs. 'Tis an unfiniſh'd Pićture, I confeſs, but the Lines and Features are ſo like, that it cannot be miſtaken for any other; and with- out writing any name under it, every beholder muſt cry out, at the firſt ſight, this was deſign'd for Atticut 5 but the bad Art- ift, has caſt too much of him into ſhades. But I have this Ex- cuſe, that even the greater Maſters commonly fall ſhort of the beſt Faces. They may flatter an indifferent Beauty; but the excellencies of Nature, can have no right done to them: For there both the Pencil and the Pen are overcome by the Digni- ty of the Subječt 5 -as our admirable Waller has expreſs'd it 3 The Hero's Race tranſcend, the Poet's Thought. There are few in any Age who can bear the load of a Dedica. tion; for where Praiſe is undeſerv'd, 'tis Satyr: Tho Satyr on Fol- ly is now no longer a Scandal to any one Perſon, where a whole Age is dipt together 5 yet I had rather undertake a Multitude one way, than a ſingle Aiticut the other 5 for 'tis eaſier to deſcend, than 'tis to climb. I ſhou'd have gone aſham'd out of the World, if Ihad not at leaſt attempted this Addreſs, which I have long thought owing: And if I had never attempted, Hmight have been vain enough to think I might have ſucceeded in it : now I have made the Experiment, and have fail'd, through my Un- worthineſs. I may reſt ſatisfi'd, that either the Adventure is not to be atchiev'd, or that it is reſerv'd for ſome other hand. Be pleas'd therefore, ſince the Family of the Attici is and ought to be above the common Forms of concluding Letters, that I may take my leave in the Words of Cicero to the firſt of them: Me, O Pomponi, valdé panitet vivere : tantim teoro, ut quoniam me ipſe ſemper amäſij, ut eodem amore ſt; 5 ego mimirum, idem ſum. Inimici mei mea mihi mom meipſum ademerant. Cura, Attice, at valear. T H E . Dabam Cal. - Jan. 1690,
Page Scan 14

T H E Wº: it happen'd through a long diſiſe of Writing, that I forgot the uſual compaſs of a Play; or that by crowd- ing it, with Charađers and Incidents, I put a neceſſity upon my Jelf of lenghthning the main Aáion, I know not 5 but the firſt days Audience ſufficiently convinc d me of my error 5 and that the Poem was inſupportably too long. 'Tis an ill ambition of us Poets, to pleaſe an Audience with more than they can bear : And, ſuppoſing that we wrote as well, as wainly we imagin our ſelves to write; yet we ought to conſider, that no man can bear to be long tickled. There is a mauſeouſneſs in a City feaſt when we are to ſit four hours after we are cloyd. I am, therefore, in the firſt plate, to acknow- ledg with all manner of gratitude, their civility; who were pleas'd to endure it with ſo much patience, to be weary with ſo much good mature and ſilence, and not to explode an entertainment, which was deſign'd to pleaſe them 3 or diſcourage an Author, whoſe misfortunes have once more brought him againſt his will, upon the Stage. While I continue in theſe bad circumſtances, (and truly I ſee very little probability of coming out ; ) I muſt be oblig'd to write, and if I 'may ſtill hope for the ſame kind uſage, I ſhall the leſ, repent of that hard neceſſity. I write not this out of any expediation to be pityed; for I have Enemies enow to wiſh me yet in a worſe condition; but give me leave to ſay, that if I can pleaſe by writing, as I ſhall endeavour it, the Town may be ſomewhat oblig'd to my misfortunes, for a part of their diverſion. Having been longer acquainted with the Stage, than any Poet mom living, and having obſerv'd how dif- ficult it was to pleaſe ; that the humours of Comedy were almoſt ſpent, that Love and Honour (the miſtaken Topickſ of Tragedy) were quite worn out, that the Theaters cou’d not ſupport their charges, that the Audience forſook them, that young men without Learning ſet up for judges, and that they talk d loudeſt, who underſtood the leaſt: all fhºſe diſcouragements had not only weam'd me from the Stage, but had alſo given me a loathing ºf it. But enough of this ; the #. tie Cºlºzé'ſ
Page Scan 15

The PR EFACE. culties continue; they increaſe, and I am ſtill condemm'd to dig in thoſe exhauſed Mines. Whatever fault I mext commit, reſt aſſur’d it jhall not be that of too much length: Above twelve hunder'd limes have been cut off from this Tragedy, ſince it was firſt deliver'd to the Aliors. They were indeed ſo judiciouſly lopt by Mr. Betterton, to whoſe care and excellent attion, I am equaly oblig'd, that the connexion of the ſtory was not loſt 5 but ºn the ether ſide, it was impoſſible to prevent ſome part of the aâion from being precipitated, and coming on without that due preparation, which is requir'al to all great events: as in particular, that of raiſing the Mobile, in the beginning of the Fourth Aá; which a Man of Benducar's cool Charajer, cou’d not maturally attempt, without taking all thoſe pre- cautions, which he foreſaw wou'd be meceſſary to render his deſign ſucceſsful. On this conſideration, I have replac'd thoſe limes, through the whole Poem ; and thereby reſtor'd it, to that clearneſs of concep- tion, and (if I may dare to ſay it) that luftre, and maſculine vigour, in which it was firſt written. 'Tis obvious to every underſtanding Reader, that the moſt poetical parts, which are Deſcriptions, Ima- ges, Similitudes, and Moral Sentences 5 are thoſe, which of neceſſ- ty were to be par'd away, when the body was fivoln into too large'a bulk for the repreſentation of the Stage. But there is a vaſt diffe- rence betwixt a publick entertainment on the Theatre, and a pri- vate reading in the Cloſet. In the firſt we are confin'd to time, and though we talk not by the hour-glaſs, yet the Watch often drawn out of the pocket, warns the Aāors, that their Audience is weary; in the laſt, every Reader is judge of his own convenience; he can take up the book, and lay it down at his pleaſure 5 and find out thoſe beau- tier of propriety, in thought and writing, which eſcap'd him in the tumultand hurry of repreſenting, And I dare boldly promiſe for this Play, that in the roughneſs of the numbers and cadencer, (which I aſure was not caſual, but ſo deſign'd) you will ſee ſomewhat more ma- ſterly ariſing to your view, than in moſt, if not any of my former Tra- gedies. There is a more noble daring in the Figures and more ſit- able to the loſtineſ of the Subject 5 and beſides this ſome newneſſes of Engliſh, tranſlated from the Beauties of Modern Tongues, as well as from the elegancies of the Latin 3 and here and there ſome old words are ſprinkled, which for their ſignificance and ſound,aleſºrv'd not to be antiquated 3 ſuch as we often find in Saliji amongſt the - 3. Roman
Page Scan 16

y - The PREF A C E. Roman Authors, and in Milton's Paradiſe amongſt ours; though perhaps the latter inſtead of ſprinkling, has dealt them with ido free a hand, even ſometimes to the obſcuring of his ſenſe. As for the ſtory or plot of the Tragedy, 'tis purely fiſſion; fºr I take it up where the Hiſtory has laid it down. We are aſſur’d by all Writers of thoſe times, that Sebaſtian a young Trince of great cou-- rage and expediation, undertook that War partly upon a religiou, account, parily at the ſolicitation of Muley-Mähumet, who had been driven out of his Dominions, by Abdelmelech, or as other, call him Muley-Moluch his migh Kinſman, who deſcended from the ſame Family of the Xeriffs 5 whoſe Fathers Hamet and Maho- met had conquer'd that Fmpire with joint Forces 3 and ſhar'd it be- twixt them after their vićiory : That the body of Don Sebaſtian was never found in the Field of Battel; which gave occaſion for many to believe, that he waſ not ſlain; that ſome year; after, when the Spa- niards with a pretended title, by force of Arms had Uſurp'd the Crown of Portugal, from the Houſe of Braganza, a certain Perſon who call d himſelf Don Sebaſtian, and had all the marks of his body and features of his face, appear'd at Venice, where he was own’d by ſºme of his Country-men 3, but being ſeiz'd by the Spaniards was firſt Impriſon'd, then ſent to the Gallies, and at | put to Death in pri- wafe. 'Tis moſt certain, that the Portugueſts expečed his return for almoſt an Age together after that Battel; which is at leaſt a proof of their extream love to his Memory; and the uſage which they had from their new Conquerors, might poſſibly make them ſo extravagant in their hopes and miſles for their old Maſter. Thiſ ground work the Hiſtory afforded me, and I deſire no better to build a Play upon it. Fºr where the event of a great ačion is left doubtful, there the Poet is left Maſter . He may raiſe what he pleaſes on that foundation, provided he makes it of a piece, and according to the rule of probability. From hence I was only oblig'd, that Sé- baſtian ſhou'd return to Portugal mo more 5 but at the ſame time I had him at my own diſpoſal, whether to beftom him in Affrick, or in any other corner of the World, or to have clos'd the Tragedy mºth his death 5 and the laſt of theſe mas certainly the moſt eaſie, but for the ſame reaſon, the ſeaft artful; becauſe as I have ſomewhere ſaid, the poyſm and the dagger are ſtill at hand, to butcher a Herot, when a Pºet wants the brains to Jave him. It being therefore only neceſſary - - - according
Page Scan 17

The PREF ACE. according to the Laws of the Drama, that Sebaſtian ſhou'd no more be ſeen vpon the Throme, I leave it for the World to judge, whether or no I have diſpoſed of him according to art, or have bungled up the concluſion of his adventure. In the drawing of his charader I for- got not piety, which any one may obſerve to be owe principal ingredient of it 3 even ſo far as to be a habit in him ; though I ſhow him once to be tranſported from it by the violence of a ſlidden paſſion, to em. deavor a ſelf murther. This being preſuppos'd, that he was Religious, the horror of his inceſt, tho immocently committed, mas the beſt rea- Jon which the Stage could give for hind ring his returm. , 'Tis true I have no right to blaſt his Memory, with ſuch a crime; but declaring it to be fidiom, I deſire my Audience to think it no longer true, than while they are ſeeing it repreſented: For that once ended, he may be a Saint for ought I know; and we have reaſon to preſume he is. On this ſuppoſition, it was unreaſonable to have kill'd him ; for the Learned Mr. Rymer has well obſerv'd, that in all puniſhments we are to regulate our ſelves by Poetical juſtice 5 and according to thoſe meaſures an involuntary ſin deſerves not death; from whence it fol- lows, that to divorce himſelf from the beloved obječ, to retire into a deſart, and deprive himſelf of a Throne, was the utmoſt puniſhment, which a Poet cou’d inflić, as it was alſo the utmoſt reparation, which Sebaſtian cou’d make. For what relates to Almeyda, her part is wholly fiditious ; I know it is the ſurname of a moble Family in Portugal, which was very inſtrumental in the Reſtoration of Don John de Braganza, Father to the moſt Illuſtrioia and moſt Pious Princeſ, our gºueen Dowager. The French Author of a Novel, call'd Don Sebaſtian, has given that name to an Affrican Lady of his own invention, and makes her Siſter to Muley-Mahumet. But I have wholly chang'd the accidents, and borrow'd mothing but the ſuppoſition, that ſhe was lelov’d by the King of Portugal. Tho, if I had taken the whole ſtory, and wrought it up into a Play, I might have dome it exačily according to the pračice of almoſt all the Anci- ents; who were never accus’d of being Plagiaries, for building their Tragedies on known Fables. Thus Auguſtus Caeſar wrote an Ajax, which was not the leſ; his own, becauſe Euripides had written a Play before him on that Subjeći. Thus of late jears Corneille writ an Oedipus after Sophocles 3 and I have deſign'd one after him, which I wrote with Mr. Lee, yet neither the French Poet ſtole from the - a 2. Greek,
Page Scan 18

s ... --- ---- ------- The PREF ACE. Greek, nor we from the French man. 'Tis the comfrivance, the mem turn, and men charaders, which alter the property and make it ours. The Materia Poetica is as common to all Writers, as the Materia Medica to all Phyſicians. Thus in our Chronicles, Da- niels Hiſtory is ſtill his own, though Matthew Paris, Stow and Hollingſhed writ before him, otherwiſe we muſt have been content with their dull relations, if a better Pem had not been allow'd to come after them, and write his own account, after a new and better f/471/76.7°. - - I muſt farther declare freely, that I have not exačily kept to the three Mechanick rules of unity: I knew them and had them in my eye, but fºllow'd them only at a diſtance 5 for the Genius of the En- gliſh cannot bear too regular a Play 5 we are given to variety, even to a debauchery of Pleaſure. My Scenes are therefore ſometimes bro- ken, becauſe my Zºnder-plot requir'd them ſo to be 5 though the Ge- meral Scene remains of the ſame Caſtle; and I have taken the time of two days, becauſe the variety of accidents, which are here repre- ſented, could not maturally be ſuppos'd to arrive in one: But to gain a greater Beauty, 'tis lawful for a Poet to ſuperſede a leſs. I muſt likewiſe own, that I have ſomewhat deviated from the known Hiſtory, in the death of Muley-Moluch, who, by all relations dyed of a feaver in the Battel, before his Army had wholly won the Field; but if I have allow'd him another day of life, it was becauſe Iſtood in need of ſo ſhining a Charađer of brutality, as I have given him ; which is indeed the ſame, with that of the preſent Emperor Muley Iſhmael, as ſome of our Engliſh Officers, who have been in his Cºurt, have credibly inform'd me. I have been liſtming what objećirms had been made, againſt the condad of the Play, but found them all ſ, trivial, that if I ſhou'd name them, a true critick wou'd imagin that 1 play’d booty, and on- y rair’d up fantoms for my ſelf to conquer. Some are pleas'd to y the Writing is dull; but astatem habet de ſe Hoquatur. Others that the double poſºn is unnatural ; let the common received opinion, and Auſonius his famous Epigram anſwer that. Lºftly a more ig- zorant fºrt of Creatures than either of the former, maintain that the charađer of Dorax, is not only unnatural, but inconſiſtent with it ſelf; let them read the Ph9 and think again, and if yet they are not ſatisfied, cºſt their eyes on that Chapter of the Pºſe - - Montaigne, * , w º t *
Page Scan 19

The PR EFA CE." - - Montaigne, which is intituled de l’Inconſtance des aétions hu-, - maines. A longer reply, is what thoſe Cavillers deſerve not ; but I - will give them and their fellows to underſtand, that the Farl of * Dorſet, was plear'd to read the Tragedy twice over before it was Aćied; and did me the favour to ſend me word, that I had writ- ten beyond any of my former Playſ 5 and that he was diſpleas'd any thing ſhou'd be cut away. If I have not reaſon to prefer his ſingle . judgment to a whole Faàion, let the World be judge; for the oppo- ſition is the ſame with that of Lucan's Heroe againſt an Army; con- currere bellum, atque virum. I think I may modeftly conclude, that whatever errors there may be, either in the deſign, or writing. of this Play, they are mot thoſe which have been obječjed to it. I think alſo, that I am not yet arriv'd to the Age of doating 3 and that I have given ſo much application to this Poem, that I cou’d not pro- bably let it run into many groſ; abſurdities; which may caution my Enemies from too raſh a cenſure 5 and may alſo encourage my friends, who are many more than I cou’d reaſonably have expected, to believe their kindneſ, has not been very undeſervedly beſtowed on me. This is not a Play that was huddled up in haſt 5 and to ſlew it was mot, I will own, that beſide the general Moral of it, which is given in the four laſt limes, there is alſo another Moral, couch'd un- der every one of the principal Parts and Charađers, which a judi- cious Critick will obſerve, though I point mot to it in this Preface. And there may be alſo ſome ſecret Beauties in the decorum of parts, and uniformity of deſign, which my puny judges will not eaſily find out 5 let them conſider in the laſt Scene of the fourth Ać, whether I have not preſerv'd the rule of decency, in giving all the advantage : to the Royal Charaſier; and in making Dorax fift ſubmit : Per- haps too they may have thought, that it was through indigence of Cha- račfers, that I have given the ſame to Sebaſtian and Almeyda ; and conſequently made them alike in all things but their Sex. But let them look a little deeper into the matter, and they will find that this identity of Charaćier in the greatneſs of their Soul: ; was in- tended for a preparation of the final diſcovery, and that the likeneſs . of their nature, was a fair hint to the proximity of their blood. To avoid the imputation of too much vanity (for all Writers, and eſpecially Poets will have ſome) I will give but one other inſiance, in relation to the Uniformity of the deſign. I have obſerva, | ." - th? . . . *
Page Scan 20

The PREF AcE. the Engliſh will not bear a thorough Tragedy 5 but are pleas'd, that it ſhould be lightned with underparts of mirth. It had been eaſe for me to have given my Audience a better courſe of Comedy, I mean a more diverting, than that of Antonio and Morayma. But I dare appeal even to my Enemies, if I or any man cou’d have invented one, which had been more of a piece, and more depending, on the ſerious part of the deſign. For mhat cou’d be more uniform, than to draw from out of the members of a Captive Court, the Subječ of a Comi- cal entertainment & To prepare this Epiſode, you ſe Dorax giving the Charačer of Antonio, in the beginning of the Play, upon his Jirſt ſight of him at the Lottery 5 and to make the dependence, An- tonio is ingag’d in the Fourth Aá, for the deliverance of Almey- da; which is alſo prepard, by his being firſt made a Slave to the Captain of the Rabble. I ſhou'd leg pardon for theſe inſtances 3 but perhaps they may be of uſe to future Poetſ, in the conduá of their Plays : At leaſt if I appear too poſitive; I am growing old, and thereby, in poſſeſſion of Jome experience, which men in years will always aſſume for a right of talking. Certainly, if a Man can ever have reaſon to ſet a value on himſelf, 'tis when his umgenerous Enemies are taking the advan. tage of the Times upon him, to ruin him in his reputation. And therefore for once, I will make bold to take the Counſel of my Old Maſter Virgil. - Tu, necede malis ; ſed, contra, audentiorito. ~ - - PRO-
Page Scan 21

P R O L O GUI E T O DON SEBASTIAN King of Portugal. Spoken by a Woman. HE judge remov’d, tho he's no more My Lord, May plead at Bar, or at the Council-Board: So may caſt Poets write; there's no Pretenſion, To argue loſs of Wit from loſs of #" Tour looks are cheerful 5 and in all this place - I ſee mot one, that wears a damming face. The Britiſh Nation, is too brave to ſhow, Ignoble vengeance, on a vamguiſh'd foe, At #. be civil to the Wretch imploring; And lay your Paws upon him, without roaring :- Suppoſe our Poet was yourſº before ; Tet mow, the bui'neſs of the Field is o'er; 'Tis time to let your Civil Wars alone, - When Troops are into Winter-quarters gone. - --- Jove was alike to Latian and to Phrygian; - And you well know, a Play's of mo Religion. Take good advice, and pleaſe your ſelves this day 5 No matter from what hands you have the Play. Among good Fellows ev'ry health will paſs, That ſerves to carry round another glaſ, : When, with full bowls of Burgundy you dine, Tho at the Mighty Monarch you repine, : 7ou grant him ſtill moſt Chriſliam, in his Wine. ! Thus far the Poet, but his brains grow. Addle; And all the reſt is purely from this Noddle. Tou’ve ſeen young Ladies at the Senate door, Prefer Petitionſ, and your grace implore; How ever grave the Legiſlators were. ~ * Their
Page Scan 22

- ‘Their cauſe went ne'er the worſe for being fair, Reaſon, as weak as theirs, perhaps I bring; But I cou’d bribe you, with as good a thing. I heard him make advances of good Nature; That'he for once, wou'd ſheath his cutting Satyr: Sign but his Peace, be vows he'll me'er again The ſacred Names of Fops and Beańs profane. Strike up the Bargain quickly 5 for I ſwear, As Times go now, he offers very fair. - . Be not too hard on him, with Statuter neither, - Be kind; and do not ſet your Teeth together, To ſtretch the Laws, as Coblers do their Leather. Horſes, by Papiſts are not to be ridden ; But ſure the Muſes Horſe was ne'er forbidden. or in mo Rate-Book, it was ever found That Pegaſus was valued at Five-pound: Fine him to daily Drudging and Inditing; ...And let him pay his Taxes out, in Writing. Don

End of Title Page. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 1
Page 1

( t ) Don Sebaſhan, - - - King of Portugal. Act I. Sc E N E I. The Scene at Alcazar, repreſenting a Market. Place under the Caſtle. Muley-Zeydan, Benducar. Muly-Zeyd. OW Affrica's long Wars are at an end; - And our parch'd earth is drench'd in Chri- - ſtian Blood, z My conquering Brother will have Slaves enow, To pay his cruel Vows for Vićtory. What hear you of Sebaſtian, King of Portugal £ - Benducar. He fell among a heap of ſlaughter'd Moors; Though yet his mangled Carcaſe is not found. The Rival of our threatned Empire, Mahumet, Was hot purſued; and in the general rout, - Miſtook a ſwelling Current for a Foord; And in Mucazer's Flood was ſeen to riſe; Thrice was he ſeen; at length his Courſer plung’d, And threw him off; the Waves whelm'd over him, And helpleſs in his heavy arms he drownd. . Mul.2eyd. Thus, then, a doubtful Title is extinguiſh'd : Thus, Moluch, ſtill the Favorite of Fate, -- B Swims
Page 2

( 2 ) Swims in a ſanguine torrent to the Throne. .. As if our Prophet only work'd for him: The Heavens and all the Stars are his hir'd Servants, As Muley-Zeydan were not worth their care, - And younger Brothers but the draff of Nature. - Bend. Be ſtill, and learn the ſoothing Arts of Court 3. Adore his fortune, mix with flattering Crowds, And when they praiſe him moſt, be you the loudeſt 5. Your Brother is luxurious, cloſe, and cruel, - Generous by fits, but permanent in miſchief. The ſhadow of a diſcontent wou'd ruin us 5. We muſt be ſafe before we can be great: . . Theſe things obſerv'd, leave me to ſhape the reſt. . - Mul, Zeyd, You have the Key, he opens inward to you... . Bend. So often try’d, and ever found ſo true, Has given me truſt, and truſt has given me means. Once to be falſe for all. I truſt not him : . , For now his ends are ſerv'd, and he grown abſolute, How am I ſure to ſtand who ſerv'd thoſe ends & º I know your nature open, mild, and grateful 5. , - - In ſuch a Prince the People may be bleſt, And I be ſafe. Mul. Zeyd, My Father l’ [Embracing him, Bend. My future King! (auſpicious Muley-Zeydan:) Shall I adore you? No, the place is publick 5 Fworſhip you within; the outward ačº Shall be reſerv'd till Nations follow me, And Heaven ſhall envy you the kneeling World. You know th' Alcald of Alcazar, Dorax * - Mulzeyd. The gallant Renegade you mean? Bend. The ſame: That gloomy outſide, like a ruſty Cheſt, Contains the ſhining Treaſure of a Soul, Reſolv'd and brave; he has the Souldiers hearts, And time ſhall make him ours. Mul. He's juſt upon us: , Bend. I know him from a far, By the long ſtride and by the ſullen port: Retire my Lord. 1. Wait on your Brothers Triumph, yours is next, Higrowth ºur wild and finitieſ pian, ril * -
Page 3

( 3 ) " ' I'll cut his barren branches to the ſtock, And graft you on to bear. —’ - Mul. Zeyd. My Oracle ! [Exit Muley-Zeyd. Bend. Yes, to delude your hopes, poor credulous Fool, To think that I wou'd give away the Fruit - Of ſo much toil, fuch guilt, and ſuch damnation; If I am damn'd, it ſhall be for my ſelf: This eaſie Fool muſt be my Stale, ſet up To catch the Peoples eyes; he's tame and merciful, Him I can manage, till I make him odious By ſome unpopular ačt, and then dethrone him. Enter Dorax, Now Dorax / Dorax, Well Bembowcar ! Bend. Bare Bembowcar ! Dor. Thou wouldſthave Titles,take 'em then, Chief Miniſter, Firſt Hangman of the State. Bend. Some call me Favourite. Dorax, What's that, his Minion ? Thou art too old to be a Catamite! - * * Now prithee tell me, and abate thy pride, Is not Benducar Bare, a better Name - In a Friend's mouth, than all thoſe gawdy Titles, Which I diſdain to give the Man I love? - - Bend. But always out of humor, - º Dorax, I have cauſe: - - . Tho all mankind is cauſe enough for Satyr. Bend. Why then thou haſtréveng'd thee on mankind They ſay in fight, thou hadſt a thirſty Sword, And well 'twas glutted there. t Dorax, I ſpitted Frogs, I cruſh'd a heap of Emmets, A hundred of 'em to a ſingle Soul, And that but ſcanty weight too: the great Devil Scarce thank'd me for my pains; he ſwallows Vulgar Like whip’d Cream, feels’em notingoing down. Bend. Brave Renegade 1 cou’dſt thou not meet Sebaſtian £ Thy Maſter had been worthy of thy Sword. - Dorax, My Maſter? By what title, * 3. .* g -- * B 2 Becauſe ^1 º
Page 4

* ( 4 ) - Becauſe I happen'd to be born where he Happen'd to be a King? And yet Iſerv'd him, Nay, I was fool enough to love him too. You know my ſtory, how I was rewarded, . For Fifteen hard Campaigns, ſtill hoop'd in Iron, And why I turn'd Mahometan: I'm grateful, But whoſoever dares to injure me, Let that man know, I dare to be reveng'd. - - Bend. Still you run off from biaſs; ſay what moves Your preſent ſpleen 2 Dorax, You mark'd not what I told you: I kill'd not one that was his Makers Image; H met with none but vulgar two-leg'd Brutes. . . . . . . . Sebaſtian was my aim ; he was a Man: . . . Nay, though he hated me, and I hate him, Yet Imuſt do him right 3 he was a Man, Above man's height, ev'n towring to Divinity. i Brave, pious, generous, great, and liberal: Juſt as the Scales of Heaven that weigh the Seaſons, He lov'd his People, him they idoliz'd : - And thence proceeds my mortal hatred to him, ~ That thus unblameable to all beſides He err'd to me alone: - His goodneſs was diffus’d to human kind, And all his cruelty confin'd to me. Bend. You cou’d not meet him then?- Dorax, No, though I ſought - -- . Where ranks fell thickeſt 5 'twas indeed the place . . To ſeek Sebaſtian: through a track of Death I follow'd him, by Groans of dying Foes, But ſtil I came too late, for he was flown Like Ligtning, ſwift before me to new Slaughters, I mow’d acroſs, and made irregular Harveſt, - Defac'd the pomp of Battel, but in vain, For he was ſtill ſupplying Death elſewhere: This mads me that perhaps ignoble hands Have overlaid him, for they cou’d not conquer: Murder'd by Mukitude", whom I alone. s - Had - z
Page 5

- ( 5 ) - Had right to ſlay; I too wou'd have been ſlain, That catching hold upon his flitting Ghoſt I might have robb'd him of his opening Heav'n; And drag'd him down with me, ſpight of Predeſtination. Bend. 'Tis of as much import as Affrie's worth To know what came of him, and of Almeyda. The Siſter of the Vanquiſh’d Mahumet, Whoſe fatal Beauty to her Brother drew The Lands third part, as Lucifer did Heav'ns. Dor. I hope ſhe dy'd in her own Female calling, Choak'd up with Man, and gorg'd with Circumciſion. As for Sebaſtian we muſt ſearch the Field, And where we ſee a Mountain of the Slain, Send one to climb, and looking down below. There he ſhall find him at his Manly length With his face up to Heav'n, in the red Monument; Which his true Sword has digg'd. - - - - - Bend. Yet we may poſſibly hear farther news 5: . For while our Affricans purſu'd the Chaſe, t The Captain of the Rabble iſſued out, With a black ſhirt-leſs train to ſpoil the dead, w And ſeize the living. - - Dor. Each f 'em an Hoaſt, A Million ſtrong of Vermine ev'ry Villain : No part of Government, but Lords of Anarchy, Chaos of Power, and priviledg’d deſtrućtion. - Bend. Yet I muſt tell you Friend the Great muſt uſe.’em, . Sometimes as neceſſary tools of tumult. } Dor. I wou'd uſe 'em. Like Dogs in times of Plague, out-laws of Nature, , Fit to be ſhot and brain'd 5 without a proceſs, To ſtop infe&tion, that's their proper death. Bend. No more, Behold the Emperor coming to ſurvey The Slaves, in order to perform his Wow. Exter"
Page 6

-(-6 ) Enter Muley-Moluch the Emperor, with Attendants. The Mufty, and Muley Zeydan. Moluch. Our Armours now may ruſt, our idle ſcymitars Hang by our ſides, for Ornament not uſe: - Children ſhall beat our Atabals and Drums, And all the noiſie trades of War, no more - Shall wake the peaceful morn: the Xeriff; blood No longer in divided Channels runs, The younger Houſe took end in Mahumet. Nor ſhall :*: formidable Name, Be longer us’d to lull the crying babel , Mufty. For this Vićtorious day our Mighty Prophet Expects your gratitudc, the Sacrifice “Of Chriſtian Slaves, devoted, if you won. Mol. The purple preſent ſhall be richly paid: That Vow perform'd, faſting ſhall be aboliſh'd : None ever ſerv'd Heav'n well with a ſtarv'd face: Preach Abſtinence no more; I tell thee Mufty * Good feaſting is devout: and thou our Head, Haſt a Religious, ruddy Countenancc : We will have learned Luxury : our lean Faith Gives ſcandal to the Chriſtians; they feed high : Then look for ſhoals of Converts, when thou haſt Reform'd us into feaſting. , Muf Faſting is but the Letter of the Law: Yet it ſhows well to Preach it to the Vulgar. Wine is againſt our Law, thar's literal too, But not deny'd to Kings and to their Guides, "Wine is a Holy Liquor, for the Great. [Dorax aſde. This Mufti in my conſcience is ſome Engliſh : Renegade, he talks ſo ſavourly of toping. Mol, Bring forth th' unhappy Relicks of the War. Emter
Page 7

( x ) ! Bnter Muſtapha captain of the Rabble with his followers of the Black Guard, &c. and other Moors : with them a Company of Portugueſe Slaves without any of the chief * Perſons. M. Mol. Theſe are not fit to pay an Emperors Vow ; Our Bulls and Rams had been more noble Vićtims; Theſe are but garbidge not a Sacrifice. Muf. The Prophet muſt not pick and chooſe his Offrings; Now he has giv'n the Day, 'tis paſt recalling : And he muſt be content with ſuch as theſe." M. Mol. But are theſe all? Speak you who are their Maſters. Muſta. All upon my Honour: If you'll take 'em as their Fathers got 'em, ſo. If not, you muſt ſtay till they get a bet-. ter generation: Theſe Chriſtians are mere bunglers; they pro- create nothing but out of their own Wives; And theſe have all the looks of Eldeſt Sons. M. Mol. Pain of your lives let none conceal a Slave. Muff. Let every Man look to his own Conſcience, I am . ſure mine ſhall never hang me. -- Bend. Thou ſpeak'ſt as thou wert privy to concealments :- Then thou art an Accomplice. - Muff. Nay if Accomplices muſt ſuffer, it may go hard . with me 5 but here's the Devil on't, there's a Great Man and . a Holy Man too, concern'd with me. Now if I confeſs, he'll be ſure to ſcape between his Greatneſs and his Holineſs, and . I ſhall be murder'd, becauſe of my Poverty and Raſcality, Mufti winking at him. º, Then if thy ſilence ſave the Great and Holy, , , 'Tis ſure thou ſhalt go ſtraight to Paradiſe - Muft. Tis a fine place they ſay 5 but Dočtor.I am not worthy on't: I am contented with this homely World, 'tis good enough for ſuch a poor raſcally Muſulman as I am : Beſides I have learnt ſo much good manners, Dočtor, as to let my Betters be ſerv'd , before me. * - - M. Mol. Thou talk'ſt as if the Mufty were concern'd: Muft, Your Majeſty may lay your Soul on't : but for my . - - part, *
Page 8

--- - . . . . ( 8 ) - - part, though I am a plain Fellow, yet I ſcorn to be trick'd in- to Paradice, I wou'd he ſhou'd know it. : The troth on't is an’t like you, His reverence bought of me the flower of all the Market; theſe theſe are but Dogs meat to 'em, and a round price he pay’d me too I'll ſay that for him; but not enough for me to venture my neck for : If I get Paradice when my time comes I can't help my ſelf; but I'll venture nothing before-hand, upon a blind Bargain. M. Mol. Where are thoſe Slaves? produce 'em. \ Muf. They are not what he ſays. M. Mol. No more excuſes. [One goes out to fetch them. Know thou may'ſt better dally With a dead Prophet, than a living King. Muf. I but reſerv'd 'em to preſent thy Greatneſs An Offring worthy thee. - Muft. By the ſame token there was a dainty Virgin, (Vir- : gin ſaid Il but I won't be too poſitive of that neither) with a roguiſh leering eyel he paid me down for her upon the nail a thouſand golden Sultamins 5 or he had never had her I can tell him that : Now is it very likely he would pay ſo dear for ſuch a delicious Morſel, and give it away out of his own mouth; when it had ſuch a farewel with it too 2 Enter Sebaſtian comdućied in mean habit, with Alvarez, An- tonio, and Almeyda: her face veild with a Barnus. M. Mol. Ay; Theſe look like the Workmanſhip of Heav'n: This is the porcelain clay of human kind, * And therefore caſt into theſe noble moulds. Dorax aſide while the Emperor whiſpers Benducar. By all my wrongs - -- 'Tis he ; damnation ſeize me but ’tis hel - * My heart heaves up and ſwells; he's poyſon to me 3 My injur'd honour, and my raviſh'd love, Bleed at their Murderers ſight. Benducar _-_--_---
Page 9

- (, 9 ) - -- - [Bend. to Dor, aftale. The Emperor wou'd learn theſe Prisºners names; You know 'em. Dor. Tell him, no. And trouble me no more. I will not know 'em. Shall I truſt Heav'n, that Heav'n which I renounc'd, [Aſide. With my revenge? then, where's my ſatisfaction 2 No, it muſt be my own; I ſcorn a Proxy. M. Mol. 'Tis decreed, Theſe of a better aſpect, with the reſt Shall ſhare one common Doom, and Lots decide it. For ev’ry number'd Captive put a ball Into an Urn 5 three only black be there, The reſt, all white, are ſafe. Muf. Hold Sir, the Woman muſt not draw. M. Mol. O Mufti. We know your reaſon, let her ſhare the danger. Muf. Our Law ſays plainly Women have no Souls: M. Mol. 'Tis true; their Souls are mortal, ſet her by : Yet were Almeyda here, though Fame reports her The faireſt of her Sex, ſo much unſeen, - I hate the Siſter of our Rival Houſe, Ten thouſand ſuch dry Notions of our Alcoran Shou'd not protećt her life; if not Immortal : Dye as ſhe cou’d, all of a piece, the better, That none of her remain. Here an Urn is brought in ; the Prisºners approach with great concernment 5 and among the reſt Sebaſtian, Alvarez and Antonio 5 who come more chearfully. Dor. Poor abjećt Creatures how they fear to dye [Aſide. Theſe never knew one happy hour in life, Yet ſhake to lay it down: is load ſo pleaſant? Sr has Heav'n'hid the happineſs of Death That Men may bear to live? Now for our Heroes. C The
Page 10

( to ) - The three approach. O, theſe come up with Spirits more reſolv'd I Old venerable Alvarez, well I know him, The Favºrite once of this Sebaſtian's Father ; Now Miniſter; (too honeſt for his Trade) Religion bears him out, a thing taught young, -In Age ill pračtis'd, yet his prop in Death. O, he has drawn a black 3 and ſmiles upon't, As who ſhould ſay my Faith and Soul are white Tho my Lot ſwarthy: Now if there be hereafter He's bleſt ; if not, well cheated, and dyes pleas'd. Anton. holding his Lot in his clench'd hand. Here I have thee, Be what thou wilt: I will not look too ſoon. Thou haſt a colour ; if thou provºſt not right, I have a minute good ere I behold thee. Now, Let me rowl, and grubble thee, Blind Men ſay white feels #. and black feels rough; Thou haſt a rugged skin ; I do not like thee. Dor. There's th’Amorous airy ſpark, Antonio; The wittieſt Womans toy in Portugal. Lord what a loſs of Treats and Serenades! The whole She Nation will b in mourning for him. Antonio. I've a moiſt ſweaty palm; the more's my Sin; If it be black, yet only dy'd, not odious Damn'd Natural Ebony, there's hope in rubbing To waſh this Ethiope white. (Looks) Pox of the Proverb! As black as Hell: another lucky ſaying ! - I think the Devils in me: — good again, I cannot ſpeak one ſyllable, but tends - * To Death or to Damnation. [Holds up his ball. Dor. He looks uneaſie at his future Journey: [Aſide. And wiſhes his Boots off again 5 for fear - Of a bad Road, and a worſe Inn at night. Go
Page 11

( 1 1 ) Go to bed fool, and take ſecure repoſe For thou ſhalt wake no more. (Sebaſtian comes up to draw.) M.Mol, to Ben. Mark him who now approaches to the Lott'ry, He looks ſecure of Death, ſuperior greatneſs, Like jove when he made Fate, and ſaid thou art The Slave of my Creation 5 I admire him. Bend. He looks as Man was made, with face erect, That ſcorns his brittle Corps, and ſeems aſham'd He's not all ſpirit, his eyes with a dumb Pride, Accuſing Fortune that he fell not warm: Yet now diſdains to live. (Sebaſt draws a black) M. Mol. He has his wiſh; f And I have fail'd of mine ! - Dor. Robb'd of my Vengeance, by a trivial chance 1 [Aſide. Fine work above, that their anointed care Shou'd dye ſuch little Death: or did his Genius Know mine the ſtronger Demon, fear'd the grapple, And looking round him, found this nook of fate To skulk behind my Sword 5 ſhall I diſcover him? Still he wou'd dye not mine: no thanks to my Revenge: reſerv'd but to more royal ſhambles. ‘Twere baſe too; and below thoſe Vulgar Souls, That ſhar'd his danger, yet not one diſclos'd him : But ſtruck with Rev'rence kept an awful ſilence. I'll ſee no more of this: Dog of a Prophet ! [Exit Dorax. Mul. Mol. One of theſe Three is a whole Hecatomb; And therefore only one of 'em ſhall dye. The Reſt are but mute Cattle; and when Death Comes, like a ruſhing Lion, couch like Spaniels, With lolling tongues, and tremble at the paw, Let Lots again decide it. (The Three draw again : and the Lot falls on Sebaſtian.) Sebaſt. Then there's no more to manage l if I fall It ſhall be like my ſelf; a ſetting Sun Shou'd leave a track of Glory in the Skies. Be. C 2. C.
Page 12

º ( 12 ) Behold Sebaſtian King of Portugal. - * M. Mol. Sebaſtianſ haſ it muſt be he 5 no other Cou'd repreſent ſuch ſuffring Majeſty : … I ſaw him, as he terms himſelf, a Sun Strugling in dark Eclipſe, and ſhooting day On either ſide of the black Orb that veil'd him. Sebaſt. Not leſs ev’n in this deſpicable now, Than when my Name fill'd Africk with affrights, And froze your hearts beneath your torrid Zone. - Bend, to M. Mol. Extravagantly bravel ev'n to an Impudence Of Greatneſs. Sebaſt. Here ſatiate all your fury; Let fortune empty her whole Quiver on me, I have a Soul, that like an ample Shield Can take in all 5 and verge enough for more. I wou'd have conquer'd you; and ventur'd only A narrow neck of Land for a third World; ‘Fo give my looſen'd Subječts room to play. Fate was not mine, - Nor am I Fate's : Now I have pleas'd my longing, And trod the ground which I beheld from far, I beg no pity for this mouldring Clay : For if you give it burial there it takes Poſſeſſion of your Earth : * If burnt and ſcatter'd in the air: the Winds That ſtrow my duſt, diffuſe my royalty, And ſpread me o'er your Clime: for where one Atome Of mine ſhall light; know there Sebaſtian Reigns. M. Mal. What ſhall I do to corquer thee? Seb. Impoſſible ! Souls know no Conquerors. M. Mol. I'll ſhow thee for a Monſter through my Affrick, Seb. No thou canſ only ſhow me for a Man: Affrick is ſtor'd with Monſters; Man's a Prodigy, Thy Subječts have not ſeen. Mul. M. Thou talk'ſt as if . Still
Page 13

- ( 13) Still at the head of Battel. * - Seb. Thou miſtak'ſt, -- f For then I would not talk. . Bend. Sure he wou'd ſleep. º Sebaſt. Till Dooms-day 5 when the Trumpet ſounds to riſe; For that's a Soldiers call, - M. Mol. Thou'rt brave too late: Thou ſhou'dſt have dy'd in battel, like a Soldier, Seb. I fought and fell like one, but Death deceiv'd me, I wanted weight of feeble Moors upon me, - To cruſh my Soul out. M. Mol. Still untameable ! In what a ruine has thy head-ſtrong Pride, And boundleſs thirſt of Empire plung'd thy People. Sebaſt. What ſay'ſt thou, ha! No more of that. M. Mol. Behold, What Carcaſes of thine thy Crimes has ſtrew'd, And left our Affric Vultures to devour. • , - Bend. Thoſe Souls were thoſe thy God intruſted with thee, To cheriſh not deſtroy. Sebaſt. Witneſs, O'Heaven, how much This fight concerns me! Wou'd I had a Soul For each of theſe : How gladly wou'd I pay The Ranſom down: But ſince I have but one, Tisa King's life, and freely'tis beſtow'd. Not your falſe Prophet, but eternal Juſtice Has deſtin'd me the Lot, to dye for theſe: 'Tis fit a Sovereign ſo ſhou'd pay ſuch Subjećts; For Subječts ſuch as they are ſeldom ſeen, Who not forſook me at my greateſt need ; Nor for baſe lucre ſold their Loyalty, * ~ * But ſhar'd my dangers to the laſt event, * º And fenc'd 'em with their own: Theſe thanks I pay you: ... " - - - [Wipes his Eyes. And know, that when Sebaſtian weeps, his Tears - Come harder than his Blood. M. Mol. They plead too ſtrongly To be withſtood : My Clouds are gath'ring too, - - In
Page 14

- ( 14 ) In kindly mixture with this Royalſhowr: Be ſafe, and owe thy Life, not to my gift, But to the greatneſs of thy mind, Sebaſtian : Thy Subjećts too ſhall live 5 a due reward For their untainted Faith, in thy concealment. . . Mufti, Remember, Sir, your Vow. [A general ſhout. Mul. M. Do thou remember - Thy Funètion, Mercy, and provoke not blood. Mul, Zeyd. One of his generous Fits, too ſtrong to laſt. [Aftde to Benducar. Bend. The Mufti reddens, mark that holy Cheek. [To him. He frets within, froths Treaſon at his mouth, And churns it through his teeth; leave me to work him. Sebaſt. A mercy unexpečted, undeſir'd, Surprizes more: You've learnt the art to vanquiſh: You cou’d not (give me leave to tell you Sir) Have giv'n me life but in my Subjećts ſafety: Kings, who are Fathers, live but in their People. M. Mol. Still great, and grateful, that's thy character. Unveil the Woman; I wou'd view the Face That warm'd our Mufti's Zeal: Theſe pious Parrots peck the faireſt Fruit: Such Taſters are for Kings. [Offcers go to Almeyda to unveil her. Almeyda, Stand off ye Slaves, I will not be unveil'd. M. Mol. Slave is thy Title: Force her. Seb. On your lives, Approach her not. * - tº M. Mol. How’s this! - Seb. Sir pardon me, And hear me ſpeak.- Almeyda, Hear me 5 I will be heard: - - - I am no Slave; the nobleſt blood of Affric Runs in my Veins; a purer ſtream than thine; For, though deriv'd from the ſame Source, thy Current Is puddl’d, and defil'd with Tyranny. M. Mol. What Female Fury have we here! Almeyda, Iſhou'd be one, ~ Becauſe
Page 15

( 15 ) Becauſe of kin to thee: Wou'dſt thou be touch'd By the preſuming hands of ſawcy Grooms? The ſame reſpect, nay more, is due to me: More for my Sex; the ſame for my deſcent. Theſe hands are only fit to draw the Curtain. - Now, if thou dar'ſt behold Almeydar face. [Z/nveils her ſelf. Bend. Wou'd I had never ſeen it ! . [aſide. Almeyda, She whom thy Mufti tax'd to have no Soul; Let Affric now be judg; Perhaps thou think'ſt Imeanly hope to 'ſcape, As did Sebaſtian when he own'd his greatneſs. But to remove that ſcruple know, baſe Man, My murther'd Father, and my Brother’s Ghoſt Still haunt this Breſt, and prompt it to revenge. Think not I cou’d forgive nor dare thou pardon. - M. Mol. Woud'ſt thou revenge thee, Trait’reſs, hadſt thou, pow'r? Alm, Traitor, I wou'd; the Name's more juſtly thine: Thy Father was not more than mine, the Heir Of this large Empire; but with arms united - They fought their way, and ſeiz'd the Crown by force:: And equal as their danger was their ſhare: For where was Elderſhip, where none had right, But that which Conqueſt gave? 'Twas thy ambition. Pull'd from my peaceful Father what his Sword Help'd thine to gain: Surpriz'd him and his Kingdom, No provocation given, no War declar'd. M. Mol. I'll hear no more. l Alm. This is the living Coal that burning in me. Wou'd flame to vengeance, cou’d it find a vent. My Brother too, that lies yet ſcarcely cold In his deep watry bed: My wandring Mother, Who in exile died. O that I had the fruitful Heads of Hydra, That one might bourgeon where another fell ! Still wou'd I give thee work ; ſtill, ſtill, thou Tyrant, And hiſs thee with the laſt. M. Mol. Something, I know not what, comes over me:: …” Whether:
Page 16

( 16) Whether the Toyls of Battel, unrepaird With due repoſe, or other ſudden qualm. Bemducar do the reſt. [Goes off, the Court follows him. Bend. Strange; in full health ! This pang is of the Soul; The Body's unconcern'd: I'll think hereafter. Condućt theſe Royal Captives to the Caſtle; Bid Dorax uſe 'em well, till farther order. [Going off, ſtops. The inferior Captives their firſt owners take, To ſell, or to diſpoſe.—You, Muſtapha, - Set ope the Market for the ſale of Slaves [Exit Benducar. The Maſter, and Slaves come forward, and Buyers ofJºral ualities come in and chaffer about the ſeveral Owners, who make their Slaves do Tricks. Muſtapha, My Chattels are come into my hands again, and my Conſcience will ſerve me to ſell'em twice over; any price now, before the Mºſti comes to claim 'em. Firſt Merchant to Muſtapha. What do'ſt hold that old Fellow at 2 [Pointing to Alvarez. He's tough, and has no ſervice in his limbs. Muft. I confeſs he's ſomewhat tough 3, but I ſuppoſe you . wou'd not boyl him. I ask for him a thouſand Crowns. 1ſt. Mer. Thou mean'ſt a thouſand Marvedi's. Muft. Prithee Friend, give me leave to know my own mean- - II]2. º Mer. What virtues has he to deſerve that price 2 uſt. Marry come up Sir Virtues quoth ah! I took him in the King's Company 5 he's of a great Family, and rich, What other Virtues wou'dſt thou have in a Noble-man? 1ſt. Mer. I buy him with another man's Purſe, that's my comfort. - My Lord Dorax, the Governor, will have him at any rate:— There's Handſel. Come, old Fellow, to the Caſtle. Alvar. To what is miſerable Age reſerv'd [Aſide. But oh the King! Andoh the fatal Secret ! Which I have kept thus long, to time it better, And
Page 17

- ( 17 ) And now I wou'd diſcloſe, 'tis paſt my pow'r, - - [Exit with his Maſter. Muft. Something of a Secret, and of the King I heard him mutter: A Pimp I warrant him, for I am ſure he is an old Courtier. - - Now to put off t'other remnant of my Merchandize, -— Stir up, Sirrah [to Antonio. Anton. Dog, what wou'dſt thou have l - Muſt. Learn better manners, or I ſhall ſerve you a Dog- trick 5 come, down upon all four immediately 5 I'll make you know your Rider. Ant. Thou wilt not make a Horſe of me? Muft. Horſe or Aſs, that's as thy Mother made thee — But take earneſt in the firſt place for thy Sawcyneſs. [Laſhes him with his Whip. Be advis'd Friend, and buckle to thy Geers: Behold my Enſign of Royalty diſplay'd over thee. Amt. I hope one day to uſe thee worſe in Portugal. Muft, Ay, and good reaſon,Friend,if thou catcheſt me a con- quering on thy ſide of the water, lay me on luſtily, I'll take it as kindly as thou doſt this. - [Holds up his Whip. Antonio lying down. - Hold my dear Thrum-cap: I obey thee chearfully, I ſee the Dočtrine of Non-Reſiſtance is never practis'd thorough- ly but when a Man can't help himſelf. - Enter a Second Merchant. 2d. Merchant. You, Friend, I wou'd ſee that Fellow do his Poſtures. Muſtapha bridling Antonio. Now Sirrah follow, for you have rope enough: | To your paces Villain, amble, trot, and gallop : * Quick, about there.— ... Yeap, the more Money's bidden for you, the more your credit. - Antonio follows at the end of the Bridle on his hands and feet, and does all his Poſtureſ. D 2d, Merch.
Page 18

- - ( 18) 2d. Merch. He's well chin'd, and has a tolerable good back; that's half in half. [To Muſtapha.] I wou'd ſee him ſtrip, has he no Diſeaſes about him 2 - Muſi. He's the beſt piece of Man's fleſh in the Market, not an Eye-ſore in his whole body: Feel his Legs, Maſter, neither Splint, Spavin, nor Wind-gall. [Claps him on the ſhoulder. Merchant feeling about him, and then putting his hand.to his ſide. Out upon him, how his flank heaves | The Whorſon's broken-winded. - Muft. Thick breath'd a little: Nothing but a ſorry cold with lying out a nights in Trenches 5— but ſound Wind and Limb, I warrant him. - Try him at alooſe trot a little. Puts the Bridle into his hand, he ſtrokes him. Anton. For Heaven's ſake Owner ſpare me 3 you know I am but new.broken. - ad. Merch. 'Tis but a waſhy Jade,I ſee: What do you ask for this Bauble 2 Muft.Bauble do you call him;he's a ſubſtantial true-bred Beaſt; bravely forehanded 5 mark but the cleanneſs of his ſhapes too; his Dam may be a Spaniſh Gennet, but a true Barb by the Sire, or I have no skill in Horſe-fleſh. Marry I ask Six Hundred Xeriffs for him. Enter Mufti. Mufti, What's that you are asking, Sirrah 2 Muft. Marry, I ask your Reverence Six Hundred Pardons; I was doing you a ſmall piece of ſervice here, putting off your Chattel for you. . - Mifti, And putting the Mony into your own Pocket. .Muſ. Upon vulgar reputation, no my Lord, it was for your profit and emolument. What, wrong the Head ofmy Religion? I was ſenſible you wou'd have damn'd me, or any man that ſhou'd have injur'd you in a ſingle Earthing 5 for I knew that was Sa- crifice, - - - 2. / Mufti,
Page 19

(19) Mufti, Sacriledge you mean, Sirrah, and damning ſhall be the leaſt part of your puniſhment; I have taken you in the man- mer, and will have the Law upon you. Muft. Good my Lord, take pity upon a poor man in this World, and damn me in the next. ~ * Mufti, No Sirrah, ſo you may repent, and ſcape puniſhment: Did not you ſell this very Slave amongſt the reſt to me, and take Mony for him. Muft. Right my Lord. - Mufti, And ſelling him again? Take Mony twicefor the ſame Commodity? Oh, Villain But did you not know him to be my Slave, Sirrah 2 Muft. Why ſhou'd Ilye to your Honor, I did know him; and thereupon, ſeeing him wander about 5 I took him up for a ſtray, and impounded him, with intention to reſtote him to the right Owner. - - Mufti, And yet at the ſame time was ſelling him to another: How rarely the Story hangs together. Muff. Patience, my i. * - I took him up, as your Heriot, with intention to have made the beſt of him, and then have brought the whole produćt of him in a Purſe to you 5 for I know you wou'd have ſpent half of it upon your pious Pleaſures, have hoarded up the other half, and given the remainder in Charities to the Poor. Mufti, And what's become of my other Slave? Thou haſt ſold him too I have a villainous ſuſpicion. Muff. I know you have, my Lord 5 but while I was managing this young robuſtous Fellow, that old Spark who was nothing but Skin and Bone, and by conſequence, very nimble, ſlipt through my fingerslike an Eel, for there was no hold faſt of him, and ran away to buy himſelf a new Maſter. Mufti to Antonio. Follow me home, Sirrah : [to Muſt.] I ſhall remember you ſome other time. [Exit Mufti with Antonio. Muff. I never doubted your Lordſhips memory, for an ill turn: And I ſhall remember him too in the next riſing of the Mobile, for this ačb of Reſumption; and more eſpecially for the Ghoſtly Counſel he gave me before the Emperor, to have hang'd my ſelf in ſilence, to have ſav'd his Reverence. The D 2 v beſł 7

End of Section 1. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 2
Page 20

( 20 ) beſt on’t is, I am beforehand with him, for ſelling one of his Slaves twice over. And if he had not come juſt in the nick, I might have pocketed up t'other: For what ſhould a poor Mando, that gets his living by hard labor, but pray for bad times when he may get it eaſily. O, for ſome incomparable Tumult! Then ſhou'd I naturally wiſh, that the beaten Party might prevail, becauſe we have plundered tother fide already, and there's nothing more to get of 'em. Both rich and poor for their own intereſt pray, 'Tis ours to make our Fortunes while we may 5 For Kingdoms are not conquer'd every day. [Exit Muſtaph. - A c t II, - Scene 1. Suppos'd to be a terrace Walk, on the ſide of the Caſtle of Alcazar. Emperor. Benducar. Emper. A ND thinkeſt thou not it was diſcovered? Bend. No : The thoughts of Kings are like religious Groves, The Walks of muffled Gods: Sacred retreat, Where none but whom they pleaſe t'admit, approach. Emp. Did not my conſcious Eyes flaſh out a Flame To lighten thoſe brown horrors, and diſcloſe The ſecret path I trod? Bend. I cou’d not find it, 'till you lent a Clue To that cloſe Labarynth 5 how then ſhou'd they 2 Emp. I wou'd be loth they ſhou'd: it breeds contempt For Herds to liſten, or preſume to pry, When the hurt Lion groans within his Den : But is 't not ſtrange 2 - - Bend. To love? not more than 'tis to live; a Tax Impos'd on all by Nature, paid in kind, - . Familiar as our being. Emp. Still
Page 21

(?, 1 } Emp. Still 'tis ſtrange To me: I know my Soul as wild as winds, That ſweep the Deſarts of our moving Plains 3 Love might as well be ſow'd upon our Sands, As in a breſt ſo barren: To love an Enemy, the only One Remaining too, whom yeſter Sun beheld, Muſtring her charms, and rolling as ſhe paſt, By every Squadron her alluring eyes: To edge her Champions sºi, and urge my ruin. The ſhouts of Soldiers, and the burſt of Cannon, Maintain ev'n ſtill a deaf and murm'ring noiſe; Nor is Heav'n yet recover'd of the ſound Her Battel rows'd: Yet ſpight of me I love. Bend. What then controuls you? Her Perſon is as proſtrate as her Party. Emp. A thouſand things controul this Conqueror, My native pride to own th' unworthy paſſion, Hazard of Int’reſt, and my Peoples love: To what a Storm of Fate am I expos'd What if I had her murder'd 2 'tis but what My Subjećts all expect, and ſhe deſerves. Would not th' impoſſibility Of ever, ever ſeeing, or poſſeſſing, Calm all this rage, this Hurrican of Soul? Bend. That ever, ever, I mark'd the double, ſhows extream reluctance To part with her for ever. Emp. Right thou haſt me, I wou'd, but cannot kill: I muſt enjoy her: I muſt, and what I muſt be ſure I will. What's Royalty but pow'r to pleaſe my ſelf? And if I dare not, then am I the Slave, And my own Slaves the Sovereigns, 'tis reſolv’d, Weak Princes flatter when they want the pow'r To curb their People 5 tender Plants muſt bend, But when a Government is grown to ſtrength, Like ſome old Oak, rough with its armed Bark, It z.
Page 22

( 2.2 ) It yields not to the tug, but only ncds, And turns to ſullen State. Bend. Then you reſolve T'implore her pity, and to beg relief? Emp. Death, muſt I beg the pity of my Slave * Muſt a King beg 2 Yes, Love's a greater King 5 A Tyrant, nay a Devil that poſſeſſes me: He tunes the Organs of my voice, and ſpeaks Unknown to me within me 5 puſhes me, And drives me on by force. Say I ſhould wed her, wou'd not my wiſe Subjects Take check, and think it ſtrange 2 perhaps revolt? Bend. I hope they wou'd not. Emp. Then thou doubt'ſt they wou'd? Bend. To whom? Hmp. To her Perhaps, or to my Brother, or to Thee. [Bend, in diſorder. To me ! me did you mention? how I tremble! The name of Treaſon ſhakes my honeſt Soul. If I am doubted, Sir, Secure your ſelf this moment, take my life. Emp. No more: if I ſuſpected thee --- I wou'd. Bend. I thank your kindneſs: Guilt had almoſt loſt me! [Aſide. Emp. But clear my doubts: think'ſt thou they may rebel. [Bend. aſide. w This goes as I wou'd wiſh: --- (to th’ Emp) 'Tis poſſible. A ſecret Party ſtill remains, that lurks Like Embers rak'd in aſhes— wanting but A breath to blow aſide th’involving duſt, And then they blaze abroad. Emp. They muſt be trampled out. Bend. But firſt be known. - Emp. Torture ſhall force it from ‘em. Bend. You wou'd not put a Nation to the rack? Emp. Yes, the wholeWorld; ſo I be ſafe, I care not. Bend. Our Limbs and Lives º Are yours, but mixing Friends with Foes is hard. Emp.
Page 23

(23) Emp. All may be foes; or how to be diſtinguiſh'd, If ſome be friends 2 Bend. They may with eaſe be winnow'd : Suppoſe ſome one, who has deſerv'd your truſt, Some one who knows Mankind, ſhou'd be employ'd To mix among 'em, ſeem a Malcontent, And dive into their breaſts, to try how far They dare oppoſe your love? Emp. I like this well: 'Tis wholeſom wickedneſs. Bend. Whomever he ſuſpects, he faſtens there, And leaves no cranny of his Soul unſearch'd : Then, like a Bee bag’d with his honey'd venome, He brings it to your Hive : if ſuch a Man So able, and ſo honeſt, may be found 3 If not, my projećt dyes. – Emp. By all my hopes thou haſt deſcrib'd thy ſelf: — Thou, thou alone art fit to play that Engine, Thou only coudſt contrive. * - Bend. Sure I cou’d ſerve you: º I think I cou'd : — but here's the difficulty, I'm ſo entirely yours, That I ſhou'd ſcurvily diſſemble hate; The cheat wou'd be too groſs. - Emp. Art thou a Stateſman * * And canſt not be a Hypocrite 2 Impoſſible: - Do not diſtruſt thy Vertues. - Bend. If I muſt perſonate this ſeeming Villain, Remember’tis to ſerve you. Emp. No more words: Love goads me to Almeyda, all affairs Are troubleſom but that 5 and yet that moſt. - - [Going- Bid Dorax treat Sebaſtian like a King; I had forgot him 5 — but this Love marrs all, And takes up my whole breſt. [Exit Emperor, Bend. (to the Emp.) Be ſure I'll tell him. — With all the aggravating Circumſtances [Alone.. I can, to make him ſwell at that Command, - ( The w
Page 24

( 24 ) The Tyrant firſt ſuſpečted me: Then, with a ſudden guſt, he whirld about, And truſted me too far: Madneſs of Pow'r Now, by his own conſent, I ruin him. For, ſhou'd ſome feeble Soul, for fear or gain Bolt out t'accuſe me, ev'n the King is cozen'd, And thinks he's in the ſecret. How ſweet is Treaſon when the Traytor's ſafe! (Sees the Mufti and Dorax entring and ſeeming to confer.) The Mufti, and with him my ſullen Dorax, That firſt is mine already. 'Twas eaſie work to gain a cov'tous mind, Whom rage to looſe his Prisºners had prepard : Now, caught himſelf, He wou'd ſeduce another 5 I muſt help him: For Church-men, though they itch to govern all, Are ſilly, woful, awkard Politicians; They make lame miſchief, though they mean it well: Their Int’reſt is not finely drawn, and hid, But ſeams are coarſly bungled up, and ſeen. Muf. He'll tell you more. Dor, I've heard enough already To make me loath thy Morals. Bend. to Dor. You ſeem warm: The good Man's zeal, perhaps has gon too far. Dor. Not very far; not farther than zeal goes “Of courſe; a ſmall days journey ſhort of Treaſon. Muf. By all that's Holy, Treaſon was not nam'd: I ſpar'd the Emperors broken Vows to ſave The Slaves from Death; though it was cheating Heav'n, But I forgave him that. Dor. And ſlighted o'er [ſcornfully, The wrongs himſelf ſuſtain'd in property: When his bought Slaves were ſeiz'd by force, no loſs “Of his conſider'd, and no coſt repaid. Muf
Page 25

( 25 ) Mufti, Not wholly ſlighted o'er, not abſolutely: Some modeſt hints of private wrongs I urg'd. Dorax, Two thirds of all he ſaid: there he began; To ſhew the fulneſs of his heart, there ended : Some ſhort excurſions of a broken Vow, He made indeed, but flat inſipid ſtuff: But when he made his loſs the Theme, he flouriſh'd, Reliev'd his fainting Rhetorick with new Figures, And thunder'd at oppreſſing Tyranny. - Mufti, Why not, when Sacrilegious Pow'r wou'd ſeize My Property, 'tis an affront to Heav'n, Whoſe Perſon, though unworthy, I ſuſtain. Dorax. You've made ſuch ſtrong Alliances above, That 'twere Profaneneſs in us Laiety - To offer earthly Aid. I tell thee, Mufti, if the World were wiſe, They wou'd not wag one finger in your quarrels. Your Heav'n you promiſe, but our Earth you covet. The Phaethons of mankind, who fire that World, Which you were ſent by Preaching but to warm. Bend. This goes beyond the mark. Mufti, No, let him rail; His Prophet works within him; He's a rare Convert. Dorax, Now his Zeal yearns, To ſee me burnt; he damns me from his Church, Becauſe I wou'd reſtrain him to his Duty; Is not the care of Souls a load ſufficient 2 Are nor your holy ſtipends pay’d for this? -- Were you not bred apart from world'y noiſe, To ſtudy Souls, their Cures and their Diſeaſes? If this be ſo, we ask you but our own: Give us your whole Employment, all your care: The Province of the Soul is large enough To fill up every Cranny of your time, And leave you much to anſwer, if one Wretch Be damn'd by your neglect. E * - Bend.
Page 26

- ( 26 ) - Bend. to the Mufti. He ſpeaks but reaſon. Dorax, Why then theſe forein thoughts of State-Employments, Abhorrent to your Funètion and your Breeding? Poor droaning Truants of unpračtis'd Cells, Bred in the Fellowſhip of bearded Boys, What wonder is it if you know not Men? Yet there. you live demure, with down-caſt Eyes, And humble as your Diſcipline requires: "... 2 But, when let looſe from thence to live at large, Your little tinéture of Devotion dies: Then Luxury ſucceeds, and ſet agog With a new Scene of yet untaſted Joys, You fall with greedy hunger to the Feaſt. Of all your College Vertues, nothing now But your Original Ignorance remains: Bloated with Pride, Ambition, Avarice, You ſwell, to counſel Kings and govern Kingdoms. Mufti. He prates as if Kings had not Conſciences, And none requir'd Direétors but the Crowd. S Dorax, As private men they want you, not as Kings; Nor wou'd you care tº inſpect their publick Conſcience, But that it draws dependencies of Pow'r, And Earthly Intereſt which you long to ſway. Content you with monopolizing Heav'n, And let this little hanging Ball alone; - For give you but a foot of Conſcience there, And you, like Archimedes, toſs the Globe. We know your thoughts of us that Laymen are Lag Souls, and rubbiſh of remaining Clay, Which Heav'n, grown weary of more perfe&t work, Set upright with a little puff of breath, And bid us paſs for, Men. Mufti. I will not anſwer, Baſe foul mouth'd Renegade; but I'll pray for thee To ſhew my Charity. Exit Mufti. Dorax, Do; but forget not him who needs it moſt: Allow thy ſelf ſome ſhare : He's gone too ſoon; I had to tell him of his holy jugglings; - Things
Page 27

- ( 27 ) Things that wou'd ſtartle Faith, and make us deem Not this or that, but all Religions falſe. Bend. Our Holy Oratour has loſt the Cauſe: - [Aſide. But I ſhall yet redeem it—(to Dorax) let him go; For I have ſecret Orders from the Emperour, Which none but you muſt hear: I muſt confeſs I cou’d have wiſh’d ſome other hand had brought 'em. When did you ſee your Priſºner Great Sebaſtian Dorax, You might as well have ask'd me when I ſaw A creſted Dragon, or a Baſilisk; Both are leſs Poiſon to my Eyes and Nature. He knows not I am I; nor ſhall he ſee me Till time has perfeóted a lab’ring thought, That rouls within my breſt. - Bend. 'Twas my miſtake: I gueſs'd indeed that time, and his misfortunes, And your returning duty had effac’d The mem'ry of paſt wrongs; they wou'd in me; And I judg'd you as tame and as forgiving. - Dorax, Forgive him no, I left my fooliſh Faith Becauſe it wou'd oblige me to forgiveneſs. Bend. I can but grieve to find you obſtinate: For you muſt ſee him; 'tis our Emp'rours will, And ſtrićt Command. - Dorax, I laugh at that Command. Bend. You muſt do more than ſee; ſerve, and reſpect him. Dorax, See, ſerve him, and reſpect, and after all My yet uncancell'd wrongs, I muſt do this! But I forget my ſelf. Bend. Indeed you do. - \ Dorax, The Emp'rour is a ſtranger to my wrongs; I need but tell my ſtory, to revoke - This hard Commiſſion. Bend. Can you call me Friend, And think I cou’d neglect to ſpeak, at full Th’ Affronts you had from your ungrateful Maſter Dorax, And yet enjoyn'd my Service, and Attendance? Bend. And yet enjoyn'd 'em both: wou'd that were all; . E 2 He
Page 28

( 28 ) - He ſcru'd his Face into a harden'd ſmile, And ſaid, Sebaſtian knew to govern Slaves. Dorax, Slaves are the growth of Africk, not of Europe: . By Heav'n I will not lay down my Commiſſion; Not at his foot, I will not ſtoop ſo low; But if there be a part in all his Face is More ſacred than the reſt, I'll throw it there. Bend. You may; but then you loſe all future means Of Vengeance on Sebaſtian, when no more Alcalde of this Fort. Dorax, That thought eſcap'd me. Bend. Keep your Command 5 and be reveng'd on both : Nor ſooth your ſelf; you have no pow'r t'affront him; The Emp'rours love protećts him from inſults. And he, who ſpoke that proud ill-natur'd word, Following the bent of his impetuous temper, May force your reconcilement to Sebaſtian: Nay bid you kneel, and kiſs th’ offending foot, That kick'd you from his Preſence. But think not to divide their puniſhment ; You cannot touch a hair of loath'd Sebaſtian, While Muley-Moluch lives. Dorax, What means this Riddle? Bend. 'Tis out: there needs no Oedipus to ſolve it. Our Emp'rour is a Tyrant, fear'd aud hated; I ſcarce remember in his Reign, one day Paſs guiltleſs o'er his execrable head. He thinks the Sun is loſt that ſees not bloud: When none is ſhed we count it Holiday. We, who are moſt in favour, cannot call This hour our own — you know the younger Brother Mild Muley Zeydan;. Dorax, Hold and let me think. Bend. The Soldiers Idolize you, He truſts you with the Caſtle, The Key of all his Kingdom. - Dorax, Well; and he truſts you too. t Bend.
Page 29

( 19 ) Bend. Elſe I were mad, - To hazard ſuch a daring Enterprize. Dorax, He truſts us both; mark that, ſhall we betray him * A Maſter who repoſes Life and Empire On our fidelity: I grant he is a Tyrant, That hated name my nature moſt abhors; More, as you ſay, has loaded me with ſcorn : Ev’n with the laſt contempt, to ſerve Sebaſtian. Yet more I know he vacates my revenge; Which, but by this revolt I cannot compaſs: But, while he truſts me, ’twere ſo baſe a part To fawn and yet betray, I ſhou'd be hiſs'd And whoop'd in Hell for that Ingratitude. Bend. Conſider well what I have done for you. Dorax, Conſider thou what thou woud'ſt have me dos. Bend. You've too much honour for a Renegade. Dorax, And thou too little faith to be a Favºrite. Is not the bread thou eat'ſt, the Robe thou wear'ſt, Thy Wealth, and Honours, all the pure indulgence Of him thou wou'dſt deſtroy And wou'd his Creature, nay his Friend betray him?. Why then no Bond is left on human kind: - Diſtruſts, debates, immortal ſtrifes enſue; Children may murder Parents, Wives their Husbands. All muſt be Rapine, Wars, and Deſolation, When truſt and gratitude no longer bind. Bend. Well have you argued in your own defence: You, who have burſt aſunder all thoſe bonds, And turn’d a Rebel to your Native Prince. Dorax, True, I rebell'd : but when did I betray?" Indignities, which Man cou’d not ſupport, Provok'd my vengeance to this noble Crime. * But he had ſtrip'd me firſt of my Command, Diſmiſs'd my Service, and abſolv'd my Faith; And, with diſdainful Language, dar'd my worſt. I but accepted War, which he denounc'd, ~ Elſe had you ſeen, not Dorax, but Alonzo, With his couch'd Lance againſt your foremoſt Mori. * . . . *-*. retiagº.
Page 30

º ( 30 ) - *Perhaps too turn'd the fortune of the day 5 . . . Made Affrick mourn, and Portugal triumph. Bend. Let me embrace thee. Dorax, Stand off Sycophant, ...And keep Infection diſtant. Bend. Brave and honeſt. Dorax, In ſpight of thy Temptations. Bend. Call 'em Trials: - They were no more : thy faith was held in Balance, And nicely weigh’d by jealouſe of Pow'r ; Vaſt was the truſt of ſuch a Royal Charge; And onr wiſe Emperour, might juſtly fear Sebaſtian might be freed and reconcil'd, By new Obligements to thy former love. Dorax, I doubt thee ſtill; thy reaſons were too ſtrong, And driv'n too near the head, to be but Artifice. And after all, I know thou art a Stateſman, Where truth is rarely found. Bend. Behold the Emperour; - (Enter Emp. Seb, and Almeyda.) Ask him, I beg thee to be juſtify'd, If he employ'd me not to foord thy Soul, And try the footing whether falſe or firm, - - Dorax, Death to my Eyes, I ſee Sebaſtian with him Muſt he be ſerv'd avoid him, if we meet, , Ht muſt be like the cruſh of Heav'n and Earth, T’involve us both in ruin. (Exit Dorax. Bend. "Twas a bare ſaving game I made with Dorax, But better ſo than loſt ; he cannot hurt me, That I precaution'd : I muſt ruin him. But now this Love; Ay, there's the gath'ring ſtorm' The Tyrant muſt not wed Almeyda; no, * That ruins all the Fabrick 1 am raiſing. Yet ſeeming to approve it, gave me time, And gaining time gains all. - w - ( Bend,
Page 31

{ 31 ). - (Benducar goes and waits behind the Empe (The Emperour; Sebaſtian and Almeyda advance front of the Stage.) Guards and Attendants. rour; ). to the , Emp to Seb. I bad 'em ſerveyou, and if they obey not, I keep my Lions keen within their Dens, To ſtop their maws with diſobedient Slaves. Seb. If I had Conquer'd, ". They cou’d not have with more obſervance waited: Their eyes, hands, fect, • Are all ſo quick they ſeem t' have but one motion, To catch my flying words. Onely the Akayde. Shuns me, and with a grim Civility, , Bows, and declines my Walks. Emp. A Renegade: I know not more of him: but that he's brave, And hates your Chriſtian Sečt. If you can frame : A farther wiſh, give wing to your deſires, And name the thing you want. Sebaſt. My Liberty: For were ev'n Paradiſe it ſelf my Priſon, Still I ſhou'd long to leap the Chryſtal walls. Emp. Sure our two Souls have ſomewhere been acquainted: In former beings; or, ſtruck out together, - One ſpark to Africk flew, and one to Portugal. Exped a quick deliverance: (turning to Alm: ) here's a third, , Of kindred Soul to both: pity our Stars Have made us Foes! I ſhou'd not wiſh her death. Almeyda, I ask no pity; if I thought my Soul Of kin to thine, ſoon wou'd I rend my heart-ſtrings, And tear out that Alliance: but thou Viper Haſt cancell'd kindred, made a rent in Nature, And through her holy bowels gnaw'd thy way, . Through thy own Bloud to Empire. Emper. This again: — And yet ſhe lives; and only lives t" upbraid 111 º’. - Sebaſt ... What's
Page 32

º ºf | - ( 3 x ) Sebaſ. What honour is there in a Womans death ‘Wrong’d as ſhe ſays, but helpleſs to revenge; Strong in her Paſſion, impotent of Reaſon, Too weak to hurt, too fair to be deſtroy'd. Mark her Majeſtick Fabrick; She's a Temple Sacred by birth, and built by Hands Divine; Her Soul's the Deity, that lodges there: Nor is the Pile unworthy of the God. - Emp. She's all that thou canſt ſay or I can think. But the perverſneſs of her clam’rous Tongue Strikes Pity deaf. Seb. Then onely hear her Eyes; Though they are mute they plead; nay more, command; For beauteous Eyes have Arbitrary Power. All Females have prerogative of Sex, The Shes ev’n of the ſalvage herd are ſafe; And when they ſnarl or bite, have no return But Courtſhip from the Male. - Emp. Were She not She, and I not Muley-Moluck, She's Miſtreſs of unevitable Charms, For all but me; nor am I ſo exempt, But that — I know not what I was to ſay — But I am too obnoxious to my Friends; And ſway’d by your Advice. Sebaſt. Sir, I advis'd not. By Heav'n, I never counſell'd Love but Pity. Emp. By Heav'n thou didſt : deny it not, thou didſt: For what was all that Prodigality Of praiſe, but to enflame me? — Sebaſt. Sir, - Emp. No more : º Thou haſt convincid me, that ſhe's worth my Love. Seb. Was ever Man ſo ruin’d by himſelf! (Aftae. Almeyda, Thy Love; that odious Mouth was never fram'd To ſpeak a word ſo ſoft: Name Death again, for that thou canſt pronounce With horrid grace, becoming of a Tyrant. Love is for human hearts, and not for thine, Where w
Page 33

( 33 ) Where the brute Beaſt extinguiſhes the Man. Emper. Such if I were, yet rugged Lions love, And grapple, and compel their ſavage Dames.—— - - Mark my Sebaſtiam, how that ſullen frown, [She fromns. Like flaſhing Lightning, opens angry Heaven; And while it kills delights. But yet, inſult not Too ſoon, proud Beauty, I confeſs no love. Seb. No Sir, I ſaid ſo, and I witneſs for you, Not love; but noble pity mov’d your mind: Int’reſt might urge you too to ſave her life; For thoſe who wiſh her party loſt, might murmur At ſhedding Royal Blood, Emp. Right, thou inſtrućt'ſt me; Int’reſt of State requires not Death, but Marriage; T'unite the jarring Titles of our Line. Seb. Let me be dumb for ever, all I plead, [Aftle. Like Wild-fire thrown againſt the Wind, returns With double force to burn me. - Emp. Cou'd I but bend to make my beauteous Foe The Partner of my Throne, and of my Bed. Almeyda, Still thou diſſembleſt, but I read thy heart, And know the power of my own Charms ; thou lov'ſt, And I am pleas'd for my revenge thou doſt. - Emp. And thou haſt cauſe. Alm. I have 5 for I have pow'r to make thee wretched. Be ſure I will, and yet deſpair of freedom. * Emp. Well then, I love, - And 'tis below my greatneſs to diſown it: Love thee implacably, yet hate thee too; Wou'd hunt thee bare-foot, in the mid-day Sun, Through the parch'd Deſarts, and the ſcorching Sands, T'enjoy thy Love, and once enjoy'd to kill thee. Alm. 'Tis a falſe Courage, when thou threat'neſt me 5 Thou canſt not ſtir a hand to touch my Life: . Do not I ſee thee tremble while thou ſpeakſt? Lay by the Lions Hide, vain Conqueror, x And take the Diſtaff; for thy Soul's my Slave. . Emp. Confuſion! How thou vieweſt my very Heart! -
Page 34

(34) …--- I cou’d as ſoon, Stop a Spring tide, blown in, with my bare hand, As this impetuous Love:-Yes, I will wed thee; In ſpight of thee, and of my ſelf, I will. Alm. For what 3 To people Affric with new Monſters, Which that unnatural mixture muſt produce 2 No, were we joyn'd, evn tho it were in death, Our Bodies burning in one Funeral Pile, The Prodigy of Thebes wou'd be renew’d, And my divided flame ſhou'd break from thine. Emp. Serpent, I will engender Poyſon with thee;. Joyn Hate with Hate, add Venom to the birth; Our Offſpring, like the ſeed of Dragons Teeth, Shall iſſue arm’d, and fight themſelves to death. Alm. I'm calm again; thou canſ not marry me. Emp: As gleams of Sun-ſhine ſoften ſtorms to ſhow'rs, So, if you ſmile, the loudneſs of my rage In gentle Whiſpers ſhall return, but this, - That nothing candivert my Love, but Death. Alm, Seehow thou art deceiv'd, I am a Chriſtian 3. *Tis true, unpraćtis'd in my new Belief, Wrongs I reſent, nor pardon yet with eaſe: Thoſe Fruits come late, and are of ſlow increaſe Inhaughty Hearts, like mine: Now, tellthy ſelf. If this one word deſtroy not thy deſigns: Thy Law permits thee not to marry me. Emp. Tis but a ſpecious Tale, to blaſt my hopes, And baffle my pretenſions. Speak, Sebaſtian, And, as a King, ſpeak true. Sebaſt. Then, thus adjur’d, On a King's word 'tis truth, but truth ill tim'd; For her dear Life is now expos'd anew; Unleſs you wholly can put on Divinity, And graciouſly forgive. Alm. Now learn by this, The little value I have left for life, - And trouble me no more. Emp. I thank thee Woman 3. Thou
Page 35

º - - - - - (35) Thou haſt reſtor'd me to my native Rage; And I will ſeize my happineſs by force. --- - - - Sebaſt. Know Muley-Moluch when thou dar'ſ attempt— Emp. Beware, I wou'd not be provok'd to uſe A Conqueror's right, and therefore charge thy ſilence. If thou wou'dſt merit to be thought my Friend, I leave thee to perſwade her to compliance: If not, there's a new guſt in Raviſhment, Which I have never try’d. Bend. They muſt be watch'd; - [aſſae. For ſomething I obſerv'd createsa doubt. . . . . [Exeunt Emperour and Benducar. Seb. I've been too tame, have baſely born my Wrongs, And not exerted all the King, within me 3 I heard him, Oſweet Heavens, he threat'ned Rape; . Nay inſolently urg'd me to perſwade thee, Ev’n thee, thou Idol of my Soul and Eyes; For whom I ſuffer Life, and drag this being. Alm. You turn my Priſon to a Paradiſe; But I have turn'd your Empire to a Priſon: In all your Wars good fortune flew before you; Sublime you ſate in Triumph on her Wheel; Till in my fatal Cauſe your Sword was drawn; The weight of my misfortunes drag'd you down. Seb. And is't not ſtrange, that Heav'n ſhou'd bleſs my Arms Incommon Cauſes, and deſert the beſt? Now in your greateſt, laſt extremity, When I wou'd, ayd you moſt, and moſt deſire it, I bring but Sighs, the ſuccors of a Slave, - - Alm, Leave then the luggage of your fate behind, To make your flight more eaſie, leave Almeyda. Northink me left a baſe ignoble Prey, Expos'd to this inhuman Tyrant's luſt 3. My Virtue is a guard beyond my ſtrength, And Death, my laſt defence, within my call. - Seb. Death may be call'd in vain, and cannot come; Tyrants can tye him up from your relief: Nor has a Chriſtian privilege to dye,
Page 36

, - – v ( 36 ) Alas thou art too young in thy new Faith; Brutus and Cato might diſcharge their Souls, - t And give 'em Furlo's for another World : But we, like Centry's, are oblig'd to ſtand In ſtarleſs Nights, and wait the pointed hour. - Alm. If ſhunning ill be good, then Death is good. To thoſe who cannot ſhun it but by Death: Divines but peep on undiſcover'd Worlds, And draw the diſtant Landſhape as they pleaſe: But who has eer return'd from thoſe bright Regions, To tell their Manners, and relate their Laws? Pll venture landing on that happy ſhoar With an unſuily'd Body, and white Mind ; If I have err'd, ſome kind Inhabitant Will pity a ſtray’d Soul, and take me home. Seb. Beware of Death, thou canſt not dye unperjur'd And leave an unaccompliſh'd Love behind: Thy Vows are mine; nor will I quit my claim: . . . The tye of Minds are but imperfeót Bonds, Unleſs the Bodies joyn to ſeal the Contračt. Alm. What Joys can you poſſeſs or can I give? Where groans of Death ſucceed the ſighs of Love. Our Hymen has not on his Saffron Robe; But muffled up in Mourning, downward holds . His dropping Torch, extinguiſh'd with his Tears. Seb. The God of Love ſtands ready to revive it With his etherial breath. - Alm. "Tis late to joyn, when we muſt part ſo ſoon. Seb. Nay rather let us haſte it, ere we part: Our Souls, for want of that acquaintance here, May wander in the ſtarry Walks above, And, forc'd on worſe Companions, miſs ourſelves. Alm. The Tyrant will not long be abſent hence; And ſoon I ſhall be raviſh'd from your arms. Seb. Wilt thou thy ſelf become the greater Tyrant, And give not Love, while thou haſt Love to give? In dang'rous days, when Riches are a Crime, The wiſe betimes make over their Eſtates: º Make
Page 37

( 37 ) Make oer thy Honour, by a deed of truſt, And give me ſeizure of the mighty wealth. Alm. What ſhall I do! O teach me to refuſe! I wou'd 3 and yet I tremble at , the grant. For dire preſages fright my Soul by day, And boding Viſions haunt my Nightly Dreams : Sometimes, methinks, I hear the groans of Ghoſts 3 Thin, hollow ſounds, and lamentable ſcreams 3. Then, like a dying Eccho, from afar, - My Mothers Voice, that cries, Wed not Almeyda | Forewarn'd Almeyda, Marriage is thy Crime. Seb. Some envious Demon, to delude our joys 3 Love is not Sin, but where 'tis ſinful Love. Alm. Mine is a flame ſo holy, and ſo clear, That the white taper leaves no ſoot behind 3 No ſmoak of Luſt; but chaſt as Siſter's love, When coldly they return a Brothers kiſs, Without the zeal that meets at lovers mouths. Seb. Laugh then at fond preſages; I had ſome 3 Fam'd Noſtradamus, when he took my Horoſcope, Foretold my Father I ſhould wed with Inceſt: - Ere this unhappy War my Mother dy’d 5 And Siſters I had none 5 vain Augury! - A long Religious Life, a Holy Age, - My Stars aſſign'd me too 5 impoſſible. r For how can Inceſt ſuit with Holineſs, Or Prieſtly Orders with a Princely State?. Alm. Old venerable Alvarez'--- (fighing.) Seb. But why that ſigh in naming that good Man 2 Alm. Your Fathers Counſellor and Confident Seb. He was 5 and, if he lives, my ſecond Father: &c. Æð - Alm. Mark'd our farewel, when going to the fight, You gave Almeyda for the word of Battel; 'Twas in that fatal Moment, he diſcover'd The Love that long we labour'd to conceal. I know it; though my eyes ſtood full of tears, Yet, through the miſt, I ſaw him ſtedfaſt gaze : Then knock'd his Aged breaſt, and inward groan'd 5 Like : -
Page 38

- (38) … Like ſome ſad. Prophet, that foreſaw the doom - Of thoſe whom beſt he lov'd, and cou’d not ſave. -> Seb. It ſtartles me! and brings to my remembrance, - That, when the ſhock of Battel was begun, He wou'd have much complain'd (but had not time} Of our hid paſſion; then, with lifted hands, He beg'd me by my Fathers Sacred Soul, \ Not to eſpouſe you, if he dy'd in fight: For if he liv'd, and we were Conquerors, He had ſuch things to urge againſt our Marriage, / As, now declar'd, wou'd blunt my ſword in Battel; And daſtardize my Courage. Alm. My blood cruddles; And cakes about my heart. Seb. I'll breath a ſigh, ſo warm into thy boſom, Shall make it flow again. My Love, he knows not Thou art a Chriſtian; that produc’d his fear : Leſt thou ſhoud'ſt ſooth my Soul with charms ſo ſtrong, That Heav'n might prove too weak. Alm. There muſt be more: This cou’d not blunt your Sword. Seb. Yes, if I drew it, with a curſt intent, To take a Misbeliever to my Bed; It muſt be ſo. Alm. Yet Seb. No, thou ſhalt not plead With that fair mouth, againſt the Cauſe of Love. Within this Caſtle is a Captive Prieſt, My Holy Confeſſor, whoſe free acceſs Not ev'n the barb'rous Vićtors have refus’d 5 This happy hour his hands ſhall make us one. . . - Alm. I go; with Love and Fortune, two blind Guides, To lead my way: half loth and half conſenting. - If, as my Soul fore-bodes, ſome dire event Purſue this Union, or ſome Crime unknown, Forgive me Heav'n 3 and all ye Bleſt above, Fxcuſe the frailty of unbounded Love. Exeunt Ambo. Scene
Page 39

(39) . Scene 2. Suppoſd a Garden; with Lºng Tooms behind it; or on the ſides. ~ * *;Muſtis Antonio as a Slave; and Johayma the Mufti's 7Iſe, - Mufti. A Nd, how do you like him, look upon him well 5 he's a perſonable Fellow of a Chriſtian Dog. Now I think you are fitted, for a Gardiner : Ha what ſayiſt thou johayma 2 johayma. He may make a ſhift to ſow lettice, raiſe Melons, and water a Garden-plat. But otherwiſe a very filthy Fellow ; how odiouſly he ſmells of his Country garlikel fugh, how he ſtinks of Spain. Mufti. Why honey-bird I bought him a purpoſe for thee; didſt not thou ſay thou long dſt for a Chriſtian Slave? joh. Ah, but the fight of that loathſom creature has almoſt cur'd me; And how can I tell that he's a Chriſtian 2 and he were well ſearch'd he may prove a jew for ought I know. And beſides I have always long'd for an Eunuch; for they ſay that's a Civil Creature, and almoſt as harmleſs as your ſelf Husband : ſpeak fellow, are not you ſuch a kind of peace- able thing 2. Amt. I was never taken for one in my own Country; and not very peaceable neither, when I am well provok'd. Mufti. To your Occupation Dog; bind up the Jeſſamines in yond Arbor, and handle your pruning knife with dexteri. ty; tightly I ſay, go tightly to your buſineſs; you have coſt me much ; and muſt earn it in your work ; here's plentiful proviſion for you, raſcal, ſillating in the Garden, and water in the tanck, and on Holy days the licking of a platter of Rice, when you deſerve it. - joh. What have you been bred up to Sirrah, and what can you perform to recommend you to my ſervice P £Antonio making legs. - - - Why Madam, I can perform as much as any Man, in a fair Ladies Service, - I.
Page 40

- (40 ) I can play upon the Flute, and Sing3. I can carry'your Um- brella, and fan your Ladyſhip, and cool you when you are too hot : in fine, no Service either by day or by night ſhall come amiſs to me; and beſides am of ſo quick an apprehenſion, that you need but wink upon me at any time, to make me under- ſtand my duty. [She winks at him. Anton. Very fine, ſhe has tipt the wink already. [Aſide. joh. The Whelp may come to ſomething in time, when I have enter'd him into his buſineſs. Muf. A very malapert Cur, I can tell him that ; I do not like his fawning, you muſt be taught your diſtance Sirrah. - - (Strikes him.) joh. Hold, hold. He ha's deſerv'd it I confeſs; but for once let his igno- rance plead his pardon; we muſt not diſcourage a beginner. Your Reverence has taught us Charity ev'n to Birds and Beaſts: here you filthy brute you : — take this little Alms, to buy you plaiſters. (gives him a piece of money) Amt. Money and a Love-pinch in the inſide of my palm into the bargain. - [Aſide. (Enter a Servant. Sir, my Lord Benducar is coming to wait on you, and is al- ready at the Palace Gate. Muf. Come in johayma, regulate the reſt of my Wives and Concubines, and leave the Fellow to his work. , joh. Look how ſtupidly he ſtares about him , like a Calf new come into the World: I ſhall teach you Sirrah to know your buſineſs, a little better. —— this way you awkard raſ- cal, here lyes the Arbour, muſt I be ſhowing you eternally 2 - - - (turning him about.) Muf Come away Minion; you ſhall ſhow him nothing. joh. I'll but bring him into the Arbor, where a Roſe-tree and a Myrtle are juſt falling for want of a prop 5 if they were bound together they wou'd help to keep up one ano- ther: — He's a raw Gardiner, and 'tis but Charity to teach him. - Muf. No *

End of Section 2. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 3
Page 41

(41 Muf. No more deeds of & to day 5 come in, or I ſhall think you a little better diſpos'd than I cou’d wiſh you. . job. Well, gobefore, I will follow my Paſtor. Muf. So you may caſt a ſheeps eye behind you: In before me. And you, ſawcineſs, mind your pruning knife; or I may chance to uſe it for you. Exeunt Mufti and johayma. Ant, alone. Thank you for that; but I an in no ſuch haſt to be made a Muſulman. For his Wedlock, wº. 1 all her haughti- neſ, I find her coming. How far a Chriſtian ſhou'd reſiſt, I partly know; but how far a lewd young Chriſtian can reſiſt is another queſtion. She's tolerable, and I am a poor Stran- ger, far from better Friends, and in a bodily neceſſity: Now have I a ſtrange temptation to try what other Females are be- longing to this Family: I am not far from the Womens apart- ment I am ſure; and if theſe Birds are within diſtance, here's that will chuckle 'em together. (pulls out his Flute). If there be variety of Moors fleſh in this Holy Market ’twere madneſs to lay out all my money upon the firſt bargain. - [He plays. A Grate opens and Morayma the Mufti's Daughter ap- pears at it. - - Anton. Ay there's an Apparition This is a Morſel worthy of a Mufti 5 this is the reliſhing bit in ſecret ; this is the My- ſtery of his Alcoran, that muſt be reſerv'd from the know- ledg of the profane Vulgar. This is his Holyday Devotion; ſee, ſhe beckons too. - (She beckons to him.) Morayma. Come a little nearer and ſpeak ſoftly. Ant. I come, I come I warrant thee; the leaſt twinckle had brought me to thee 3 ſuch another kind ſyllable or two, wou'd turn me to a Meteor and draw me up to thee. G Mor. I

End of Section 3. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 4
Page 42

( 4.) - Mor, I dare not ſpeak, for fear of being over-heard; but if you think my #. worth your hazard, and can deſerve my love —— the reſt this Note ſhall tell you —— (throws down a handkerchief) No more, my heart goes with you. Exit from the Grate. Antonio. O thou pretty little heart 5 art thou flown hither, I'll keep it warm I warrant it, and brood upon it in the new neſt: but now for my Treaſure trove, that's wrapt up in the handkerchief: No peeping here, though I long to be ſpelling her Arabick ſcrawls and pot hooks. But I muſt carry off my prize, as Robbers do ; and not think of ſhar: ing the booty, before I am free from danger, and out of eye-ſhot from the other Windows. If her wit be as poy- nant as her Eyes, I am a double Slavé. Our Northern Beau- ties are meer dough to theſe: Inſipid white Earth, meer To. baccopipe-clay; With no more Soul and Motion in 'em, than a Fly in Winter. º - Here the warm Planet ripens, and ſublimes The well bak'd Beauties of the Southern Climes; Our Cupid's but a bungler in his Trade 5 His kecneſt Arrows are in Affrick made [Exit Antonio.

End of Section 4. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 5
Page 43

( 43 ) A cr. III. Scene 1: A Terrace-walk; or ſome other publick place - in the Caſtle of Alcazar. t - - Emperor Muley-Moluch ; Benducar. Emper. Arry'd I’ll not believe it; 'tis impoſture; Improbable they ſhould preſume t'attempt, Impoſſible they ſhou'd effect their wiſh, - Bend. Have patience till I clear it. Emp. I have none: - Go bid our moving Plains of Sand lye ſtill, And ſtir not, when the ſtormy South blows high : º From top to bottom thou haſt toſſ'd my Soul, And now 'tis in the madneſs of the Whirl, w Requir'ſt a ſudden ſtop? unſay thy lye, That may in time do ſomewhat. Bend. I have done: - - For, ſince it pleaſes you it ſhou'd be forg'd, 'Tis fit it ſhou'd : far be it from your Slave, To raiſe diſturbance in your Sacred breſt. Emp. Sebaſtian is my Slave as well as thou; Nor durſt offend my love by that preſumption. Bend. Moſt ſure he ought not. Emp. Then all means were wanting; No Prieſt, no Ceremonies of their Sečt 5 Or, grant we theſe defects cou’d be ſupply'd, How could our Prophet do an Aćt ſo baſe, So to reſume his gifts, and curſe my Conqueſts By making me unhappy l No, the Slave That told thee ſo abſurd a ſtory, ly’d. * Bend. Yet, till this moment I have found him faithful : He ſaid he ſaw it too. - - Emp. Diſpatch; what ſaw he? - - - G 2 - Bend.
Page 44

(44), Bend. Truth is, conſidering with what earneſtneſs, Sebaſtian pleaded for Almeyda’s life, Inhanc'd her beauty, dwelt upon her praiſe, Emp. O ſtupid, and unthinking as I was I might have mark'd it too: 'twas groſs and palpable? Bend. Methought I trac'd a Lover ill diſguis'd; And ſent my ſpy, a ſharp obſerving Slave, T'inform me better, if I gueſs'd aright. He told me, that he ſaw Sebaſtians Page Run croſs the Marble Square ; who ſoon return'd, And after him there lag’d a puffing Fryar 5 Cloſe wrap'd he bore ſome ſecret Inſtrumenti --> Of Chriſtian Superſtition in his hand: My ſervant follow'd faſt, and through a chink, Perceiv'd the Royal Captives hand in hand: And heard the hooded Father mumbling charms, That make thoſe Misbelievers Man and Wife. Which done, the Spouſes kiſs'd with ſuch a fervour, And gave ſuch furious earneſt of their flames, That their eyes ſparkled, and their mantling blood Flew fluſhing o'er their faces. - Emp. Hell confound 'em! Bend. The Reverend Father, with a Holy leer, Saw he might well be ſpar'd, and ſoon withdrew : This forc'd my Servant to a quick retreat, For fear to be diſcover'd 3 gueſs the reſt. Emp. I do. My fancy is too exquiſite, And tortures me with their imagin'd bliſs. Some Earthquake ſhou'd have ris'n, and rent the ground, Have ſwallow'd him, and left the longing Bride, - - In Agony of unaccompliſh'd Love. (Walks diſorderly) Enter the Mufti. - y Bend. In an unlucky hour [Aſide. That Fool intrudes, raw in this great affair, And uninſtructed how to ſtem the tide. Coming º
Page 45

( 45) Coming up to the Mufti aftae. The Emp'ror muſt not marry, nor enjoy 5 Keep to that point 5 ſtand firm, for all's at ſtake. Emperor ſeeing him. You, Druggerman of Heaven, muſt I attend Your droaning Prayers ? Why came you not before ? Doſt thou not know the Captive King has dar'd To wed Almeyda 3 Cancel me that Marriage, And make her mine ; about the buſineſs, quick, Expound thy Mahomet; make him ſpeak my ſenſe, Or he's no Prophet here, and thou no Mufti, - Unleſs thou know'ſt the trick of thy vocation, - To wreſt and rend the Law to pleaſe thy Prince. Mufti, Why, verily the Law is monſtrous plain: There's not one doubtful Text in all the Alchoran, Which can be wrench'd in favor to your Projećt. Emp. Forge one, and foiſt it into ſome by-place, Of ſome old rotten Roll ; do't, I command thee: Muſt I teach thee thy Trade 2 Mufti, It cannot be. For Matrimony being the deareſt point Of Law, the People have it all by heart: - A Cheat on Procreation will not paſs. Beſides th’ offence is ſo exorbitant, [In a higher tone. Tomingle with a misbelieving Race, That ſpeedy Vengeance wou'd purſue your Crime, And holy Mahomet launch himſelf from Heav'n, Before th' unready Thunderbolt were form'd. Emperor taking him by the Throat with one hand, ſnatches out his Sword with the other, and points it to his Breſt. Emp. Slave, have I rais'd thee to this pomp and pow'r, To preach againſt my Will? Know I am Law ; And thou, not Mahomet's Meſſenger, but mine: Make it, I charge thee, make my pleaſure lawful: Or firſt I ſtrip the of thy ghoſtly greatneſs, Then ſend thee poſt, to tell thy Tale above; And
Page 46

( 46 ) And bring thy vain Memorials to thy Prophet Of Juſtice donebelow for Diſobedience. Mufti, For Heaven's ſake hold, the reſpite of a moment,- To think for you. - Emp. And for thy ſelf- - Mufti, For both. Bºnd. Diſgrace, and Death, and Avarice have loſt him! [Aſide. Mufti, 'Tis true, our Law forbids to wed a Chriſtian; But it forbids you not to raviſh her. You have a Conqueror's right upon your Slave 3 And then, the more deſpight you do a Chriſtian, You ſerve the Prophet more who loaths that Sečt. Emp. Oh now it mends; and you talk reaſon, Mufti. But ſtay ! I promis'd freedom to Sebaſtian : Now ſhou'd I grant it, his revengeful Soul Wou'd ne'er forgive his violated Bed. Mufti, Kill him, for then you give him liberty: His Soul is from his earthly Priſon freed. Emp. How happy is the Prince who has a Churchman So learn’d and pliant to expound his Laws. - Bend. Two things I humbly offer to your prudence. Emp. Be brief; but let not either thwart my love. Bend. Firſt, ſince our holy Man has made Rape lawful, Fright her with that: proceed not yet to force: Why ſhould you pluck the green diſlaſtful Fruit From the unwilling Bough, When it may ripen of it ſelf and fall 2 Emp. Grant her a day; tho that's too much to give Out of a Life which I devote to Love. Bend. Then next, to bar All future hopes of her deſir'd Sebaſtian, - Let Dorax be enjoyn'd to bring his head. * , Emperor to the Mufti. Go Mufti, call him to receive his Orders. £Exit Mufti. I taſte thy Counſel, her deſires new rowz'd, And yet unſlak'd, will kindle in her fancy, And make her eager to renew the Feaſt, ^ - Bend. -
Page 47

- ( 47 ) Bend, aſide. Dorax, I know before, will diſobey: There's a Foe's Head well cropt.— But this hot love precipitates my Plot; And brings it to projećtion ere its time. Enter Sebaſtian and Almeyda hand in hand; upon/* of the - Emperor, they ſeparate and ſeem diſturb’d. Almeyda, He breaks, at unawares, upon our Walks, And like a mid-night Wolf invades the Fold: Make ſpeedy preparation of your Soul, And bid it arm apace: He comes for anſwer, And brutal miſchief ſits upon his brow. - Sebaſt. Not the laſt ſounding, cou’d ſurprize me more, That ſummons drowzy Mortals to their doom, When call'd in haſte, they fumble for their Limbs, And tremble unprovided for their charge: My ſenſe has been ſo deeply plung'd in Joys, The Soul out-ſlept her hour; and, ſcarce awake, Wou'd think too late, and cannot l But brave Minds At worſt can dare their Fate.— º • Emperor coming up to them. Emp. Have you perform'd Your Embaſſy, and treated with ſucceſs 2 Selaſt. I had not time. - Emp. No, not for my Affairs, But for your own too much. - - Sebaſt. You talk in Clouds, explain your meaning, Sir. - Emp. Explain yours firſt: What meant you hand in hand, And when you ſaw me, with a guilty ſtart, - You loos'd your hold, affrighted at my preſerce? Seb. Affrighted 2 - - Emp. Yes, aſtoniſh'd, and confounded. Seb. What mak’ſ thou of thy ſelf, and what of me? Art thou ſome Ghoſt, ſome Demon, or ſome God 2 That I ſhou'd ſtand aſtoniſh'd at thy fight? . If thou cou’dſt deem ſo meanly of my Courage, Why didſt thou not engage me man for man, l Ant
Page 48

(48) And try the virtue of that Gorgon Face, To ſtare me into ſtatue? Emp. Oh, thou art now recover'd, but by Heav'n, Thouwert amaz'd at firſt, as if ſurpriz'd At unexpected baſeneſs brought to light. for know, ungrateful man, that Kings, like Gods, Are every where; walk in th' abyſs of minds, And view the dark receſſes of the Soul. Seb. Baſe and ungrateful never was I thought; Nortill this turn of fate, durſt thou have call'd me 3 . . But, ſince thou boaſt'ſt th' omniſcience of a God, Say, in what cranny of Sebaſtian's Soul, Unknown to me, ſo loath'd a Crime is lodg'd? • . Emp. Thou haſt not broke my truſt repos'd in thee? Seb. Impos'd, but not receiv'd : Takeback that falſehood. Emp. Thou art not marry'd to Almeyda £ / Seb. Yes. Emp. And own'ſt the uſurpation of my Love? Seb. I own it in the face of Heav'nand thee No Uſurpation; but a lawful claim, Of which I ſtand poſſeſt. Emp. Sh’ has choſen well, Betwixta Captive and a Conqueror. Almeyda, Betwixt a Monſter and the beſt of Men. He was the envy of his neighb'ring Kings; For him their ſighing Queens deſpis'd their Lords, And Virgin Daughters bluſh’d when he was nam'd. To ſhare his noble Chains is more to me, Than all the ſalvage greatneſs of thy Throne. Seb. Were I to chooſe again, and knew my fate, For ſuch a night I wou'd be what I am. The Joys I have poſſeſt are ever mine; Out of thy reach behind Eternity, Hid in the ſacred treaſure of the paſt; But bleſs'd remembrance bring's 'em hourly back. Emp. Hourly indeed, who haſt but hours to live: O mighty purchaſe of a boaſted bliſs l To dream of what thou hadſt one fugitive night, And never ſhalt have more. Sek.
Page 49

- (49) - ~ Seb. Barbarian, thou canſt part us but a moment 5– We ſhall be one again in thy deſpight : Life is but air, - That yields a paſſage to the whiſtling Sword, . And cloſes when’tis gone. - - . Alm. How can we better dye than cloſe embrac'd, Sucking each others Souls while we expire 2 - Which ſo transfus'd, and mounting both at once, The Saints deceiv'd, ſhall by a ſweet miſtake, Hand up thy Soul for mine, and mine for thine. Emp. No, I'll untwiſt you : * . I have occaſion for your ſtay on earth : - Let him mount firſt, and beat upon the Wing, - &c. And wait an Age for what I here detain. sc Or ſicken at immortal Joys above, º: , , -- And languiſh for the Heav'n he left below. ." - Alm. Thou wilt not dare to break what Heav'n has joyn'd? Emp. Not break the Chain, but change a rotten link, And rivet one to laſt. - Think'ſt thou I come to argueright and wrong? - Why lingers Dorax thus? Where are my Guards, . . . . . - [Benducargoes out for the Guards, and returns. To drag that Slave to death? . . [Pointing to Sebaſt. Now ſtorm and rage, , , , ; - *: - . r - Call vainly on thy Prophet, then defie him ºf . . . . For wanting power to ſave thee... ºn tº . . . . . . . . . . . . . Seb. That were to gratifiethy Pride: I’ll ſhew thee How a Man ſhou'd, and how a King dare dye : . . . . So even, that my Soul ſhall walk with eaſe Out of its fleſh, and ſhut out Life as calmly As it does words; without a Sigh, to note . . . . . . . . . . One ſtruggle in the ſmooth diſſolving frame. . . Almeyda to the Emperor. Expect revenge from Heav'n, inhuman Wretch; Nor hope t'aſcend Sebaſtian's holy Bed. . . - - Flames, Daggers, Poyſons, guard the ſacred ſteps : . . . Thoſe are the promis'd Pleaſures of my love. Emp. And theſe might fright another, but not me.” Or me, if I deſign'd to give you pleaſure; - - jº º - H I ſeek
Page 50

* ( 50 ) , - I ſeek my own, and while that laſts, you live. . . . . . Enter imo of the Guardſ. . . . .” - - Go, bear the Captive to a ſpeedy death, -- " . . . . . Ard ſet my Soul at eaſe. . . . - . . . . . . Alm. I charge you hold, ye Miniſters of death, . . . . . . Speak my Sebaſtian ; . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Plead for thy life: Oh ask it of the Tyrant; º!... ." 'Tis no diſhonor, truſt me, Love, ’tis none: … , i. I wou'd die for thee, but I cannot plead; . . . . . . . . . . . My haughty heart diſdains it, ev’n for thee. tº ºt Still ſilent | Will the King of Portugal, ſº. ". . . . . ." Go to his death, like a dumb Sacrifice Pº ºn 2 × . . . " Big him to ſave my life in ſaving thise. . . . . * … --- * Seb. Farewel, my life's not worth another word. . . . - Emp to the Guards. Perform your Orders, " : . . . . . .3 Alm. Stay, take my farewel too::, sº tº ºf tºº. Farewel the greatneſs of Almeyda's Sou!! iſ: cº º- Look, Tyrant, what exceſs of love can do, '' * . . . ; It pulls me down thus low, as to thy feet; iſ Kneel; to him, Nay to embrace thy Knees,with loathing hands, Tºgº tº Which bliſter when they touch thee: Yet ev'n thus, ºil ºff º' ... Thus far I can to ſave. Sebaſtian's life:21ſtººd. - - Emp, A ſecret pleaſure trickles through my Weins ::::::: - It works about the inlets of my Soul, º, … - To feel thy touch ; aſid pity tempts the paſs; r. º.º.º. tº But the tough metal of my heart reſiſts; 31 Tºcq: " : * > . 'Tis warm'd with the ſoft firé, wrot: melted down. º ºf Alm. A flood of ſcalding Tears will make it run, is º Spare him, Oh ſpare 5 canyou'pretendito love, . . . .” And have no pity P Love and that are Twins... ... º. ºilo º Here will I grow 5 ºr o: º f iſ ºri º bºob ºr Thus compaſs you with theſe ſupplanting Cords, º' at And pull ſo long till the proud Fabrick falls. - Emp. Stijl kneel, and ſtill embrace; 'tis double pleaſure So to be hugg’d, and ſee Sebaſtian dye. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Ala. Loºk Tyrant, when thou nam'ſt Sebaſtian's death; : Thy very Exccutioners turn pale, is ſº hºi º ºse ºf Rough as they are, and harden'd in the trade ' ' . Of Death, they ſtart at an anointed Head, . . . . 4. And - - - - >
Page 51

(.5i, ) And tremble to approach: He hears me not 3 Nor minds th’ impreſſion of a God on Kings; Becauſe no ſtamp of Heav'n was on his Souſ: But the reſiſting Maſs drove back the Seal. Say, though thy heart be rock of Adamant, it . . . Yet Rocks are not impregnable to Bribes: ... . . . . . . Inſtruct me how to bribe thee: Name thy price; Lo, I reſign my Title to the Crown; - -Send me to exile with the Man I love, And baniſhment is Empire. . . ... is . . . . . . . . . . . . . Emp. Here's my claim ; [Clapping his hand to his Sword. And this extinguiſh'd thine; thou giv'ſt me nothing. - Alm. My Father's, Mothers, Brothers death I pardon: That's ſomewhat ſure; a mighty Sum of Murther, Of innocent and kindred blood ſtrook off. . . . . . . . . My Prayers and Penance ſhall diſcount for theſe, tº . . . And beg of Heav'n to charge the Billon me: . . º. º. Behold what price I offer, and how dear . . º To buy Sebaſtian's life. - Emp. Let after reck’nings trouble fearful fools; , : .. I'll ſtand the tryal of thoſe trivial Crimes: ". But, ſince thou beg'ſt me to preſcribe my terms, ' ' ' ' ' ', The only I can offer are thy love; - And this one day of reſpite to reſolve. . . . Grant or deny, for thy next word is Fate; , And Fate is deaf to Pray’r. … . . . - Alm. May Heav'n be ſo . . . . . . . . . [Riſing up. At thy laſt breath to thine: I curſe theenot, For who can better curſe the Plague or Devil, Than to be what they are? That Curſe be thine. - Now, do not ſpeak Sebaſtian, for you need not, , But dye, for I reſign your Life: Look Heav'n, Almeyda dooms her dear Sebaſtian's death! But is there Heav'n, for I begin to doubt; - The Skyes are huſh'd; no grumbling Thunders roul: Now take your ſwing, ye impious 5. Sin unpuniſh'd; º Eternal providence ſeems overwatch'd, . . . . . . . . And with a ſlumb'ring Nod aſſents to Murther. - H 2. - Enter
Page 52

(52 ) Enter Dorax attended by three Soldiers. Emp. Thou mov'ſt a Tortoiſe pace to my relief. Take hence that, once a King; that ſullen pride That ſwells to dumbneſs 5 lay him in the Dungeon, And ſink him deep with Irons; that when he wou'd, He ſhall not groan to hearing, when I ſend The next Commands are death. - Alm. Then Prayers are vain as Curſes. Emp. Much at one In a Slaves mouth, againſt a Monarch's Pow’r. This day thou haſt to think ; At night, if thou wilt curſe, thou ſhalt curſe kindly; Then I'll provoke thy lips 5 lay fiege ſo cloſe, That all thy ſallying breath ſhall turn to Bleſſings. Make haſte, ſeize, force her, bear her hence. Alm. Farewel, my laſt Sebaſtian / I do not beg, Ichallenge Juſtice now ; O Pow’rs, if Kingsbe your peculiar care, Why plays this Wretch with your Prerogative? Now flaſh him dead, now crumble him to aſhes; Or henceforth live confin'd in your own Palace; And look not idely out upon a World That is no longer yours. - She is carried off ſtrugling, Emperour and Benducar follow. Sebaſtian ſtruggles in his Guards Arms, and ſhakes off one of them, but two others come in, and hold him ; he ſpeak, not aſ the while. Dor. I find I'm but a half-ſtrain’d Villain yet; [Aſide. But mungril-miſchievous 5 for my Blood boylid, - To view this brutalaćt; and my ſtern Soul Tug'J at my arm to draw in her defence. Down thou rebelling Chriſtian in my heart; "... Redeem thy fame on this Sebaſtian firſt 5 - Then think on others wrongs, when thine are righted. - [Walk, a turn. But
Page 53

(53 ) But how to right 'em? on a Slave diſarm'd, Defenceleſs, and ſubmitted to my rage 2 A baſe revenge is vengeance on my ſelf?' [walkſ again. I have it; and I thank thee, honeſt head, Thus preſent to me at my great neceſſity:- - [Comes up to Sebaſtian. You know me not? Sebaſt. I hear Men call thee Dorax. Dor. 'Tis well, you know enough for once: you ſpeak too; You were ſtruck mute before. . Sebaſt. Silence became me then. Dor. Yet we may talk hereafter. Seb. Hereafter is not mine : - Diſpatch thy work, good Executioner. Dor. None of my blood were hangmen; add that falſhood To a long Bill that yet remains unreckon'd. Seb. A King and thou can never have a reck'ning. Dor. A greater ſumm perhaps than you can pay. Mean time I ſhall make bold tincreaſe your debt, - - - (gives him his Sword) Take this, and uſe it at your greateſt need. Seb. This hand and this, have been acquainted well; (Looks on it.) - It ſhou'd have come before into my graſp, To kill the Raviſher. - Dor. Thou heardſt the Tyrants orders; Guard thy life When 'tis attack'd, and guard it like a Man. - Seb. I'm ſtill without thy meaning but I thank thee. Dor. Thank me when I ask thanks; thank me with that. Seb. Such ſurly kindneſs did I never ſee 1. (Dorax to the Captain of his Guard.) Muza, draw out a file, pick man by man, Such who dare dye, and dear will ſell their death. Guard him to th’ utmoſt 5 now condućt him hence, And treat him as my Perſon. * * Seb. Some-

End of Section 5. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 6
Page 54

* - • ( 54 ) . Seb. Something like That voice methinks I ſhou'd have ſomewhere heard : But floods of woes have hurry'd it far off; - Beyond my kenn of Soul. Dor. But I ſhall bring him back ungrateful Man, I ſhall, and ſet him full before thy fight, w When I ſhall front thee, like ſome ſtaring Ghoſt, - With all my wrongs about me. What ſo ſoon Return'd 2 This haſt is boding. - * > Enter to him Emperor, Benducar, Mufti. Emp. She's ſtill inexorable, ſtill Imperious 3 And loud, as if like Bacchus born in thunder. Be quick, ye falſe Phyſicians of my mind, Bring ſpeedy Death or Cure. - N. * Bend. What can be counſell'd while Sebaſtian lives 2. The Vine will cling, while the tall poplar ſtands: But that cut down creeps to the next ſupport, And twines as cloſely there. [Exit Sebaſtian with the Soldiers. [Solw. re- Emp. That's done with eaſe, I ſpeak him dead: proceed. Muf. Proclaim your Marriage with Almeyda next, That Civil Wars may ceaſe; this gains the Crowd; Then you may ſafely force her to your will: For People ſide with violence and injuſtice, When done for publick good. Emp, Preach thou that doćtrine. Bend. Th’ unreaſonable fool has broach'd a truth [Aſide. That blaſts my hopes; but ſince 'tis gone ſo far, He ſhall divulge Almeyda is a Chriſtian: If that produce no tumult I deſpair. Emp. Why ſpeaks not Dorax P JDor. Becauſe my Soul abhors to mix with him. Sir, ſet me bluntly ſay, you went too far To truſt the Preaching pow'r on State Affairs, ºr w To
Page 55

- ( 55 ) To him. ot any Heavenly Demagogue, - * . 'Tis a limb lopt from your Prerogative, - And ſo much of Heav'ns Image blotted from you. . .” ) Muf. Sure thou haſt never heard of Holy Men (So Chriſtians call 'em) fam'd in State Affairs; Such as in Spain Ximenes, Albornoz, * -- In England Woolſey; match me theſe with Laymen. Dorax. How you triumph in one or two of theſe, Born to be Stateſmen, hap'ning to be Church-men : Thou call ſt 'em holy 5 ſo their function was 5 But tell me, Mufti, which of 'em were Saints? . . . . Next, Sir, to you ; the ſumm of all is this; Since he claims pow'r from Heav'n, and not from Kings, When 'tis his int’reſt, he can int’reſt Heav'n To preach you down; and Ages oft depend On hours, uninterrupted, in the Chair. " Emp. I'll truſt his Preaching while I rule his pay. And I dare truſt my Affricans, to hear - Whatever he dare. Preach. - Dor. You know 'em not. The genius of your Moors is mutiny; - They ſcarcely want a Guide to move their madneſs: Prompt to rebel on every weak pretence, - Bluſtring when courted, crouching when oppreſt. Wiſe to themſelves, and fools to all the World. Reſtleſs in change, and perjur'd to a Proverb. They love Religion ſweetn'd to the ſenſe; A good, luxurious, palatable faith. - Thus Vice and Godlineſs, prepoſt'rous pair, Ride cheek by joul; but Churchmen hold the Reins, And, when ere Kings wou'd lower Clergy greatneſs, They learn too late what pow'r the Preachers have, And whoſe the Subječts are 5 the Mufti knows it; Nor dares deny what paſs'd betwixt us two. . - Emp, No more ; what ere he ſaid was by Command. - - ,- * * . . Dor. Why -
Page 56

(56) Dor. Why then no more, ſince you will hear no more; Some Kings are reſolute to their own ruin. Emp. Without your medling where you are not ask'd, Obey your Orders, and diſpatch Sebaſtian. - Dor. Truſt my revenge; be ſure I wiſh him dead. Emp. What mean'ſt thou ! what's thy wiſhing to my will; Diſpatch him, rid me of the Man I loath, Dor. I hear you Sir, I’ll take my time and do.'t — Emp. Thy time? what's all thy time, what's thy whole life To my-one hour of eaſe? no more replies, But ſee thou do'ſ it 5 Or — Dor. Choak in that threat: I can ſay Or, as loud. Emp. "Tis well, I ſee my words have no effect, But I may ſend a Meſſage to diſpoſe you. [It going off. Dor. Exped an anſwer worthy of that Meſſage. Muf. The Prophet ow'd him this: [Aſide. And thank'd be Heav'n, he has it. Bend. By Holy Alha, I conjure you ſtay, And judge not raſhly of ſo brave a Man. (Draws the Emperor aſide and whiffer, him.) I'll give you reaſons why he cannot execute Your Orders now, and why he will hereafter. Muf. Benducar is a fool to bring him off, [Aſide. I'll work my own revenge, and ſpeedily. . - Bend. The Fort is his, the Soldiers hearts are his 5 A thouſand Chriſtian Slaves are in the Caſtle, Which he can free to reinforce his pow'r, Your Troops far off, beleaguering Larache, Yet in the Chriſtians hands. - Emp. I grant all this 5 But grant me he muſt dye. Bend. He ſhall; by poyſon : . 'Tis here, the deadly drug prepar'd in powder, Hot as Hell-fire: then, to prevent his Soldiers. From riſing to revenge their Gen'rals death, While
Page 57

(57) sº While he is ſtruggling with his Mortal pangs, The Rabble on the ſudden may be rais'd to ſeize the Caſtle. - Emp. Dot 5 'tis left to thee. Bend. Yet more; but clear your brow 3 for he obſerves. (They whiſper again.) Dor. What will the Favºrite prop my falling fortunes, - O Prodigie of Court 1 - [Aſide. Emperor and Benducar return to Dorax. Emp. Your Friend has fully clear'd your Innocence; I was too haſty to condemn unheard, And you perhaps too |. in your replies. As far as fits the Majeſty of Kings, I ask excuſe. Dor. I'm ſure I meant it well. Emp. I know you did: — this to our love renew’d. – * [Emperor drink. Benducar fill to Dorax. Benducar turns and mixes a powder in it. Dor. Let it go round for all of us have need * To quench our heats; 'tis the Kings health Benducar. — [He drinks. And I wou'd pledge it though I knew 'twere poyſon. Bend. Another Bowl, for what the King has touch'd, - [Drinks out of another Bowl. And you have pledg'd, is ſacred to your loves.- - Muf. Since Charity becomes my calling, thus Let me provoke your friendſhip: and heav'n bleſs it As I intend it well. Drinks 3 and turning aſide pours ſome drops out of a little Pial into the Bowl; then preſents it to Dorax. Dor. Heav'n make thee honeſt, On that condition we ſhall ſoon be friends, – [Drinks. I - Mufti.
Page 58

- (58) - Muf. Yes, at our meeting in another World ; [Aſide. For thou haſt drunk thy paſsport out of this. Not the Nonacrian fount, nor Lethe's Lake, Cou'd ſooner numb thy nimble faculties Than this, to ſteep eternal. - Emp. Now farewel Dºrax ; this was our firſt quarrel, And I dare propheſie will prove our laſt, Exit Emperor with Benducar and the Mufti. Dor. It may be ſo: I'm ſtrangely diſcompos'd ; Quick ſhootings through my limbs, and pricking pains, Qualms at my heart, Convulſions in my nerves, Shiv'rings of cold, and burnings of my entrails Within my little World make medley War, Loſe and regain, beat and are beaten back; As momentary Vićtors quit their ground. Can it be poyſon poyſon's of one tenour, Or hot or cold 5 this neither, and yet both. Some deadly Draught, ſome enemy of life Boils in my bowels, and works out my Soul. Ingratitude's the growth of ev'ry Clime 3 Affrick, the Scene remov’d, is Portugal. Of all Court-ſervice learn the common lot 5 To day 'tis done, to morrow 'tis forgot. Oh were that all! my honeſt Corps muſt lye Expos'd to ſcorn, and publick Infamy : . - . My ſhameful Death will be divulg’d alone; . . The worth and honour of my Soul unknown. - - - [Exit. Scene
Page 59

(9) Scene 2. Is a Night Scene of the Mufti's Garden where an Arbour is diſcover'd. \ Enter Antonio. Amt. SH: names her ſelf Morayma; the Mufti's only Daugh. ter, and a Virgin l This is the time and place that ſhe appointed in her letter, yet ſhe comes not. Why thou ſweet delicious Creature, why to torture me with thy delay ! dar'ſ thou be falſe to thy Aſſignation? What, in the cool and ſilence of the night, and to a new Lover ? Pox on the Hypocrite thy Father , for inſtructing thee ſo little in the ſweeteſt point of his Religion. Hark, I hear the ruſtling of her Silk Mantle. Now ſhe comes 5 now ſhe comes; no, hang't, that was but the whiſtling of the wind through the Orange Trees. Now again, I hear the pit a pat of a pretty foot through the dark Alley : No, 'tis the Son of a Mare that's broken looſe and munching upon the Melons: — Oh the miſery of an expecting Lover ! Well I'll e'en deſpair, go into my Arbour, and try to ſleep 5 in a dream I ſhall enjoy her in deſpight of her. [Goes into the Arbour and lyes down. Enter Johayma wrapt up in a Mooriſh Mantle. job. Thus far my love has carry'd me, almoſt without my knowledg whither I was going : Shall I go on, ſhall I diſcover my ſelf — What an injury am I doing to my old Husband l — Yet what injury, ſince he's old, and has three Wives and ſix Concubines beſides me! 'Tis but ſtealing my own Tythe from him. - [She comes a little mearer the Arbour. Antonio raiſing himſelf a little and looking. At laſt ’tis ſhe : this is no illuſion I am ſure 5 'tis a true She- devil of Fleſh and Blood; and ſhe cou’d never] have taken a fitter time to tempt me. -- I 2 joh.
Page 60

º (60) - job. He's young and handſome. — Ant. Yes, well enough I thank nature. - [Aſde. joh. And I am yet neither old nor ugly ſure he will not refuſe me. Ant. No, thou mayſt pawn thy Maiden-head upon't he Wonnot. - [Aſide. joh. The Mufti wou'd feaſt himſelf upon other Women, and keep me faſting. Ant. O, the holy Curmudgeon? [Aſide. Joh. Wou’d Preach abſtinence, and practice luxury ! but I thank my Stars, I have edify'd more by his example than his precept. & Anton. Moſt divinely argu'd; ſhe's the beſt Caſuiſt in all Affrick, [Aſide, He ruſhes out and embraces her. I can hold no longer from embracing thee my dear Moray- ma: the old unconſcionable Whorſon thy Father, cou’d he exped cold chaſtity from a Child of his begetting? joh. What nonſenſe do you talk 2 do you take me for the Mufti's Daughter? - Ant. Why are you not Madam? [throwing off her Barnus. foh. I find you had an appointment with Morayma. Ant. By all that's good, the nauſeous Wife. [Aſide. joh. What you are confounded and ſtand mute?’ Amt. Somewhat nonpluſ! I confeſs 5 to hear you deny your name ſo poſitively; why are not you Morayma the Mufti's Daughter? Did not I ſee you with him, did not he preſent me to you? Were you not ſo charitable as to give me Mo: ney 2 Åy and to tread upon my foot, and ſqueeze my hand too, if I may be ſo bold to remember you of paſt favours. joh. And you ſee I am come to make 'em good, but I am neither Morayma nor the Mufti's Daughter. - Amt. Nay, I know not that: but I am ſure he is old enough to be your Father: and either Father, or Reverend Father, I heard you call him, - joh. Once
Page 61

( 61 ) johayma, Once again, how came you to name Morayma £ Ant. Another damn'd miſtake of mine: For, asking one of my fellow Slaves, who were the chief Ladies about the houſe 5 he anſwer'd me Morayma and johayma 5 but ſhe it ſeems is his Daughter, with a Pox to her, and you are his beloved Wife. joh. Say your beloved Miſtris, if you pleaſe 3 for that's the Title I deſire. This Moon-ſhine grows offenſive to my Eyes, come, ſhall we walk into the Arbor 2 There we may reëtifie all miſtakes. , - i Ant. That's cloſe and dark. job. And are thoſe faults to Lovers? . . Ant. But there I cannot pleaſe my ſelf, with the fight of your beauty. * ; Perhaps you may do better. Ant. But there's not a breath of air ſtirring. oh. The breath of Lovers is the ſweeteſt air; but you are fearful. - Ant. I am conſidering, indeed, that if I am taken with you.- … oh. The beſt way to avoid it, is to retire, where we may not be diſcover'd. r - Ant. Where lodges your Husband 2 - joh. Juſt againſt the face of this open Walk. Amt. Then he has ſeen us already, for ought I know. job. You make ſo many Difficulties, I fear I am diſpleaſing to you. - - 7. Amt. aſide. Iſ Morayma comes and takes me in the Arbor with her, I have made a fine exchange of that Diamond for this Pebble. - job. You are much ſaliſm off, let me tell you, from the fury of your firſt embrace. Ant. I confeſs, I was ſomewhat too furious at firſt, but you will forgive the tranſport of my paſſion ; now I have conſider'd it better, I have a qualm of Conſcience. - * joh. Of Conſcience Why, what has Conſcience to do with two young Lovers that have opportunity? - Ant. Why truly Conſcience is ſomething to blame for inter- poſing in our matters: But how can I help it, if I have a Scruple, to betray my Maſter? • jeh.
Page 62

( 6.2 ) joh. There muſt be ſomething more in it; for your Conſci. ence was very quiet when you took me for Morajma. Ant. I grant you, Madam, when I took you for his Daughter: For then I might have made you an honorable amends by Mar- II.3976. º, You Chriſtians are ſuch peeking Sinners, you tremble at a Shadow in the Moon-ſhine. Amt. And you Affricans are ſuch Termagants, you ſtop at nothing. I muſt be plain with you, you are married, and to a Holy Man, the Head of your Religion : Go back to your Chamber, go back, I ſay, and conſider of it for this night , as I will do on my part: I will be true to you, and invent all the Arguments I can to comply with you 5 and who knows, but at our next meeting, the ſweet Devil may have more power over me: I am true fleſh and blood, I can tell you that for your comfort. joh. Fleſh without blood I think thou art 3 or if any, 'tis as cold as that of Fiſhes. But I'll teach thee, to thy coſt, what Vengeance is in ſtore for refuſing a Lady, who has offer'd thee her Love: Help, Help, there; will nobody come to my aſſiſtance? Amt. What do you mean, Madam, for Heaven's ſake peace; your Husband will hear you; think of your own danger, if you will not think of mine. - joh. Ingrateful Wretch, thou deſerv'ſt no pity: Help, Help, Husband, or Iſhall be raviſh'd : The Villain will be too ſtrong for me. Help, help, for pity of a poor diſtreſſed Creature. Amt. Then I have nothing but impudence to aſſiſt me: I muſt drown her clamor what e'er comes on't. - He takes out his Flute, and plays as loud as he can poſſibly, and ſhe continues crying ont. Enter the Mufti in hiſ Night-gown, and two Servants. Mufti, O thou Villain, what horrible impiety art thou com. mitting? What raviſhing the Wife of my Boſom & Take him - - away,
Page 63

(63) away, ganch him, impale him, rid the World of ſuch a Monſter. - [Servants ſeize him. . Ant. Mercy, dear Maſter, Mercy: Hear me firſt, and after, if I have deſerved hanging, ſpare me not: What have you ſeen to provoke you to this cruelty? Mufti, I have heard the out-crys of my Wife; the bleatings of the poor innocent Lamb: Seen nothing, ſay'ſt thou? If I ſee the Lamb lye bleeding, and the Butcher by her with his Knife drawn and bloody, is not that evidence ſufficient of the Murther? I come too late, and the Execution is already done. Amt. Pray think in reaſon, Sir, is a Man to be put to death for a ſimilitude? No Violence has been committed 5 none in- tended: The Lamb's alive; and if I durſt tell you ſo, no more a Lamb than I am a Butcher. joh. How's that, Villain, dar'ſt thou accuſe me? Ant. Be patient Madam, and ſpeak but truth, and I'll do any thing to ſerve you: I ſay again, and ſwear it too, I'll do any thing to ſerve you. - joh, aſide. I underſtand him; but I fear, 'tis now too late to Pray hear him ſpeak, Husband 5 perhaps he may ſay ſomething for himſelf; I know not. Mufti, Speak thou, has he not violated my Bed and thy onor 2 joh. I forgive him freely 3 for he has done nothing : What he will do hereafter, to make me ſatisfaction, himſelf beſt knows. Amt. Any thing, anything, ſweet Madam: I ſhall refuſe no drudgery. Aſif. But, did he mean no miſchief? Was he endeavouring nothing? - joh. In my Conſcience, I begin to doubt he did not. Muf 'Tis impoſſible: Then what meant all thoſe out-crys? job. I heard Muſick in the Garden, and at an unſeaſonable time of night; and I ſtole ſoftly out of my Bed, as imagining it might be he. Muf. How's that johayma & Imagining it was he, and yet you went 2 - joh, fave him: ~
Page 64

- (64) joh. Why not, my Lord? Am not I the Miſtris of the Family 2 And is it not my place to ſee good Orders kept in it? I thought he might have allur'd ſome of the Shee-ſlaves to him; and was reſolv'd to prevent what might have been betwixt him and them 3 when on the ſudden he ruſh'd out upon me, caught me in his arms, with ſuch a fury. - Muf I have heard enough, away with him. oh. Miſtaking me, no doubt, for one of his fellow Slaves: With that, affrighted as I was, I diſcover'd myſelf, and cry’d aloud: But as ſoon as ever he knew me, the Villain let me go, and I muſt needs ſay, he ſtarted back, as if I were ſome Ser- pent; and was more afraid of methan I of him. Muf. Othou corrupter of my Family, that's cauſe enough of death; once again, away with him. job. What, for an intended Treſpaſs? No harm has been done, whatever may be. He coſt you five hundred Crowns I take it.— Muf. Thouſay'ſt true, avery conſiderable Sum: He ſhall not dye, tho he had committed folly with a Slave; 'tis too much to loſe by him. - Amt. My only fault has ever been to love playing in the dark, and the more ſhe cry'd, the more I play'd; that it might be ſeen I intended nothing to her. - Muf. To your Kennel, Sirrah, mortifie your fleſh, and con- ſider in whoſe Family you are. - joh. And one thing more; remember from henceforth to obey better. - Muſ, aſide. For all her ſmoothneſs, I am not quite cur'd of my Jealouſie; but I have thought of a way that will clear my doubts. ~ [Exit Mufti with Johayma and Servants, Ant. I am mortify'd ſufficiently already, without the help of his ghoſtly Counſel. Fear of Death has gone farther with me in two Minutes, than my Conſcience wou'd have gone in two Months. I find my ſelf in a very dejećted condition, all over me; poor Sinlyes dormant, Concupiſcence is retir'd to his win- - ter
Page 65

-** ( 65 ) ter qarters; and if Morayma ſhou'd now appear, I ſay no more, but alas for her and me! ( Morayma comes out of the Arbour; ſhe ſteals behind him, - and claps him on the back.) Morayma, And if Morayma ſhou'd appear, as ſhe does appear, alas you ſay for her and you! Antonio, Art thou there, my ſweet temptation my Eyes, my Life, my Soul, my all! ". . . . . Morayma, A. mighty Complement, when all theſe, by your own Confeſſion, are juſt nothing, e - Ant. Nothing, till thou cam'ſt to new create me; thou doſt not know the power of thy own Charms: let me embrace thee, and thou ſhalt ſee how quickly I can turn wicked. - Morayma ſtepping back. Nay, if you are ſo dangerous, 'tis beſt keeping you at a diſtance; I have no mind to warm a frozen Snake in my boſom; he may chance to recover, and ſting me for my a111S, º' - . . . . . p Ant. Conſider what I have ſuffer'd for thy ſake already; and make me ſome amends: two diſappointments in a night, O cruel Creature! . . . . . . . ºf . . . . Mor, And you may thank your ſelf for both : I came eagerly to the Charge, before my time, through the back walk behind the Arbour; and you, like a freſh-water Soldier, ſtood guarding the Paſs before: if you miſs'd the Enemy, you may thank your own dulneſs. . . . * - - Anton. Nay, if you will be uſing ſtratagems, you ſhall give me leave to make uſe of my advantages, now I have you in my power: we are fairly met; I'll try it out, and give no quarter. Mor. By your favour, Sir, we meet upon treaty now, and not upon defiance. -- Ant. If that be all, you ſhall have Carte blanche immediately; for I long to be ratifying. Mor. No, now I think on't, you are already enter'd into Articles with my Enemy fohayma : Anything to ſerve you Ma dam ; I ſhall refuſe no drudgery: whoſe words were thoſe. * * * . -** - - K Gentle.
Page 66

(, 66 ), Gentleman? was that like a Cavalier of honour? . Anton. Not very heroick; but ſelf preſervation is a point a. bove Honour and Religion too Antonio was a Roguc I muſt confeſs 3 but you muſt give me leave to love him. Mor. To beg your life ſo baſely 3 and to preſent your Sword to your Enemy; Oh Recreant! Ant. If I had died honourably, my fame indeed wou'd have ſounded loud, but I ſhou'd never have heard the blaſt : Come, don't make your ſelf worſe natur'd than you are: to ſave my life, you wou'd be content I ſhou’d promiſe any thing. Mor. Yes, if I were ſure you wou'd perform nothing. Amt. Can you ſuſpect I wou'd leave you for johayma £ Mor. No; but I can expect you wou'd have both of us: Love is covetous, I muſt have all of you; heart for heart is an equal truck. In ſhort, I am younger; I think handſomer; and am ſure I love you better, ſhe has been my ſtep-mother theſe fifteen years: you think . that's her face you ſec,but 'tis only a dawb'd Wizard: ſhe wears an Armour of proof upon’t : an inch thick of Paint, beſides the Waſh; her Face is ſo fortifi'd that you can make no approaches to it, without a Shovel. But for her conſtancy,I can tell you for your comfort, ſhe will love till death, I mean till yours : for when ſhe has worn you out ſhe will certainly diſpatch you to another world, for fear of telling tales; as ſhe has already ſerv'd three Slaves, your Predeceſſors of happy memory in her favours. She has made my pious Father a three pil’d Cuckold to my knewledg: and now the wou'd be robbing me of my ſingle : [OO. ſº Prithee prevent her then; and at leaſt take the ſhearing of me . Tirit. - Mor. No ; I'll have a Butchers Pen'worth of you; firſt ſecure the Carcaſs, and then take the fleece into the bargain. Ant. Why ſure, you did not put your ſelf and me to all this trouble, for a dry come off: by this hand ---- (taking it: ) Mor, Which you ſhall never touch; but upon better aſſurances than you imaginc. - (Puſling her hand away.) Ant. I'll marry thee, and make a Chriſtian of thee thou pretty damn'd Infidel. - Mor. I mean you ſhall: but no earneſt, till the bargain be made - before witneſs: there's love enough to be had, and as much as - you
Page 67

( 67 ) you can turn you to ; never doubt it, but all upon honourable ICrimS. - Ant. I vow and ſwear by Love; and he's a Deity ina!! Religions. Mor. But never to be truſted in any : he has another name too, of a worſe ſound. Shall I truſt an Oath, when I ſee your Eyes lan. guiſhing your Cheeks fluſhing,and can hear your heart throbbing? no, I'll not come near you: He's a fooliſh Phyſitian who will feel the pulſe of a Patient, that has the Plague ſpots upon him. Ant. Did one ever hear a little Moppet, argue ſo perverſly a- gainſt ſo good a Cauſe! Come, prithce, let me anticipate a little of my Revenue. Mor. You wou'd feign be fingring your Rents before-hand; but that makes a man an ill Husband ever after. Conſider, Mar- riage is a painful Vocation, as you ſhall prove it, manage your In- comes as thriftily as you can, you ſhall find a hard task on't, to make even at the years end, and yet to live decently. Ant. I came with a Chriſtian intention, to revenge my ſelf up- on thy Father; for being the head of a falſe Religion. Mor. And ſo you ſhall; I offer you his Daughter for your Se- cond : but ſince you are ſopreſſing, meet me under my Window, to morrow . body for body, about this hour; I'll ſlip down out of my Lodging, and bring my Father in my hand. Ant. How, thy Father! w Mor. I mean all that's good of him; his Pearls, and Jewels, his whole contents, his heart, and Soul; as much as ever I can carry. I'll leave him his Alchoran; that's revenue enough for him: every page of it is Gold and Diamonds. He has the turn of an Eyc, a demure Smile, and a godly Cant, that are worth Millions to him. I forgot to tell you, that I will have a Slave prep º', at the Poſtern gate, with two Horſes ready ſadled : no rº, for I fear, I may be miſs'd; and think I hear 'em calling for me, … if you have conſtancy and Courage. - Amt. Never doubt it: and love, in abundance to wander with thee all the World over. ( ke; ; – Mor. The value of twelve hundred thouſand Crowns in a Chſ. Ant. A heavy burden Heaven knows! but we muſi pray for pa- tience to ſupport it. K 2 Mor
Page 68

( 68 ) Mor. Beſides a willing Tift that will venture her Corps with you:-Come, I know you long to have a Parting blow with me; and therefore to ſhew I am in Charity— (He kiſſes her.) Ant. Once more, for pity; that i may keep the flavour upon my lips till we meet again. - - Aer. No 3 frequent Charities make bold Beggars; and beſides I have learnt of a Falconer, never to ſced up a Hawkwheni would have him fly: that's cnough but if you will be nibling, here's a hand to ſtay your ſtomach. (Kiſſing her hand) Aiton; Thus Conquer'd Infidels, that Wars may caſe, Are forci to give their hands, and ſign the Peace. Mºr. Thus Chriſtians are outwitted by the Foe; You had her in your Pow'r, and let her go. If you releaſe my hand, the fault's not mine; You ſhou'd have made me ſeal, as well as ſign. - -( - ** ºff, he follows her to the door; then comes back again, and goes out at the other. Aćt.

End of Section 6. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 7
Page 69

{ 69 ) A c T IV. Scene 1. Benducar's Pallace in the Caſtle of Alcazar. . Bend. Y future.Fate, the colour of my life, (Soluſ. My all depends on this important hour: This hour my Lott is weighing in the Scales, And Heav'n, perhaps, is doubting what to do. Aſmeyda and a Crown, have puſh'd me forward; 'Tis fix'd, the Tyrant muſt not raviſh her : He and Sebaſtian ſtand betwixt my hopes; He moſt; and therefore firſt to be diſpatch'd. Theſe and a thouſand things are to be done In the ſhort compaſs of this rowling Night, And nothing yet pcrform'd, None of my Emiſſaries yet return'd. Enter Haly— Firſt Servant. Oh Haly, thou haſt held me long in pain. What haſt thou learnt of Dorax P is he dead 2 - Haly, Two hours I warily have watch'd his Palace;. All doors are ſhut, no Servant peeps abroad; ‘ Some Officers with ſtriding leaſt paſs'd in, - While others outward went on quick diſpatch ; * ... * * Sometimes huſh'd ſilence ſeem'd to reign within; Then Cries confus'd, and a joint clamour follow'd : * Then Lights went gliding by, from room to room, - And ſhot like thwarting Meteors croſs the houſe: Not daring farther to enquire : I came - With ſpeed, to bring you this imperſed news. V. Bend..
Page 70

( zo) Bend. Hence I conclude him either dpad or dying: His mournful Friends, ſummon'd to také their leaves, Are throng’d about his Couch, and fit in Council, What thoſe Caballing Captains may deſign, I muſt prevent, By being firſt in Aćtion. . . To Muley Zeydan fly with ſpeed, deſire him . To take my laſt inſtrućtions; tell th’ importance - And haſt his preſence here. (Exit Haly. How has this Poiſon loſt its wonted way? It ſhou'd have burnt its paſſage, not have linger'd In the blind Labyrinths and crooked turnings Of human Compoſition; now it moves Like a ſlow Fire that works againſt the Wind, As if his ſtronger Stars had interpos'd. Enter Hamet. Well Hamet, are our Friends the Rabble rais'd : From Muſtafa, what Meſſage 2 - Hamet, What you wiſh: The ſtreets are thicker in this noon of Night: Than at the Mid-day Sun: a drowzy horrour Sits on their Eyes, like fear not well awake, , All crowd in heaps, as at a Night Alarm --- The Bees drive out upon each others backs, - * Tº imboſs their Hives in cluſters; all ask news: Their buſie Captain runs the weary round To whiſper Orders; and commanding ſilences Makes not noiſe ceaſe ; but deafens it to murmurs. . Bend. Night waſts apacc: when, when will he appear? Hamet, He only waits your Summons. Bend. Haſt their coming. - Let ſecrecy and ſilence be enjoin'd c In their cloſe march : what news from the Lieutenant 2 Hamet, I left him at the Gate, firm to your Intereſt, Tº admit the Townſmen at their firſt appearance. Bend.
Page 71

(71) - Bend. Thus far ’tis well; go haſten Muſtafa. - - (Exit Ham. Enter Orchan the Third Servant. . O, Orchan, did I think thy diligence Wou'd lag behind the reſt ? what from the Mufti & Orchan, I ſought him round his Palace; made enquiry Of all the Slaves: in ſhort, I us'd your name And urg'd th’ importance home; but had for anſwer That ſince the ſhut of Evening none had ſeen him. Bend. O the curſt fate of all Conſpiracies! They move on many Springs, if one but fail The reſtiff Machine ſtops.- In an ill hour he's abſent; Tis the firſt time, and ſure will be the laſt That e'er a Mufti was not in the way, When Tumult and Rebellion ſhou'd be broach'd. Stay by me; thou art reſolute and faithful; I have Employment worthy of thy Arm. (Walfº, • -- Enter Muley Zeydan. Cº. ºf . Muley Zeyd. You ſee me come impatient of my hopes, And eager as the Courſer for the Race: . . " Is all in readineſs? - Bend. All but the Mufti. Mul. Zeyd. We muſt go on without him. Bend. True we muſt; For 'tis ill ſtopping in the full Career, - How e'er the leap be dangerous and wide. - Orchan looking out. I ſee the blaze of Torches from afar; . And hear the trampling of thick beating feet; This way they move. - Bend. No doubt the Emperour. We muſt not be ſurpriz'd in Conference. Truſt to my management the Tyrants death; * And:
Page 72

( 72 ) And haſt your ſelf to join with Muſtafa. The Officer who guards the Gate is yours; When you have gain'd that Paſs, divide your Force; Your ſelf in Perſon laead one choſen half, And march tº oppreſs the Fa&ion in Conſult With dying Dorax: Fate has driv'n 'em all Into the Net: you muſt be bold and ſudden: Spare none, and if you find him ſtrugling yet With pangs of Death, truſt not his rowling Eyes - And heaving gaſps; for Poiſon may be falſe, The home-thruſt of a friendly Sword is ſure. Mul. Zeyd Doubt not my Condućt: they ſhall be ſurpriz'd; Mercy may wait without the Gate one Night, At Morn l'Il take her in. — Bend. Here lies your way, You meet your Brother there. . . Mul. Zeyd. May we ne'er meet : For, like the Twins of Leda, when I mount. He gallops down the Skies. Exit Muley Zeyd. Bend. He comes: now Heart - Be ribº with Iron for this one attempt: Set ope thy Sluces, ſend the vigorous bloud Through every ačtive Limb for my relief: Then, take thy reſt within thy quiet Cell, For thou ſhalt drum no more. Enter Mulcy Moluch and Guards attending him. Mul. Mol. What news of our Affairs, and what of Dorax & Is h; no more ſay that, and make me happy. ... Bend. May all your Enemies bei like that Dog, Whoſe parting Soul is labring at the Lips. Mul, Mol. The People, are they rais'd 2 Bend. And Marſhall'd too; Juſt ready for the March. Mul, Mol. Then I’m at eaſe. Bend.
Page 73

(73) Bend. The Night is yours, the glitt'ring Hoaſt of Heav'n Shines but for you; but moſt the Star of Love, That twinckles you to fair Almeyda's Bed. Oh there's a joy, to melt in her embrace, Diſſolve in pleaſures; - - - And make the gods curſe Immortality, That ſo they cou’d not dye. But haſte, and make 'em yours. Mul, Mol. I will; and yet A kind of weight hangsheavy at my Heart; My flagging Soul flyes under her own pitch; Like Fowl in air too damp, and lugs along, As if ſhe were a body in a body, And not a mounting ſubſtance made of Fire. My Senſes too are dull and ſtupifi’d, Their edge rebated 5 ſure ſome ill approaches, And ſome kind Spirit knocks ſoftly at my Soul, To tell me Fate's at hand. - Bend. Mere Fancies all. .. Your Soul has been beforehand with your Body, And drunk ſo deep a Draught of promis'd bliſs, She ſlumbers o'er the Cup 5 no danger's near, But of a Surfeit at too fulla Feaſt, - !. Mul. Mol. It may be ſo; it looks ſo like the Dream That overtook meat my waking hour.' . . . . . . . . . . This Morn; and Dreams they ſay are then divine, When all the balmy Vapors are exhal’d, , - . And ſome o'er-pow'ring God continues ſleep. - 'Twas then methought Almeyda, ſmiling, came . . . Attended with a Train of all her Race, - Whom in the rage of Empire I had murther'd. But now, no longer Foes, they gave me Joy Of my new Conqueſt, and with helping hands . Heav'd me into our Holy Prophet's arms, - - Who bore me in a purple Cloud to Heav'n. A Bend. Good Omen, Sir, I wiſh you in that Heaven; Your Dream portends you. - t Which preſages death- [Aſide. - L ! Mul. .
Page 74

- ( 74 ) Mul, Mol. Thou too wert there; * - - And thou methought didſt puſh me from below, With thy full force to Paradiſe. Bend. Yet better. - Mul. Mol. Ha! What's that grizly Fellow that attends thee * Bend. Why ask you Sir 2 Mul, Mol. For he was in my Dream; And help'd to heave me up. Bºnd. With Pray'rs and Wiſhes; For I dare ſwear him honeſt. Mul. Mol. That may be 5 But yet he looks Damnation. Bend. You forget, - The Face wou'd pleaſe you better: Do you love, And can you thus forbear 2 Mul, Mol. I'll head my People; Then think of dalliance, when the danger's o'er. .. My warlike Spirits work now another way 5. And my Soul's tun'd to Trumpets. . . Bend. You debaſe your ſelf,' ' ' ' . To think of mixing with th' ignoble Herd. Let ſuch perform the ſervile Work of War, Such who have no Almeyda to enjoy. - * * What ſhall the People know their God-like Prince . . . . Skulk'd in a nightly Skirmiſh P. Stole a Conqueſt, - Headed a Rabble, and profan'd his Perſon, : " ' tº Shoulder'd with Filth, born in a tide of Ordure, ' ' Gº And ſtified with their rank offenſive Sweat 2 º'- - Mºl. Mol. I am off again: I will not proſtitute The Regal Dignity ſo far, to head'ém, oº'ſ fºr Bºnd. There ſpoke a King. eiº Hº tº ºil . Diſmiſs your Guards to be employ'd elſewhere {a ruder Combats: You will want no Seconds. In thoſe Alarms you ſeek. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Mul, Mol. Go joyn the Crowd 30ſo gº ºf [to the Guard. Fem.lucar, thou ſhalt lead’em, in thy place. “DExetent Guardſ, The Cod of Love once more has ſhot his Fires, . . . i – tº . . . . . Into --- - * º- J • * * *
Page 75

(75 ) Into my Soul; and my whole Heart receives him. Almeyda now returns with all her Charms; I feel her as ſhe glides along my Weins, And dances in my Blood: So when our Prophet ' Had long been ham'ring in his lonely Cell, Some dull, inſipid, tedious Paradiſe, - A brisk Arabian Girl came tripping by; Paſſing ſhe caſt at him a ſide-long glance, And look'd behind in hopes to be purſu'd : He took the hint, embrac'd the flying Fair; - - And having found his Heav'n, he fix’d it there. [Exit Mul, Mol. Bend. That Paradiſe thou never ſhalt poſſeſs. His death is eaſie now, his Guards are gone; And I can ſin but once to ſeize the Throne, All after Aćts are ſančtify’d by pow'r. Orchan. Command my Sword and Life. Bend. I thank thee Orchan, And ſhall reward thy Faith: This Maſter Key Frees every Lock, and leads us to his Perſon: And ſhou’d we miſs our blow, as Heav'n forbid, Secures retreat : Leave open all behind us; And firſt ſet wide the Mufti's Garden Gate, Which is his private paſſage to the Palace: For there our Mutineers appoint to meet, And thence we may have aid. Now ſleep ye Stars That filently o'erwatch the fate of Kings; Be all propitious Influences barr'd, And none but murd’rous Planets mount the Guard. - [Exit with Orchan. A Night Scene of the Mufti's Garden. Enter the Mufti alone, in a Slave's habit, like that of Antonio. Mufti, This 'tis to have a ſound Head pieces by this I have . . . got to be chief of my Religion; that is, honeſtly ſpeaking, to teach others what I neither know nor believe myſelf. For L 2. - What's :
Page 76

(76) - - what's Mahomet to me, but that I get by him 2 Now for my Policy of this night: I have mew'd up my ſuſpected spouſé in her Chamber. No more Embaſſies to that luſty young Stallion of a Gardiner. Next my habit of a Slave; I have made myſelf as like him as I can, all but his youth and vigor; which when I had, I paſs'd my time as well as any of my Holy Predeceſſors. Now walking under the Windows of my Serag- lio, if johgma look out, ſhe will certainly take me for . mio, and call to me 5 and by that I ſhall know what Concupiſ- cence is working in her; ſhe cannot come down to COmmit Igiquity, thºre's my ſafety; but if ſhe peep, if ſhe put her Noſe abroad, there's demonſtration of her pious Wilſ: And I'll not make the firſt precedent for a Church-man to forgive Injuries. - Enter Morayma running to him with a Casket in her hand, and embracing him. - Mor. Now I can embrace you with a good Conſcience; here are the Pearls and Jewels, here's my Father. º Muf. I am indeed thy Father; but how the Devil didſt thou know me in this diſguiſe? And what Pearls and Jewels doſt thou mean? - Mor, going back—What have I done, and what will now - become of me ! Muf. Art thou mad, Morajma £ Mor. I think you'll make me ſo. Muf. Why, what have I done to thee? Recolled thy ſelf, and ſpeak ſenſe to me. Mor. Then give me leave to tell you, you are the worſt of Fathers. - .. . . . . . . . . Mºf Did I thinkſ had begotten ſuch a Monſter? proceed my dutiful Child, proceed, proceed. - Mor. You have been raking together a maſs of Wealth, by indirect and wicked means 5 the Spoils of Orphans are in theſe Jewels, and the Tears of Widows in theſe Pearls." Muf. Thou amazeſt me ! Mor. I
Page 77

(77) Mor. I wou'd do ſo. This Casket is loaded with your Sins; 'tis the Cargo of Rapines, Simony, and Extortions; the Ini- quity of thirty Years Muftiſhip, converted into Diamonds. Muf Wou'd ſome rich rayling Rogue would ſay as much to me, that I might ſqueeze his Purſe for ſcandal. - Mor. No Sir, you get more by pious Fools than Raylers, when you inſinuate into their Families, manage their Fortunes while they live, and beggar their Heirs by getting Legacies when they dye. And do you think I'll be the receiver of your Theft? I diſcharge my Conſcience of it: Here take again your filthy Mammon, and reſtore it you had beſt to the true Owners. Muf. I am finely documented by my own Daughter. Mor. And a great credit for me to be ſo: Do but think how decent a Habit you have on, and how becoming your "Funètion to be diſguis'd like a Slave, and eves-dropping un- der the Womens Windows, to be ſaluted, as you deſerve it richly, with a Piſs-pot: If I had not known you caſually by your ſhambling gate, and a certain reverend awkardneſs that is natural to all of your Function, here you had been. expos'd to the laughter of your own Servants; who have been in ſearch of you through your whole Seraglio, peep- ing under every Petticoat to find you. Muf. Prithee Child reproach me no more of human Failings; they are but a little of the pitch and ſpots of the World. that are ſtill ſticking on me 5 but I hope to ſcour 'em out in time: I am better at bottom than thou think'ſt 5 I am not the Man thou tak'ſt me for. - Mor. No, to my ſorrow Sir you are not. Muf. It was a very odd beginning, tho methought, to ſee thee come running in upon me with ſuch a warm embrace 3 prithee what was the meaning of that violent hot Hugº , Mor. I am ſure I meant nothing by it, but the zeal and afteåion which I bear to the Man of the World, whom I may love lawfully. - Muf But thou wilt not teach me at this age the nature of a cloſe Embrace 2 -- - - Mor. *
Page 78

z - ( 78 ) w ... Mor. No indeed 5 for my Mother in Law complains, that you are paſt teaching: But if you miſtook my innocent Embrace for Sin, I wiſh heartily it had been given where it wou’d have been more acceptable. - - Muf. Why, this is as it ſhou'd be now : Take the Trea- ſure again, it can never be put into better hands. - Mor. Yes, to my knowledg but it might. I have confeſs'd my Soul to you, if you can underſtand me rightly ; I never- diſobey'd you till this night, and now ſince through the vio- Jence of my Paſſion, I have been ſo unfortunate, I humbly beg your pardon, your bleſſing, and yºur leave, that upon the firſt opportunity I may go for ever from your ſight 5. for Heaven knows, I never deſire to ſee you more. - Muf Wiping his Eyes. Thou makit me weep at thy un- kindneſs ; indeed dear Daughter we will not part. Mor. Indeed dear Daddy but we will. Muf. Why if I have been a little pilfering, or ſo, I take it bitterly of thee to tell me of it 5 ſuice it was to make thee rich ; and I hope a Man may make bold with his own Soul, without offence to his own Child: Here take the jewels again, take 'em I charge thee upon thy Obedience. Mor. Well then, in vertue of Obedience I will take 'em 5 but on my Soul, I had rather they were in a better hand. Muf. Meaning mine, I know it. Mor. Meaning his whom I love better than my life. Mif. That's me again. - Mor. I wou'd have you think ſo. * Muf. How thy good nature works upon me; well I can do no leſs than venture damning for thee, and 1 may put fair for it, if the Rabble be order'd to riſe to Night. Enter Antonio in an Affrican rich habit. Ant. What do you mean my Dear, to ſtand talking in this ſuſpicious place, juſt underneath Johayma's Window 2 (to the Mufti). You are well met Comerade, I know you are the friend of our flight? are the horſes ready at the poſtern gate? - - Muf.
Page 79

( 79 ) Muf, Antonio, and in diſguiſe! now I begin to ſmell a rat. Amt. And I another, that out-ſtinks it 5 falſe Morayma, haſt thou thus betray'd me to thy Father - Mor. Alas, I was betray'd my ſelf: He came diſguis'd like you, and I poor Innocent ran into his hands. Muf. In good time you did ſo ; I laid a trap for a Bitch Fox, and a worſe Vermine has caught himſelf in it: you wou'd fain break looſe now, though you left a limb behind you; but I am yet in my own Territories and in call of Company, that's my comfort. - [Antonio, taking him by the throat. No 3 I have a trick left to put thee paſt thy ſqueeking : I have giv'n thee the quinzey ; that ungracious tongue ſhall Preach no more falſe Dočtrin. - Mor. What do you mean? you will not throttle him 2 con- ſider he's my Father. - Amt. Prithee let us provide firſt for our own ſafety; if I do not conſider him, he will conſider us with a vengeance afterwards. - * . - . . Mor. You may threaten him for crying out, but for my ſake give him back a little cranny of his Wind-pipe, and ſome part of Speech. - - - Amt. Not ſo much as one ſingle Interjećtion : Come away Father-in-Law, this is no place for Dialogues, when you are in the Moſque you talk by hours, and there no Man muſt in- terrupt you ; this is but like for like, good Father-in-Law 5 now I am in the Pulpit 'tis your turn to hold your tongue. . - - [He ſtruggler. Nay if you will be hanging back, I ſhall take care you ſhall hang forward. -. - (Pulls him along the Stage; with his Sword at his reins.) Mor. T'other way to the Arbour with him; and make haſt. before we are diſcover'd. -. * , , - Azt.
Page 80

(8o ) Amt. If I only bind and gag him there, he may commend me hereafter for civil uſage 3 he deſerves not ſo much favour by any ačtion of his life. Mor. Yes, pray bate him one, for begetting your Miſtreſ. Amt. I wou'd, if he had not thought more of thy Mother than of thee; once more come along in ſilence, my Pythago- rean Father-in-Law. - joh. At the Balcony. — A Bird in a Cage may peep at leaſt; though ſhe muſt not fly; what buſtle's there beneath my Win- dow 2 Amtomio by all my hopes, I know him by his habit; but ... what makes that Woman with him, and a Friend, a Sword drawn, and haſting hence? this is no time for ſilence: Who's within, call there, where are the Servants, why Omar, Abedin, Haſan and the reſt, make haſt and run into the Garden; there are Thieves and Villains 5 arm all the Family, and ſtop 'em. - - [Antonio turning back. O that Schriech Owl at the Window ! we ſhall be purſu'd immediatly 3 which way ſhall we take 2 (Morayma giving him the Casket.) 'Tis impoſſible to eſcape them ; for the way to our Horſes 1yes back again by the Houſe 5 and then we ſhall meet 'em full in the teeth 5 here take theſe Jewels 3 thou may’ſ leap the Walls and get away. Amt. And what will become of thee then poor kind Soul ? Mor. I muſt take my fortune 5 when you are got ſafe into your own Country, I hope you will beſtow a figh on the me. mory of her who lov'd you ! - Amt. It makes me mad, to think how many a good night will be loſt betwixt us! take back thy Jewels 5 'tis an empty Casket without thee 3 beſides I ſhou'd never leap well with the weight of all thy Fathers ſins about me, thou and they had been a bargain. º . Mor. Prithee take 'em, 'twill help me to be reveng'd on him. Amt. No 3 they'll ſerve to make thy peace with him. Mor.
Page 81

( 81 ) Mor. I hear 'em coming; ſhift for your ſelf at leaſt , re- member I am yours for ever. - (Servant, crying this way, this way, behind the Scene) - Aut. And I but the empty ſhadow of my ſelf without thee! farewel Father-in-Law, that ſhou'd have been, if I had not been curſt in my M thers belly — Now which way fortune.— . " (Runs amazedly backwards and forwards.) Servants within. Follow, follow, yonder are the Villains. Ant. O here's a gate open; but it leads into the Caſtle; yet I muſt venture it. - [Going out. (A ſhout behind the Scenes where Antonio is going out) , Amt. There's the Rabble in a Mutiny; what is the Devil up at Midnight! — however 'tis good herding in a Crowd. [Runs out. (Mufti runs to Morayma and lays hold on her, then ſnatches away the Casket.) Muf. Now, to do things in order, firſt I ſeize upon the Bag, and then upon the Baggage: for thou art but my fleſh and . blood, but theſe are my Life and Soul. -- Mor. Then let me follow my fleſh and blood, and keep to your felf your Life and Soul. - Muf. Both or none 5 come away to durance. - Mor. Well, if it muſt be ſo, agreed 5 for I have another trick to play you; and thank your ſelf for what ſhall follow. [Enter Servants. joh. From above. One of them took through the private way into the Caſtle; follow him be ſure, for theſe are yours already. - - Mor. Help here quickly Omar Abedin; I have hold on the Villain that ſtole my jewels; but 'tis a luſty Rogue, and he will prove too ſtrong for me; what, help I ſay, do you not know your Maſters Daughter? - M Mºf.
Page 82

( 82 ) Muf. Now if I cry out they will know my voices and then I am diſgrac'd for ever : Othou art a venomous Cock- atricel - - Mor. Of your own begetting. ... [The Servants ſeize him. Firſt Servant. What a glorious deliverance have you had Madam from this bloody-minded Chriſtian | Mor. Give me back my Jewels, and carry this notorious Malefactor to be puniſh’d by my Father. I'll hunt the other dry-foot. , , (Takes the jewel, and runs out after Antonio at the ſame Paſſage.) Firſt Servant. I long to be handſelling his hide, before we bring him to my Maſter. - Second Servant. Hang him, for an old Covetous Hypocrite: : deſerves a worſe puniſhment himſelf for keeping us ſo ardly. Firſt Servant. Ay, wou'd he were in this Villains place; thus I wou'd lay him on, and thus. - - [Beats him. Second Servant. And thus wou'd I revenge my ſelf of my laſt beating, (He beats him too, and then the ref.) Muf. Oh, oh, oh! . . . . . Firſt Servant. Now ſuppoſing you were the Mufti, Sir, – - * at him again. Mºf The Devil's in that ſuppoſing Raſcal; I can bear no more 5 and I am the Mufti : Now ſuppoſe your ſelves my Servants, and hold your hands; an anointed halter take you all. - Firſt Servant. My Maſter! you will pardon the exceſs of our zeal for you, Sir, indeed we all took you for a Villain, and ſo we us'd you. - Mufti, Ay ſo I feel you did 5 my back and fides are abun. dant teſtimonies of your zeal. Run Rogues, and bring me back my Jewels, and my Fugitive Daughter: run I ſay. Tw º
Page 83

(8; ) (They run to the Gate and the firſt Servant runs back again.) -,-,- Firſt Servant. Sir, the Caſtle is in a moſt terrible combu- ſtion; you may hear 'em hither. - Muf "Tis a laudable commotion: The voice of the Mobile is the voice of Heaven. I muſt retire a little, to ſtrip me of the Slave, and to aſſume the Mufti; and then I will return : for the piety of the People muſt be encouraged; that they may help me to recover my Jewels, and my Daughter. - - Exit Mufti and Servants. Scene changes to the Caſtle-yard, and diſcovers Antonio Muſta- fa, and the Rabble ſhouting, they come forward. Amt. And ſo at length, as I inform'd you, I eſcap'd out of his covetous clutches; and now fly to your illuſtrious feet for my protećtion. - Muft. Thou ſhalt have it, and now defie the Mufti. 'Tis the firſt Petition that has been made to me ſince my exaltation to Tumult; in this ſecond Night of the Month Abib, and in the year of the Hegyra; the Lord knows what year; but 'tis no matter; for when I am ſettled, the Learned are bound to find it out for me: for I am reſolv'd to date my Authority over the Rabble, like other Monarchs. Amt. I have always had a longing to be yours again; though I cou’d not compaſs it before, and had deſign'd you a Casket of my Maſters jewels too; for I knew the Cuſtom, and wou'd not have appear'd before a Great Perſon, as you are, without a preſent: But he has defrauded my good intentions, and baſe- ly robb'd you of 'em, 'tis a prize worth a Million of Crowns, and you carry your Letters of mark about you. Muft. I ſhall make bold with his Treaſure, for the ſupport of my New Government. [The People gather about him. What do theſe vile Ragga-muffins ſo near our Perſon 3 your ſa- vouris offenſive to us; bear back there, and make room for ho- neſt Mento approach us; theſe fools and knaves are always in- M 2 pudently
Page 84

( 84 ) pudently crowding next to Princes, and keeping off the more deſerving, bear back I ſay. - [They make a wider Circle. That's dutifully done; now ſhout to ſhow your Loyalty. (A great ſhout.) Hear'ſt thou that, Slave Antonio 2 theſe obſtre. perous Villains ſhout, and know not for what they make a noiſe. You ſhall ſee me manage 'em, that you may judge what ignorant Beaſts they are. For whom do you ſhout now 2 who's to Live and Reign º tell me that the wiſeſt of "Oll. G - y Firſt Rabble. Even who you pleaſe Captain. Muſi. La you there; I told you ſo. Second Rabble. We are not bound to know who is to Live and Reign; our buſineſs is only to riſe upon command, and plunder. - Third Rabble, Ay, the Richeſt of both Parties; for they are our Enemies. º - Mºſt. This laſt Fellow is a little more ſenſible than the reſt; he has enter'd ſomewhat into the merits of the Cauſe. Firſt Rabble. If a poor Man may ſpeak his mind, I think, Captain, that your ſelf are the fitteſt to Live and Reign, I mean not over, but next and immediatly under the People; and thereupon I ſay, A Muſtafa, A Muſtafa. - (All Cry) A Muſtafa, A Muſtafa. - ** Muft. I muſt confeſs the ſound is pleaſing, and tickles the ears of my Ambition; but alas good People, it muſt not be I am contented to be a poor ſimple Vice-Roy ; but Prince Mu- ley-Zeydan is to be the Man: I ſhall take care to inſtrućt him in the arts of Government 5 and in his duty to us all : and therefore mark my Cry: A Muley-Zeydan, A Muley Zeydam. (All Cry) A Muley-Zeydan, A Muley-Zeydan. . Muft. You ſee Slave Antonio, what I might have been. Antonio. I obſerve your Modeſty. Muft. But for a fooliſh promiſe I made once to my Lord Bendºcar, to ſet up any one he pleas'd, . . . . Re-enter
Page 85

{ 85 ) (Reenter the Muñi with his Servants.) r Ant. Here's the Old Hypocrite again ; now ſtand your ound, and bate him not an inch. Remember the Jewels, the Rich and Glorious Jewels; they are deſtin'd to be yours, by virtue of Prerogative. - Maff. Let me alone to pick a quarrel, I have an old grudge to him upon thy account. - º | - (Mufti, making up to the Mobile.) Good People, here you are met together. Firſt Rabble. Ay, we know that without your telling, but why are we met together, Dočtor? for that's it which no body here can tell. - Second Rabble. Why to ſee one another in the Dark; and to make Holy-day at Midnight. * - Muf. You are met, as becomes good Muſulmen; to ſettle the Nation 5 for I muſt tell you, that though your Tyrant is a lawful Emperor, yet your lawful Emperor is but a Tyrant. Aut. What ſtuff he talks! * - - - Muft. "Tis excellent fine matter indeed, Slave Antonio; he has a rare tongue; Oh, he wou'd move a Rock of Elephant!” Amt. Aſide. What a Block have I to work upon, [To him. But ſtill remember the Jewels, Sir, the Jewels. Muft. Nay that's true on t'other fide: the Jewels muſt be mine; but he has a pure fine way of talking 5 my Conſcience goes along with him, but the Jewels have ſet my heart againſt him. Muf. That your Emperor is a Tyrant is moſt manifeſt 5 for you were born to be Turks, but he has play'd the Tark with you 5 and is taking your Religion away. w Second Rabble. We find that in our decay of Trade; I have ſeen for theſe hunder'd years, that Religion and Trade always go together. N ... " Mufti.
Page 86

(86 ) Mufti. He is now upon the point of Marrying himſelf, without your Sovereign conſent ; and what are the effects of Marriage 2 - Third Rabble. A ſcoulding, domineering Wife, if ſhe prove honeſt; and if a Whore, a fine gawdy Minx, that robs our Counters every Night, and then goes out, and ſpends it upon our Cuckold-makers. Mufti. No, the natural effects of Marriage are Children: Now on whom wou'd he beget theſe Children? Even upon a Chriſtian | Oh horrible; how can you believe me, though. I am ready to ſwear it upon the Alcoran | Yes, true Believ- ers, you may believe me, that he is going to beget a Race •of Misbelievers. ------ -- Muft. That's fine, in earneſt; I cannot forbear hearkening to his enchanting Tongue. - - Ant. But yet remember, Muſt, Ay, Ay, the Jewels l Now again I hate him ; but yet my Conſcience makes me liſten to him. Mufti, Therefore to conclude all, Believers, pluck up your Hearts, and pluck down the Tyrant: Remember the Courage of your Anceſtors; remember the Majeſty of the People 5 re- member your ſelves, your Wives and Children; and laſtly, above all, remember your Religion, and our holy Mahomet; all theſe require your timous aſſiſtance; ſhall I ſay they begit? No, they claim it of you, by all the neareſt and deareſt Tyes of theſe three P's Self-Preſervation, our Property, and our Pro- ‘phet. Now anſwer me with an unanimous chearful Cry, and follow me, who am your Leader to a glorious Deliverance. (All cry, A Mufti, A Mufti, and are following him off the Stage.) Amt. Now you ſee what comes of your fooliſh Qualms of ‘Conſcience: The Jewels are loſt, and they are all leaving you. Muft. Whatam I forſaken of my Subjećts? Wou'd the Rogue purloin my liege People fromènel I charge you in my own Name come back ye Deſerters; and hear me ſpeak, 1ſt. Rabble, What will he come with his Balderdaſh, after the Mufti's eloquent Oration 2 - - 2d. Rabble,
Page 87

( 87 ) 2d. Rabble, He's our Captain, lawfully pick'd up, and elečted upon a Stall; we will hear him. Omnes, Speak Captain, for we will hear you. Muſt. Do you remember the glorious Rapines and Robbe- ries you have committed 2 Your breaking open and gutting: of Houſes, your rummaging of Cellars, your demoliſhing of Chriſtian Temples, and bearing off in triumph the ſuperſtitious Plate and Pićtures, the Ornaments of their wicked Altars, when all rich Moveables were ſentenc'd for idolatrous, and all that was idolatrous was ſeiz'd? Anſwer firſt for your remem- brance, of all theſe ſweetneſſes of Mutiny; for upon thoſe Grounds I ſhall proceed. Ommer, Yes we do remember, we do remember. - Muft. Then make much of your retentive Faculties. And who led you to thoſe Hony-Combs & Your Mufti & No, Be. lievers, he only preach'd you up to it; but durſt not lead you; he was but your Counſellor, but I was your Captain; he only lood you, but 'twas I that led you. - Omnes, That's true, that's true. Ant. There you were with him for his Figures. Muft. I think I was, Slave Antonio. Alas I was ignorant of my own Talent-Say then, Believers, will you have a Captain for your Mufti º Or a Mufti for your Captain 2 And further to inſtructyou how to Cry, Will you have a Mufti, or no Mufti.” Ommes, No Mufti, no Mufti. Muft. That I laid in for’em, Slave Antonio— Do I then ſpet upon your Faces? Do I diſcourage Rebellion, Mutiny, Rapine, and Plundering? You may think Ido, Believers, but Heaven forbid : No, I encourage you to all theſe laudable Undertakings; you ſhall plunder, you ſhall pull down the Go- vernment 5 but you ſhall do this upon my Authority, and not by his wicked Inſtigation. 3d. Rabble, Nay, when his turn is ſerv’d, he may preach up Loyalty again, and Reſtitution, that he might have another Snack among us. 1ſt. Rabble, He may indeed; for 'tis but his ſaying'tis Sin, and then we muſt reſtore; and therefore I wou'd have a new Re- - ligion,
Page 96

- ( 96 ) ligion, where half the Commandments ſhou'd be taken away, , the reſt mollifi'd, and there ſhou'd be little or no Sin remain- II]94. %m, Another Religion, a new Religion, another Reli- 1OI). - g Muft. And that may eaſily be done, with the help of a little Inſpiration: For I muſt tell you, I have a Pigeon at home, of Mahomet's own breed; and when I have learnt her to pick Peaſe out of my Ear, reſt ſatisfi'd 'till then, and you ſhall have another. But now I think on't, I am inſpir'd already, that 'tis no Sin to depoſe the Mufti. Ant. And good reaſon; for when Kings and Queens are to be diſcarded, what ſhou’d Knaves do any longer in the pack 2 Omnes, He is depos'd, he is depos'd, he is depos'd. Muft. Nay, if he and his Clergy will needs be preaching up Rebellion, and giving us their Bleſſing, 'tis but juſtice they ſhou'd have the É. fruits of it.—Slave Antonio, take him into cuſtody; and doſt thou hear, Bey, be ſure to ſecure the little tranſitory Box of Jewels: If he be obſtinate, put a civil Queſtion to him upon the Rack, and he ſqueaks I warrant him. Ant. ſeizing the Mufti..Come my quondam Maſter, you and . I muſt change Qualities. - Mufti, I hope you will not be ſo barbarous to torture me, we may preach Suffering to others, but alas, holy Fleſh is too well pamper'd to endure Martyrdom. Muff. Now, late Mufti, not forgetting my firſt Quarrel to you, we will enter our ſelves with the Plunder of your Palace: 'tis good to ſanétifie a Work, and begin a God's name. 1ſt. Rabble, Our Prophet let the Devil alone with the laſt Mob. Mob. But he takes care of this himſelf. As they are going out enter Benducar leading Almeyda: He with a Sword in one hand 3 Benducar's Slave follows with Muly- Mokuch's Head upon a Spear. Muft. Not \ *
Page 97

(97) Not ſo much haſt Maſters; comeback again: you are ſo bent upon miſchief, that you take a man upon the firſt word of Plunder. Here's a ſight for you: the Emperour is come upon his head to viſit you. [Boiving] Moſt Noble Emperour, now I hope you will not hit us in the teeth, that we have pull'd you down, for we can tell you to your face, that we have exalt- cd you. • • - [Zhey alſhout.j [Bendºcar to . Think what I am, and what yourſelfmay be, Almeyda apart. In being mine: refuſe not proffer'd Love - that brings a Crown. [Almeydata I have reſolv’d, [ him. And theſe ſhall know my thoughts. Bend, to her. On that I build.—(He comes up to the Rabble.). Joy to the People for the Tyrants Death! | Oppreſſion, Rapine, Baniſhment and Bloud Are now no more; but ſpeechleſs as that tongue. That Jyes for ever ſtill. “ . . . . . . How is my grief divided with my joy, - º When I muſt own I kill'd him 1 bid me ſpeak, For not to bid me, is to diſallow: - - What for your ſakes is done, *- • Muſtafa. In the name of the People we command you ſpeak: But that pretty Lady ſhall ſpeak firſt ; for we have taken ſome- what of a likeing to her Perſon, be not afraid Lady to ſpeak to theſe rude Ragga-muffians: there's nothing ſhall offend you, unleſs it be their ſtink, and pleaſe you. [Making a Zegg. Almeyda. Why ſhou'd I fear to ſpeak who am your Queen? . My peacefull Father ſway'd the Scepter long; - And you enjoy'd the Bleſſings of his Reign, - While you . name of Affricans. º Then not commanded, but commanding you, . - Pearleſs I ſpeak: know me for what I am, - - Bend. How ſhe aſſumes! I like not this beginning. [.. aſide : Almeyda. I was not born ſo baſe, to flatter Crowds, And move your pitty by a whining tale: Your Tyrant would have forc'd me to his Bed; But in th’ attempt of that foul brutal A&t, Theſe Loyall Slaves ſecur'd me by his Death. [Pointing to Ben. O Bezá, -
Page 98

(98) - w Bºnd. Makes ſhe no more of methen of a Slave? ...[affle. . . Madam, I thought I had inſtrućted you C to Aſm. To frame a Speech more ſuiting to the times: - The Circumſtances of that dire defign, Your own deſpair, my unexpe&ted ayd, my Life endanger'd by his bold defence, And after all, his Death, and your Deliv'rance, Were themes that ought not to be ſlighted o're. - | Maſtafa. She might have paſs'd over all your petty buſi- neſſes and no great matter: But the Raiſing of my Rabble is an Exploit of conſequence; and not to be mumbled up in ſilence for all her pertneſs. - - Almeyda. When force invades the gift of Nature, Life, The eldeſt Law of nature bids defend : . Cours: And if in that defence, a Tyrant fall, his Death's his Crime not Suffice it that he’s Dead: all wrongs dye with him; When he can wrong no more I pardon him : Thus I abſolve my ſelf; and him excuſe, - Who ſav'd my life, and honour; but praiſe neither. . . Benducar. 'Tis cheap to pardon, whom you would not pay; *But what ſpeak I of payment and reward f : . Ungratefull Woman, you are yet no Queen; Nor more than a proud haughty Chriſtian ſlave: - As ſuch I ſeize my right. [going to lay bold on her. [.. Almyda drawing Dare not to approach me; [a Dagger. Now Affricans, - He ſhows himſelf to you; to me he ſtood. ‘Confeſt before, and own’d his Inſolence - Teſpouſe my perſon, and aſſume thc Crown, Claym'd in my Right; for this he ſlew your Tyrant 5’ “Oh no, he only chang'd him for a worſe; • * Imbas'd your Slavery by his own vileneſs, And loaded you with more ignoble bonds : Then think me not ungratefull, not to ſhare, Th’ Imperial Crow n with a preſuming Traytor. He ſays I am a Chriſtian ; true I am, - Put yet no Slave: if Chriſtians can be thought, unfit to govern thoſe of other Faith, 'Tis
Page 99

| ... , , , , (99) 'Tis left for you to judge, - Bendacar. I have not patience; ſhe conſumes the time In Idle talk, and owns her falſe Belief: ar Seize her by force, and bear her hence unheard. [Almeyda to the No, let me rather dye your ſacrifice LPeople. ... Than live his Tryumph ; I throw my ſelf into my Peoples armes; As you are Men compaſſionate my wrongs, And-as good men Protećt me. - | [Antonio aſſae Something muſt be done to ſave her. . . [To Muſtafa, This is all addreſs'd to you Sir: She ſingled you out with her eye, as Commander in chief of the Mobility. AMuſtafa. Think'ſt thou ſo Slave Antonio” - Antonio. Moſt certainly Sir ; and you cannot in honour but protećther, Now look to your hits, and make your fortune. Muſtafa Methought indeed ſhe caſt a kind leer towards me: Our Prophet was but juſt ſuch another Scoundrell as I am, till he rais'd himſelf to power,and conſequently to Holyneſs, by marrying his maſters Widow : I am reſolved I'le put forward for my ſelf: for why ſhould I be my Lord Benducars Fool and Slave, when I may be my own fool and his Maſter : - Benducar. Take her into poſſeſſion, Muſtafa. - Afaftafa. That's better Counſell than you meant it: Yes I do take her into poſſeſſion, and into protećtion too: what ſay you, Maſters, will you ſtand by me? Ommer. One and all; One and ail. Beudacar. Haſt thou betray’d me Traytor? Mufti ſpeak & mind'em of Religion. . . [Mufti ſhakes his head. Muſtafa. Alas the poor Gentleman has gotten a cold, with a Sermon of two hours long, and a prayer of four; and be- ſides, if he durſt ſpeak, mankind is grown wiſer at this time of day, than to cut one anothers throats about Religion. Our Mufti is a Green coat, and the Chriſtians is a black coat; and we muſt wiſely go together by the ears, whether green or black ſhall ſweep our ſpoils. [Drums within and ſhouts. Benductr. Now we ſhall ſee whoſe numbers will prevail: The Conquering Troups of Muley Zeydan, come To cruſh Rebellion, and eſpouſe my Cauſe. - - O 2 - Muſtafa.
Page 100

( 1 oo ) Muſtafa. We will have a fair Tryall of Skill for't, I can teſt him that. When we have diſpatch'd with Maley Zeydaw, your Lordſhip ſhall march in ji proportions of your body, to the four gates of the City; and cvery Tower ſhall have a Quarter of you, [Antonio draws them up and takes Almeyda by the hand º - [Shouts again and Drums. Enter Dorax and Sebaſtian attended by African Soldiers and Por. tugueſes. (Almeyda and Sebaſtian run into each others armts and both ſpºk together. w &b. and Am. My Sebaſtian' My Almeyda! Alm, Do you then live? - - Seb. And live to love thee ever. Bend. How! Dorax and Sebaſtian ſtill alive! - The Moors and Chriſtians joyn'd / I thank thee Prophet. - Dorax. The Citadell is ours; and Muley Zeydan ... . . Safe under Guard, but as becomes a Prince. - Lay down your armes: ſuch baſe Plebeian, bloud • Would only ſtain the brightneſs of my Sword, And blunt it for ſome nobler work behind. - - - - Muff. I ſuppoſe you may put it up without offence to any man here preſent 2. For my part, I have been Loyall to my Soveraign Lady: though that Villain Benducar, and that Hy- pocrite the AZufti, would have corrupted me ; but if thoſe two ſcape publick Juſtice, then I and all my latchoneſt Sub- jećts here, deſerve hanging. L Benducar I'm ſure I did my part topoyſon thee, to Dorax. T What Saint ſoe’re has Sodder'd thee again. A Doſe leſs hot had burſt through ribs of Iron. Muf. Not knowing that, I poyſon'd him once more, And drench'd him with a draught ſo deadly cold That, had'ſt not thou prevented, had congeal’d The channell of his bloud, and froze him dry. . . . . . Bend. Thou interpoſing Fool, to mangle miſchief, , , And think to mend the perfect work of Hell, Dorax. Thus, when Heaven pleaſes, double poyſons cure. ... I will not tax thee of Ingratitude - º To - - --- O -
Page 101

A. (1 or ) - Tome thy Friend, who haſt betray'd thy Prince: Death he deſerv'd indeed, but not from thee, But fate it ſeems reſerv'd the worſt of men To end the worſt of Tyrants. -> Go bear him to his fate. - - And fend him to attend his Maſters Ghoſt, Let ſome ſecure my other poys'ning Friend, ‘Whoſe double dilligence preſerv'd my life. Ant. You are fall’n into good hands, Father in law; your ſparkling Jewells, and Morayma's eyes may prove a better bail than you deſerve. - - - - - Muf. The beſt that can come of me, in this condition, is to have my life begg'd firſt, and then to be begg'd for a Fool afterwards. [Axit Antonio mith the Mufti, and at the ſame time Benducar is carry'd off. [Dorax tº You and your hungry herd depart untouch'd; Muſtafa.] For Juſtice cannot ſtoop ſolow,to reach The groveling ſin of Crowds : but curft be they Who truſt revenge with ſuch mad Inſtruments, Whoſe blindfold bus'neſs is but to deſtroy: And like the fire Commiſſion'd by the Winds, Beginson ſheds, but rouling in a round, On Pallaces returns. Away ye skum, - That ſtill riſe upmoſt when the Nation boyls: - Ye mungrill work of Heaven, with humane ſhapes, Not to be damn'd, or ſav'd, but breath, and º, That have but juſt enough of ſence, to know - The maſters voice, when rated, to depart. - [Exeunt Muſtafa and Rabble. [Almeyda kneeling to him. With gratitude as low, as knees can pay To thoſe bleſt holy Fires, our Guardian Angells, Receive theſe thanks; till Altars can be rais'd, - tº ..[Dorax raiſing her up - . Ariſe fair Excellence,and pay no thanks, - Till time diſcover what I have deſerv’d. Seb. More then reward can anſwer. If Partugal and Spain were joyn'd to Affrique,
Page 102

- - ( 162 ) . . . 4. - And the main Ocean cruſted into Land, . . . . . . If Univerſall Monarchy were mine, . . . . . Here ſhould the gift be plac'd, - Dorax. And from ſome hands I ſhou’d refuſe that gift : Be not too prodigall of Promiſes; - - But ſtint your bounty to one only grant. Which I can ask with honour. Seb. What I am - *. Is but thy gift, make what thou canſ of me. Secure of no Repulſe. - Dorax to Sebaſtian: Diſmiſs your Train. [To Almeyda. You, Madam, pleaſe one moment to retire. [Sebaſtian ſignes to the Portugueſes to go off. Almeyda bowing to him, goes off aſſo; ſhe Affricansfollow her. Dorax To the Captain of his Guard. . With you one word in private. . [Gots out with the Captain. Sebaſtian Solus Reſerv'd behaviour, open Nobleneſs, A long miſterious Track of a ſtern bounty. But now the hand of Fate is on the Curtain, And draws the Scene to fight. Ae-enter Dorax, having taken off his 7 urbant and put on a - Peruque Hat and Crevar. Dorax. Now do you know me £ Sch. Thou ſhouldſt be Alonzo. Dorax. So you ſhou'd be S baſtian : . But when Sehaſtian ceas'd to be himſelf, I ceas'd to be/lonzº. . . . . . . . - Seb. As in a Dream. . . . . . . . . . . . I ſee thee here, and ſcarce believe mine eyes. Dorax Is it ſo ſtrange to find me, where my wrongs, * And your Inhumane Tyranny have ſent me . . . . . . . .” Think not you dream: or, if you did, my Injuries. . . . tº Shall call ſo loud, that Lethargy ſhould wake; . . . . . And Death ſhould give you back to anſwer me. . A Thouſand Nights have bruſh'd their balmy wings .. Over theſe eyes, but ever when they clos'd, º: i , , Your Tyrant Image forc’d 'emope again, • * , And dry'd the dewes they brought.
Page 103

( 103 ) The º expected hour is come at length, By manly Vengence to redeem my fame; And that once clear'd, eternall ſleep is welcome. Sebaſt. I have not yet forgot I am a King 3 Whoſe Royall Office is redreſs of Wrongs: If I have wrong'd thee, charge me face to face; I have not yet forgot I am a Soldier. Dorax. 'Tis the firſt Juſtice thou haſt ever done me. • Then, though Iloath this Womans War of tongues, Yet ſhall my Cauſe of Vengeance firſt be clear: And, Honour, be thou Judge. - Sebaſt. Honour befriend us both. Beware, I warn thee yet, to tell thy griefs In terms becoming Majeſty to hear: I warn thee thus, becauſe I know thy temper Is Inſolent and haughty to Superiours: How.often haſt thou brav'd my peacefull Court, Fill'd it with noiſy brawls, and windy boaſts; And, with paſt ſervice, nauſeouſly repeated, Reproach'd ev'n me thy Prince f Dorax. And well I might, when you forgot reward, The part of Heav'n in Kings: for puniſhment Is Hangmans work, and drudgery for Devils. I muſt and will reproach thee with my ſervice, Tyrant, (it irks me ſo to call my Prince.) But juſt reſentment and hard uſage coyn’d Th' unwilling word; and grating as it is Take it, for 'tis thy due. - * Sebaſt. How Tyrant? Dorax Tyrant. - Sebaſt. Traytour? that name thou canſt not Eccho back : That Kobe of Infamy, that Circumciſion III hid beneath that Robe, proclaim thee Traytor: And, if a Name - More foul than Traytor be, 'tis Renegade, - Dorax. If I'm a Traytor, think and bluſh,thou Tyrant; Whoſe Injuries betray'd me into treaſon. Effac'd my Loyalty, unhing'd my Faith, - And
Page 104

- (104) - - And hurrycd me from hopes of Heaven to Hell. * ..." r- All theſe, and all my yet unfiniſh'd Crimes, , i. When I ſhall riſe to plead before the Saints, ' ' ' '. I charge on thee, to make thy damning ſure. Sebaſſ. Thy old preſumptuous Arrogance again, That bred my firſt diſlike, and then my loathing. Once more be warn'd, and know me for thy King. Dorax. Too well I know thee ; but for King no more: This is not Zibonne, nor the Circle this, . Where, like a Statue, thou haſt ſtood beſieg'd, By Sycophants and Fools, the growth of Courts: Where thy gull'd eyes, in all the gawdy round, Met nothing but a lye in every face; . And the groſs flattery of a gaping Crowd, Envious who firſt ſhould catch, and firſt applaud The Stuff of Royall Nonſence: when I ſpoke, , , "," My honeſt homely words were carp'd, and cenſur'd, “ . . For want of Courtly Stile; related A&tions, . . . . Though modeſtly reported, paſs'd for boaſts: -- " . Secure of Merit if I ask’d reward, - . . . t Thy hungry Minions thought their rights invaded, “ . . And the bread ſnatch'd from Pimps and Paraſits. . . . . " Anriquez anſwer'd, with a ready lye, * To f. his King's, the boon was begg'd before. -- Sebaſt. What ſayſt thou of Anriguez’ now by Heaven - - Thou mov’It me more by barely naming him, - . . . . Than all thy foul unmanner'd ſcurril taunts. “ . . . Dorax. And therefore 'twas to gaul thee, that I nam’d him: That thing, that nothing, but a cringe and ſmile; - That Woman, but more dawb'd : or if a man, Corrupted to a Woman; thy Man Miſtreſs. Sebaſt. All falſe as Hell or thou, Dorax. Yes 5 full as falſe - . As that I ſerv'd thee fifteen hard Campaignes, And pitch'd thy Standard in theſe Forreign Fields: By methy greatneſs grew ; thy years grew with it, , But thy Ingratitude outgrew 'em both. - Sebtſ. I ſee to what thou tend’ſt,but tell me firſt - + i . . . . -
Page 105

( 1 of ) If thoſe great Ağs were done alone for me ! If love produc’d not ſome, and pride the reſt 2 Dorax. Why Love does all that's noble here below But all th' advantage of that love was thine. För, coming fraughted back, in either hand With Palm and Olive, Vićtory and Peace, I was indecd prepar'd to ask my own: (For Pºlante's vows were mine before:) Thy malice had prevention, ere I ſpoke: And ask'd me Piolante for Enriquez. " Seb. I meant thee a reward of greater worth : Dor. Where juſtice wanted, could reward be hop'd? Could the robb’d Paſlenger cºpećt a bounty, From thoſe rapacious hands who ſtript him firſt? Seb. He had my promiſe, ere I knew thy love, Dor. My Services deſerv'd thou ſhould'ſt revoke it. Seb. Thy Inſolence had cancell'd all thy Services To violate my Laws, even in my Court, Sacred to peace, and ſafe from all affronts; E’ven to my face, as done in my deſpight, Under the wing of awfull Majeſty To ſtrike the man I lov’d' - 2 Dor. Even in the face of Heaven, a place more Sacred, Would I have ſtruck the man, who propt by power, Would Seize my right, and rob me of my Love: But, for a blow provok'd by thy Injuſtice, The haſty produćt of a juſt deſpair, When he reſus’d to meet me in the field, That thou ſhoud'ſt make a Cowards Cauſe thy own! Seb. He durſt; nay more deſir'd and begg’d with tears, To meet thy Challenge fairly : 'twas, thy fault o make it publique 5 but my duty, then, Tº: ; on pain of my diſpleaſure, Betwixt your Swords, - * Dor. On pain of Infamy He ſhould have diſobey'd. - Seb. Th’ Indignity thou didſt, was ment to me; Thy gloomy eyes were caſt cºns, with ſcorn, - *, - ** Aş
Page 106

( 106) - As who ſhould ſay the blow was there intended; But that thou didſt not dare to lift thy hands Againſt Annointed power: ſo was Iforc'd To do a Soveraign juſtice to my ſelf; ` - And ſpurn thee from my preſence. Dor. Thou haſt dar'd To tell me, what I durſt not tell my ſelf: -- I durſt net think that I was ſpurn'd,and live ; And live to hear it boaſted to my face. All my long Avarice of honour loſt, Heap'd up in Youth, and hoarded up for Age; Has honours Fountain then ſuck'd back the ſtream 2 He has; and hooting Boys, may dry-ſhod paſs, And gather pebbles from the naked Foord. Give me my Love, my Honour; give 'em back:— Give me revenge 3 while I have breath to ask it.— Seb. Now, by this honour'd Order which I wear, More gladly would I give, than thou dar'ſ ask it: Nor ſhall the Sacred Charaćter of King Beurg'd, to ſhield me from thy bold appeal. If I have injur'd thce, that makes us equall: The wrong, if done, dcbas'd me down to thee. But thou haſt charg’d me with Ingratitude : Haſt thou not charg'd me a ſpeak? Dor. Thou know'ſt I have: If thou diſown'ſt that Imputation, draw, And prove my Charge a lye. Seb. No 5 to diſprove that lye, I muſt not draw: Beconſcious to thy worth, and tell thy Soul What thou haſt done this day in my defence: To fight thee, after this, what were it elſe, Than owning that Ingratitude thou urgeſt ? That Iſthmus ſtands betwixt two ruſhing Seas; Which, mounting, view each other from afar; And ſtrive in vain to meet. Dor. I’le cut that Iſthmus. Thou know'ſt I meant not to preſerve thy Life, - - 4-. But to reprieve it, for my own revenge. - º
Page 107

( 167) Iſav'd thee out of honourable malice : Now draw; I ſhould be loath to think thou dar’ſ not: . Beware of ſuch another vile excuſe. Seb. Opatience Heaven! Dor. Beware of Patience too 5 That's a Suſpicious word: it had been proper Before thy foot had ſpurn'd me; now 'tis baſe: Yet, to diſarm thee of thy laſt defence, . I have thy Oath for my ſecurity: The only boon I begg’d was this fair Combat: Fight or be Perjur'd now; that's all thy choice. [Sebaſ Now I can thank thee as thou wouldſt be thank'd, drawing: Never was vow of honour better pay’d, If my true Sword but hold, than this ſhall be. The ſprightly Bridegroom, on his Wedding Night, More gladly enters not the lifts of Love. Why 'tis enjoyment to be ſummon'd thus. Go; bear my Meſſage to Henriquez Ghoſt; And ſay his Maſter and his Friend reveng’d him. Der. His Ghoſt then is my hated Rivall dead? Seb. The queſtion is beſide our preſent purpoſe 3 Thou ſeeſt me ready ; we delay too long. Dor. A minute is not much in eithers Life, When their's but one betwixt us; throw it in, And give it him of us, who is to fall. (him. Sebaſt. He's dead: make haſt, and thou mayſt yet o're take Dor. When I was haſty, thou delay'ſt me longer. I prethee let me hedge one moment more Intothy promiſe: forthy life preſerv'd : Be kind ; and tell me how that Rivall dy'd, Whoſe Death next thine I wiſh'd. - Seb. If it would pleaſe thee thou ſhould'ſt never know : But thou, like Jealouſy, enquir'ft a truth, - - Which, found, will torture thee: He dy’d in Fight: Fought next my perſon 5 as in Conſort fought : Kept pace for pace, and blow for every blow 5 Save when he heav'd his Shicld in my defence; And on his naked ſide receiv'd my wound. . Then, when he could no more, he fell at once : P 2. But
Page 108

( 1 o'S) But rowl'd his falling body croſs their way; And made a Bulwark of it for his Prince. Dor. I never can forgive him ſuch a death! Seb. I prophecy'd thy proud Soul could not bear it. Now, judgethy ſelf, who beſt deſerv'd my Love. - I knew you both ; (and durſt I ſay) as Heaven - Foreknew among the ſhining Angell hoſt Who would ſtand firm, who fall. Dor. Had he been tempted ſo, ſo had he fall’m ; And ſo, had Ibeen favour’d, had I ſtood. Seb. What had been is unknown; what is appears : Confeſs he juſtly was preferr'd to thee. Dor. Had Ibeen born with his indulgent Stars, My fortune had been his, and his been mine. O, worſe than Hell! what Glory have I loſt, And what has he acquir'd, by ſuch a death.' I ſhould have fallen by Sebaſtians ſide ; My Corps had been the Bulwark of my King, His glorious end was a patch'd work of fate, Ill ſorted with a ſoft effeminate life: It ſuited better with my life than his So to have dy'd : mine had been of a peice, - Spent in your ſervice, dying at your feet. Seb. The more effeminate and ſoft his life, The more his fame, to ſtruggle to the field, And meet his glorious fate:Confeſs, proud Spirit, (For I will have it from thy, very mouth) That better he deſerv'd my love than thou. Dor. O, whether would you drive me! I muſt grant, . Yes I muſt grant, but with a ſwelling Soul, . Henriquez had your Love with more deſert: For you he fought, and dy'd 5 I fought againſt you; , Through all the mazes of the bloudy field, Hunted your Sacredlife; which that I miſs'd , Was the propitious errour of my fate, Not of my Soul; my Soul's a Regicide. Seb. Thou might'ſt have given it a more gentle name: ſmore calmly.] Thou meant'ſt to kill a Tyrant, not a King : sk - ~ peak.
Page 109

- Io9), Speak didſt thou not, Alonzo: * - Dor. Can I ſpeak' º Alas, I cannot anſwer to Alonzo: No, Dorax cannot anſwer to Alonzo : Alonzo was too kind a name for me. Then, when I fought and conquer'd with your Armes, In that bleſt Age I was the man you nam'd : Till rage and pride debas'd me into Dorax; And loſt like Zucifer, my name above. Seb. Yet, twice this day I ow'd my life to Dorax. Dor. Iſav'd you but to kill you; there's my grief. Seb. Nay,if thou can’t be griev'd,thou can't repent: . Thou coud'ſt not be a Villain, though thou woud'ſt : Thou own’ft too much, in owning thou haſterr'd; And I too little, who provok'd thy Crime. - Dor. O ſtop this headlong Torrent of your goodneſs: : It comes too faſt upon a feeble Soul, Halfdrown'd in tears, before 5 ſpare my confuſion: For pitty ſpare, and ſay not, firſt, you err'd. For yet I have not dar'd, through guilt and ſhame, [Falls at his To throw my ſelf beneath your Royall feet. feet] Now ſpurn this Rebell, this proud Renegade: . 'Tis juſt you ſhould, nor will I more complain. Seb. Indeed thou ſhoud'ſt not ask forgiveneſs firſt, [taking him up. But thou preventſt me ſtill,in all that’s noble. . Yet I will raiſe thee up with better news:. . . Thy Piolante's heart was ever thine; . - Compell'd to wed, becauſe ſhe was my Ward, Her Soul was abſent when ſhe gave her hand : : Nor could my threats, or his purſuing Courtſhip, Effect the Conſummation of his Love: - So, ſtill indulging tears, ſhe pines for thee, A Widdow and a Maid. Dor. Have Ibeen curſing Heav'n while Heav'n'bleſt me! I ſhall run mad with extaſy of joy: - - What, in one moment, to be reconcil'd To Heaven, and to my King, and to my Love! . But pitty is my Friend, and ſtops me ſhort, 'Foº 1. - ---
Page 110

( 1 to ) For my unhappy Rivall: poor Henriquez! Seb. Art thou ſo generous too, to Pitty him? Nay, then I was unjuſt to love him better. # Embrac- Here let me ever hold thee in my arms : ing him. And all our quarrells be but ſuch as theſe, Who ſhall love beſt, and cloſeſt ſhall embrace: Be what Enriquez was ; be my Alonzo. --- Dor. What,my Alonzo ſayd you ? my Alonzo I Let my tears thank you 5 for I cannot ſpeak: And if I cou’d, Words were not made to vent ſuch thoughts as mine. Seb. Thou canſt not ſpeak, and I can ne’re be filent. Some Strange reverſe of Fate muſt, ſure attend This vaſt profuſion, this extravagance - Of Heaven, to bleſs me thus, "Tis Gold ſo pure It cannot bear the Stamp, without allay. Be kind, ye Powers, and take but half away : With eaſo the giſts of Fortune I refign; But, let my Love, and Friend, be ever mine. Ezeunt A C T V. The Scene is a Room of State. • Enter Dorax and Antonio. As, in the Scene of opening Paradice, . The whole Creation danc'd at their new being: Pleas'd to be what they were; pleas'd with each other. Such Joy have I, both in my ſelf, and Friends: And double Joy, that I have made'em happy. Antonio, Pleaſure has becn the bus'neſs of my life ; And every change of Fortune eaſy to me, Becauſe I ſtill was eaſy to myſelf. The loſs of her Ilov'd would touch me neareſt; Yºt, if I found her, I might love too much 5 \ *Por. J% is on every face, without a Cloud: And
Page 111

( 1 11 J And that's uneaſy Pleaſure. , - Dor. If ſhe be fated Tobeyour Wife, your fate will find her for you : Predeſtinated ills are never loſt. Anton. I had forgot T*Enquire before, but long to be inform’d, How, poiſon’d and betray'd, and round beſet, You could unwindyour ſelf from all theſe dangers; . And move ſo ſpeedily to our relief! - Dor. The double poiſons, after a ſhort Combat, ... Expell'd each other in their CivillWar, “. By natures benefit; and rows'd my thoughts - To Guard that life which now I found Ättack'd. I ſummon'd all my Officers in haſt, On whoſe experienc'd Faith I might rely: All came ; reſolv'd to dye in my defence, Save that one Villain who betray'd the Gate. Our diligence prevented the ſurprize . We juſtly fear'd: ſo, Muley-Zeydan found us . Drawn-up in Battle, to receive the charge, . Ant. But how the Moors and Chriſtian ſlaves were joyn'd, d, You have not yet unfolded. l Dor. That remains. !-- - , We knew their Int’reſt was the ſame with ours : . And though I hated more than Death, Sebaſtian; I could not ſee him dye by Vulgar hands: But prompted by my Angell, or by his, - Freed all the Slaves; and plac'd him next my ſelf, . . Becauſe I would not have his Perſon known. I need not tell the reſt, th” event declares it. . . . Aut. Your Conqueſt came of courſe; their men were raw, . And yours were diſciplin'd : one doubt remains, ſº Why you induſtriouſly conceal’d the King, . Who, known, had added Ceurage to his Men? . . . . Dor. I would not hazard civillbroils, betwixt ; , ; His Friends and mine: which might prevent our Combat: . Yet, had he fall'n, I had diſmiſs'd his Troops; 2. c : , Or, if Wićtorious, order'd his eſcape, . But ku sºlº tº |
Page 112

(112) But I forgot a new increaſe of Joy, - - To feaſt him with ſurprize 3 I muſt about it: - - Expect my ſwift return. - [Axit Dorax, . * Enter a Servant to Antonio, Serv. Here's a Lady at the door, that bids me tell you, ſhe is come to make an end of the game, that was broken off be. twixt you. * * - - Ant. What manner of Woman is ſhe? Does ſhe not want two of the four Elements? has ſhe anything about her but ayr and fire : -. - Servaut. Truly, ſhe flys about the room, as if ſhe had wings inſtead of legs; I believe ſhe’s juſt turning into a bird: a houſe- bird I warranther: and ſo haſty to fly to you, that, rather than fail of entrance, ſhe wou’d come tumbling down the Chim- ºney, like a Swallow. *- w Anter Morayma. [Antoniornnning to her and Embracing her. Look if ſhe be not here already: what, no deniall it ſeems will ſerve your turn? why I thou little dun, is thy debt ſo preſfing f Mor. Little Devill if you pleaſe: your leaſe is out, good Mr. Conjurer; and I am come to fetch you Soul and Body; not an hour of lewdneſs longer in this world for you. Ant. Where the Devill haſt thou been? and how the Devill didſt thou find ime here 2 * - . Mor. I follow'd you into the Caſtle-yard: but there was no- thing but Tumult, and Confuſion: and I was bodily afraid of being F. up by ſome of the Rabble: conſidering Ihad a double charge about me, my Jewells & my Mayden-head. Aut. Both of 'em intended for my Worſhips ſole uſe and Property. - ... - . tº- º º tº i, j : - ! Mor. And what was poor little I among’em all? Amt. Not a mouthfull a piece: ’twas too much odds in Con- fcience...92 ºzºº . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Mor. So ſeeking for ſhelter, I naturally ran to the old Ph. T. . . | Of ... tº 2 " * - " - .*.*... I'- i. * --
Page 113

( II 3) - of Aſſignation, the Garden-houſe: where for want of inflina, you did not follow me. Aut. Well for thy Comfort, I have ſecu'd thy Father; and I hope thou haſt ſecur’d his effects for us. Mor. Yes truly I had the prudent forefight to conſider that when we grow old, and weary of Solacing one another, we, might have, at leaſt, wherewithall to make merry with the World; and take up with a worſe pleaſure of eating and drinking, when we were diſabled, for a better. Ant. Thv fortune will be c’en too good for thee: for thou art going iuto the Country of Serenades, and Gallantries ; where thy ſtreet will be haunted every Night, with thy fool- iſh Lovers, and my Rivals; who will be ſighing, and ſinging underthy inexorable windows, lamentable distics,and call thee. Crucii, & Goddeſs, & Moon, and Stars, and all the Poeticall names of wicked rhyme: while thou and I, are minding our bus'neſs, and jogging on, and laughing at 'em ; at leiſure- minuts,which will be very few,take that by way of threatning. Mor. I am afraid you are not very valiant, that you huff ſo much before hand; but, they ſay, your Churches are fine places for Love-devotion: many a ſhe-Saint is there worſhip’d. Ant. Temples are there,as they are in all otherCountries,good conveniences for dumb enterviews: I hear the Proteſtants an’t much reform'd in that point neither;for theirSectaries call their Churches by the naturall name of Meeting-houſes, therefore I warn thee in good time, not more of devotion than needs muſt, good future Spowſe ; and allways in a veile; for thoſe eyes of thine are damn'd enemies to mortification. - . . . Mor. The beſt thing I have heard of Chriſtendom, is that we women are allow'd the priviledge of having Souls; and I aſſure you, I ſhall make bold to beſtow mine, upon ſome Lo- ver, when ever you begin to go aſtray, and, if I find no Con- venience in a Church,a private Chamber will ſerve the turn. Ant. When that day comes, I muſt take my revenge and turn Gardener again: for I find I am much given to Planting. Mor. But take hecd, in the mean time, that ſome young Antonio does not ſpring up in your own Family; as falſe as his Father, though of another mans planting. - Re-enter * - – - - -
Page 114

, a. ( 1-14) Renter Dorax with Sebaſtian and Almeyda. Sebaſtian enters ~ ſpeaking to Dorax, while in the mean time Antonio preſents Morayma to Almeyda. Seb. How fares our Royall Pris’ner, Muley Zeydan'? . . . Dor. Diſpos'd to grant whatever I deſire, To gain a Crown, and Freedom: well I know him, Of eaſy temper, naturally geod, - s, And faithfull to his word. Seb. Yet one thing wants, Tofili the meaſure of my happineſs I'm ſtill in pain for poor Alvarez's life. Dor. Releaſe that fear; the good old man is ſale : I pay’d his ranſome : , - - And have already order'd his Attendance. . Seb. Obid hilu enter for I long to ſee him. Anter Alvarez, with a Servant, who departs when Aivarez is fater'd. - [Alvarez fºing down and embracing the Kings kyees T. Now by my Soul, and by theſe hoary hairs, I’m ſo ore-whelm'd with pleaſure, that I feel A latter ſpring within Iny with’ring limbs, That Shoots me out again. Sebaſtian, raiſing him J Thou good old Man! - Thou haſt deceiv'd me into more, more joys ; Who ſtood brim-full before. . Alv. O my dear Child ! • I love thee ſo, I cannot call thee King, Whom I ſo oft have dandled in theſe arms! What, when I gave thee loſt to find thee living! * Tis like a Father, who himſelf had ſcap'd A falling houſe, and after anxious ſearch, Hears from afar, his only Son within : *: . And digs through rubbiſh, till he drags him out T - - 2
Page 115

( II 5) To ſee the friendly light. - Such is my haſt ſo trembling is my joy - To draw theeforth from underneath thy Fate. Jek. The Tempeſt is ore-blown; the Skys are clear, And the Sea, charm'd into a Calm ſo ſtill, - That not a wrinkle ruffles her ſmooth face. Alv. Juſt ſuch ſhe ſhows before a riſing florm: And therefore am I come, with timely ſpeed, To warn you into Port. - - - - Almeyda. My Soul fore-bodes Laſſae. Some dire event involv’d in thoſe dark words; - And juſt diſcloſing, in a birth of fate. - Av. Is there not yet an Heir of this vaſt Empire, Who ſtill Survives, of Muley-Moluchs branch * . Dor. Yes ſuch an one there is, a Captive here, And Brother to the Dead. ... • Alv. The Power's above Be prais'd for that: My prayers for my good Maſter I hope are heard. - . . . Seb. Thou haft a right in Heav'n, But why theſe prayers for me? Alv. A door is open yet for your deliv'rance, Now you my Country-men, and you Almeyda, Now all of us, and you (my all in one) May yet be happy in that Captives life. Seb. We have him here an honourable Hoſtage For terms of peace: what more he can Contribute To make me bleſt, I know not. - Alv. Vaſtly more : - * Almeyda may be ſettled in the Throne; And you review your Native Clime with fame: A firm Alliance, and efernall Peace, (The glorious Crown of honourable War,) . Are all included in that Princes life: Let this fair Queen be giv'n to Muley-Zeydan ; • And make her love the Sančtion of your League. Seb. No more of that: his fife's in my diſpoſe; And Pris'ners are not to inſiſt on terms. . Q_2 ; ** - Or
Page 116

-( i ; 6) ~ Or if they were, yet he demands not theſ. Alv. You ſhou’d exact 'em. Alm. Better may be made; - Theſe cannot: I abhor the Tyrants race; - - . My Parents Murtherers, my Throne's Uſurpers. - But, at one blow to cut off all diſpute, Know this, thou buſy, old, officious Man, - I am a Chriſtian ; now be wiſe no more; - Or if thou woud'ſt be ſtill thought wiſe, be ſilent, Alv. O! I perceive you think your Int’reſt touch'd : 'Tis what before the Battail I obſerv'd : . But I muſt ſpeak, and will. - Seb. I prethee peace 5 Perhaps ſhe thinks they are too near of bloud: . Alv. I wiſh ſhe may not wed to bloud more near. Seb. What if I make her mine? Alv. Now Hea’vn forbid! - - - Seb. Wiſh rather Hea’wn may grant. For, if I cou’d deſerve, I have deſerv'd her: My toyls, Iny hazards, and my Subječts. lives, (Provided ſhe conſent) may claim her love: And, that once granted, I appeal to theſe, If better, I cou’d ehuſe a beauteous Bride, Aat. The faireſt of her Sex. Mor: The pride of Nature. Dor. He only merits her; ſhe only him, - So payr'd, ſo ſuited in their minds and Perſons, , That they were fram'd the Tallyes for each other. If any Alien love had interpos'd It muſt have been an eyeſore to beholders, And to themſelves a Curſe. - Alv. And to themſelves - The greateſt Curſe that can be, werc to joyn. Seb. Did I not love thee, paſt a change to hate, That word had been thy ruine; but no more, . . . I charge thee on thy life, perverſe old man. Alv Know, Sir, I wou'd be ſilent if I durſt: But, if on Shipbord, I ſhou'd ſee my Friend, Growſ;
Page 117

• ( 1 17 ) Grown frantique in a raging Calenture, And he, imagining vain flowry fields, Wou'd headlong plunge himſelf into the deep, Shou'd l not hold him from that mad attempt, Till his ſick fancy were by reaſon cur'd? Seb. I pardon thee th’effects of doting Age: . . Vain doubts, and idle cares, and over-caution; The ſecond Non-age of a Soul, more wiſe 5 But now decay’d, and ſunk into the Socket, Peeping by fits and giving feeble light. A/v. Have you forgot? ... - Sek. Thou mean'ſt my Fathers Will, - In bar of Marriage to Almeyda’s bed: Thou ſeeſt my faculties are ſtill entire, Though thine are much impair’d, I weigh'd that Will, . . . And found ’twas grounded on our diff'rent Faiths; But, had he liv'd to ſee her happy change, He wou'd have cancell'd that harſh lnterdićt, ‘And joyn'd our hands himſelf. Alv. Still had he liv'd and ſeen, this change, He ſtill had been the Same. Seb. I have a dark remembrance of myFather; His reas'nings and his A&tions both were juſt ; And, granting that, he muſt have chang'd his meaſures. Av. Yes, he was juſt, and therefore cou’d not change... Seb. 'Tis a baſe wrong thou offer'ſt to the Dead. . A/v. Now Hea’wn forbid, - º That I ſhou’d blaſt his pious Memory: - . . - No, I am tehder of his holy Fame: . . . . For, dying he bequeath’d it to my charge. - Believe I am; and ſeek to know no more, . But pay a blind obedience to his will. For to preſerve his Fame I wou'd be ſilent. seb. Craz'd fool, who woud'ſt be thought an Oracle, Come down from off thy Tripos, and ſpeak plain; • My Father ſhall be juſtify'd, he ſhall: ‘Tisa Son's part to riſe in his defence; And to confound thy malice, or thy dotage. ' - Alv. It does not gricve me that you hold me craz'd; * Bił
Page 118

( i 18) : But, to be clear'd at my dead Maſters coſt, Othere's the wound ! but let me firſt adjure you, By all you owe that dear departed Soul, No more to think of Marriage with Almeyda. Seb. Not Hea’vn and Earth combin'd, can hinder it. Alv. Then, witneſs Hea’vn and Earth, how loath I am To ſay, you muſt not, nay you cannot wed. And ſince not only a dead Fathers fame, But more a Ladies honour muſt be touch'd, Which nice as Ermines will not bear a Soil; Let all retire; that you alone may hear What ev’n in whiſpers I wou'd tell your ear. [Allare going out. Alm. Not one of you depart; I charge you ſtay. - And, were my voice a Trumpet loud as Fame, . " To reach the round of Hea’vn, and Earth, and Sea, All Nations ſhou'd be Summon'd to this place. So little do I fear that Fellows charge : So ſhou'd my honour like a riſing Swan, Bruſh with her wings, the falling drops away, And proudly plough the waves. - - Seb. This noble Pride becomes thy Innocence : And I dare truſt my Fathers memory, To ſtand the charge of that foul forging tongue. Alv. It will be ſoon diſcover'd if I forge : Have you not heard your Father in his youth, When newly marry'd, travel’d into Spain, And made a long abode in Phillips Court 2 Seb. Why ſo remote a queſtion?, which thy ſelf Can anſwer to thy ſelf, for thou wert with him, His Fav'rite, as I oft have heard thee boaſt: And neareſt to his Soul. º - 2/v. Too near indeed, forgive me Gracious Heaven That ever I ſhould boaſt I was ſo near. - The Confident of all his young Arnours. - [To Almeyda T And have not you, unhappy beauty, heard, Have you not often heard, your Exil'd Parents Were refug'd in that Court, and at that time? . Al , . - - - - - -- lſ/?. - -
Page 119

( 1 19 ) Alm, 'Tis true; and often ſince, my Mother own’d How kind that Prince was, to eſpouſe her cauſe: Slie Counſell'd, nay, Enjoyn'd me on her bleſſing To ſeek the Sančtuary of your Court : - - Which gave me firſt encouragement to come, And, with my Brother, beg, Sebaſtians aid. Sebaſt, Thou help it me well, to juſtify my War: to Alme..] My dying Father ſwore me, thena Boy; And made me kiſs the Croſs upon his Sword, Never to ſheath it, till that exil'd Queen Were by my Arms reſtor'd. . . . . . Av. And can you finde . . . . . . . . - No miſtery, couch'd in this exceſs of kindneſs 2 Were Kings e're known, in this degenerate Age, So paſſionately fond of noble A&ts, -- . Where Intereſt ſhar'd not more than half with honour? Seb. Baſe groveling Soul, who know'ſt not honours worth;. But weigh'ſt it out in mercenary Scales 5 . The Secret pleaſure of a generous A&t, Is the great minds great bribe. A/v. Show me that King, and I'le believe the Phoenix. But knock at your own breaſt, and ask your Soul If thoſe fair fatall eyes, edg’d not your Sword, More than your Fashers charge, and all your vows? . . If ſo; and ſo your filence grants it is, . . . . Know King, your Father had, like you, a Souls And Love is your Inheritance from him. Almeyda’s Mother too had eyes, like her, And not leſs charming, and were charm'd no leſs Than your's are now with her, and her’s with you. Alm, Thou ly'ſt Impoſtor, Perjur’d Fiend thou ly'ſt. Seb. Wa'ſt not enough to brand my Father's fame, But thou muſt load a Ladies memory? O Infamous baſe, beyond repair. And, to what end this ill concerted lye, Which, palpable and groſs, yet granted true, . It barrs not my Inviolable vows. - Alv. Take heed and double not your Fathers crimes; T - - ... " (10
Page 120

(110) To his Adult'ry, do not add your Inceſt. Know, ſhe is the product of unlawfull Love: - And 'tis your Carmall Siſter you wou’d wed. seb. Thou ſhallt not ſay thou wert Condemn'd unheard. Elſe, by my Soul,this moment were thy laſt. - Alm. But think not Oaths ſhall juſtify thy charge 5 Nor Imprecations on thy curſed head, . . . . For who dares lye to Heaven, thinks Heaven a Jeſt. Thou haſt confeſs'd thy ſelf the Conſcious Pandar Of that pretended paſſion: A Single Witneſs, infamouſly known, Againſt two Perſons of unqueſtion’d fame; Alv. What Int’reſt can I havc, or what delight To blaze their ſhame, or to divulge my own? If prov'd you hate me, if unprov'd Condemnº Not Racks or Tortures could have forc'd this ſecret, . But too much care, to ſave you from a Crime, Which would have ſunk wou both. For let me ſay, Almeyda's beauty well deſerves your love : - Alm. Out, baſe Impoſtor, I abhor thy praiſe. - - Dorax. It looks not like Impoſture: but a truth, - On utmoſt need reveal’d. - - Sebaſt. Did I expect from Dorax, this return ? Is this the love renew’d 2 Dorax. Sir, I am ſilent; Pray Heav'n my fears prove falſe. • * r * - Sebaſt. Away; you ail combine to make me wretched. . Alv. But hear the ſtory of that ſarall Love; Where every Circumſtance ſhall prove another ; * And truth ſo ſhine, by her own native light, , That if a Lye were mixt, it muſt be ſeen. . . . . . . . " Sebaſt, No 5 all may ſtill be forg'd, and of a piece. No; I can credit nothing thou can’t ſay: ' ". . - Alv. One proof remains; and that's your Fathers hand: Firm'd with his Signet; both ſo fully known, That plainer Evidence can hardly be, Unleſs his Soul wou’d want her Hea’wn a while, - And come on Earth to ſwear, - - !, Seh. ---
Page 121

( 12 1 ) Seb. Produce that Writing. . . . . . [Alver. Alonzo has it in his Cuſtody.. to Dorax || The ſame, which when his nobleneſ; redeem'd me, And in a friendly viſit own'd himſelf, For what he is, I then depoſited: And had his Faith to give it to the King. Dorax giving 4 ſeal’d Paper to the King. Untouch'd, and Seal’d as when intruſted with me, Such I reſtore it, with a trembling hand, Leſt ought within diſturb your peace of Soul. Sebaſt. tearing open the Seals. Draw near Almeyda; thou art moſt concern'd. - For I am moſt in Thee. . . . Alonzo, mark the Charaćters: . . - Thou know'ſt my Fathers hand obſerve it well: ' ', And if th’Impoſtors Pen, have made one ſlip, - - - - That ſhows it Counterfeit, mark that and ſave me. Dorax. It looks, indeed, too like my Maſters hand: . . . So does the Signet; more I cannot ſay; . . . * - - But wiſh’twere not ſo like. º ** - - Sebaſt. Methinks it owns - - The black Adult'ry, and Almeyda's birth; But ſuch a miſt of grief comes o're my eyes, I cannot, or I wou’d not read it plain. - - - Alm. Heavn cannot be more true, than this is falſe. - sºft. occudºſithou prove it, with the ſame aſſurance! . Speak, haſt thou ever ſeen my Fathers hand? Alm. No; but my Mothers honour has been read - * - … - -- y - º, tº . . . . ºi - -- - - - By me, and by the world, in all her Aëts; . . . . . º In Charaćters more plain, and legible ..." º Then this dumb Evidence, this blotted lye. . . . . | “... Oh that I were a man, as my Soul's one, "... . ... . ". º º To prove thec, Traytor, an Aſſaſſinate . . . . . . . - - - - 1 fli R" . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ii º' of ... i
Page 122

( 172 ) . - of her fair ſame : thus wou'd I tear thee, thus—: [(Tearing And ſcatter, o're the field, thy Coward limbs, #; Like this foul offspring of thy forging brain. •. . . . (stattºring the Paper) Alv. Juſt ſo, ſhalt thou be torn from all thy hopes. . . " For know proud Woman, know in thy deſpight, - The moſt Authentidue proof is ſtill behind. Thou wear'ſt it on thy finger : 'tis that Ring, ºf Which match'd with that on his, ſhall clear the doubt. 'Tis no dumb forgery: for that ſhall ſpeak; - And ſound a rattling peal to eithers Conſcience: Seb. This Ring indeed, my Father, with a cold And ſhaking hand, juſt in the pangs of Death, Put on my finger; with a parting ſigh, And wou'd have ſpoke; but falter'd in his ſpeech, With undiſtinguiſh’d founds. Alv. I know it well: - - For I was preſent: Now, Almeyda, ſpeak: And, truly tell us, how you come by yours? . Alm. My Mother, when I parted from her fight, " To go to Portugal bequeath'd it to me, - Preſaging ſhe ſhou'd never ſee me more: - She pull'd it from her finger, ſhed ſome tears, … . Kiſs'd it, and told me’twas a pledge of Love; - - And hid a Miſtery of great Importance Relating to my Fortunes. Alv. Mark me now, - While I diſcloſe that fatall Miſtery. - - Yhoſe rings, when you were born, and thought anothers, Tour Parents, glowing yet in ſinfull love, - Bid me beſpeak: a Curious Artiſt wrought 'em: With joynts ſo cloſe, as not to be perceiv'd 3 Yet are they both each others Counterpart. Her part had juan inſcrib'd, and his had 24yda. )You know thoſe names are theirs: ) and in the midſt, A heart divided in two halves was plac’d. - Now if the rivets of thoſe Rings, inclos'd, i Fit
Page 123

- ( 12; ) ". . . . . . Fit not each other, I have forg'd this lye : - . . . But if they joyn, you muſt for ever part, [Seb. pulling off his Seb, Now life, or death. Ring. Alm, does the Alm. And either thine, or ours. ſame, and gives it to . Alm, I'm loſt for ever.——(ſwoons) Alv. who unſcrues (Zhe Women and Morayma, take both the Rings & fits her up and carry her off. ) one half to the other.] [Seb. here ſtands amaz'd without motion, his eyes fixt upward.] Seb. Look to the Qyleen my Wife; For I am paſt All Pow'r of Aid, to her or to my ſelf. Alv. His Wife, ſaid he, his Wife! O fatall ſound! For, had I known it, this unwelcome news Had never reach'd their ears. So they had ſtill been bleſt in Ignorance, And I alone unhappy. . Dor. I knew it, but too late: and durft not ſpeak. [ Seb. ſtarting I will not live : no not a moment more; out of his amaze- I will not add one moment more to Inceſt. zºemf. I’le cut it off, and end a wretched being. For, ſhould I live, my Soul's ſo little mine, And ſo much hers, that I ſhould ſtill enjoy. Ye Cruell Powers, Take me as you have made me, miſèrable; You cannot make me guilty; 'twas my fate And you made that, not I. [Draws his Sword. -- ~ Antonio and Alv, lay holā on him, and Dorax wreſts the Sword out of his hand. An For Heav'ns ſake hold, and recolled your mind. Alvarez. Conſider whom you puniſh, and for what ; Your ſelf? unjuſtly: You have charg’d the fault, - R 2 On
Page 124

( 12.4) . . On Heav'n that beſt may bear it. - - Though Inceſt is indeed a deadly Crime; … . . . You are not guilty, ſince, unknown 'twas done, . . . . And, known, had been abhorr'd. - - Seb. By Heaven y’re Traytours, all, that hold my hands, If death be but ceſſation of oilr thought, - 2 -- Then let me dye for I would think no more; I'le boaſt my Innocence above; • * , And let 'em ſee a Soul they cou’d not ſully: " I ſhall be there before my Fathers Ghoſt 5 That yet muſt languiſh long, in froſts and fires, .. For making me unhappy by his Crime: [ſtruggling Standoff and let me take my fill of death.; again. For I can hold my breath in your deſpight, And ſwell my heaving Soul out, when I pleaſe. - Alv. Heav'n comfort you!. - - - `. *. - *. Seb. What art thou given comfort! - Wou'dſt thougive comfort, who haſ giv'n deſpair . Thou ſeeſt Alonzo ſilent; he's a man. He knows, that men abandon'd of their hopes. Shou'd ask no leave, nor ſtay for ſueing out A tedious Writ of eaſe, from lingring Heaven, ... . But help themſelves, as timely as they cou’d, , , And teach the fates their duty. [Dorax to Alv. Let him go: - and Anto. I He is our King; and he ſhall be obey'd: Alv. What to deſtroy himſelf, O Particide t >. Dor. Be not Injurious in your fooliſh zeal, But leave him free 5 or by my ſword I ſwear, To hew that Arm away, that ſtops the paſſage To his Eternal reſt. t º ſ Anto. ſetting Let him be Guilty of his own death if he go his hold.] pleaſes: for I'l: not be guilty of mine : by holding him. - 7he King ſhakes off Alvarez . . . . . . . . . . . . 24varez, to Dorax... Infernal Fiend, Is this a Subjećts part? . . . . . . r - . . . . . . . . Dor.
Page 125

- - - - (125) Dor, 'Tis a Friends Office. He has convinc'd me that he ought to dye. . . And, rather than he ſhould not, here's my ſword To help him on his Journey. Seb. My laſt, my only Friend, how kind art thou And how Inhuman theſe ! - Dor. To make the trifle death, a thing of moment! . Sib. And not to weigh th? Important cauſe I had, To rid myſelfoſſife 2 Dor, True : for a Crime. . . So horrid in the face of Men and Angells,.. . . . As wilfull Inceſt is / . . . Seb. Not wilſull neither. Dor. Yes, if you liv'd and with repeated Aćis, . Refreſh'd your Sin, and loaded crimes with crimes, , To ſwell your ſcores of Guilt. Seb. True; if I liv'd. . . . Dor. I ſaid ſo, if you liv'd. º Seb. For hitherto’was fatall ignorance: And no intended crime. Dor, That you beſt know.' - - But the Malicious Worldwill judge the worſt. Alv. O whata Sophiſter has Hell procur'd, To argue for Damnation! Dor. Peace, old Dotard. - - Mankind that always judge of Kings with malice, Will think he knew this Inceſt, and purſu'd it. His only way to reëtify miſtakes, - - And to redeem her honour, is to dye. w Seb. Thou haft it right, my dear, my beſt Alonzo! - And that, but petty reparation too 3. - . But all I have to give. Dor. Your pardon, Sir; . . . . . You may do more, and ought. - seb. What, more than death 3. - (Death. Dor. Death? Why that's Childrens ſport: a Stage-Play, We A&t it every Night we goto bed. Death -
Page 126

- ( 126) . . . . . . . . Death tòa Man in mifery is ſleep. º ... . i Wou'd you; who perpetrated ſuch a Crime, , ...'" . . As frighten’d nature, made the Saints above " ' º Shake Heav'ns Eternal pavement with their trembling, To view that ačt, wou'd you but barely dye 2 - But ſtretch your limbs, and turn on t'other ſide, To lengthen out a black voluptuous ſlumber, And dream you had your Siſter in your arms. - Seb. To expiate this, can I do more then dyer Dor: O yes: you muſt do more; you muſt be damn'd: , You muſt be damn'd to all Eternity. . . - And, ſure, ſelf Murder is the readieſt way. Seb. How, damn'J f Dor. Why is that News? Alvar. O, horrour ! horrour ! -- - * . . . . . Dor. What, thou a Stateſman, - ". . . . ºn . .” And make a busineſs of Damnation ? . . . . . . . In ſuch a World asthis, why’tis a trade. . . ; The Scriv'ner, uſurer, Lawyer, Shop keeper, - And Soldier, cannot live, but by damnation. . . . . The Polititian does it by advance: … . . . . . . . And gives all gone before-hand. . . . . . Seb. O thou haſt giv'n me ſuch a glimſe of Hell, So puſh'd me forward, even to the brink, - Of that irremeable burning Gulph, ". . . . . . . . . . . That looking in th’Abyſſi, Idare not leap. . . . . . . . . . And now I ſee what good thou meanſt my Soul, ..." " And thank thy pious fraud: Thou haſtindeed, Appear'd a Devill, but didſt an Angelis work... . . . bor. 'Twas the laſt Remedy, to give you leiſure. … For, if you cou’d but think, I knew you ſafe. . . . . . . Seb. I thank thee, my Alonzo : I will live: , , But never more to Portugall return : - - - For, to go back and reign, that were to ſhow Triumphant Inceſt, and pollute the Throne. . . Alv. Since Ignorance— tº . . . . '8-b. O, palliate not my wound: . . . . . . . . ". . .
Page 127

(127) When you have argu'd all you can, 'tis Inc.cſt: No, 'tis reſolv'd, Icharge you plead no more; I cannot live without Almeyda's fight, - Nor can I ſee Almeyda but Iſin, Hea’vn has inſpir'd me with a Sacred thought, To live alone to Hea’wn:, and dye to her. Dorax. Mean you to turn an Anchoret? Seb. What elſe? “sº sº The world was once too narrow for my mind, But one poor little nook will ſerve me now ; To hide me from the reſt of humane kinde. Affrique has deſarts wide enough to hold - Millions of Monſters, and Iam, ſure, the greateſt. Alv. You may repent, and wiſh your Crown too late. Seb. Onever, never: I am paſt a Boy, A Scepter's but a play thing, and a Globe A bigger bounding Stone... He who can leave Almeyda, may renounce the reſt with eaſe. ' Dorax. OTruly great! - - A Soul fix’d high, and capable of Hea’vn. Old as he is your uncle Cardinall, Is not ſo far enamour’d of a Cloyſter, - But he will thank you, for the Crown you leave him. Seb, To pleaſe him more, let him believe me dead : That he may never dream I may return. - 4lonzo, I am now no more thy King, But ſtill thy Friend, and by that holy Name, Adjure thee, to perform my laſt requeſt. Make our Conditions with yon Captive King, Secure me but my Solitary Cell 5 'Tis all I ask him for a Crown reſtor’d. Dor. I will do ſabre : º - .. But fear not Muley-Zeyden; his ſoft mettall Melts down with eaſy warmth; runs in the mould, And needs no farther forge. - . - Exit Dorax. - Æe-enter * tº:... . t --- - ---- -
Page 128

(118) -- tº Re-enter Almeyda, led by Morayma, and follow a . . . . . . . by her Attendants. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . -" -- ...º. tº :: * ~ : seb. See where ſhe comes again. ºf By Hea’vn when I behold thoſe beauteous eyes, . . . . . Repentance laggs and Sin comes hurrying on. ----. Alm. This is too cruell! ": i , !! . Seb. Speak'ſt thou of Love, of Fortune, or of Death, Or double Death, for we muſt part Almeyda. * - Alm. I ſpeak of all. - For all things that belong to us are cruell. But what's moſt cruell, we muſt love no more. ..., O'tis too much that I muſt never ſee you, … tº *:: But not to löve you is impoſſible: . . . . . . . . . . . No, I muſt love you : Hea’vn may bate me that, ... . . . . And charge that Sinfull Sympathy of Souls; Upon our Parents, when they lov'd too well. . . . … (thine. Seb. Good Hea’vn, thou ſpeakſt my thoughts,and 1 ſpeak Nay then there’s Inceſt in our very Souls. Tº . . . . For we were form'd too like. . . . . . . . . . . Alm. Too like indeed, - . . . . . . . . . . . And yet not for each other. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 'Sure when we part (for I reſolv’d it too. :- ſº ſº, . Tho' you propos'd it firſt,) however diſtant, º, . . . . We ſhall be ever thinking of each other. . . . . . . . . . . And, the ſame moment, for each other pray. . . . - . - - - - Seb. But if a wiſh ſhou’d come a thwart quº pray: rs! :... ºf Alm. It wou'd do well to curb it.: if we cou’d.; toot'. º y Seb. We cannot look upon each others face, coºl, ... . But, when we read our love, we read out guilt, … . . . . And yet methinks I cannot chuſe but love; ; ; ; ; ; , . . Alm, I wou'd have ask'd you, if I durſt for ſhame, lºsſ if ſtill you lov'd you gave it Airbefore me.º. c. 1.4 Ah why were we not born both of a Sex; sº ſº, , i. For then we might have lov’d, without a Crime!... . . . . . Why was not Iyour Brother ? though that wiſh Iuwolvd our Parents guilt, we had not parted; - - -- - - - - - - -
Page Scan 143

º (11.9 ) . we had becn Friends, and Friendſhip is hot inceſt. Seb. Alas, I know not by what mattic to call thee! Siſter and wife are the two deareſt Nanſes, And I wou'd call thee both 5 and both are sin. Unhappy we! that ſtill we mitiſt confound . . ." . . The deareſt Namcs, into a contion Curſe." ... Alm, To love, and be belov'd, and yet be wrctiched : . . Seb. To have but one poor night of all our lives ; It was indeeda glorious; guilty night: - So happy, that,forgive me Hea’vn, I wiſh With all its guilt, it were to come again. . . . . . . Why did we know ſo ſoon, or why at all, That Sin cou’d be conceal’d in ſuch abliſſe? Alm. Men have a larger priviledge of words, Elſe I ſhou’d ſpeak: but we muſt part, Sebaſtian, That's all the name that I have left to call thee. I muſt not call thee by the name I wou'd; But when I ſay Sebaſtian, dear Sebaſtian, J - I kiſs the name I ſpeak. - Seb. We muſt make haſt, or we ſhall never part. I wou'd ſay ſomething that's as dear as this 5. Nay, wou'd do more than ſay: one moment longer, And Iſhou'd break through Laws Divine, and Humane; And think 'em Cobwebs, ſpred for little man, - Which all the bulky herd of nature breaks. The vigorous young world, was ignorant Of theſe reſtriëtions, 'tis decrepit now; Not more devout, but more decay'd, and cold. . . . All this is impious; therefore we muſt part: - For, ..º. at thy fight, ... . . . And, once burnt down to tinder, li; ht again * Much ſooner then before.” Renterporax. . als. Here comes theſid denouncer of my fats, Townline murmukhal ºpinions ~~ --- - Avvº.
Page Scan 144

(, ; }9). While I, as on my Death-bed, hear the ſound, , That warns me hence for ever, . . . . . . . . . . - [Sebaſtian to, Now be brief, 2 Dorax. And I will try to liſten, And ſhare the minute that remains,betwixt The care I owe my Subjects and my Love. . . Dorax. Your fate has gratif'd you all ſhe can; Gives eaſy miſery, and makes Exile pleaſing. I truſted Muley Zeydan, as a friend, - But ſwore him firſt to Secreſy: he wept - Your fortune, and with tears, not ſqueez'd by Art, , But ſhed from nature, like a kindly ſhower : In ſhort, he proffer'd more than I demanded; A ſafe retreat, agentle Solitude, . Unvex'd with noiſe, and undiſturb’d with fears: ". I choſe you one,— . . . . . . . . . - - º - * ~ - 1 - * . I . . . . - - Alm. Odo not tell me where: . . . For if I knew the place of his abode,. . . . I ſhou'd be tempted to purſue his ſteps, And then we both were loſt. … - Seb. Evn paſt redemption. 2 : " : " . . . . .” " For, if I knew thou werton that deſign, . . . . . . . . (As I muſt know, becauſe our Souls are one.) . . . . I ſhou'd not wander but by ſure Inſtinét, . . . . . . . . Shou'd meet thee juſt halfway, in pilgrimaged . . . . And cloſe for ever , for Iknow my love . . . . . . . . . . More ſtrong than thine, and I more frail, than thou..., - Alm. § me not that: for I muſt boaſt my Crime, , And cannot bear that thouſhoud'ſt better love. . . . . Dorax. I may inform you both.; for you muſt go, . . . Where Seas, and winds, and Deſºrts will divide you..., ...; Under the ledge of Atlas, ;:...” 3, ... . . . - Cut in the living Rock, by Natures hands: " " ' " ' The Venerable Seat of holy Hermites. . . Who there, ſecure in ſeparated 3. - Sacredev'n to the Moors, enjoy Payotion:hºo gº; als. And from the purlingStreams and ſavagº fruits, i. "Hå ... tº - *** - - - - . . . - - - - - - - - ir ºf 2 º' - a . . . . . . . * * * * - *** - .
Page Scan 145

(13 ) Have wholeſome bev'rage, and unbloudy feaſts. Seb. 'Tis pennance too Voluptuous, for my Crime. Dor, Your Subjećts, conſcious of your life are few: But all deſirous to partake your Exile; - And to do office to your Sacred Perſon. The reſt who think you dead, ſhall be diſmiſs'd, Under ſafe Convoy till they reach your Fleet. | Alm. But how am wretched Ito be diſpos'd? A vain Enquiry, ſince I leave my Lord: For all the world beſide is Baniſhment! Dor. I have a Siſter, Abbeſſe in Tercera's, Who loſt her Lover on her Bridall day.— . Alm. There, fate provided me a fellow-Turtle; To mingle fighs with ſighs, and tears with tears, Dor, Laſt, for my ſelf, if I have well fullfill'd My ſad Commiſſion, let me beg the boon, To ſhare the ſorrows of your laſt receſs: ...And mourn the Common loſſesofour loves. ... * Av. And what becomes of me? muſt I be leſt, As Age and time had worn me out of uſef) heſe Sinews are not yet ſo mueh unſtrung, To fail me when my Maſter ſhou'd be ſerv’d; And when they are, then will I ſteal to death ; Silent, and unobſerv'd, to ſave his tears, Jeb. I've heard you both Alvarez have thy wiſh. But thine Alonzo, thine, is too unjuſt. - I chargethee with my laſt Commands, return, And bleſs thy Piolante with thy vows, - Antonio, be thou happy too, in thine. Laſt, let me ſwear you all to Secreſy; And to conceal my ſhame conceal my life. Dor. Ant, Mor. We ſwear to keep it ſecret, Alm. Now I wou'd ſpeak the laſt farewell, I cannot, It wou'd be ſtill farewell, a thouſand times: And, multiply'd in Eccho's, ſtill farewell. I will not ſpeak; but think at...ouſand thouſand; And be thou ſilent too, my laſt *: •
Page Scan 146

. . ( ; ; ; ). So let us part in the dumb pomp of grief. - My heart's too great; or I wou'd dye this moment: … . But Death I thank him, in an hour, has made ". . . . . . A mighty journey, and I haſt to meet him: ". . . . (she ſtaggers and her Women hold her up) Seb. Help to ſupport this feeble, drooping *This tender Sweet, ſo ſhaken by the ſtorm. - - - For theſe fond arms muſt, thus be ſtretch'd in vain, And never; never muſt embrace her more. -- Tispaſt:—my Souls goes in that word;—farewell. Hower: Alvarez goes with Sebaſtian to one end of the Stage. Women with . . . . . . . . . . . . - .* * Almeyda to the other. t • cº- - -- - tº e Dorax, coming up to Antonio and Morayma, who ſtand on the Middle of the Stage. * . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ', ' , , , , , , ; Dor Haſt to attend Almeyda: for your ſake. Your Father is forgiven : but to Antonio . Heforfeits half his Wealth; be happy both:- And let Sebaſtian and Almeyda's Fate, ... . . . . . . This dreadfull Sentence to the World relate, . . . … That unrepented Crimes efDarents dead, Are juſtly puniſh'd on their Childrenshead. - - - 1. * * * y - F 1 N I S. . . . . P R o Lo Gu E.

End of Section 7. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 8
Page Scan 147

Sent to the Authour by in unknown hand, and propos'd to beſººn - - By Mrs. Monford draft like an offer. , , , - > l Bº. Beauties who in awfull Circle ſº, And you grave Synod of the dreadfull Pir, And you the Upper-tire of pºp-gun wir. - Pray caſe me of my ronder if you may * * * * Is all this Crowd barely to ſee the play. Oriºt the Poets Execution dy? - - º Płis breath is in your hand, I will preſume . But I adviſe y a to deferr bis docm : * Till you cav, got a better in his room. And don't maliriouſly combine together, As if in fight and ſpleen you were come hither, For he has kept the Pen tho' loft the feather. *And on my Honour Ladies I avow, • This Play was writ in Charity to you, For ſuch a dearth of Wit whoever knew 2 Sure 'tis a judgment on this Sinfull Nation. For the abuſe of ſo great Diſpenſation: . . . And therefore I reſolv'd to change Vocation, , For want of Petty-coat I’ve put on buff, To try what may be got by lying rough: How think you Siri, is it not well enough f of Bully Criticks I aſſroup woºdltad; - z - Aint one reply'd, thank youthere’s no ſuch need, I at Groom-Porters Sir can ſafer bleed. Another who the name of danger loathſ, - Wow'd he would go, and ſwore me Forty Oathſ, But that his Horſes were in body-cloathi, - Athird - - - - - - - - third *
Page Scan 148

ºth delyd, pammy bloud, I'd be conteui . . . . . . To puſh my Fºrtune, if the Parliament - Wºuld but recall Claret from Baniſhment. 4 Fourth (and I have done) made thiſ excuſe Pde draw my Sword in Ireland Sir to chuſe Had not their Womengouty lºgg, and wore no ſhoeſ! Wil, I may marth though I and fight and trugº, ſº." . Thyther would fight ºn juſt as here theyjudge. - ... Here they will pay for leave to find a fault, But when their Honour calls they can't be bought, Honour in danger,hloud and wound, is ſought, Left Wirtus whether fled, or where's thy dwelling, Who can reveal, at leaſt 'tis paſt my telling, - ºnleſ; thou art Embarkt for Iniskelling on carrion tits thoſe Sparks denounce their rage - - In boot of wift and Leinſter freeſt ingage, - * * What wouldyou do inſuch an Equipage * - * . The Siege of Derry does you Gallants threaten - Not on of Errant ſhame of being beaten, A fear of wanting meat ºr being eaten . . . . . .” Were Wit like honour to be won by fighting. . . . . . . . . . . . Ham few juſt judge wenld there bººf ºriº || - - - - - - - Thinyon wºuld lºve this Pilanom backbilić, . . . . . roh), Talents lye how to expreſſ your figh' - - But where it he knowſ º: praiſe #. . . . . . . . - roupraft #e comard, but like criticº fight - £aat, he wift,and wean theſe yearling Calveſ ... . . . . . . . . . . . . Whº in yºurServict too art inter faux-braveſ, Thyſſig, and writ and fight, and ~Love') halveſ, º EP I Lo Gu E. ' - - - - -

End of Section 8. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 9
Page Scan 149

Don Sebaſtian, King of Portugall, . Spoken betwixt Antonio and Morajma. Mor, T Quak'd at heart fºr fear the Royal Faſhion - Iš. have ſeduc’d Us two to Separation: To be drawn in, againſtour onn deſire, - * * Poor I to be a Nun, poor You a Fryar. Ant. I trembled when the Old Mans hand may in, . He mould have prov’d we were too near of kins Diſcovering old Intrigues of Love, like t’other, º Betwixt my Father and thy ſinfull Mother; º - To makeº sifter Turkanāchriftian Bºiler. * * . Mor. Excuſe me there; that League ſhou'd have been r ather ºr Betwixt your Mother and my Mufti-Father; . - 'Tis for my own and my Relations Credit . Tour Friends ſhou'd bear the Baſtard, mine ſhou'd get it. An; Sºppoſe ºf two Almeyda and Sebaſtian § With Inceſt prov’d upon us — - - Mor. Without queſtion : Their Conſcience was too queazy of digeſtion. , . ... Ant. Thou woud'ſ have º the Councell of thy Brother And ſinn'd till we repented of each other. Mor. Beaft as you are on Natures Laws to trample; Therefilter that we follow'd their Example d . . - . And

End of Section 9. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 10
Page Scan 150

And ſince all Marriage in Repentance endº,. . . . 'Tis good for us to part while we are Friends. Tº five a Maids remorſes and Confuſiºn; Eºn leave me now before We try Cºncluſions. Ant. To copy their Example firſt make certain Of one good hour like theirs before our parting ; Make a debaucho're Night of Love and Aſadneſs; And marry when we wake in ſoberſº - Mor. I’le follow no new Sečis of your inventing, One Night might coſt me nine lºng months repenting: Firſt wed, and #.you find that life a fetter, - Dye when youpleaſe,theſooner Sir the better:, ... . . . . My wealth wou'd get me love e're I cou’d ask it : . Oh there's a ſtrange Temptation in the Casket: All theſe Toung Sharpers wou'd my gract importune, ...And make me thundring Votes of lives and fortune. ~ — --. — - - - - - - - - 4. - . . . . . . * -- - * * .. * . ." . ^ *- - - -, * * - - - - - - - - * -, -, -, ... . . . ~~ -- - - - a - # - - , , * -- wº-- - ~, - -- - - -- * - * - - - * - *... . - - * -- - - * . . ." -º- ~ - . . . . . . . . . . . [iº. - v Y . . . . º Aº, 9. Tº - ". . . - .*.*.* . . . . . . . . . . . ." . º tº \, , ) vſ. A. º.º. - - . . . . . . . . . . * * * * * - - - . . . -, * : * ~ * * * * * - " -, -, * * ; : . . . . . . º * * , sº ºf * ~, . . . " ... *…* … . . J. . - - - - - - - * . . . . ." • . . . . . - - - * * --- * : * . . . º.º. ... ." . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . tº "... ". . . . . . -- - - * - -
Page Scan 151

Blank page
Page Scan 152

* Ce2. tº t. + | ? / | 4t tº twº ſº º f : z - º ºr ol, * * ***** * * tº st + 2 re. , tº tº . f : ------ - ºf 2 (« £ſ. Cº. */ - 2. &
Page Scan 153

~52 - - -*
Page Scan 154

Blank page
Page Scan 155

Blank page
Page Scan 156

Blank page

This page contains an image.

End of Section 10. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents

End of text. Return to beginning.
