She wou'd if she cou'd : a comedy : as it is acted at the Theater-Royal, by Their Majesties servants / written by Sir George Etherege., . | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
She wou'd if she cou'd : a comedy : as it is acted at the Theater-Royal, by Their Majesties servants / written by Sir George Etherege., .
Author
Etherege, George, 1636-1691 or 1692.Etherege, George, 1636-1691 or 1692.
Published
London :Printed by T. Warren for Henry Herringman, and are to be sold by R. Bentley, J. Tonson, F. Saunders, and T. Bennet,1693.
Description
76 p. ;23 cm (4to)
Rights
Public Domain, Google-digitized.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc1.31175033434294

Table of Contents

    Front Cover
    Title Page on page number 1
    Section 1 on page number 2
    Section 2 on page number 3
    Section 3 on page number 5
    Section 4 on page number 14
    Section 5 on page number 23
    Section 6 on page number 27
    Section 7 on page number 60
    Section 8 on page number 75

Book Text
Front Cover
Page Scan 1

- -

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 2

*=IN THE BEGINNING...



Page Scan 3

Blank page
Page Scan 4

Blank page

End of Front Cover. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Title Page
Page 1

=––– She woud if She coud, “ y a As it is Aard at the THEATER-Ro KAL, By - - Their MAJESTIES Servants. with by . . . Sir GEORGE ETHEREGE. . . . — *_ . . . . . . - - L O N DO N, ; !.- --• - :*-- -- -- —- - Printed by T. Warren for Henry Herringman, and are to be Sold by R. Bentley, j. Tonſon, F. Saunders, and T. Bennet, 1693.

End of Title Page. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 2

- - º - Dramatis Perſonae. IR Oliver Cockwoood, and - Two Country Knights. Sir Joſlin jolley, - Mº* Two honeſt Gentlemen of the Mr. Freeman, Town. My Lady Cockwood, - Ariana, Two Ladies. Kinſ - - young Ladies, Kinlwo- cº ( men of Sir Joſlin jolly's. Mrs. &nty, º My Lady Cockwood's Gentle- - woman. Mrs. Gazette, . . . - - and . . . : Two Exchange-Women. Mrs. Trincket, - . Mr. Rake-hell, A Knight of the Induſtry. . " Thomas, Sir Oliver Cockwood's Man. A Servant belonging to Mr. Courtall. wº. " " - Waiters, Fidlers, and other Attendants. .

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 3

_ - w She woud if She coud A CT L S C E N E 1. A Dining-Rom. Enter Courtall and Freeman, and a Servant bruſhing Courtall. Court. O, ſo, 'tis well; let the Coach be made ready. Serv. It ſhall, Sir. - Court. Well, Franck, what is to be done to day? Free. 'Faith, I think we muſt e'en follow the old Trade; eat well, and 3. our ſelves with - A Bottle or two of good Burgundy, that our Old Acquaintance may look lovely in our Eyes: For, for ought as I ſee, there is no hopes of new. Court. Well! this is grown a wicked Town, it was .Otherwiſe in my Memory; a Gentleman - Should not have gone out of his Chamber, But ſome Civil Officer or other of the Game, Wou’d have been with him, and have given him [Ex. Servant. -Notice, where he might have had a Courſe or Two in the Afternoon. Free. Truly, a good motherly Woman of my Acquaintance Tºother day, talking of the Sins of the Times, ‘Told me, with Tears in her Eyes, That there are a Company of higling Raſcals, who, partly For themſelves, but more eſpecially for ſome Secret Friends, daily foreſtall the Markets; Nay, and that many Gentlemen, who formerly had Been Perſons of great Worth and Honour, are, of late, For ſome private Reaſons, become their own Purveyors, To the utter Decay and Diſencouragement Of Trade and Induſtry. Court. I know there are ſome wary Merchants, Who never truſt their Buſineſs to a Fačtour; - But for my part, I hate the Fatigue, and had . . - . • A 2 - - . Rather
Page 4

4. She wou'd if She cou’d. Rather be bound to back my own Colts, and man -- My own Hawks, than endure the Impertinencies of bringing a young Wench to the Lure. . - Enter Servant. Serv. Sir, there is a Gentlewoman below Deſires to ſpeak with you. - Court. Ha, Freeman, this may be Some lucky Ádventure. , Serv. She ask'd me, if you were alone. Court. And did not you ſay Ay? Serv. I told her, I would go ſee. Court. Go, go down quickly, and tell her, Ham. Franck; prithee let me put thee into this Cloſet awhile. - - Free. Why, may not I ſee her ? Court. Qn my life, thou ſhalt have fair play, And go halves, if it be a purchace that may with Honour be divided ; you may over-hear all : But for decency ſake, in, in, Man. Free. Well, good Fortune attend thee. . . Enter Mrs. Sentry. - * - - Court. Mrs. Sentry, this is a Happineſs Beyond my Expečtation. - Sent. Your humble Servant, Sir. - Court. I hope your Lady’s come to Town? ...'. Sent. Sir Oliver, my Lady, and the whole Family. Well!' we have had a ſad time in the Country: . My Lady’s ſo glad ſhe's come to enjoy the Freedom Of this place again, and, I dare ſay, longs to have The Happineſs of your Company. Court. Did ſhe ſend you hither ? - Sent. Oh no; if ſhe ſhould but know, that I did ſuch a Confident trick, ſhe’d think me a good one, I'faith: the Zeal I have to ſerve you, made me Venture to call in my Way to the Exchange, To tell you the good News, and to let you know Our Lodgings are in james's-ſtreet, at the Black Poſts, Where we lay the laſt Summer. - Court. Indeed it is very obligingly done. Sent. But I muſt needs deſire you to tell my Lady, That you came to the knowledge of this by ſome Lucky chance or other; for I would not be diſcover'd For a World. - - Court. Let me alone, I warrant thee. . *Enier - t-

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 5

She wou'd f She could 5 Enter Servant. Serv. Sir Oliver Cockwood, Sir, is come to wait on you. Sent. Oh, Heaven! my Maſter | my Lady, ºnd my ſelf Are both undone, undone.----- court. 'sDeath! why did you not tell him I was buſie? Sent. For Heavens ſake, Mr. Courtall, . . . . What ſhall I do? - - - Court. Leave, leave trembling, and creep into the - - - Wood-Hole here. [She goes into the Wood-Hole. Enter Sir Oliver. Court. Sir Oliver Cockwoodſ - [Embraces him. Sir Oliv. Honeſt Ned Courtall, by my troth, I think º Thou tak'ſt me for a pretty Wench, thou Hugg'ſt me ſo very cloſe and heartily. Court. Only my joy to ſee you, Sir Oliver, And to welcome you to Town. "- Sir Oliv. Methinks, indeed, I have been an Age abſent, But I intend to redeem the time; and how, and how Stand Affairs’prethee now P Is the Wine good 2. Are the Women kind? - - - - Well, faith a Man had better be a Vagabond In this Town, than a Juſtice of Peace in the Country: I was e'en grown a Sot, for want. Of Gentleman-like Recreations; If a Man. Do but rap out an Oath, the People ſtart . As if a Gun went off; and if one chance But to couple himſelf with his Neighbour's Daughter, without the help of the Parſon of The Pariſh, and leave a little Teſtimony of His kindneſs behind him, there is preſently Such an uproar, that a poor Man is fain to Fly his Country; as for Drunkenneſs, ’tis true, . It may be us'd without Scandal, but the Drink Is ſo abominable, that a Man would forbear it For fear of being made out of love with the Vice. Court. I ſee, Sir Oliver, you continue ſtill - - Your old Humour, and are reſolv’d to break * . . . Your ſweet Lady’s Heart. - Sir Oliv. You do not think me ſure ſo barbarouſly. - linkind, to let her know all this; no, no, theſe. - Are Secrets fit only to be truſted to ſuch Honeſt Fellows as thou art. - . - Court. Well may I, poor Sinner, be excus'd, ſince: A Woman of ſuch rare Beauty, ſuch incomparable. . . . Parts, and of ſuch an unblemiſhed - - - Reputation,
Page 6

6 - She wou'd if She cou’d. = - Reputation, is not able to reclaim you from Theſe wild Courſes, Sir Oliver. - - - Sir Oliv. To ſay the truth, ſhe is a Wife, that no Man Need be aſham'd of, Ned. - Court. I vow, Sir Oliver, I muſt needs blame you, Conſidering how tenderly ſhe loves you, . . . . Sir Oliv, Ay, Ay; the more is her Misfortune, . . And mine too, Ned : I would willingly give thee A pair of the beſt Coach-Horſes in my Štabſe, So thou could'ſt but perſwade her To love me leſs. - - Court. Her Vertue and my Friendſhip, ſufficiently Secure you againſt that, Sir Oliver. Sir Oliv. I know thou wert never married ; , . But has it never been thy Misfortune to have " A Miſtreſs love thee thus entirely 2 . . . Court. It never has been my good Fortune, Sir Oliver. But why do you ask this Queſtioh 2 Sir Oliv, Becauſe then, perchance, thou might'ſt have Been a little ſenſible, what a damn'd trouble it is. * Court. As how, Sir Oliver P . Sir Oliv. Why look thee, thus: For a Man cannot be Altogether ungrateful, ſometimes one is oblig'd To kiſs, and fawn, and toy, and lie fooling an hour . Or two, when a Man had rather, if it were not for The Diſgrace ſake, ſtand all that while in the Pillory, Paulted with rotten Eggs and Oranges. Court. This is a very hard caſe indeed, Sir Oliver. Sir Oliv. And then the Inconvenience of keeping Regular Hours; but above all, that damn'd Fiend, jealouſie, does ſo poſſeſs theſe paſſionate Lovers, That I proteſt, Ned, Under the Roſe be it ſpoken, If I chance to be a little prodigal in my Expence, On a private Friend, or ſo, I am call'd to ſo ſtrićt An account at night, that, for Quietneſs ſake, I am Often forc’d to take a Doſe of Cantharides, - To make up the Summ. - 2 º' Court. Indeed, Sir Oliver, every thing conſider'd, You are not ſo much to be envy'd, As one may raſhly imagine. . . - ... " Sir Oliv. Well, a Pox of this tying Man and Woman Together, for better, for worſe!, upon my Conſcience, It was but a Trick, that the Clergy might have A feeling in the Cauſe. . " . . Court. I do not conceive it to be much for their Profit, Sir Oliver: for I dare lay a good Wager, Let’em but allow Chriſtian Liberty, and they -- ----
Page 7

2 - She wou'd if She could. Shall get ten times more by Chriſtnings, Than they are like to loſe by Marriages. | Sir Oliv. 'Faith, thou haſt hit it right, Ned; And now thou taikºſt of Chriſtian Liberty, — Prithee, let us dine together today, - And be ſwingingly merry, but with all Secrecy. Court. I ſhall be glad of your good Company, Sir Oliver. Sir Oliv...I am to call on a very honeſt Fellow, whom * I left here hard by, making a Viſit, Sir joſlin jolly, A Kinſman of my Wife's, and my Neighbour in the Country: We call Brothers, he came up to Town With me, and lodgeth in the ſame Houſe; • He has brought up a couple of the prettieſt Kinſwomen, Heireſſes of a very good Fortune: Would thou Hadſt the inſtrućting of 'em a ſittle. Faith, if I am not very much miſtaken, They are very prone to the Study -- a Of the Mathematicks. - court. I ſhall be beholden to you For ſo good an Acquaintance. Sir Oliv. This Sir joſlin is in great Favour with my Lady, one that ſhe has an admirable good Opinion of, and will truſt me with him Any where; but to ſay truth, he is as arrant A Sinner as the beſt of us, and will boggle at . Nothing that becomes a Man of Honour. We will go and get leave of my Lady;. For it is not fit I ſhould break out ſo ſoon, Without her Approbation, Ned. Court. By no means, Sir Oliver. Sir Oliv. Where ſhall we meet about an hour hence 2 Court. At the French Houſe, or the Bear. - Sir Oliv. At the French Houſe by all means. Court. Agreed, Agreed. ; Sir Oliv. Would thou could'ſt bring a fourth Man. Court. What think you of Franck Freeman?. | Sir Oliv. There cannot be a better----- well----- Servant, Ned; Servant, Ned' - Court. Your Servant, Sir Oliver. Mrs. Sentry? Sent. in the Hole..] Is he gone? Court. Ay, Ay H You may venture to bolt now. Sent. crawling out...] Oh, Heavens! I would not. Endure ſuch another Fright. Court. Come, come, prithee be compos'd. - ... • Sent. I ſhall not be my ſelf again this Fortnight; I never was in ſuch a taking, days of my Life. [Ex. Sir Oliver. To
Page 8

8 She wou'd if She wa To have been found falſe, and to one, who, to . Say truth, has been always very kind - And civil to me : but above aii, I was concern’d For my Lady’s Honour------ . . . . Court. Come, CGme------ -- there's no harm done. Sent. Ah! Mr. Courtall, you do not know Sir Oliver So well as I do ; he has ſtrange Humours ſometimes, And has it enough in his Nature to play the - Tyrant, but that my Lady and my ſelf Aw him by our Policy. - Court. Well, well, all's well ; Did you not hear. What a tearing Blade Sir Oliver is ? .. Sent. Ah! 'tis a vile diſſembling Man. How fairly He carries it to my Lady’s Face | But I dare not Diſcover him, for fear of betraying my ſelf. Court. Well, Mrs. Sentry, I muſt dine with 'em, And after I have enter'd them with a Beer-glaſs, Or two, if I can, I will ſlip away, And pay my Reſpects to your Lady. . Sent. You need not queſtion your welcome, I aſſure you, Sir------ Your Servant, Sir. . . . . . Court. Your Servant, Mrs. Sentry; I am very ſenſible Of this Favour, I aſſure you. - . Sent. I am proud it was in my power To oblige you, Sir. - Court. Freeman Come, come out of thy Hole; How haft thou been able to contain? . - Free. Faith, much ado, the Scene was very pleaſant: But, above all, I admire thy Impudence, - I cou’d never have had the Face to have ..Wheadled the poor Knight ſo. - - Court. Piſh, Piſh; 'twas both neceſſary and honeſt : ... We ought to do all we can to confirm A Husband in the good º of his Wife. Free. Pray how long, if, without offence, a Man may Ask you ; Have you been in good Grace with this Perſon Of Honour? I never knew you had that - Commendable Quality of Secrecy before. Court. You are miſtaken, Freeman ; things go not As you wickedly imagine. . . Free. Why, haſt thou loſt all ſenſe of Modeſty 2 Doſt thou think to paſs theſe groſs Wheadles on Me too 2 Come, come ; this good News ſhou'd make . - Thee a little mérrier... 'Faith, though ſhe be an old Acquaintance, ſhe has the advantage of four or five Months Abſence, 'slid, I know not how proud You are, but I have thought my ſelf very ſpruce [Exit Sentry. .
Page 9

2 - - - - She wou'd if She could. . . . . 9 Ere now in an old Sute, that has been bruſh'd - * * - And laid up awhile. - - -- court. Freeman, I know in Caſes of this Nature thou ". . Art an Infidel; but yet methinks the Knowledge Thou haſt of my ſincere dealing with my * Friends ſhould make thee a little more confiding. Free. What deviliſh Oath could ſhe invent to . Fright thee from a Diſcovery 2 - Court. Wilt thou believe me, if I ſwear, the Preſervation • Of her Honour, has been my Fault, and not hers ? Free. This is ſomething. - - Court. Why then, know that I have ſtill been as Careful to prevent all Opportunities, as ſhe has been to Contrive 'em ; and ſtill have carried it ſo like A Gentleman, that ſhe has not had the leaſt ſuſpicion Of unkindneſs. She is the very Spirit of Impertinence, So fooliſhly fond and troubleſome, that no Man above Sixteen is able to endure her. - - Free. Why did you engage thus far then 2 * - Court. Some Conveniences which I had by my 'Acquaintance with the Sother Husband, made Me extraordinary civil to her, which preſently - By her Ladiſhip was interpreted after the manner - Of the moſt obliging Women. This Wench came Hither by her Commiſſion to day. Free. With what Confidence ſhe deny'd it! Court. Nay, that's never wanting, I aſſure you: Now is it expe&ted I ſhould lay by all other Occaſions, and watch every Opportunity to wait upon her; ſhe would by her good Will give her Lover no more reſt, than a young Squire that Has newly ſet up a Coach, does his only Pair of Horſes. Free. 'Faith, if it be as thou ſay’ſt, I cannot much Blame the Hardneſs of thy Heart. But did Not the Oaf talk of two young Ladies 2 Court. Well remember'd, Franck, and now I think On’t, 'twill be very neceſſary to carry on my Buſineſs With the old one, that we may the better have An Opportunity of being acquainted with them. Come, let us go, and beſpeak Dinner, and by the Way conſider of theſe weighty Affairs. - - Free. Well, ſince there is but little ready Money + -Stirring, rather than want Entertainment, - I ſhall be contented to play awhile upon Tick. - * - Court. And I, provided they promiſe fair, and we find There's hopes of Payment hereafter. - Free. Come along, come along. - - [Excunt. - B - - . A CT ->
Page 10

I O. She wou'd if She cou’d. sc E N E II. Sir Oliver Cockwood’s Lodging. • Enter Lady Cockwood. La. Cock. 'Tis too late to repent: I ſent her, but yet I cannot but be troubled to think ſhe ſtays ſo long : Sure, if ſhe has ſo little Gratitude to let him, he has More Honour than to attempt any thing to the Prejudice of my Affection-----Oh------Sentry, are you come 3- Enter Sentry. Sent. Oh Madam ſº there has been ſuch an Accident La. Cock. Prithee do not fright me, Wench----- Sent. As I was diſcourſing with Mr. Courtall, in came. Sir Oliver. La. Cock. Oh!----- I'm ruin'd----- undone for ever ! Sent. You'll ſtill be ſending me on theſe deſperate Errands. - - La. Cock. I am betray’d, betray’d— by this Falſe----- what ſhall I call thee P - Sent. Nay, but, Madam— have a little patience------ La. Cock. I have loſt all Patience, and will never More have any—-- Sent. Do but hear me, all is well------- La. Cock. Nothing can be well, unfortunate Woman!' Sent. Mr. Courtall thruſt me into the Wood-hole. La. Cock. And did not Sir Gliver ſee thee? Sent. He had not the leaſt Glimpſe of me-------- La. Cock. Dear Sentry------ and what good News 2 Sent. He intends to wait upon you in the Afternoon, Madam----- - La. Cock. I hope you did not let him know I ſent you." Sent. No, no, Madam----- I’ll warrant you I did every, Thing much to the Advantage of your Honour. Ła. Cock. Ah, Sentry! if we could but think of ſome. Lucky Plot now to get Sir Oliver out of the way. Sent. You need not trouble your ſelf about that, Madam, he has engag’d to dine with Mr. Courtal at the: French-Houſe, and is bringing Sir joſlin jolly to get Your good Will ; when Mr. Courtall has fix’d 'em. With a Beer-Glaſs or two, he intends to ſteal, Away, and pay his Devotion to your Ladiſhip. . Ła. Cock. Truly, he is a Perſon of much Wortº Ayid Honour, , - - ---
Page 11

3 * * - _ _x- - - She wou'd if She could II Sent. Had you but been there, Madam, to have - Over-heard Sir Oliver's Diſcourſe, he would have Made you bleſs your ſelf; there is not ſuch another Wild Man in the Town; all his Talk was of Wenching and ſwearing, and drinking, and tearing. La. Cock, Ay, Ay, Sentry; I know he'll talk of Strange Matters behind my back ; but if he be not An abominable Hypocrite at home, and am not I a Woman eaſily to be deceived, he is notable To play the Sparkabroad thus, I aſſure you. * - Enter Sir Oliver, and Sir Joſlin ; Sir Joſlin ſinging. My deareſt Dear, this is kindly done of thee To come home agen thus quickly. Sir Oliv. Nay, my Dear, thou ſhalt never have any Juſt Cauſe to accuſe me of unkindneſs. La, Cock. Sir foſlin, now you are a good Man, and I ſhall truſt you with Sir Oliver agen. - Sir joſ. Nay, if I ever break my word with a Lady, I will be deliver'd bound to Mrs. Sentry here, - And ſhe ſhall have leave to carve me for a Capon. - Sent. Do you think I have a Heart cruel enough - - For ſuch a bloody Execution. - Sirjoſ. Kindly ſpoke, i'faith, Girl; I'll give thee. A Buſs for that." La. Cock. Fie, fie, Sir joſlin, this is not ſeemly in my Preſence. - Sirjoſ. We have all our Failings, Lady, and this is Mine: A right bred Grey-hound can as well forbear Running after a Hare, when he ſees her, as I can . Mumbling a pretty Wench, when ſhe comes in my way. La. Cock. I have heard, indeed, you are a parlous Man, "Sir joſlin. - - Sirjoſ. I ſeldom brag, Lady; but for a true Cock of The Game, little joſlin dares match with the beſt of 'em. Sir Oliv. Sir joſlin's merry, my Dear. . . La. Cock. Ay, Ay; if he ſhould be wicked, I know -Thou art too much a Gentleman, to offer an Injury To thine own dear Lady. - -- Sir joſ. Faith, Madam, you muſt give my Brother Cockwood leave to dine abroad to day. La. Cock. I proteſt, Sir joſlin, you begin to make Me hate you too; well you are e'en grown as bad As the worſt of 'em you are ſtill robbing me of The ſweet Society of Široliver. - Sirjoſ. Come, come; your Diſcipline is too - - B 2. Severe [Kiſts her.
Page 12

- 2 y - 2 I 2. She wou'd if She cou’d. Severe, i'faith, Lady. ' - La. Cock. Sir Oliver may do what he pleaſes, Sir; He knows I have ever been his obedient Lady. Sir Oliv. Prithee, my Dear, be not angry, | Sir Joſeph was ſo earneſt in his Invitation, that none But a Clown could have refus’d him. - - Sirjoſ. Ay, Ay; we dine at my uncle Sir Joſeph jolly's Lady. La. Cock. Will you be ſure now to be a good Dear, And not drink, nor ſtay out late 2 Sirjoſ. I’ll engage for all, and if there be no Harm in a merry Catch, or a waggiſh Story------ Enter Ariana, and Mrs. Gatty. Ha, Ha! Sly-Girl, and Mad-Cap, are you got up? I know what you have been meditating on; But never trouble your Heads, let me Alone to bring you Conſolation. Gatty. We have often been beholden to you, Sir ; For every time he's drunk, he brings us,’ Home a Couple of freſh Servants. Sir Oliv. Well, farewel, my Dear, prithee do not Sigh thus, but make thee ready, viſit, and be merry. La. Cock. I ſhall receive moſt Satisfaction In my Chamber. Sir joſ. Come, come along, Brother: Farewel One and all; Lady and Sly-Girl, Sly-Girl and Mad-Cap; our Servant, your Servant-------- La. Cock, to Sentry aſide.J. Sentry, is the New Point I bought, come home 2 and is every thing in a Readineſs? Sent. Every thing, Madam. - - La. Cock. Come, come up quickly then, Girl, and Aria. Doſt not thou wonder, Gatty, ſhe ſhould be So ſtrangely fond of this Coxcomb? - Gatty. Well, if ſhe does not diſſemble, may I ſtill Be diſcover'd when I do; didſt thou not ſee how Her Countenance chang'd, as ſoon as ever their Backs were turn'd, and how earneſtly ſhe whiſper'd With her Woman 2 there is ſome weighty Affair In hand, I warrant thee: My dear Ariana, how Glad am I we are in this Town agen. Aria. But we have left the Benefit of the freſh Air, and the Delight of Wandring in the Pleaſant Groves, Dreſs me. [Ex, Lady Cockwood and Sentry. - [Exeunt Sir Oliver, and Sir Joſlin ſinging, Gatty.
Page 13

She would if She cond I 3 Gatty. Very pretty things for a young Gentlewoman . . . To bemoan the Loſs of indeed, that’s newly come to A Rºliſh of the good things of this world. Aria. Very good, Siſter | Gatty. Why, haſt not thou promis'd me A thouſand times to leave of this Demureneſs? Aria. But you are ſo quick. - Gatty. Why, would it not make any ºn: mad to hear Thee bewail the Loſs of the Country Speak But one grave Word more, and it ſhall be my daily Prayers thou may’ſt have a jealous Husband, then You'll have enough of it, I warrant you. ... Aria. It may be, if your Tongue be not altogether So nimble, I may be conformable: But I hope You do not intend we ſhall play ſuch mad Freaks As we did laſt Summer ? - Gatty. 'slife, doſt thou think we come here to be Mew’d up, and take only the Liberty of going from our Chamber to the Dining-Room, and from the Dining-Room to our Chamber again? and like a Bird in a Cage, with two Perches only, to hop up and down, up and down? Aria. Well, thou art a mad Wench. Gatty. Would'ſt thou never have us go to a Play But with our grave Relations, never take the Air but With our grave Relations? To feed their Pride, And make the World believe it is in their Power To afford ſome Gallant or other a good Bargain 2 Aria. But I am afraid we ſhall be known again. Gatty. Piſh the Men were only acquainted with Our Vizards, and our Petticoats, and they are wore Out long ſince : How I envy that Sex ; Well! We Cannot plague 'em enough, when we have it in Our Power, for thoſe Privileges which Cuſtom Has allow'd 'em above us. . . - Aria. The truth is, they can run and ramble here “ And there, and every where, and we, poor Fools, . Rather think the better of 'em. - Gatty. From one Play-houſe, to the other Play-houſe, And if, they like neither the Play, nor the Women, They ſeldom ſtay any longer than the combing Of their Perriwigs, or a whiſper or two with A Friend ; and then they cock their Caps, and out they Strut again. - - Aria. But whatſoever we do, prithee now let us Reſolve to be mighty honeſt. Gatty. There l agree with thee. *…* Aria,

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 14

- . Tº - 2 - 2 14. She wou'd if She could. Aria. And if we find the Gallants like lawleſs Subjećts, who the more their Princes grant, The more they impudently crave. Gatty. We'll become abſolute Tyrants, and deprive 'Em of all the Privileges we gave 'em------- Aria. Upon theſe Conditions I am contented to trail A Pike under thee------ March along, Girl. [Exeunt. º ACT II. SCENE 1. The Mulberry Garden. v Enter Courtall and Freeman. Court. WA S there ever a Couple of Pops better match'd, Than theſe two Knights are: - Free. They are Harp and Violin, Nature has ſo Tun'd 'em, as if ſhe intended they ſhould Always play the Fool in Conſort. - Court. Now is Sir Oliver ſecure; for he dares not go Home’till he's quite drunk, and then he grows Valiant, inſults, and defies his ſweet Lady ; - For which, with Prayers and Tears, he's forc’d To feign a bitter Repentance the next Morning. Frce. What do we here idling in the Mulberry Garden? Why do not we make this Viſit then P Court. Now art thou as mad upon this Trail, as if We were upon a hot Scent. - Free. Since we know the Buſh, why do we not ſtart The Game 2 - Court. Gently, good Franck : Firſt, know that the Laws Of Honour preſcrib'd in ſuch nice Caſes, will Not allow me to carry thee along with me ; and next, Haſt thou ſo little Wit to think, that a diſcreet Lady, that has had the Experience of ſo much humane Frailty, can have ſo good an Opinion of the Conſtancy Of her Servant, as to lead him into Temptation ? Free. Then we muſt not hope her Ladiſhip ſhou'd Make us acquainted with theſe Gentlewomen. Court. Thou may’ſt as reaſonably expečt, that an Old Rook ſhould bring a young Snap acquainted With his Bubble; but Advantages may be - Hereafter made, by my Admiſſion into the Family. " Frve. What is to be done then? - Court.
Page 15

- 2 - 2 - 2 º' She wou'd if She could Court. Why, look you, thus I have contriv'd it: Sir Oliver, when I began to grow reſty, that he º Might incline me a little more to Drunkenneſ, In my Ear diſcover'd to me the Humour of His dear Friend Sir joſlin: He aſſur’d me, that When he was in that good natur'd Condition, . To requite their Courteſie, he always carried The good Company home with him, and Recommended them to his Kinſwomen. Free. Very good! Court. Now after the freſh Air has breath'd on us Awhile, and expell'd the Vapours of the Wine : We have drunk, thou ſhalt return to theſe Two Sots, whom we left at the French Houſe, According to our Promiſe, and tell 'em, I am A little ſtay’d by ſome unlucky Bus'neſs, and Will be with 'em preſently; thou wilt find 'em Tir'd with long fight, weak and unable to obſerve Their Order; charge 'em briskly, and in a moment Thou ſhalt rout’em, and with little or no damage To thy ſelf, gain an abſolute Vićtory. Free. Very well! Court. In the mean time, I will make my viſit to the Longing Lady, and order my Buſineſs ſo Handſomely, that I will be with thee again immediately, To make an Experiment of the good Humour of , Sir joſlin. J. Free. Let’s about it! Court.” Tis yet too early; we muſt drill away a little Time, that my Excuſes may be more probable, And my Perſecution more tolerable. Enter Ariana and Gatty with Vizards, and paſs nimbly over the Stage. - Free. Ha, Ha---- How wantonly they trip it! there is Temptation enough in their very Gate, to Stir up the Courage of an old Alderman: Prithee let us follow 'em. . - Court. I have been ſo often balk'd with theſe Wizard-Masks, That I have at leaſt a dozen times Forſworn 'em ; they are a moſt certain Sign Of an ill Face, or what is worſe, an old - Acquaintance. - Free. The truth is, nothing but ſome ſuch weighty Reaſon, is able to make Women deny themſelves. The Pride they have to be ſeen.
Page 16

- - 2 º - 2 I 6 She wou'd if She cou’d. - Court. The Evening's freſh and pleaſant, and yet There is but little Company. Free. Our Courſe will be the better; theſe Deer Cannot Herd : Come, come, Man, let's follow, Court. I find it is a meer Folly to ſwear any Thing; it does put make the Devil more - Earneſt in his Temptation. [They go after the Women, - Enter Women again, and croſs the Stage, Aria. Now if theſe ſhould prove two Men of War That are cruiſing here, to watch for Prizes. Gatty. Would they had Courage enough to ſet upon lls. I long to be engaged. Aria. Look, look yonder; I ploteſt they chaſe us. Gatty. Let us bear away then ; if they be truly valiant They’ll quickly make more Sail, and board us. . - [The Women go out, and go about behind the Scenes to the other Door. Enter Courtall and Freeman. Free. 's Death, how fleet they are whatſoever Fault They have, they cannot be broken-winded. - Court. Sure, by that little mincing ſtep, they Shou'd be Country Fillies, that have been breath’d At Courſe a Park, and Barley Break: We ſhall - Never reach 'em. - Free. I’ll follow direétly; do thou turn down the Croſs-walk and meet 'em. Enter the Women, and after 'em Courtall at the lower Door, and Freeman at the upper, on the contrary ſide. Court. By your Leave, Ladies------ - • Gatty. I perceive you can make bold enough - Without it. - - Free. Your Servant, Ladies------ º Aria. Or any other Ladies that will give themſelves The trouble to entertain you. - Free. 'slife, their Tongues are as nimble as their Heels. Court. Can you have ſo little good Nature to daſh A couple of baſhful young Men out of Countenance, Who came out of pure Love to tender - You their Service P - Gatty...”Twere pity to baulk 'em, Siſtet. Ariá, indeed, methinks they look as if they never Had been ſlippºd before. - Free. Yes, faith, we have had many a fair Courſe
Page 17

air ºl. … . . - She wou'd if She could. 17 In this Paddock, have been very well fleſh'd, And dare boldly faſten. … -- - [They kiſs their hands with a little force. Aria. Well, I am not the firſt unfortunate Woman - That has been forc’d to give her hand, where She never intends to beſtow her Heart. Gatty. Now, do you think 'tis a Bargain already? Court, Faith, would there were ſome luſty Earneſt Given, for fear we ſhould unluckily break Off again. Free. Are you ſo wild, that you muſt be hooded thus P. Court. Fie, fie; put off theſe Scandals to all good Faces. - - Gatty. For your Reputations ſake we ſhall keep 'em On : ’sLife, we ſhould be taken for your Relations, If we durſt ſhew our Faces with you thus - Publickly. - . . - Aria. And what a Shame that would be to a Couple . * Of young Gallants : Methinks you ſhould bluſh - To think on't. - - - Court. Theſe were pretty Toys, invented, firſt, merely For the good of us poor Lovers to deceive - The jealous, and to blind the malicious; but The proper uſe is ſo wickedly perverted, That it makes all honeſt Men hate the - - - Faſhion mortally. ** / Free. A good Face is as ſeldom cover'd with a Vizard-Mask, As a good Hat with an oyl’d Caſe: And yet, on my Conſcience, you are both Handſome. - - - - - Court. Do but remove 'em a little, to ſatisfie a fooliſh - - Scruple. - - . Aria. This is a juſt Puniſhment you have brought Upon your ſelves, by that unpardonable Sin of Talking. - - . Gatty. You can only brag now of your Acquaintance With a Farendon Gown, and a Piece Of black Velvet. Court. The truth is, There are ſome vain Fellows Whoſe looſe Behaviour of late, has given Great Diſcouragement to the honourable Proceedings Of all vertuous Ladies. Free. But I hope you have more Charity, than To believe us of the Number of the Wicked. Aria. There's not a Man of you to be truſted. Gatty. What a Shame is it to your whole Sex, That a Woman is more fit to be a Privy Counſellour, Than a young Gallant a Lower? Court. -
Page 18

- - **** - 2 o 2. 18 She wou'd if She cou’d. * * court. This is a pretty kind of fooling, Ladies, for ‘Men that are idle; but you muſt bid - A little fairer, if you intend to keep us From our ſerious Bus'neſs. Gatty. Truly you ſeem to be Men of grea Imployment, that are every moment ratling from The Eating-Houſes to the Play-Houſes, from the Play-Houſes to the Mulberry-Garden, that Łive in a perpetual Hurry, and have little Leiſure for ſuch an idle Entertainment. - Court. Now would I not ſee thy Face for the World; If it ſhould be but half ſo good as thy Humour, Thou would'ſt dangerouſly tempt me to dote . Ilpon thee, and forgetting all Shame, become Conſtant. ... - Free. I peròive, by your fooling here, that Wit and Good Humour may make a Man in Love with ' A Black-a-moor. That the Devil ſhould contrive It ſo, that we ſhould have earneſt Busneſs now. Court. Wou'd they wou'd but be ſo kind to meetus Here again to morrow. - Gatty. You are full of Bus'neſs, and 'twould but Take you off of your Employments. - Aria. And we are very unwilling to have the Sin to . • Anſwer for, of ruining a Couple of ſuch Hopeful Young Men. - Free. Muſt we then deſpair? "Aria. The Ladies you are going to, will not be ſo. Hard-hearted. N - Court. to Free. On my Conſcience they love us, . And begin to grow jealous already. Free. Who knows but this may prove the luckier Adventure of the two 2 . Court. Come, come, we know you have a Mind toº #. us: We cannot ſee you bluſh, ſpeak it out Boldly. - Gaity. Will you ſwear then, not to viſit any other Women before that time? - Aria. Not that we are jealous, but becauſe we would Not have you tir’d with the Impertinent - Converſation of our Sex, and come to us dull And out of Humour. Court. Invent an Oath, and let it be ſo horrid: 'Twould make an Atheiſt ſtart to hear it. Free. And I will ſwear it readily, that I will not. So much as ſpeak to a Woman, till I. - Speak to you again. - --- Gatty."
Page 19

3 ºf " ſº . º She jou'd if She could 19. ,--- Gatty. But are you troubl’d with that fooliſh Scruple of Keeping an Oath 2 - Free. O moſt religiouſly - Court. And may we not enlarge our Hopes upon a Little better Acquaintance 2 - 2 Aria. You ſee all the Freedom we allow. Gatty. It may be we may be intreated to hear A Fiddle, or mingle in a Countrey Dance, or ſo. Court. Well we are in too deſperate a Condition To ſtand upon Articles, and are reſolv’d to Yield on any Terms. - ‘Free. Be ſure you be punétual now ! - Aria. Will you be ſure ? - Court. Or elſe may we become a Couple of credulous Coxcombs, and be Jilted ever after. ------Your Servant, Ladies. - Aria. I wonder what they think of us! - Gatty. You may eaſily imagine; for they are not of A Humour ſo little in Faſhion, to believe the beſt: I aſſure you, the moſt favourable Opinion they can Have, is, That we are ſtill a little wild, and ſtand in Need of better Manning. . - Aria. Prithee, dear Girl, what doſt think of 'em 2 Gatty. Faith, ſo well, that I’m aſham'd to tell thee. Aria. Would I had never ſeen 'em 1 Gatty. Ha! Is it come to that already ? Aria. Prithee, let’s walk a Turn or two . More, and talk of 'em. . Gatty. Let us take care then we are not too particular In their Commendations, leſt we ſhould diſcover We intrench upon one anothers Inclinations, And ſo grow quarrelſome. SCENE II. Sir Oliver's Lodgings. Enter Lady Cockwood and Sentry. Sent. Dear Madam, do not afflićt your ſelf thus unreaſonably; I dare lay my Life, it is not want Of Devotion, but Opportunity that ſtays him, La. Cock. º ! to be ſo inſenſible Of a Lady’s Paſſion' Sent. If I thought he were ſo wicked, I ſhould Hate him ſtrangely------ But, Madam------ La, Cock. Do not ſpeak one word in his behalf, I am reſolv'd to forget him; perfidious Mortal, To abuſe ſo ſweet an Opportunity? c 2. [Ex. Men. - [Exetint, Señt.
Page 20

zo She woºd if she could Sent. Hark, here is ſome-body coming up ſtairs. La. Cock. Peace, he may yet redeem his Honour. * > Enter Courtall. Court. Your humble Servant, Madam. La. Cock. ſtarting. Mr. Courtall, for Heav'n ſake How came you hither ? -- " - Court. Guided by my good Fortune, Madam----- Your Servant, Mrs. Sentry: - * Sent. Your humble Servant, Sir; I proteſt you made. Me ſtart too, to ſee you come in thus unexpe&tedly. La. Cock. I did not imagine it could be known I was in Town yet. - Court. Sir Oliver Did me the Favour to make me A Viſit, and dine with me to day, which brought Me to the Knowledge of this Happineſs, Madam; And as ſoon as I could poſſibly, I got the Freedom to come hither and enjoy it. La. Cock. You have ever been extreme obliging, Sir, Sent. 'Tis a worthy Gentleman, how punétual He is to my Direčtions ! - La. Cock. Will you be pleas'd to repoſe, Sir Sentry, ſet ſome Chairs. - Court. With much difficulty, Madam, I broke Out of my Company, and was forc’d by the . Importunity of one Sir joſlin jolly, I think they Call him, to engage my Honour, I would Return again immediately. - * La. Cock. You muſt not ſo ſoon rob me Of ſo ſweet a Satisfaction. . . . - Court. No Conſideration, Madam, could take Me from you, but that I know my ſtay at this Time muſt needs endanger your Honour; and how . . Often H have deny'd my ſelf the greateſt Satisfaction - In the World, to keep that unblemiſhed, you . Yblfr ſelf can witneſs. - . . . . . Lä. Cock. Indeed I have often had great Tryals Of your Generoſity, in thoſe many Misfortunes That have attended our innocent Affections. Court. Sir Oliver, Madam, before I did perceive it. . Was got near that Pitch of Drunkenneſs, Which makes him come reeling home, and ilmmanfully inſult over your Ladiſhip; and how Subjećt he is then to injure you with an unjuſt Suſpicion, you have often told me; which makes : Me careful not to be ſurpriz'd here. La. Cock. Repoſe your ſelf a little, but a little, a [Aſide. [Ex. Sént. . Dèar
Page 21

2 - 1 - - • . - - She wou'd if She cou’d. 2 I Dear Sir: Theſe vertuous Principles make you worthy to be - Truſted with a Lady’s Honour: Indeed Sir Oliver - Has his Failings; yet, I proteſt, Mr. Courtall, I love Him dearly, but cannot be altogether unſenſible Of your generous Paſſion. - - Court. Ay, ay ; I am a very paſſionate Lover ! Aſide. Indeed this Eſcape has only given me leiſure To look upon my Happineſs. - La. Cock. Is my Woman retir’d P Court. Moſt dutifully, Madam. La. Cock. Then let me tell you, Sir----- yet we May make very good uſe of it. Court. Now am I going to be drawn in agen. - Aſide. La. Cock. If Sir Oliver be in that undecent Condition You ſpeak of, to morrow he will be very ſubmiſſive, As it is meet for ſo great a Miſdemeanour; then Can I, feigning a deſperate Diſcontent, take My own Freedom, without the leaſt Suſpicion. Court. This is very luckily and obligingly Thought on, Madam. - La. Cock. Now if you will be pleas'd, Make an Aſſignation, Sir. . . Court. Tomorrow about Ten a Clock in the Lower-walk of the New Exchange, out of which We can quickly pop into my Coach. - - - La. Cock. But I am ſtill ſo peſter'd with my Woman; , I dare not go without her; on my Conſcience º She's very ſincere, but it is not good to truſt our Reputations too much to the Frailty of a Servant. Court, I will bring my Chariot, Madam, . That will hold but two. - La. Cock, O moſt ingeniouſly imagin'd, dear Sir! For, , . By that means, I ſhall have a juſt Excuſe to give her - Leave to ſee a Relation, and bid her ſtay - - There till I call her - - Court. It grieves me much to leave you ſo ſoon,” - - Madam; but I ſhall comfort my ſelf with the - Thoughts of the Happineſs you have made me hope for.” La. Cock. I wiſh it were in my power eternally To oblige you, dear Sir. Court. Your humble Servant, Madam. - La. Cock. Your humble Servant, ſweet Sir. . - - - - - - - - - -" - - [Fxit Court, Sentry------ why, Sentry------- Where are you ? - - Eniºr " i;
Page 22

22 She wou'd if She cou’d. - º Enter Sentry. Sent. Here, Madam. La. Cock. What a ſtrange thing is this ' will you Never take warning, but ſtill be leaving me alone In theſe ſuſpicious Occaſions? Sent. I was but in the next Room, Madam. La. Cock. What may Mr. Courtall think of my Innocent Intentions 2 I proteſt, if you ſerve me So agen, I ſhall be ſtrangely angry: You ſhould Have more regard to your Lady’s Honour. Sent. If I ſtay in the Room, ſhe will not ſpeak Kindly to me in a Week after ; and if I go out, ſhe ‘Always chides me thus: This is a ſtrange Infirmity. She has, but I muſt bear with it; for on my - Çonſcience, Cuſtom has made it ſo natural, She cannot help it. f La. Cock. Are my Couſins come home yet? Sent. Not yet, Madam. • La. Cock. Do’ſt thou know whither they went This Evening P. - . . . Sent. I heard them ſay, they would go tak The Air, Madam. La. Cock. Well, I ſee it is impoſſible with vertuous Counſel to reclaim them ; truly, they are ſo careleſs Of their own, I could wiſh Sir joſlin would remove 'Em, for fear they ſhould bring an unjuſt Imputation on my Honour. Sent. Heavens forbid, Madam? La. Cock. Your Servant, Couſins. - - Enter Ariana and Gatty. - - Amb. Your Servant, Madam. - La, Cock. How have you ſpent the Cool of the Evening 2 Gatty. As the Cuſtom is, Madam, breathing the Freſh Air, in the Park and Mulberry-Garden. La. Cock. Without the Company of a Relation, Or ſome diſcreet Body, to juſtifie your Reputations - - To the World----- You are young, and may be yet Inſenſible of it; but this is a ſtrange cenſorious Age, . ." I aſſure you. - [Noiſe of Muſick without. Aria, Hark! What Muſick’s this 2 - - Gatty. I’ll lay my Life my uncle's drunk, and hath Pickt us up a Couple of worthy Servants, • And brought them home with him in Triumph. - - . Enter

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 23

She would if she could 23 Enter the Muſick playing, Sir Oliver ſtrutting, and ſwaggering, Sir Joſlin ſinging * and dancing with Mr. Courtall and Mr. Freeman, in tº hand; Gatty and Ariana ſeeing Courtal and Freeman, ſhriek, and ------ Sirjoſ. Hey-day ! I told you they were a Couple of Skittiſh Fillies, but I never knew 'em boggle - At a Man before; I’ll fetch 'em agen, I warrant You, Boys. [Exit after them, Free, to Court. Theſe are the very ſelf-ſame Gowns And Petticoats. v__ Court. Their Surprize confirms us it muſt be them. arºs -- Free. 'slife, we have betray’d our ſelves - Very pleaſantly. - - - e-y Court. Now am I undone to all Intents and purpoſes, - - - For they will innocently diſcover all to my Lady, And ſhe will have no Mercy. - Sir Oliv. Dam, Dan, Da-ra, Dan, &c. [Strutting. Avoid my Preſence, the very fight of that Face Makes me more impotent than an Eunuch. La. Cock. -Dear Sir Oliver ! w - - [Offering to embrace him. Sir Oliv. Forbear your Conjugal Clippings, * I will have a Wench, thou ſhalt fetch me a - ! -- Wench, Sentry. - Sent. Can you be ſo inhumane to my dear Lady ? Sir Oliv. Peace, Envy, or I will have thee executed For Petty Treaſon; thy Skin flay’d off, ſtuff"d, and Hung up in my Hall in the Countrey, as a Terrour to my whole Family. - Court. What Crime can deſerve this horrid Puniſhment? - - Sir Oliv. I’ll tell thee, Ned: 'Twas my Fortune Tother day to have an Intrigue with a Tinker’s Wife in the Countrey, and this malicious Slut Betray'd the very Ditch where we us’d to r Make our Aſſignations, to my Lady. . . - N Free. She deſerves your Anger indeed, Sir Oliver : . -* - But be not ſo unkind to your Vertuous Lady. ' f , Sir Oliv. Thou do'ſt not know her, Franck; I have - Had a Deſign to break her heart ever ſince the . . . . . - Firſt Month that I had her, and ’tis ſo tough, • That I have not yet crack'd'one String on’t. Court. You are too unmerciful, Sir Oliver. Sir Oliv. Hang her; Ned, by wicked Policy ſhe- Would uſurp my Empire, and in her lan is a - Very
Page 24

ºr n < - 2 . 24. She would if She could. - -- Very Pharaoh , for every Night ſhe's a putting * Me upon making Brick without Straw. Court. I cannot ſee a vertuous Lady ſo afflićted, Without offering her ſome Conſolation: Dear Madam, is it not as I told you? , [Aſide to her. La. Cock. The Fates could not have been more - Propitious, and I ſhall not be wanting to the - - Furthering of our mutual Happineſs. [To Court, aſide. Enter Sir Joſlin, with Ariana and Gatty in each - hand; dancing and ſinging. . C A T C H. .# -------- This is ſly and pretty, - - And this is wild and witty; If either ſtay’d - Till ſhe dy’d a Maid, - Tfaith 'twould be great Pity. * - Sir Joſlin. Here they are, Boys, i'faith; and now little Joſlin's a Man of his Word. Heuk! Sly-Girl and Mād-cap, to 'em, to 'em, to 'em, Boys, Alou ! [Flings ’em to Courtall and Freeman, who - - - kiſs their hands. What's yonder, your Lady in Tears, Brother Cockwood 2 Come, come ; I'll make up all Breaches. [He ſings---- And we'll all be merry and frollick. Fie, fie ; though Man and Wife are ſeldom in good Humour alone, there are few want the Diſcretion To diſſemble it in Company. - [Sir Joſlin, Sir Oliver, and Lady, ſtand talking together. - Free. I knew we ſhould ſurprize you, Ladies. Court. Faith, I thought this Conjuring to be but A meer jeſt till now ; and could not believe the Aſtrological Raſcal had been ſo skilful. Free. How exačtly he deſcrib'd 'em, and how Punétual he was in his Direétions to apprehend'em Gat. Then you have been with a Conjurer, Gentlemen. ... - Court. You cannot blame us, Ladies; the Loſs of Our Hearts was ſo conſiderablé, that it may well Excuſe the indirect means we took to find out The pretty Thieves that ſtole’em. Aria. Did not I tell you what Men of buſineſs * - fheſe
Page 25

She wou'd if She cou’d. 25 Theſe were, Siſter 2 - - Gat. I vow, I innocently believ'd they had ſome Præ-engagement to a Scrivener or a Surgeon, And wiſh'd 'em ſo well, that I am ſorry To find 'em ſo perfidious. Free. Why, we have kept our Oaths, Ladies. Aria. You are much beholden to Providence. Gatty. But we are more, Siſter; for had we once Been deluded into an Opinion they had been Faithful, who knows into what Inconveniences That Errour might have drawn us? - . Court. Why ſhould you be ſo unreaſonable, Ladies, To expect that from us, we ſhould ſcarce Have hop'd for from you? Fie, fie; the keeping - Of ones Word, is a thing below the Honour - Of a Gentlemán. - Free. A poor Shift! Fit only to uphold the - * -. . Reputation of a paultry Citizen. - . . - - Sir joſ. Come, come ; all will be well agen, . I warrant you, Lady. ---. - La, Cock. Theſe are inſupportable Injuries; but I will Bear'em with an invincible Patience, and to morrow Make him dearly ſenſible, How unworthy he has been. Sir joſ. To morrow my Brother Cockwood will Be another Man-----.So, Boys ; and how do you like : The Fleſh and Blood of the jollies P ---- Heuk, Sly-Girl— And Mad-cap, Hey---- Come, come ; you have Heard them exerciſe their Tongues awhile ; now You ſhall ſee them ply their Feet a little ! This is A clean Limb’d Wench, and has neither Spavin, Splinter, nor Wind-gall; tune her a Jig, and play’t roundly, You ſhall ſee her bounce it away like a nimble . . Friggat before a freſh Gale— Hey, methinks I ſee her under Sail already. - . . ." - . . . [Gatty dances a jigg. Sir joſ. Hey, my little Mad-cap------- Here’s a Girl, º Of the true Breed of the jollies, i'faith----- But hark you, - Hark you ; a Conſultation, Gentlemen------ Bear up, Brother Cockwood, a little: What think you, If we pack theſe idle Houſ wifes to Bed now, And retire into a Room by our ſelves, and have A merry Catch, and,a Bottle or two of the Beſt, and perfºr the good Work we have So unanimouſly carry’d on to-day ? Sir Oliv. A moſt admirable Intrigue------Tan, dam, Da, ra, dan; Come, come, march to your ſeveral Quarters: Go, we have have ſent *; a civil Perſon or two, And
Page 26

26. She wou'd if She cou’d. And are reſolv’d to fornicate in private. La. Cock. This is a barbarous Return Of all my Kindneſs. - Free. : Your humble Servant, Madam, Court. - [Ex, La. Cockwood and Sentry. Court. Hark you! Hark you! Ladies, do not harbour Too ill an Opinion of us, for faith, when you have Had a little more Experience of the World, you'll Find we are no ſuch abominable Raſcals. Gatty. We ſhall be ſo charitable to think no worſe. Of you, than we do of all Mankind for your Sakes, only that you are perjur’d, perfidious, Inconſtant, ingrateful. Free. Nay, nay; that's enough in all Conſcience, Ladies;. And now you are ſenſible, what a ſhameful thing It is to break one's Word, I hope you’ll be more Careful to keep yours to morrow. Gatty. Invent an Oath, and let it be ſo horrid------ Court. Nay, nay, it is too late for Raillery, i'faith, Ladies *::: § Well, your Servant, then. Free. - Court. $ Your Servant, Ladies. Sir Oliv. Now the Enemy's march'd out------ Sir joſ. Then the Caſtle's our own, Boys----- Hey... . And here and there I had her, And every where I had her, - Her Toy was ſuch, that every Touch Would make a Lover madder. £, } Hey, brave Sir joſlin Sir Oliv. Ah, my dear little witty foſlin. Let me hug the. y y foſlin, - Sir joſſin. Strike up, you obſtreperous Raſcals, and March along before us. * - [Exeunt Singing and Dancing. Act.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 27

She wou'd if She coºd. r 27 ACT III. SCENE 1. The New Exchange. • Mrs. Trincket ſitting in a shºp, People paſſing by as - in the Exchange. - - y Mrs. Trin. (7 Hat d'ye buy 2 What d'ye lack, Gentlemen? Gloves, Ribbons, and Eſſences; Ribbons, Gloves, and Eſſences? - Enter Mr. Courtal. . . Mr. Courtall ! I thought you had a Quarrel To the Change, and were reſolv’d we ſhould never See you here again. . . Court. Your unkindneſs indeed, Mrs. Trincket, had Been enough to make a Man baniſh himſelf For ever. - w - Enter Mrs. Gazette. . Trinck. Look you, yonder comes fine Mrs. Gazette, Thither you intended your Viſit, I am ſure, Gaz. Mr. Courtall ! Your Servant. Court. Your Servant, Mrs. Gazette. Gaz. This Happineſs was only meant to Mrs. Trincket, had it not been my good fortune To paſs by, by chance, I ſhould have loſt My ſhare on’t. Court. This is too cruel, Mrs. Gazette, when all the - º is on your ſide, to rally your Servant Thus. º - - Gaz. I vow this tedious Abſence of yours, made Me believe you intended to try an Experiment On my poor Heart, to diſcover that hidden Secret, How long a deſpairing Lover may languiſh Without the ſight of the Party. - Court. You are always very pleaſant on this Subjećt, Mrs. Gazette. - - Gaz. And have not you reaſon to be ſo too? Court. Not that I know of. - Gaz. Yes, you hear the gºod News, Court. What good News : - Gaz. How well this diſſembling becomes you ? But now I think better on't, it cannot - Concern you, you are more a Gaumº than. - 2 ~ To
Page 28

- - - - 2 º : 28 She wou'd if She cou’d - To have an Amour laſt longer than an Eaſter - - Term with a Countrey Lady 3 and yet there Are ſome, I ſee, as well in the Countrey, as in - - The City, that have a pretty way of Houſ wifing * ~ * --" - A Lover, and can ſpin an Intrigue out a great - is Deal farther, than others are willing to do. - ~. Court. What pretty Art have they, good Mrs. Gazette 2 Gaz. When Tradeſ-men ſee themſelves in an ill’ Condition, and are afraid of Breaking; can they do Better, than to take in a good ſubſtantial Partner, to help to carry on their Trading? Court. Sure yotr have been at, Riddle me, riddle me, Lately, you are ſo wondrous witty. Gaz, And yet I believe my Lady Cockmood is ſo Haughty, ſhe had rather give over the Vanity of anº Intrigue, than take in a couple of young JHandſome Kinſwomen to help to maintain it. Court. I knew it would out at laſt ; indeed it is the . . . . . . Principle of moſt good Women that love Gaming, - When they begin to grow a little out of Play Themſelves, to make an Intereſt in ſome Young Gameſter or other, in hopes to rook A Favour now and then : But you are quite out . *_{n your Policy, my Lady Cockwood is none of . heſe, I aſſure you ~ * Hark you, Mrs. Gazette, you muſt needs beftir." Your ſelf a little for me this morning, or elſe Heaven have Mercy upon a poor Sinner. - - - Gaz, I hope this wicked Woman has no Deſign. Upon your Body already : Alas! I pity your Tender Conſcience. - Court. I have always made thee my Confident, and Now I come to thee as to a Faithful Counſellor. * Gaz. State your Caſe. - - Court. Why, this Ravenous Kite is upon Wing already, .. . is fetching a little Compaſs, and will be Here within this half hour to ſwoop me. - Away. --> - Gaz. And you would have me your Scar-Crow 2 Court. Something of that there is in tº ſhe is ſtill Your Cuſtomer. - Gaz. I have furniſhed her, and the young Ladies, With a few faſhionable Toys ſince they came. - To Town, to keep ’em in Countenance at a Play, or in the Park. / . Coºrt. I would have thee go immediately to the Young Ladies, and, by ſome DeYiccior other, . º inticº
Page 29

2 - a - She wou'd if She cou’d. 29 Intice ’em hither. . . . . . . . . . ... " Gaz. I came juſt now from taking meaſure of 'em ‘For a Couple of Handkerchiefs. - • Court. How unlucky’s this - * ...". They were calling for their Hoods and Scarfs, And are coming hither, to lay out a little Money In Ribbons and Eſſences: I have recommended Them to Mrs. Trincket's Shop here. Court. This falls out more luckily than what I had Contriv'd my ſelf, or could have done; for here Will they be buſie juſt before the Door, - Where we have made our Appointment: But if this - Long-wing'd Devil ſhould chance to truſs me . . - Before they come. - Gaz. I will only ſtep up, and give ſome Direétions . - To my Maid, about a little Bus'neſs that is in - - - is Haſte, and come-down again and watch her; if you Are ſnapp'd, I’ll be with you. and reſcue You, I warrant you, or at leaſt ſtay you, till More Company come: She dares not force you. Away, in my ſight; ſhe knows I am great with “ Sir Oliver, and as malicious a Devil as the beſt “. . . Of 'em---- Your Servant, Sir. - "[Ex. Gazet, “ . Enter Freemán, 2 Court. Freeman 1 'Tis well you are come. * - Free. Well ! what Counter-plot? What hopes of Diſappointing the Old, and ºſeeing the Young - - Ladies 2 I am ready to receive your Orders. - - x Court. Faith, things are not ſo well contriv'd as - . I could have wiſh'd 'em, and yet I hope, by The help of Mrs. Gazet, to keep my word, Franck. r - Free. Nay, now I know what Tool thou haſt made - Choice of, I make no Queſtion, but the Bus'neſs Will go well forward; but, I am afraid, This laſt unlucky Bus’neſs has ſo diſtaſted heſe young Trouts, they will not be ſo eaſily a Tickl’d as they might have been. - Court. Never fear it; whatſoever Women ſay, I am ſure - They ſeldom think the worſe of a Man, for . Running at all; ’tis a Sign of Youth, and high - …” Mettle, and makes them ºather picquee, who ſhall Tame him: That which troubles me moſt, is, we Loſt the hopes of Variety, and a ſingle Intrigue º \ In Love, is as dull as a ſingle Plot in a Play; . . . - - - And .
Page 30

36 - -- • 2 2 r She wou'd if She cou’d. And will tire a Lover worſe, than t’other does An Audience, - Free, we cannot be long without ſome under-plots In this Town, let this be our main Deſign, And if we are anything fortunate in our Contrivance, We ſhall make it a pleaſant Comedy, Court. Leave all things to me, and hope the beſt: Be gone, for I expect their coming immediately; Walk a turn or two above, or fool awhile With pretty Mrs. Anvil, and ſcent your Eye-brows And Perriwig with a little Eſſence of Oranges, Or Jeſſimine; and when you ſee us all together At Mrs. Gazett's Shop, put in as it were by chance: I proteſt, yonder comes the old Haggard, to your Poſt quickly 'sDeath ! where's Gazette and theſe Young Ladies now 2 ... [Ex. Freem. Enter Lady Cockwood, and Sentry. O Madam, I have waited here, at leaſt, an hour, And time ſeems very tedious, when it delays ſo great A Happineſs as you bring with you. La. Cock. I vow, Sir, I did but ſtay to give Sir Oliver His due Correótion for thoſe unſeemly Injuries He did me laſt Night. Is your Coach ready? Court. Yes, Madam: But how will you diſpoſe of Your Maid 2 La. Cock. My Maid " For Heavens ſake, what do you Mean, Sir? Do I ever uſe to go abroad without her ? Court. 'Tis upon no Deſign, Madam, I ſpeak it, I aſſure you ; but my Glaſs-Coach broke laſt Night, And I was forc’d to bring my Chariot, which can hold But two. - w La. Cock. O Heaven! You muſt excuſe me, dear Sir ; For I ſhall deny my ſelf the ſweeteſt Recreations In the World, rather than yield to anything that May bring a Blemiſh upon my ſpotleſs Honour. f Enter Gazette. Gaz. Your humble Servant, Madam. Your Servant, Mr. Courtall. Eady t and § Your Servant, Mrs. Gazette. - Cºzzº. ar. I am extreme glad to ſee your Ladiſhip here; iiºnic! to ſend my Maid to your Lodgings This i
Page 31

2 - - • 2 º' She wou'd if She cou’d. 3 I This Afternoon, Madam, to tell you, I have AParcel of New Lace come in, the prettieſt Patterns That ever were ſeen; for I am very deſirous ſo Good a Cuſtomer as your Ladiſhip ſhould ſee 'em Firſt, and have your Choice. 3. La. Cock. I am much beholden to you, Mrs. Gazette, I was newly come into the Exchange, and intended To call at your Shop before I went home. Enter Ariana and Gatty, Gazette goes to them. Court. 'sDeath, here are your Couſins too! now there Is no hope left for a poor unfortunate Lover to comfort himſelf withal. 3. % Your Servant, Madam. La, Cock. I am newly come into the Exchange, and By chance, met with Mr. Courtall here, who will needs Sive himſelf the trouble, to play the Gallant, and Wait upon me. Gatty. Does }. Ladiſhip come to buy? - , La. Cock. A few Trifles; Mrs. Gazette ſays ſhe has A Parcel of very fine new Laces, ſhall we go look Upon 'em P - - ... Aria. We will only fanſie a Sute of Knots or two - At this Shop, and buy a little Eſſence, and wait upon your Ladiſhip immediately. Gat. Mrs. Gazette, you are skill'd in the Faſhion, Pray let our Choice have your Approbation. º [All go to the Shop to look upon Ware, but Courtall, and Lady Cockwood. . Gaz. Moſt gladly, Madam. - Court. 'sDeath, Madam, if you had made no Ceremony, But ſtept into the Coach preſently, we had eſcap'd this Miſchief. - - La. Cock. My Over-tenderneſs of my Honour, has Blaſted all my Hopes of Happineſs. - Court. To be thus unluckily ſurpriz'd in the height Of all our Expediation, leaves me no Patience. La. Cock, Moderate your Paſſion a little, Sir? I may Yet find out a way, - Court. Oh 'tis impoſſible, Madam, never thinkon’t Now you have been ſeen with me; to leave 'em upon Any Pretence will be ſo ſuſpicious, That my Concern For your Honour will make me ſo feveriſh and Diſordered, that I ſhall loſe the Faſte of all the Happineſs you give me.. - La, Cock, Methinks you are too ſcrupulous, HeroickSir. - - - Cºff,
Page 32

- 2 I • 2 32 She wou'd if She could Court. Beſides the Concerns I have for you, Madam; You know the Obligations I have to Sir Oliver, And what Profeſſions of º there are on - Both Sides; and to be thought perfidious and ingrateful, What an Afflićtion would that be to a generous Spirit ! La. Cock. Muſt we then unfortunately part thus * * Court. Now I have better thoughton't, that is not - Abſolutely neceſſary neither. -- - - La. Cock. Theſe words revive my dying Joys, Dear Sir, go on... z - * - - Court. I will, by and by, when I ſee it moſt convenient, Beg the Favour of your Ladiſhip, and your * - Young Kinſwomen, to accept of a Treat, and A Fiddle; you make ſome little difficulty at Firſt, but upon earneſt Perſwaſion comply, and life your Intereſt to make the young Ladies Do ſo too: Your Company will ſecure their Reputations, and their Company take off from You all Suſpicion. -- - La. Cock. The natural Inclination they have to be jigging, will make them very ready to comply: But what Advantage can this be to our Happineſs, dear Sir 2 - Court. Why, firſt, Madam, if the young Ladies, or Mrs. Gazette, have any Doubts upon their ſurprizing lls together, our joining Company will clear 'em all; . Next, we ſhall have ſome Satisfaction - In being an Afternoon together, though we enjoy Not that full Freedom we ſo paſſionately - - Deſire. . . . . - - La. Cock. Very good, Sir. . - Court. But then laſtly, Madam, we gain an Opportunity . . . To contrive another Appointment to morrow, Which may reſtore us unto all thoſe Joys . - We have been ſo unfortunately diſappointed Of to day. - - - La. Cock. This is a very prevailing Argument Indeed ; but ſince Sir Oliver believes I have Conceiv'd ſo deſperate a Sorrow, 'tis fit we Should keep this from his Knowledge. Court. Are the young Ladies ſecret? La. Cock. They have the good Principles not To betray themſelves, I aſſure you. * - Cºurt. Then 'tis but going to a Houſe that is - Not haunted by the Company, and we are ſecure, And now I think ont, the Bear in Drury-lane Is the ſitcſt place for our purpoſe. - La. cock.
Page 33

- 3. º *------, She wou'd if She could 33 La, Cock. I know your Honour, dear Sir, - And ſubmit to your Diſcretion------- Have you gratifi'd your Fancies, Couſins 2 [To them Ariana, Gatty, and Gazette, from the Shop. Aria. We are ready to wait upon you, Madam. - Gatty. I never ſaw Colours better mingled. Gaz. How lively they ſet off one another, and How they add to the Complexion! La. Cock. Mr. Courtal, your moſt humble Servant. Court. Pray, Madam, let me have the Honour To wait upon you and theſe young Ladies, Till I ſee you in your Coach. - - º La. Cock. Your Friendſhip to Sir Oliver would Engage you in an unneceſſary Trouble. - Aria. Let not an idle Ceremony take you from Your ſerious Buſineſs, good Sir. - Gatty. I ſhould rather have expećted to have ſeen You, Sir, walking in Weſtminſter-Hall, watching To make a Match at Tennis, or waiting to Dine with a Parliament-Man, than to meet You in ſuch an idle Place as the Exchange is. - - - - Court. Methinks, Ladies, you are well - - *. Acquainted with me upon the firſt Viſit. * - Aria. We received your Charaćter before, you * - - - - Know, Sir, in the Mulberry-Garden, upon Oath. - - *. Court. aſide..] 'speath ! what ſhall I do? w - T- Now out comes all my Roguery. - - Z. Gatty. Yet I am apt to believe, Siſter, that was Some malicious Fellow that wilfully perjur’d Himſelf, on purpoſe to make us have an Ill Opinion .# this worthy Gentleman. - Court. Some raſh Men would be apt enough To enquire him out, and Cut his Throat, Ladies; But I heartily forgive him whoſoever he was ; - - For, on my Conſcience, ’twas not ſo much out Of Malice to me, as out of Love to you he did it. Gaz. He might imagine Mr. Courtall was his Rival. Court. Very likely, Mrs. Gazette. w - - La. Cock. Whoſoever he was, he was an unworthy ~ Fellow, I warrant him; Mr. Courtall is known - To be a Perſon of Worth and Honour. Aria. We took him for an idle Fellow, Madam, And gave but very little Credit to what he ſaid. Court. 'Twas very obliging, Lady, to believe Nothing to the Diſadvantage of a Stranger------- - What a Couple of young Devils are theſe ? . . . La. Cock. Since you are willing to sº - . [4.
Page 34

- 2 º º - 34. She wou'd if She cou’d. Your ſelf this Trouble. - Y - Court. I ought to do my Duty, Madam. • - * [Exeunt all but Ariana and Gatty. TAria. How he bluſh'd, and hung down his Head : - Gatty. A little more had put him as much out Of Countenance, as a Country Clown is When he ventures to compliment His Attorney’s Daughter. - [They follow. S C E N E II. Sir Oliver's Dining-Room. Enter Sir Joſlin, and Servant ſeverally. Sir joſ. How now, old Boy' where's my Brother Cockwood to day ? Serv. He deſires to be in private, Sir. Sir joſ. Why, what's the matter, Man? Serv. This is a Day of Humiliation, Sir, with him, For laſt Night's Tranſgreſſion. - Sirjoſ. I have Bus'neſs of Conſequence to impart To him, and muſt and will ſpeak with him------ So, ho Brother Cockwood P. º Sir Oliv. without..] Who's that, my Brother jolly 2 Sir joſ. The ſame, the ſame 5 come away, Boy. Sir Oliv. without..] For ſome ſecret Reaſons I deſire to be in private, Brother. | Sir joſ. I have ſuch a Deſign on foot, as would Draw Diogenes out of his Tub to follow it: Therefore I ſay, come away, come away. - - Sir Oliver entring in a Night-Gown, and Slippers, Sir Oliv: There is ſuch a ſtrange Temptation - In thy Voice, never ſtir. - Sir joſ. What, in thy Gown and Slippers yet!' why, Brother, I have beſpoke Dinner, and engag’d Mr. Rake-hell, the little ſmart Gentleman I haye Often promis'd thee to make thee acquainted. Withal; to bring a whole Bevy of Damſels, In Sky, and Pink, and Flame-colour’d Taffeta's. Come, come, dreſs thee quickly ; there's to be Madam Rampant, a Girl that ſhines, and will drink, At ſuch a rate, ſhe's a Miſireſ; for Alexander. Were he alive agen. - Sir Oliv. How unluckily this falls out : Thomas, what Clothes have I to put on 2 Serv. None but your Penitential Sute, Sir : At!
Page 35

2 º - - r--- - - She wou'd if She could. 35 All the reſt are ſecur’d. . Sir Oliv. Oh unſpeakable Misfortune! that I Should be in diſgrace with my Lady now ! Sirjoſ. Come, come, never talk of Clothes; Put on anything; thou haſt a Perſon and a Mind, will bear it out bravely. Sir Oliv. Nay, I know my Behaviour will ſhow I am a Gentleman; but yet the Ladies Will look ſcurvily upon me, Brother. .. Sir joſ. That's a Jeſt, i'faith; He that has Terra firma In the Country, may appear in any thing before 'em. . For he that would have a Wench kind, Ne'er ſmugs up himſelf like a Ninny; But plainly tells her his Mind, And tickles her firſt with a Guinny. Hey, Boy------ Sir Oliv. I vow thou haſt ſuch a bewitching Way with thee! w Sir joſ. How lovely will the Ladies look, When they have a Beer-Glaſs in their Hands ! Sir Oliv. I now have a huge Mind to venture; But if this ſhould come to my Lady's Knowledge. Sir joſ. I have beſpoke Dinner at the Bear, the Privat’ſt Place in Town: there will be No Spies to betray us, if Thomas be but ſecret, I dare warrant thee, Brother Cockwood. s Sir Oliv. I have always found Thomas very - Faithful: but, faith, 'tis too unkind, conſidering How tenderly my Lady loves me. Sirjoſ. Fie, fie; a Man and kept ſo much under Correótion by a Busk and a Fan Sir Oliv. Nay, I am in my Nature as valiant As any Man, when once I ſet out; but, i'faith, I Cannot but think how my dear Lady will be Concern'd, when ſhe comes home and miſſes me. Sir joſ. A Pox upon theſe Qualms. Sir Oliv. Well, thou haſt ſeduc’d me; But I ſhall look ſo untowardly. Sirjoſ. Again art thou at it? In, in, and make All the haſte that may be ; Rake-hell and the - . Ladies will be there before us elſe. ... . Sir Oliv. Well, thou art an errant Devil----- hey---- For the Ladies, Brother jolly. Sir joſ. Hey for the Ladies, Brother Cockwood. - - [EX. ſinging- For he that wou'd, &c. - E 2 - SCENE . - - * -
Page 36

36 She wou'd if She cou’d. . S C E N E III. The B E A R. Without. Ho, Francis, Humphrey, ſhow a Room there ! - - - : * Enter Courtal, Freeman, Lady Cockwood, Ariana, Gatty, and Sentry. Court. Pray, Madam, be not ſo full of Apprehenſion; * . There is no fear that this ſhould come to - Sir Oliver's Knowledge. - - La. Cock. I were ruin’d if it ſhould, Sir Dear, how I tremble! I never was in one of theſe Houſes before. Sent. This is a Bait, for the young Ladies to Swallow; ſhe has been in moſt of the Eating-houſes ſ About Town, to my Knowledge. - [Aſide. Court. Oh, Francis I - - Enter Waiter. Wait. Your Worſhip's welcome, Sir; but I Muſt needs deſire you to walk into the next Room, for this is beſpoke. - - La. Cock. Mr. Cºurtall, did not you ſay, this Place was private 2 - Court. I warrant you, Madam. What Company dines here, Francis 2 - Wait. A couple of Country Knights; Sir joſlin jolly, And Sir Oliver Cockwood; very honeſt Gentlemen. La. Cock. Combination to undo me ! Court. Peace, Madam, or you'll betray Your ſelf to the Waiter. La. Cock. I am diſtraćted Sentry, did not I command thee to ſecure all Sir Oliver's Clothes, And leave nothing for him to put on, but his Penitential Sute, that I might be ſure he Could not ſtir abroad to day ? Sent. I obey'd you in everything, Madam; but I have often told you this Sir joſlin is a wicked Seducer, Aria. If my llncle ſees us, Siſter, what Will he think of us? Gatty. We come but to wait upon her Ladiſhip. Free. You need not fear; you, Chickens, are Rºute - Inder the Wings of that old Hen. Court. Is there to be no Body, Francis, " * - But Sir Oliver, and Sir Joſlin? - - - - - -- Wait,
Page 37

She wou'd if She cou’d. 37 t Wait. Faith, Sir, I was enjoin’d Secrecy; but You have an abſolute Power over me: Coming Lately out of the Country, where there is but Little Variety, they have a Deſign to ſolace Themſelves with a freſh Girl or Two, as L llnderſtand the Buſineſs. ” - La. Cock. Oh, Sentry Sir Oliver diſloyal My Misfortunes come too thick upon me. Court. aſide.] Now is ſhe afraid of being Diſappointed on all hands. La. Cock. I know not what to do, Mr. Courtall; - I would not be ſurpriz'd here my ſelf, and yet I would prevent Sir Oliver from proſecuting His wicked and perfidious Intentions. Aria. Now ſhall we have admirable Sport, What with her Fear and Jealouſie. Gatty. I lay my Life, ſhe routs the Wenches. Enter Waiter. Wait. I muſt needs deſire you to ſtep into the next Room; Sir joſlin, and Sir Oliver are below already. La. Cock. I have not power to move a foot. Free. We will conſider what is to be done, Within, Madam. Court. Pray, Madam, come; I have a Deſign in my Head, which ſhall ſecure you, ſurprize Sir Oliver, and free you from all your Fears. La. Cock. It cannot be, Sir. Court. Never fear it: Francis, you may own Mr. Freeman and I are in the Houſe, if they ask for us; But not a word of theſe Ladies, as you tender The wearing of your Ears. Enter Sir Joſlin, Sir Oliver, and Waiter. Sirjoſ. Come, Brother Cockwood, Prithee be brisk, Sir Oliv. I ſhall diſgrace my ſelf for ever, Brother, Sirjoſ. Pox upon Care, never droop like a Cock In moulting time; thou art Spark enough in all Conſcience, Sir Oliv. But my Heart begins to fail me; When I think of my Lady. Sir joſ. What, more Qualms yet P - - - Sir Oliv. Well, I will be couragious: But it is not Neceſſary theſe Stangers ſhould know this is My Penitential Sute, Brother. - Sir joſ. They ſhall not, they ſhall not, Hark. [Exit Waiter. [Excunt.
Page 38

- * . 2 ”I 2. 38 She wou'd if She could. You, old Boy, is the Meat provided? Is the Wine And Ice come 2 And are the Melodious Raſcals At hand I ſpoke for 2 - Wait. Every thing will be in readineſs, Sir. Sir joſ. If Mr. Rake-hell, with a Coach full, or two, Of Vizard-Masks, and Silk Petticoats, call at the * Door, uſher'em up to the Place of Execution. . . . Wait. You ſhall be obey'd, Sir. . Enter Rake-hell. Sir joſ. Ho, here's my little Rake-hell come ! Brother Cockwood, let me commend this ingenious Gentleman to your Acquaintance; he is a Knight Of the Induſtry, has many admirable Qualities, I aſſure you. , - Sir Oliv. I am very glad, Sir, of this Opportunity To know you. - * . Rake. I am happy, Sir, if you eſteem me your Servant. Hark you, Sirjoſlin, is this Sir Oliver Cockmood, in earneſt ? - ** Sir joſ. In very good earneſt, I aſſure you, . . . He is a little fantaſtical now and then, and dreſſes Himſelf up in an old Faſhion; but that’s all one Among Friends, my little Rake-hell. Sir Oliv. Where are the Damſels you talk'd of, brother jolly 2 I hope Mr. Rake-hell has not forgot'em. Rake. They are arming for the Ran-counter. Sir joſ. What, tricking and trimming? Rake. Even ſo, and will be here immediately. Sir Oliv. They need not make themſelves ſo ‘Full of Temptation; my Brother jolly and I can Be wicked enough without it. - Sir joſ. The truth is, my little Rake-hell, we are Both mighty Men at Arms, and thou ſhalt.ſee us Charge anon, to the Terrour of the Ladies. Rake. Methinks that Dreſs, Sir Oliver, is a little Too ruſtical for a Man of your Capacity. - Sir Oliv. I have an odd Humour, Sir, now, and Then ; but I have wherewithal at home, To be as ſpruce as any Man. Rake. Your Perriwig is too ſcandalous, Sir Oliver, Your black Cap and Border is never . Wore but by a Fiddler or a Waiter. Sir joſ. Prithee, my little Rake-hell, do not put my Brother Cockmood out of conceit of himſelf; Methinks your Calot is a pretty Ornament, and . Makes a Man look both Polite and Politick. . . [Exit waiter. - - Rake. º |
Page 39

She wou'd if She could. 39 Rake. I will allow you, 'tis a grave Ware, and fit For Men of Buſineſs, that are every moment bending Of their Brows, and ſcratching of their Heads, every Projećt would claw out another Perriwig; but a Lover had better appear before his Miſtreſs with a Bald Pate; twill make the Ladies apprehend a Savour, Stop their Noſes, and avoid you: 'slife, Love in a Cap is more ridiculous than Love in a Tub, or Love In a Pipkin. - Sir Oliv. I muſt confeſs your whole Head is Now in Faſhion; but there was a time when Your Calot was not ſo deſpicable. Rake. Here's a Perruque, Sir. Sir Oliv. A very good one. - Rake. A very good one º 'Tis the beſt in England. Pray, Sir joſlin, take him in your hand, and draw A Comb through him, there is not ſuch. Another Friz in Europe. - - Sirjoſ. 'Tis a very fine one indeed. Rake. Pray, Sir Oliver, do me the Favour to Grace it on your Head a little. Sir Oliv. To oblige you, Sir. Rake. You never wore any thing became you half. So well in all your Life before. Sir joſ. Why, you never ſaw him in your Life before. Rake. That's all one, Sir, I know ’tis impoſſible. Here's a Beaver, Sir Oliver, feel him ; for Fineneſs, Subſtance, and for Faſhion, the Court of France Never ſaw a better; I have bred him but a Fortnight, and have him at Command already. Clap him on boldly, never Hattook the Fore-Cock, And the Hind-Cock at one motion ſo naturally. Sir Oliv. I think you have a Mind to make A Spark of me before I ſee the Ladies. Rake. Now you have the Meen of a true Cavalier, . And with one Look may make a Lady kind, and A He&tour humble: And, ſince I nam’d a He&tour, Here's a Sword, Sir : Sa, ſa, ſa; try him, Sir joſlin, . Put him to't, cut through the Staple, run him Through the Door, beat him to the Hilts, if he Breaks, you ſhall have the liberty to break my Pate, And pay me never a Groat of the Ten for’t. - Sir joſ. 'Tis a very pretty Weapon, indeed, Sir. . . . . Rake. The Hilt is true French wrought, and - Doree by the beſt Workman in France. This Sword, And this Caſtor, with an embroider’d Button and Loop, which I have to vary him upon occaſion, . Were:
Page 40

4-O She wou'd if She could Were ſent me out of France for a Token, by my elder Brother, that went over with a handſome Equipage, To take the Pleaſure of this Campagne. - Sir Oliv. Have you a Mind to ſell theſe things, Sir 2 Rake. That is below a Gentleman; yet if a Perſon Of Honour, or a particular Friend, ſuch as I eſteem You, Sir Oliver, take at any time a Fancy to a Band, A Cravat, a Velvet-Coat, a Veſt, a Ring, a Flajolet, Or any other little Toy I have about me, I am Good-natur'd, and may be eaſily perſwaded To play the Fool upon good Terms. - - Enter Freeman. Sir joſ. Worthy Mr. Freeman 1 Sir Oliv. Honeſt Franck, how cam'ſt thou to Find us out, Man? - Free. By meer chance, Sir; Ned Courtall is without, Writing a Letter, and I came in to know, whether You had any particular Engagements, Gentlemen. Sir Oliv. We reſolv’d to be in private; but You are Men without exception. Free. Methinks you intended to be in private, Indeed, Sir Oliver. 'sDeath, what Diſguiſe have You got on ? Are you grown grave ſince laſt Night, and come to ſin incognito P - . Sir Oliv. Hark you in your Ear, Franck; this is My Habit of Humiliation, which I always put on The next day after I have tranſgreſſed, the better To make my Pacification with my incens'd Lady------- Free. Ha, ha, ha----- º - Rake. Mr. Freeman, your moſt humble Servant, Sir. Free. Oh, my little dapper Officer | Are you here 2 Sir joſ. Ha, Mr. Freeman, we have beſpoke all the Jovial Entertainment, that a merry Wag can wiſh for, Good Meat, good Wine, and a wholſome - Wench or two for the Digeſtion, we ſhall have * Madam Rampant, the Glory of the Town; The brighteſt ſhe that ſhines, or elſe my little Rake-hell Js not a Man of his Word, Sir. - Rake. I warrant you ſhe comes, Sir joſlin. a Sir Joſlin ſings. And, if ſhe comes, ſhe ſhall not ſcape, If Twenty Pounds will win her; Her very Eye commits a Rape, 'Tis ſuch a tempting Sinner. Enter - -
Page 41

She wou'd if She could . . 4. I. :- -- Enter Courtall. court. Well ſaid, Sir Joſlin, I ſee you hold up ſtill, And bate not an Ace of your good Humour. Sirjoſ. Noble Mr. Courtall I Court. Bleſs me, Sir Oliver, what, are you going To ačt a Droll P How the People would throng About you, if you were but mounted on a Few Deal-boards in Covent-Garden now ! Sir Oliv.Hark you, Ned, this is the Badge of my Lady’s Indignation for my laſt Night's Offence ; Do not inſult over a poor ſober Man in Afflićtion. Court. Come, come, ſend home for your Clothes; I hear you are to have Ladies, and you are not - To learn at theſe Years, how abſolutely neceſſary A rich Veſt and a Perruque are to a Man That aims at their Favours. Sir Oliv. A Pox on’t, Ned, my Lady's gone abroad, In a damn'd jealous, melancholy Humour, And has commanded her Woman to ſecure 'em. Court. llnder Lock and Key P - Sir Oliv. Ay, ay, Man; 'tis uſual in theſe Caſes, - Out of pure Love, in hopes to reclaim me, and To keep me from doing my ſelf an Injury, By Drinking two days together. Court. What a loving Lady "tis' Sir Oliv. There are Sots that would think themſelves Happy in ſuch a Lady, Ned; but to a true-bred Gentleman, all lawful Solace is Abomination. - Rake. Mr. Courtall, your moſt humble Servant, Sir. Court. Oh! my little Knight of the Induſtry, I am glad to ſee you in ſuch good Company. . . . . Free. Courtall, hark you, are the Masking-Habits, Which you ſent to borrow at the Play-houſe, come yet? Court. Yes, and the Ladies are almoſt dreſs'd : This Deſign will add much to our Mirth, and give us the Benefit of their Meat, Wine, and Muſick, For our Entertainment. Free. 'Twas luckily thought of. Sir Oliv. Hark, the Muſick comes. Sirjoſ. Hey, Boys------ let'em enter, let'em enter. - Enter Waiter. . . Wait. An’t pleaſe your Worſhips, there is a Mask Of Ladies without, that deſire to have the Freedom to come in and dance. Sir joſ. Hey! Boys-------- F [Muſick. Sir
Page 42

2 - 2 4.2 . She wou'd if She cou’d. , Sir Oliv. Did you bid 'em come *en Maſquerade, Mr. Rake-hell ? Rake. No ; but Rampant is a mad Wench; ſhe was half a dozen times a mumming, in private Company, laſt Shrove-tide; and I lay my life ſhe has Put 'em all upon this Frollick. . . - Court. They are mettled Girls, I warrant them, Sir foſlin, let them be what they will. * Sir joſ. Let 'em enter, let 'em enter, ha Boys— EnterMuſick, and the Ladies in an Antick, and then they take out; my Lady Cock- wood, Sir Oliver; the roung Ladies, Courtall and Freeman; and Sentry, Sir Joſlin; and dance a Set Pance. - Sir Oliv. Oh, my little Rogue? have I got thee 2 How I will turn and wind, and fegue thy Body! Sir joſ. Mettle on all ſides, Mettle on all ſides, Pfaith; how ſwimmingly would this pretty littlé Ambling Filly carry a Man of my Body! . S I N G S. "She’s ſo bonny and brisk, - Hom ſhe'd curvet and frisk, A If a Man were once mounted upon her " * , , Let me have but a Leap, . Where 'tis wholeſome and cheap, And a fig for your Perſon of Honour. Sir Oliv. 'Tis true, little goſlin, i'faith. - Court. They have warm'd us, Sir Oliver. - Sir Oliv. Now am I as rampant as a Lion, Ned. nd could love as vigorouſly as a Sea-man, that - newly landed after an Eaſt-India Voyage. - Court. Take my Advice, Sir Oliver, do not in your- age deprive your ſelf of your only Hope f an Accommodation with your Lady. - Sir Oliv. I had rather have a perpetual Civil War, / Than purchaſe Peace at ſuch a diſhonourable rate. A poor Fidler, after he has been three days perſecuted At a Country Wedding, takes more Delight in ſcraping upon his old ſqueeking Fiddle, than I do in fumbling On that Domeſtick Inſtrument of mine. Court. Be not ſo bitter, Sir Oliver, on your Own dear Lady. - - - Sir Oliv. I was married to her when I was young, ~ Ned, with a Deſign to be baulk'd, as they tye Whelps. . Tº the Bell-Wether; where I have been ſo butted, - *Twere - | }
Page 43

- 2 • * * - She wou'd if She could. 4-3 *Twere enough to fright me, were I not pure Mettle, from ever running at Sheep again. Court. That's no ſure Rule, Sir Oliver; for a Wife's a Diſh, of which if a Man once ſurfeit, he ſhall Have a better ſtomach to all others ever after, Sir Oliv. What a Shape is here, Ned'ſ ſo exačt and Tempting, 'twould perſwade a Man to be an - Implicite Sinner, and take her Face upon Credit. : Sir jaſ. Come, Brother Cockwood, let us get 'em To lay aſide theſe Masking Fopperies, and then - We'll fegue’em in earneſt: Give us à Bottle, Waiter. Free. Not before Dinner, good Sir joſlin | Sir Oliv. Lady, though I have out of Drollery Put my ſelf into this contemptible Dreſs at preſent, I am a Gentleman, and a Man of Courage, as you Shall find anon by my brisk Behaviour. Rake. Sir foſlin Sir Oliver ! Theſe are none of our Ladies; they are juſt come to the Door in a Coach, and Have ſent for me down to wait upon 'em up to you. Sir joſ. Hey-------Boys! more Game, more Game! . Fetch 'em up, fetch 'em up. - Sir Oliv. Why, what a Day of Sport will here be, Aſed P } \ [Exit Rake-hell. Sir joſ. They ſhall all have fair Play, Boys. - Sir Oliv. And we will match our ſelves, and make A Prize on’t; Ned Courtall and I, againſt Franck Freeman * * And you, Brother jolly, and Rake-hell ſhall be - - Judge for Gloves and Silk Stockings, to be Beſtow'd as the Conquerour ſhall fanſie. - Sir joſ. Agreed, agreed, agreed. º Court. and Free. A match, a match. Sir Oliv. Hey---------Boys! | | - - [Lady Cockwood counterfeits a Fit. | Sentry pulling off her Mask. O Heavens ! my dear Lady Help, help ! . • Sir Oliv, What's here? Sentry and my Lady | - * 'sDeath, what a Condition am I in now, Brother jolly * You have brought me into this Premunire: For . Heavens ſake run down quickly, and ſend the Rogue And Whores away.' Help, help ! Oh help! - - - : Dear Madam, ſweet Lady f - .…. * * [Exit Sir Joſlin. - - - [Sir Oliver kneels down by her. - Sent. Oh, ſhe's gone, ſhe's gone ! / Free. Give her mole Air. ' - º Court. Fetch a Glaſs of cold Water, Freeman. - Sir Oliv. Dear Madam, ſpeak. - - - F 2 - Sent.
Page 44

44 She wou'd if She cou’d. Sent. Out upon thee, for a vile Hypocrite thou Art the wicked Authour of all this; who but ſuch a . Reprobate, ſuch an obdurate Sinner as thou art, Could go about to abuſe ſo ſweet a Lady ? Sir Oliv. Dear Sentry, do not ſtab me with thy Words, But ſtab me with thy Bodkin rather, that I may here Dye a Sacrifice at her Feet, for all my diſloyal Aétions. Sent. No, live, live, to be a Reproach and a Shame - To all Rebellious Husbands; ah, that ſhe had but - - My Heart but thou haſt bewitch'd her Affections; * Thou ſhould'ſt then dearly ſmart for - - This abominable Treaſon. - - Gatty.So, now ſhe begins to come to her ſelf. - - Aria. Set her more upright, - - - And bend her a little forward. - La. Cock. Unfortunate Woman let me go, Why do you hold me? would I had a Dagger at My Heart, to puniſh it for loving that ungrateful Man. Sir Oliv. Dear Madam, were I but worthy Of your Pity and Belief. -- * La. Cock. Peace, peace, perfidious Man, I am too Tame and fooliſh----- Were fevery day at the Plays, The Park, and Mulberry Garden, with a kind Look Secretly to indulge the unlawful Paſſion of ſome Young Gallant; or did I aſſociate my ſelf with the Gaming Madams, and were every Afternoon at my r Lady Brief's, and my Lady Meanwel's at Umbre, - . And Quebas, pretending ill Luck to borrow Money of a Friend, and then pretending good Luck to excuſe the . Plenty to a Husband, my ſuſpicious Demeanour had Deſerv'd this; but I, who out of a ſcrupulous Tenderneſs to my Honour, and to comply with thy Baſe Jealouſie, have deny'd my ſelf all thoſe blameleſs - Recreations, which a vertuous Lady might enjoy, . . . . To be thus inhumanely revil'd in my own Perſon, And thus unreaſonably robb’d and abus'd in thiné too! Court. Sure ſhe will take up amon, or crack her Mind, or elſe the DeviPs in't. La. Cock. Do not ſtay and torment me with thy ſight; Go, graceleſs Wretch, follow thy treacherous Reſolutions, Do, and waſte that poor ſtock of Comfort, - - Which I ſhould have at home, upon thoſe ravenous, . Corraorants below: I feel my Paſſion begin to Swell again. ... • [She bas a little Fit again, Court. Now will ſhe get an abſolute Dominion over - Him, and all this will be my Plague in the end. - - - Sir
Page 45

2 y - She wou'd if She cou’d. 4-5 ; - [Sir Oliver running up and down. Sir Oliv. Ned Courtall, Franck Freeman, - Couſin Ariana, and dear Couſin Gatty, For Heavens ſake, join all, and moderate her Paſion------ - Ah, Sentry forbear thy unjuſt Reproaches, take pity On thy Maſter! thou haſt a great Influence over her, And I have always been mindful of thy Favours. - Sent. You do not deſerve the leaſt Compaſſion, Nor would I ſpeak a good Word for yon, but that I know, for all this, 'twill be acceptable to my poor Lady. Dear Madam, do but look up a little; - Sir Oliver lies at your Feet an humble Penitent. Aria. How bitterly he weeps how ſadly he fighs . Gatty. I dare ſay he counterfeited his ſin, - And is real in his Repentance. Court. Compoſe your ſelf a little, pray, Madam 3 All this was meer Raillery, a way of Talk, which Sir Oliver, being well bred, has learned among The gay People of the Town. Free. If you did but know, Madam, what an odious ſ Thing it is to be thought to love a Wife in good Company, you would eaſily forgive him. - - La. Cock. No, no; 'twas the mild Correótion which - r I gave him for his inſolent Behaviour laſt Night, That has encourag’d him agen thus to inſult - - Over my Affe&tions. - - Court. Come, come, Sir Oliver, out with your Boſom-ſecret, and clear all things to your Lady ; - Is it not as we have ſaid 2 z - - Sir Oliv. Or may I never have the Happineſs to be * - ſ In her good Grace agen; and as for the Harlots, Dear Madam, here is Ned Courtall, and Franck Freeman, That have often ſeen me in Company of the Wicked; Let 'em ſpeak, if they ever knew me tempted º - To a diſloyal A&ion in their Lives. - - - Court. On my Conſcience, Madam, I may more Šafely ſwear, that Sir Oliver has been conſtant to Your Ladiſhip, than that a Girl of Twelve years old * Has her Maiden-head this warm and ripening Age. Enter Sir Joſlin. Sir Oliv. Here's my Brother jolly too can witneſs The Loyalty of my Heart, That I did not intend . Any Treaſonable Pračtice againſt your Ladiſhip, In the leaſt. | Sirjoſ. lin: 's feguing 'em with a Beer-glaſs, - be included in . . Statute. Come, Mr. Courtall, to . Satisfie —º-- - - *
Page 46

46 She wou'd if She could Satisfie my Lady, and put her in a little good Humour, Let us ſing the Catch I taught you yeſterday, that was Made by a Country Vicar on my Brother Cockwood and me. f They Sing. * Love and Wenching are Toys, Fit to pleaſe Beardleſs Boys, Th’ are Sports we hate morſe than a Leaguer; When we viſit a Miſs, We ſtill brag how we Kiſs, But 'tis with a Bottle me fºgue her. Sir joſ. Come, come, Madam, let all things be Forgot; Dinner is ready, the Cloth is laid in the TNéxt Room, let us in and be merry; there was no Harm meant as I am true littlejoſlin. La. Cock. Sir Oliver knows I can't be angry with Him, though he plays the naughty Man thus: But Why, my Dear, wou'd y” expoſe your ſelf in this Ridiculous Habit, to the Cenſure of both our Honours? Sir Oliv. Indeed I was to blame to be over-perſwaded; I intended dutifully to retire into the Pantry, And there civilly to divert my ſelf at Back-Gammon With the Butler. Sir joſ. Faith, I muſt even own, the Fault was mine; 1 intic'd him hither, Lady. - Sir Oliv. How the Devil, Ned, came they to find lls out here 2 - - Court. No Blood-hound draws ſo ſure as a jealous Woman. Sir Oliv. I am afraid Thomas has been unfaithful : Prithee, Ned, ſpeak to my Lady, That there may be A perfect underſtanding between us, and that Sentry May be ſent home for my Clothes, that I may no Longer wear the Marks of her Diſpleaſure. - Court. Let me alone, Sir Oliver. . . [He goes to my Lady Cockwood. How do you find your ſelf, Madam, after N This violent Paſſion ? La. Cock. This has been a lucky Adventure, Mr. Courtall; now am I abſolute Miſtreſs of My own Condućt for a time. Court. Then ſhall I be a happy Man, Madam : I knew this would be the Conſequence of ali, And yet could not I forbear the Projećt. , Sir Oliv. How didſt thou ſhuffle away Rake-bell, And the Ladies, Brother ? - - - - [To Sir Joſlin. Sirjoſ. I have appointed 'em to meet us at ſix a Clock, At |- -|
Page 47

/ 2. - - 2- A She wou'd if She could. At the New Spring-Garden. , - Sir Oliv. Then will we yet, in ſpight of the Stars' That have croſs'd us, be in Conjunétion with Madam Rampant, Brother. Court. Come, Gentlemen, Dinner is on the Table. Sir # Ha! Sly-Girl and Mad-Cap, I’ll enter You, i'faith; ſince you have found the way To the Bear, I’ll fegue you. S I N G S. When we viſit a Miſs, We ſtill brag how we Kiſs; But 'tis with a Bottle we fºgue her. ~ [Exeunt ſinging. ACT IV. SCENE I. A Dining-Room. Enter Lady Cockwood. La. Cock. Lady cannot be too jealous of her Servants Love, this faithleſs and inconſtant Age: His amorous Carriage to that prating Girl to day, Though he pretends it was to blind Sir Oliver, Ifear, will prove a certain Sign of his revolted - Heart; the Letters I have counterfeited in theſe Girls Name will clear all; if he accept of that Appointment, And refuſes mine, I need not any longer doubt. - Enter Sentry. Sentry, have the Letters - And Meſlage been deliver'd, as I dire&ted 2 - Sent. Punétually, Madam; I knew they were to be. Found at the latter end of a Play, I ſent a Porter Firſt with the Letter to Mr. Courtall, who Was at the King's-houſe, he ſent for him out By the Door-Keeper, and deliver'd it into His own Hands. - La. Cock. Did you keep on your Vizard, that The Fellow might not know how to deſcribe you ?:. Sent. I did, Madam. - La. Cock. And how did he receive it? . Sent. Like a Traytour to all Goodneſs, with All the Signs of Joy imaginable. La. Cock. Be not angry, Sentry, 'tis as my Heart Wiſht
Page 48

48 - She wif She cou’d. ---. Wiſht it: What did you do with the Letter to Mr. Freeman? For I thought fit to deceive 'em both, To make my Policy leſs ſuſpicious to Courtall. Sent. The Porter found him at the Duke's houſe, Madam, and delivered it with like care. La. Cock. Very well. Sent. After the Letters were deliver'd, Madam, I went my ſelf to the Play-houſe, and ſent in For Mr. Courtall, who came out to me immediately; I told him your Ladiſhip preſented your humble Service to him, and that Sir Oliver was going Into the City with Sir joſlin, to viſit his Brother Cockwood, and that it would add much more To your Ladiſhip's Happineſs, if he would be pleas'd To meet you in Grays-Inn Walks this lovely Evening. La. Cock. And how did he entertain the Motion ? Sent. Bleſs me ! I tremble ſtill to think upon it ! I could not have imagin'd he had been ſo wicked; He counterfeited the greateſt Paſſion, railed at His Fate, and ſwore a thouſand horrid Oaths, That ſince he came into the Play-houſe, he had Notice of a Buſineſs, that concern’d both his -Honour and Fortune; and that he was an undone Man, if he did not go about it preſently; Pray'd me to deſire your Ladiſhip to excuſe Him this Evening, and that to morrow he Wou’d be wholly at your Devotion. La. Cock. Ha, ha, ha! he little thinks how Much he has oblig'd me. Sent. I had much ado to forbear upbraiding Him with his Ingratitude to your Ladiſhip. La. Cock. Poor Sentry be not concern’d for me, I have conquer'd my Affečtion, and thou ſhalt find It is not Jealouſie has been my Counſellour in this. Go, let our Hoods and Masks be ready, . That I may ſurpriſe Courtall, and make the Beſt Advantage of this lucky Opportunity. Sent. I obey you, Madam., La. Cock. How am I fill'd with Indignation? To find my Perſon and my Paſſion both deſpis'd, And what is more, ſo much precious Time Fool'd away in fruitleſs Expediation: I wou’d poiſon My Face, ſo I might be reveng'd on this ingrate Enter Sir Oliver. Sir Oliv. My Deareſt! - La. Cock. My Deareſt Dear ! prithee do – . Not go into the City to Night. ful Villain. - [Exit Sentry. Sir

Page 49

- * - She would if She coºd. 49 Sir Oliv. My Brother jolly is gone before, And I am to call him at Counſellour Trot’s Chamber in the Temple. - La. Cock. Well, if you did but know the fear I have upon me, when you are abſent, you would Not ſeek Occaſions to be from me thus. - Sir Oliv. Let me comfort thee with a Kiſs; What ſhould'ſt thou be afraid of? . La. Cock. I cannot but believe that every Woman That ſees thee, muſt be in Love with thee, as I am : Do not blame my Jealouſie. - Sir Oliv. I proteſt, I wou’d refuſe a Counteſs Rather than abuſe thee, poor Heart. La. Cock. And then you are ſo deſperate upon The leaſt Occaſion, I ſhou'd have acquainted You elſe with ſomething that concerns your Honour. Sir Oliv. My Honour! you ought in duty to do it. La. Cock. Nay, I knew how paſſionate you wou'd Be preſently; therefore you ſhall never know it. Sir Oliv. Do not leave me in doubt, I ſhall Suſpe&t every one I look upon; I will kill A Common-Council-Man or two, before I come Back, if you do not tell me. La. Cock. Dear, how I tremble! Will you Promiſe me you will not quarrel then? If you tender My Life and Happineſs, I am ſure you will not. Sir Oliv. I will bear any thing rather than be An Enemy to thy Quiet, my Dear. La. Cock. I cou’d wiſh Mr. Courtall a Man of better Principles, becauſe I know you love him, my Dear. Sir Oliv. Why, what has he done? La. Cock. I always treated him with great Reſpects, Out of my Regard to your Friendſhip; but he, like An impudent Man as he is, to day miſconſtruing My Civility, in moſt unſeemly Language, Made a foul Attempt upon my Honour. Sir Oliv. Death, and Hell, and Furies' I will Have my Pumps, and long Sword.' La. Cock. Oh, I ſhall faint | did not you promiſe Me you wou'd not be ſo raſh? Sir Oliv. Well, I will not kill him, for fear of Murdering thee, my Dear. - La. Cock. You may decline your Friendſhip, and By your Coldneſs give him no Encouragement To viſit our Family. - Sir Oliv. I think thy Advice the beſt for this once indeed; - For it is not fit to publiſh ſuch a Bus'neſs: But
Page 50

to She wou'd if She cord But if he ſhould be ever tempting or attempting, Let me know it prithee, my Dear. - La. Cock. If you moderate your ſelf according. To my Direétions now, I ſhall never conceal Any thing from you, that may increaſe your Juſt Opinion of my Conjugal Fidelity. Sir Oliv. Was ever Man bléſs'd with ſuch a Vertuous Lady ? Yet cannot I forbear going . . . . . - - A ranging agen. Now muſt I to the Spring-Garden, - -- [Aſide. To meet my Brother jolly and Madam Rampant. La. Cock. Prithee be ſo good to think how - Melancholy I ſpend my time here; for I have -- Joy in no Company, but thine , and let that: - - Bring thee home a little ſooner. - - : . . . . Sir Oliv. Thou haſt been ſo kind in this Diſcovery, " . . That I am loth to leave thee. - * . . . La. Cock. I wiſh you had not been engag’d ſo far. , - - - Sir Oliv. Ay, that’s it: Farewel, my vertuous Dear. [Ex. Sir Oliv. La. Cock. Farewel, my deareſt Dear. I know - He has not Courage enough to queſtion Courtall; . But this will make him hate him, encreaſe his Confidence of me, and inſtifle my baniſhing that. Faiſe Fellow out Houſe: It is not fit a Man that Has abus'd my Love, ſhould come hither, and pry into my Aétions; beſides, this will make his "" Acceſs more difficult to that wanton º; C. . - Enter Ariana and Gatty with their Hoods and Marks. Whither are you going, Couſins 2 Gatty. To take the Air upon the Water, Madam. Aria. And for variety, to walk a Turn or two In the New Spring-Garden. • La. Cock. I heard you were gone abroad. - - - With Mr. Courtall, and Mr. Freeman. - - Gatty. For Heaven’s ſake, why ſhould your Ladiſhip Have ſuch an ill Opinion of us? La. Cock. The Truth is, before I ſaw you, I believ’d. It meerly the vanity of that prating Man; - Mr. Courtall told Mrs. Gazette this morning, That you were ſo well acquainted already, that you. Wou'd meet him and Mr. Freeman any where; And that you had promis'd’em to receive. - And make Appointment by Letters. - Gatty. Oh impudent Man!” . - Aria. Now you ſee the Conſequence, Siſter, . Of our rambling; they have rais'd this falſe Story, from our innocent fooling with 'em in the Mulberry-Garden laſt night. . Gatty, I cou’d almoſt forſwear ever ſpeaking to a Man agen. La. Cock - - - - - Co.: *
Page 51

She woºd if she old sº La. Cock. Was Mr. Courtall in the Mulberry-Garden, laſt night? Aria. Yes, Madam. . - - La. Cock. And did he ſpeak to you?. - … ". . . Gatty. There paſs'd a little harmleſs Raillery ! . Betwixt us; but you amaze me, Madam. - -- Aria. I cou’d not imagine any Man cou’d be thus unworthy. La. Cock. He has quite loſt my good Opinion too: - In Duty to Sir Oliver, I have hitherto ſhow'd Him ſome Countenance ; but I ſhall hate him - - Hereafter for your ſakes. But I detain you from your Recreations, Couſins. Gatty. We are very much oblig'd to your Ladiſhip for this timely notice. Aria. Gatt. Your Servant, Madam. [Ex. Aria. and Gatt. La. Cock. Your Servant, Couſins - - In the Mulberry-Garden laſt night! when I ſate languiſhing, And vainly expe&ting him at home: This has Incens'd me ſo, that I could kill him. I am glad Theſe Girls are gone to the Spring-Garden, It helps my Deſign; the Letters I have counterfeited, Have appointed Courtall and Freeman to meet Them there, they will produce 'em, and confirm All I have ſaid: I will daily poiſon theſe Girls - * With ſuch Lies, as ſhall make their Quarrel to - Courtall irreconcileable, and render Freeman Only ſuſpećted; for I would not have him Thought equally guilty: He ſecretly began To make an Addreſs to me at the Bear, and This Breach ſhall give him an Opportunity . . To purſue it. - / ~ Enter Sentry. Sent. Here are your things, Madam. La. Cock. That's well: Oh Sentry I ſhall once More be happy; for now Mr. Courtall has given Me an Occaſion, that I may, without Ingratitude, Check his unlawful Paſſion, and free my ſelf From the trouble of an Intrigue, that gives me Every day ſuch fearful Apprehenſions of my Honour. - - [Ex. Lady Cockwood and Sentry. is C E N E II. New Spring-Garden. 2- / - > Enter Sir Joſlin, Rake-hell, and Waiter. Wait. Will you be pleas'd to walkinto an Arbour, Gentlemen P Sirjoſ. By and by, good Sir. - Rake, I wonder Sir Oliver is not come yet, - - C - Qir Cºnſ
Page 52

52 She wou'd if She cou’d. Širjoſ. Nay, he will not fail, I warrant thee, Boy; but what's the matter with thy Noſe, my little Rake-hell ? Rake. A fooliſh Accident; jeſting at the Fleece This Afternoon, I miſtook my Man a little, a dull Rogue that could not underſtand Raillery, , Made a ſudden Repartee with a Quart-pot, Sir Joſlin. Sir joſ. Why didſt not thou ſtick him to the Wall, my little Rake-hell? Rake. The truth is, Sir Joſlin, he deſerv’d it; But look you, in caſe of a doubtful Wound, I am unwilling to give my Friends too often the Trouble to bail me; and if it ſhou'd be Mortal, you know a younger Brother has * Not wherewithal to rebate the edge of a Witneſs, and mollifie the Hearts of a Jury. Sir joſ. This is very prudently conſider'd indeed. Rake. 'Tis time to be wiſe, Sir ; my Courage has º Almoſt run me out of a conſiderable Annuity. When I liv'd firſt about this Town, I agreed With a Surgeon for Twenty pounds a Quarter, To cure me of all the Knocks, Bruiſes, and Green Wounds I ſhould receive, and in one half Year The poor Fellow begg'd me to be releas'd Of his Bargain, and ſwore I wou’d undo him Elſe in Lintand Balſom. - - Enter Sir Oliver. - Sirjoſ. Ho! here’s my Brother cockwood come------ Sir Oliv. I, Brother jolly, I have kept my word, You ſee; but 'tis a barbarous thing to abuſe my Lady, I have had ſuch a Proof of her Vertue, I will tell thee all anon. w But where's Madam Rampant, and the reſt of The Ladies, Mr. Rake-hell ? * Rake. Faith, Sir, being diſappointed at noon, They were unwilling any more to ſet a Certainty At hazard: 'Tis Term-time, and they have Severally betook themſelves, ſome to their - - Chamber-pračice, and others to the Places of Publick Pleading. | Sir Oliv. Faith, Brother jolly, let us elen go into An Arbour, and thenfegue Mr. Rake-hell. - Sirjoſ. With all my Heart, wou’d we had Madam Rappant. SING S. . - She’s as frollick and free, As her Lovers dare be, Never aw’d by a fooliſh Punčilio; She'll not ſtart from her Place, Though thou nam'ſ a black Ace, 4...1 -iji I.2.1 - n-2. -1 - r +2 c----.1:1:-"
Page 53

She wou'd if She could 53 Hey, Boys! Come, come, come! let's in, And delay our Sport no longer. - - [Ex, ſinging, She'll not ſtart from her, &c. Enter Courtall and Freeman, ſeverally. - Court. Free/M41. - - Free. Courtall, what the Devil's the matter with thee? I have obſerv'd thee prying up and down The Walks like a Citizen's Wife, that has dropt her Holiday Pocket-Handkercher. Court. What unlucky Devil has brought thee-hither ? - Free. I believe a better-natur'd Devil than yours, - Courtall, if a Leveret be better Meat than an old Puſs, that has been cours'd by moſt of the young Fellows of her Country: I am not working my Brain - For a Counter-plot, a Diſappointment is not my bus'neſs. Court. You are miſtaken, Freeman : Prithee be w - Gone, and leave me the Garden to my ſelf, or - - * \ . . . I ſhall grow as teſty as an old Fowler that is put - By his ſhoot, after he has crept half a mile upon his belly. Free. Prithee be thou gone, or I ſhall take it as - llnkindly as a Chymiſt wou'd, if thou ſhould'ſt Kick down his Limbeck in the very minute - That he look'd for projećtion. Court. Come, come ; you muſt yield, Freeman, sº Your buſineſs cannot be of ſuch conſequence as mine. Free. If ever thou hadſt a bus’neſs of ſuch - Conſequence in thy Life as mine is, I will condeſcend To be made incapable of Affairs preſently. - - Court. Why, I have an appointment made me, +. Man, without my ſeeking, by a Woman, for Whom I wou'd have mortgag'd my whole Eſtate, To have had her abroad but to break a Cheeſe-Cake. Free. And I have an Appointment made me without *... My ſeeking too, by ſuch a ſhe, that I will break the whole - - Ten Commandments, rather than Diſappoint her of her breaking one. Court. Come, you do but jeſt, Freeman; a forſaken Miſtreſs Cou'd not be more malicious than thou art : prithee be gone. - Free. Prithee do thou be gone. - - * - - Court. 'sDeath! the ſight of thee will ſcare my Woman for ever, - Free. 'sDeath ! the ſight of thee will make my - - * - Woman believe me the falſeſt Villain breathing. - - Court. We ſhall ſtand fooling till we are both ºlndone, and I know not how to help it. - * Free. Let us proceed honeſtly like Friends, . Diſcover the truth of things to one another, and - * ---------------, * - - - § - -
Page 54

s 4. She wou'd if She cou’d. - º If we cannot reconcile our Buſineſs, we will Draw Cuts, and part fairly. . Court. I do not like that way; for talk is only Allowable at the latter end of an Intrigue, and Shou'd never be us’d at the beginning of an Amour, For fear of frighting a young Lady from Her good Intentions—yet I care not, though I Read the Letter, but I will conceal the Name. - Free. I have a Letter too, and am content to do the ſame. Court. reads. Sir, in ſending you this Letter, -- I proceed againſt the Modeſty ºf our Sex----- . . . Free. 'sſ)eath, this begins juſt like my Letter. Court. Do you read on then-------- *...* Free, reads. But let not the good Opinion I have Conceiv'd of you, make you too ſevere in your Cenſuring of me------ Court. Word for word. Free. Now do you read agen. Chart. reads. If you give your ſelf the trouble to be Walking in the New Spring-Garden this Evening, I will meet you there, and tell you a Secret, which I have reaſon to fear, becauſe it comes to your - łºnowledge by my mºans, will make you hate Your humble Servant. - - Frce. Verbatim my Letter; Hey-day ! • *- Court. Prithee let's compare the Hands. - - [They compare 'em. Free. 'sDeath, the Hand's the ſame. Court. I hope the Name is not the ſame too------ - Free. If it be, we are finely jilted, faith. – Court. I long to be undeceiv'd; prithee do Thou ſhow firſt, Freeman. - Free. No-----. But both together, if you wil". Court. Agreed. -- Frce. Ariana. - Court. Gatty----- Ha, ha, ha. - Frce. The little Rogues are maſculine in their Proceedings, and have made one another Confidents in their Love. - - Court. But I do not like this altogether ſo well, Franck; I wiſh they had appointed us ſeveral Places: For though 'tis evident they have Truſted one another with the bargain, no Woman ever ſeals before Witneſs. Frce. Prithee how didſt thou eſcape the ſhares Of the Old Devil this Afternoon? Court. With much ado: Sentry had ſet me; if her - - - - Ladiſhip º º-
Page 55

She wou'd if She cou’d. 55 Ladiſhip had got me into her clutches, there Had been no getting me off without a Reſcue, Or paying down the Money; for ſhe Always Arreſts upon Execution. Free. You made a handſome Lie to her Woman. Court. For all this, I know ſhe's angry; for ſhe Thinks nothing a juſt Excuſe in theſe Caſes, Though it were to ſave the Forfeit of a Man's Eſtate, or reprieve the Life of her own natural Brother, Free. Faith, thou haſt not done altogether like A Gentleman with her; thou ſhould'ſt faſt thy & Self up to a Stomach now and then, to oblige Her; if there were nothing in it, but the hearty Welcome, methinks twere enough to make thee Bear, ſometimes, with the Homelineſs of the Fare.. Court. I know not what I might do in a Camp, Where there were no other Woman; but I ſhall Hardly in this Town, where there is ſuch Plenty, Forbear good Meat Fºr this is rather in Averſionin thee, than any Real Fault in the Woman; if this lucky Bus'neſs Had not fallen out, I intended, with your good leave, To have out-bid you for her Ladiſhip's Favour. Court. I ſhould never have conſented to that, Franck; Though I am a little reſty at preſent, I am not ſuch A Jade, but I ſhould ſtrain if another rid againſt me; I have 'ere now lik’d nothing in a Woman, That I have lov’d at laſt in ſpite only, Becauſe another had a mind to her. Free. Yonder are a º of Vizards tripping towards us. . Court. 'Tis they, i'fait Free. We need not divide, ſince they come together. . Court. I was a little afraid when we compar’d - Letters, they had put a Trick upon us; but now I am confirm'd they are mighty honeſt. . - ! Enter Ariana and Gatty. . Aria. We cannot avoid 'em. Gatty. Let us diſſemble our Knowledge of their Bus'neſs a little, and then take 'em down in The height of their Aſſurance. - - Court. Free. Your Servant, Ladies. Aria. I perceive it is as impoſſible, Gentlemen, To walk without you, as without our Shadows; Never were poor Women ſo haunted by the - Ghoſts of their ſelf-murder'd Lovers, - - Gatty. If itſhou'd be our good Fortunesto have - to get my ſelf an Appetite to Horſe-fleſh. Yººt ºn
Page 56

- -- --~ . , 3 I e 2 56 She would if She coºd. You in Love with us, we will take care you Shall not grow deſperate, and leave the World in an ill Humour. Aria. If you ſhou'd, certainly your Ghoſts Would be very malicious. Court. Twere pity you ſhou’d have your Curtains Drawn in the dead of the Night, and your pleaſing º Slumbers interrupted by any thing but Fleſh and Blood, Ladies. Free. Shall we walk a Turn ? Aria. By your ſelves, if you pleaſe. - Gatty. Our Company may put a conſtraint upon you; For I find you daily hover about theſe Gardens, - As a Kite does about a Backſide, - f Watching an opportunity to catch up the Poultry. Aria. Wo be to the Daughter or Wife of ſome . Merchant-Taylor, or poor Felt-maker now ; For you ſeldom row to Fox-hall, without Some ſuch Plot againſt the City. Free. You wrong us, Ladies, our bus'neſs . Has happily ſucceeded, fince we have the -- - Honour to wait upon you. . Gatty. You could not expe&t to ſee us here. Court. Your true Lover, Madam, when he miſſes His Miſtreſs, is as reſtleſs as a Spaniel that has - Loſt his Maſter; he ranges up and down - , - The Plays, the Park, and all the Gardens, and t - Never ſtays long, but where he has the . Happineſs to ſee her. . - Gatty. I ſuppoſe your Miſtreſs, Mr. Courtall, is Always the laſt Woman you are acquainted with. Court. Do not think, Madam, I have that falſe Meaſure of my Acquaintance, which Poets have Of their Verſes, always to think the laſt beſt. Though I eſteem you ſo, in Juſtice to your Merit. - Gatty. Or if you do not love her beſt, you always Love to talk of her moſt ; as a barren Coxcomb, That wants Diſcourſe, is ever entertaining Company out of the laſt Book he read in. Court. Now you accuſe me moſt unjuſtly, Madam; ~ Who, the Devil, that has common ſenſe, will go A Birding with a Clack in his Cap? . . . - Aria. Nay, we do not blame, Gentlemen, Every one in their way ; a Huntſman talks of his Dogs, a Falconer of his Hawks, a Jocky of His Horſe; and a Gallant of his Miſtreſs. Gatty. Without the allowance of this Vanity, an Amour would ſoon grow as dull as Matrimony. \ , Coºrt.
Page 57

She would if She could 57 ~ - Court. Whatſoever you ſay, Ladies, I cannot Believe you think us Men of ſuch abominable Principles. sº Free. For my part, I have ever held it as ingrateful To boaſt of the Favours of a Miſtreſs, as to deny The Courteſies of a Friend. Court. A Friend that bravely ventures his Life in The Field to ſerve me, deſerves but equally with A Miſtreſs that kindly expoſes her Honour to Oblige me, eſpecially when ſhe does it as Generouſly too, and with as little Ceremony. Free. And I would no more betray the Honour Of ſuch a Woman, than I would the Life of a . Man that ſhou’d rob on purpoſe to ſupply me. Gatty. We believe you Men of Honour, and know It is below you to talk of any Woman that deſerves it. Aria. You are ſo generous, you ſeldom inſult after a vićtory. Gatty. And ſo vain, that you always triumph before it. Court. 'sDeath! what’s the meaning of all this P. Gatty. Though you find us ſo kind, Mr. Courtall, Pray do not tell Mrs. Gazette to morrow, that we came Hither on purpoſe this Evening, to meet you. Court. I would as ſoon Print it, and fee a Fellow To poſt it up with the Play-bills. Gatty. You have repos'd a great deal of Confidence In her, for all you pretend this ill Opinion Of her Secrecy now. Court. I never truſted her with the name of A Miſtreſs, that I ſhould be jealous of, if I ſaw her Receive fruit, and go out of the Play-houſe With a Stranger. Gatty. For ought as I ſee, we are infinitely Oblig'd to you, Sir. Court. 'Tis impoſſible to be inſenſible of ſo Much Goodneſs, Madam. Gatty. What Goodneſs, pray, Sir? Court. Come, come, give over this Raillery. Gatty. You are ſo ridiculouſly unworthy, that’twere A Folly to reprove you with a ſerious look. Court. On my Conſcience, your Heart begins to Fail you now we are coming to the point, as a Young Fellow's that was never in the Field before. Gatty. You begin to amaze me. Court. Since you your ſelf ſent the Chalienge, You muſt not in Honour flie off now. Gatty. Challenge Oh Heavens ! this confirms all : Were I a Man, I would kill thee for the Injuries thqu haſt already done me, H Free,
Page 58

58 . She wou'd if She cou’d. Free, to Aria. Let not your ſuſpicion of my - linkindneſs, make you thus ſcrupulous; was ever City ill treated, that ſurrendred without Aſſault or Summons 2 -dria. Dear Siſter, what ill Spirit brought us hither ? Iº. º ſo much Impudence in my Life. Jourt. aſide.] Hey, Jilts! they are as at it Already as the Old #! º: good at i Free. Come, Ladies, you have exercis'd your Wit enough; you wou'd not venture Letters Of ſuch conſequence for a Jeſt only. " Gatty. Letters! Bleſs me, what will this come to? Court. To that none of us ſhall have cauſe to Repent, I hope, Madam. Aria. Let us flie’em, Siſter, they are Devils, And not Men, they could never be ſo malicious elſe. Enter Lady Cockwood, and Sentry. La. Cock. Your Servant, Couſins. - Court, ſtarting. Ho, my Lady Cockwood! My Ears Are grown an inch already. - - Aria. My Lady She’ll think this an Appointment, Siſter. Free. This is Madam Matchiavil, I ſuſpećt, Courtall. Court. Nay, 'tis her Plot doubtleſs: Now am I As much out of Countenance, as I ſhould be if Sir Qliver Should take me making bold with her Ladiſhip. La. Cock. Do not let me diſcompoſe you, I can walk alone, Couſins. Gatty. Are you ſo uncharitable, Madam, to think We have any buſineſs with 'em 2 Aria. It has been our ill Fortune to meet them here, And nothing could be ſo lucky as your Coming, . Madam, to free us from 'em. Gatty. They have abus'd us in the groſſeſt manner. - - Aria. Counterfeited Letters under our Hands. - * La. Cock. Never trouble your ſelves, Couſins, - - I have heard this is a common praćtice with ſuch - linworthy Men: Did they not threaten to divulge Them, and defame you to the World 2 - Gatty. We cannot believe they intend anything leſs, Madam, La. Cock. Doubtleſs, they had ſuch a mean Opinion Of your Wit and Honour, that they thought to Fright you to a baſe compliance with their wicked Purpoſes. Aria. I hate the very ſight of 'em. Gatty, I could almoſt wiſh my ſelf a Diſeaſe, To breathe Infečtion upon 'em. Court. Very pretty 2 we have carried on our deſigns. Very luckily againſt theſe young Ladies, Free. We have loſt their good Opinion for ever, - La. Cock.
Page 59

- She wou'd if She could 59 La. Cock. I know not whether their Folly or their Impudence be greater, they are not worth your Anger; they are only fit to be laugh'd at, and deſpis'd. . Court. A very fine Old Devil this La, Cock. Mr. Freeman, this is not like a Gentleman, s. To affront a couple of Young Ladies thus; but I Cannot blame you ſo much; you are, in a manner, A Stranger to our Family: But I wonder how that Baſe Man can look me in the Face, conſidering How civilly he has been treated at our Houſel Court. The truth is, Madam, I am a Raſcal; but I fear you have contributed to the making me ſo: Be not as unmerciful as the Devil is to a poor Sinner. Sent. Did you ever ſee the like? Never truſt Me, if he has not the Confidence to make my Vertuous Lady acceſſary to his Wickedneſs. La. Cock. Ay, Sentry, 'tis a Miracle if my Honour Eſcapes, conſidering the Acceſs which his Greatneſs With Sir Oliver has given him daily to me. Free. Faith, Ladies, we did not counterfeit theſe Letters, we are abus’d as well as you. Court. I receiv'd mine from a Porter at the King's Play-houſe, and I will ſhow it you, that you may See if you know the Hand. - La. Cock. Sentry, are you ſure they never ſaw Any of your Writing? Court. 'sDeath ! I am ſo diſcompos'd, I know - : Not where I have put it. - Sent. Oh Madam now I remember myſelf, Mrs. Gatty help'd me once to indite a Letter to my Sweet-heart. La. Cock. Forgetful Wench! them I am undone. Court. Oh, here it is— Hey, who's here? - - [As he has the Letter in hand, Enter Sir Joſlin, Sir Oliver, and Rake-hell, all drunk; with Muſick. They Sing. She’s no Miſtreſs of mine, That drinks not her Wine, Or froms at my Friends Drinking-Motions; If my Heart thou would'ſ gain, Drink thy Bottle of Champaign, *Twill ſerve thee for Paint, and Love-Potions. Sir Oliv. Who's here? Courtall, in my Lady’s - Company I’ll diſpatch him preſently; - Help me, Brother jolly. [He draws. - H 2. ' Hla. Cock.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 60

6o She wou'd if She cou’d. La. Cock. For Heavens ſake, Sir Oliver : Courtall drawing.] What do yo mean, Sir 2 Sir Oliv. I’ll teach you more manners, than To make your Attempts on my Lady, Sir. La. Cock. and Sent. Oh Murder Murder 1 - . [They ſhriek. La. Cock. Save my dear Sir Oliver, Oh my Dear Sir Oliver 1 - *~~ --- [The roung Ladies ſhriek, and run out; they all draw to part them ; they fight off the Stage; ſhe ſhrieks, and runs out. ACT V. SC E N E I. Sir Oliver’s Dining-Room. Enter Lady Cockwood, Table, and Carpet. La. Cock. I Did not think he had been ſo deſperate in - His drink; if they had kill'd one another, I had then been reveng'd, and freed from all my Fears----- - Enter Sentry. Sentry, your Careleſneſs and Forgetfulneſs Some time or other will undo me; Had not Sir Oliver, and Sir joſlin, came ſo luckily Into the Garden, the Letters had been diſcover'd, And my Honour left to the Mercy of a falſe Man, And two young fleering Girls: Did you ſ To Mr. Freeman unperceiv'd in the Hurry : Sent. I did, Madam ; and he promis'd me to diſ-ingage Himſelf as ſoon as poſſibly he could, and wait llpon your Ladiſhip with all Secrecy. La. Cock. I have ſome reaſon to believe him A Man of Honour. - Sent. Methinks indeed his very Look, Madam, Speaks him to be much more a Gentleman Than Mr. Courtall; but I was unwilling before Now to let your Ladiſhip know my Opinion, for Fear of offending your Inclinations. - La. Cock. I hope by his means to get theſe Letters. Into my own bands, and ſo prevent the Inconveniencies. They may bring upon my Honour. Sent. I wonder, Madam, what ſhould be Sir Oliver's Quarrel to Mr. Courtall. - - La. Cock. .
Page 61

- She would ifShe could 6 I La. Cock. You know how apt he is to be ſuſpicious In his Drink; 'tis very likely he thought Mr. courtall Betray’d him at the Bear to day. Sent. Pray Heaven he be not jealous of your Ladiſhip, finding you abroad ſo unexpećtedly; if He be, we ſhall have a ſad hand of him when He comes home, Madam. - La. Cock. I ſhould have apprehended it much My ſelf, Sentry, if his drunkenneſs had not unadviſedly Ingag’d him in his Quarrel ; as ſoon as he grows A little ſober, I am ſure his Fear will bring him Home, and make him apply himſelf to me, with All Humility and Kindneſs; for he is ever under-hand, Fain to uſe my Intereſt and Diſcretion to Make Friends to compound theſe Buſineſſes, Or to get an Order for the ſecuring his Perſon and his Honour. Sent. I believe verily, Mr. Courtall wou'd have Been ſo rude to have kill’d him, if Mr. Freeman and The reſt had not civilly interpos'd their Weapons. La. Cock. Heavens forbid! though he be a wicked Man, I am oblig'd in duty to love him: Whither Did my Couſins go after we came home, Sentry? Sent. They are at the next door, Madam, Laughing and playing at Lantrelou, with my old. Lady Love-youth and her Daughters. La. Cock. I hope they will not come home then Tb interrupt my Affairs with Mr. Freeman. - w Hark! ſome body knocks; it may be him : Run down quickly. - Sent. I fly, Madam. La. Cock. Now if he has a real Inclination for my Perſon, I'll give him a handſome Opportunity To reveal it. - - > Enter Sentry and Freeman. Frée. Your Servant, Madam. - La. Cock. Oh, Mr. Freeman this unlucky Accident Has robb'd me of all my Quiet; I am almoſt diſtraćted. With thinking of the danger Sir Oliver's dear Life is in. Free. You need not fear, Madam, all things will. Be reconcil'd again to morrow. Sent. You wou’d not blame my Lady’s Apprehenſions, did you but know the Tenderneſs of her Affečtions. w [Knocking without. [Exit Sentry. La. Cock.
Page 62

2 - º 62 She wou'd if She could. 'La, Cock. Mr. Courtall is a falſe and mercileſs Man. " Free. He has always own’d a great Reſpect for Your Ladiſhip, and I never heard him mention You with the leaſt Diſhonour. La. Cock. He cannot, without injuring the truth; Heaven knows my Innocence: I hope you did Not let him know, Sir, of your coming hither. . Free. I ſhou’d never merit the Happineſs To wait upon you agen, had I ſo abus’d This extraordinary Favour, Madam. - . La. Cock. If I have done anything unbeſeeming - ~ My Honour; I hope you will be juſt, Sir, and - - Impute it to my Fear; I know no Man ſo proper To compoſe this unfortunate Difference, as Your ſelf; and if a Lady's Tears and Prayers Have power to move you to compaſſion, I know you will imploy your utmoſt endeavour, - - To preſerve me, my dear Sir Oliver. Free. Do not, Madam, afflićt your ſelf ſo much; I dare ingage my Life, {His Life and Honour ſhall be both ſecure. La. Cock. You are truly Noble, Sir; I was ſo Diſtraćted with my Fears, that I cannot well Remember how we parted at the Spring-Garden. . Free. We all divided, Madam, after your Ladiſhip And the Young Ladies were gone together; Sir Oliver, Sir foſlin, and the Company with them, Took one Boat, and Mr. Courtall and I another. , La. Cock. Then I need not apprehend their Meeting again to Night. Free. You need not, Madam; I left Mr. Courtall in His Chamber, wondring what ſhould make Sir Oliver draw upon him; and fretting and Fuming about the Trick that was put upon us With the Letters to day. La. Cock, Oh! I had almoſt forgot my ſelf; I aſſure you, Sir, thoſe Letters were ſent by one, That has no Inclination to be an Enemy of yours. [Knocking below. Some Body knocks. [Exit Sentry. If it be Sir Oliver, I am undone, he will hate me mortally, - If he does but ſuſpećt I uſe any ſecret Means, To hinder him from juſtifying his - Reputation honourably to the World. Enter
Page 63

She wou'd if She could 63 - . ... Enter Sentry. Sent. Oh Madam | Here is Mr. Courtall below in The Entry, diſcharging a Coachman; I told Him your Ladiſhip was buſie, but he wou'd Not hear me, and, I find, do what I can, He will come up. - La. Cock. I would not willingly ſuſpect you, Sir. Free. I have deceiv'd him, Madam, in my coming Hither, and am as unwilling he ſhou'd find me Here, as you can be. La. Cock. He will not believe my innocent buſineſs. . With you, but will raiſe a new Scandal on my Honour, and publiſh it to the whole Town. Sent. Let him ſtep in the Cloſet, Madam. La. Cock. Quick, Sir, quick, I beſeech you, I will. . Send him away again immediately. - Enter Courtall. La. Cock. Mr. Courtall ! Have you no ſenſe of Honour nor Modeſty left? after ſo many Injuries, To come into our Houſe, and without my Approbation, rudely preſs upon my Retirement thus? Court. Pray, Madam, hear my Buſineſs. La. Cock Thy Buſineſs is maliciouſly to purſue My Ruine; thou comeſt with a baſe deſign to have Sir Oliver catch thee here, and deſtroy the Onely Happineſs I have. - Court. I come, Madam, to beg your pardon for - - The Fault I did unwillingly commit, and to know - Of you the reaſon of Sir Oliver's Quarrel to me. La. Cock. Thy guilty Conſcience is able to tell Thee that, vain and ungrateful Man Court. I am innocent, Madam, of all things that May offend him; and I am ſure, if you wou'd. But hear me, I ſhou’d remove the Juſtice Of your Quarrel too. La. Cock. You are miſtaken, Sir, if you think I am concern'd for your going to the Spring-Garden This Evening; my Quarrel is the ſame with Sir Oliver, and is ſo juſt, that thou deſerv'ſt to Be poyſon'd for what thou haſt done. Court. Pray, Madam, let me know my Fault. La. Cock, bluſh to think upon’t: Sir Oliver, ſince. We came from the Bear, has heard ſomething Thou haſt ſaid concerning me; but what it is . - * I cou’d
Page 64

64 She would if She cond I could not get him to diſcover: He told me 'twas Enough for me to know he was ſatisfi'd º 's Of my Innocence. Court. This is meer Paſſion, Madam. La. Cock. This is the uſual Revenge of ſuch baſe Men as thou art, when they cannot compaſs Their Ends, with their venemous Tongues To blaſt the Honour of a Lady. - Court. This is a ſudden alteration, Madam; within Theſe few hours you had a kinder Opinion of me. La. Cock. 'Tis no wonder you brag of Favours . Behind my back, that have the Impudence to llpbraid me with Kindneſs to my face; doſt Thou think I cou’d ever have a good thought of Thee, whom I have always found ſo treacherous In thy Friendſhip to Sir Oliver. [Knock at the door. - - Enter Sentry. Sent. Oh, Madam here is Sir Oliver come home. La. Cock. O Heavens ! I ſhall be believ'd guilty Now, and he will kill us both. [He draws. Court. I warrant you, Madam, I’ll defend your Life. La. Cock. Oh! there will be Murder, Murder; -- - For Heaven's ſake, Sir, hide your ſelf in ſome Corner or other. - Court. I'll ſtep into that Cloſet, Madam. Sent. Hold, hold, Sir ; by no means: his Pipes And his Tabacco-box lie there, and he - Always goes in to fetch 'em. - . . . La. Cock. Your malice will ſoon be at an end: Heaven knows what will be the fatal Conſequence Of your being found here. - Sent. Madam, let him creep under the Table, The Carpet is long enough to hide him. La. Cock. Have you good Nature cºgh to Save the Life and Reputation of a Lady ? Court. Anything to oblige you, Madam. [He goes under the Table. - Lady Cockwood running to the Cloſet. La. Cock. Be ſure you do not ſtir, Sir, Whatſoever happens. Court. Not unleſs he pulls me out by the Ears. Sent. Good he thinks my Lady ſpeaks to him. - Enter Sir Oliver. La. Cock. My dear Sir Oliver------- - Sir Oliv. I am unworthy of this Kindneſs, Madam. La. Cock. Nay, I intend to chide you for your Naughtinëſs
Page 65

- 3 - º - She wou'd if She could. 65 Naughtineſs anon; but I cannot chuſe but hu - - Thee, and kiſs thee a little firſt; I was j I ſhou'd never, have had thee alive within Theſe Arms agen. Sir Oliv. Your Goodneſs does ſo increaſe myº Shame, I know not what to ſay, Madam. - La. Cock. Well, I am glad I have thee ſafe at Home, I will lock thee up above in my Chamber, And will not ſo much as truſt thee down ſtairs, Till there be an end of this §§ - Sir Oliv. I was ſo little my ſelf, I knew not what - * , I did, elſe I had not expos'd my Perſon to ſo - t Much danger before thy Face. - \, - Sent. 'Twas cruelly done, Sir, knowing the killing Concerns my Lady has for you. - La. Cock. If Mr. Courtall had kill'd thee, I was Reſolv’d not to ſurvive thee; but before I had - Dy'd, I wou'd have dearly reveng'd thy Murder. - - - - Sir Oliv. As ſoon as I had recolle&ted my ſelf, - - . . . . º A little, I could not reſt till I came home to give thee - -- This ſatisfačtion, that I will do nothing without Thy Advice and Approbation, my Dear: I know Thy Love makes thy Life depend upon mine, And it is unreaſonable I ſhou'd, upon my own Raſh Head hazard that, though it be for the - Juſtification of thy Honour. - - uds me, I have let fall a China-Orange, that - " .. Was recommended to me for one of the beſt * . . . . That came over this Year; "slife, light the Candle, ‘. . . . Sentry, 'tis run under the Table. [Knock. La. Cock. Oh, I am not well ! . **. [Sentry takes up the Candle, there is a great knocking at the door, "… . fhe runs away with the Candle. º - . . . . . " Sent. Oh Heaven! who's that knocks - . So haſtily P Sir Oliv. Why, Sentry! bring back the Candle; Are you mad to leave us in the dark, and your Lady not well? How is it, my Dear?' La. Cock. For Heaven's ſake run after her, Sir Olive, Snatch the Candle out of her hand, and teach .. - - Her more Manners. , - --- . . . . . . . . . Sir Oliv. I will, my Dear. - - La. Cock. What ſhall I do 2 Was ever Woman So unfortunate in the management of Affairs Court. What will become of me now 2 - La. Cock. Tt muſt be ſo; I had better truſt my 1 - Honour
Page 66

66 she woºd if she cord Honour to the Mercy of them two, than be Betray'd to my Husband: Mr. Courtal, give 3Me your Hand quickly, I beſeech you. - Court. Here, here, Madam, what's to be done now? ~ La. Cock. I will put you into the Cloſet, Sir. . . º º - ... Court. He'll be coming in for his Tabacco-box - And Pipes. - . . . . . . . . La. Cock. Never fear that, Sir. - - . . . . [Freeman out of the Cloſet-door. - Free. Now ſhall I be diſcover'd; - Pox on your honourable Intrigue; - - . . Wou'd I were ſafe at Gifford's. - La. Cock. Here, here, Sir ; this is the door: Whatſoever you feel be not frighted; for Shou'd you make the leaſt diſturbance, - -. You will deſtroy the Life, and what is more, - - The Honour of an unfortunate Lady. - - Court. So, ſo; if you have occaſion to remove . . . . Agen, make no Ceremony, Madam. - - Enter Sir Oliver, Sentry, Ariana, Gatty. Sir Oliv. Here is the Candle; how doſt thou, My dear? * - . . La Cock. I cou’d not imagine, Sentry, you had . . . . . . . . Been ſo ill-bred, to run away, and leave your . . . . . . . . . . . . . Maſter and me in the dark. Sent. I thought there had been another Candle upon the Table, Madam. La. Cock. Good! you thought t you are always Excuſing of your Careleſneſs; ſuch another Miſdemeanor— - - Sir Oliv. Prithee, my Dear, forgive her. La. Cock. The truth is, I ought not to be very Angry with her at preſent; 'tis a good-natur’d Creature: She was ſo frighted for fear of Thy being miſchief'd in the Spring-Garden, That I verily believe ſhe ſcarce knows What ſhe does yet. , Sir Oliv, Light the Candle, Sentry, that I - May look for my Orange. - La. Cock. You have been at my Lady Love-youth's, Couſins, I hear. - Aria. We have, Madam. . . Gatty. She charg’d us to remember her Service to you. Sir Oliv. So, here it is, my Dear, I brought it Home on purpoſe for thee. - La. Cock.
Page 67

Shºwaif shºw. 67 La. Cock 'Tis a lovely Orange indeed! Thank you, . . * My Dear; I am ſo discompos'd with the Fright I have had, that I wou'd fain be at reſt. . . . . Sir Oliv. Get a Candle, Sentry; Will you go - -, * To bed, my Dear? " . . . . . - La. Cock. With all my heart, Sir Oliver; 'Tis late, Couſins, you had beſt retire to your Chamber too. Gatty. We ſhall not ſtay long here, Madam. - > Sir Oliv. Come, my Dear. - - La. Cock. Good night, Couſins. . - * . . . . . . Gat. and Aria. Your Servant, Madam. - - [Éxeant Sir Oliver, Lady Cockwood, and Sentry. Aria. I cannot but think of thoſe Letters, Siſter. Gatty. That is, you cannot but think of Mr. Freeman, ~Siſter; I perceive he runs in thy head as much as , A new Gown uſes to do in the Country, the - Night before 'tis expected from London. Aria. You need not talk, for I am ſure the Loſſes Of an unlucky Gameſter are not more his Meditation, than Mr. Courtall is yours.” 2 Gatty. He has made ſome ſlight impreſſion on my Memory, I confeſs; but Hope a night will . . . . . Wear him out again, as it does the noiſe - - Of a Fiddle after Dancing. -- Aria. Love, like ſome ſtains, will wear out of it Self, I know, but not in ſuch a little time as You talk of, Siſter. - - Gatty. It cannot laſt longer than the ſtain of a . . . . . . . Mulberry at moſt ; the next Seaſon out that goes, “ . . . . . . . . And my Heart cannot be long unfruitful, ſure. . Aria. Well, I cannot believe they forgºd theſe Letters; . . . . What ſhou'd be their End 2 - - . 2 - Gatty. That you may eaſily gueſs at; but methinks, . . . . º. They took a very improper way to compaſs it. Aria. It looks more like the Malice or Jealouſe " . . . . . . . . ; *. Of a Woman, than the Deſign of two witty Mem., ºf . . . . Gatty. If this ſhould prove a Fetch of her Ladiſhip's . . . . . . Now, that is playing the loving Hypocrite º * --> Above with her dear Sir Oliver. - - . . . . . .” --> Aria. How unluckily we were interrupted, º, . . . . . . . . . *- When they were going to ſhow us the Hand: c. º. . . . . . . . . Gatty. That might have diſcover'd all: H have a . . .cº. 2 º' Small ſuſpicion, that there has been a little… . . ºf tº f : . . Familiarity between her Ladiſhip and . . . . i.” . . . . . . . . Mr. Courtall. - . . . . . ." ... . . . ." Aria. Our finding of 'em together in the Exchange, . . . . . . And ſeveral paſſages I obſerv’d at the Rear, have -- * . I 2 Aſmoſt
Page 68

3. - 3. 68 She wou'd if She cou’d. Almoſt made me of the ſame Opinion. - - Gatty. Yet I wou'd fain believe the continuance . Of it is more her Deſire. than his Inclination: . . . . That which makes me miſtruſt him moſt, is her - … Knowing we made 'em an Appointment. ! - Aria. If ſhe were jealous of Mr. Courtall, ſhe Wou'd not be jealous of Mr. Freeman too; they . . . . . .” Both pretend to have receiv'd Letters. ºr ... Gatty. There is ſomething in it more than we are Able to imagine; time will make it out, I hope, -- To the Advantage of the Gentlemen. * Aria. I would gladly have it ſo; for I believe, Shou'd they give us a juſt cauſe, we ſhould find it A hard task to hate them. - Gatty. How I love the Song I learn'd tºother day, - Since I ſaw them in the Mulberry-Garden : . . She. Sings. To little or no purpoſe I ſpent many days, , , In ranging the Park, th’Exchange, and the Plays; For ne'er in my Rambles, till now, did I prove . So lucky to meet with the Man I cou’d love. Oh! how I am pleas'd, when I think on this Man, That I find I muſt love, let me do what I can 2. ' How long Iſhall love him, I can no more tell, Than had I a Fever, when I ſhou'd be well. . My Paſſion ſhall kill me before I will ſhow it - And yet I wou'd give all the World he did know it : But oh, how I figh, when I think, ſhow'd he wooe me, I cannot deny what I know wou’d undo me! . Aria. Fie, Siſter, thou art ſo wanton. - - • * Gatty. I hate to diſſemble when I need not; 'Twould look as affeóted in us to be reſerv'd Now w” are alone, as for a Player to maintain - - - - The Charaćter ſhe ačts, in the Tyring-Room. - Aria. Prithee ſing a good Song. . . . . . . . . Gatty. Now art thou for a melancholy Madrigal, ºg viz Compos'd by ſome amorous Coxcomb, who i.irits. Swears in all Companies he loves his Miſtreſs . : ::, ; , , , - So well, that he wou'd not do her the Injury, were ſhe willing to grant him the Favour, And it may be is Sot enough to believe he . Wou'd oblige her in keeping his Oath too. ' s Jóriá.
Page 69

She wou'd if She could Aria. Well, I will reach thee thy Guitar, out of The Cloſet, to take thee off of this Subjećt. Gatty. I'd rather be a Nun, than a Lover at Thy rate; Devotion is notable to make Mehalf ſo ſerious as Love has made Thee already. Court. Ha, Freeman Is this your Bus'neſs with a Lawyer? Here's a new Diſcovery, I'faith: Free. Peace, Man, I will ſatisfie your jealouſie Hereafter ſince we have made this lucky Diſcovery, let us mind the preſent buſineſſes.. [Courtall and Freeman catch the Ladies, and bring them back. - Court. Nay, Ladies, now we have caught you, There is no eſtaping till w” are come to a right llnderſtanding. - [Ariana opens the Cloſet, Courtal and Freeman come out. * * , [They ſhriek and run out. * - Enter LadyCockwood, Sir Oliver, and Sentry. Free. Come, never bluſh, we are as loving as . You can be for your hearts, I aſſure you. Court. Had it not been our good Fortunes to Have been conceal’d here, you wou’d have Had ill Nature enough to diſſemble with lls at leaſt a fortnight longer. - - La. Cock. What's the matter with you here? Are you mad, Couſins? Bleſs me, Mr. Courtall and Mr. Freeman in our Houſe at theſe - llnſeaſonable hours' Sir Oliv. Fetch me down my long Sword, Sentry, I lay my Life Courtall has been tempting the Honour of the young Ladies. La. Cock. Oh, my Dear ! - Gatty. We are almoſt ſcared out of our Wits, My Siſter went to reach my Guitar out of the §. and found'em both ſhut up there. La, Cock. Come, come, this will not ſerve your Turn; I am afraid you had a Deſign ſecretly To convey’em into your Chamber : Well, I will have no more of theſe doings in my Family, my Dear; Sir joſlin ſhall remove Theſe Girls to morrow. Free. You injure the young Ladies, Madam; Their Surpriſe ſhews their Innocence. s - Court. If any body be to blame, it is Mrs. Sentry. Sent. What mean you, Sir? Heaven knows º [She holds him." - Iknow
Page 70

70 She woºd if She coºd. ; : . . . I know no more of their being here------ . Court. Nay, nay, Mrs. Sentry you need not Be aſham'd to own the doing of a couple of Young Gentlemen ſuch a good Office. - - 2. - - - º ºr), . . . Sent. Do not think to put your tricks upon me, Sir, ' , ; , i.e. ::, . s Court. Underſtanding by Mrs. Sentry, Madam, That theſe young Ladies would very likely . . . . ; ; ; ; Sit and talk in the Dining-Room an hour before : They went to bed, of the Accidents of the . . . Day 3 and being impatient to know, whether That unlucky bus'neſs which happen'd in . . . . . . . . The Spring-Garden, about the Letters, had . . . . . . . . . . . Quite deſtroy'd our hopes of gaining their . . -- - Eſteem; for a ſmall Summ of Möney, Mr. Freeman And I obtain'd the Favour of her to ſhut us up where we might over-hear’em. La. Cock. Is this the Truth, Sentry 2 . . " Sent. I humbly beg your pardon, Madam. La. Cock. A Lady's Honour is not ſafe, that keeps A Servant ſo ſubjećt to Corruption; I will turn Her out of my Service for this. . . * --- Sir Oliv. Good! I was ſuſpicious their bus'neſſes Had been with my Lady, at firſt, . La. Cock. Now will I be in Charity with him. . . . - Agen, for putting this off ſo handſomely. Šir'Oliv. Hark you, my Dear; ſhall I forbid º º Mr. Courtall my Houſe 2 - - º La. Cock. Oh! by no means, my Dear: I had forgot to tell thee, ſince I acquainted thee with that busineſs, I have been diſcourſing with my Lady Love-youth, and ſhe blam'd me infinitely For letting thee know it, and laugh’d exceedingly At me, believing Mr. Courtall intended thee No injury, and told me’twas only a harmleſs Gallantry, which his French Breeding Has us’d him to. Sir Oliv. Faith, I am apt enough to believe it; For on my Conſcience, he is a very honeſt Fellow. Ned Courtall ! How the Devil came it about, That thee and I fell to Sa, Sa, in the Spring-Garden P - - Court. You arc beſt able to reſolve Your ſelf that, Sir Oliver. - Sir Oliv. Well, the Devil take me, if I had the Leaſt llnkindneſs for thee------ Prithee let us Embrace and kiſs, and be as good Friends As ever we were, dear Rogue. • * - - . . . ." ſ, a * ! . . . º, iſ, ori. 1;5}o tº . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . " '' . - -* . . Court . . - * - - º -
Page 71

- . 2 e - ** She wou'd if She could Court. I am ſo reaſonable, Sir Oliver, that I will Ask no other Satisfačtion for the Injury you - - Have done me. Free. Here's the Letter, Madam. - . Aria. Siſter, look here, do you know this Hand 2. Gatty. 'Tis Sentry’s. - La. Cock. Oh Heavens! I ſhall be ruin’d yet. Gatty. She has been the contriver of all this Miſchief. Court. Nay, now you lay too much to her Charge In this; ſhe was but my Lady's Secretary, I . Aſſure you, ſhe has diſcover'd the whole - Plot to us. . . . . . Sent. What does he mean? La. Cock. Will he betray me at laſt? Court. My Lady being in her Nature ſeverely Vertuous, is, it ſeems, offended at the innocent Freedom you take in rambling up and down By your ſelves; which made her, out of a Tenderneſs to your Reputations, counterfeit Theſe Letters, in hopes to fright you to that Reſervedneſs which ſhe approves of La. Cock. This has almoſt redeem'd my Opinion Of his Honour. Couſins, the little regard you had to the good Counſel I gave you, puts me upon this Buſineſs. - - Gatty. Pray, Madam, what was it Mrs. Gazette Told you concerning us? La. Cock. Nothing, nothing, Couſins: What I told You of Mr. Courtall, was meer Invention, the better To carry on my Deſign for your Good. - Court. Freeman Fray, what brought you hither 2 . Free. A kind Summons from her lºg - * -. Court. Why did you conceal it from me? º Free. I was afraid thy peeviſh jealouſe might º Have deſtroy'd the deſign I had of getting an Opportunity to clear our ſelves to the f Young Ladies. \ - Court. Fortune has been our Friend in that Beyond expečtation. -- To the Ladies.] I hope, Ladies, you are ſatisſ'd ". Of our Innocence now. . . , - Gatty. Well, had you been found guilty of the Letters, we were reſolved to have counterfeited S Two Contraćts under your Hands, and have Suborn’d Witneſſes to ſwear 'em. - - - Aria. That had been a full Revenge; for I know. - -- * * * Yº...
Page 72

72 • She wou'd if She cou’d. You would think it as great a Scandal to be . . . . . . . . . . Thought to have an Inclination for Marriage, . . . . . As we ſhou'd to be believ'd willing to take - . - - Our Freedom without it. - - - -, - . . . Court. The more ſº. thing, Ladies, had ..., , , , , , -- - - - * , ºf . . . . . . . . . Been only to pretend a Promiſe; we have ~ º zi ºt Now and then Courage enough to venture ſo far ºf . . . . . . . . . . . . For a valuable Conſideration. . . . . . . , , , , , , Gatty. The truth is, ſuch experienc'd Gentlemen | As you are, ſeldom mortgage your Perſons - - Without it be to redeem your Eſtates. court. "Tis a Mercy we have ſºap'd the miſchief “ *:: º t So long, and are like to do Penance only for * …" ºr . . . Qur own Sins; moſt Families are a Wedding . . . . . . . . . . . . Behind-hand in the World, which makes " ' ". . . . . . .”. So many young Men fool'd into Wives, to pay - - - - - Their Fathers Debts: All the Happineſs a . Gentleman can deſire, is to live at Liberty, . . . . . . . . . - Till he be forc'd that way to pay his own. . . . . . . . . . * . . . . . Free. Ladies, you know we are not ignorant " . . . . . . . Of the good Intentions you have towards us; Pray let us treat a little. - - Gatty. I hope you are not in ſo deſperate A Condition, as to have a good Opinion Of Marriage, are you? c - - - - - - - - , , Aria. 'Tis to as little purpoſe to treat with us, - * * * * * * * Of any thing under that, as it is for thoſe kind. - Ladies, that have oblig'd you with a valuable Conſideration, to challenge the Performance Of your Promiſe. - Sir Oliv. Well, and how, and how, my dear Ned, - Goes the buſineſs between you and theſe Ladies? , . … * * * --- l Are you like to drive a Bargain 2 Court. Faith, Sir Oliver, we are about it. Sir Oliv. And cannot agree, I warrant you; . . . ... * , They are for having you take a Leaſe for Life, and you are . . . . . For being Tenants at Will, Ned, is it not fº - - - Gatty. Theſe Gentlemen have found it ſo convenient Lying in Lodgings, they'll hardly venture on the Trouble of taking a Houſe of their own. Court. A pretty Country-Seat, Madam, with a . . . . . . . . Handſome Parcel of Land, and other Neceſſaries . . . . Belonging to’t, may tempt us; but for a Town-Tenement, - That has but one poor Conveniency, We are reſolv’d we’ll never deal. - - [A noiſe of Muſick without. Sir Oliv. Hark! my Brother jolly's come home. w Aria.
Page 73

She woºd if She coºl 73 Aria. Now, Gentlemen, you had beſt look to . . . . . . . Your ſelves, and come to an Agreement with us . . . . . . . . . . . . Quickly; for I'll lay my Life my uncle has -, --- “… . . . Brought home a couple of freſh Chapmen, . . . . . . . . . . . That will out-bid you. . . . . . . . . . ; : ". . . . . . . * * * * . . . . • 2. ! { .. - - - - , , , --> º - Enter Sir Joſlin with Muſic. . . . … Sir joſ. Hey, Boys! - "[Dance. SI N G.S. A Catch and a Glaſs; . . . . . . . A Fiddle and a Laſs, . . . What more wou'd an honeſt clºfan have P : . . . . Hang your temperate Sot, , , , , … ." . . . . Who wou'd ſeem what he's not ; ; ; ; ; , , *Tis 1 am wiſe, he’s but grave. Sir joſ. What's here, Mr. Courtall and Mr. Freeman 1. . . . ." Sir Oliv. Oh, Man! here has been the prettieſt, - The luckieſt Diſcovery on all ſides: We are: ' ". . . . . . . . - All good Friends again. ºf . . . . . . . . º. i. ºf . . . . . . . . . . . Sir joſ. Hark you, Brother Cockrood, ºf i , , ; cf. : " . . . . . . . I have got Madam Kampant; Rake-hell and ſhe are without. - Sir Oliv. Oh, Heavens ! Dear Brother jolly, ſend tº 'i, . . . . . . Her away immediately; my Lady has ſuch an averſion . . . . . . . . To a naughty Woman, that ſhe will ſwound,'º', ; , . . . . . . . . . . . . ; If ſhe does but ſee her. .*:: *... . . . . . . . . . ." Sir joſ. Faith, I was hard put to it, it wanted.º.º. º' ºf . . . . . . A Lover, and rather than I would break my old ſº . . . . . . " ' " Wont, I dreſs'd up Rampant in a Sute I bought ; : . . . . . . . . . . . . Of Rake-hell; but ſince this good Company's here, " . . . . . . . . * ... [Enter Rake-heti, . . . . . I’ll ſend her away. My little Rake-bell; come tºº iſ . . . . . . .” Hither; you ſee here are two powerful Rivals; º' - "º . . . . . . . . Therefore for fear of kicking, or a worſe diſaſter, . ." . " " ' ". . . Take Rampant with you, and be going quickly." tºo. . . . . . . . Rake. Your humble Servant, Sir. . . . … [Ex. Rake-hell and Rampant. Court. You may hereafter ſpare yeurſelf: this ſº... z º. * ... " - Labour, Sir joſlin 3 Mr. Freeman and I have vow’dziº. ". . . . . . . . . . . . ... Our ſelves humble Servants to theſe Ladies... º. i.: ; , ;... . . . . . . . . . . . . Free. I hope we ſhall have your Approbation, Sir.' . . . . . .” ' ' ', Sir joſ. Nay, if you have a mind to commitº. I - " - ". . . . Matrimony, I'll ſend for a Canonical Sirjº iºd ºf . ." . . . . . . ) Shall diſpatch you preſently. º'cº ºf . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Free. You cannot do better. …i.d. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . " Court. What think you of taking us in the humour?.… . . . . . . . . Conſideration may be your Foe, Ladies. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . …” K - . Avia.
Page 74

*- • 2 y - 3 ?4. She wou'd if She cou’d. , ºria. Come, Gentlemen, PH make you a fair ºr : *, Pºppoſition; ſince you have made a diſcovery . . . . . . Of our Inclinations, my Siſter and I will be content : * : . . . . To admit you in the quality of servants. -- . . . . º Gatty. And if after a Month's experience of your ... . . . . . . . Good Behaviour, upon ſerious Thoughts, you have Sºurage enough to engage further, we will accept Of the Challenge, and believe you Men of Honour. . Sir Joſ. Well ſpoke, i'faith, Girls; and is it * /* A Match, Boys 2 -- - - Court. If the Heart of Man be not very deceitful, 'Tis very likely it may be ſo. - Free. A Month is a tedions time, and will be a tº . . - . . Dangerous Tryal of our Reſolutions; but I º - Hope we ſhall not repent before Marriage, . . . . . . . - What-e'er we do after. . . . Sirjoſ. How ſtand matters between you and - Your Lady, Brother Cockwood 2 Is there . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Peace on all ſides 2 - . . . . tº - Sir Oliv. Perfeit Concord, Man: I will tell . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Thee all that has happen'd ſince I parted from . . . . . . . . . . Thee, when we are alone 'twill make thee laugh . . . ." . . . . . . . Heartily. Never Man was ſo happy in a - , , - Vertuous, and a loving Lady ? - - - - . . . . . . . . . . . - Širjof though ſhave iºdsir oliver aſtray . . . . . . . . . . This day or two, I hope you will not exclude me … . . . . . . . . . . . The Aét of Oblivion, Madam. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . La. Cock. The nigh Relation I have to you, * * *... . . . . . . . ; * And the Reſpect I know Sir Oliver has for you, , . . . . . . . . . . . ºf A. Makes me forget all that has paſs'd, Sir; but pray. . . . . . . . - Be not the Occaſion of any new Tranſgreſſions. . . . ." . . . . . . . . . . . Sent. I hope, Mr. Curtall, ſince my Endeavours . . . . . . . To ſerve you, have ruin'd me in the Opinion of i ºr ºf My Lady, you will intercede for a Reconciliation, j . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Court. Moſt willingly, Mrs. Senty--- Faith, Madam, : * ~ *:::". - Since things have fallen out ſo luckily, you muſt ... … . . . . . . . . f Needs receive your Woman into Favour again. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . La. Cock. Her Crime is unpardonable, Sir. . . . . . . . . * Sent. upon ſolemn Proteſtations, Madam, that . . . . . . . . The Gentlemens Intentions were honourable; * , º, . . . . . . . g . And having Reaſon to believe the young Ladies ºn . . . . . . . . . . . Had no Averſion to their Inclinations; I was … . . . . . . . . . . . . - Qf Opinion I ſhould have been ill-natur'd, if I -, - tº . . . . . tº Had not aſſiſted them in the removing thoſe ºf . , ." . " - Đifficulties that delay'd their Happineſs. . . . . . . . . . . . Sir Oliv. Come, come, Girl, confeſs how many º Guineys previºpon your eaſie Nature. . . . . . . . . . . . . . …”. / - &nt. At •

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 75

She wou'd if She could. Sent. Ten, an’t pleaſe you, Sir. Sir Oliv. 'slife, a Summable to corrupt an honeſt Man in Office! Faith, you muſt forgive her, my Dear. La. cock. If it be your pleaſure, Sir Oliver, I cannot but be obedient. º Sent. If Sir Oliver, Madam, ſhou'd ask me to See this Gold, all may be diſcover'd yet. Lacoſ. if he does, I will give thee Ten Guineys out of my Cabinet. Sent. I ſhall take care to put him upon’t; *Tisfit, that I who have bore all the Blame, Should have ſome reaſonable Reward for’t. Court. I . Madam, you will not envy me The Happineſs I am to enjoy with your fair Relation. La. Cock. Your Ingenuity and Goodneſs, Sir, Have made a perfeº Atonement for you.. Court. Pray, Madam, what was your Bus'neſs With Mr. Freeman P - La. Cock. Only to oblige him to endeavour 'A Reconciliation between you and Sir Oliver; For though I was reſolv’d never to ſee your face agen, it was Death to me to think Your Life was in danger. Sent. What a miraculous come off is this, Madam? La. cock. It has made me ſo truly ſenſible of Thoſe dangers, to which an aſpiring Lady Muſt daily expoſe her Honour, that I am Reſolv’d to give over the great Bus'neſs of This Town, and hereafter modeſtly Confine my ſelf to the humble Affairs of my own Family. Court.” Tis a very pious Reſolution, Madam; And the better to confirm you in it, Pray entertain an able Chaplain. La. Cock. Certainly Fortune was never before So unkind to the Ambition of a Lady. Sir joſ. Come, Boys, Faith we will have A Dance before we go to bed-----Sly-Girl and Mad-Cap, give me your Hands, that I may - Give 'em to theſe Gentlemen, a Parſon ſhall - join you’ere long, and then you will have Authority to dance to ſome purpoſe: Brother Cockmood, Take out your Lady, I am for Mrs. Sentry. " We'll foot it, andfid: it, my pretty little Miſs, And when we are weary we'll lye down and kiſs. . . Play away, Boys. K 2. - -- - - -- " .. " - ** 75 r s . [They Dance. Court. r
Page 76

76 She wou'd if She cou’d. Court. to Gatty. Now ſhall I ſleep as little Without you, as I ſhou'd do with you: . . .ſi. Madam, Expediation makes me almoſt As reſtleſs as jealouſie. - Free. Faith, let us diſpatch this Bus'neſs: Yet I never cou’d find the pleaſure of waiting . - For a Diſh of Meat, when a Man was heartily hung. . . . Gatty. Marrying in this Heat wou'd look as ill As fighting in your Drink. - Aria. And be no more a proof of Love, Than t’other is of Valour. - Sir joſ. Never trouble your Heads further; Since I perceive you are all agreed on the - Matter, let me alone to haſten the Ceremony: ... Come, Gentlemen, lead 'em to their Chambers; Brother Cockwood, do you ſhew the way With your Lady. Ha, Mrs. Sentry S I N G S. • I gave my Love a green Gown, I’th’ merry Month of May, And down ſhe fell as wantonly, As a Tumbler does at Play. . Hey, Boys, Lead away, Boys. Sir Oliv. Give me thy Hand, my Vertuous, my Dear; Henceforwards may our mutual Loves encreaſe, And when we are a-bed, we'll ſign the Peace. - --r- - e.” F I N I S. :
Page Scan 81

Blank page
Page Scan 82

Blank page
Page Scan 83

Blank page
Page Scan 84

Blank page

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents

End of text. Return to beginning.
