The city bride, or, The merry cuckold : a comedy, acted at the New Theatre, in Litt[le] Lincolns Inn-Fields, by His Majesty's servants., . | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
The city bride, or, The merry cuckold : a comedy, acted at the New Theatre, in Litt[le] Lincolns Inn-Fields, by His Majesty's servants., .
Author
Harris, Joseph, ca. 1650-ca. 1715.Harris, Joseph, ca. 1650-ca. 1715.
Published
London :Printed for A. Roper and E. Wilkinson ...,[1696]
Description
[8], 47, [1] p. (last page blank) ;21 cm.
Rights
Public Domain, Google-digitized.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/nyp.33433074861026

Table of Contents

    Front Cover
    Title Page
    Section 1 on page number 1
    Section 2 on page number 5
    Section 3 on page number 40
    Section 4

Book Text
Front Cover
Page Scan 1

|||||

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 2

–

Page Scan 3

\ 0 \
Page Scan 4

Blank page

End of Front Cover. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Title Page
Page Scan 5

~~~~~~ - - - \ t f ºx ºf K. T H E - ! ºr (ERARY CITY BRIDE: O R, The Merry Cuckold. - - A COMEDY, A&ted at the New Theatre, in Little Lincolns Inn-Fields. - B Y º 39ig ſºlajtſty's $truants, _ Spero Meliora. - - L O N D O N : – Printed for A. Roper and E. Wilkinſºn at the Black-B,

Page Scan 6

- I. : " . " 1, 1.14) J. H. R.A.R.Y - º - - - 42: 34:52();} Asºr º, LL.M.C.N. ANI, "ill-at... ºn Nºat: 0xs 19:2 r - - , - - - - --- - - - - - - * - . . . - -- - - - - - t - - - 2 - - - - - - - - - S- - -- - -- - - - * : - - - - - - - º - - - - * --- - - - - - -- - - - - * ~ - . Sº -" * • *--> - - : - - - - - - -," - * - - - w - * , - 4'ſ -- * * : . . . . . ---" - - - - - - - - - - - * - * - - . * * - * - * * . *, * - - - - - º * * - - -- - - . . . . ~~ - - -- +. - - ~ * * ..., - - ----- - - - - --

Page Scan 7

: , - . . . - To T H E I Sir John Walter, Bar. ", S I R, . . . . . . . . | T TNder the preſent Licenſe of the Preſ, and Freedom of Re- U J ligion, Two very fair Eſtabliſh'd Engliſh Liberties; me- thinks I have the Ulmbrage even of a Law on my ſide, to Authorize my Preſumption, in paying this publick Devotion, to ſo Worthy a Patron; and fixing ſo fair a Name, in the Frontiſpiece of ſo poor a Trifle. You muſt pardon me, Sir, if I lay hold of all occaſions, and every Argument to warrant my Ambition: Beſides, I have a ſtronger Charter than Poetick Priviledge, 'tis my Gratitude that dićtates to my Pen; You have already vouchſafd to Honour me with your Smiles, (and where ſuch Goodneſs deſcends, 'tis natural for our Pride to aſpire) whilſt warm'd and animated . that only Encouragement, I am embolden'd to make you this Dedication; inſomuch that my preſent Devoirs have more of the Thankſgiving, than the Prayer; a Duteous Acknow- ledgment for Bleſfings already received. And here I muſt avow to the World, That in Addreſſing to a perſon Enrich'd with ſo. many Generous Accompliſhments, I ſet not out a Diſcoverer, a Columbus to any unknown Colden Coaſt: No, Sir, You; - - . . . . . .”. A 2 - -
Page Scan 8

*... * . . … The DE DICAT10 & - paſt Favours have ſwell'd my Sails, whilſt I am carried by a fair Levant to an open free Port, and a Hoſpitable Shoar. That Sweetneſs of Temper runs through all Your Conver- ſation, ſo free from any Allay of Pride, (that too comme Taint of Proſperity,) that You haye all the Sweets of the Rol. without the prickles. Your Goodneſs ſo Frank, and ſo diffu. five, and the Acceſs to it ſo Eaſie, that thoſe who have the more particular happineſs of Your neareſt Intimacay, and Friendſhip, find thoſe Charms in Your Converſation, that they are ſcarce (pardon the ſecming Contradićtion,) to be enjoy'd : For the more they are poſſeſt, the more they are deſir'd. HONOLIR, and GALLANTRY are not only Born, but bred up with You. You Challenge not only all the Ad- Yantages of a Fair and Generous Birth, but You have all the Improvements of a Generous and Sprightly Genius too, with ſo forward, ſo hopeful, and ſo growing a Merit (that ample, Addition to your Hereditary Deſert) that the Stem is a Grace to the Root. - - - If Providence does ever Study for her Fair Creations, ſhe Think, when ſhe makes a Compleat Gentleman. And Fortune. in the Donations of her Golden Favours upon You, has not Showr'd them at Random; ſhe found that WORTH, that challeng'd her Smiles, and her Graces are not her Gift, but her Reward. - But to all Your other Felicities there's the chief one yet want- ing, to compleat the Summ; the Charms of LOVE, that double Heaven of Joy, where You muſt give Bleſſings when You receive them. And here I muſt beg your leave, to wiſh You, that truly fair and Virtuous Choice, That like the Famous Youth. of Troy, You may have Rival Beauties all waiting when your kind Hand ſhall give the Prize, and beſtow the Ball of Gold. And truly, the Generous and the Brave ſhou'd ever *::::: N. - : ...: '... ::: :-. º
Page Scan 9

The DEDICATIox. ----- ~ their neareſt Care. For indeed, Love is the only Foundation of Immortality. For though Noble Virtues, a Sweet Fame, and Fragrant Memory may keep a fair Name alive; yet to make Your ſelf live for Everyou quly wanta Lovely Feminine Partner, But I muſt not dwell too longupon this Subject, For as Dedi- cations are by Cuſtom, only the Panegyricks upon the Patrons Virtues, poſſibly to ſo much ning Perfections,) I may make but ungrateful Muſick on that Theme. Yet why ſhou'd WORTH and HONOu R any more Bluſh to hear their own juſt Praiſes, then the Hero, or Monarch his Triumph, or Coronation Song. The Theme on this * fide may beas Copious, and as i. as that; Deſert and Ap- plauſe are not confind only to Palaces and Thrones; the Chap-fi flet ſometimes may Sparkle, as well as the Diadem. Tistrue the " fincomiums of Extraordinary Deſert; are what my pooreſt of uills ſhould not preſume to attempt, as being a Province for to draw Living Copies from ſo Excellent an Original. * Modeſty, (one of your moſt ſhi- the ElderSons of Apollo ; and yet when I conſider, that the Ayres" heartily * though not ſo ſweetly and loud as to a Silver" I ha Trumpet; I have that only Plea for this Boldneſs, which gives me the Honour of Subſcribing my ſelf, - - º - }! Sir, ! Tour moſt Gblig'd, Mºſt Devoted, > And Obedient Servant, , Joſiph Hatº - † that are tuned but to an Oaten Pipe, may be as chearfully and
Page Scan 10

—- - * Spoke by Mr. T HU RMOND gi-Bºz º.º. ºn ºil, T ,- . . ; 3.1 :: * ~ *- : * -- - 3. f - *- To gain your Favour. Beggi - gº Fºgging, Brºwing. Prº tºº / * - if a., a Beggar, I yout Alms implore . . Methink your Charity ſhºuld aid the Por; Pºſider, I never begd of you befºre. . . . ; if I addreſs by Prºyer, and lºud Cºmplaints 1 then ºblige jee, for Imake you şauntſ ;. and ſure none here can think it Superſtition, Tº pray to $ intº that are of no Religion 1, ... pray * Religion - *- - iſ lºcation will not do my Work,.., - - - ... Man may horrow ºf a Jew or Turk; . -- ", r " : Priy land nie Gentlemen your Applauſ. and Prai £2 Iſ take it fºr a gºod as Currant Bºys ; Zºd if / mere repay it, 'tis no more Tº tº many of you Sparkſ have done before: With this diffin:lion, that you ran indebt For mºſt ºf Mingy, we for want of Wit. 7 mºn ſplead 1 a Man as ſoon may get }ſºlid Silver, as one frvour from the Pit. —Hºld then– now I think ont, yi ( : ' ' , , , - - *2. º. - - r - - •. -- - • * > - --- - - -- z - . . . .22 + . . . . . . . . . . .2 * : f - º, --- - * . . . i , (). . . . . " , ; * - . . . . . . . - -, - v * * * * * * *-* + HREE Ways there are, and all accº ſ/e'.a tara Thief, and ſteal your kind Affetton, hid when I veg't your Hearts, claim your protetſun : - 1:2, ii. - - E. jø. } . . . - . . . . . . . . - " -- . . - - - * f. ºf . . . . . . . . . . º !. “. . . ---> -- - -, - ; : {? V, ºr rº, . . . J. : : **, * : - ' ' ". . . - - -- ... "...i * , , , ºf . - ** * - ſ * . - --------' ... 'r Af - --- - tº ºr - i . . . . . ºf ** - - - - - - tº . . . ;- º 3. º " … f ... ." . º ; , ºf f : …ſi'ſ … º º -- - º º, - - 4. “, … . . <- - - - Tºu * ... º. º. ::::::A; of 1ſ: 'i

Page Scan 11

Tºu can't Gazette me ſure for ſuch a crime, Since neither Mare nor Lap-dog, I purloin : While you Rab Ladies Bºſºms every day, - . And filch their pretious Maiden-head; away; Pll plead good nature fºr this Brat the Play; A Play that plagues no more the thread-bare Theme of powder'd Beaux, or trick; oth Godly Dame, But in your humours let's ye all alone, - , And not ſº much as Fools themſelves runs down. Our Author try’d his beſt, and Wiſemen tell, 'Tis half well doing to endeavour well ; What the his poor Allay runs not ſo fine; Tet, let it paſs as does our preſent Coin; , For wanting fairer Ore, and riches mould He ſº s in Braſ, what others print in Gold : - - - - - - - -- r - - : - - > - - - - Smile on him but this time, the next perhaps, ºf he gueſ; right be may deſerve your Claps. --- . . . . * . º * - - - º \{{ t - - - ...” o, ſº- , - r - Tramats ~ - ----- - - . . - * * -- > - *
Page Scan 12

Dramatis Perſonae. * : * * * * * * . . , . . . . . . . . º * \ - - * . -, .. * - - t - * : Bonvile, 77 e Bridegroom. - Mr. Boman. Friendly, His Friend, in Love with Clara. . . . . . . . . Mr. Thurmond. Juſtice Merryman, Father to Arabella. ..., \, , , , , . Mr. Bright. ..., Summerfield, A Gentleman, but Tounger Brother, neceſ. ‘..Mr. Scudemore. tated to take the High-Way.' . . . . . . . . . . Mr. Ventre, A Merchant. * . . . . 'Mr.'Arnold. ºr. Spruce, A City Beau. * *** - Mr. Bayly. ' Compaſſe, A Maffer of a Weſel. e. . . . . . . . Mr. Freeman. A Councellor. ... " ..Mr. Davis. §. % Two Attorneys. . . . . . . . #.s. ... • *** * 'º' * - sº º * º t º *. Sailers, Neighbours, Drawers, Servants, Boys, . . . . . - Singers and Dancers. a r *- -- - Arabella, The Bride. Mrs. Boman. º Clara, Friendly's ºft, but ſecretly in Love with Mrs. Boutell. -- Bonvike. - - - Mrs. Ventre, The Merchant's Wife. Mrs. Lacy. Peg. Compaſſes Wiſe. Mrs. Perin. Nurſe. - - Mrs. Lawſon. Lucy, Clara's Maid. . . . . . . ...--------—Miſs Prince. ** Women Neighbours. a - - º SCENE London.

End of Title Page. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 1

- - - : | - ". - ** T H E oR. THE - Merry Cuckold. ---------- TACFTSCENETI The Curtain draws up, and diſcovers ſeveral ſitting at a Banquet. An Enter- tainment of Inſtrumental Muſick, Compos'd by Signior Finger: Then a Song, ſet by Mr. John Eccles, and Sung by Toung La Roche. - A Nr. I've lik'd, and ſome Enjoy'd, But if I ſaid I Lov’d, I ly'd, Inconſtant as the wandring Bee, - - From once touch'd Sweets I us’d to flee; º - Nor all the Power of Female Skill, - Cou'd curb the freedom of my Will: Clarinda only found the Art, - 70 Conquer and to keep my Heart. [After this a Dance, and then the Scene ſhut. i Enter Friendly and Clara. Friend. His is is a Day of Mirth and Jollity my Clara, Clara. 'Tis ſo, for ſuch as can be merry, Mr. Friendly. | Friend. Why not for us my Love, we have a Noble Preſident, and methinks ſhou'd Imitate (thrö Envy) this their happineſs. Clara. I am not of your Opinion, - Friend. Why not my Fair 2 Clara. I'll tell you, becauſe I purpoſe not to Marry. * __º_-- --------- - Yo -
Page 2

A. */º he reaſon I ſuppoſe is this, becauſe they have Crowds - *** ----- ^_ 2 The City Bride : Or the Merry Cuckold. Fºi, Prithee be ſerious, and reform that Thought : Think of my paſt Service, and iºdge by that my future; weigh all the reſpect I have paid you long, and ever lov'd you beyond my ſelf. - - Cla. I know your Weakneſs, and will reward it too. . . . . . - Fri. I am ſure you will, you muſt be kind; And can you think an Anſwer of this killing Nature, a juſt return for all my faithful Love? - Cla. As to that I have already ſaid. \ Fri. Oh ſpeak, from whence this Coldneſs doth aiſe! Be at leaſt ſo kind as to ' tell me that ; Is it ſome late Diſguſt you have conceived of my Perſon; or rather your deſire, (I fear) of ſome unworthier, happy Creature, baſe in the Attempt, as you unkind in thinking of a Change; If neither, - - - - - - - * - * * ~~ • -- - I muſt impute it to your Woman's Will, * , - Still pleaſed with what it fancies, Good or ill. Clara. Be't what it will, thus it is, and with this. Anſwer pray reſt ſatisfied; there is but one way ever to win me, and draw me unto Marriage, which who. foever finds, 'tis like he may have me, if not, I am ſtill my own. . . . . . . . Fr. Oh name it then I Thou deareſt Treaſure of my Life I my Soul! my AIIf I - am in a maze of Extaſie, to think there's any means to gain you, and hope you'll be ſo kind to tell me how I may be happy. . . . . . . . - - - - Cla. I'll retire a while; and with my ſelf reſolve what muſt be done, and in the tend ſend you my Reſolution. - Exit Clara. Fri. I'll here expečt it : What more can I deſire, than now beftisfied and know *my Doodm. - • *, *, * , - • . . . . C. - Suſpence is the worſt Torment we endure, … 'Tis Knowledge makes the Wound both -Jafe and ſure. º _ _* Enter Spruce and Mr. Venter. *tra. How now jack! What all alone Man 2: . . . . . . . Fri. No, for I have heard ſome ſay, Men are ne're leſs alone, then when alone. of Thoughts, that ſtill per- plex the Mind; which wou'd be like . Soul retired and free, thereby to enjoy that ſweet kepoſe, which rought but that can Grant. Spr. Pſhaw! Pox of this Morality and dull Stuff; Prithee let us be Merry, and Entertain the Bride and Bridegroom. Óds-fiſh there a parcel of rare Creatures within' But of aii Mrs. Clara for my Money, ... . . . . . . .1- ..... Mr. Ven. And truly, I am of your Opinion Mr. Spruce; for ſetting aſide her pre- ſent Melancholly and Diſcontent, I think ſhe is beyºnd compariſon with any other. Spr. Od's nigs, I know the Cauſe of her Diſorder. . . . . . Went. What I pray P - - - * x spr. Why, I'll tell ye; In all Conditions of Eſtates, Profeſſons, and Degrees, in Arts or Sciences, yet know thete's a kind of Envious Emulation... - - A*, ºn. kišić. - ... • - . . . . . . . . . *
Page 3

~ - The City Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. 3 spr. So in this of Arabella's Marrying; for Clara being Lady of much the fºre Birth and Quality, Grieves I — ſuppoſe to ſee her Rival get the ſtart of her. - - º Mr. Ven. Troth like enough. º rºi. 'Y'are pleaſant Gentlemen— Or elſe becauſe ſhe having had ſo many Courtiers— - - - Spr. And you among the reſt i. Fi. She now perhaps does caſt a more favourable Eye upon ſome one that does not like her. . . . . " - Spr. Why Faith, and that may be too. Enter Lucy with a Letter. Lucy. Sir, my Miſtriſs preſents her humble Service to you, and has ſent you this Letter; pray Heaven it be to your liking Sir. - - Fº, I thank the kind Lucy: There,there's for the Poſtage Girle: [Gives her Money She has kept her Promiſe for once i ſee; I'm reſolved to read it, thā I were ſure my Death was Comprehended in it. Reads. Tºy all your Friends, and find out the beft and neareſ to jour Heart, That - done, be ſure iſ kill him for my ſake. This fail not to do, if you reſpeš and Love ... (as you pretend.) - - Clara. ºf 'Tis as I far'd, and what I know, ſhe moſt deſires: Miſchief, and Murder, are al her Sexes Pračtice, and Delight 2 Yet ſuch is the Extravagancy of my Paſſion, muſt obey the Mandate, thé to my certain Ruine: "Tis ſtrangely difficult, and dot - require Mature Deliberation. * [Exi - Spr, What has Friendly left us? - Mr. Ven. I believe the Letter was the occaſion, it may be it was a Challenge. * Spr; A Challenge! No, no; Women don't uſe to bring Challenges, I rather b * lieve 'tis an Amour; And that Letter as you call it a Billet Deux, which is to Co . - - dućt him to the place appointed; and in ſome Sence you may take that for Challenge. - Mr. Ven. And ſhe the Civil Embaſſadreſs to uſher him in. - Spr. Yes, yes, but ſee the Bride and Bridegroom, with the reſt of the go Company. - - Enter juſtice Merry-man, Bonvile, Arabella , Mrs. Venter and others, as Gueſts Invited to the Wedding. Mr. Son Bonvile, what callye the Gentleman we met at the Garden Door ct; Friendy Sir, a moſt approv'd and worthy Gentleman, and one of my chic uelts. - - : Mer. Ay, ay, it may be ſo: But yet me thought he ſeemed ſomewhat pleaſed, thā.Son. Hah, What think you? § Bon. No ſure Sir, he cannot be Angry, when his Friend's ſo happy, 'ſ - R 2.
Page 4

–– r - r - - 4 : The City Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. Mer, I can't tell Boy, but I believe there's ſomething more than ordinary in the i matter, Why ſhould he leave the Company elſe?. And Mrs. Clara I miſs her too; . Why Gentlemen, why do you ſuffer this? . . 2. Ara. Unknown to any Sir, ſhe withdrew ſoon as we riſe from Table. - - Mer. Sick of the Maid perhaps; becauſe ſhe ſees you Mrs. Bride, her Quo : Play-fellow Married before i. i. Gentlemen, º - , her Quº milm Mr. Ven. 'Troth like enough Brother Merry-man. - - Mer. Go, go, find her out for ſhame Gentlemen; and do not ſtand idle thus, Od's bobs, when I was a Young fellow and invited to a Wedding, I uſed to frisk, | and Jump, and ſo beſtir my ſelf, that I made all the Green-ſickneſs Girles in the Room; . h buſh like Rubies. Ah, halil I was a brisk Fellow in thoſe Days, I'faith, and uſed to, - i Cut Capers, a Yard high: Nor am I yet ſo Old, but I can take a round or two ſtill i -—Cóme, come Gentlemen, lets in again and firk it away, ſhall we not?. - Spr. Withall my Heart Mr. Juſtice. . . - - Mr. Why that's well ſaid Mr. Spruce, Qds bobs it was, and 1 thank you heartily, Spr. Come Madam, you muſt along with us, without you all's nothing. -- Arab. I'll wait on you Gentlemen; if you will give me leave Sir. . . [fo Bonvile. - if Bon. Oh my beſt Joy! This Day you may Command, , -- - M, Mºr: That's right, that's right ifāith Gentlemen! This Day ſhe Commands, and he for ever after. Ods bobs I have done ſo my ſelf, and hope I ſhall do ſo ſtill. P Siſter Winter, My I preſume to ask if my Brother . ſay as much?' [Exit Bonvile, , , -- ir - Arab. Spruce, and the reſt of the Gueſts. - ! Mrs. Vent. Yes Brother, I think he may, I freely Give him leave. ſt of efts.] º: - 9. that Brother, ſhe freely gºes you leave : But who Gives leave the . - 2, Maſter or the Servant P: “ , ” “... • - “ . . . . . . - T. M. Ven. You are Merry Brother, and truly you have reaſon, having but one Baughter and ſee her Married as you would have her. . . . iſ Mer. Yes, I have one thank Heaven! You wou'd be glad Siſter you cou’d ſay ſo, 2 i. . Barrenneſs does give your Husband leave (if he pleaſe) to lodk for Game ewhere. º' i' . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . -- " - P "Mººn, well, well Sir, thó you jeer me, and make a ſcorn of my Sterility—- I , #. No, no, not I Siſter, Hſcorn not your Sterility, nor your Husbands Virility. ! :] [I] Cl." - " _ " - - - - - * - - - - . Afts. Ven. My Husband's virility! Pray ſpare my Husband; for he has not been Tº idle as you º ; He may have an—Offspring abroad for ought you know, r at you never heard of. - * * * * * W. Af. Wes. Oh fye Wife, You will not make it publick will you?” .. Tº Fo Mr. ºn And yet he keeps himſelf within compaſs for all that... " " . A- as . . 22 ºf , Aſr. Ven. If you love me Winn)— - Mrs. Vem. . Na, I ſay no more, but thereby hangsa Tale, * r - º !!! #2, Sayºff thouſo old Girle?” what and has he been ſtragling then? Nay, may - now he is a Venterſome Man; And a-Merchant of ſmall Wares ſometimes, , iſ ecially when he can gºta good Commodity: I love him the better for't Pfaith, * spobs I do— A notable ſpark with a Young Wench in a corner. Is he not P. #, rue Chip of the old. Block, his Father I warrant him— But Siſter, I have ºne toty to you in private, concerning my Daughter. - - --- - —-

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 5

The City Bride: or, the Merry Cuckold. * , Enter Nurſe. . Nurſe. By your leave Good Folks, Is Maſter Venter the Merchant here I pray 2 Mr. Ven. Öh Nurſe! I am glad to ſee thee, How does my Boy 2 - Nurſ, very well, I thank Heaven Sir! He grows bravely I aſſure you. 'Tis Chopping Lad I promiſe you, and as like your good Worſhip; . As if he had bee ſpit out of your Mouth. - Mr. Ven. Softly, Nurſe ſoftly. . . . - Nurſe. I proteſt 'tis one of the forward'ſt Infants in the Univerſe; Lord! how i will Crow, and Chirup like a Sparrow! I am afraid Sir he is about Teeth, for h Dribbles extreamly, #ſo, Your Worſhip muſt provide him a Silver Corral with Whiſtle and Chain. 7 ** r , - Mr. Ven. Weh, well, he ſhall have every thing Nurſe, my Wife ſhall fºnd then to ye; in the mean time, there, there's a Piece, to buy the a Pair of Gloves, and ſo leave us, for I am buſie at preſent, therefore ſteal away behind me, and flip ou at the back Door. - - Nurſe. Yes Sir, I am gone, Heavens bleſs your Worſhip, a Piece Marry ! and that's a ſufficient Charm to lye ". any Nurſes Tongue in Chriſtendom. [Ex Nurſ. juſt. Mer. Well well, it ſhall be done; Come Brother we are miſt I warrant yo amongſt the Young Fry, let's to 'um and, Dance till our Legs ake again, come l'i lead the way. - a - - Mr. Vºw, we follow you. . . . . - i. - [Exeum Enter Friendly Reading the the Letter. Fr. Heaven in its exceſs of Göodneſs, beſtow'd no greater Bleſſing on Manking than that of Friendſhip—To Murder any one is a Crime unpardonable ! But . Friend! And of all Friends the neareſ to my Heart— 'Tis ſuch an Impoſitio that Hellit ſelf 'tilſ now cou’d never parallel; And yet this Devil of a Woman haſ power over me beyond; all Virtue...I am diſtraćted in my Thoughts, and know not what to do; yet ſomething muſt be done without delay, or elſe I loſe her quite And yet I fear.'tis moſt Impoſſible, for Friendſhip left the World, when Juſtice fled and all who agw do wear that Name are the worſt of Hypocrites, . Like Counterfeited Coin on which is ſeem,” - The formal Stamp; but ſordid. Droſ, within... º Enter Bonivile. Ban. My Friend alone and Thoughtful? fly for whit . . . That you alone appear with Diſcontent,..., - When all my Friends Congratulate my Bliſs P : Is it becauſe (which I durſt ne're ſuſpect). Your Love to me was not intirely true P : - - Or elſe perhaps, this Crown of Happineſs. -
Page 6

6 The City Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. Fri. Forbear ſuch cruel Words— How can you ent, rtain a Thought ſo Vile Of him whom ſo long you have call'd your Friendſ May all the Bleſſings Heaven can beſtow - On us poor Mortals in this World below, Crown all your Days, and may you nothing ſee But flowing Tides of ſweet Felicity; But I, alas ! - Bºn. Alas! What means my Friendly 2 Much hidden Grief that wretched Word portends, Which thus diſturbs the Quiet of my Friend? But come diſcloſe it to me, And ſince the Burthen is too much for one, - l'll bear a part to eaſe thy troubled Breaſt. . . Fri. Oh Bomvile ! . - Seek not to force this Fatal ſecret from me—— Bon. I muſt know it, by my beſt hopes I muſt. . . . Fri. Oh no I cannot, Nay I dare not * - Bom. How dare not truſt a ſecret to a Friend ? Fri. Oh Bonville, Bonville I Call me not fºur Friend, That Names ſtrikes horrour to my very Soul. - Bon. Ha ( Art thou then a Stranger to that Name? -- Fri. Indeed I am, and muſt be ſo for ever now. . . . . . Bon. Yet hear me Friendly; Deny me if thou can'ſ, - Fixt as a Rock, I vow I'll here remain, Until I have forc'd this Dire ſecret from thee. - Fri. Pardon me Sir, I hope you ſoon will hear it, * r * * , - But I [offers to go.] . . Bom. Yet ſtay, and ſince intreaty can't prevail, . ... ----. By all the Friendſhip which you once profeſs'd, …: ' '. By all that's Holy, both in Heaven and Earth, - ** . - now Conjure thee to impart it to me, Or by this Life - - - Hold, hold, and ſince I can no longer hideit - - - * - Know 'tis my Honour then which lyes at Stake. • - - Bon Thy Honour ! How 2 Proceed. . . . . . - Fri. By chance a Quarrel happen'd to ariſe - 3etwixt another and my ſelf, The Field, Time, Place, and all appointed, - - Nay Secords muſt aſſiſt us in the Deed: - have relied on many ſeeming Friends, " . - Such as profeſs the bare and empty Name) And all refuſe to venture in my Cauſe. Boa. Is this all 2 - - Fri. All, Is it not enough To ſeemy Reputation, (the Lifes Blood of my Soul) Nay all that's Dear, i be left. " :
Page 7

, The City Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. Bon. Not while thy Bonvile lives and wears a Sword: - May all things frown that I wou'd have to ſmile, - May I live Poor, and Dye deſpiſed by all, If I out live the ruine of thy Honour! Tell methe time my Friend? - - Fri. Oh, ſpare me that, for, if once known the time, - - You'l Cancel this your promiſe, and recall Your Friendly proffer. - Bon. Away with theſe Excuſes, come the time / Fri. At Seven this Evening. Bon. The place 2 - Fri. Barn-Elms : - ~ * , . Oh the fatal place! Where I too well foreſee, The certain fall and Ruine of my Honour ! - Bon. No, Thou ſhalt not ſtay to forfeit thy lov'd Honour, Come I’m ready to aſſiſt my Friend; and will along with your. Fri, Alas! What mean you ? - Of all my Friends on you I ne're Relied ; ; , But ſure I Dream, I Rave, by Heav'ns I'm Mad?" My Bonvile leave his Wife? And on his Wedding Day ?. His Bride whom he perhaps may ne're Enjoy P And all for me 2 O moſt unhappy Man! Bon. Pleaſure before my Friend I'll ne're prefer, Nor is it loſt, thé for a while delay'd. Fri. Are you then reſolv'd to go? Bon. I am, as fixt in my Reſolve, asis the Libertin in Vice; Which Death alone can part. - - Fri. Yet ſtay, and think what it is you undertake, Recall this Raſh and ſuddain Reſolution, Léaſt you repent, alas when it is too late. - Bon. This were enough to ſhake a weaker Soul," - But mine it moves not; like to a Mighty Oake, I'm plac'd above the Storms of Fear or Doubt. - Enter. Arabella. Fri. Sir no more, the Bride, Ara. Oh, Heavens defend me ! Bon. What ailes my Deareſt Life 2'- - Ara. I've loſt the Key of this Chain I wear about my Neck'; And of theſe Bracelets, Ch Unhappy Omen - - Bow. No, no, my Love; I found it as it lay at Random in your Chambér, fearing it might be forgot, or loſt, have laid it by; 'Tis ſafe my Love. Ara. Indeed I’me very glad you've found it, but yet—- ſſ. Bon. Yet, What my Dear? from whence proceeds that ſigh 2. - - Arab. Alas, I kno w not tº . Some buſie Genius Whiſpers to my Soul: ,
Page 8

P- 8 The loſs of this upon my Wedding Day Portend’s a greater e're the Day be paſt. Bon. Baniſh ſuch Fears, let's in and ſee our Friends. Ara. Indeed they all expect you; come I'll lead the way. Bon. I'll go with you. Barn-Elms you ſay? Fri. Yes that's the place, at Seven preciſely; The City Bide; or, the Mary Cuckold. Bon. I'll meet you on the Exchange, and go together; : If you are there before me, Take a turn or two. The only, only Man that I can call Friend, And only Friend that I am bound to Kill? A Friend, that for my ſake wou'd ſtake his Life, Leave a Chaſt Brid and untouch'd Nuptial Bed For me baſe Man, nay worſe than Savage Beaſt: The generous Lyon, never kills his kin They ſay, althó provoked to utmoſt rage; Yet I vile Monſter, more º: Man, kil Thus unprovoked, muſt my Brother Creature, And which is worſe, my Dear and only Friend! All for the pleaſure of a Fooliſh Woman. O cruel Woman thus to Command , A Task ſo hard, Tet what I can't withſtandi Oh! thou rare Copy of the Original, - By which free Man at firſt received his fall; For ſhe not only wou'd her ſelf undo, ...And all her Sº, but Damn all Mankind too. * * * - [Aſide to Friendly. - [Exit Bonvile, and Arabella. Fri. Oh my Dear Bonvile ! Art thou then the Man? - - ------> * The End file Firſ. 4d.
Page 9

~ The City-Bride ; 0, the Merry Cuckold. 9 \ . - A C T the Second. - Sc E N E the Firſt. The Fields. Enter Summerfield ſolus. - - / - Shm. Younger Brother 'Tis a poor Title, and very hard to bear with : The Elder Fool inherits all the Land, whilſt we aré forc’d to follow Legacies of Wit, and get ’um when we can...Why ſhou'd the Law, by which we are deprived of equal Portion with the Firſt-begotten, not bind our Fathers to ceaſe from Pro- creation, and ſo as well deprive us of a wretched Being, as of the Thing we cannot be without : No, no, our Mothers ne're will conſent to that, they love to groan and fguall, tho at the ſame time the Gallows eccho's to their Groans, and both together labour for us. From the firſt we travel forth—to thers our Journey's End. All this I know, yet I muſt forward: To beg, my Birth will ne're conſent to ; and borrowing is quite out of date—Yet ſtarve I cannot, nor murder 1 wou’d not : It muſt be the High- way then, the old Trade we poor honeſt Rogues are forc’d too—This Place will ſerve for a Beginner well enough—A Beginner did I ſay? Yes; for this is the very firſt day I open Shop—Fortune, they ſay, uſes to help the Bold, I hope ſhe will be kind to me. Ha! who have we here 2 A Gentlewoman well rigg’d, and only a Servant with her, She may be a Prize worth the boarding, and faith 1’ll venture hard but I’ll carry her. [He retires to a corner of the Stage. - - Enter Arabella in great diſorder, lºſing about her, with Symon her Srvant. Arab. This way, ſay'ſt thou Symon, with Friendly f Sym. Yes forſooth Miſtreſs, with Mr. Friendly. Arab. Alas! I'm tired and cannot travel further ; my Heart is full of Fear, and yet I know not why, nor can I tell why he ſhould uſe me thus; It is not com- mon ſure for Men to leave their Brides upon the Wedding-day : And yet I cannot tell but it may be ſo! O wretched State of Marriage, and of Love, if this be Love! Here will I lie me down, and reſt a while [Lies down.] my wearied Limbs, unuſed to theſe ſad Frights and Fears +But prethee do thou run after him, and if it be poſſible o'retake him too: Tell him the ſtrange Diſorder thou doſt leave me in ; and let him know my Father's Anger, his Friends Concern, and what is mºre, his Ara- bella's ſad Complaint; tell him, I grieve, I ſaint, I die ; tell him any thing that may ſtay him. - - Sym, Yes Forſooth. - - -
Page 10

-- N- _Ara. Bleſſings on your Good - I * lo The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold: ' , Arab. Intreat him to return; nay, urge him all thou canſt to make him come a- gain : Nay haſte, good Symon, fly if thou canſt, for I can ſtir no further. Sym. Well, well, Forſooth, I am gone. [Exit Symon. Arab. Alas, how wretched and forlorn am I? - I ſhe whom once ſo many did admire, Whoſe Wit and Charms the coldeſt Hearts cou’d fire-f Now wretched Maid, and moſt unhappy Wife, - In Sighs and in Complaints muſt end my Life. - Abandoned by my Huband, e're enjoy'd, * / With thoughts of Pleaſure, yet untaſted, cloy'd. He leaves me now to my ſad Frights a Prey"; 0, my dear Bonvile ! whither doff thou ſīrayf Onheard, alas! I make my amarous Moans; The Winds and Waves refuſe to bear my Groans : Ecche her ſelf can't ſuffer my Complaint, But with repeated Sighs grom’s tir’d and faint. Where to find him, good Heaven direšt me f For loſing him, I more than loſe my ſelf. [Riſes, and Exit. Sum, I muſt after her, ſhe's worth my Acquaintance, and has good Moveables about her I perceive, whate’re the Ready is. The next Turning has a moſt convenient Hollow for the Purpoſe, and there I'll make her ſure. Now Luck, or never. - * [Exit after Arabella. Reenter Arabella, and Summerfield after her. Ara. I’m at a ſtand already, and know not where I am. Sam. I'll direét you, Madam; Well overtaken. - Ara. Bleſs me, Sir, What are you? Sum, A Man. Ara. An honeſt Man, I hope P º, Sum. Yes faith in ſome Reſpects, I'm very honeſt, but not altogether ſo ; I were not fit to live in the World if I were too honeſt, Child. Ara. Alas! then I begin to fear: Pray tell me what you are 2 Sum, Why, faith, an honeſt Thief. - Ara. How, honeſt, and yet a Thief? I never heard they were of Kin before; Pray, Heaven, I find it now. Sum. Indeed I a very honeſt Thief. - - - Ara. Well, Sir, ſince that’s your Title, pray uſe me kindly : Nay, l’m ſure you will, there's ſomething in your Looks which ſpeaks you mild and noble. Sum. Yes, I am a Gentleman, and you ſhall find me ſo , for I'll not offer you the leaſt ſhew of Violence, or offer to corrupt your Chaſtity; tho indeed you are tempt- ing Fair, and might inflame a colder Heart than mine: Yet Raviſhing's no part of my Profeſſion as yet; or if it were, you look ſo charming Innocent, you wou'd diſarm my wildeſt Thoughts.
Page 11

The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. i I Sum. Are you a Maid, or Wife 2 - - Ara. I am both, Sir. - - - - Sun. Then this it ſeems is your Wedding-day, and theſe the Hours of Interim that keep you in that double State 2 - * , Ara. Indeed you are in the right. - - Sum. Come then, I'll be brief, and hinder not your deſired Hymen, You have ſome ſuperfluous Toys I ſee about you, which you muſt deliver; I mean, that Chain of Gold and Pearl about your Neck, and thoſe pretty Bracelets about your Arms, (pray, Heaven, they prove not Emblems of the combined Hemp which is to halter mine); come, Madam, pray deliver 'em. . - Ara. Nay, I intreat you, Sir, to take 'em, for I cannot give 'em, they are lock'd you ſee, and truly I have not the Key about me; it may be you are furniſh'd with In- ſtruments that may unlooſe 'em, I pray do. Sum. No faith, Madam, I’m but a Beginner in this ſame Buſineſs, and am wholly unprovided of any Pick-lock Tools beſides this Sword. . . . LDraws his Sword. Ara. O, good Sir, do not ſhew me that, 'tis too frightful ; pray hurt me not, for I do yield them freely : llſe your Hands, perhaps their ſtrength will ſerve to tear 'em from me withoutmore ado. Some Pain I'll quietly endure, provide you do not hurt me much. - - Sun. Alas, dear Lady, I'll uſe you as gently as I can He endeavours to break the upon my Word; but 'tis deviliſh ſtrong If I hurtl. Chain about her Neck. you, pray ſpeak. -Ara. Not much, Sir. Sun. I am gladon’t, S'death, I can't do it. [She dram's his Sword, and ſtands - - upon her Guard. Ara. No Sir, nor ſhall not now : You a Highway-man and guard your ſelf no bet- ter: Come, Sir, what Money have you? Deliver quickly. Sum. Not a Croſs by this fooliſh Hand of mine ! Ara. How, no Money, 'twere pity then to take this from thee; y Gives him his Here, take it again, I know you’l uſe mene're the worſe for whatl. Sword again. } I have done. * Sum. No, by my Life! - - - * Ara. I do believe you; and now pray hear me — Here on my Knees, in ſight of Heaven, I make this ſolemn Proteſtation, That if you'l but forbear the Rifling of this Chain and Bracelets, and go but with me Home, by all the Vows which I this Day have plighted to my deareſt Husband, I will deliver you in Money the full Value of theſe I wear, and cannot for my Life get off. - Sam. Ha! Ready-money is the Prize I look for ; it paſſes without ſuſpicion every where, when Chains and Jewels are often ſtop’d and call’d for before the Magi- ſtrate: But - Ara. Nay never doubt' You ſaw I gave youmy Advantageup, and queſtioned not my ſafety at your hands, pray fear not yours in mine. Sam. I know not what to do. - Ara. Pray tell me, Sir, did you ever thinka Woman true? Sum. I have heard of ſome, but very few. . dra. Willyou add one more to your belief? -
Page 12

- 12 The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. Sum. I think I may, for they were fewer than the Articles of my Faith, therefore I have room for you, and will believe you Yet ſtay, you ſay you’l ranſom your jewels with Ready-money when you come Home ; ſo you may, and then diſcover IIIC, - - - Ara. Shall I repeat the Vows I made 2 - - - | Sum, No, for I'll truſt you ; and if you do betray me, then Mercy upon me, and Farewel. I knew a Gentleman that had been a Courtier at Whitehall fifteen Years, and he was buriede're he took a Bride : 'Tis very ſtrange you’l ſay 3 and may be my Caſe in another way. - - . . . . . - Ara. Come, Sir, never fear : A Man and afraid 3. Fie, fiel - - 1 Sum. Give me your Hand, I'll wait on you ; and if you are (as I believe you) True: and Juſt, you are the World's Wonder | Come, Madam. [Exeunt. - r - - - S C E N E II. Enter two Boys, one with a Child in his Arms. Compaſs on the other ſide. - * . . - * . I Boy. jack, Who's this? 2 Bºy. Ojeminy: I’ll be hang'd if it ben’t Goodman Compaſ, that they ſaid was dead three Years ago. . . . . ** - ". . It ſº" ſ. 1 Boy, Od's Life, and ſo it is 1 - . Comp O London ſweet London I Do I live to ſee thee once again? My Eyes are full of Brine for Joy. And if my deat Peggy be but living ſtill, I ſhall cry’em out. 1 Boy. Goodman Compaſ, I am glad to ſee you; You are welcome home. * Comp. Thank you, good Lad: Honeſt jack here too? Why, thou art grown a little Man fince I ſaw thee laſt : What, is that thy own, heh 2 - 2 Boy. I am fain to keep it, you ſee, whoever got it it may be other Mens Caſes as well as mine. - - - --~ - Comp. Thou fy'ſ true jacks But whoſe pretty Knave is it 2. - 2 Boy. My Dame's where I live. ºr - Comp. And not thy Maſter's 2 w 2 Boy. Nay, nay, I can't tell that neither: My Maſter loves it as well as if it were lis own, and for ought I ſee betterjhan my Dame. - Comp. A very good Lad by my Troth! . . . n . , . . . . . . -2 Boy. But, Goodman Compaſs, I can tell you News, Your Wife has a brave Boy too of her own, not above a Quarter old, as big as two of this... tº - * * * . . - Comp. Ha! ſay’ſ thou ſo, jack f Ha, ha, ha, by my Troth I am heartily glad to hear it : Pll give thee a dozen of Ale, and thy News be true, Boy. Boy. I aſſure you 'tis very true: All your Neighbours can tell you the ſame. . | Comp. Ha, ha, ha! But a Quarter old, and ſo luſty, ſay you & What plaguy thun- dering Boys are got now-a-days: I Gad, I ſhall ſplit my $.60s with Laughing; Ha, ha, ha.—But, jack, I have been loth to ask thee all this while, for fear of ill News, how does my Wife 2 : º . . . . - t 2 Boy, O never better, nor ever ſo luſty and handſome—And truly ſhe wears better * Clothes than ſhe was wont, eſpecially on Holy days: ſhe has Silk-Gowns, and Lac'd- Petticoats, and fine Holland Smocks too, they ſay, that have ſeen 'em : And ſome of Yºr Neighbºurs ſay, they were taken upiñCheaf * - Nay dia ºs--- *
Page 13

--- The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. 13 ... Comp. Like enough, jack 3 and there they muſt be paid for—Well, good Lads, go and tell my Wife the joyful Tidings of my Return. 2 Boy. That I will with all my Heart, for ſhe heard you were dead long agó. - 1 Boy. Nay, I'll go along with you jack. º - 2 Boy, Come then. [Exeunt 2 Boys. Comp. Well, Peggy, if I am one of the Livery, I thank thee for it: The Cuckolds. are the greateſt Company in all the City: And we have more Aldermen among us, than all the other put them together. - - Enter Peg, Compaſs's Wife. -- Peg, O my dear ſweet Honey-ſuckleſ Art thou alive 2 I am glad {* and kiſ M. to ſee thee with all my Heart and Soul, ſo I am. fes him, Comp. O, ho! good Spouſe, give me leave to ſhed a few pearly Tears; the Foun- tain of Love will have its Courſe: And thé I cannot Sing at firſt ſight, yet I can Cry. you ſee. I am as it were new come into the World; and Children Cry before they Laugh, a long time you know. - * . Pig. Yes; and ſo thou art new born indeed to me, my Numpy; for I was told, you were dead long ſince, and never thought to ſee this dear ſweet Face of thine again : I heard thouwert div'd to the bottom of the Sea, and that you never did intend to ſee poor Peggy more. . - • Comp. He, he, he, I was going down, as you ſay Peg, but I thought better orºt, and turn'd back: I heard an ill Report of my Neighbours whºſe; the devouring Sharks, and other Sea-Monſters, whoſe Company, to tell you the Truth, I did not like; and therefore reſolv’d to come home and bide with thee my Girl--Come, kiſs thy poor Hubby, kiſs me I ſay, for Sorrow begins to ebb apace. Peg. A thouſand, thouſand Welcomes home dear Numpy Comp. An Ocean of Thanks, kind Peggy: Well, and how goes all at Home? What Lank ſtill, poor Peg f Wil’t ne're be full Sea at our Wharf 2 - Peg. Alas, Husband, what do you mean? Comp. A Laſs is it, or a Lad, Wench 2 I ſhou’d be glad of both; I look'd for a pair of Compaſſes long afore now. - Peg. What, and you from home, Love 2 - - Comp. I from home 2. Why the I was from homg, and other of our Neighbours. from home, does that follow that every body elſe is from home? , Peg. I am pleaſed you are ſo merry, Husband. - - Comp. Merry, nay I'll be merrier yet; why ſhou'd I be ſorry? I hope my Boy's well, is he not ? Od's fiſh, I look for another by this Time. - Pig. Boy, what Boy, Deary.” . - -- * * Comp. What Boy why the Boy I got when I came home in the Cock-boat one Night, about a Year ago You have not forgotten it, I hope, I think I left behind: me for a Boy, and a Boy I look for. - Peg. I find he knows all—What ſhall I do? ... [Aſide.] . O dear Husband, pray pardon me. [Kneels.] - - Comp. Pardon thee s why I hope thou haſt not made away with my Boy, haſt #: *Od's death Pilhangth:e, if there were never a Whore more in Lºndon, if thou- * . - Pºrº
Page 14

| - - 14 The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. Peg, Ono, but your long Abſence, and the Rumour of your Death, [criti.] made me think I might venture. - Comp. Venture, quoth a, I can’t blame thee Peg ; for Wapping, if it were twice Wapping, can't hold out always, no more than Redriff, Limehouſe or Shadwel, nay or the ſtrongeſt Suburbs about London ; and when it comes to that, wo be to the Čity too, Girl. - - Peg. Conſider, Husband, I’m but a Woman, neither the firſt or laſt that have done the ſame 3 and truly I won’t deny but I have a Child. Comp. Have you ſo? And what by Conſequence muſt I have then, I pray ? . Peg. If you’l forgive me this Time, it ſhall be ſo nomore, indeed and indeed, now. Comp. Well, well, I will forgive thee, Peg, upon this Condition, that you tell me who it was that fell foul aboard thee, and ſprung this Leak in thee. Peg, O dear Husband 1 - Comp. Nay, no Excuſes, for I muſt know. Pºg. Why then truly it was Mr. Wenter the Merchant. -- Comp. I am beholding to him, and wou’d requite his Civility, if his Wife were but as willing, thé he be one of our Merchants at Sea, he ſhall give me leave to be Owner at home; and where is my Boy 2 what, ſhan’t I ſee him 2 - Peg. Yes if you pleaſe, good Husband : He's nurs'd at Bednal green; 'tis now too late, to Morrow will be better. - cº, Come then we'l home and to bed. 1st other Fº repine at Scoffs and Scorns, I’ll teach the Cuckold how to hide his Horns. [Exeunt. Enter ſuffice Merryman, Mr. Venter, Spruce, Mrs. Wenter and Clara: Mer. Was the like ever known, that a Bridegroom ſhou'd abſent himſelf on his Wedding-Day ? Mr. Ven. "Tis ſomewhatſtrange indeed. - Mer. And thé Bride too my Daughter, ſhe's out of the way: Why what ſhou'd be the meaning of all this, Od's bobs I can't tell ? Mrs. Ven. Perhaps they’r buſy Brother, privately conferring Notes together : You tan't tell but that the young Man may have a ſtomach to his Supper, and fall too unawares, and we ne're the wiſer. Spr. Od's nigs, very true; what wou'd you ſay then Sir, if they ſhou'd be ſtol’n a- way, and a-bed together ſeriouſly 7 -- Mer. What wou'd I ſay?' marry I wou'd ſay, Speed 'em well: And if no worſe News ever comes to me, i'll be hang'd if e're I cry’d for't. Enter Nurſe. How now, what's the Buſineſs with you? Nurſe. Buſineſs enough, Forſooth; for I have the ſtrangeſt Tydings! Mer. Of any One that's loſt, Woman & - Nurſe. Noforſooth, of One that’s found again, an’t pleaſe you. j Mer. O, he ' ' then it ſeems.
Page 15

- ... The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. T Mr. Wan. Her Buſineſs is with me, I believe Brother; is it not, Woman 2 , Nurſe. Yes, Sir. - º, Mr. Ven. Come hither then, [Nurſe whiſpers Mr.Venter.] - How, return’d 2. - Nurſe. Yes indeed, Sir, and all diſcovered. Mr. Ven. Ah Curſe on the Wind that blew him aſhore. Nurſe. Aye, ſo ſay I Sir, and did not ſink him when he was going. Mr. Ven. Well, well, be ſure you do not let him come near the Child. Nurſe. I warrant you, Sir, if you charge me to the contrary. 5 ~ Mr.Ven. Yes, I do ſtrićtly charge you as you tender my Diſpleaſure. Nurſe. Well then let me alone morning with his Wife and ſee him. . Mr. Wen. I’ll meet him there; and if he chance to be there before me, be ſure to Beſides, Sir, he intends to come to morrow keep the Child ſafe, and not let him touch it. , Nurſe. I warrant you, let me alone. - [Exit Nurſ. Enter Summerfield and Arabella. Mer. So, ſo, Heaven be praiſed, they are not both loſt I ſee, here's the Bride, my Daughter, come again. y - Ara. Father, and Gentlemen, I deſire ye to treat this Stranger here with all Re- ſpect and Generoſity : He's a loving Kinſman of my Bonvils's, who kindly came to congratulate our Wedding. - - Mer. Sir, you are heartily welcome, Od’s bobs you are. Mr. Wen. Welcome to all of us. Spruce. Seriouſly, Sir, and ſo you are. - - Mer. But where's the Bridegroom, Girl? Od’s bobs we're all at a Nonplus here, at a ſtand, quite out; the Muſicks ceas'd, and we all look as thé there were neithera light Heart or Heel among us ; nay, my Couſin Clara too as cloudy as on a waſhing Day. Clara. 'Tis then becauſe you will not dance with me, Sir. Ara. 'Tis I alone have cauſe to be ſad, if this Day's Happineſs cou’d admit of a- ny : But I’ve long reaſon'd with my preſſing Thoughts, and from them drawn ſome Symptoms of Relief. Suppoſe this Day hath been long ſince appointed by my dear Bonvile, to meet ſome Foe, and right his injur’d Reputation : Nay, ſay he fights, a- las! Why ſhou'd I fear, when all the Powers above, that guard true Love and Inno- cence, will never ſee him fall. - Mer. Prethee peace, good Girl hold thy tongue; Od’s bobs thou’lt make us all Cowards, to hear a Woman preach up Valour thus. Ara. Well, Sir, I have done: But pray entertain this Gentleman kindly for my ſake. Indeed I was afraid when I ſaw him firſt. - Sam. Ha! what does ſhe ſay ? Qd’s Death ſhe’l tell! - * * Ara. Being in ſearch of my dear Bonvile, I had quite loſt my Way when he moſt opportunely came unto my Aid, and gave me many marks of his Eſteem in my di- ſtreſs of Fears; nay more than this, which I'll declare at large. Sum. Death and Hell, ſhe’l betray me. *
Page 16

- - - | :16 The City.Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. Ara. Well, Gentlemen, ſince the Bridegroom's abſent, I muſt ſupply his Place : Come, when I have waited on you to your Pleaſure, I will return [To S - to you, Sir, we muſt diſcourſe more of my Bonvile yet. o Summerfield.j - [Exeunt all but Summerfield. - Manet Summerfield ſolu. Sun. What a trembling Trade's this, when Conſcience, that ſhou'd be our only Guide, flies and leaves us to our acculing Guilt. A Thief!, the very Name and Thought chills my Blood, and makes me tremble like an Ague fit. A Dog, nay every Bough that moves, puts us in fear of preſent Apprehenſion. Sure I ſhall never thriv. on this Trade : Perhaps I need take no further Care, I may be now near to my- Journey’s End, or at leaſt in a fair way to Newgate, and from thence to Tyburn, the only Place that we poor Rogues can claim for an Inheritance. Truſt a Woman, and with a Matter of ſuch Importance, what a ſimple Dog am I? I cou’d find in my Heart to run away: And that were baſe to run from a Woman I can lay claim to nothing but her Vows, and thoſe the Women ſeldom or never mind. Enter Arabella. Ara. So, Sir, now you ſhall find a Woman as good as her Promiſe; Here are 20 Pieces, the full Value, on my Life, of what they coſt. - Sum. Pray, Madam, do not thus ſuſpend my doubtful Soul , but if you do deſign to inſnare my Life, ſpeak, ſpeak freely : Or if the Conſtable be at the Door, let him ſhew his Staff of Authority, perhaps I may corrupt him with a Bribe. ... Ara. How! baſe ungrateful Man, do you ſuſpect my Faith? Nay then, Father, llncle, and Gentlemen, where are you ? - - Enter all a, before. AMer. How now, how now ! What’s the matter, Girlf Ara. For ſhame, will you not entertain your Kinſman here a little better 3 you leave him here alone, as thé you deſpiſed his Company. - AMer. Is that all 2 I thought the Bridegroom had been return'd : Sir, pray pardon this Rüdeneſs; But indeed I had quite forgot you, quite forgot you, as I hope to be ſav'd : But what makes youtremble, Sir, are you ill diſpos'd. - Ara. Think you he hath not reaſon to be ill-diſpoſed at this cold { Aſide to juſtice Entertainment 2 for my part I bluſh for ſhame. Merryman. } Spr. Come pray, Sir, ſhake off this Dulneſs, and participate of our Mirth, Od's nigs do. ſt Sum. I am very well, Sir, I thank you, only the Gentleman is a little under a Mi- ake. Mer. It may be ſo, Ay, ay, it may be ſo; I vow I thought you had trembled, but I believe it might be my own Hand 5 you muſt pardon me, I was ſtiffer once. Sum. Sir, your humble Servant. - AMer. But, Gentlemen, what think you of an Adventure ? Spr. Adventure whither ? A...
Page 17

— — . - . - - - • - The City Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. 17 Mer. Why, to the Eaſt-Indies I have a Veſſel, Gentlemen, called the Sea-Horſe, -bound thither, and to morrow 1 do expect her to ſail. Now, Gentlemen, if you'l venture, ye ſhall have fair Dealing, that I’ll promiſe you. And for the French, you need not fear them, for ſhe is a ſmart new Weſſel: Nay, ſhe hath a Letter of Mart too, and twenty brave roaring Boys on both Sides her, Starboard and Larboard : And I intend to go as far as Marget down with her, 'twill be as good as Phyſick to me. Spr. A very good Motion, Sir, I begin, there's my ten Pieces. Sum, And, Sir, if a proffer'd Love may be accepted, be pleaſed to take my ten Pieces with you. - Mer. Your’s above all the reſt, Sir. - : That's kindly ſaid, Sir, and I thank you: Now pray venture Ten more for II] ake. -- - 's. Alas, Madam, it’s a younger Brother’s Portion. Ara. At my Requeſt, Sir, venture the other Ten; if you want, I’ll ſupply you with as many more. - Sum. With all my Heart then : Come, Sir, if you pleaſe, I’ll double mine : So now ſhe's got her Gold again, and I am now no Thief, (affile) Sir, I have a Suit to you, [To Merryman. Mer. You may command it, for I am always at your Service: But pray your Pleaſure ? - Sum. My Requeſt, Sir, is, to have the Honour of keeping you Company to Sea, for I have a great deſire to ſee Marget. Mer. Sir, I ſhall be very happy in your good Company. Ara. I hope you will be both better acquainted e're you return; and by that time your Kinſman may be here to make you more welcome. - * ‘nd for the Gold at my Requeſt you lent, * - A 4 double it to give you more content. Sum, Why ſhou'd I fear, ſince ſhe is prov’d ſo juſt * I'll quit my Trade : Now Jack Catch do thy worff. - Exeumt. * The End of the Second ACT.
Page 18

- The City-Bide: Or, the Merry Cuckold. * *- 18 A C T the Third. ... * A Wood. - º - - Enter Bonvile and Friendly, 2. yet i'th Field; let's walka Turn or two, perhaps by that time he may ar. - TiVº, - . - - - - Fri. I’m very confident that he's here already. * . Bºn. Thy Looks, me-thinks, ſpeak Conqueſt ſure thy own; an ardent Rage has kiddled both thy Cheeks. . . . . . - Fri. Like a red Morning, Friend; which ſtill foretels a ſtormy Day to follow— : now I well obſerve your Face, me-thinks it waxes pale, there’s Death in it al- ſtady. - - - Ben. How, Friendly, do you then take me for a Coward 2 My Face look pale, and Death in it already ? By Heav'n, ſhould any but my Friendly dare to tell me what thou haſt ſaid, my Sword ſhou’d ram the baſe Affront down the curſt Willain's Throat. But you are my Friend, and I muſt only chide your Error. But prethee tell me who is it you are to fight with, for as yet I am iſnorant both of the Cauſe and Perſon. F. i. Hº, his Name ! Did you enquire his Name 2. Bon. Yes.. - - - - Fri. I dare not yet reveal it for fear of * Bon. For fear of what ? - Fri. O Confuſion . I know not what to ſay : - - - Bon. How, afraid to tell his Name? Then I begin to doubt the Jūſlice of your Quarrel. - • * Fri. Too well you may, for by yon’ ſetting Sun, that Globe of heavenly Light ! ſwear, I come to kill the only Mail that ſtrives to ſave my Life Man did I ſay ? Nay more than common Man, for thoſe the World abound with; but ſuch a Man be- . fides, all this vaſt Land affords not. - - Ron. By this your large Encomium of your Friend, I'm afraid 'twas Wine firſt made your Quarrel, and thereupon this Challenge did enſue. - Fri. O no I call the Powers above to witneſs, that in all the Courſe of our un-- happy Friendſhip, I to my knowledg never did receive the leaſt Affront or Injury from him. . . . . . ; – Bon. How came this Challenge then? - - Fri. O dear Friend, the nobleſt that Mān cou’d ever boaſt of: [embraces him] When firſt my rigid Fate threw on me this Command to fight, I had recourſe to ma- my whom I always thought my Friends, "bat when the Touchſtone of my Danger try'd 'em, I found'em like the curſed Fruit of Sodim, fair without, but rotten * - - t 8bn, CŞ ME my brave Friendly, I think we are here the firſt: Your Enemy is not
Page 19

Friendſhip too to back it. - The City.Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold 19 • the Heart: But then I found out Bonvile, my only deareſt Friend. Bonvile no ſooner heard of my Engagement, but flew unto my Succour with as much Bravery, as a great General haſtned by Alarms, marches to meet the Foe: You left your Nuptial Bed erhaps to meet your Death. O unheard-of Friendſhip ! My Father gave me Life, tis true; but you, my Friend, ſupport my Honour. All this for me, while I, un- grateful Man, thus ſeek your Life: Fur to my eternal Horror be it ſpoke, you are the Man whom I come here to kill. - - Bom. Ha! - - Fri. Too true alas ! there read the Warrant for your Death. [Gives him the Letter. Bon. 'Tis a Woman's Hand. . . . . Fri. Yes, and a bad One too, they all ſpeak fair, write foul, but mean worſe. . Bon. How ! kill me? Sure, I dream, and this is all Deluſion, or elſe thou doſt it only to try thy Friend. - r Fri. O, from my Soul, I wiſh it were no more. But read, read on, ſee how I’m fet- ter'd in a Circe's Charms—I love beyond Imagination, love even to Madneſs, and muſt as madly do a Deed will damn me to the hotteſt Flames of Hell. - Bon. And woo’t thou kill thy Friend for ſuch a Woman 2 - Fri, Alas! I muſt, you ſee I am commanded, commanded too by Love; Love more powerful than all the Sacred Ties of Friendſhip, therefore draw, and guard thy ſelf. . [Draws. - Bon. Not I by Heaven! What wou'dſt thou have me draw and kill my Friend? Fri. There thou ſtab'ſt my Soul. O where, where is now my Reſolution fled 2 A fatal Blaſt has ſtruck me , a ſudden Horror ſhot me thrö the Heart; a Trembling ſeiz'd my Knees, that I can hardly ſtand, and all my Vital Powers methinks ſeem dead; yet Love's the Fire muſt kindle all again, therefore I charge thee draw, or naked as thou art, I will aſſail thee. Bon. I am defended againſt all that thou canſ: do, in having Juſtice on my Side, and But ſince Humanity now bears ſo ſway, To this unguarded Breaft come make your way. Strike home be ſure. * [open, his Boſm. Fri. That were a barbarous Murder. - Bon. How can the Effect prove different from the Cauſe 2 Or how can any thing but damn'd Barbarity enſue a Woman's much more damn'd Deſign? Who wou'd ex- pećt Reaſon from one that raves, or hope for Mercy in a Tyger's Den? Believe me, Friendly, all this may ſooner be: Mercy may ſooner dwell among the Salvage Wolves and Bears, than in a Woman’s Breaſt. - Fri. O, my too rigid Fate, to place me thus on ſuch a dangerous Precipice, that whereſoe’re I turn my ſelf for help, I ſee my Ruin ſtill beforé mine Eyes... seems to weep. Bon. [Pauſing.]ºtay The Command which thy Medea ſent thee, was to kill thy only deareſt Friend, was it not ? - Fri. Alas! it was. Bon, Then here, all Frienſhip dies between us ; thus haſt thou kill'd thy Friend, and ſatisfied that infernal Hag, thy curſed Miſtreſs, who thus commanded thee: Away, I ſay, begon, and never ſee me more. Fri. Ha! w D 2 'º,
Page 20

- - z _ 2. O The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. - Bon, Yes, baſe ungrateful Wretch, farewel, (Offers to go) — Yet ſtay, and ſince that Sacred Tie of Friendſhip's broke, know thou, moſt vile of Men, that Bon- wilº's now thy Enemy; therefore do thou draw and guard thy ſpotted Life. Fri. How, Friend 1 - - Bon. Friend didſt thou call me? On forfeit of thy Life that word no more the very Name of Friend from thee, ſhall be a Quarrel: How can I tell but that thou loveſt my Wife, and therefore feign'd this damn'd Deſign to draw me from her Arms? Fri. How ! wrong thy Wife? O no, I never had a Thought ſo vile ! Yet you muſt forgive me, indeed you muſt, by all that once was dear to me; and what I dare not men- tion more, by Love and Honour, I implore thy Pardon- Still art thoudeaf to my Complaints?—Nay, then upon my Knees I will enforce thy Pity. Behold me, Bon- vile, proſtrate at thy Feet, crawling for Mercy, ſwimming in Tears, and almoſt drown'd with Shame; extend thy Arm to help me, as thou’rt a Man, be God-like in thy Nature, and raiſe me from the Grave 3 turn thy Eyes on me, and fink me not with Frowns ; O ſave me, ſave me, or I fall for ever, Ban, As ſoon ſhall Heav'n reverſe the Fate of Hell, as I recal what I have ſaid, or plant thee in my Breaſt again. - Fri. Nay, then I am loſt to thee, and all the World beſides. . ERiſes. Bon. Thou artindeed for ever loſt to me; ſee what a miſerable Wretch thy Folly now has made thee: A Creature ſo far below my Pity, that I deſpiſe and ſcorn thy baſe Submiſſion, and will never hear thee more, more. z Fri. Say but thou haſt forgiven me, and I will ask no more. Bon. I never will. - * . Fri. O cruel Bonvile ! - - Bon. More barbarous Friendly : Hold off, or I will uſe thee like a Dog, tread thee to Earth, and ſpurn thee like a Slave, baſe as thou art, Fri. Still thou art my Friend Bon. Thou ly’ſt, I have abjured the Name. Fri. Let me but go with thee. - Bon. Not for the World ; I'de rather venture my ſelf with Crocodiles, catch the laſt dying Gaſps of ſome poor Wretch infected with the Plague, than truſt my ſelf with thee. º Farewel, 1 leave thee with the greateft Curſe, - ~ Condemn'd to Woman, Hell #. no worſe. -- - - Exit, breaking from him. Friendly ſolus, riſing in a Paſſion. Fri. Death and Deſtruſtion, am I thus deſpiſed Condemned to Woman's Luſt, and ſcorn’d by Man. By Bonvile too, after imploring, like a School. Boy, at his Feet —My Blood boils high, and ſcalds my very Heart! My inward Grief calls on me for Revenge, and I am all on fire O that I had the proud Bonvile here now at my Feet, I'de uſe him worſe than he did me before. . But ſince that open Force yield; no Relief, Private Ravenge ſhall eaſe my ſwelling Grief. With
Page 21

The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. 21. With Thoughts of jealouſy I’ll fill his Soul, Which ſhall its Powers of all their Reft controul. Thuſ for a Woman Pve begun a War, . . . - And for her ſake muſt damn mySoul like her. [Exit. S C E N E the Second. s Enter Nurſe, Compaſs, and his Wife. Nurſe. Indeed you muſt pardon me, I can't let ye ſee the Child 5 to tell you the Truth, I am commanded to the contrary. - - comp. Commanded ! Prethee who commanded thee * Nurſe. The Father. - - Comp. The Father, Why who am I? -" Nurſe. Not the Father ſure, the Civil Law has found it otherwiſe. comp. The Civil Law found it otherwiſe ! Why then the uncivil Lawſhall make it mine again, I'll be as dreadful as a Shrove-Tueſday to thee; for I'll beſiege thy ſqual- ling catterwauling Caſtle, with my Friends the Mob, and gut thy ſtinking Nurſery, but I’ll both ſee and have my Child. Nurſe. Harkee, Goodman Swabber, ſay but half ſo much again, and I’ll call the Conſtable, and lay Burglary to your Charge. You wou’d not be ſo hot if the Ene- my were in view, nor if you had to do with any body but a poor innocent Woman, ſo you wou’d’nt. - - Peg. Good Husband be patient, and let me alone with her : Come, come, good Nurſe, let him ſee the Boy. Nurſe. Indeed Idare not Goody ºft : The Father firſt you know delivered me the Child, and order'd me to let no body ſee it. He pays me well and weekly for my Pains, and therefore I’ll do as he bad me, ſo I will. - Comp. Why thou white Baſtard-breeder; Is not this Woman here the Mother ? Nurſe. Yes; I grant you that. Comp. Do you ſo? Well, and I grant it too; And is not the Child then my own by the Wives Copy-hold 2 --- - - Nurſe. The Law muſt try that. Comp. The Law J What then you think I'll be but its Father-in-Law 2 I tell thee, * all the Wit and Law 'twixt Cuck'd.-Point and Weſtminſter-Hall, ſhan’t keep my own. dear Fleſh and Blood from me, I warrant you that. No an’t does, I’ll be hanged at the Main-yard: Why, who, doſt think, uſes to get my Children but my ſelf? Nurſe. Nay, I can’t tell, you muſt look to that, for my part I ne're knew you get any. - - Comp. Say'ſt thou ſo? Why, look you, do butput on a clean Smock, and try me, if thou darſt, I’ll hold thee three to one I get thee with Child before I leave thee : Heh what ſay'ſt thou? [Offers to lay hold on her. Nurſe. I’ll ſee you hang'd firſt—Nay, pray be quiet, and don't offer to ſpoil my Milk. Lord, you are as boiſterous as my Husband was the firſt Night we were mar- ried: Pray, Goody Compaſs, take off your Cur, or elſe he’l bite me, Pºg. No never fear him, Nurſe, he's not ſo furious I aſſure ye. Enter
Page 22

. 21 The City.Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. " . ~ --- : Enter Mr. Venter and his Wife. Nurſe. O ! here's my Maſter, the Child's Father, now talk with him. Mr. Ven. Good morrow Neighbour, good morrow to ye both. Comp. Both ! Good morrow to you and your Wife too, if you go to that, ... Mr. Ven. I wou'd ſpeak calmly with you, Friend, if you think fit. Comp. I know what belongs to Calm, and a Storm too; and if you pleaſe, a cold word or two wi' you. - Mr. Ven. With all my Heart. - Comp. I underſtand that you have ty'd your Mare in my Ground. Mr. Pen. My Mare, Friend, nay I aſſure you’twas only my Nag. Comp. Your Nagº Well your Nag then let it be : Harke, Sir, to be ſhort, I’ll cut off your Nag's Tail, if e're I catch him there again. - - Mr. Ven. Pray hear me, you are too rough to maintain Comp. I ſay, Sir, you ſhall maintain no Child of mine ; my Wife does not beſtow her Labour for that purpoſe. Mr. Wen, You are too paſſionate—.I will not maintain- Comp. No marry ſhall you not. - * * Mr. Pem. The Deed I have done to be lawful, I have repented it, and given Satiſ. fağion to the Law, my Purſe has paid for't; therefore I wou'd treat milder with you if you’d be pleaſed. - Comp. Yes, yes, I am very well pleaſed, and ſhall be better pleaſed if you can ſerve me ſo ſtill: For, look you Sir, one of theſe Days I ſhall to Sea again, you know where my Wife lives; yet you'l but loſe your labour, for get as many Children as you can, I aſſure you, you ſhall keep none of them. - - Mr. Pen. I think you are mad. Camp. Why, if I am Horn mad, what’s that to you? . Mr. Ven. Nay then, ſince you are ſorough, I tell you plainly you are—a— Comp. A what? What am I, heh - Mr. P'en. A Coxcomb. - Comp. A Coxcomb! a Cuckold you mean, and you a Fool for your pains. Mr. Van. The Child is mine, I am the Father of it, and will keep it. - - - Comp. Yes if you can, I know you will. But pray tell me, is not my Wife the Mother ? You may be as far from being the Father as I am, for my Wife's acquain- ted with more Whore-maſters beſides your ſelf; ay, and as crafty Merchants too, let me tell you that. - Peg. No indeed Husband, I had to do with no body elſe, 'twas he begot, indeed and indeed now. Yet for all that, the Child's mine, I bred it and bore it, and I'll have it and keep it, ſo I will. - - Mrs. Ven. Pray hold there Mrs. Jill-flurt, the Child's my Husband's, and he ſhall have it, or I'll tear your Eyes out, ye Whore you. - Comp. Good Words, Miſtreſs ; d’ye hear, give good Words you'd beſt, or I ſhall tell you your own. ‘. . . . . . Mr. Win, I'll have no more to ſay to ye, the Law ſhall determine it; in the mean time Nurſe keep the Child for me, there, there’s Money for thee. [Gives bºr Money. - - - * . Comp. - º -º -
Page 23

r s The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. 2; Camp. There's Money for me too, keep it for me, Nurſe; give him both thy Duggs at once, I pay thee for the right one, Girl. Nurſe. I have two Hands, you ſee Gentlemen; this does but ſhew ye how the Law will hamper ye; even thus you’l be uſed, Gentlemen, if you go to Law. -- Mr. Ven. It can't be helpf, for I won't loſe my Right. Comp. Nor I mine for all you’re a Merchant. Mrs. Ven. Nor l mine for all I did not bear it. Peg. Nor I, thé but a poor Sailer’s Wife. \ Mr. Wen. Well, fare ye well, we ſhall meet in another Place—Come Winny. - - [Exit venter and his Wife. Comp. Ay, ay, I'll meet you when and where you dare, and do your worſt, I fear you not: By the Lord Harry the World's come to a fine Paſs, that we muſt go to Law for our Children. No wonder the Lawyers are all ſo rich, yet e're the Law ſhall have a Limb, a Leg, a Joint or Nail of this ſame Boy, , . 'Tſhall coſt me more than a whole Child in getting, Some win by play, and ſtanders by with Betting. - º [Exeunt. - S. C. E. N. E. the Third. Enter Spruce, Arabella with a Letter in her Hand, Clara, - AMr. Venter, and AMrs. Venter. - Mr. Pen. Froni whence came that Letter, Niece 4ra. From Putney, Sir, and from my Husband. - Mr. Pen. And pray be free , Does he tel, ye the Cauſe of his leaving you ſo absº ruptly on his Wedding-day? - * - 4ra. Yes, Sir, yet this had been ſufficient to have let me known what he is gone - about, without the formal Addition of an Epiſtle. - - Spruce. That, why what is that I pray Madam 2 - , Ara. His Will, Sir, wherein he makes me his ſole Executrix. - - &r. Will ! why what the Devil does he mean, ſeriouſly I can’t find it out : Ara. Why, Sir, he’s gone to fight. - Spr. How fight. Madan On my Soul then I believe Friendly's Second. dra. You're in the right, he is ſo, and I am loſt for ever ! . - Cia., O fool ſh Friendly, this thy Miſtake has made me the moſt wretch.d of Wo- man-kind | Such variety of Thoughts load my aſflićted Breaſt, that I know not what * to think: I rave, ammad, not knowing what my Folly may produce ; I fear for both, for both my Heart does bleed. - - w * , Ara. Miſerable Maid nay, miſèrable Wife but much more miſerable Widow O my dear Bonvile'ſ - - - Spr. Duce take me, if e're I ſaw a Company ſo Phlegmatick infall my Life : Mr. **ter, prethce let's have a Song to paſs away the Time, and put Life into the Bride. - \
Page 24

=-- *|† - - w - --- 24 . The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. - , Mr. Pen. With all my Heart, Mr. Spruce : Here, who waits 2–$Servant Enter Call in the Muſick, and deſire’em to oblige the Ladies with a new? and Exit. } Song. ) - - Cla. Your ſelf, Sir, you mean 2 .. | Spr. Nay all of us I proteſt. Mr. Wen, Ay, ay, all of us. / Enter Muſick and others who ſing. A Dialogue ſet by Seignior Baptiſt. s Man. A Woman’s Love — Woman. And Man's is ſuch, Man. Still too little, – Wom. Or elſe too much. Wom. Men are Extreams, – Man. And Women too, Wom. All, all are falſe, - — Man. All, all like you. Wom. Tou’l ſwear and lie, -— Man. If you’l believe, Wom. And figh and die, – Man. Tet ſtill deceive. Wom. Tour Vows and Oaths, Man. Tour Smiles and Tears, Wom. Are all but Baits, – Man. Are all but Snares. Wom. To win a Heart, — Man. And then deſtroy, Wom. The eaſy Fool, -— Man. The promis’d joy. n Another Strain. *4, . - - **, Wom. I’le have you offer no more your Pretending, • Man, Nor will I ſuffer your modiſh Diſſembling : - ~~. Wom. For Honour commands, - - Man. - And Freedom withſtands, Wom. What you ? 2- Man. And you. - Wom. I know wou’d have me be, your Slave, Man. I know wou’d have me be, your Slave. Wom. O, no, no, no Man. No, no, no, no Wom. I never will agree, . . . Man. I ever will be free. After the Song enter juſtice Merryman, Summerfield, and three or four Sailers. Mer, Daughter, Daughter! Where's my Daughter 2 I ſay, Where's my Daugh: ter? O Girl, I have the beſt News to tell you Ara. What of my Husband, Sir 2 - r Mer. No, no, of your Couſin, Girl, of your Couſin. . - r - - 4. f ––

Page 25

_* The City-Bride; Or, the Merry Cuckold. 2; Ara. What of him, Sir? ſ - - Mer. Such a Couſin, Girl, ſuch a dear Couſin he is, as Alexander the Great, if he were alive, might be proud and boaſt of. - Ara. You're welcome here again, Sir ; You've made but a ſhort Voyage, pray what occaſion'd your Return ſo ſpeedily 2 - Sum. Madam, I render you ten thouſand Thanks; Your Generoſity and Goodneſs has wholly made me yours; I am the humbleſt of your faithful Admirers. º Ara. Forbear ſuch laviſh Gratitude; You’r too profuſe in your Acknowledgment of your ſmall Favours. But pray be brief, and let me know the happy Occaſion of this your ſudden Return, I long methinks to hear it. • * * , Sum. Madam, you may command me —Not to moleſt the Company with the Recital of every vain and needleſs Circumſtance; 'twas briefly thus. Scarce had we paſſed by Marget on our Courſe, when on a ſudden, from the Top-maſt head, a Sai- ler cries, All hands Aloft, three Sails ahead : With that we rumidg and clear our Deck, our Gun-room arm’d, and all things now are ready for a Fight. The Ships before deſcried, with warlike Stems cut the reſiſting Waves, whilſt from their Pen- dants fluttering in the Air, we found they were three Dunkirk Privateers; they having made our Engliſh Croſs advanced, ſalute us with a Broad-ſide, to make us ſtrike and yield: But we, who ne’re knew as yet what 'twas ſo cowardly to yield, and not regarding their unequal Gdds, fell boldly on, returning Fire for Fire. The * Engagement then grew deſperate, for they on either Side fired in amain, whilſt we withſtood their Force. At length they boldly grappled, and laid us cloſe aboard, and we as bravely beat them off again. Mer. But now, Daughter, mark what follows, for that's worth all, I faith it is ; therefore go on, dear Cuz go on. - -> -- - Sum. Sea-room at length we got 3 when (as Fate wou'd have it): an unlucky Shot ſtruck both the Captain and Lieutenant dead. Then we began to fear, and all our noble Hearts were trembling with deſpair. . . . . . . ** mí" No, no, not all Daughter — But you ſhall hear more — Ods bobs you ll. - r > * Sum. How cou’d it be otherwiſe, when both our Commanders now were loſt 2 therefore to ſtrike was all the Talk - Mar. Ay, ay, now Daughter, now comes the Play, the other was only the Pro- logue. * … *. But Fortune favouring, and the Wind ſpringing a freſh Gale, we got clear off and try’d to make a running Fight. . Mer. Ay, but Cuz, how did we do all this? by whoſe Order and Direétion? Sum, Pardon me, Sir, 'twas of ſo ſmall Moment, that already it has ſlipt my trea- cherous Memory. - Mer. Oh, ho! has it ſo I Ha, ha, ha! But it has not mine, I thank you, no mar- , ry has it not, as you ſhall hear—Then he, with an undaunted Spirit, ſtarted up amongſt the Saylers, and - ... Sum, Nay pray Sir—— ” . . . . . . . . Mer. By the Foot of Pharaoh I’ll not be balkt; he, I ſay, with an Heroick Voice cried out, Courage brave Boys, Charge and Diſcharge amain ; come I’ll ſupply Your fºn Captain's place. At this bleſt News they all fell on again, with ten thouſand - more Fury than before: Wićtory, Wićtory, was all their cry, whilſt he my **-
Page 26

26 The City:Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. Couſin here, whom I ſhall ne're forget, for by the Lord, methinks, I ſee him in the Fight this very Inſtant, now running this way, now running that way, now down to the Gun-room to encourage thoſe that fought there; now upon the Deck again, ſtill crying out, Fear not, brave Boys, the Day will ſoon be our’s. um. Opray, Sir, let me intreat you to forbear, you make me aſhamed, I proteſt, to hear you. . . . . . & * . . - - - AMer. Aſhamed, ſay you? Ha, ha, iia. -- - - . . . . . . . Ara. Good Sir, go on. . . - - - , , , :: . . . . . ;-- 3.44er. I will, I will—At length the proud French ſwallowing too many of our Eng: liſh Balls, two of 'em very ſaily cried, Your Servants Gentlemen, farewel, and down they went. The other having loſt moſt of her Men, reſolved to leave us; but we being too nimble, overtook her, clapt ſome Men aboard, and brought her in a Prize: And this my brave Man of War here, was the firſt that, boarded her with Sword in Hand. ... " i' ºw ºf . . . . . . . . - - - - "... tº it) - 2.1 Sailer. Of all this I was an Eye-witneſs. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ; . zSailer. And ſo was 1. . . . . . . . . . . . … " " . . . . . . . . . .” 3 Sailer. And I, and all of us. ºw A * : * ~~~. . …" Aſer. Yes, and many more ſtout Boys beſides. . . . . [.. . . . . ; : *, *...i Spruce. Sir, we are all indebted to your Valour; ſuch Voyages as theſe, from ſmall Venturers, in time may make us great Merchants, ºr ºſ i.” ". . . . . . : , Mer. Well, never was Fight better managed before, that's certain." … : : * I Sail. No, never, never ! '', 3: . . . . . . . . . . ... Yº . .” 2 Sail. Better, ſay you? No nor half ſo well..., , ; ; , , , ... ºd - i. 3 Sail. If it were in our Power, we'd make him Admiral, ſo we would...... . . . Sum. Gentlemen, 'tis to your Valours all, that I am indebted for the Honour I have gain% :, And that I may not ſeem wholly upgrateful, there, there's ſomething in token of my Thankfulneſs. . . . . [Gives 'em Money. - " " … . . . 1, 2, 3 Sailers. Heaven bleſs your Worſhip. . . . . . . . . . . … º. ºo 4rs: Come Couſin, we'l withdraw into the Parlour: And if theſe honeſt Friends will be pleaſed to drink what our Houſe affords, they ſhall be welcome. . . " * I Sail. Thank you Miſtreſs with all *:::::::: ... [Exeunt aſ but Sailers. . . 2 Sail. Well, this Mr. Summerfield is a brave Fellow, Gadzooks he is. : * -3 Sail, Ay Tom ſo he is ; had it not been for him, we had all been taken on my *Conſcience. 1 Sail. On my Soul and ſo we had: O if you had but ſeen him when he boarded the Monſieur, 'twou'd have made you laugh'till, you had ſplit your Sides. . He game up to the Captain o'this faſhion with a Slap-ha! and gave him ſuch a back-banded wipe, that he cutoff his Head as genteely, as tho, he had ſerved ſeven Years Appren- ticeſhip to't. . . . . . . . Jo 12 in : cºiº 3 , - ...' . . . . . . . ." ' ' . . . . . . º.º. Enter Servant, wit a Bowl of Punch. . . ºr f :: * : * * --- "...S 2 ºf , ſº ºft. Serv. Gentlemen, Mr. Summerfield deſires yeto be merry, and has ſent you this to drink his Health. . . . . . . . . ! . . . . . . . . . 1 Jail. O, the Lord bleſs him, he's a fine Gentleman, and ſo pray tell him, and, withal give him our hearty Thanks; Doſt hear Boy 2 - | -- ; , , , ..." Serv, Yes, yes, I will. . . . [Exit. -
Page 27

The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. 27 2 Sail. What is't Brother ? 3 Sail. Punch by this Light ! Omnes. Hoo-ra, Hoo-ra; Viva Mr. Summerfield, Viva, Hoora. [The firſt Sailer takes the Bowl of Punch, walks in ſtate round the Stage, and ſings; the others all follow.] * -- Here’s a Health to jolly Bacchus, - . . Here’s a Health to jolly Bacchus, - - Hi ho, hi ho, hi %. - ~ 0. For he will merry make us, For he will merry make us, Hi ho, hi ho, hi ho. Then ſit ye down together, Then ſit ye down together. [They all ſit down with the Bowl in the middle. 2 Sail. Pſhaw Pox o'th' this old Song, prithee let's have a Dance. 3 Sail. With all my Heart; ſtrike up Muſick. The Sailers and their Wives dance. After the Dance. 1 Sail. So, well done my Lads, now let’s aboard amain, - And ſuck our Faces o're and o're again. Brandy we’ve #. enough, by this bleſt Chance, We'l nothing drink but Punch, when we get France. Omn. Hoora ! Hoora ! Exeunt omnes, t ' ~ The End of the Third ACT. A CT
Page 28

2. - -- * - - -- - - º - - - - - * - - * --- - - - - * - * . - • -->1 -- - - - - - - -** * - - - - - - \, . * * * - - - - - - - * , . - - - - - - - - * - - • * - * - - - - - * - - - - } ºr * * * * - * - * I







Page 29

/ - * - Tucky Bride; or, the Merry Cuckold 29 — T * * , C T the Fourth / . . ... . - - - 2 Tables, three r . . . A Tavern. - - {{... - Enter Compaſſe, Peg, and Pettifog. - - A Dramer meets them. º - rawer, Wi. Gentlemen. Pleaſe to walk into a Room? Compaffe: Aye Boy. Come Mr. Pettifºg, pleaſe you ſit. Pettifog : With all my Heart; Come Miſtreſs. Draw. What Wine will you be pleaſed to drink, Gentlemen? - Pett. Ask the good Woman : ſpeak Miſtreſs. - Com. Canary for her; I know what reliſhes her Palat beſt. A Quart of brisk Ca- nary. Boy. - * - #. $. ſhall have the beſt in England—Coming, Coming, Sir. [Exit. Com. What call you this ſame Tavern, Mr. Attorney 2 Pett. The King's Head, Sir. - - Com. The King's Head: Marry, it has a good Neighbour of Guild-hall. It takes many a fair Pound upon that’n Account, I warrant you. Draw, (within) A Quartof Canary in the King's-head, ſcore. Enter Drawer, fills a Glaſs, and gives it Compaſſé. Draw. Sir, Here's a Glaſs of the richeſt Canary that ever came over, the very Quinteſſence of the º I aſſure you. ~. com. Say'ſt thou ſo? Why then there’s a Teſter for thee, and ſo leave us—. Come, Mr. Pettifog, [Exit Drawer] and’t pleaſe you my Service to you. [Trink. Pett. I thank you kindly, Sir.—Mrs. my Service to you, your Husband's good Health. . . . . [Drink. - . . Peg. With all my Heart indeed, Here my dear black ey’d Rogue, thy n’own good Health. LDrinkſ. - - - - com. Thank you Peg, thank you, ſo now let's mind our Buſineſs. Enter Mr. Wentere, his Wife, and Dodge, to anºther Table in the ſame Room. Mr. Pen. Show a Room, Drawer. * ~ Dras. Here Sir. - - - Mr. Wan. Ne're a private Room 2 * Prew. No Sir, the Houſe is full. - - - cap. Ods fiſh, whom have we here, my wº Merchant, with his Lawyer
Page 30

- z o: The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. Pett. Yeknow we promiſed to give him a Meeting here. Comp. Tis true we did ſo, -but come to *:::::::::::. ----- - - - - [Pettifog and Compaſſe talk privately, Mr. Ven.Well, bringus a Bottle of your beſt Red, fog º paſſ; talkp y | Draw. You ſhall have it, Sif.; ; ; ; ;LExit Drawer, Mr. Ven. And what do you think of my Cauſe, Mr. Dodge f - Dodge. Q we ſhall carry it moſt certainly: You have Money to go through with the Buſineſs; and me’re fear but we’ll trounce them ſwingingly. Mr. Wem. I warrant you think it very ſtrange, Mr. Dodge, that I am at this Charge and Expence to bring a farther Charge upon me. , Dodge. Not I, I aſſure you, Sir, É. now you are a wiſe Man, and know very well what you do , beſides you have Money, Money enough, Sir. Mr. Wen. Why the ſhort and the long of the Buſineſs is this ; I made a Purchaſe lately, and in that I did eſtate the Child. (about which I’m. ſucd). Joint-Purchaſer with me in all the Land'I bought.", " ' ". . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . º Mrs. Wen. Right Husband; and you know ’twas I that sº to º: Purchaſe, and therefore I’ll never give my Conſent to have the #. up by ſuch a ſinking Tar-barrel as now ſues for him; he'd only bring him up to be a Swab- £er ; no, no, he was born a Merchant and a Gentleman, and he ſhall live and die ſo, Dodge. You are a worthy Gentlewoman upon my word, there are but few of ſićha, noble Temper: But what makes the Fool of the Husband then ſo troubleſome 3 does He iſot know when he's well? . . . . . . . - . . . . . . ; Mrs. Pem. So’tis a ſign. "...A.T. . . . . . … * ºd: A Blockhead, to prºclaim his own Diſgrace, and make himſelf laugh'īāt. Mr. Wem. That's not it, he hopés to be the better by what is ſettled on the Boy. -ºſi Dodge. O, God's ſo, that's true: But never fear, I'll be hang'd if he carry it, for Tou have Money, as I told you, Sir, before: but ſee, Sir, there they are Mr. Wes. Yes, Yes, I ſaw them befork; but come, where's our wine? - " . * * * (Within) [the Bell rings as at the Bar. : : -ºº 2, . rt - Enter Drawr with a Battle ºf Wint. . . . . . . . o Train. Hère Sir,"—Coming, Coming, Sir : Philip, ſpeak up in the Mermaid, and bid jack light a Fire. . . . . [Exit Drawer. . . . . . comp. Well'Mr. Pettifºg, and what think you of my Suit, Sir 2, … , , . . . . Pett. Why look you Sir, the Defendant you know was arreſted firſt by a Latitat - in an Aćtion of Treſpaſs. " . . . - - - ... ." Comp. Yes, and a Lawyer tºld me, it ſhou'd have been an Aćtion of the Caſe, did he not. Wife? - -----" -- - - - - - - - F.' I have no Skill in the Lawygu know Husband, but the Gentleman did ſay ſo. Feit. Age, but your Aëtion .# Caſe in this Point is too tickliſh. comp. Well, but pray tell me, do you think I ſhall overthrow my Adyerſary? … Petr. Without all doubt, the Čhild he ſays is none of yours, What of that J mat- ºw awidow, and am by Conſequence poſſeſs'd of a Ward. Now ſhall not I have the Management of that Ward Now Sir you lie at a ſtronger Ward, for Partº ſºft y ºn, ſays the Civil Law . So that if you were within the Compaſs of the fourº mºnon Law goes, the Child muſt be yours, that's certain. ca,

Page 31

: The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. 31 1 comp. Say you’ſo, Sir, Why then the Child's my own, for I have been a Coaſter º: Years and mores and ſomy Service to you: [Drinks]. O your Attor- Heys is guild-hall have a rare time on’t, by the Lord Harry. - . . . . . . . . . ºf pag. They areas it wereboth Judgand.jury themſelves. . . . . . . . . ." camp. And O how they will º at their Clients when they ſit in a Tavern, and call them Fools, Blockheads and Coxcombs, and then whip up their Cauſes as nimbly as a Barbertrims his Cuſtomers on a Chriſtmas-Eve; a Snip, a Wipe and away. Pett. That's very common, you ſhall have the like at a Niſ rt. . . . * *** -- 1 --- ºrg. C Enter Drawer. . . . . . . . . . . .” - - - - - - - - - - -- --- - ---, *, * * * * Draw. Here's a Gentleman, one Mr. Juſtic; Merryman, enquires for Mr. Wenter: . the Merchant. . - - - * {1 - ... , Mr. Pen. Here Boy, deſire them to walk up. [Exit Drawer.1 °Tis my Brother, and a Counſeller, to make an End of this fathe Buſineſs. - . ; , ºr ** - : , ; ; -- . . - - - - - - - -- * * * - - - --- Enter juſtice Merryman and a Counſelor : Both Tables riſe and join together. | - - • * ... - . * * * º - Merr. Your Servant, Gentlemen, your Servant: Counſellor Blunder and I have been canvaſing the Buſineſs of this your Difference; and I believe, Brother, the Law will de- termine it as we have done; for it is point blank againſt you. Mr. Ven. If it is, I muſt be contented: Well Sir, the Child's your Wife's, and you ſhall have it; and to endear you the more to 't, I’ll ſettle my part of the Eſtate on you and yours for ever: Give me your Hand. . - [They ſhake Hands. We fiow are Friends. .2% º ºr ºf r: *** * *-*. " ". . . . Merr. Why that's well ſaid. … ". . . . . . . ºf ºººoººwºº Counſ. We all are Witneſs to the Agreement. * : *t ºr ºl ' ' ' ' ' ". . . Omnes. All, all. - Comp. Nay I ſcorn to be outdone in Civility; therefore if you pleaſe I have a Cal lonor two of Prize-Wine, and half a Dozen of good ſound Bruges-Capons, whic I'll treatyou and this good Company with at Supper; but no more Müttoh; no not lt. - - -- - Merr. Well Brother, I’m glad you’re Friends : Ods bobs I am. But come, let home now, and ſee what’s become of the Bride and Bridegroom': Farewel Friend farewell: Come we'll pay at the Bar... . . . . . . 7 . . . . - - [Exeunt Merr. AMr. Vent, and his Wiſ., Counſ, and Dod & comp. Come Peg, Come and kiſs me. [Compaſſe kiſſes Peg. I am Friends with thee too now. y Pett. Aye, aye, you have Reaſon, ſhe has earn'd you a good Fortune; and nec not venture to Sea any more; Yet one thing let me adviſe you, 'tis Counſel worth good Fee, for it cures Cuckoldom, , , - - - … . . . . . Comp. Sayſ thou ſo, come let's hear it. . . . ~~, ºf . , Pett. This it is, Make a flat Divorce between your ſelves, be you no longerh Husband, nor ſhe your Wife: Two or three Hours after meet again, ſalate, woo at wed afreſh, and ſo the baſe Name of Cuckold's blotted quite, "This has been ext; ºrienc'd and approved by many. - -, . ... " . " * * * * * * - tº a - rº-..
Page 32

3. The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. Comp, 'Tis excellent I faith,--There, there’s for you, and I thank you. Pºg, I renounce thee,_may and I renounce my ſelf too from thee; thou art now a Widow, Pºg: I’ll go hang my ſelf two or three Hours at one o' th' Main Yards, and ſo long thou ſhalt go drown thy ſelf. Then we'll meet in White-chappel-Fields, as it were by chance, and woo and wed again. . . . - Peg. With all my Heart, kind Sir, fare you well. - - Comp. Farewel Widow, remember Time and Place; and d'you hear, Put on your Sabbath-day beſt Clothes. +-- - Peg. I will, I will. -- [Exit Peg. Comp. Sir, I am beholding to you for your good Counſel. - Pett. No, Sir, you have paid me for 't, but I hope you do not intend to follow * your own. - Comp. What is that? Pett. Why, you ſaid you’d hangyour ſelf. . • . Comp. Nono, I have thought better on't, for Pllgo drink my ſelf dead drunk, *ē. wake again, waſh my Face, and meet the Bride. Pett. That’s well ſaid, and I'll accompany you, and wiſh you Joy. Comp, Joy, Sir, I have it Sir already, in a good Eſtate got by a Chopping Boy. . . . . . - - - - ºf EExcunt. s C E N E II. . . . - Enter Friendly ſolus. - - Fri, was ever Fortune like to this of mine? who for the Smile of a vile ſimple Wo- man, have ačted thus againſt my very Soul, all to pleaſe a Greature, whoſe next Com- mand perhaps will higher mount, it may be lighton my ſelf, as now it did on Bonvile. , - - ... a. Enter Clara, - * * * - - - tº ". r. . . i vº' ºl, * * cla. Ha! Friendly, here alone. Now, now, my Fears begin, [Aſide. So, Sir, you are return'd I ſee. [To him. Fri. Madam, I am, and like thoſe noble Knights in former times, after ſubduing all their Ladies Foes, returning with the joyful News of Conqueſt, receive her trem- bling to their longing Arms, and claim her as their own, ſo I Cia. What mean you, Sir 2 * , 21/ ... " Fri. Madam, You are obeyed, your hard Commands fulfilled ; at your Requeſt Pve kill'd my Friend, nay and my beſt of Friends. - Cla. How 2 kill'd your Friend for me. Fri. Indeed’tis true. - - - * ~ * cla. Then thou art truly wretched : But ſay, ſay quickly, who's this unhappy Man whom thy Miſtake hath thus untimely kill'd 2. - Fri, Bonvile, .* cla, Bowvile ſaid you? My Blood with an unuſual Courſe runs backward from my Heart! Horror has ſeiz'd my Soul! A thick black Miſt has overcaſt my Sight, and I - not the ſame: but ſpeak, O ſpeak again, Was it Romvile -- "Why ſhou'd you ſeek to iterate my Guilt, by a Rehearſal of that ‘. 2IIIe a
Page 33

!. him. ,-- * | * \ - \ \ - The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. 33 Name? Too ſure, alas !: it was: Bonvile's the Friend I've kill’d. - cla. Curs'd be the Tongue that ſpoke it, but doubly curs'd the Hand that did the * I barbarous Fa& • ' - - Fri. Why Madam, was it not your Command to kill my Friend; nay more, my beſt of Friends? Cla. Yes, and I thought my ſelf your beſt of Friends. Fri. I hope you wou'd not have had me murder'd you? Cla. No Monſter, no. - - Fri. Theſe are Riddles. Cla. Fool, our whole Sex is made of nothing elſe: Thou mayſt ſooner untie the Gordian Knot, expound the Problems of the monſtrous Sphynx, and read what is decreed in the myſterious Book of Fate, than unfold a Woman's ſly malitious Meaning. Fri. Very well; ſhe firſt ſet me on to do this moſt accurs'd of Deeds, and now up- an, Woman, Woman, dear deviliſh Woman, farewel. . [Offers to go. Cla. Stay Friendly, all I have ſaid was only to try your Conſtancy; and whether you'd repent of what you’ve done. But tell me truly, is Banvile ſurely dead? Fri. Indeed he is. - - - º Cla. 'Tis bravely done, and I adore thee for 't. By Heaven I love thee now, even unto Dotage 1 - - Fri. Was ever Change like this? The ſubtleſt Labyrinth Wit cou’d ere in- Aſide vent, affords not half ſo many Turnings as a Woman's Mind. : ſ What mean you, Madam, by this ſeeming Tranſport? Cla. O Friendly, Friendly, I am all o're Extaſy | Thou haſt done a Deed that ra. viſhes my Soul. At once thou haſt kill'd my dear and only Friend, and ſlain the fa- *. me; nay wou'd hang me for’t: Theſe are the Tricks of all her damning Sex. tal'ſt Enemy I had, Fri. What more Riddles Madam, pray explain your ſelf. * Cla. I will; I will declare a Secret which till now I never did diſcloſe: I lov'd that Bonvile whom thou now haſt ſlain, not as I ought to do, but with a Woman's Love, which he never did know : And Yeſterday when I beheld the fatal Marriage ended, then like a Merchant walking on the Downes, ſees a rich Weſſel of his own engaged, and after took, and born away a Prize: So I, after I’d ſeen my Bonvile loſt, (for ſo he was to me) reſuming all the Malice of a Woman, reſolved never to entertain one Thought of Love again; but lead a Life as Lapland. Witches do, only on others Ruines: Then when you approached me with the hateful Sound of Love, to daſh your Hopes, and put a Period to your growing Paſſion, I bid you kill your beſt and deareſt Friend ? / Fri. True. S - - cla. Now the beſt Friend to one in Love, is Love it ſelf. Fri. O my curs'd Stars, that wrap'd me up in ſuch a black Miſtake, What have I: done 2 - - Cla. Done ! Why you have done bravely, why do you tremble 2 Fri. An inward Guilt lies heavy on my Soul, and Horror with all her dreadful Forms ſtill haunts my Sight. And did you love this Bonvile f - * Cla. The Queen of Beauty never doted more on her beloved Adonis than I on Fri. And now as much you hate him ; othe unheard-of Inconſtancy of Women? All that they have is feign'd ; their Teeth, their Hair, their Bluſhes, and their Crºn; re.
Page 34

// - - - ... " º 34 The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. Smiles may their very Conſcience (if any ſuch they haveji is feign'd ; all counterfei and falſº: Lêt them waſh, patch and daub themſelves §º. Héliº for Natu : that Art cou'de're invent, ſtill they are Women: And let’em rob all India of its ſtore to adorn themſelves therewith, ſtill are they not all that thingtail'd woman: I know not what to do, for I love and hate this Creature both at on º: Cla. What ails my Friendly? Sº 3 - *- - * -- - - Fri. But Bonvile yet muſt feel his Enemies Rage; ſhall he ſucceed in Love, whilſt I am croſs'd in mine? No, it muſt not, cannot, nay it ſhall not be.….. . . . " - - - - --- ºr - - - .22%hiº. , ' , , ; , . • * * * "Four Head, I have, *o make a Plot not commºn; tıo * * * * * *44alice, Revenge, fhedevil, and a Woman, bit" . . . ... : *. 1. - 1, … -- - . tº ** : y : 2 [offers to go. Cla. What will you leave methen? . . . . . . .” ‘’ ºn tº . . . - * Fri. Leave thee; yes, for ever: Fly thee as 1 wou’d a Blaſt from Hell. T ºt! thy ſelf a Hell; thy baſe deteſted hateful Woman's Breathiaſetts the pureſt Airtº - - - * * . . . . ~ : i , , , * - - * Aſay my Friend's Blood, which I for thee have ſpilt, … Light on thy Head, and your’s be all the Guilt. - ". . . . . . . . . . " . . - - * ... . . . ; lºo!: . [Ewan ſeverally. Enter Compaſſ; new clothed. Pettifog, and two or three Men Neighbours. 2 * * * ~ * , , , , ; , , Yis - Comp. Gentlemen and Neighbours, as you have been Witneſſes to our Divorce, ſo fallye now be Evidences to our next Meeting, which I look for every Minute. 1ſt Neigh. I came for that Intent, Neighbour. tº: º ". . . . . Comp. I thank you : well, I do not think but you'll all ſee me come off with as ſmooth a Forehead, and make my Wife as honeſt a Woman as a Man wou’d deſire ſometimes, I mean of her Rank; and a teeming Woman, as you know ſhe has been : Nay, I do not think but the Child too will be found to be as lawful a Child as any Couple of un- married People can beget. - - 2d Neigh. We long to ſee it Neighbour Compaſſe, that ſo ſome of us may do the like upon the ſame occaſion. - Comp. You're in the right, old Stitch of the World: But ſoft, ſee where ſhe comes with a whole Bundle of as good ſound Maidens as her ſelf. - … . . .” - . . Enter Peg new cloth'd, with three or four Women Neighbours. Stand aſide a little, and mind me I pray. - - Omnes. Agreed, agreed. - Comp. Good Morrow fair Maid. - - ...” Peg. In truth Sir you are miſtaken in both, for I am neither fair, nor yet a Maid. Comp. No, what are you then I pray, a Wife? . . . . Peg. That indeed I was, but alas, 1 am now a Widow. Comp. A Widow ſay you? Nay then I muſt make bold with you; for look you, your Caſe is ſomewhat like mine, I being a Husband without a Wife. - 1ſt Neigh. Aye marry, this is ſomething like. - Pett. They begin well, let them gó on. , Camº.
Page 35

-" -* - - The City.Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. 35 comp. How long have you been a Widow, good Woman ?'Nay pray do not weep oth. - tº: I can’t chooſe but cry, to think of the great Loſs I had. - câmp. why, was he an honeſt Man 2 - Pºg. Honeſt quotha', Ivow and proteſt he was ashoneſt a Man as ere broke Bread. O I ſhall never have ſuch another. [Cries out. comp. By my Faith now Miſtreſsyou have had a great Loſs indeed, for an honeſt Man is not to be found every where, nor in every Street. Pett. The Rogue's witty', 2d Neigh. Aye, aye, let 'em go on. - - comp. And how long is it ſince you loſt this honeſt Husband 2 w Peg. Odear, his Memory is too freſh; and the Sight of you doubles my Sorrow. camp. The Sight of me, ſay you; why, was he ſo like me? ... . - eg. As one Apple to another; your two Hands are not more alike. mp. Nay then I cannot blame thee to weep: An honeſt Man he was I warrant and you have had a mighty Loſs, that’s the Truth on’t : But was he propor- tioned like me, ſo well limb'd, and of ſuch a wholeſom Complexion, heh Peg. No Twins were ever more alike. camp. well I love, his Memory is ſtill better and better: and how many Children did he leave behind him 2 - - Peg. Only one, Sir. . . . . comp. A Boy or a Girl --- Peg. Adainty fine Boy; Sir, ... - - - - - - - - Comp. Juſt my own caſe ſtill; my Wife (reſt her Soul) left mea Boy too, a luſty chopping Boy of his Age (as they tell me,' for 1 neverſaw it), Peg. So is mine. - . . . . comp. And what Profeſſion was your Husband of? - Peg. A Seaman. - ºr . comp. Heigh! my own Faculty too! And can you like a Man of that Profeſſion again? - - -- - ----- *. Yes ſurely, for his dear ſake, whom I lov’d ſo tenderly, I ſhall always eſteem a Sailer. - * : comp. Shall you ſo? why then here's your Man: What ſay you, isºt a Match? Peg. Dear me, I am ſo aſhamed, and yet to ſpeak the Truth, I do like you hugely, and wou’d like you better ſtill, if it were not for one thing, which a little troubles me, Comp. What's that ? -- * . . . . . - Peg. Why, you know ſometimes we are forc’d to endure the Abſence of our Huſ. , bands a long while, mehappen many Years, and then if there be any Slip in us, (as long Vacations will make Lawyers hungry) the World is apt to cenſure and ſcandalize us; and brand us with wanton Living and, Incontinency 3 when alas ! if they wou'd but conſider our Condition, and the mighty Longings we often naturally have for Fleſh and Blood, they wou'd not blame us, ſo they wou’d not.' ' . ... f. Comp. Come, come, no Matter, canſt thou love me, Widow 2 Pig. Ah, if i durſt but ſpeak my Mind, I know what I wou'd ſay. Comp. Durſt, why who do you fear 2 here’s none but an honeſt Gentleman, ſome few Friends and Neighbours; let them hear a God’s Name what you wou'd ſay, and never bluſh for the Matter. º . . . * * r * * * - * - - - - - * … * **, * ; ; , , , º, ºr, -- * 19 W.
Page 36

36 The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. 1ſt W. Neigh. Aye, aye, ſpeak Neighbour, pray ſpeak your Mind, and fear not. Peg. I ſhall be thought too weak to yield at firſt Sight. 2d W. Neigh. Paw ſpaw that's only Nicety. Peg. Well then I do love him dearly and dearly, ſo I do. Comp. And I thee with all my Heart and Soul. LRuns and He him. [Comp, kiſſes Peg. Now we'll be merry, and have a Song, ſhall we not my Neighbours? 3d Neigh, Marry willwe, Neighbour Luff and Mrs. Bride, will ye give us a Song? Peg. With all my Heart, come Neighbour. Man: & Woman: 3 1ſan : Woman: « A DIALOG U E. [Faith and Troth I love thee dearly, The I do but bluntly woo, Prithy then reſolve me clearly, ther I am beloved by you. Long Iſhall not keep a pother, ..] ... Like a ſenſeleſ, whining Bran 5 If you won't I’ll court another Who mill never ſay me no. < --- ſPriend, your ſelf, nor Humour neither With my Fancy diſagree, Tet I muſt find clearer Weather, Er'e I venture out to Sea. Court another at your Pleaſure, Win her in the Hony-moon, She may chance repent at leiſure, For believing you too ſoon. |- fleave your damn'd Fantaſtick Triair, Which procure a Love's Pain, Pox, upon theſe ſham-Denial, 'Tis but ſpending time in vain. With Embraces happy make me, Nature fram'd you to be kind; Kiſt me, and the Devil take me If leur change my Mind. [I’ll purſue the good old Faſhion, Pratīiſ; ſtilly thoſe are piſt, Throughly try my Lover's ; E’re I let him graſp the Prize. Spite of Oaths you wou'd fºrſake me, Shos'd I let you once embrace : If I kiſs, the Devil take me, Till the Parſºn haſ ſaid Gract. ! - - - - ------ ...*.*.* Cho.
Page 37

--T \ , The City Bride : Or, the Merry Cuckold, 37 ------- - - - - -------Chºrus, - - -- - - ºne, then the Natiºn * * ! #4 madtºft 'a, Kaſhion, , tº, ſº fºr ºilº, ºniº, in the Mind. ~ “A. But it is º slavery, and Priſºly. Knavery, "… “º . That Parſons mºſt conjare e're £ever, be kind, *----. , - " - * -- tº ". . . . - º gam, Se, ſo, here º we be Man and Wife again to Morrow, as goad gº eyer, What thé we fast as Strangers, we may happen to love he're the worſ, for aſ that—eigentlemen and Neighbours, invite ye all to my Wedding, ... gimnel, We'l not fail yolk and with yºu Joy.' ..., "ºom, Didiotſ tell 3. that I would fetch it eleyerly off? ©4 et any Man call me Cuckold if he dares now, - Petri. 'Tis ſlander in him aſſire you who ever does, - £am, Nay it will be Fetti Laeruary at leaſt, and witheut Compaſs of the General Pardon too? And for the Child, leſſ the hear his that dares ſay, 1 am not the Father, Petti, Surs hºne will dare diſpute it, - £am. Gr that my Wife that is to be, is Hot 35 heaett & Wºłł41, sºbbie ether Mers Wives are, - * Petti, No queſtion ºf that, - W £om. Ó he w fine and ſmººth any Bºgws ars h9W - º i A4. Neigh. Age but when you're garried, they'll gains tº themſelves again; war, rant ye, - * - £on. My friends, if you pleaf, you say call the Me, Bridegreeth hew, for ths Gueſts are à!! bidden to the W&gding: - - Af, Neigh, we knºw it, Mr. Bidegrgoſh, they are indeed, and we'ſ Het fail yºu ºpen our Words. - - €ship, flame thºu, brik Widºw, fºre the best Etº aud Tids, * * ty?ridºrsa, and then ſhºt be a brid, - Jºhn't gºne tº . The End ºf the Fourth A&T. --- --- - -------- -- **-tierrºr-rºtºtrºr:rºr:***-tºº-º-º-º-º-º-ºrrºrt...sºr is….--------...-a, G Act
Page 38

T---____- - - 38 Tº City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. —al -T- - a rais. A C T the Fifth. - sº ... ." *** * * *. .*. Enter Arabella on one Side... . . . . . - -: sº -- a- A * * * * , * * -- ***. a .3 - Summerfield meeting her from the other. Tº - * tº - ..." ,, . . . . . . . - Ara. R. Summerfield, I now am truly happy, my Prayers at laſt are heard; and Heaven has reſtored my Husband to my Arms. " * - " - ". . . Sum. I juſt now heard the joyful News, and thought to have been myſelf the wel- com; Meſſenger of his Return, but find I’me come too late; have you ſeen him?” e. Ara. No 3 as yet I have not. - - Sum. 'Tis ſomewhat ſtrange | - -, *-iy º 4:4. Others perhaps may judgit ſo, but my uncommon Joy for his Return, admits no other Thought, but thoſe of Tranſport for his Safety. Sam. O happy Bonvile How I admire and wonder at thy Choice Enter Friendly. Madam, a Wife like you, exceeds the greateſt Bleſfing ſure on Earth. Fr. The neareſt way to a ſecure Revenge, is private Malice, which, likel a Spark long lying hid amongſt neglected Aſhes, by the leaſt Blaſt of Wind becomes it ſelf a Flame—Ha! who have we here 2 Thrice bleſt Occaſion | which thus have offered me at once the Scope of my revengeful Wiſhes. Tis Arabella and her Darling Summerfield, one who, in the Bridegroom's Abſence, > is grown thus intimate with his beloved Bride. A ſtrong Foundation on which I’ll now creſt a brave Revenge; I’ll ſtep aſide and obſerve them. . - [Retires to one ſide of the Stage.j Aſide. Ara. Sir, I hope he’ll ſoon be here, and return the Kindneſs you have ſhown me; ſo I take my leave, with hourly expectation of a much-long'd for Husband. - Sam. And I, with a Gratitude never to be forgotten, kiſs your fair Hand, and hope that all things will anſwer your Expºtation. [Exit Arabella. - Fri, Ay, 'tis ſo, now muſt i counterfeit a friendly Face to make a farther Diſ-, covery. [Aſide. - - Sir, your humble Servant: without Offence, may I be ſo bold as to beg the Favour of . your Name * - - - Sum. The Queſtion I muſt confeſs is ſomewhat familiar, and in my Opinion im- proper for a Sºranger at firſt ſight; but yet I ne're diſown'd it to a Gentleman — 'tis Summerfield. - - Fri. Summerfield Sir, I kiſs your Hands; and muſt congratulate your good Suc. ceſs, but more admire your Valour. Had we many ſuch nobie Commanders on board " Fleet, we need not fear it where e're it ſails. – iſ Sum.
Page 39

** : * - ... *, + - -, - - - The City-Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold. 3 sum. Pray, Sir, ſtretch not your Love into Flattery, 'twill make me then ſuſpect your Kindneſs. And the Author of this Story was too much my Friend I ſee, ſince he has given you this ſo very partial Account, the more to augment my Fame. Fri, o that's your Modeſty, Sir: But if I might be ſo happy as to be honour'd with your Acquaintance— - - "suſ, Sir, the Honour (if any) would be wholly on my Side; therefore I deſic to know your Name. • . . . . . . . - . . - . . . . . . * -- . 1 - - Fri. Friendly, Sir. tº re - " - * : . . . . -sun. An Acquintance, f ſuppoſe, of Mr. Bantile's.". • *- Fri. One that thinks himſelf much honour’d in being ſtiled his Friend. Sum. I have often heard your Name indeed before 3 but till now Fortune never aſ- ſorded me the ſight of you. - - - - - - Fri. You of all Menought to bleſs Fortune, who ſtill has been indulgent to you on all Occaſions; and ſcatter'd her Favours on you, with as prodigala Hand as tho you were her ſole Care and only Minion." - - Sum. What mean you, Sir Again you exceed the Bounds of Love and Friend- ---, - tº ſhip; I never thought any of Bonvil's Friends cou’d be guilty of ſo baſe and vile a thing as Flattery : But, pray, unfold your meaning. . . . . . . . . . - * * Fri. #. *I juſt 1. ſaw you part with the Bride, with ſuch courteous Ati- ons, as ſpoke no ſmall Eſteem in her kind Favour; and, therein. I think you the bap- pieſt of Men. . . . " - - - - - - - - * Sum. Ho ! . . . . . . . . . . . . ! . . . . . . . -- . . . . . . . . . Fri. Miº me not, I only as a Friend applaud your Happineſ, blºſs the Influ- ence of your kinder Stars, and praiſe your Fortune that hath given yet this ſweet Occaſion. ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' - . . . . . . Sum. What Occaſion, Sir 2 . . . . . . . . . . . sº, ... . . . . Fri. Of being ſerviceable to the fair Virgin Bride in her extreameſt need, after her being ſo ...; nay, on her Wedding Day, by an ungrateful Husband, in do-, ing her thoſe neglected Duties, her Youth and Beauty juſtly did demand. . . . Sum. On my Life ſome Plot againſt the Bride: I’ll ſound him 'till I find the very Bottom [Aſide.]—Sir, you are merry: But ſuppoſe the Caſe your own, wou'd you have miſs'd ſo tempting an Occaſion ? . . . . . . . Fri. No, Sir, they’re too precious to be omitted: But I hear you two call Couſins, comes your Kindred by the Merryman’s or the Bonvile's 2 - Sum. Neither we were wholly Strangers’till of late, and 'tis a word of Courteſy only interchang'd between us for ſome private Reāſons. Fri. This goes as I cou’d wiſh. [Aſide.] - - - . . Sam. I deſire you not to grow too inward with me, on ſo ſhort an Acquaintance : Not that I'de have you think the Lady of ſo baſe a Diſpoſition to grant me any thing beyond the Rules of Decency and Honour. The only Favour ſe’re receiv'd from her, was a Preſent of thoſe Bracelets ſhe wears about her Arms, and that Chain of Gold and Pearl ſhe has about her Neck; all which either of us may own without a Buſh. - Fri. How, the Chain and Bracelet, ſay you ! Thoſe were the firſt Tokens of her - - Husband’s Love. - ºf 45.2): Sum. Methinks you look concern’d at what I’ve ſaid; yet I have ſaid no more than what I am C liged in Honour to maintain, and will ; therefore I hope, as you’r a Gen- tlann an or turn Informer. -

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 40

Pri. Opray think not ſo poorly of me. -- Enter a servant who whiſpers Summerfield. Sum. Tell her I'le wait on her immediately. [Exit Servant. Sir, ſome Buſineſs of Importance calls me hence; therefore ſome other time I hope I ſhall have the Happineſs of enjoying your Company longer. [Exit Sum. Fri. Sir, your humble Servant. *- - Tell her I'll wait on her immediately, ſaid he , this muſt be Arabella that he's going to : Better ſtill. - - The Work’s begun, now I am made or loſt; - He runs the beſt who holds out to the Poſt': - 4nd all the Comfort in Adverſity, It to ſee others as miſerable as me. Who have we here 2 Old Merryman As I live ’tis he - *. Enter juſtice Merryman. Mer. O Maſter Friendly, you're happily returned : But where's my Son-in-Law 2 Fri. Alas, Sir, the unhappy Bonvile is— - Azer. Is, is, what is he 3 Heh ſpeak , is he living, or is he dead; or what's be- come of him? Fri. O! that I had the Marble Niobes Heart! Or that I had ſuck’d the Milk of Wolves and Tigers; ſo that I might have told, without the leaſt remorſe of Sorrow, what now I dare not, nay, I cannot ſpeak, for fear at once I melt my ſelf in Tears, and break your aged Heart. [Seems to weep. - - - Aſer. Then I ſuppoſe he’s killed 3 ſay, is he not? Haſt thou inticed him from his Bride for this, thou inhumane Wretch Yet ſpeak, and tell me truly, for I'm prepa- red to hear the worſt of Ills; Is he then ſlain 2 - Fri. No, Sir, but dangerouſly wounded. - Aſer. Not mortally, I hope; but whereabouts is he ſo deſperately wounded? In his Arms, his Legs, or Body ? - - - Fri. Neither, Sir, but in as perfeót Health as when he left you. A4er. Strange! ſure thou art all o're a Myſtery, and form'ſt theſe Riddles to try my Wit. º, No, Sir, for all I have ſaid, you in effect will ſurely find I told you he was wounded, did I not? A4r. Yes, you did. Fri. And ſo he is. Mer. But where, where about, I ask you once again 2 Fri. I ſee you force the unwilling Secret from me—Why, he's wounded. Mer. He’s wounded, he’s wounded; but where, where is he wounded ? Fri. In his Fame, Honour and Reputation, more mortal than a thouſand fleſhy Wounds. For ſuch ſlight Baubles, Cures are of obtain’d ; But injur’d Honour ne’re can be regain'd. - - Aſſex --- 1 - - -
Page 41

* | - -- - \. The City-Bride ; or, the Merry Cuckold. , 4 Mer. How ! how ! how’s this 1 wounded in his Honour, ſay'ſt thou? Tell me the Villain that has defam'd him, and this good old Sword ſhall ſlit the Raſcal's Wind- 1DC. - - Pº, O, Sir, your Daughter, your Daughter, Sir Mer, Ha! what’s that ? what’s that 2 is ſhe injur’d too 2 Fri, No, no Sir, my falling Tears quite drown my feeble Voice, I cannot utter what I fain would ſpeak——Your Daughter's falſe, falſe to her Bonvile ! And by the help of her beloved Summerfield, has robb'd my Friend of all he cou’d call Dear, I mean his Fame. [Seems to weep. - * AMer. A Pox o' your Crocodile's Tears. Why, Sirrah, Sirrah, do you call my Daughter Whore ? Hey, Swords and Daggers, Blunderbuſſes and Piſtols, ſhall I bear this 2 Hark you, you my Friend, and no Friend, what a Kin do you take me to be to this Gentlewoman, Heh 2 - - Fri. Her Father, Sir, AMer. Audacious Villain, O that I had thee in ſome private Corner, where none cou’d either ſee or hear us, this Sword ſhou’d juſtify my Daughter's Honour; I'de Whore you with a Pox to you, ſo I wou’d. Fri. Your Pardon, Sir, I only did inform you as a Friend, that by your fatherly Admonitions, you might refrain her from her undecent Courſe. Mer. Pox o' your friendly Intelligence. Fri. The Jewels which her Husband did preſent her, as the firſt Sign and Confir- mation of the happy Contračt, ſhe to my certain Knowledg has given to— º To whom, to whom thou wicked Slanderer 2 tell me, Sarrah, quickly, quick, quick. Fri. To Summerfield. - Mer. Ha, ha, ha, the Fool makes me laugh; Ha, ha, ha, why ’twas but juſt now that I ſaw e”m on her Neck and Arms. Fri. She was no Woman, had ſhe not the Senſe to get them againſt her Husband's coming. w - Mer. But pray tell me, how is't poſſible that ſhe cou’d part with elm, when they are lock’t on, and the Key with her Husband 2 - Fri. O, Sir, that's no Queſtion to be ask’d in theſe Times : Women have found a way to make uſe of other Keys beſides their Husbands : And no doubt but Summerfield has got a Key will open your Daughter's Lock as well as Bonvile’s. A4ir. Sirrah you lie, you lie Sirrah ; and I’le tell thee thou ly'ſt, again and again, ſo I will. Nay, and I were to pay a 1 co Pounds for every Lie I give thee, as Men do Twelve-pence for every Oath they ſwear, I wou’d ſpend all the Thouſands I am worth, in giving thee the Lie. 'Tis likely indeed, that ſuch a brave Gentleman as Summerfield, that fought at Sea like a Dragon to ſave my Life, ſhould ſhorten my Days on Land in ruining my Daughter; therefore once more I tell you you Lie. Fri. 'Tis very well. 44er. Do you hear Sir, have you told this Lie to any body elſe but me 2 Fri. I am no Informer, Sir. - - - Mer. Why then for fear you ſhould, doiye ſee, draw, [Draws] Draw, I ſay, I am not ſo old but I can make a ſhift to cut your Throat ſtill ; I'le ſpoil you: Cackling I'le warrant ye. * Enter
Page 42

- 4. Tº city Bide: 0, the Merry Cuckold. Enter Bonvile and Clara. A pox on’t, here’s my Son-in-Law come to hinder me, Duce take him cou’d he not ſtay a little longer ? D'ye hear Sir, begon, leave this Place immediately, or l’le— !’le—I’le—Gad I cou’d find in my Heart, ſo I cou’d, but be gone. - Fri. Bonvile here with Clara too, excellent. This goes to Arabella, and may it encreaſe the Storm. . . [Exit Frie. - . . . . . Bon. My Father in Anger. - . . . " - - Aſer. O Son, Son, Son dear Boy, welcome home, Od’s bobs you are. Bon. I humbly thank you, Sir ; but am ſorry to ſee you ſo diſturb’d. Mr. Nothing, nothing, only Mr. Freindly and I have had a Word or two, that's all, that’s all. - - - - - Bon. About my going with him, I ſuppoſe ; but that's paſt, and I hope, Sir, you'l be ſo kind as at my Requeſt to pardon him. - - A4er. Indeed Son it was ſomething elſe; By the Lord Harry I can't forbear laugh- | ing at the Coxcomb, Ha, ha, ha§ He told me, Ha, ha, ha, that one Summerfield, a ' very honeſt Fellow as ever liv'd, is grown exceeding familiar with my Daughter, . . your Wife. - - - - | ". . . Bon. Ha! my Wife. - - - Mer. Yes, your Wife, and that he had received Love-Tokens from her. Bon. How, Love-Token from her Aſer. Aye, aye, Love-Tokens I call'd 'em when I was a young Man: Nay, the Rogue was ſo impudent to tell me, that ſhe had given him thoſe Jewels which are lock’d about her Neck; Ha, ha, ha. - - Bon. The Jewels about her Neck, ſaid you? - - - - Mer. Aye, what ails you Man that you change Colour ſo? 'Tis all a Lie Boy I warrant thee: And hadſt thou not comé juſt in the Nick of Time, I think o' my Con- ſcience I ſhou’d have cut his Throat. - - Bon. As I will your Daughters if I find her falſe : Death, Hell, and Furies, am I made a Monſter already ? - . . . - Cla. What, Sir, are you return'd for this 2 .. : - Aſer, Harky'Son, härk you; ſuppoſe that this Mr. Friendly ſhou'd have a ſecret Inclination to your Spouſe, d’ye ſee , and therefore, by reaſon he can’t obtain his De- fire, poſſeſſes you with Jealouſy to make a Breach 'twixt you and your Wife. Od’s . bobs, I don't know, I can’t tell what ſhou’d be the meaning of his carrying you away on your Wedding-Day elſe, heh, Son, heh. Cla. Has the Italian Plague then infected you, that you ſtand thus unmov’d 2 Enter Summerfield leading Arabella. * . . A - But ſee here's your Bride. - Bon. And her beloved. Adulterer with her! Death and Damnation, muſt I ſtand ſtill and ſee this 2 - AMer. Hey day ! what the Matter now 2 - - Ara, Bonvile here with Clara! Alas too true I find what before I ſcarce dar'd to t ſo. Is Bonvile then a Traitor, and falſe to Arabella [Aſide, l Cla.
Page 43

* * The City-Bride: 0, the Merry Cuckold. 43 cla. Madam, at laſt Pve found the pretious Jewel that you ſo long have ſought in vain. * [To Arab., - - - Ara. Wear it your ſelf Madam, Floſt it, and it muſt be mine no more. Cla. What means this ſudden Alteration? - Mer, Ods bodikins, as you ſay, what does ſhe mean? Are ye both mad, heh? Sum. Sir, I’m come to pay my Reſpečts to you, and humbly beg a farther Know- ledg of - #. Of whom, ſweet Sir, my Wife or me? Sum. Ha! your Wife. Bon. Yes Sir, my Wife, I think the word needs no explaining. Mer. Pray, Sir, at my Requeſt bear with him, he's ſtrangely out of Order I aſ- ſure you. * , , - - Bon. The Jewels are as I left 'em ; but the Jewel of her Heart is loſt and thrown away.—Madam, I ſent you my Will, did you receive it. - Ara. Yes, I did. Rom. Let me ſee it. Ara. You ſhall. [Exit. Ara. Bon. Sir, I deſire a Word or two in private with you, [to Summer. Sum. With all my Heart, Sir. - - Mer. What's that, what's that, I'll have no Whiſpering, Gentlemen. Enter Arabella with the Will. Ara. There's your Will, Sir. — [Throws it dorm, Bonvile takes it up. . Bon. 'Tis well now as you've chang'd your Mind, I’ll change this too, and find another to ſupply your Place: There's no harm done, the Marriage is not yet coli- ſummated, and you are free to enjoy any, ſo am I. Ara. As you pleaſe for that: A Man may make a Garment for the Moon, count all the Stars which twinckle in the Skies, or empty the vaſt Ocean, Drop by Drop, ſooner than pleaſe a Mind ſo light, ſo various as yours. Mer. Ods bobs, what's this you talk of, altering your Will 2 Bon. Yes, Sir, I am ſo reſolved, and will ſee 't perform'd within this Hour: My Lawyer lives hard by, and ſo farewel. [Exit. Bon. Mer. Farewel thou peewiſh Boy, I can alter my Will too ſo I can, marry can I; I had left him zoooo Pound after my Death, and he ſhall ſee I can find another Exe- cutor too. Within this Hour did he ſay, Gad I'll be with one as ſoon as he, unleſs he rides Poſt to the Devil, and that’s the neareſt way to a Lawyer. -- Sum. I’ll follow him, and aſſwage his Paſſion. Mer. By no means, Sir.--—But now I thinkon't, I’ll go with you, and find him Out: But did you ever ſee the like, did you ever ſee the like 2 Come Sir, come follow Ine. [Exit. Merr. & Summer. Cla. Dear Arabella, what can all this mean 2 - Ara, Can you be doubtful of the Effect, who are your ſelf the Cauſe 2 Cla. I the Cauſe, Inform me how 2 , 4r4. O Clara, Clara, your Syrens Voice has drawn my Bonvile from theſe ſpotleſs Virgins Arms, and made me ever wretched . *-
Page 44

º - - * - - - - *- - - 4. The City.Bride: Or, the Merry Cuckold, Cla. Who (if thou ever lov'dſt me, as once you caus'd me to believe you did) has tax'd me with a Crime ſo foul, as I abhor to hear it only named --fra, Friendly. - - Cla. O Arabella, forgive and pity me, who am indeed thc innocent unhappy Cauſe of all thoſe Griefs which now affiº you both which I'll relate in brief, if you. will pleaſe to withdraw one Moment with me. Ara. With all my Heart. Cla. Come then : And ſince your Ruine I did firſt conſpire, I'll all appeaſe ; thu, Fire's expedia by Fire, , - - Exehnt, - Enter juſtice Merryman and Summerfield, Mer. Sir, do you take me for your Friend? Šum. Why dº you ask me ſuch a Queſtion, Sir 'twere baſe Ingratitude to enter. tain any other Thought. , B 4. Why then d’ye ſee, Sir ; as you are my Friend, you muſt not fight my son Jattle. - Sum. Not fight him Sir you amaze me. Mer. Aye, aye, aye that's all one : I underſtand your dumb Signs and your low Whiſpers, the French Mode all over, to ſmile and grin a Man in the Face, and at the ſame time privately cut his Throat. Therefore prithe be ruled by me, and don't fight him, for ſhou'd you kill him, my poor Girl wou'd break her Heart, quite break her Heart." [Sobs and cries.] I grant that you are wrong'd, and ſo I dare ſwear is my dear Child: but he's her Husband, and muſt be born with, ods bobs he mºſt. Sum. Heaven be my Witneſs, I ne're entertain’d a Thought like it ! Alſer. That's well, that's well, I am heartily glad on 't, cds bobs I am heartily glad. - [Enter Friendly. 8st here comes one that has made all this Miſchief; and him I'll fight my ſelf for all I'm a Juſtice of the Peace. Come, come, Sir, Draw, draw ; you'll belie my Daugh- ter again will you? Come, draw, I ſay, Draw. LDraws, - - Fri. Sir, as I am a Gentleman, I ſcorn to deny my Words, but there's my Author, whether good or ill. Afer. Who, he He, doye mean him? Fri. Yes, Sir. - sum. True, Sir, I am j. For at his Return to Town from Barn. Elms, it was my Chance to meet him ; and after a ceremonious Complement or two, I found him diving into my private Thoughts concerning the Bride your Daughter: I, not to be behind-hand with him, join'd Wit with Wit to ſound his ſhallow Soul. I told him then, how her Jewels once were mine; but the manner of my obtaining them, I for my ºwn ſake did conceal from him; and now, if you 're diſpoſed, I'll here re- - life it. Jºrºr
Page Scan 57

- - - - - *- . The City, Bride: 0, . --- .*...* **, * * ***. Enter Bonvile leading Awabella, Clarãends gs ºn tº ºvº Mer. Let it be before all this Campany th too ſolowing again? Nay then at 'swell, odsº bobs they ſhall. *** --> tº ºf , º, º - Hon. I have heard the Story, Sir, already an Enemies in War take all Occaſions to undo each ot. I’ll be generous ſtill, and make you * of #. º: “. ....t.c. : : - . To Clara.] e, Madam, refeive this worthier Onºf yout Friendly, whom I know you both dmiréahd |...} hy [&#ves ... Friendly." Friendly, IIl Next ſmuſt obtain your Pardon for * ... al., 2 Sun. Sir, 'tis what I #######ººk.” that the World may’nt tax this innocent Lady of a Crime to her pureſt Thoughts unknown, I'll here begin my Story from my firſt Acquaintance pathishºppy Hours J C ~ * Mer, Prithy do. - * * * . . . .."." ºxx' -, º *: ". ; : " ..." Y. sum, the firſt time that e're tºº, #: have rºdłº, Mr. Ah Rogue! What, a Thief, a ſhief, hºw º: her of 2 Sum. Not her Honoº. ; but only of *Jewels which ſhe Wears. tº ºso" sº, sº tº . , º, º 'ye Mr. Ods bobs, thou wer’taphoneſt. Thief for that I faith he was . . . . . sum. They being faſt, I cou’d not get 'em off without ſome Harm and Pain to her . which for the Indies I’d not have done, And ſhe, in anſwer to my. Civility, brought me home, and ranſom'd them with the fuſiº. in § with whichi made my Venture) and the more to hide my Shaºlº ſh § dºme with the Title of her Kinſman. .v.sº sº; sº sº *-* * * * * v- a “º Mr. Ay, ay, and ſo ſhe mightwell; fºr ſhe was a little cunning Thief too, to ſteal the Gold ſhe gave you from her. Husband; 'ttias all his now, but that’s no mat- ******** - Sum. The reſt you know alreadyºtipº, ; , ºesº ( , ; , ", , , " : Mer. Ay, ſo I do, ods bobs I ſº thy Valour my brave Boy, thy Valour, for which I'll do for thee, that thouſalt never need to rob again I warrant thee; ods bobs i will. But come, come, we loſe time, for we have another Wedding yet to ſee perform’d, but that ſhall be done within. . . . . . . . . , *, * : * * * * * J , , ºr ". . . . . . .” Sum. Then farewel all ye treacherous Pathſ of Kice; . . . . . . . . Which lead Men blindfold to their End, , , , , , , - In time like me repent you that are wiſe, - - And by Reſtraint your vicious Courſes end Ara War, Iwanºf Havini, greaft hiſ ſº " on E.th, it cou’d beſtow not one like this. . . . . . . . . . After a Storm the Sun ſtill ſhines moſt bright, … . - ºdnd from the Chaos ſprung the purer £ºm. - , Swººs vºs.” “* * * * - - * * * - * > *, * : * * * * * * - - H." * º -- ºn ºn - - *** | *** - \
Page Scan 58

-- - - * º 2. never been, *fºre were ſeen. - ay Overthrow, 4 ware now, ºil 'i ºf my Days Pll; * . . . . . . . ºft I miſtake my Friend. - - º, tº Cº.; * - --- * r - - t — ~– * . . .] go” ºr, h :1: ... fl ºz o. . . . * - ſº- • * +------- i. . . .” --- º . spoke by the City-Bride. tº flºº; ; , !" or gº. 2 s a tº - Ov met withgood Intention to be witty, And rally the Grave Cuckolds of the City; . . But diſappointed of your #; . . . . . . I in your Looks can read the Play's Dan Lord! how ye ſtare to find an honeſt Bride, A thing you thinka Monſtee in Cheapſide. Whither you boaſt that you ſo often come, -- Tet 'tis no little Comfort t'u, howe're, ~~~~ - * 2 - “a 1 * r * is is . . . ; -- - * ~ * -- : , T: ; ; 2. ". ...º . . . . …?" - - - - * . . . . . * . . . … . . .'; . . .. v And leave your Footmen tº perform at home. . . . . . - Toa oftner bring th' Eſtate than get the Heir. vnjuſtly therefore you your Fortine blame, i. 6 ºf . , , ... She’s kinder to your Blood than to your Name. 3 After all this, I know you thinkit Pity," That I ſhou’d break the Cuſtom of the City: I hear a Beau cry, 'tis ſome damm'd Miſtaker; --- -- - º- - , , , - - ; : * - t E - I L O G u, E, ºf . * Merry Cuckold. - . * - i: , s: jù’ ºf tº * ,-- -o vi ji " . , N. … 1 - 1 : 10 - 3 -º . . . ." - - • * * - *s Weſt ºxiº lº to 4 sº, ºr 1.3.3 .*.*. `. - * :- . . . . 27 woº ſlyl iT was 2 - a .db : ot v. t. * - tº 2: .. * , ; Li ::\t, 30, is ! “ *** - A Cheap-ſide Vertue, City-Cuckold maker. . . . . . ud wº ºf .3. This is a Fault no Gentleman can pardon, It gives Cheapſide the Sins of Covent-Garden: wº We muſt refine on Vice, and take new Meaſures;..." { since inlihain'a Citi invade our darling pºſirº Take w Advice, employ at home year Bººks, v vºn This Cuckolding to you’s a loſing Trade," That pay for making, and for being wade." The Ladies wif my Charader excuſe, 4nd not condemn a Vertue which they uſe. Or Locket's Revels may revenge Pontack's .8wº wo * *, ***** ***, *, *. .ſritſ? * * *

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page Scan 59

_*- …” The City-Bride; or, the Meñy cuckold, ºf any here be guilty of Tranſgreſſion, 'Tis of Netºffº, not inclination : Thº'd be contented in their proper Houſes, Cou'd they reform their unperforming Spauſe: Tet if ſome wanton Appetite; there be, Han many are there that can faſt like ºve. Thoſe are enow, if I have their 4pplauſ, The Port has his End, and Imy cºſt. F IN I S. - --
Page Scan 60

* --- -- w -- - * --- -- - - - I - . - - - 1 - - - ... ** . - - - - - - :* . * . - - - - - --- - - - - - ... * * * - - --. . . . . . . \s . . . . ... º.º. º.º.º is 4 º' \º . * * … -- " - * * * * * - ... Yº sº, º ºvº, sº . ... • ! ---. sº - - - * * *- : * : * > . . - - • *- C - , " , --> w- , , , º - * * * * * . . -- - - * . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - - ... . . . . ~ - ---- - - ... - ...tº sº... * * * **, ; it * * *- : ***.* * *. - - *, *, *, *, *- : * * * - * -- .* tº ‘wº ºr , , , , , º ºxi, sº º *\ ...) &\ * * * --- *** **** -- sº • * * - - - > - --- -*------------ -- - - ---- - - - - ----- - - - - - - - - > - - 2 : * , ; ; ; / .* * * - - - \ - * - - - º - - ~ - - -

Page Scan 61

Blank page
Page Scan 62

Blank page
Page Scan 63

1942 n. SEP 2 5

Page Scan 64

Blank page

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents

End of text. Return to beginning.
