Catiline his conspiracy : a tragedy : as it is now acted by His Majesty's servants ; at the Threatre [sic] Royal / The author B.J., . | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
Catiline his conspiracy : a tragedy : as it is now acted by His Majesty's servants ; at the Threatre [sic] Royal / The author B.J., .
Author
Jonson, Ben, 1573?-1637.Jonson, Ben, 1573?-1637.
Published
London :Printed for A.C. and are to be sold by William Cademan,1674.
Description
78 p. ;22 cm.
Rights
Public Domain.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc2.ark:/13960/t84j0d39d

Table of Contents

    Title Page
    Copyright

Book Text
Title Page
Page Scan 1

Blank page
Page Scan 2

UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT LOS ANGELES
Page Scan 3

Blank page
Page Scan 4

Blank page
Page Scan 5

Blank page
Page Scan 6

Blank page
Page Scan 7

.- ,..j. ---- -- - T' Jonson (B.) Cataline, his conspiracy, a tragedy
Page Scan 8

Blank page
Page Scan 9

Blank page
Page Scan 10

Blank page
Page Scan 11

CATILINE H I S CONSPIRACY T* r^ . d As it is now A&ed by His The Author B. Ho RAT. H/j non fltbet, Verttm equitis quo^jam tnigravit ab attrs w, ad inctnos ocitlos^ P tinted for A. C. and are to be fold by William Cade man at the Popes Head in the Lower walk of the New-Exchange. 1674

End of Title Page. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Copyright
Page Scan 12

Blank page
Page Scan 13

PROLOGUE To CATILINE, To be MefVily fpoke by Mrs. Ne//, in an AmAzonian Habit. Woman's Prologue ! This is vcni'rous News $ ^ a Poet wanting Why fionldoHr Brains lye Fallow, 4s if they Without His fre, were -meer Prometehan Clay? In Natttr's Plain-Song we may bear cur parts ; Al 'though We want choice Defiant from the Arts. Among ft Muficians j / the Philomel May in Whild-Notes, though not tn Rules exceU. And when tth vcc^rFeffelWit doth lye ; Though into Froth it Will workjottt, andflye. But Gentlemen, Toft kpow our formal way,' Although wrefure 'tisftlfe, yet we muftfay, Nay Pijh, Nay F\c, in troth it is not good y When we the while, thinkjt not underftood : Hither repair all yon that arefcr Ben; Let th" Houfe holdfttll^ We'r- fme to carry 't then. Slight not this penal Summons ; Phoebus- rayes, To Crown his Poets, t urn'd our Sex to Bayes. And Ladies fure j cu'i votef- r us entire , (This Plot doth prompt the Prologue to conffire) Such inojfenfvue Combination can JBtttfoow, who yeft defervc true worth in Man. And Ton, with Ytttrgnrt Author taking Part} May chance be thought, Uke him to know the Art t f^ottchfafethfn, as you lock, to fpeakjts fair, Let the Gallants dtflikc it, if they dare : They will fo forfeit the repute of Judges, Ton may turn Am'ZQBS, and make them Drudges, Man's claim to Rule >, in hit Reafonbred ; This Mafculine Sex of Brain may makjVpM He ~Tis real Skill, in th* Right plac* to'^ije^ EM more, to have the Wit, not to Write Playcs
Page Scan 14

The Pcrfons of the Play. Sylla's Gbofi Catiline. Lentulus. Cethegus. Curias. Autronius. Vargunteius; Longinus. Lecca. Fulviust Beftia. Gabinius. Statilius, Geparius. Cornelias. Volturtius^ Aurelia. Fulvia. Sempronijr. Galla. Cicero^ Antoniuse Cato. Gatulus^ Craffus. Caefar. QH. Cicero. Syllanas. Flaccas. Pomtinius. Sanga. Senators Allobroges. Petreius. Souldiers. Porter. Liftors. ScrvantSo Pages. The Scene Romtl
Page 1

CATILINE. ACT L Ghoft. DOft thou not feel me, .R(?/ / hot yet ? Is night So heavy on thee, and my weight fo light ? Can Sylla's Ghoft arife within thy Walls, Lefs threatning, than an Earth-quake, the quick falls OF thee, and thine ? (hake not the frighted Heads Of thy fteep Towers? Or (brink to their fir/I Beds? Or, as their ruine the large Tyber fills, Make that fvvell up, and drown thy f even proud H ills ? What fleep is this doth feize thee, fo like Death, And is not it ? Wake, feel her in my breath : Behold, I come, fent From the Stygian found, As a dire vapor, that had cleft the ground, T' ingender with the Night, and blaft the Day ; Or like a Peftilence, that mould difplay Infection through the World : which ,thus,I do. 5 Difcovers Catiline Pluto be at thy councells ^ and into c in his Study. Thy darker bofom enter $ylla'$ Spirit : All, that was mine, and baH, thy l^eft inherit. Alas, how weak is that, for Ca'ilint \ Did I but fay f vain Voice ! ) all tV at was mine ? All, that the Gracchi, Cintr*, Manns would j What now, had I a body again I could, Coming from Hell ; what Fiends wbttld wifh, mould be 3; And hanmb*! could not have wifh'd to f- e : Think thou, and jjra.ftifc. Let t^e long-hid Seeds Of Treafon,' in tfiee, now Ihoot fc tS in deeds, B Ranker,
Page 2

a C At t LI N E. Ranker, thanhorror^ and thy former fafts Not fall in mention, bui to urge new Afts : Confcience of them provoke thee on to more. Be ftill thy Incefts, Murders, Rapes, before Thy fence} thy forcing firft zfejtal Nun$ Thy Parricide, late, on thine own only Son, After his Mother; to make empty way fcor thy laft wicked Nuptials j worfe than they, That Ware that Aft of thy inceftious Life, Which got thec, at once, a Daughter , and a Wife.. I leave the flaughters that thou didft for me, Of Senators; for which, I hid for thee Thy murder of thy Brother, (being fo brib'd) And writ him in the lift of my profcrib'd After thy fad, to fave thy little fliame : Thy Inceft , with thy Sifter , I not name. Thefe are too light. Fate will have thee purfue Deeds, after which, no mifchief can be new j The ruine of thy Country : thou wert built For fuch a work , and born for no lefs guilt. What though defeated once th* haft been and known ? Tempt it again : That is thy aft , or none. What all the fevcral ills that vifit Earth, ( Brought forth by night with a finilter birth ) Plagues, Famine, Fire, could not reach unto, The Sword, nor Surfeits; let thy Fury do: Make all puft, prefcnt, future ill thine own ; And conquer all example, in thy one. Nor let thy thought find 'any vacant time To hate an old , but ftill a freflier crime Drown the remembrance : let not mifchief ceafr, But while it is in punishing, encreafe. Confcience and care die in thee } and be free Not Hcav'n it felf from thy impiety: Let Night grow blacker with thy plots ; and Day, At (hewing but thy head forth , itart away From this half-fphear; and leave Rentes blinded Walk T embrace Lufts, Hatreds, Slaughters, Funerals, And not recover fight, till their own flames Do light them to their ruines. All the names Of thy Confederates, too, be no lefs great In Hell, than here: that, when we would repeat Our ftrengths in mufter , we may name you all, And Furies^ upon you, for Furies, call. Whilft what you do, may ftrike them into fears, Or maks them grieve, and wifh your mifchief theirs.
Page 3

C A T I L IN E. g Catiline. IT is decree'd. Kor (hall thy Fate, O Rome, Refift my vow. Though Hills were fet on Hilb, And Seas met Seas, to guard thee j I would through ? I, plough up Rocks, fteep as the Alps, in duft. And lave the Tyrrhene Waters into Clouds; But I would reach thy Head, thy Head, proud City. The ills that I have done, cannot be fafe But by attempting greater; and I feel A Spirit within me, chides my fluggifh hands. And fays, they have been innocent too long. Was I a Man, bred great, as Rome her ftlf ? One, form'd for all her Honours, all her Glories? Equal to all her Titles ? that could ftand Clofe up, with Atltu^ and fuftain her name As ftrong, as he doth Heav'n ? And, was I f Of all her brood, mark'd out for the repulfe By her no voice, when I flood Candidate ^ To be Commander in the Pontiik^ War ? I will, hereafter, call her Step-dame, ever. If me can loofe her Nature , I can loofe My Piety ; and in her ftony entrails Dig me a feat: where, I will live again, The labour of her Womb, and be a burden Weightier than all the Prodigies and Monfters That (he hath teem'd with, fmce (he firft knew Mars. Catilint, Aureli*. WHo's there ? Attr.'Tis I. Cat. Amelia f ^r.Ycs. Cat. Appear, And break, like day, my beauty to this circle : Upbraid thy PhahM, that he is fo long In mounting to that point, which (hould give thee Thy proper fplendour. Wherefore frowns my Sweet? Have I too long been abfent from thefe Lips, [Me kiffeth tke>* This Cheek, thefe Eyes ? What is my trefpafs ? fpeak. Aur. t feems; you know, that can accufe your felf. Cat. I will redeem it. Aur. Still you fay fo : When ? Cat. When OrcftiUa, by her bearing well Thefe my Retirements, and ftoln times for thought, Shall give their effects leave to call her Queen Of all the World, in place of humbled Rome. Aur. You court me, now. Cat. A" I would always, Love, By this Am\>ro(im\! . Kifs, and this of Ntttar, WotJ ft thou but htar as gladly as I fpeak. Could my Aiirth* think i meant her lefs$ B 2
Page 4

4 C A T / L I N E. When, wooing her, I firft remov'd a Wife, And then a Son, to make my Bed and Houfe Spacious, and fit t'embrace her? Thefe were deeds- Not t'have begun with, but to end with more, And greater : tc He that, building, ftays at one " Floor, or the fecond, hath erected none. Twas how to raife thee, I was meditating ; To make fome a.i of mine anfvver thy love : That love, that, when my ftate was now quite funk, Game with thy wealth, and weigh'd it up again, And made my emergent- fortune once more look Above the main; which., now, mall hit the Stars, And flick my Oreftill^ there, amongft 'hem, If any temped can but make the billow, And any billow can but lift her greatnefs. But, I muft pray my Love, (he will put on Like habits with my felf. I have to do With many men, and many natures. Some, That muft be blown, and footh'd ; as Lemulut, Whom I have heav'd> with magnifying his bloud, And a vain dream, out of the Sjbill's Books, That a third man, of that great Family, Whereof he is defcended* the Cornclii, Should be a King m-Rome : which I have hir'd ; The flattering Augures to interpret him, Cinna, and Sylla dead. Then, bold Cethegntj Whofe valour I have turn'd into his poifon, And prais'd fo into daring, as he would Go on upon the Gods, kifs Lightning, wreft The Engine from the Cyclops, and give fire At face of a fulF Cloud, and ftand his ire: When I would bid him move. Others there are> Whom envy to the State draws, and puts on, For contumelies receiv'd, (and fuch are fure ones) As Curhu, and the fore-nam'd Lentnlm^ Both which have been degraded, in the Senate, And mu/t have their difgraces, ftill, new rubbd, To make 'hem fmart, and labour of revenge. Others, whom meer ambition fires, and dole Of Previnces abroad, which they have feign'd To their crude hopes> and I as amply promis'd; Thefe, Lecca, V^rgHnteitu^ Beftia, Antronius. Some, whom their wants opjprefs/ as th' idle Captains Of Syllas troops: and- divers Roman Knights (The profufc Wafters of their Patrimonies) So threatned with their Debts, as they will,- now, Run
Page 5

CAriLINE. 5 Run any dcfpcrate fortune, for a change. Thefe, for a time, we mutt relieve, Amelia, And make our Houfe the fafe-guard : like, for thpfe, That fear the Law, or ftand within her gripe, For any aft paft, or to come. Such will From their own crimes, be factious, as from ours. Some more there be, flight Airlings, will be won With Dogs and Horfes; or, perhaps, a Whore; Which muft be had : and if they venture Lives For us, Amelia, we muft hazard Honours ^A little/ Get the^ ftore, and change of Women, 'As I have Boys; and give 'hem time, and place, And all connivence : be thy felf, too, courtly ; And entertain, and feaft, fit up, and revel ; Gall all the great, the. fair, and fpirited Dames Of R^me about thee; and begin a fafliion Of freedom, and community. Some will thank thee, Though the fowre Senate frown, whofe Heads muft.ake In fear, and feeling too. We muft not fpare Or coft, or modefty. It can but fhew Like one of Juno's,' or of Jaw's difguifesj In either thee, of me : and will as foon, When things fucceed, be thrown by, or let fall, As is a Vail put off, a Vifor chang'd, Or the Scene fhifted in our Theaters [A not ft without. Who's that ? It is the voice of Lentulits. Am. Or of CethegHs, Cat. In, my fair Amelia , And think upon thefe arts. They muft not fee, H6"w far you are trufted with thefe privacies; Though on their Shoulders, Necks, and Heads you rife. Lentil! us > Cethegu^ Catiline. JT is, me thinks, a morning, full of fate ! It rifeth flowly, as her fullen Carr Had all the weights of fleep, and death hung at it ! She is not rofie-finger'd but fwoln black! Her face is like a water, turn'd to bloud, And her fi'ck head is bound about with clouds, As if (he threatned* nigbt, ere noon of day! It does not l6ok> as it would have a hail, Or health, wim'd in it, as on other morns. Cet. Why, all the fitter, Leutn!ns : our corning. Is not for falutation, we have bufmefs. Cat. Said nobly, brave Cethegm. Where's Antronins ? Cet. Is he not come? Cat. Not here. Ctt. Nor VarwnteiHs? Cat. Neither, . Cet . A fire in., their beds, and bofoms, That fo will ferve their floth, rather than vcrtue. They
Page 6

6 C A r I L 1 . tf E. They arc no Romans, and at fuch high need As now. Lett. Both they, Lvngitw, Lecca, Fttlviw, Galtintt) gave me word, Jafl night, By Latin* Beftta, they would all be ierc, And yearly. Get. Yes, as you, had I not caiTd you. Come, we all deep, and are meer Dormice j Flies, A little lefs than dead : more duinefs hangs On us, than on the Morn. Ware Spirit-bound, In Ribs of Ice j our whole Biouds are one intone, And Honour cannot thaw us, nor our wants, Though they burn, hot as Fevers, to our States. Cat, I mufe they would be tardy, at an hour Of fo great purpofc. Get. If the Gods had call'd Them, to a purpofe, they would jmt have come With the fame Tortoife fpeed ! that are thus How To fuch an action, which the Gods will envy: As asking no lefs means, than all their Powers Conjoyn'd, t' effeft. I would have feen Rome burnt By this time, and her Afh;?s in an Urn j The Kingdom of the Senate rent afunder, And the degenerate talking Gown , run frighted Out of the Air of Italy. Cat. Spirit of Men ! Thou Heart of our great Enterpife ! how much I love thefe Voices in thee ! Get. O, the days Of Sylla's fway, when the free Sword took leave To aft all that it would ! Cat. And was familiar With the entrails, as our Augures ? Get. Sons k ill *d Fathers, Brothers their Brothers. Cat. And had price, and praife. AH hate had licence given it : all rage reigns. Get. Slaughter bcftrid the Streets, and ftretch'd himfdf To fecm more huge ; whilft to his ftained Thighs The Gore he drew flow'd up : and carried down Whole heaps of Limbs and Bodies through his Arch. No Age was fpar'd, no Sex. Cat. Nay, no Degree. Get. Not Infants, in the porch of life were free. The Sick, the Old, that could but hope a day Longer, by Natures bounty, not let ftay : Virgins, and v ido-.vs, Matrons, pregnawt Wives, All died. Cat. Tvvas crime enough, they that had Lives. To (hike but only thofe that could do hurt, Was dull and poor. Some fcH to make the number, As fome the prey. Get. Tie rugged Charon fainted, And ask'd a N-.vy, rather than a Boat, To ferry over t\ie fad World that came : The Maws and Dens of Beafts, could not receive The Bodies, that thofe Souls were frighted from*, And
Page 7

c 4 r i L i x E. And e'en tte Graves were fiH'd with them, yet living, Whofc flight and fear had mix'd them, with .the dead. Cat. And this (hall be again, and more and more, Now Lcntultu, the third Corneiiw 9 Is to ftand up in Rome. Len. Nay, urge not that Is fo uncertain. Cat. How ! Len. I mean, not clear'd, And , therefore, not to be reflected on. Cat. The Sybil's leaves uncertain ? or the comments Of our Grave, deep, divining men not clear ? Len. All Prophecies, you know, fufTer the torture. Cat. But this, already, hath confefs'd, without : And fo been weighed, examin'd, and compar'd, As 'twere malicious ignorance in hfm, Would faint in the belief L&n. Do you believe it? Cut . Do I love LentttlKt ? or pray to fee it ? Len. The Atig res all are conftant, I am meant. Cat . They had loft their Science elfe. Len. They count from Cinn*. Cat. And Sy/la next, and fo make you the third ; All that can fay the Sun is ris'n, muft think it. L n. Men mark me more, of late, as I come forth ! Cat. Why, what can they do lefs? Cinna and Sytt*. Are fet, and gone: and we muft turn our eyes On htm that is, and fhines. Noble Cetktgw, But view htm with me, here ! He looks, already, As if he (hook a Scepter o're the Senate, And the aw'd Purple dropt their Rods and Axes? The Statues melt again ; and Houfhold-Gods In groans confefs the travel of the City The very Walls fweat Blood before the change ; And Srdnes ftart out to ruine, ere it comes. Cet. But he, and we, and all are idle ftiU. Ltn. I am your Creature, Sergiw,: And whate're The great Ccrndian Name fliali win to be, It is not Augury ', nor the Sylfills Books, But Catiline that makes it. Cat. I am fhadow To honour'd Lentttltu, and Cethegus here, Who are the heirs of Mars.- Cet. By Mars hirafelf, Catiline is more my Parent : for whofe vertue Earth cannot make a (hadow great enough, Though envy fhould come too. O, there they are r Now we fh all talk more, though we yet do nothing. Varguntf]ut> Longinw, Curitu, L(cta y Cabintu &c. C^ them. . HAii Lucius, Catiline. Var. Hail noble SergAu* Lon. Hail Pub. Lentnlw. Cur. Hail the third Cornelius, Lee, Caiw, Cthe?w hail, Cet, Hail floth and wotds,
Page 8

S C A T I L I X E. In ftead of -Men gnd Spirits. Cat. Nay, dear Cr. Are your cyes l yet -unfecl'd ? Dare they look Day In the full face? CV. He's zealous for the affair, And blames your tardy coming, Gentlemen. Get. Unlefs we had fold our fclves to deep and eafe, And would be our (laves flaves- Cat. Pray you forbear. Get. The North is not fo itark and cold. Cat. Cethegw Zcs. We (hall redeem all, if your fire will let us. Cat. You are too full of Hghtning, noble Cain*. Boy, fee all doors be (hut, that none approach us, On this part of the Houfe. Go you, and bid The Prieit, he kill th<. Slave I mark'd laft riight. And bring me of his Bloud, tyjhen I fhall call him : Till then, wait all without. F^r. How is't, Autroniui \ Aut. Longimu ? Lfw.Cttrifu ? Cnr.Lecca f Var. -Feel you nothing ? Lon. A Orange, un-wonted horrour doth invade me, ( A darkve fs I know not what it is ! Lcc. The Day goes back, < comes over Or elfe my Scnfes! Cur. As at Amut Feaft ! (.the place. Fnl. Darknefs .grows more and more ! Len. The ^tflal flame \_A groan of many people is beard wider ground^\ I think, be out. Cab. What groan was that. Get. Our phant'fies Strike fire out of our felves, and force a Day. Am. Again it founds! Bes. As all the City gave it! Cet.Wc fear what our felves feign. f^r.What light is this? i^n'f for. Cur. Look forth. Len. It ftil) grows greater ! Lee. From whence comes if?,, ^ A fiery light Lon. A bloudy Arm it is , that, holds a Pine \ appears. Lighted, above the Capitol \ and, ROW, It waves unto us ! Cat. Brave and ominous ! Our cntcrprife is feal'd. Get. In fpight of Darknefs, That would difcountenance it. Look no more;. We lofe time, and our felves. To what we. came for, Speak, Liiciw, we. attend you. Cat. Nobleft RomAnt^ If you were lefs,"or that your Faith andVertue Did not hold good that title, with your Bloud, I mould not, now, unprofirably fpend My felf in words, or .catch at empty hopes, By airy ways, for folid certainties. But fmce in many, and the greatett dangers, I (lill have known you no Icfs true, than valiant, And that I taffe, in you, the fame affcclions, To will, or nilJ, to think things good, or bad, Alike with me : (which-,argues your firm friendfhip) I dare the bokiiier, wtfh.Vypa, fet on foot, Or lead, nhW this ^Veat And goodiieit aclion,- What I have thought of it afore, you all Have
Page 9

C A T I I l N & Have heard apart. J then exprefs'4 my Zcat Unto the Glory; now, the ncecf enflames me t When I fore-think the hard conditions Our States muft undergo, except in time We do redeem our felves to liberty, And break the Iron yoke, forg'd for our necks. For what Icfs can we call it ? when we fee The Commonwealth engrofs'd fo by a few, The Giants of the State, that do, by turns, Enjoy her, and defile her ! All the Earth, Her Kings and Tetrarchs, are their Tributaries; People, and Nations, pay them hourly Stipends: The Riches of the World flows to their Coffers, And not to Romes. While (but thofe few) However great we are, honeft, and valiant, Are herded with the vulgar ; and fo kept, As we were only bred to confume Corn, Or wear our Wool ; to drink the Cities witer \ Ungrac'd, without Authority, or mark; Trembling beneath their rods : to whom, (if all Were well in Rom:) we mould come forth bright Axes. All Places, Honours, Offices., are theirs ! Or 'vvnere they will confer 'hem f They leave us The dangers, -the repulfes, judgments, wants: Which how long will you bear, moil valiant Spirits? Were we not better to fall once with Vertue, Than draw a wretched and difhbnour'd breath, To lofe with mame, when thefe mens pride will laugh? I call the faith of gods and men to queftion, The power is in our hands ; our bodies able ; Our minds as ftrong; o'th' contrary, in them All things grown aged, with their wealth and years: Their wants, but only to begin the bufmefs, The iflue is certain. Get. Lon. On, let us go on. Cur. Bes. Go on, brave Scrgiut. Cat. It doth ftrikc my foul, (And, who can fcape the ftroke, that hath a foul, Or, but the fmalleft air of man within him ?) To fee them fwell with treafure ; which they pour Out i'their riots, eating, drinking, building, I, i'the Sea ! plaining of Hills with Valleys, And raifing Valleys above Hills ! whilft we Have not to give our bodies neceflaries. They ha' their change of Houfes, Mannors, Lordflups; We fcarce a fire, or poor houftiold Lay / They buy rare Attic\^ Statues, Tyrian Hangings, Piftures, and Corinthian Plate, C
Page 10

10 C J T I L 1 W E. Attalic\^ Garments, and now, new found Gcmj, Since Pompey went for A\ia, which they purchafc At price of Provinces ! t"lie River Phafis Cannot afford *hem fowl : nor Lurrine Lake Oy:ters enow: Circet, too, is fearch'd To pleafe the witty gluttony of a meal! Their ancient Habitations they neelcct, And fet up new ; then, if the eccho like not In fuch a room, they pluck down thofe, build newer, Alter them too: an.1, by all frantick ways, Vex their wild wealth, as they moleft the people, From whom they force it ! yet they cannot tame, Or overcome their riches !. Not by making Baths, Orchards, Fifti- pools ! letting iia of Seas Here ! and then there, forcing 'hem out again, With mountainous heaps, for \vhich the 'Earth hath Moft of her Ribs, as Entrails! being now Wounded no lefs for Marble, than for Gold. We all this while, like calm benumb'd Spectators, Sit, till our feats do crack; and do not hear The thiind'ring mines: whUft at'home, our wants, Abroad, our debts do urge us ; our (hues daily Bending to bad, our hopes to worfe : and, what Is left, but to be cfufh'd ? Wake, wake brave friends, And meet the liberty you oft have wifh'd for. Behold, Renown; Riches, and Glory court you. Fortune holds out thcfc to you, as rewards; Me thinks (though I were dumb) th' affair iffelf The opportunity, youf needs, and 'dangers, With the brave fpoil the War brings, fttould invite you. life me your General; or Souldief i neither My mind, hoV body fhall be wanting to you. And, being Cottfol, I do not doubt f efTett All that, you wi(h, ..if tru!V hot flatter me, And you'd riot rather ftill be Slaves, than free. Cet. Free, free. Lon. Tis freedom. Cur, Freedom we all ftanid for. Cat. Why-,..thefe But that we ta"kc a- are nolle Voices ! Nothing wants thefy L frL-mri Sacrament i .,.3 f ^ i' i o To ftrengthcn our de(]gn, Cct t And fo. to act if. DifFcrring hurts, where "lowers are fo prepar'd. Ant Yet, ere we enter into an open act, (With favour) 'twere no lof^, if't might be enquir'd, What the'cbnc^ition.bf thc'e Arms would be > r-r I, and the, me^S.tp carry usthfou'gh? Cat. How', FrkHcfs ! Think you, that 'I wcrutd bicjVyou grafp t! c \Vind ? Or,eail;you to th' embracing of a Cloud?
Page 11

CATILINE. it- Put your known Valours on To dear a. bufinefs, And have no other fecond, than the danger, Nor other GyrJond than the.J&fs? Become Your own auurances. Arid for the means, Confider, firlt, the ftark fecurity The Commonwealth ?s in now; the whole, S.eMtt Sleepy, and dreaming no fuch violent blow; Their forces all abroad ; of which the greateft, That might annoy us moft,' is fardeft ,ofF, . In j4fa, under Pompey : thofe, near hind, Commanded by our Friends j one Army in Spttin,. By Cneu* Pifo ; th'other in Mturttama, ;. By Nucerinw j both which I have firm, ! And faft unto our plot. My :fejf>.then, flanding Now to be ConfuL ; with rriy;htop'd Colleague Caw Antoniui ; one, no" lefs eiigag'd By his wants, than we: and, whom I have power to melt, And caft in any.mofcld. Befide, fome others That will not yet be nam'd, (both fure, and great ones) Who, when the time comes,, (hall declare thernfeives Strong for our party: fo that no refinance In Nature- can be thought. For our reward. then, Firft, all our Debts are paid; dangers of Law, Actions, Decrees, Judgments againft us quitted; The rich men^ as in Syllas times, profcrib d$ And publication rhade 'of all their Goods ; That Houfe is yours-, that .Land is his ; thofe Waters, ' . /j Orchards, and Walks, a third's; he has that honoujr,?, - tj> And he that office: fuch a Province falls To yargunteiw : this to AfOronitu : that To bold Cethegtu : Rome to Lenttilw. You (hare the World \ her. Magistracies, Pricft^Koods, Wealth, and Felicity Imbngft'^yod, Friehds- : ^,\ And Catiline your Servant. WoMii;you^C#r#^ Revenge the contumely (luck upon yoH, In being reraov'd from the 1 -Senate ? Now, Now, is your time. Would Pt&liw- Lentnl^^ Strike, for the like dil^race ?. AI^oW, ^s:hi$ .ItirttT, fj i.\ Would ftout Longinw- Walk t^ie Streets' of Rvme. Facing the Pr&tor ?_ No^ 'ha8>tre a time . - X To fpurn, and -tifead the fafces. into .dirt, . Made of the Ufurers, and the 'Litlors brains. Is there a Beauty here in Rome you love*?- , . An Enemy you would kitt? What, Head's ;nof yors? Whofe Wife, whidi Boy, tttofcfe Daughter, of t wbaf race, That th'Husband, -or ^iad' Parents ifeall/BOt brjpg you, C z
Page 12

II C A ? I L I N Z. And boafting of the Office ? only fpare Your felves, and you have all the Earth befidc, A Field, to exercife your longings in. I fee you rais'd, and read your forward minds High, in your faces. Bring the Wine and Bloud You have prepar'd there. Lon. How! Cat. I have kill'd a Slave, And of his Bloud caused to be mix'd with Wine. Fill every man his Bowl. There cannot be; A fitter drink, to make this fautlion in. Here, I begin the Sacrament to all. O, for a clap of Thunder now, as loud As to be heard throughout the Univerfe, To tell the World the faft, and to applaud ft. Be firm, my hand ; notflicd a drop : but pour Fiercenefs into me, with it,, and fell thirit Of more and more, till Rome be left as blond-lefs>. As ever her fears made her, or the Sword. And when I leave to wifh this to thee, Step-dame, Or flop, to effecl it, with my powers fainting } So may my blotid be drawn, and fo drunk up As is this flaves. Lon. And-fo be mine. Lcn. And mine. [They drink. Ant. And mine; ->fav. And mine. Get. Swell me my bowl yet fulierw Here, I do drink this> as I would do Cato's, Or the new fellow Cicero's : with that vow Which Catiline hath given. Car. So do I. Lee. And I. Bes. And I, fxl.And L Cab. And all .of us. . Cat. Why, now's the bufiaefsTafe, ..and each man ftfengthned. Sirrah, what ail you? -P^f. "Nothing. es. Somewhat modeft. Cat hlave, I will ftrikeyotir Soul out with my foot, r He fpics Let me find you again with fuch a face : ) one of hit You Whelp Bes. Nay,/-;^ w. Cat. Are you coy ing it, boys not When I command you to be free, and general (.anfveer- To all ? Be s. You'll be obfcrv d. Cat. Arife, and fhew But any leaft averfion i'your look To him that boards you next, and your throat opens. Noble Confederates, thus far is perfect. Only your fufFragrs I wiHexpecl At the AfTembly for choofing Covfuls, And all the voices you can make -by friends To my election. Then, let me workout Your fortunes, and mine own. Mean while, all reft Seal'dup, and filent,- as when rigid fro is Have bound up brooks and rivers, ^forc'd wUd bea#& Unto their caves, and birds into tfre tyfipdsi Clowns tc) ttifefr ho^ifes, and the Country Heeps : . j Xhaf when chc 5uddQ thaw comes, we ifcay break -on
Page 13

c A r j t i N s. Upon 'hem like a deluge, bearing down Half Rome before us, and invade the reft With cries, and noife able to wake the urns Of thofe are dead, and make the afhes fear, The horrours, that do ftrike the World, fhould come Loud, andunlook'd for : till they ftrike, be dumb. Get. Oraculous Sergiw \ Len. God-like Catiline ! Chorus. CAn nothing great, and at the height^ Remain fo long ? but its own weight Will mine it .* Or is't blind chance That fill de fires new States t' advance, And quit the old ? lfe 9 why waft Rome Be by it felf\ now, overcome i Hath foe not foes inow of thofe Whom foe hath made fitch, and enclofe Her round about ? Or, are thy none y Except fie firft become her own . ? O wretchednefs of greateft States, . To be obnoxiotu to thefe fates : That cannot keep what they dogaii\ . And what they raife, fo ill fftftain \ Rome now is Miftrefs of the whole World, Sea and Land to either Pole ; And even that fortune will deftroy The power that mack it : foe* doth joy - S much in plenty $ wealth and eafe 3 As now th' excefs is her difeafe. She builds in Gold, and to the Stars, As if foe threatned Heavn with Wan And feck* fcr Hrilin Quarries deep, Giving the Fiends that there do k$ep t A hope of day. Her women wear The f poils of Nations in av ear, Chang d for the treafure of a foell ; And in their loofe Attires do fwell More light than Sails, when all winds jlay: Yet are the men more light than they \ More kemb'd^and bath 'A, and rub'd, and trim More flefk'd, more f oft > and flatter ' As pro flit ute : fo much, that kind May jetk, ** f e tf there, and not find. They eat on Beds of Stlk^ and Gold y At. Ivory Tables, or Wood fold Beaver than it ; and leaving Plate 3 To drink^ in Stone, if higher r*te*
Page 14

CATILINE. They bunt all Grounds ; ind drm -a/I foul every rok >d Btijh^ to pleafe Their wanton Baftts: anA vt feqtteft Have new, a^id rare things ; not the leeft ! Hence comes that wtlu^ and vaft exfence t That hath eif'jrca Romcs venue thence, Which fimpte Poverty fir Ji made: And, now, Ambition doth *i>rv fide fjer Staff, with eating Avarice, Riot, and. evtry other Pice. Y.. Decrees are bought, and Laws are fold* Honours, and < . ff.ces for Gold ; The Peoples voices } a:-^d -the free Tongues > in the Senate, bnbed.be. Such ruinc <f her Manners Rome Doth fofftr new, at foe's become -C Without the Gods it fron gain- fay.) Both hir own fpwler, and own prey. So Afia, art ihou irnlly even With w, f^r all the blows thee gtven ^ When we, vehofc f^ertue Conquer a thee, 7hta, by thy Vtcct, ruin 'd be. ' itty Galla, Servant. THofe rooms do fmell extreamly. Bring niy Gfafs, And Table hither, Calla. Gal. Madam, ful. Look Within, i'niy blew Cabinet, for the Pearl I had fent me lad, and bring it. Gal. Tha.t from Clodim ? Ful. From Cains Ctfar. You are for CUduu ft^ll. Or Curtm. Sin ha, if Quinttu Curiu, come, I run not in fit mood ; I keep tny Chamber : Give warning fo without. Cial. Is this it, Madam? Ful. Yes, help to hang it in mine ear. Gal. Believe me, It is a rich one, Madam. Ful. \ hope fo : It mould not be \vorn there elfe. Make an end, And bind my Hair up. Gal. As 'twas yefterday ? Ful. No, nor the t'other day. When knew you me Appear two days together in one drefllng ? Gal. \Aillyou ha't i'the globe or fpirc? Fid. Howthou wilt; Any way, fo thou wilt do it, good Impertinence : Thy company^ iifi flept not very well A
Page 15

CATILINE. Jj A nights, would make me an errant Fool with Queftions. Cat. Alas, Madam fid. Nay, Gentle half o'the Dialogue, ceafe. Gal. ( do it indeed, but for your exercife, As your Phyfician bids me. f nl. How ! Do's he bid you To anger me for exercife ? Gal. Not to anger you, But ftif your bloud a little : There's difference Between .hike-warm-, and boyling, Madam. Ful. jov ! She means to cook me, I think : Pray you, ha' done. Gal. I mean to drefs you, Madam. Ful. O, my Juno I Be friend to me ! Offring at wit, too? Why, G*tta\ Where haft thou been ? 6*/. Why,Madam! Ful. What haft t^ou done With thy poor innocent felf? Gal. Wherefore ? fweet Madam \ Ful. Thus to come forth, fofuddain!y ? a Wit-worm. Gal. It pleafes you to flout one. I did dream Of Lady Sempronia Ful. O, the wonder is out, That did infect thee? Well, and how? Gal. Me thought She did difcourfe the beft Ful. That ever thou heard'ft ? Gal. Yes. Ful. I'thy deep ? Of what was her difcourfe ? Gal. O' the Republik:-) Madam, and the ^tate, And how (he was in debt, and where fhe meant To raife frefh fams : She's a great States- woman !' Ful. Thou dream'ft all this? Gal. No, but you know (He is,Madanv And both a Miftrefs of the Latine Tongue, And of the Greeks Ful. I, but I never dreamt it, Gal/a, As thou had done, and therefore you muft pardon me Gal. Indeed, you mock me, Madam Ful Indeed, no. Forth, with your learned Lady. She has-a wit, too? Gal. A very Mafculine one. Fid. A fhe-C'um^, Galla*. And can compofe in Verfe, and make quick Jefts, Modeft, oromerwife? Gal. Yes, Madam. fW. She can fing., too ; And play on Inftruments ? Gal. Of all kinds, they fiy. Ful. And doth dance rarely ? 'Gal. Excellent ! So well, As a bald Senator made i jeft, and fa id, Twas better thananhoneft Woman need. Ful. Tut, (he may bear that. Few wife Womens honeilies Will do their courtfhip hurt. Gal. She's liberal too, Madam. Ful. What! of her Money, or her Honour, pray thee? Gal. Of both, you know not which (he doth fpareleaft. Ful. A comely commendation. Gal. Troth, 'tis pity, She is in years. Ful Why? Gal. For it is. Ful. O is that aH ? T thought thou had'ft had a reafon. Gal. Why, fo I have. She has been a fine Lady, And, yet, fhe drefles her felf (except you, Madam) One o'the beft in Rome : and paints, -and hides Her decays very well. Ful. They fay, it is Rather a.Vifor, than a Face ffce wears, Gal.
Page 16

16 CATILINE. Gal. They wrong her verily, Madam, (he do's Heck With crumbs of bread and milk, and lies a nighti In as neat Gloves But me is fain of late To feck more than (he's fought to (the fame is) And fo fpends that way. Ful. Thou know'rt all ! But, What fay you to Catiline's Lady, Ore ft ilia ? There is the Gallant ! Gal. She does well. She haf Very good Sutes, and very rich : but then She cannot put 'hem on. She knows not how To wear a Garment. You mall have her all Jewels and Gold fometimes, fo that her felf Appears the leaft part of her felf. No in troth, As I live, Madam, you put 'hem all down With your nicer ftrength of judgment ! and do draw too, The world of Route to follow you ! you attire Your felf fo divcrfly ! and with that fpirit ! Still to the nobleft humours ! They could make Lov^ to your drefs, although your face wear away, they fay. Ful. And body too, and ha' the better match on't ? Say they not fo too, GalU ? Now ! What news Travails your countenance with? Ser. If't pleafeyou, Madam, The Lady Sempronia is lighted at the Gate. Gal. Caftor, my dream, my dream. Ser. And comes to fee you. Gal. For Vemu fake, good Madam, fee her. Ful. Peace, The fool is wild, I think. Gal. And hear her talk, Sweet Madam, of State-matters, and the Senate. Scmpronia, Fulvia^ Galla. FVfaia, Good Wench, how do;t thou ? Ful. Well, Scrnproni*. Whither are you thus early addreft ? Sem. To fee Aurclia, Ore ft ilia : She fent for me : I came to call thee with me, wilt thou go ? Ful. I cannot now in troth, I have fome Letters To write, and fend away; Sem. Alas, I pity thee. I ha' been writing all this night (and am So very weary) unto all the Tribes And Centuries, for their voices, to help Catiline In his ele<ftion. We mail make him Confitl, I hope, amongfl us. Crajfw^ I, and Cafar, Will carry it for him. Ful. Does he ftand for't ? Sem. He's the chief Candidate. Ful. V Vho ftands befide ? (Give me fome wine and pouldcr for my teeth. Sent. Here's a good pearl in troth ! FuL A pretty one. Sem. A very orient one!) There are Competitors, Caiut Anton'wt) Publitu Galba^ Lucius LonginHt, Qnintw CornificiHs y Lifiniw, and that talker Cicero. But
Page 17

C A r I L I N E. 17 But Catiline-) and Antcmus will be chofen : For four o* the other, Liciniw, Longing Galba, and Cornificiu* will give way. And Cicero they will not choofe. Ful. No ? why ? Sent. It will.be crofs'd, by the nobility. Gal. (How flic do's understand the common bufinefs !) Sem. Nor, were it fit. He is but a new fellow, An in-mate, here, in Rome (as Catiline calls him) And the Patricans fhould do very ill, To let the C<w//-mip be fo defil'd As 't would be, if he obtain'd it ? A meer upflart, That has no pedigree, no houfe, no coat, No enfigns of a family ? Fnl. He'has vertue. Sem. Hang vertue, where there is no blond : 'tis vice. And, in him, iaucinefs. Why mould he prefume To be more learned, or more eloquent, Than the nobility ? or boaft any quality Worthy a noble man, himfelf not noble ? Ful. 'Twas vertue onely, at firft, made all men noble. Sem. I yeild you, it might,at firft, in Romes poor age 5 When both her Kings, and Confuls held the plough, Or garden'd well : But, now, we ha' no need, To digg, or lofe our fweat for't. We have wealth, Fortune and cafe, and then their ftock, to fpend on, Of name, for vertue ; which will bear us out 'Gainft all new commers : and can: never fail us. While the fucceflionftays. And, muft we glorifie, Amufhrome? one of yefterday? a fine fpeaker ? 'Caufe he has fuck'd at Athens ? and advance him, To our own lofs ? No, Fnhia. There are they Can fpeak^d^too, if need were. Cxfar^ and I, Have fet upon him ; fo hath Cr<tjfus, too : And others. We have all decreed his reft, For rifing farder. Gal. Excellent rare Ludy ! Ful. Semproniaj you are beholden to my woman, here. She do's admire you. Sem. O good Galla, how doft thou ? Gal. The better,for ytrnr learned Lady mip. Sent. Is this grey poulder, a good dentifrice ? Ful. You fee I ufe it. Sem. I have one is whiter. Ful. It may be fo. Sew. Yet this fmells well. Gal And qlenfes Very well, Madam, and refills the crudities. Sem. Fuhia^ I pray thee, who comes to thec, now ? Which of our great Patricans ? Fni. Faith, I keep No catalogue of 'herru Sometimes I have one, Sometimes another, as the toy takes their blouds. Thou hart them all. Faith, when was Quint its D
Page 18

IS C A r / L I N E. Thyfpecial fervant, here? Ful. My fpccialfervant? Sem. Yes, thy Idolater, I cali him. Ful. He may be yours, If you do like him, Sem. How! Ful, He comes, not here, I have forbid him, hence. Sem. f^tnus forbid ! Ful. Why ? Sem. Your fo conftant lover. Ful. So much the I would have change. J-,o would you too, I am fure. And now you may have him. Scrn. He's frefh yet, Beware, how you do attempt me. Ful. Faith, for me, He' islKmwhat too frefh, indeed. The fait is gone, That gave him feafon. His good gifts are done. He do's not ycild the crop that he was wont. And, for the ad, I can have fecret fellows, With backs worth ten of him, and mail pleafc me (Now that the land is fled) a myriade better. Sem. And thofe one may command. Ful. Tis true : thefc Lording*, Your noble Fauns, they are fo imperious, fancy, Rude, and as boiftrous as Cemttarcs, leaping, A Lady, at firit fight. Sent. And mnft be born Both with, and out, they think. Fid. Tut, I'lcobfcrve None of 'hem all r nor humour 'hem a jot Longer, than they come laden in- the hand, And fay. here's t' one, for th* tother. Sim. Do's Cffar give welt? Ful. They (half all give, and pay well, that come here. If they will have it : and that jewels, pearl, Plate, or round fums, to buy thefe. Tarn not taken With a cob-fwan, or a high-mounting bull, As foolifh Leda, and Eftropa were, But the bright gold, with Danac. For fuch price, I would endure, a rough, harfh Jupiter, Or ten fuch thundring gamfters : and refrain To laugh at 'hem, till they are gone, with my much fufTering.. Sem. Th' art a mod: happy wench, that thus canft make life of thy youth, and frcflinefs, in the feafon : And haft, it to make ufb of. Ful. (Which is the happinefs.) Sem. I am, now, fain to give to them, and keep Mufick, and a continual table, to invite 'hem : Ful. (Yes, and they ftudy your kitchin, more than you) Sem. Eat my fclf out with ufury , and rny Lord too, And all my officers, and friends befide, To procure moneys, for the needful charge Imuftbeat, to have 'hem: and, yet, fcarce Can T atchieve 'hem, fo. Ful. Why, that's becaufc You airl'd young faces only., and fnaopth chins, Semfronia. If youl'd love beards, andbriftles, (One with another, as others do) or wrinkles Who's that! LookG'aft*, Gal. 'Tis the party, Madam. */
Page 19

C A T I L I # E. \ 9 Put. What party ? Has he no name ? Gal. "fts Qtintus Curit'.s. Ful. Did I not bid 'hem, fay, I kept my chamber? Gal. Why, fo they do. Sem. He leave you, Ftttvi*. Fid. Nay, good Sempronia, ftay. Sem. In faith, I will not. Ful. By /*, I would not fee him. SCM. 1'le not hinder you. Ful. tou know he will not be kept out, Madam. Sem. No, Nor (hall not, careful GdU, by my means. Ful. As I do live, Semyroma. Sem. What needs this ? ful. Go, fay, I am a fleep, and ill at eafe. Sem. By Cafiori no, Tie tell him you are awake ; And very well. Stay Galla ; Farewell Ftdvi* : I know my manners. Why do you labour, thus, With action, againftpurpofc : Qnna Cri&Hj^ She is, I faith, here, and in difpolition. Ful. Spight, with your courtefie ! How (hall I be tortur'd ! Curim, Futvia, Galla. W Here are you, fair one, that conceal your felf, And keep your your beauty, within locks and bars, here, Like a fools trenfure ? Ful. True, fhe was a fool, When, firft, (he (hew'd it to a thief. Cur. How, pretty fullennefs \ So harm, and fhort ? Ful. The fools artillery, Sir. Cur. Then, take my gown off, for th' encounter. Ful. Stay Sir. I am not in the mood. Cur. Tie put you into't. F/. Beft put your felf, i'your cafe again, and keep Your furious appetite warm, againft you have place for't. Cur. What do you coy it? Ful. No Sir. I'am not proud. Cur. I would you were. You think, this ftate becomes you ? By Hercules^ it do's not. Look i'your glafs, now, And fee, how fcurvily that countenance {hews ; You would be loth to own it. Ful. I (hall not chang it. Cur. Faith, but you muft ^ and flack this bended brow ; And (hoot lefs fcorn : there is a fortune coming Towards you, Dainty, that will take thee, thus, And fet thee aloft, to tread upon the head Gf her own ftatue, here, in Rows. Ful. I wonder, Who let this promifer in : Did^you, good diligence ? Give him his bribe, again. Of if you had none, Pray you demand him, why Ire-is fo ventr^ds, To prefs, thus, to my chamber, being forbidden, Both, bymyfelfv andfervants? Cwr.How! This's handfom ! And fomwhat a new drain ! Ful. 'Tis not fhain'd, Sir. 'Tis very natural. Cur. I have known it otherwife, Between the parties, though/ 'F*/'. For your fore-knowledge* Thank that, which. rhacteit. If will norbefo, Hereafter, I aflure you. C^.-'No, myMiftrefsB fttl. No, though you bring thefame materials, :G<r* Hiarme,
Page 20

ao CATILINE. You over aft when you mould under-do. A little call your felf again, and think. If you do this to pra<ftifc on me, or find At what forc'd diltance you can hold your fervant ; That it be an artificial trick, to enflame, And fire me more, fearing my love may need it, As, heretofore, you ha' done: why, proceed. Ful. As I ha' done heretofore ? Cur. Yes, when you'ld fain Your husbands jealoufie, your fervant watches, Speak foftly, and run often to the dore, Or to the window, from ftrange fears that were not ^ As if the pleafure were lefs acceptable, That were fecure. Fid. You are an impudent fellow. Cur. And, when you might better have done it, al the gate, To takenne in at the cafement. 'Fid. \ take you in ? Cur. Yes, you my Lady. And, then, being a-bed with you. To have your well taught waiter, here, come running, And,ciy, her Lord, and hide me without caufe, Crufh'dinacheft, or thruft upjna chimney. When .he;. tame crow* was winking 'at his farm ; Or, had he been here, and prefent, would have kept BoiheyesV and beak feal'd up, for fafcfterees. Ful. You have a fhnderous, beaftly, unwafh'd tongue, I'your rude mouth,' and favouring your fclf, Un-manner'd Lord, citr. How now ! Ful. It is your title, Sir. Who (fiuce you.ha' loft your own good name, and know not/ What oxfofc. more) care not, whofe honor you wound, Or fame you poifon with it'. You mould go, And vent your felf, i' the region, where you live, Among the fuburb : brothels, bawds, and brokers, Whither your broken fortunes have defign'd you. Cur. Nay, then 1 muft;ftop your fury, and.pJuck. TJie tragick vifor ofljV Come, Lady Cypri^ ' [_He offers to father, andfac .drtiws her K Know your own vertuos^tiiokly. Ilk not be Put to the wooirigx)f you thus, a-frefh, At every turn, for alllhcr^wbin^njC) Yeild, and be pliant ; cyrby / > :c/feAr4-rt-MHo.'w nmv r Will Lais turn a Lvcrfce ? >'/J No, butby.Crfr/?^, Hold ofFyoM^fa-vTifhQrJsiha'uds,! I ,peir<*e your heart, cHt /ie not be put ro3i.ijliuy.fel6> as fhd did. For you, fweet7V^. "What? do you fall .off? Nay, it.b^odrttesyou.graciofifly] Putn^tjop. You'I fooner draw your ^D&apbit.ort'me,, I. think it; ,7 Than on the Senat e ; who hiv c .cti ft 'y/ju. forth rdoefuiy r " io-be tbecomniQnly.tak & Of
Page 21

C A r 1 L I N E. *r Of the whole City ; bafe infamous man! For, were you other, you would there imploy Your defperate Dagger. Cur. Fuhia^ you do know The rtrengths you have upon me : do not ufe Your power too like a Tyrant : I can bear. Almoft until you break me. Ful, I do know Sin So do's the Senate^ too, know you can bear Cttr. By all the Gods, fat-Senate will fmart deep- For your upbraidings. I fhould be right forry To have the means fo to be vcng'd on you, (At leaft , the willj as I mail fhortly on-them. But go you on ftill, fare you well dear Lady : You could not ftill be fair, unlefs you where proud. You will repent thefe moods, and ere't be long, too. Ifliall ha* you come about, again. Ful. Do you think fo ? Cur. Yes, and I know fo. Ful. By what augury ? Cur. By the fair entrails of the matrons chefts, Gold, pearl, and jewels, here mRome, which Fufai& W ill then (but late) fay that me might have fhar'd : And grieving, mifs. Ful. Tut > all your promifed mountain?,." And feas, I am fo ftalely acquainted with- Cur. But, when you fee the univerfal floud Run by your coffers ; that my Lords, the Senators, Are fold for flaves, their wives for bond-women, Their houfes, and fine gardens given away^ And all their goods, under the fpear, at out-cry, And you have none of this ; but are ftill 'Fithia-, Or perhaps lefs, while you are thinking of it : . You will advife then, Coinefs with your cufliion. And look o' your fingers ; fay, how you were wifli'd j . Andfo, he left you. Ful. . Call him again, Galla: This is not ufiial ! fomthing hangs on this That [ mud win out of him. Cm. How now, melt you ? Ful. Come, you will laugh, now, at my eafmefs ! But 'tis no miracle : Doves, they fay, will bill,. After their pecking, and their murmuring. Cur. Yes, And then 'tis kindly. I would have my love Angry, fomtimes, to fweeten off the reft Of her behaviour. Fui. You do fee, I ftudy How I may pleafe you, then. But you think, Curias, Tis covetife hath wrought me : if you love me, Chang that unkind conceipt. Cur. By my lov'd foul, I love thee, like to it j and 'tis my ftudy, More than mine ow,it reveng, to- make thee happy. Ful. And 'tis that juft reveng, doth make me happy To-hsaryouprofecute^andwbich, indeed,
Page 22

22 C A T 1 L I N E. Hath won me to you, more, than all the hope Of what can elfe be proinis'd. I love Valour Better, than any Lady loves her Face, Or dreffing : than my felf do's. Let me grow Still, where I do embrace. But, what good means Ha 1 you I'effcd it ? Shall I know your project ? Cur. Thou malt, if thou'lt be gracious. Ful. As I can be. Cur. And wilt thoukifs me, then? Ful. Asclofe as (hells Of Cockles meet. Cur. And print 'hem deep? Ful. Quite through Our fubtle lips. Cur. And often ? Fid. \ Will fow 'hem Fatter, than you can reap. What is your plot : Cur. Why, now my Fuhta lookes, 1 ike her bright name ! And is her felf! Ful. Nay, anfwer me, your Plot: I pray thee tell me, Quivfus. Cur. I , thefe founds [She kifies and flatters him along ftiR. Become a Miftrefs, Here is harmony ! When you ate harfh, I fee, the way to bend you Is not with violence, but fervice. Cruel, A Lady is a fire : gentle, a light. Ful. Will you not tell me what I ask you ? Cur. All, That I can think, fweet love, or Hiy breaft holds, -He pour into thee. Ful. What is your defign then ? Cur. He tell thee ; Cat-line mall now be Conful : But, you will hear more fhortly. Fnl. Nay, my dear love Cur. He fpcak it, in thine armes, let us go in. Rome will be fack'd, her wealth will be our prize ; By publique ruinc, private fpirits muft rife. Chorus. Father Mars, and greater Jove, By whofe hig h aufpicc , Rome hath flood So long ; andfirjt vtds built in blood \>our great Nephnv, that then ftrovc Not with his brother, but your rites : J3e prefcnt to htr MVP, as then, And let not proud, and factious men Again ft your wills opfofs their mights. Our Confuls now, arc to be made 5 O, put it in the pitblique Voice , To make a free and worthy choice : Excluding fuch as would invade The common Wealth. Let whom ivc name Have Wtfdom, f ore-fight ^ j &e more with Ftith, WAnfAce.^
Page 23

CATILINE. And J9 ady confidence , above Fame. Such, as not feekjto get the ft art Inflate, by power, parts, or bribes," Ambition's bawds : but move the Tribes Hy Venue, Modcfty, Defert, Such as to juftice will adhere, What ever great one it offend ; And from the' embraced truth not bend For envy, hatred, gifts, or fear. That, by their deeds, will make it kgovgn, Whofe dignity they dofnftain And Life, State, Glory, all they gain, Count the republtqtte's, not their own. Such the old Bruti, Decii were The Cipi, Curtii, who did give Themselves for Rome : and would not line. As men, good, only for a year. Such were the great Camilli too The Fabii, Scipio's j that fti/l thought: No work-, at price enough, was bought^ That for their Countrey they could do.. And to her Honour fo did kgit j As all their acls were underftood :. The jinews of the publi^good : And they themf elves, onefonl, with it* Thife men were truly Magistrates ; Thefe neither praftu'dforce, nor formes :; Nor did they leave the Helm, in Storms] And fitch they are make happy fates. A<3 IIL Ciscro, Cato, Catulns, Antonms, Craffus, C&far, Chorus Liclors. GReat honors are great burdens : but, on whom They' are call with envy, he doth bear two loads. His cares muft ftill.be double to his joys, In any dignity ;, where if he err He finds no pardon : and, for doing weft A moft fmall praife, and that wrung out by. force. I fpcak this, Romans^ knowing what the weight Of the high charge, you' have trufted to me, is Not, that thereby I would vmh art decline
Page 24

*4 CATILINE* The good, or greatnefs of your benefit ; -for, I afcribe it to your fmgular Grace, And vow, to owe it to no title elfc, Except the Gods, that Cicero' is your ConfuL I have no urns j no duity Monuments j No broken Images of Ancestors Wanting an Ear, or Nofe ; no forged tables Of long defcents } to boaft falfe honors from : Or be my under-takers to your trull. But a new man ( as I am ftil'd in Rome) Whom you have dignified ; and more in whom Yo* have cut away, and left it opt- for vertue Hereafter, to that place : which our great men Meld (hut up, with all ramparts, for themfelves. Nor have but few of them, iu time been made \ourConfuh) fo ; new men, before me, none : At my firtt fuit, in my juft year ^ preferd To all competitors j and fome the nobleft Cra. Now the vein fwells. C*f. Up glory. Cic. And to have Your loud confents, for your own utter'd voices ; Not filent books : nor for the meaner Tribes, But firft, and laft, the univcrfal concourfe ! This is my Joy, my gladnefs. But my care, My induftry, and vigilance now muft work, That ftill your Councels of me be approv'd ; Both, by your felves and thofe to whom you have, With grudge, prefer'd me : two things I muft labour, That neither they upbraid, nor you repent you. For every lafp of mine will now be call'd Your error, if I make fuch. But my hope is, So to bear through, and out, the Confnl-{hip, -As fpite (lull ner'e wound you, though it may me. And for my felt, I have prepar'd this Itrength, To do fo well ^ as, if there happen ill Unto me, it (hall make the Gods to blufh : And be their crime, not mine, that I am envy'd. C&f. O confidence ! more new, than is the man ! Cic. I know well, in 'what terms I do receive The common-wealth, how vexed, hovV perplex'd : In which, there's not that mifchief, or ill fate, That good men fear not, wicked men exped not. I know, befide, fome turbulent prafHfes Already on foot, and rumors of more dangers- C,a. Or you wiH make them, if there be none. Cic. Lath I knovy 'twas this, which made the envy, and pride Quhc great Ryman bloud bate, and give way To
Page 25

C ATI LI HE. To my election. Cat. Marcus Tuttius, true ; Our need made thee our Confal, and thy vertue. C<zf. Cato, you will on-do him, with your prail'e, Cat*. C&far will hurthimfelf, with his own envy. Chor. The voice ofCato is the voice of Rome. Cato. The voice of Rome is the confent of heaven \ And that hath plac'd thee, Cicero^ at the helm, Where thou muft render, now, thy felf a man, And mailer of thy art. Each petty hand Can fteer a fhip becalm'd , but he that will Govern, and carry her to her ends, muft know* His tides, his currents ; how to fhift his fails j What fhe will bear in foul, what in fair weathers ; Where her fprings ore, her leaks j and how to flop 'hem ' 7 What fands, what (helves, what rocks do threaten her j The forces, and the natures of all winds, Gufts, ftorms, and tempefts ; when her keel ploughs hellj And deck knocks heaven : then, to manage her, Becomes the name, and office of a Pilot. Cic. Which Tie perform, with all the diligence, And fortitude I have, not for my year, JBut for my life ; except my life be lefs, And that my year conclude it : if it muft, Your will, lov'd Gods. This heart (hall yet employ A day, an hour is left me., fo, for Rome, As it mall fprmg a life, out of my death, To mine, for ever glorious in my facts. The vicious count their years, vertuous their acls. Chor. Moft noble ConfuL \ Let us wait him home. C<ef. Moft popular Conful he is grown, methinks ! Cra. How the rout cling to him ! Caf. And Cat leads 'hem ! Cra. You his colleague, Antoniw, are not look't on. Ant. Not I, nor do I care. C#f. He enjoys reft, And eafe, the while. Let th' others fpirit toil. And wake it out, that was infpir'd for turmoil. Catu. If all reports be true, yet, Caim C&far^ The time hath need of fuch a watch, and fpirit. Ce/. Reports ? Do you believe 'hem Catulfu, Why, he do's make r and breed 'hem for the people $ Tendear his fervice to 'hem. Do you not taft An art, that is fo common ? Popular men, They muft create ftrange monfters, and then quell 'hem ; To make their arts feem fomthing. Would you have Such an Hmfflcan aftor in the fcene, E And
Page 26

26 CATILINE. And not his Hydra ? They muft fweat no lefs. To fit their properties, than t' cxprefs their parts. Cra. Treafons, and guilty men are made in ftates Too oft, to dignifie the magiftrates. Catu. Thofe Itates be wretched, that arc forc'd to buy Their rulers fame, with their own infamy. Cra. We therefore, fhould provide that ours do not. C&f. That will Antomw make his care. Ant. \ ftpll. C<tf. And watch the watcher. Catu. Here comes Catiline. How do's he brook his late repulfe ? Cxf. I know not. But hardly fure. Cat . LongivM^ too, did (land ? Caf. At firft : but he gave way unto his friend. C am. Who's that come? LentulM ? C<tf. Yes. He is again Taken into the Senate. Ant. And made Viator. Cat. I know't. He had my fuffrage, next the Confnls' y True, you were there, Prince of the Senate^ then. Catiline^ Antoniw, Catnltts, C<cfar t Crajfiis, LonglnM 3 Lentulus. Tl Ail nobleft Romans. The moil worthy. Confnl^ l~l I gratulate your honor. Ant. I could wifh It had been happier, by your fellowfhip, Mod noble Scrgius, had it pleas'd the'people. Can. It did not pleafe the Gods ; who inftrufl the people : And their unqueftion'd pleafures muft be ferv'd. They know what's fitter for us, than our fclves-; And 'twere impiety, to think againft them. Catu. You bear it rightly, Lucius^ and, it glads me^ To find your thoughts fo even. Cati. I (hall ftill Study to make them fuch to Rome^ and heaven. (I would withdraw with you, a little, Julius. C*f. lie come home to you : Craffns would not ha* you. To fpeak to him, 'fore Quimw. Cantlw. Cati. I apprehend you.) No, when they (hall judg Honors convenient for me, 1 (hall have 'hem, With a full hand : / know it. /n mean time, They are no le r s part of the common-wealth, That do obey, than thofc, that do command. ditn. O<, let me kifs your fore-head, Lucius. How are you wrong'd ! Cati. By whom?CV///. Publike reporfc That gives you qut, to ilomack your repulfe ; . And brook it deadly. Cati. Sir, fhe brooks not me. Believe me rather, and your felf, now, of me : 7t is a kind of flander, to trult rumour. Cat it. /know it. And /could be angry with it. Cati. So may not I. Where it concerns Who's angry af a dander, makcs^it true.
Page 27

CATILINE. 27 Catft. Moft noble Sergius \ This your temper melts me. Cra. Will you do office to the,CV// QtantMt ? Cxf. Which Cato, and the rout have done the other? Catu. I wait, when he will go. Be ilill your felf. He wants noftate, or honors, that hath vertue. Cati. Did /appear fo tame, as this man thinks me ? Look'd I fo poor ? So dead ? So like that nothing, Which he calls vertuous ? O my breafr, break quickly ; An J fhew my friends my in-parts, left they think / have betraid 'hem. (Lon. Where's Gabinws ? Lcn. Gone. Lon. And VargHnteiwi /. Lcn. Slipt away ; all (hrunk : Now that he mift the Confnl-(hip.) Cati. I am The fcorn of bond- men j who are next to beads. What can / worfe pronounce my felf, that's fitter ? The Owl of Rome, whom boys and girles will hout! That were / fet up, for that woodden God, That keeps our gardens, could not fright the crows, Or the lead bird from muiting on my head. (Lon. Tis ftrange how he fhould mifs it. Lett, /s't not ffranger The upftart Cicero fhould carry it fo, By all confents, from men fo much his matters ? Lon. 'Tis true) Cati. To what a fhadow, /am melted 1 {Lon. Anton'ms wan it but by fome few voices.) Cati. Struck through, like air, and feel it not. My woundr Clofe fatter, than they're made. CLen. The whole defign, And interprife is loft by 't . All hands quit it, Upon his failj Cati. I grow mad at my patience, /t is a vifor that hath poifon'd rne. Would it had burnt me up, and /died inward : My heart fir (I turn'd to alhes (Lon. Here's Cethegtts yet.) Catiline, Cethegm, Lemultts, Longinus, Cato. REpulfe upon repulfe ? An in-mate, Confitl ? . That / could reach the axell, where the pins are, Which bolt this frame, that / might pull 'hem out, And pluck all into chaos, with my felf. Cet What, are we wifhing now ? Cati. Yes, my Cethegus. Who would not fall' with all the world about him ? Cet. Not /, that would (land -on it, when it falls ; And force new nature out, to make another. Thefe wifhings taft of woman, not of Roman. Let us feek other arms. Cati. What (hould we do ? Cet. Do r andnotwifh; fomething that wifiies take not : Sofudden, as the gods (hould not prevent, No, fcarce hav * time, to fear. Cati. O nob!e Cains I Cet. /t likes me better, that; you are not Conful. I would not go through open doors, but break 'hem ; E 2 Swim
Page 28

28 C J T 1 L I N E. Swim to my ends, through bloud ; or build a bridge Of carcafles j make on, upon the heads Of men, ftruck down, like piles ; to reach the lives Of thofe remain, and ftand : Then is't a prey, When danger ftops, and ruine makes the way. Cati. How thou doft utter me,brave foul, that may not, At all times, fhew fuch as I am ; but bend Unto occafion? Lcmitlus, this man, If all our fire were out, would fetch down new, Out of the hand of Jove } 'and rivet him To Caucaftt^ fhould he but frown , and let His own gaunt Eagle flie at him, to tire. Lev. Peace, here comes Cats. Cati. Let him come, and hear. I will no more diffemble. Quit us all; I, and my lov'd Cethegiu here, alone Will undertake this giants war, and carry it. Lev. What needs this, Lucius ? Lon. Sergim, be more wary. Cati. Now, MarcmCato, our new Confftt'sfpy, What is your fowre aufterity fent t'explore. Cato. Nothing in thee, licentious Catiline : Halters, and racks cannot exprefs from thee More, than thy deeds. Tisonly judgment waits thee. Cati. Whofe? Gate's? fhall he judge me ? Cato. No, the gods; Who, ever, follow thofe, they go not with : And Senate ,who, with fire, muft purge Tick Rome Of noifome citizens, whereof thou art one. Begone, orelfclctmc. Tis bane to draw The fame air with thee. Get. Strike him. Len. Hold, good Caiiu* Cet. Fear'ft thou not, Cato : Cato. Rafh Crtbeto*) no. Twcrc wrong with R.om, when Catiline and thou Do threat, \iCtto fear'd. .Cati. The fire you fpeak of If any flame of it approach my fortunes, lie quench it, not with water, but with ruine. Cato. You here this, Romans. Cati. Bear it to the Confnl. Gtt. I would have fent away his Soul, before him. You are too heavy, Ltntulw, and remifs ; It is for you we labour, and the Kingdom Promis'd you by the Sybili's. Cati. Which his Prstor-ftup, And fome fniall flattery of the Senate more, Will make him to forget. Len. You wrong me, Lucius. Lon. He will not need thefe fpurs. Cet. The action needs 'hem-. Thcfe things, when they proceed not, they go backward. Len. Let us confult then, Cet. Let us, firft, take arms. They that deny as juft things, now, will^ivc Ail that we ask ; if once they fee our fwords. Caj. Our objects rauft be fought with wounds, not words.
Page 29

CATILINE. Cicero Fulvia. IS there a heaven ? and gods ? and can it be They fhould fo flowly hear, fo flowly fee ! Hath Jove no thunder ? Or is Jove become Stupid as thou art ? O near wretched Rorxe, When both thy Senate, and thy gods do deep, And neither thine, nor thine own ftates do keep ! What will awake thee, heaven ? what can excite Thine anger, if this pra<fttce be too light ? His former drifts partakeof former times, But this laft plot was only Catilines. O, that it were his laft. But he, before Hath fafely done fo much, he'll ftill dare more. Ambition., like a torrent, ne're looks back ; And is a fwelling, and the laft affection A high mind can put off: being both a rebel Unto the foul, and reafon, and enforceth All laws, all confcience, treads upon religion j And offereth violence to natures felf. But,here, is that tranfcends it! A black purpofe To confound nature : and to ruine that, Which never age, nor mankind can repair I Sit down, good Lady j Cicero is loft /n this your fable : for, to think it true Tempteth my reafon. /t fo far exceeds All infolent fictions of the tragick/ow ! The common- wealth, yet panting, under-neath The ftripes, and wounds of a late civil war, Gafping for life, and fcarce reftor'd to hope, To feek t'opprefs her, with new cruelty, And utterly extinguifh her long name, Withfo prodigious, and unheard-of fiercenefs ! What fink of mon(ters,\v retches of loft minds, Mad after change and dcfp'rate in their ftates, Wearied, and gall'd with their neceffities, (For all this / allow them) durft have though it ? Would not the the barbarous deeds have been believ'd, Of Mantis, and Sylla, by our children, Without this fad had rife forth greater, for them ? All, that they did, was piety, to this! They, yet, but murdred kinsfolk, brothers, parents., Ravim'd the virgins, and, perhaps, fome matrons , They left the City (landing, and the temples : The gods, and majefty of Rome were fafe yet ! Thefe purpofe to fire it. to difpoile them, (Beyond the other evils) and lay waft The far-triumphed world : for, unto whom E 3
Page 30

jl CATILINE. Rome is too little, what can be enough ? F/. Tis true,my Lord,I had the fame difcourfe. Cic. And, then, to take a horrid facramcnt In human bloud, for execution Of this their dire defign; which might be call'd The height of wickednefs : but that, that was higher For which they did it ! Ful. I aflure your Lordfriip, The extreme horror of it almoft turn'd me To air, when firft I heard it j I was all A vapor, when 'twas told me : and I long'd To vent it any where. Twas fuch a fecret, I thought it would have burnt me up. Cic. Good Fnhta t Fear not your ad ; and lefs repent you of it. Ful. I do not, my good Lord. I know to whom I have utter'd it. Cic. You have difcharg'd it, fafely. Should Rome, for whom you have done the happy fervice, Turn moil ingrate ; yet were your vertue paid In confcience of the faft : fo much good deeds Reward themfelves. Ful. My Lord, I did it not To any other aim, but for it felf. To no ambition. Cic. You have learn'd the difference Of doing office to the publike weale, And private friend (hip: and have fhewn it, Lady. Be ftill your felf. I have fent for Quintus Curwt, And (for your vertuous fake) if I can win him, Yet, to the common wealth ; he (hall be fafe, too. Ful f 7le undertake, my Lord, he fhall be won. Cic. Pray you,joyn with me, then : and help to work him. Cicero, Littor, Fulvia, Curias. Tl Ow now? Is he come?L/c.He's here,my Lord.C/c. Go prefently, I Pray my colleague Antoniw, I may fpeak with him, About fome prefcnt bufmefs of the (late ; -And (as you go) call on my brother Ouimus, And pray him, with the Tribunes to come to me. Bid Canus enter. Fuhia, you will aid me ? Ful. h is my duty. Cic. O,my noble Lord ! /have to chide you, if fth,Give rncyour hand. Nay.,be not troubled; 'ifhall be gently, Cnrius. You look upon th ; s Lady?What ! do yOu guefs My btfinefc, yet ? Come, if you frown, / thunder : Ihcr cfore, put on your better looks,and thoughts. There's nought but fair, and good, intended to you.; And / would make thofe your complexion. Would you, of whom theSwwf* had that hope, A S on my knowledge, i: was in their purpofe, ^ T -'xt fitting, to reftore you : as they ha' done. The
Page 31

CATILINE. The ftupfd, and ungrateful Lentulw (Excufe me, that I name you thus, together, For, yet, you are not fuch) would you, I fay, A perfon both of bloud and honor, ftock't In along race of vcrtuous anceftors, Embark your felf for fuch a hellifh action, With parricides, and traitors ; men tucn'd/*n, Out of the wait, and ruine of their fortunes ? (For 'tis defpair, that is the mother of ma .nefs) Such as want (that, which all con pirators, But they>have firit) meer colour for their mifchief. O, I muft blufh with you. Come, you mall not labour To extenuate your guilt, but quit it clean ; Bad men excufe their faults good men will leave 'hem. He acls the third crime, that defends the firft. Herejs a Lady, that hath got the ftart. In pi"ty, of us all ; and for whofe vertue, I could almofr, turn lover, again : but that Terentia would be jealous. What an honor Hath me atchieved to her felf ! What voices, Titles, and loud applaufes will purfue her, Through ever ftreet ! What windows will be fill'd, To moot eyes at her ! What envy, and grief in matrons, They are not me ! when this her aft mall feem Worthier a Chariot, than if Pom ty came, With Afia chain'd ! .All this is, while (he lives. But dead, her very name will be a ftatue ! Not wrought for time, but rooted in the minds Of all pofterity : when brafs, and marble, /, and the Capirol it felf is duft ! Ful. Your honor thinks too highly of me. Cic. No /cannnot think enough. And / would have Him emulate you. 'Tis no fhame, to follow The better precedent. She fhewsyou, dtritt* t What claim your countrey layes to you : and what duty, You owe to it : be not afraid, to break With murderers nnd traitors, for the faving A life, fo n^ararui neceflary to you, As is your countrey 's. Think but on her right. No child can be too natural to his parent. She is our common mother ,and doth challeng The prime part of us ; do not ftop, but give it : He, that is v M i of fear, may foon be juft. And no religion binds men to be traitors. Ful. My Lord, he und. rilandsit : and will follow Your Civingcounfel : but (hame, yet, Hayes him*
Page 32

3* CATILINE. I know, that he is coming. Cur. Do you know it ? Ful. Yes,let me fpeak with you.CV.O you are jFWAVhat am I ? Cur. Speak not fo loud. ful. I am, what you fhould be. Come, do you think, I'ld walk in any plot, Where Madam Semproni* fliould take place of me, And Fttlvia come i' the rcre , or o' the by ? That I would be her fecond ; in a bufmefs, Though it might vantage me, all the Sun fees ? It was a filly phant'fie of yours. Apply Your felf to me, and the Conful, and be wife ; .Follow the fortune I ha' put you into : You may be fomthing this way, and with fafety. Cic. Nay, I mud tolerate no whifperings, Lady. Ful. Sir, you may hear. I tell him, in the way, Wherein he .was, how hazardous his courfe was. Cic. How hazardous ? how certain to all ruinc ? Did he, or do, yet, any of them imagine The gods would fleep, to fuch a Stygtan praftice, Againft that common-wealth, which they have founded With fo much labour, and like care have kept, Now near feven hundred years ? It is a madnefs, Wherewith heaven blinds 'hem, when it would confound 'hem, That they fliould think it. Come, my Curias, I fee your nature's right ; you fhall no more Be mention'd with them : I will call you mine, And trouble this good fhame, no farder. Stand Firm for your countrey ; and become a man Honor'd, and lov'd. It were a noble life, To be found dead, embracing her. Know you, What thanks, what titles , what rewards tne Senate Will heap upon you, certain, for your fervice ? Let not a defperate action more engage you, Than fafety (hould : and wicked friendfhips force What honefty, and vertue cannot work. Ful. He tells you right,fwect fri :nd:'Tis faving counfcl. Cur. Moft noble Conful^ I am yours, and hers, I mean my countrey's : you* have form'd me new. Infpiring me, with what I fliould be, truly. And I intreat, my faith may not feem cheaper For fpringing out of penitence. Cic. GoodCwuis, It frnll be dearer rather, and becaufe Il'd make it fuch, hear, how I truft you more. Keep frill your former face : and mix again With thefe loft fpirits. Run all their mazes with 'hem : For fuch are Treasons. Find their winding out, And fubtlc turnings j watch their fnaky ways, Through
Page 33

CATILINE. Through brakes, and hedges, into woods of da rknefs, Where they are fain to creep upon their breafts In paths- ne're trod by men, but wolves, and panthers,' Learn, befide Catiline, Lenndu^ and thofe, Whole names I have ; what new ones they draw in'j Who elfe are likely ; What thofe great ones are, They do not name ; what wayes they mean to take : And whither their hopes point : to war, or ruiney- By fome furprize. Explore all their intents, And what you find may profit the republique. Acquaint me with it, -either, by your felf, Or this your friend, on whom I lay The care of urging you. He fee, that Rome Shall prove a thankful, and a bounteous mother : Be fecret, as the night. Cur. And conftant, Sir. Cic. I do not doubt it. Though the time cut off All vows. The dignity of truth is loft, With much proteiting, Who is there f This way. Left you be feen, and met. And when you come, Be this your token, to this fellow. Light 'hem. Hffevphifpers with t>im t O Rome) in what a ficknefs art thou fallen f How dangerous, and deadly ! when thy head Is drown'd in fleep, and all thy body fev'ry ! No noife, no pulling, no vexation wakes thee< ? Thy lethargy is fuch or if by chance, Thou heav'ft thy eye-lids up, thou doft forget Sooner, than thou wert told, thy proper danger. I did un-reverendly, to blame the gods, Who wake for thee, though thou fhore to thy felf. Is it not ftrange, thou fhould'ft be fo difeas'd, Andfofecure? But more, that the firftfymptomes Of fuch a malady, mould not rife out From any worthy member, but a-bafc And common ftrumpet,- worthlefs to be nam'd A hair, or part of thee ? Think, think hereafter, What thy needs were, when thou rnuft ufe fuch means ./4nd lay it to thy breaft, hafte much the gods Upbraid thy foul negleA of them ; by making So vile a thing, the author of thy fafety. They could have wrought by nobler wayes : have (truck Thy foes with forked Ijghtnfng ; or ram'd thundery Thrown hills upon 'hem, in the a'cl: ; have fent Death, like a damp, . to all their families ; Or caus'd their conferences to burft 'hem. But, When they will (hew thee, what thou art, and make
Page 34

34 CATILINE. A fcornful difference 'twixt their power, and thee, They help thee by fuch aids, as geefe, and harlots. How now ? What anfwer ? Is he come ? Lie. Your brother, Will flreight be here ; and your colleague Antonws Said, colaly, he would follow me. Cic. I that Troubles me fomwhat. and is worth my fear.. He is a man, 'gainft whom I mud provide, That fas he'll do no good) he do no harm,. He, though he be not of .the plot; will like it, And wifli it mould proceed . for, unto men, Preft with their wants, all change is ever welcoin. I muft with offices, and patience win him j Make him by art, that which he is not born, A friend unto the publique } and beftow The Province on him j which is by the Senate Decreed to me : that benefit will bind him ; 'Tis well, if fome men will do well for price : So few are vertuous, when the reward's away. Nor muft I be unmindful of my private ; For which I have call'd my brother, and the tribunes^ My kins-folk, and my clients to be near me : He that Hands up 'gainft traitors, and their ends, Shall need a double guard, of law, and friends : Efpecially, in fuch an envious irate, That fooncr will accufe the magiftrate, Than the delinquent ; and will rather grkve The treafon is not acted, thunbeleve Ccrfar, Catiline. T He night grows on ; and you are for your meeting * lie therefore end in few. Berefolute, And put your enterprife in aft : the more Aftions of depth, and danger areconfider'd, The lefs afTuredly they are performed. And thence it hapneth, that the braved plots (Not executed ftraight) have been difcover'd. Say, you are conftant, or another, a third, Or more , there may be yet one wretched fpirit, With whom the fear of punimment (hall work; Bove all the thoughts of honor, and revenge. You arc not, now, to think what's 'beft to do, As in beginnings ; but, what rmift be done, Being thus entred : and flip no advantage That may fecure you. i,et them call it mlfchief. When it is paft, and profper'd, 'twill be vertuc. Th'are petty crimes, are punifli'd, great rewarded Nor muft you think of peril , fince attempts, Begun-,
Page 35

C VI T I L I N E* Begun with danger, ftill do end with glory : And, when need fpurs, defpair will be cali'd wifdom, Lefs ought the care of men , or fame to fright you -, For they, that win, do feldome receive mame Of victory : how ere it be atchiev'd ; And vengeance, leaft. For who, befieg'd with wants, Would flop at death, or any thing beyond it? Come, there was never any great thing, yet, Afpired, but by violence, or fraud: And he that flicks (for folly of a confcier.ce) To reach it Cat . Is a good religious fool. Cc/~. A fuperftitiousflave, and will die bead. Good night. You know what Crajfos thinks, and I, By this : Prepare you wings, as large as fails. To cut through air, and leave no print behind you. A ferpent, ere he comes to be a dragon, Do's eat a bat : and fo muft you a CV/W, That watches. What you do, do quickly Sergittt. You fhall not ftir for me. Cat. Excufe me, lights there. C<c/!By no means Cat. Stay then All good thoughts to <efar 9 And like to Craffus. C&f. Mind but your friends counfeli. Catiline^ Anreli(t y Lecca. OR, I will bear no mind. How now, Attrelia ? Are your confederates come ? the Ladies ? Aur. Yes, Cat. Artd is Semproaia there ? Aur. She is. Cat That's weB. She has afulphurous fpirit, and will take Lightatafpark. Break with them, gentle love, About the drawing as many of their husband, Into the plot, as can : if not, to trid 'hem. That'll be the eafier practice, unofome, Who have been tir'd with 'hern long. Sollicite Their aids, for money : and their fervants help, In firing of the city, at that time Shall be defign'd. Promife 'hem ftates, and empires, And men, for lovers, made of better clay, Than ever the old potter Titan knew. WHO'S that ? O, Porcius Lecca } are they met ? Ltc. They are all here.c<zr.Love,you have your inftruclionf lie truilyou with the fluff you have to work on. You'll form it ? Porcius^ fetch the filver eagle I ga' you in charge. And pray 'hem they will enter. Catiline,
Page 36

I JX j Cetbegus, CUTJHS, Lent-ulus^ Vargu.vteiH^Lwginits> Gabinius, Cepanus^ Antronius, &c. O, Friends, your faces glad me. This will be Ourlaft, I. hope, of confutation. Get. So it had need, Cur. We lofe occafion, daily. C/K . I, and our meajis : whereof OBC, wounds me mofl, That was the faireft. Pifo is deaeb 4n Spam. Cet. As we are,here. Lon. And.as it isthought,by-envy Of Pompefs followers, Len. He too's coming back, Now., out of Afia. Cat. Therefore, what we intend, We mult be-fwift it. Take your feats, and hear, I have, already, fent Sept Into the Picene territory ; To raife force, for us, in Manilas at Fefala, is (by this time) up, W ith the old needy troops, that follow'd Sylla : Andall do but txpeft, when we will give The blow^at home./ Behold this fflver eagle, Twas yl/4>jftandard, in the Cimbfian war, Fatall to Rom? ; and, as our augures tell me, Shall ftill be fo : for which one ominous caufc, 1' have kept it fafe, and done it facred rites, As to a ged-head, iiv-a chappel built OfpiJrfitffe.to.it. Pledg -then all your- hands, To follow it, with vows oftJeatn.j and ruine, Struck filently, and'h'orne! So waters fpeak When they run deepcft.' Now's the time, this year,- " The twenti'th from the firing of the Capitol, As fatal too, to Rome, by aH pf editions : And, in which, hono<i />>#/////*. rnwll rife A King, ifhepurfiK . If he do not, He is not worthy the great deftiny. Len. It is too great for fiie, but what the godsj And their great loves decree me, I mufl: not Seem carelefs of. Cat . No, nor we envious. We have enoug!\beJideyall Gaffta, Bclgia. ce ftyl&Hfrlid ^frickl Cat, I, and dfi Greece lHfrlid ^frickl Cat, I, and dfiatQO, Now Pompey is returning; CAt. Nobleft 'Romances, Methinks our looks, are 'hot To-quick and high, As they were wont. Cur. No ? whofe is not ? Cat.. We have No anger in our eyes, no ftorm, no lightning : Our hate is fpent, and fum'd away in vapour> Before our hands be at work. I can accufe Not. anyone, butallofflack%f. Cct. Yesj
Page 37

C A TIL I N j?. 37 Ahdbeyourfelffuch, while you do it. Cat. Ha? Tis fharply anfwer'd, Cains, Get. Truly, truly. Len. Come, let us each one know his part to do, And then be accus'd. Leave thefe untimely quarrels. Cur. I would there were more Romes than- one, to ruin, (natures, Cet. More Romes ? More worlds. Cur. Nay, then, more gods, and If they took part. Len. When fhall the time be firft ? Cat. I think the Satitrnals. Cet. 'Twill be too long. Cat. .They are not now far off, 'tis not a month. Cet. A week, a day, an hour is too far off, Now, were the fitted time. Cat. W ha'notkid All things fo fafe, and ready. Cet. While, we'are laying,: We mall all lye, and grow to earth. Would I Were nothing m it, if not now. Thefe things They mould be done,e're thought. Cat. Nay, now your reafou Forfakes you, Cains. Think, but what commodity That time will miniftcr-; the Cities cuftome, Of being, then, in mirth, andfeaft Len. Loos'd whole /n pleafufe and fecurity Ant. Each houfe Refolv'd in freedom Cur. Every (lave a matter- Lon. And they toc^ no mean aids -Cur. Made from their hope- . Of liberty 'Len. Or hate unto their lords. Far. Tis fure, there cannot be a time found out . More apt, and natural. Len. Nay, goodCethegut, . Why do your paffions, now, d ilturb our hopes ? Cet. VVhy do your hopes delude your certainties ? Cat. , You muft lend him his way. Think, for the order, Andprocefs of it. Lon Yes, Len. /like not fire: 'Twill too much waft my-City. CV, Were it embers, . There will be wealth enough, rak't out of them, To fpring anew. It mult be fire, or nothing. Lon. What elfe fhould fright, or terrifie 'hem ? Par. True, /n that confufion, muft be the chief (laughter. Cur. Then we mail kill 'hem braveil. C-ep. ^nd in- heaps. Slut . Strew facrifices, C//r, Make the earth an altar. Lw. And Rome the fire. Lee. Twill be a noble night. Var. ^nd worth all -Syllas days. CHT. When husbands, wives, Grandfires, and nephews, fervants, an-d their lords, Virgins, and prieils, the infant, and the nurfe, Go all to hellj together in a fleet. Cat. I would have you, Lo.-giniis^w&StatiUuS) To take the charge o'the firing, which muft be, At a fign given with a trumpet, done In twelve chief places of the City, . at once, The flax, and f^Fphur, are already laid' ' Irij at Cetktjfa houie/ -So-are the weapofis.
Page 38

CATILINE. J, you, with other force (hall ftop The pipes, and conduits : and kill thofe that come For water, Cnr. What (hall I do ? Cat. All will have Employment, fear not . Ply the Execution. Cw. For that, truft me, and Cethegtu. Cat. I will b At hand, with the army, to meet thofe that fcape. And Lenndus, begirt you Pornpey's houfc, To feize his fons alive : for they are they Muft make our peace with him. All clfe cut off, As Tarqui-'ic did the poppy-heads ; or mowers A field of thirties ; or elfe, up, asploughes Do barren lands ; andftrike together flints, ArA clods ; th'ungratful Senate^ and the people : TillnoTage, gone before, or coining after, May weigh-Avith yours, though horror leapt her felf Into the fcale ; but, in your violent a<fts, The fall of torrents, and the noife of tempefts, The boyling ofCharybdv, the feas wilenefs, The eating force of flames, and wings of winds, Be all out-wrought, by your tranfcendent furies. It had been done, e'rc this, had I been Conful ; We had had no (top, no let. Len. How find you Antonitu ? Cat. The other ha s wonne him, loft : that Cicero Was born to be my oppofition, ^4nd ftands in all our ways Cur. Remove him fir/I. Cct. May that, yet, be done fooner ? Cat . Would it were doae. Chr. V*r. I'll do't. Or. It is my province ; none ufurpe it. Len. What are your means ? Of. Enquire not. He {hall dye. Shall, u x as too flow ly faid. He is dying. That Is, yet/tooflow. He is dead. Cat. Brave, only Romans f Whofe foul might be the worlds foul, were that dying j Refufe not, yet, the aids of thefe your friends. Len. Here's Va.rguvtsiw holds goo i quarter with him. Cat. slnd under the pretext of clientele, ./4nd vifitation, with the morning hail, Will be admitted. Or. What is that to me far. Yrs, we may kill him in his b.dj andfifely. Cet. Saf is your way, then; take it. Mine's mine own. Cat Follow him, Fargunttiut, and perfvvade, The morning is the fitteft time. Lon. The night Will turn aU into tumult Len. AK& perhaps MifTo of him too. Cat. Intreat, and conjure him, In allour names Len. Byallourvows, and friendftiips. Sempronia, Au^eli, ffihla. [To them. VT / Hat ! is our counfel broke Up firft? ^r.-.Vou fay, V V Women are greateft talkers, Sem. We ha done j
Page 39

CATILINE. 2 ufodarenowfitforaftions. Lon. Which is paffion. There's your beft activity, Lady. Sew. How Knows your wife fatnefs that ? Lon. Your mothers daughter Did teach me, madam. Cct. Come Semprovia, leave him : He is a giber. And our prefent bufmefs Is of more ferious confequence. Aurelra. Tells me, you have done molt mafculincly within, -^nd plaid the orator. Sem. But we muft haften To our defign as well, and execute : Not hang ftill, in the fever of an accident. Cat. You fay well, Lady. Sem. I do like our plot Exceeding well, 'tis fure ; and we mall leave Little to fortune, in it. Cat. Your banquet flays. Aurelia, take her in. Where's Fuhia ? Sem. O, the two lovers are coupling. Cur. In good faith, She's very ill, with fitting up. Se >./. Youl'd have her Laugh, and lye down ? FuL No, faith, Scmfronia, I am not well: Tie take my leave, it draws Toward the morning : Curias mall ftay with you. Madam, I pray you, pardon me, my health Imuftrefpecl. Ant. Farewell, goodFttlvia. Cur. Make haft & bid him get his guards about him. f Curt, vs/bif* For Pargunteius > and Cornelius <pers this to Have undertain it, mould Cethegtts mifs ; {Ftilvia* Their reafon, that they think his open rathnefs Will fuffer eafier difcovery, Than their attempt, fo vailed under friendfhip. Ik bring you to your coach. Tell him, betide, OfC'tfars coming forth, here. Cat. My fweet madam, Will you be gone ? ful. I am, my Lord, in truth, In fome indifpofition. Cat. I do wifh You had all your health, fweet Lady : Lemnlus, Y.ou'Jdoherfervice. Len. To her coach, and duty. Catiline. WHat miniftcrs men muft, forpradlice, ufe! The rafh, th' ambitious, needy, defperate, Foolifh, and wretched, ev'n the dregs of mankind, To whores, and women ! ftill, it maft be fo, Each have their proper place ; and x in their rooms, They are the beft. Grooms fittteft kindle fires. Slaves carry burthens, Butchers are for {laughters, Apothecaries Butlers, Cooksfor poifbns ^ As thefe for me : dull, ftup'd Lentulus, My ftale, with whom I ftalk ; the ra(h Cethegtts, My Executioner ; and fat Longinns r SratiUus* QuriKs* Ceparitts, Qm^er-
Page 40

4<* CAT I L I N , My-Labourers, Pioners, and Incendiaries ; With thefe domeftick Traytors, boforn Theeves, Who rricuftome hath call'd wives; the readied helps, To betray.heady husbands ; rob the eafie : And lend the moneys, on returns of lull. Shnll Catiline not do, now, with thefe aids, So fought, fo forted, fornething (hall be call'd Their labour but his profit ? and make C<tf#r Repent his ventring counfels, to a fpirit, So much his Lord in mifchief ? when all thefe, Shall, like the brethren fprung of dragons teeth, Ruin each other ; and he fall amongft 'hem : With Craffus, lomyey, or who elfe appears, But like, or near a great one. May my brain Refolve to water, and my bloud turn phlegmc, My hands drop off, unworthy of my fword, And that b'infpired, of it felf, to rip My breft,for my loft entrails ; when I leave A foul, that will not ferve : and who will, are The fame with flaves, fuch clay I dare not fear. The cruelty, Imeantoad, I wifli Should be. call'd mine, and tarry in rny jiame ; Whii'ft, after- rages do toil out themfelvcs, In thinking for the like, but do it lefs : And, were the power of all the fiends let loofe, With fate to boot, it mould be, ftill example. When, what the GW, or -Macr could not efFeft, Nor emulous Carthage^ with their length of fpight. Shall be the work of one, and that my night. Cicero, Ful-via, Qnintus. I Thank your vigilance. Where's my brother,.Q//;;///j ? Call i-ll my fervants up. Tell noble Curing _/4nd fay it to your felT you are my favers ; But that's too little Tor you., you are Rams : What could I then, 'hope Icfs ? O brother ! now, The engines I told you of, are working ; The matchinc'gin's to move. Where are your weapons ? Arm all my houfe-hold prefently. And charge The porter, he let no man in, till day. . ^/z.Not clients, and your friend ? Cic. They were thofc names, That come to murther me. Yet fend for Catv, AndQiiintus Catulns ; thofe I dare truft : And Flaccfts, ' and Pomtinuu, the Pr<etors, By the back way. .Q. Take care, good brother Manas, Your fears be not form'd greater than they fhould ; And make your friends grieve, while your enemies laugh. , Cic.
Page 41

CATILINE. 41 'Cic. 'Tis brothers counfel, and worth thanks. But do As Intreat you. I provide, not fear. Was Ca>far there, fay you ? Ful. Cttriut fays, he met him Coining from thence. Cic. O, fo. And, had you a counfd Of ladies too ? Who was your fpeaker, Madam ? Ful. She that would be, had there been forty mere ; Sempronia, who had both her greek arid figures - And, ever and anone, woald ask us, if The witty Ccnfnl could have mended that ? Or Orator Cicero could have faid it better ? Cic. She's my gentle enemy. Would Ccthcgw Had no more danger in him. But, my guards Are you, great powers ; and th'unbated ftrengths Of a firm confcience, which (hall arm each tlep Tane for the ftate, and teach me flack no pace For fear of malice. How now, brother? Qui. Cats, And Quintits Catulns were coming to you, And Crafliu with 'hem. I have let 'hem in, By th'garden. Cic. What would Crafiu have ? Qui. I hear Some whifpering 'bout the gate ; and making doubt, Whether it be not yet too early, or no ? But I do think, they are your friends, and clients, Are fearful to difturb you. Cic. You will change To'another thought anone. Ha'you giv' ( n the porter The charge, I will'd you ? QM. Yes. Cic. VVithdraw, and hearken. Fargumeius, Cornelius, Porter, Ciccrt, CatOj Catttlits, Crajfus. THe dore's not open, yet. Or. You were beft to knock. Far. Let them ftandclofe, then : And when we are in, Rum after us. -Cor. But where's Cetkegut ? l r *r. He Has left it, fmce he might not do't his way. For. Who's there ? Van. A friend, or more. For. I may not let Any man in, till day. Far. No? why? Cor. Thyreafon? Per. I am commanded fo. Var. By whom ? Cor. I hope We are not difcover'd. Far. Yes. by revelation, Pray thee good flavc, who has commanded thee ? For. He thctt may beft, the Covful. Far. We are his friends. Fur. All's one. Cor. Beft give your name. Far. Do'ft thouhear, I have fome inllant bufmefs with the Confitl. (fellow ? My name is Farguntcitts. Cic. True, he knows it j rCicrofpeaks -xfrid for what friendly office you arc fcnt. < to thea^from C'rneliui, too, is there ? Far. We arebetraid. ^(Woi>s. Cic. AK& defperate Ctth-gtu, is he not ? Far. Speak you, he knows my voyce. Cic. What fay you to't ? Cor. You are deceived, fir. Cic. No, 'tis you are fo j Poor, mif-led men. Your dates are yet worth pity, G If
Page 42

42 C A r T L I N E. If you would hear, and change your favage minds, Leave to be mad ; forfake your purpofes Of treafon, rapine, murder, fire, and horror : The commonwealth hath eyes, that wake as fliarply Over her life, as yours do for her ruin. Be not deceiv'd, to think her lenity Will be perpetual ; or, if men be wanting, The gods will be, to fuch a calling caufe. Confider your attempts, and while there's time, Repent you of 'hem. It doth make me tremble. There mould thofe fpirits yet breath, that when they cannot LivehoneAly, would rather perifh bafely. Cats. You talk too much to 'hem, Marcus, they are loft. Go forth and apprehend 'hem. Catu. If you prove This practice, what fhould let the commonwealth To take due vengeance ? Var. Let us fhift away. Toe darknefs hath conceal'd us, yet. We'l fay Some have abus'd our names. Cor. Deny it all. Cato. Quint it*) what guards ha' you ? Call the Tribunes aid, And raife the City. Confttl, you are too mild, The foulnefe of fome fa els takes thence all mercy : Report it to the Senate. Hear : The gods C It thunders.. Grow angry with your patience. Tis their care, \and lightens And muft be yours, that guilty men efcape not. jviolentlyon As crimes do grow, juftice fliould roufc it felf. {the fuddairi.. Chorus. WHat is it) heavens , you prepare Withfo much fwiftnefs andfofuddain rifin^ ? There are no fans of earth that dare, Again, rebellion ? or the i ods furfrifing ? T,je world doth _//.'<*%, <wd natures fears, Tet is the turrutlt, and the horror greater \Vtihin our mindS) than in our cars :. (kcr. So much Romes/Wtt (vow grown her fate') do threat Thefriefts, and people run about y Each order , age^ and fix atna^d at other ; And at the ports, all thronging cut, As if their fafety were to quit their mother : Yet find they the fame dangers there, trom Vfhich they make fuch haft to he f referred ^ For guilty ft ates do ever bear The flaguts about them, which they have deftrvcd. ' , till thofe ft agues do get above Tk;
Page 43

CATILINE. The mountain of onr faults, and there do fit We fee hem not. Thus, ftill we love 'The evil we do, until wefujfer it. But, mo ft, Ambition, that near vice To -vert ite, hath the fate of Rome frovcked^ And made, that now Rome's/^//* no price, To free her from the death, wherewith fie s yoked. That reftlefs til, that ftill doth build Upon fttccefs j and tnds net in afpiring : But there begins. And ne'r is fill d, While ought remains thatfeems bttt worth defir ng* Wherein the thought, unlik* the eye, To which things far , feem [mailer than they are, Deems all contentment plac'd on high : And thinks there's nothing great , but what is far. O, that in time, Rome did not caft Her errors up, this fortune to prevent ; Thave feen her crimes ere they were pa ft : Ana felt her faults, before her pttnifoment. Aft TV C Divers Se- **** L V ' \nators pafs 'and bling* CAn thefe men fear ? who are not only ours, But the worlds matters ? Then I fee, the gods Upbraid our fuffrings, or would humble them j By fending thefe affrights, while we are here : That we might laugh at their ridiculous fear, Whofe names, we trembled at, beyond the Alpes, Of all that pafs, I do not fee a face Worthy a man ; that dares look up, and (land One thunder out : but downward all, like beafts, Running away from every flam is made. The falling world could not deferve fuch bafenefs Are we emploid here, by our miferies, Like fuperftitious fools (or rather (laves) To plain our griefs, wrongs, and oppreflfions, To a meer clothed Senate, whom our folly Hath made, and ftill intends to keep our tyrannes ? It is our bafe petitionary breath That blows'hern to this greatnefs; which this prick Would foon let out, if we were bold, and wretched. When they have taken all we have, our goods, G 2 Crop,
Page 44

44 " #"--* f-f-L I tf E. Crop, lands, and houfes, they will leave us this. A weapon, and an arm will iHH be found, Though naked left, and lower than the ground. CatOjCatftltis, Cicero, Allobroges; DO; urge thine anger, ftill r good heaven, and jtift. Tell guilty men, what powers are above them. In fuch a confidence of wickednefs, Twas time, they mould know fomething fit to fear. Cattt. I never faw a morn more full of horror. Cato. To Catiline, and his :. But, to juft men, Though heaven would fpeak-, with all his wrath at once- That, with his breath, the hinges of the world Did crack, we mould ftand upright, and unfear'd. Cic. Why, fo we do, good Cato. Whobethefe? Catu. Ambafladors, from the Attobroges y I take 'hem, by their habits. All. I, thefc men Seem of another race ; let's fue to thefe. There's hope of juftice, with their fortitude.. Cic. Friends of the Senate, zntiofRome, today We pray you to forbear us : on the morrow What fute you have, let us, by Fabim Sanga, (Whofe patronage your ftate doth ufe) but know it, And, on the Corel's word, you mall receive Difpatch, or elfe an anfwer, worth your patience. All. We could not hope for more.moft worthy ConpU. This magilrate hath ftruck an awe into me, And, by his fweetnefs, wonne a more reguard Unto his place, than all the boyftrous moods That ignorant greatnefs praclifeth, to fill The large, unfit authority it wears. How eafie is a noblell fpirit difcern'd From harm, and fulphurous matte^ that flies out In contumelies, makes anpife, andftinkes! May we find good, and great men : that know ho\^ Toiloopto warrts, and meet neceffities, And will not turn from any equal fuits. Such men, they do not-fuccour more the caufe, They undertake, with favour, and furcefs ; Then, by it, their own judgments they do raife, In turning juft uiens needs, into their praife. The Senate. *T) K*. Room fer the Confnls. Fathers, take your places, Here, in the hqufc of jitptter , tire Stayer, By edift from the Cerrfal, Marcus TuHius. You are met a frequent Senate. Hear him fpeak. Cjc. What way ve'fotpffi 'iwd -jttifpicioHS-ftitt
Page 45

C A T 1 t I N E. TV Rome, tndhers. Honor'd, and confcript Fathers If I were filent, and that all the dangers Threatning the ftate, and you, were yet fo hid In night, or darknefs thicker in their brefts, That are the black contrivers; fo, that no Beam of the light could pierce 'hem : yet the voice Ofheav'n, this morning, hath fpoke loud enough, T' inftrucl you with a feeling of the horror ; And wake you from a fleep, as fork, as death, I have of late, fpoke often in this Senate^ Touching this argument, but ftill have wanted Either your ears, or faith : fo incredible Their plots have feem'd, or I fo vain, to make Thefe things for mine own glory, and falfe greatnefs, As hath been given out. But be it fo. When they break forth, and fhall declare themfelves, By their too foul effecls, then, then, the envy Of my juft cares will find another name. For me, I am but one : and this poor life, So lately aim'd at, not an hour yet fince, They cannot with more eagernefs purfue, Than I with gladnefs would lay down, and lofe, To buy Romes peace, if that would purchafe it. But when I fee, they'ld make it but the ftep To more, and greater } unto yours, Romes , all : I would with thofe preferve it, or then fall. C<ff. I, I , let you alone, cunning artificer ! See, how his gorge t'peers above his gown ; To tell the people, iu what danger he was, It was abfurdly done off^r*fftoWr To namehimfelf, before he was got in.-. Cra. It matters not, fojhey deny it all: : And can but carry the lye conftantly. Will Crff/Ym' be here ? C*/. I have fent for him. Cra. And ha' you bid him to be confident ? C<cf. To that his own neceffky will prompt him. Craf. Seem to believe nothing at all, that Citero Delates us. Crf/. It will mad him. Cra. O, and help The other party. Who is that ? his Brother ? What new intelligence ha's he brought him now ? C*f. Some cautions from his wife, how to behave him. ( Cic. Place fome of them without, and fome bring in. \Cicero Thank their kind loves. Iris a comfort yet, ^.bring in That all depart not from their Countries caufe. ~\the-. Tn~ C*/. How now,what means this mufter?O/^ j4ntonins?/bnnes } & Ant. I tfo not know, ask my colleague, he'll tell you. (, Guards. There:
Page 46

4<? CATILINE. There is fome rcafon m ftate, that I muft yield to ; And I have promis'd him : Indeed he has bought it, With giving me the Province, Cic. I profefs, It grieves me, Fathers, that I am compell'd To draw thefe Arms, and Aids for your defence ; And more, againft a Citizen of Rome^ Born here amongft you, a Patrician, A man, I mult confefs, of no mean houfe, Nor no fmall vertue, if he had employ'd Thofe excellent gifts of fortune, ami of nature, Unto the good, not ruin of the State. But, being bred in's Fathers needy fortunes, Brought up in's Sifters proftitution, Confirm'd in civil flaughter, entring firft The Common wealth with murder of the Gentry ; Since, both by ftudy and cu dome, converfant With all licentioufncfs ; what could he hop'd In fuch a Field of Riot, but a courfe Extreme pernicious ? Though, I muft proteft, I found his mifchiefs, fooner, with mine eyes, Than with my thought } and with thefe hands of mine, Before they touch'd, at my fufpicion. C&f. What are his mifchiefs, Conful ? you declame Againft his manners, and corrupt your owne : No wife man mould, for hate of gulitie men, Lofe his owne innocence. Cic. The noble C<efar Speaks god-like truth. But, when he hears, I can Convince him, by his manners, of his mifchiefs, He might be filcnt : and not caft away His fentences in vainc, where they fcarce look Toward his fubject Cato.. Here he comes himfelf. If he be worthy any good mans voyce, f Catiline pts That good man fit down by him : Cato will not. <dovw 3 & Cato Cat it. If Cato leave him,rle not keep afide. {rifts from him Cati. What face is this, the S' nate here puts on, Againft me, Fathers'* Give my modeftie Leave, to demand the caufe of fo much ftrangenefle. Caf. It is reported here, you are the head To a ftrange faction, Lmitu : Cic. I, and will Be prov'd againft hinx Cart. Let it be. Why, Conful t If in the common- wealth, there be two bodies, One lean, weak, rotten, and that hath a head ; The other ftrong, and healthfull, but hath none : If I doe give it one, doe I offend ? Reftore your felves unto your temper, Fathers ; And without pertur bation, hear me fpeak. Remember
Page 47

CATILINE- 47 Remember who I am, and of what place, What petty fellow this is, that oppofes ; One, that hath exercis'd his eloquence, Still to the bane of the uobilitie : A boafting-jinfolent tongue-man. C4f0.Peace,leud traytor, Or wafti thy mouth. He is an honeft man And loves his countrey j. would thou didft fo, too. Cati. Cato, you are too zealous for him. Cato, Noj Thou art too impudent. Catu. Catiline, be filent. Cati. Nay then, I eafily fear, my juft defence Will come too late, to fo much prejudice. (C*/. Will he fit down ?) Cati. Yet, Jet the world forfake me, My innocence muft not. Cato. Thou innocent ? So are the Furies. Ctc. Yes, and Ate, too. Do'ft thou not blufh, pernicious Catiline ? Or, hath the palenefTe of thy guilt drunk up Thy blood, and drawn thy veines, as drie of that, As is thy heart of truth, thy breft of vertue ? Whither at length wilt thou abufe our patience ? Still mail thy furie mock us ? To what licence Dares thy unbridled boldnefie runne it felf ? Doe all the nightly guards, kept on the palace, The cities watches, with the peoples fears, llie concourfe of all good mert, this fo ftrong And fortified feat here of the Senate, The prefent looks upon thee, itrike thee nothing ? Do'it thou not feel thy coun fells all laid open ? And fee thy wild confpimcie bound in With each mans knowledge? which of all this order Canft thou think ignorant (if they'll but utter Their confcience to the right) of what thou didit Laft night, what on the former, where thou wert, Whom thou didft call together, what your plots were * , O age, and manners ! This the Conful, fees, The Senate underftands, yet this.man lives ! Lives ? I, and comes here into counfell with us j Partakes the Publique cares: and with his eye Marks, and points out each man of us to {laughter. And we, good men doe fatisfie the (late, If we can fhunne but this mans fword, and madnefle. There was that venue, once, in Rome, when good men Would, with more fharpe coercion, have reftrain'd A wicked citizen, then the deadlieft foe. We have that law ftill, Catiline, for thee -, An Adi as grave, as fharpe : The St'ates not wanting : Nor the author! tie of this Senate ; we We 7
Page 48

.48 CATILINE. We, that are Confuls, onely faile our felves. This twenty dayes, the edge of that decree We have let dull, and mil; kept it fhutup, As in a (heath, which drawn fhould take thy head. Yet itill thouliv'il : and liv'it not to lay by Thy wicked confidence, but to confirme it. 1 could defire, Fathers, to be found Still merciful!, to feeme, in thefe maine perills Grafping the ftate, a man remifle, and flack ; But then, I mould condemne my felf of floth, And trecherie. Their campe's in Jtalit, Pitch'd in the jawes, here, of ffetrurta } Their numbers daily increafmg, and their, generall Within our walls: nay, in our counfell ! plotting Hourely fome fatall mifchief to the publique. If; Catiline, I fhould command thee, now,, Here, to be taken, kill'd; I make ju ft doubt, Whether all good men would riot think it done Rather too late, then any man too cruell. Cato. Except he were of the fame meal, and batch. CVt.But that,which ought to have been done long fmce, I will, and (for goodreafonj yet forbear. Then will I take thee, when no man is found So loft, fo wicked, nay, fo like thy felf. But mail profefle, 'tis done of need, and right. While there is one, that dares defend thee, live ; Thou (halt have leave ; but fo, as now thou liv'ft : Watch'd at a hand, befieged, and oppreft From working- lead commotion to the (late. I have thofc eyes, and ears, (hall ftill keep guard, And fpy-all on thee, as they have ever done, And thou not feel it. What, then, canft thou hope ? If neither night can, \v ith her darknefle, hide Thy wicked meetings ; nor a private houfe Can in her walls, conta-inetheguiltie-whifpers Of thy confpiracy : if all breakout, All be difcovered, change thy mind ?t lair. Andlof.' thy thoughts of Ruine, flame, andflaughter. Remember, how 1 told , here, to the Senate, That fuch a day, thy Liftor, Cains M*nlius, Would be in armes. Was I deceived, Catiline ? Or in the fac% or in the time ? the hour ? I told too, in this Senate, that thy purpofc Was, on the fifth Tthe kalends o$ November) T'have fl-uighter'd this whole order : which my caution Made many leave the citie. Can it thou here Denie,
Page 49

CATILINE, 4P Denie, but this thy blacjs defign was hindred, That very day, by me ? } thy felf clos'd in Within my ftrcngths, fo that thou could'/l not more Againft a publique ree^l ? when thou wert heard To fay, upon the parting of the reft, Thou would'ft content thee, with the murder of us, That did remaine. Had'ft thou nor hope, befide, By a furprizc, by night, to take Prenejte ? Where when thou cam'ft, did'ft thou not find the place Made good againft thee, with my aides, my watches ? My garrifons fortified it. Thou do'ft nothing, Begins, Thou canft endeavour nothing, nay not think, But 7 both fee, and hear it ; and am with thee. By, and before, about, and in thee, too. Call but to mind thy laft nights bufinefle. Come, 7le vfe no circumftance : at Lecca's houfe. The (hop, and mint of your confpiracie. Among your fword-men, where fo many aflbciates Both of thy mifchief, and thy madneflC; met. Dar'ft thou denie this ? wherefore art thou filent ? Speak, and this fhall convince thee : Here they arc, I fee 'hem, in this Senate, that were with thee. O, you immortall gods ! in what clime are we ? What region do we live in ? in what ayre ? What common- wealth, or ftate is this we have ? Here, here, amongft us, our own number, Fathers f In this mod holy counfell of the world, They are, that feek the fpoyleofme, of you, Of ours, of all : what I can name's too narrow : Follow the fun, and find not their ambition. Thefe I behold, being Conful j nay, laske Their counfells of the ftate, as from Fatr;ott .* Whom it were fit the axe mould hew in pieces, I not fo much as woun , yet, with my voyce. Thou waft, laft night, with Lecca Catiline, Your Chares, of Italic j you there divided ; Appointed who, and whither each (hould goe ; What men (hould ftay behind, in Romc^ xverc chofen ; Your offices fet downe ; the parts mark'd out, And places of the citie, for the fire ; Thy felf (thou affirmd'ftj waft ready to depart, Onely, a little~let there was, that ftay'd thee, That I yet liv'd. Upon the word, ftept forth Three of thy crew, to rid thee of that care j Two under-took this morning, before day, To kill me in my bed. AH this I knew,- H Your
Page 50

5.9 C A r I L I N E; Your convent fcarce difmifs'd, arm'd all my fervants, Call'd both my brother,and friends, (hut out your clients, YOU fent to vifin me ; whofe names I told To fomc there, of good place, before they came. Cato. Yes, I, and Quintus Catnips can affirme it. C<cf. He's loft, and gon. His fpirits have forfook him. Cic. If this be fo, why, Catiline, do'ft thou ftay ?- Goe, where thou mean'il. The ports are open; forth. The campe abroad wants thee, their chief, too long. Lead with thes aril thy troufsout. Purge the citie. Draw drie that noyfome, and pernicious fink, Which left) behind thee, would infecl the world. Thou wilt free me of all my feares, at once, To fee a wall between u>\ Dp 'ft thou (lop To doe that now, commanded ^ which before, Of thine own choice,thou'rt prone to ? Coc. The Bids thee, an enemie, to depart the citie Whither, thou'lt aske ? to exile ? I not bid Thee that. But aske my counfell, I perfwade it. What is there, here, in Rome ,th.at can delight thee ? Where not a foul,without thine own foul knot, But feares, and hates thee. What doraeftick note Of private filthinefs, but is burnt in Into thy life? Whatclofe, and fecret fhame, But is grown one, with thy known infamy ? What luft was ever abfent fiom thine yes ? What leud fad: from thy hands ? what wickednefle From thy whole body ? where's that youth drawn in Within thy nets, or catch'd up with thy baits. Before whofe rage, thou haft not borne a fword, And to whofe lufts thou haft not 'held a torch ? Thy latter nuptialls I letpafTe in filence ; Where fins incredible, on fins, wereheap't; - Which I not name, left, in a civill ftate, So monftruous facls mould either appear to be, Or not to bereveng'd. Thy fortunes, too, I glance not at, which hang but till next Ides. I.come to that which is more known, more.publike, The life, and fafetie of us all, by thee Threatned, and fought. Stood'ft thou not in the field, When Ltpidus, and Tnllns were our Confids, Upon the day of choice, arm'd, and with forces, To take their lives, and our chief citizens? When, not thy fear, nor confcience chang'd thy mind ? But the meer fortune of the common -wealth Withflood thy active malice ? Speak but right
Page 51

CATILINE. $i How often haft thou made attempt on me ? How many of thy affaults have I declin'd With fhifting but my body, ( as weel'd fay) Wrefted thy dagger from thy hand, how oft ? How often hath it fain, or flip't by chance ? Yet, can thy fide not want it : which, howvow'd, Or with what rites, 'tis facred of thee, I know not, That ftill thou mak'ft it a neceflity, To fix it in the body of a Cdnfttl. But let me loofe this way, and fpeak to thee, Not as one mov'd with hatred, which I ought, But pity, of which none is owing thee. Cat. No more then unto TtntalM, or Tityut. Cic, Thoucam'It, e're while, into this Senate. VVhe Of fuch a frequency, fo many friends, And kindred thou haft here, faluted thee ? Were not the feats made bare, upon thy entrance ? RiiV not the confular men ? and left their places, So fcon as thon fat'it down ? and fled thy fide, Like to a plague, or ruine ? knowing, how oft They had been, by thee, mark'd out for the mambles ? How doil thou bear this ? Surely, if my flaves At home fear'd sne with half th'afFright and horror, That, here, thy fellow-citizens do thee, I (hould foon quit my houfe, and think it need too. Yet thou dar'ft tarry here ? Go forth, at laft ; Condemn thy felf to flight, and folitude. Difcharge the Commonwealth, of her deep fear. Go ; into banimment, if thou thou wait'/l the word. Why doft tjiou look ? They all confent unto it. Do'ft thou expeft th' authority of their voices, Whofe filent wills condemn thee ? While they fit, They approve it ; while they fuffer it, they decree it - And while they are filent to it, they proclaim it. Prove thou there honed, I'le endure the envy. But there's no thought thou fhould'ft be ever he, Whom either ftiame mould call from filthinefs, Terrour from danger, ordifcourfefrom fury. Go; lintreatthee: yet, why do I fo? When I already know, they're fent afore, That tarry for thee in Aims, and do expert thee On th* Aurelian way. I know the day Serdown/twixt thee, and A&nibk- unto whom The fiiver eagle too is fent before ? Which I do hope (hall prove to thee as baneful!, As thou conceiv'ft it to tfrc commonwealth. H 2 But
Page 52

5* c A r 1 1 r jr E. But, may this wife, and hcrcd Senate fay, What mean'ft thou Marcus Tulims ? If thou know'ft That Catiline be look'd for, to belief Of an inteftine war ; that he is the author Of fuch a wickednefs the caller out Of men of mark in.mifchief, to an a3ion Of fo much horrour ; prince of fuch treafon ; Why do'ir. thou fend him forth ? why let him fcape ? This is, to give him liberty, and power: Rather, thou fhould'ft lay, hold upon him, fend him-. To deferv'd death, and a juft.punifliment. . To thefc fo holy voices, thus \ anfwer, If I did think it timely, Confeript Fathers, To punifh him with death, I would not give The Fencer ufe of one fhort hour, to breath; But when there are in this grave order, fome, Who, withfoftcenfures, ilill do nurfe his hopes; Some, that with not believing, have confirm'd His defigQS more, and whofe authority The weaker, as the worlr men, too, have follow'd : . I would now fend him, where they alj-ftiould fee Clear, as the light, his heart mine ; where no man Gould be fo wickedly, or fondly ftupid, But mould cry out, he faw, toucht, felt, and grafpt itj Then, when he hath run cut himfelf ; led forth His-defp'rate party with him ; blown together Aids of all kinds, both fhipwrack'd minds and fortunes : Not onely the grown evil, that now is fprung, And fprouted forth, would be pluck'd up, and weeded j But the ftock, root, and feed of all the mtfchiefs, Choaking the Commonwealth, Where fhould we take, Of fuch a fwarm of tray tors, onely him. Our cares and fears might feem a while rcliev'd,- But the main peril would bide ftill enclos'd Deep, in the veins and bowels- of the ftate. As humane bodies, labouring with fevers, While they a; e toft with heat, if they.do take Gold water, feem for that fhort fpacc much eas'd, But afterward, are ten times more afflicted. Wherefore, I fay, let all this wicked crew Pepart, divide themfelves from good men, gather Their forces to one head ; as I faid oft, Let 'hem be fever'd-from us with a wall ; Ijefhem leave off attempts, upon the Conful^ In his own houfe ; to circle in the Pr<etcr ;. Tc girtLthe Court with weapons i to prepare.
Page 53

C A T 1 L I N E. Fire, and balls, fwords, torches, fulphure, brands : In fhort, let it be writ in each mans forehead What thoughts he bears the publick. I here promift, Fathers CoH/iript, to you, and to my felf, That diligence in us Confuls, for my honour'd Colleague, abroad, and for my felf, at home So great authority in you j fo much Vertue, in thefe, the Gentleman of Rome. Whom I could fcarce retrain t0 day, in zeal, From feekingout the parricide, to flaughter ; So much confent in all good men, and minds, As on the going out of this one Catiline, All (hall be clear, made plain, opprefs'd, reveng'd. Andj with this omen, go, pernicious plague, Out of the city, to the wifli'd deftruclion Ofthee, and thofe, that totheruineofher, Have tane that bloudy'and blick facrament. Thou Jupiter , whom we do call the Stayer, Both of this City, and this Empire, wilt (With the fame aufpice thou didft raife it firft) Drive from thy alters, and all other temples, And buildings of this City ; from our walls j Lives, ftates, and fortunes of our citizens ; This fiend, this fury, with his complices. And all th' offence of good men (thefe known traytors.. Unto their countrey, thieves of Italy ', John'd in fo damn'd a league of mifchief) thou Wilt with perpetual plagues, alive, and dead, . Punifh for Rome , and fave her innocent head. Can. If an oration, or high language, Fathers, Could make me guilty, here is one, hath done it .- H'has ftrove to emulate this mornings thunder, With his prodigious rhetorick. But I hope, This Senate is more grave, then to give credit Rnfhly to all he vomits, 'gainft a man Of your own order, a Patrician j And one, whofe anceftors have more deferv'd QfRowe, than this mans eloquence could uttefj Turn'd the beft way : as Itill, it is the worft. Cato. His eloquence hath more deferv'd to day., Speaking thy ill, then all thy anceftors D;d ; in their good: and that the State will find, Which he hath fav'd. Catt. How, he ? were 1 that enemy. That he would make me : I'd? not wifh the State More wretched, then to need hispcrfervation. What do you make him, Cato, fuch a Herfules? Ah"
Page 54

54 CATILINE, hnAtltis? A poor petty in- mate ! Cato. Traytor. Cati. He fave the ilate ? A Burgefs fon of Arpinn>n, The gods would rather twenty Romcs fhould perifh, Then have that contumely ftuck upon 'hem. That he mould fhare with them, in the preferving A fried, orfign-poft. Catv. Peace, thou prodigie. Can. They would be forc'd thernfelves, again, and loft In the fir ft, rude, and inrligefted heap, E're fuch a wretched name, zsCtccro, Should found with theirs. Cam. Away, thou impudent head. Cati. Do you aH back him ? are you filent too ? Well, I will leave you, Fathers ; I will go. But my fine dainty fpeaker Ctc. What now, Fury f (He turns Wilt thou aflault me here ? (Cho. Help, aid the Conful.) \jmldenly Cati. See, Fathers^ laugh you not '. wl o threatned him? (.to Cicero In vain thou do'il conceive, ambitious oratour, Hope of fo brave a death, as by his hand. (Cato. Out of the Court with the pernicious tray tor) Cati. There is no title, that this flattering Senate^ Nor honour, the bafe multitude can give thee, Shall make thee worthy Catilmes anger. (Cato . Stop. Stop that portentous mouth. ) Cati. Or, when it fhall, Tie look thee dead. Cato. Will none reihain the monfter ? CatH. Parricide. QM*. Butcher, traytor, leave the Senate. Cati. I' am gone, to baniflirwent, to pleafe you, Fathers. Thruft head-long forth ? Cato. Still, do'il thou murmure, monfter ? Cati. Since I am thus put out, and made a Cic. What ? Cam. Not guiltier then thou art. Cati. I will not burn Without my funeral pile. Cato, What fays the fiend ? Cati. I will have matter, timber. Cato. Sing out fcrcech-owl. Cati. It fhall be in Catu. Speak thy imptrfecl thoughts. Cati. The common fire, rather then mine own. For fall I will with all, e're fall done. Cra. H'isloft, there is no hope of him. Cxf. Unlefs He prefently taki arms, and give a blow, Before the Ccnfnls forces can be levy'd. Cic. What is your pleafure, Fathers? fhall be done ? Cam. See, that the commonwealth receive no lofs. Cato. Commit the care thereof unto, the Consuls. (Senatt Cra. 'Tistime. C<tf. And need. Cic. Thanks to this frequent But what decree they unto Curhu, And Fuh ia. Cat it What the Conful (hall think meet. Cic. They muft receive reward, though t be not known. Left when a State needs minirters, they ha'none. Ca:o. Yet M&cm TttlliM, do not I believe, But Craffiu, and this Cafar here ring hollow. Cic.
Page 55

CATILINE. Cic. And would appear fo,if that we durft prove 'hem. Cato. Why dare we not ? What honeft aft is that, The Roman Senate ftiould not dare, and do ? Cic. Not an unprofitable, dangerous ad, To ftir too many ferpents up at once. C*far, and Craffus, if they be ill men, Are mighty ones ; and, we mud fo provide, That, while we take one head, from this foul Hydr*, There fpring not twenty more. Cato. 1' prove your counfel. Cic. They (hall be watch'd, and look'd to. Till they do Declare themfelves, I will not put 'hem out By any queftion. There they ftand. Tie make My felf no enemies, nor the State no tray tor. Catiline, Lentiilns, Ccthe^us, Curins y Gafonius^ Longing Statiliiu. FAlfe to our felves ? All our defigns difcover'd To this State-cat ? Cet. I, had I had my way, He' had mew'd in flames, at home, not i'the Senate : I had fing'd his furres, by this time. Cat. Well, there's, now. No time of calling back, or ftanding ftill. Friends, be your felves; keep the fame Roman hearts, And ready minds, you'had yefternight. Prepare To execute, what we refolv'd. And let not Labour, or danger, or difcovery fright you. He to the army : (you the while) mature Things, here, at home. Draw to you any aids, That you think fit, of men of all conditions, Or any fortunes, that may help a war. He bleed a life, or win an empire for you. Within thefe few days, look to fee my enfigns, Here, at the walls : Be you but firm within. Mean time, to draw an envy on And give a lefs fufpicion of our courfe, Let it be given out, here in the city, That I am gone, an innocent man, to exile, Into Mafiilia, willing to give way To fortune, and the times ; being unable To ftand fo great a fadion, without troubling The Commonwealth : whofe peace I rather feek, Than all the glory of contention, Or the fupport of mine own innocence. Farewell the noble Lentulus, Longinus^ Curing the reft; andthou, my better Genius, The brave Cethsgtts : when we meet again, We'll facrifice to liberty. Cet. And revenge. That
Page 56

55 c A r i L i tt z; That we may praife our hands once. Len. O, you F*te< 9 Give Fortune now her eyes, to fee with whom She goes along, that Ihe may ne're foi fake him. Cur. He needs not her, northern. Go but on^rj/w. A valiant man is his own fate, and fortune. Lon. The fate, and fortune of us all ^o with him. Gab.Sta. And ever'guard him. Car. lam all your creature. Lev. Now friends, 'tis left with us. I have already Dealt, \yyVmbrentu, with the Allcbroges, Here refrant in Rome ^ whofeftate, I hear, 1 s difcontent with the great ufuries, They are opprcfs'd with : and have made complaints Divers unto the Senate, but all vain. Thefe men, I'ave thought (both for their own oppreflions, As alfo that, by nature they're a people Warlike, and fierce, ft ill watching after change, And now in prefent hatred with our ftate) The fitted and th e eafieft to be drawn To our focicty, and to aid the war. The rather, for their feat ; being next bord'rers On Italy } and that they abound with hcrfe : Of which one want our camp doth onely labour. And I have found 'hem coming. They will meet Soon, at Semproi*s houfe, where I would pray you All to be prefent, to confirm 'hem more. The fight of fuch fpirits hurt not, nor the flore. Gab. I will not fail.5rrf.Nor I. Cwr.Nor l.Cct. Would I Had fomewhat to my felf, apart, to do. I ha' no Genius to thefe many counfels. Let me kill all the Senate, for my (hare, Tie do it at next fitting. Len. Worthy Ctitu, Yoar prefence will add much. Get. I fhall mar more. Cic(ro, Sanga, Allobrogcs. THc State's beholden to you, F*bi*sS*ng4 t For this great care: And thofe Allolroges Are more then wrctchec^, if they lend a lift'ning To fuch perfwafion. San. They, moft worthy Confttl, As men employ 'd here, from a gieved ftate,, Groaning beneath a multitude of wrongs, And being told, there was fmall hope of eafe To be expected, to their evils, from hence, Were willing, at the firft to .give an ear To any thing, that founded liberty : But fmce, on better thoughts, and my urg'd reafons, They're come about, and won., to the true fide. The fortune of the commonwealth hath conquer 'd. Cie.
Page 57

CATILINE. 57 Cic. What is that fame Vmbrenut, was the agent ? San. One that hath had negotiation In CaSia oft, and known unto their (late. Cic. Are th'embafladors come with you ? San. Yes. Cic. Well, bring 'hem in, if they be firm and honefti Never had men the means to defervc OfRome, as they. Chappy, wifh'd occafion, And thruft into my hands, for the difcovery, And manifeft conviction of thefe traytors. Be thank'd, O Jupiter, My worthy lords, j The All'&Yoges Confederates of the Senate, you are welcome. enter. I under/land by Quintus Fabihs Sang*, Your careful patron here, you have been lately Sollicited againft the commonwealth, By one Vtnbrenm ^take a feat I pray you) From Public Lentultts, to be aflociates In their intended war. I cloud a-dvife, That men, whofe fortunes are yet flourifliing, And are Rentes friends, would not, without a caufe, Become her enemies ; and mix themfelves And their eftates, with the loft hopes of Catiline, Or Lemuel whofe meer defpair doth arm 'hem : That were to hazard certainties, for air, And undergo all danger, for a voice. Believe me, friends, loud tumults arc not laid With half the eafmefs, that they are rais'd. All may begin a war, but few can end it. The Senate have decreed, that my colleague Shall lead their army, againfl Catiline ; And have declar'd both him, and Manliw traytors, MeteRus Celer hath already given Part of their troops defeat. Honours arc promis'd To all, will quit them ; and rewards pi opos'd Even to flaves, that can detect their courfes. Here, in the city, I have by the Prttors, And Tribunes^ placed my guards, and watches fo, That not a foot can tread, a breath can whifper, But I have knowledge. And be fure, the Senate, And people of Rome, of their accuftoraed greatnefs, Will fharply, and feverely vindicate, Not onely any fac>, but any praftice, Or purpofe, againft the (late. Therefore, my lords, Confult of your own ways, and think which haad Is beft to take. You, now, are prcfcnt fuitcrs For fome redrefs of wrongs i lie undertake I Not
Page 58

5* C A'T 1 I JST2. Not onely that (hall be aflurM you : but What grace, or priviledge elfe, Senate, or people, Can caft upon you, worthy fiich a fervice, As you have now the way, and means, to do 'hem, If but your wills confent with my defigns. AH. We covet nothing more, molt worthy Confal, And how fo e're we have been tempted lately, To a defection, that not makes us guilty : We are not yet fo wretched in our fortunes, Nor in our wills fo loft, as to abandon Afriendfhip; prodigally, of that price, As is the Senate, and the people of Romes, For hopes, that do precipitate themfelves. Cic. You then are wife and honeft, Do but this, then : - (When (hall you fpeak with Lemufa, and the reft ? All. We are to meet anon,- at -Britttte houfe. Cif. Who ? -Deciw Briitw ? He is not in Rome. Sam. O but his wife SewfronU. Cu. You inftruft me. She is a chief.) Well, fail not you to meet 'hem, And to exprefs the beft afrcclion You can put on, to alhhat they intend. Like it, applaud it, give the commonwealth, And Senate loft to 'hem. Promife any aids By arms, orcounfel. What they can dcfire, I would have you prevfcnt. Onely, fay this, You'have had difpatch, in-private, by the Conful. Of your affairs, and for the mdny fears The date's now in, you are will'd by him,'thi$ evening, To depart Rome: which you, by all fought meanes, Will do, ofrcafon to decline fufpicion. Now for the more authority of the bufmefs, They have trufted to you, and to give it credit With your own ftatc at home, you would defire Their letters to your Scnxt^ and your people, Which mown, you.durft engage both life, and honor, The reft mould every way anfw^r their hopes. Thofchad, pretend fudden departure, you, And, as you give me notice, at what port You will go out, rie hV you intercepted, And all the letters taken with you : So As you mail be redeem'd in ali opinions, And they convi&ed of their manifeft treafon. HI deeds are well turned back, upon their authors : And 'gainft an injurer, the revenge is juft. Thismuft be done, now. AIL Chearfully, and firmly, We are they, would rather haft to undertake.it, Then:
Page 59

C A TILIN.& if Then ftay to fay fo. OV. VVith that confidence, g<> Make your felves happy, while you make'.-fo/.w f o . By Sanga, let me have notice from you. AH. Yes. Sempronia, Lentttlus^ Cethegas^ (jabiruw> Stattti- fts 9 Longing, VoltHrtiw, Allobrogcs, WHen come thefe creatures, the AmbafTadors ? I would fain fee 'hem. Are they any fchollers? Len. I think not, madam. Sem. Ha' they no greek ? Lcn. N.o furely. Sem. Fie, what do I here, waiting on 'hem then? If they be nothing but mcer ftates-men. Len. Yes, Your ladyfhip (hall obferve their gravity, And their refervednefs, their many cautions, Fitting their perfons. Sem. I do wonder much, Thatftates and commonwealths employ not women. To be Amba(radours,fome times welhouid Do as good publick fervice, and could make As honourable fpies ( for fo Thttcididcs. Calls all AmbafladoursJ Are they come, Cethegtu ? Cct. Do you ask me ? Am I your fcout, or bawd ? Len. O Cairn, it is no fuch bufinefs. Get. No? What do's a woman sit it then ? Sem. Good fir, There are of us can be as exquifite tray tors, As e're a male-confpiratour of you all . Cet. I, at fmock-treafon, matron, I belie ve you> And if I were your husband ; but when I Truft to your cobweb-bofoms any other Let me there die a flie, and feaft you, fpider. Len. You are too fowre, and harfh Cethegus. Cet. You Are kind, and courtly. I'de be torn in pieces, With wild Hippolyttu, nay prove the death, Every limb over, e're I'de truft a woman, With wind, could I retain it. Sem. Sir, they' 1 be truftect With as good fecrets, yet, as you have any : And carry 'hem too, as clofe, and as conceal'd As you (hall for your heart.CVr.rie not contend with you Either in tongue, or carriage, good Catipfo. Lon. Th'ainbafladours are come. Cet. Thanks to thee Mercury-) That fo haft re fcu'd me. 'Len. How now, Voltttr'tiw ? Vol. They do defire fome fpoech with you, in private. Len. O ! 'tis about the pr.ophefie, belike ; And promife of the Sybitts. G^h. It may be. Sew.Shun they,to treat with me,too.6'^.No, goo^ lady You may partake : I have told 'hem, who you are. Sem. I mould be loath to be left out, and here too. Cet. Can thefe, or fuch, beany aids, to us? Look they, as they were built to lhake the world, 12, Or
Page 60

* c J r / L i N E. Or be a moment, to our enterprise ? A thoufand, fuch as they are could not make One atome of our fouls. They mould be men Worth heavens fear, that looking up, but thus, Would make Jo-ve ftandupon his guard, and draw Himfelf within his thunder \ which, amaz'd, He fhould difcharge in vain, and they unhurt. Or, if they were, like Cape? tu, at Thebes, They mould hang dead, upon the higheft fpires, And ask the fecond boh to be thrown down. Why Lentultts, talk you fo long ? This time Had been enough, t'have fcatter'd all the ftars, T' hove quenched the fun, and moon,and made the world Defpairofday, or any light, butonrs. Len. How do you like this fpirit ? In fuch men, Mankind doth live. They are fuch fouls, as thefc, That move the world. Sew. I, though he bear me hard, I, yet, muftdo him- right. He is a fpirit Of the right Martian breed 1 . All. He is a Mars. Would we had time to live here, and admire him. Len. Well, I do fee you would prevent the ConfuL And I commend your care : It was but reafon, To ask our letters,, and we had prepared them. Go in, and we will take an oath, and feal 'herru You mall have letters too, to Catiline To vifit him i'th' way, and to confirm The aflociatiofl. This our friend, VoltuniM, Shall go along with you. TelLour great Generally That we are ready here } that Lucim Beftta 7*he Tribune, is provided of a fpeech, To lay the envy, of the war on dec ro j That all but long for "his approach, and perfon : And then, you are made free-men, asourfelves. Cicero,, Flacciu, Point initt>, Sanga. I Cannot fear the war, but to fuqceed well, Both for the honour of the caufe, and worth Of him that doth command. For my colleague, Being fo ill aff-ded with the gout, Will not be able to be there in perfon ; And then Petreiw, his lieutenant, muft Of need take charge o'the army : who is much 7'he better fouldier, havjng been a Tn\>v.ne y PrefeEl, Lieutenant^ Prttor into. the war Thefe thirty years, fo cohverfant i'the army, As he knows all the fo.uldicrs, by their names. F.l*. They'l fight theji,bravely ,with him. Pw. I,and he.
Page 61

CATILINE. 6 WH1 lead 'hein on as bravely. Cic. They 'have a foe Will ask their braveries, whofe heccflities Will arm him like a fury. But, .how ever, I'le truft k to the manage, and the fortune Of good Petrcius, who's a worthy patriot : MctcttusGeler, with three legions, too, Will flop their eourfe, for Ga,lha. How now, Fabius ? San. The train hath taken. You muft inftantly Difpofe your guards upon the Jlfihian bridge : For,by that way , they mean to come. Cic. Then thither Pomtwitu, and Flacttts, I muft pray you To lead that force you have , and feize them all : Let not a perfon fcape. Th' Ambafladors- WiU yield themfelves. If there be any tumult, I'le fend you aid. I, in mean time will call Lemulus to me, Gabinitu, and Cethegus^ Statiliw, Ceparius ; and all thefe, By fev'ral mefTengers : who no doubt will come, Without fenfe, or fufpicion. Prodigal men Feel not their own ftock wafting. When I have 'hem, I'le place thofe guards, upon 'hem, that they ftart not. San. But what'll you do with Sempruni^ Cic. A ftates anger Should not take knowledge either of fools, or women. I do not know, whether my joy or care Ought to be greater -, that I have difcover'd So foul a treafon : or muft uadergo The envy of fo many great mens rate. But, happen what there can, Twill be juft, My fortune may for fake me, not my vertue : That (hall go with me, and before me, ftill, And glad me, doing well-, though I hear illi. Prttors, j4!lobroges, Volt urt ins. FLa. Stand, who goes there?>4//. We are th' jfMregft And friends of Rome. Pom. If you be fo, then yield Your felves unto the Praters, who in name Of the whole Senate, and the people of Rcme^ Yet; till you clear your felVes , charge you of practice Againft the State. Vol. Die friends, and be not taken. FU. What voice is that ? Down with 'hem all. All, We yield. Tom. What's he ftands out ? Kill him there. Vol. Hold,hold,holdi I yield upon conditions. Fla. We give none To traytors, ftrike bwrdawn; VoL My name's Vfltftrtitu, I know Potntinity. Pom. But he knows not you, While you ftand out upon thefe trayterousterms. Vol. Tie yield upon the fafcty of my life. Pom. If it be forfeited., we cannot fave it, ,
Page 62

C A T 1 L t N E. . l. promife to dolour belt. F am not fo g As many others, I can name \ and will: If you will grant me favour. Pom. AH we can Is to deliver you to the Corfful Take him, And thank the gods, that thus have faved Rome. Chows. Ow do oureans, before QKT eyes, Likf men in Miftr, Discover, who' Id tbe State farprize. Andwbo refifts ? And as thefe c lends do yield to tight , Now, do we fee, Our thoughts*/ things, hove they did fight; Which fee rnd i* agree ? Ofwbatftrange pieces are W* made, Who nothing kjow ; Eut^ as new ayret our tars invade^ Still cenfurefo ? That now dv hofc, and now do fear y And now envy ^ And then do hate, and then low dew, But know not why : Or, if we do, it is fo Late, As our heft mood, Th ugh trite, is then thought out of date^ And entity of good. How have-we chang'd, And come about In every doom, Since wicked Catiline went out, And quitted K ome ? One white, we thought him innocent ; And, then, we accus'd The Conful, for his malice font \ Jind power abus'd. Since, -that we bear, be is in arms, We thinkjiotfo : Te t charge tbe Conful, with our bwxs, T'hAt let him go. So on the ctnfore of tbe State, W ft til do wayider-, And make the careful magi ft rate The waiksf ' flaredcr. \Vbat age is this, rshert bqneft Placdattbtkelm, ,
Page 63

CATILINE* Afe 4 ffome foul month, orfen^ Shall overwhelm ? And call their diligence, dvceipt j Their vertue^ vice - y Their Watch fulnefi) hut lying i And blond, the price. O let us pluckjhis evil fed Out (four/pints \ And give to ewry noble d$edj The name it merits. Left vtefeemfaln (if this endures) Into thofe times^ To love dtfeafe : and brookjhe cures Worfe, then the crimes. A<3 V. Petreitts, (The army. IT is my fortune, and my glory, Souldiers, This day, to lead you on ; the worthy Conful Kept from the honour of it, by difeafe : And I am proud to have fo brave a caufe To exercife your arms in. . We not, now, Fight for how long, bow broad, how great, and large Th' extent, and bounds o'th' people of Rome {hall be 5 , But to retain what our great anceftors, With all their labours, counfels, arts, and aftions,. For us were purchafing fo many years. The quarrel is not, now, of fame, of tribute, Or of wrongs done unto confederates, For which, the army of the people of Rome Was wont to move : but for your own repubhque, For the rais'd temples of th' immortal gods, For the dear fouls of your lov'd wives, and children,; Your parents tombs, your rites, laws, liberty, And, briefly, for the fafety of the world : Againft fuch men, as onely by their crimes Are known ; thruft out by ryot, want, or ralhners. One fort, Sylla's old troops, left here m Fffula, Who fuddenly made rich, in thofe dire times, Are fmce, by their unbounded vafte expence, Grown needy, and poor: and have but left t expect/. From Cttilint, new bills, andjiew profcriptions. ^
Page 64

CATILINE. Thcfe men (they fay) are valiant, yet, I think 'hem Not worth your paufe : for either their old virtue Is, in their floth, and pleafurcs loll } or, if It tarry with 'heov, foill match to yours, As they are fhorc in number, or iu caufe. The fecond fort are of thofe fcity-beafts, Rather then citizens) who whilft they reach After our fortunes, have let flie their own ; ThefCjWhelnVd in wine,fwell'd up with meat^and wcakned With hourly whoredoms, never left the fide Of Catiline, in Row, nor, here, are loos'd From his embraces : fuch as (trull me) never In riding, or in ufing well their arms, Watching, or other military labour, Did excrcife their youth ^ but learn'd to love, Drink, dance, and ring, make feafts., and be fine ganefters : And the fc will wifli more hurt to you, then they bring you. The reft are a mixt kind, all forts of furies, Adulterers, dicers, fencers, out-laws, thieves, The murderers of their parents, all the fink, And plague of Italy met in qne torrent, To take, to day, from us the pnnifhrrient, Due to their mifchiefs, for ib many years. And who, in fuch a caufe, and 'gainft fuch fiends, Would not now wifh himfelf all arm, and weapon ? To cut fuch poyfons from the earth, and ht Their bloud out, to be drawn away in clouds, And pour'd, on fome inhabitable place, Where the hot fun, andflime breeds nought but monfters ? Chiefly, when this fure joy mill crown our fide, That the leaf!: man, that falls upon our party This day (as fome muft give their happy names To fate, and that eternal memory Of the belt death, writ with it, for their countrey) Shall wake at pleafure, in the tents of reft ; And fee far off, beneath him, all their hoft Tormented after life : and Catiline, there, Walking a wretched, and lefs ghoft, then he. lie urge no more : move forward, with your eagle*, And truft the Senates, and Rome* caufe to heaven. Arm. Tothee, great father M*rs^ and greater Jove. Cxfar^ Crajfus. TEver look'd for this tfLcmnlus When Catiline was gone. Cra. I gave *hem loft, Many days finre. Ctf. But xvhcrefore did you bear Their letter to the Confids, that they fcnt you, To
Page 65

C A T / -L 1 N E. To warn you from the city ? Cra. Did I know Whether he made it ? It might come from him, For ought I could aflure me : if they meant, I mould be fafe, among fo many, they might Have o>me, as well as writ. C<tf. There is no lofs In beir% fecure. I have, of late, too, ply'd him Thick, with intelligences, but they 'have been Of things he knew before. Cra. A little ferves To keep a man upright, on thefe ftate-bridges, Although the paflage were more dangerous. Let us now take the ftanding part. C&f. We muft, And be as zealous for't, as Cato. Yet I would fain help thefe wretched men. Cra. You cannot. Who would fave them, that have betraid themfclves ? Cicero, Quinttu^ Cato. I Will not be wrought to it, brother Quimns. There's no mans private enmity (hall make Me violate the dignity of another. If there were proof 'gainft C&far, or who ever, .<, To fpeak him guilty, I would fo declare him. But Qiiimus Catnips, and Pifo both, Shall know, the Confut will not, for their grudge, Have any man accus'd, or named falfly. Qui. Not falfly: but if any circumftance, By the /Mobroges, or from VolturtiM, Would carry it. Cic. That mall not be fought by me. If it reveal it felf, I would not fpare You, brother, if it pointed at you, truft me. Cato. Good Marcus Tu/liw (which is more, then great) Thou had'ft thy education, with the gods. Cic. Send Lentnlus forth, and bring away the reft, This office, I am forry, Sir, to do you. The Senate. VAT Hat may be happy fti/l, and fortunate, To Rome, and to this Senate : Pleafe you, Fathers^ To break thefe letters, and to view them round. If that be not found iivthem, which I fear, I, yet, entreat, at fuch a time as this, My diligence be not contemn'd. Ha* you brought The weapons hither, fromCff&g;#houfe? Tr&. They are without. Cic.- Be ready,w To bring him, when the Senate calls ; and fee None of the reft confer together. Fa&ers,
Page 66

'96 C A r 1 L I N E. C4to. Look there. Syl. Gods? Can fuch men draw common air > Cic. Although the greatnefs of the mifchief, Fathers, Hath often made my faith fmall, in this Senate, Yet, fmce my catting Catiline out (for now I do not fear the envy of the world, $ ttnlefs the deed be rather to befeafd, That he went hence alive ; when thofe I meant Should follow him, did not) I have fp.ent both days, And nights ; in watching, what their fury and rage Was bent on, that fo ftai<|L againft my thought : And that I might but take 'hem in that light, Where, when you me: their treafon, with your eye's, Your minds, at length, would think for your own fafety. And now, 'tis done. There are their hands and feals, Their perfons, too, are fafe, thankes to the gods. Bring in Voltuniitt and th' AtLbroges. Thefe be the men, were trufted with their letters. Vol. Fathers, believe me, I knew nothing : L Was travelling for UaBia. and am forry Cic. Quake not, Voltiirtiw^ fpeak the trutH, and hope Well of this Senate, on the Conjuls word, Vol. Then, I knew aH. But truly I was drawn in But th'other day. C*/.Say, what thou know'ft ; and fear not Thou haft the Senates faith, and Confiils word, ( Hen unfvpert To fortifie thec. Vol. I was.fent with tetters 1 with fear & And had a meffage POO- -from Lentulm fatcrntgtioni* To Catiline that he mould. ufe all aids- Servants, or others-r-and come with his army, AfiToon, unto the city as he could--- For they were ready,, and but (laid/or him -.. To intercept thofc, that fttould flee the fire -. Thefe men like (the JMobrcgesy-did hear it too, All. Yes, Fathers, and they took an oath, to us. Befides their letters that we rfiould be free ; And urg'dijs; for fome prefent aid of horfe. Cic. Nay, here be other teftimonies, Fathers, Cethegns aroioury. Cra. \Vhat, not all thefe ? (The vttaptxs Cic. Here's not the hundred part. Gall in the Fencer, <and arms are That we may know the arms to all thefe weapons, [brought forth. Gorrie, my brave fword- player, to what a<Ttiv ufe, Was all this ftcel provided ? Cet. Had you ask'd , In Sylla's days, it had'been to cut throats ; But now, it was to look on, on^ly : I lov'd To fee good blades, and feel their edge, and points : To put. a helm upon a block, and cleave it, : And
Page 67

c A r i L / N *. f 7 And, now and then, to ftab an armour through. Cic. Know you that paper? That will flab you through, Is it your hand ' Hold, favc the peices. Traytor. Hath thy guilt wak'd thy fury ? Get. I did write, I know not what - 9 nor care not : That fool Ltntttlns Did diftate, and I th' other fool, did fign it. Cic. Bring in Statilmst Do's he know his hand too ? And LentuUis. Reach him that letter. Sta. I Confefs it all. Cic. Know you that feal, yet, Purlins? Len. Yes ? it is mine. Cic. Whofe image is that, on it? Len. My grandfathers. Cic. What, that renown'd good rnai ? That did fo only' embrace his countrcy, and lov d His fellow-citizens ! Was not his picture. Though mute, of power to call chee from a facl, So foul -Le n. As what, impetuous Cicero ? Cic . As thou art, for I do not know what's fouler. Look upon thefe. Do not thefe faces argue Thy guilt, and impudence?Lf,/. What are thefe toiwe > I know 'hem not. AH. No Publius ? we were with you, At Brutus houfe.A'W.Lail night. Len. What did you there? Whofentforyou? AH. Your felf did. Wehadlettas From you, Cethegus, this Statilms here, (jabinths Ci*n er, all, but from Longinus^ Who would not write, becaufe he was to come Shortly, in perfon, after us (he faid ) To take the charge o'the horfe, which we (hould levy. Cic. And he is fled, to Catiline, I hear. Zffff.Spiesf fpies?^//.You told us too,o'the Sybills books, And how you were to be a King this year, The twcntyeth, from the burning of the Capital. That three Cornell were to reign, in Rome y Of which you were the laft : ana prais'd Cethegus, And the great fpirits, were with you in the aftion. Get. Thefe are your honourable embafladours. My foveraign Lord Get. Peace, that too bold CcthegM AH. Befides (jabiniuj your agent, naro*d -AntroniHs^ Servius Sulla. Jfcwfttntfitti, And divers others. Vol. I had letters from you, To Catiline, and a mefTage, which I have told Unto the5Mtt, truly, word for word : For which, I hope they will be gracious to me, I was drawn in by that fume wicked Cimber, And thought no hurt at all. Cic. ^eltttrtins, peace. Where is thy vifor, or thy voice, now, Lentnlus ? Art thou confounded ? Wherefore fpeak'ft thou not ? Is all foclear, fo plain fomaniteft, Hiat boththy eloquence, and impudence,
Page 68

c A And thy illnature, too;ferve left thc y atonce ? Take him afidc. Th( re's yet one more, Gabiniiu, The enginer of all. Shew him that paper, If he do know it? Gab. I know nothing. cVr. No? Gab. No. Neither will I know. Cat* Impudent head f Stick it into his throat ; were I the C//, Il'd make thee eat the mifchief, thou haft vented. Gab. Is there a law for't, Cato ? Cat. Do'ft thou ask After a law, that wouldeft have broke all laws, Of nature, manhood, conference, and religion ? Gab. Yes,! may ask for't. Cat .No, pernicious Th' enquiring after good, does not belong Unto a wicked perfon. Gab. I but Cato Does nothing, but by law. Cra. Take him afide. There's proof enough, though he confefs not. Gab. Stay,, I will confefs All's true, your fpies have told you. Make much of 'hem. Cet. Yes, and reward 'hem weH, For fear you get no more fuch. See, they do not Die in a ditch, and ftink, now you ha* done with 'hem, Or beg, o* the bridges, here in Rwnt^ whofe arches , , Their aclivc induftry hath faved. Cic. See, Fathers, What minds and fpirits theft are, that being convicled Of fuch a,treafon, and by fuch c'oud Of witnefles, dare yet retain their boldnefs ? What would their rage have done if they had conquer'd ? I thought when I had thruft out Cat iline, Neither the State, nor L fhould need t'hav^ fcar'd Z^/jfleep'here; or Longinm fat, ' Or this-Cethcgtu rafhnefs ; "it was he 1 onely watch'd, while he was in our walls, As one, that had the brain, the hand, the heart. But now, we find the contrary !. Where was there A people griev'd, or a ftate difcontent, Able to make, or help a war 'gamft Rome, But thefe,th' dilobroge s, and thofe they found ? Whom had not the juft gods been pkas'd to make More friends unto our fafety then their own, ^s it then feem'd, negleding theft mens offers, Where had we been ? of where the commonwealth ? When their great Chief had been call' d home ? this man Their abfolute king (whofe noble grandfather, ^rm'd in purfuit of the feditious Graccku, Took a brave wound, for dear defence of that Which he wou^.-fpoii; had gather'd all his aids Of ruffians, flaves, and other flaughter-tpcn ? Given .us.up for murder, to Cctk f & H ' s * '~* .- 'Si^-
Page 69

CATILINE. Th f other rank of citizens, to Gafonius The city, to be fir'd by Caffim ? And Italy, nay the world, to be laid wafte Bycurfed Catiline, and his complices? Lay but the thought of it, before you, Fathers, Think but with me you faw this glorious city, The light of all the earth, tower of all nations. Suddenly falling in one flame. Imagine, You view'd your countrey buried with the heaps. Of flaughter'd citizen's, that had no grave : This Lcmultis here, reigning, (as he dream't) And chofe his purple Senate ; Catiline comes With his fierce army j and the cries of matrons, The flight of children, and the rape of virgins, Shrieks of the living, with trie dying groans On every fide t'invade your fenfe j until The bloud QtRowe, were mixed with her afhes !' This was the fpdhcle thefe fiends intended To pleafe their malice. Cet. I, and it would Have been a brave one, Cenful. But your part- Had not been then fo long, as now it is : I mould have quite defeated your oration j And flit that fine rhetorical pipe of yours, I'the firft Scene. Cat. Infolent monfter ! Cic. Fathers^ Is it your pleafures, they fhall be committed Unto fome fafe, but a free cuftody, Until the Senate can-determine farther ? Sen. ..It pleafeth well. Civ. Then, Marcus Craffpi,. Take your charge of Gabinius : fend him home Unto your houfe. You Cafar of Statilius. Cetbegitt (hall befenf to Cornificius, And Lentulits, to Pnblitts Lxmuhis Spinther, Who now is x4idile. Cat . It were beft, the Pr<ttors Carried 'hem to their houfes, and delivered 'hem. Cic. Let it be fo. Take 'hem from hence. Ge/B Let Lentidtu put ofFhis -Prator-Givp. Lev. I do refign it hereunto the Senate. C&f. So now, there's no offence done to religion. Car. Crfar, 'twas pioufly, and timely urg'd. 'Cic. What do you decree to the Allobroges ? That were the lights to this-difcovery ? Cra. A free grant, from the ftate, of all their fuits, C&f. And a reward, out of the publick trcafure. Cat. I, and the title of honeft men, to crown 'hem. Cic. What to Volt urt ins? C*f. Life/md favour's well. Vol. I ask no more. Cat. Yes, yes, fome money, thou need'il it,
Page 70

&j CATILINE. Twill keep thce honeft v want made thee a knave. Syl. Let Flaccw, and Fomtimta^ the Pr<etors, Have publick thanks, and Qtttmns 'Fabius Sang*, For their good fervice. Cra. They deferve it all. Cat. But what do we decree unto the Conful, Whofe vertue, counfel, watchfulnefs, and wifdom. Hath free'd the Commonwealth, and withont tumult, Slaughter, or blood, or fcarce raifing a force, Refcu'u us all our of the jaws of fate ? Cra. We owe our lives unto him, and our fortunes. Caf. Our wives, our children, parcnts,and our gods. Syl. We all are faved, by his fortitude. Cato. The commonwealth owes him a cmd^garland He is the onely father of his Countrey. Caf. Let there be pubiick prayer, to all the goods. Made in that name, for him. Cra. And in thefe words. For that hf hath, by his vigilance, preferv'd Rome/row the flame, he Senate from thefword> jfnd all her citizens from maffacre. Cte.Howare my labours more then paid, grave Father Iri thefe great titles, and decreed honours ! Such, as to me, firft, of the civil robe, Of any man, fmce Rome was Rome, have hap'ned ; And from this frequent Senate, which more glads me, That I now fee yo'have fenfe of your own fafety. If thofe good days come no lefs grateful to us, Wherein we are preferv'd from fome great danger, Then thofe, wherein w'are born, and brought, to light Becaufe the gladnefs of our fafety is certain. But the condition of our birth not fo : And that we are fav'd with plenfure, but are born Without the fenfe of joy : why mould not, then, This day, to us, and all pofterity Of ours, be had in equal fame, and honour, "With that, when Romulus firft rear'd thefe walls, When fo much more is favcd, then he bult ? Cxf. It ought. C a. Let it be added to ourFaJli. Oc. What tumult's that?/ 7 /^.Here's one T^w/wtake. Going to Ca time ; and fayes he was fent 3y Marcus Crajfus : whom he names, to be Guilty of the confpiracy. C'.c. Some tying varlet. Take him away, toprifon. Cra. Bring him in, And let me fee him. C/c. He is not worth it, Cra/us. Keep him up dofe, and hungry, till he tell, By whofe pernicious counfel, he durft (lander So.great, and good a citizen. Cra, i>y yours.
Page 71

CATILINE. 7* I fear, t'will prove.) Syl. Some o'the traytors, fure, to give their aftion the more credit, bid him Name you, or any man. C/V. Iknowmyfelf, By all the trafts, and courfes of this bufinefs, Crafts is noble, juft, and loves his countrey. Ha. Here is a libel too, accufing Cxfar, From Lucius Veftius, and confirmed by Curias. Cic. A way with all, throw it out of the Court. C*/. A trick on me, too ? Ctc. It is foine mens malice, I faid to CurihSy I did not believe "him. C*/ Was not that Curius your fpie, that had Reward decreed unto him, the laft Senate, With Fulvia, upon your private motion ? Oc.Yes.G/.But, he ha's not that reward,yet.GV.N*, Let not this rronble you. C t Car, none believes it. C /. It fhaU not, if that he have no reward. But if ne have, fure I mail think my felf. V^ry untimely, and unfafely honeft. Where fuch, as he is, may have pay to accufe me. Ctc. You fhall have no wrong done you, noble C</r, But all contentment. C*f. Confal, lamfilent, Canline. [The Army T Never yet knew, Souldiers that in fight Words added vertue unto valiant men ; Or, that a Generals oration made An army fall, or ftand : but how much prowefs Habitual, or natural each mans breaft Was owner of, fo much in ad it mewed. Whom neither glory or danger can excite. Tis vain to attempt with fpeech : for the minds fear Keeps all brave founds from entring at that ear. I, yet, would warn you fome few things, my friends, And give you reafon of my prefent counfels. You know, no lefs then I, what ftate, what point Our affairs ftand in ; and you all have heard, What a calamitous mifery the floth, And fleepinefs of Lentulus^ hath pluck 'd Both on himfelf, and us : how, whilft our aids There, in the City looked for, are defeated, Our entrance into Callia, too, is ftopt. Two armies wait us : one from Rome, the other From theG ante- Provinces. And we are, fAlthongM mofl defire it) the great want O f corn, and victual, forbids longer ftay. So that, of need, we muft remove, but whither Tnc
Page 72

,7* C A 'I I L, IX E. The fword mu(V both, dire J*, and cut the paflagf . I onely, therefore, svifh you, when you ftrike, To have your valours, and your fouls, about you,. And think, you carry in your labouring hands The things you feek, glory, and liberty, Your countrey, which you want now, with the Fates, That are to be intruded, by ourfwords. If we can give the blow, all will be fafe to us, We (hall not want provifion, nor fupplies. The colonies, and free towns >vill lye open ^ Where, if we yield to fear, expeft no place, Nor friend, to flicker thofc, whom their own fortune, And ill-us'd arms have left without protection. You might have liv'd in fervitude, or exile, Or fafe at RGMC, depending on the great ones, But that you thought thofe things unfit for men. And, in that thought, you ihen were valiant. For no man ever yet chang'd peace for war, But he, that meant to conquer. Hold that purpofe. There's more nectfluy, you fhould bc.fuch, In fighting (or your felvcs, then they for others. He's bafe that trufts his feet, whole hands are arm'd. Me-thinks, Ike. Death, and the F0rfV.r, waiting What we will do j and all the heaven's at leafure For the great fpeclacle. Draw, then, your fwords : And, if our deiliny envy our vertue, The honor of the day, yet let us care To fell our felves, at fudva price, as may Undo the world, to buy us , and make Fate, "While (he tempts ours, fear her own cftate. The Senate. SEn. What means this hafty calling of the Senate ? Sen. We (hall know ftraight. Wait, till the Conful fpeaks Pom. Fathers Ccnfcnp t, bethink you of your fafeties, And what to do, with thefc confpirators - T Some of their clients, their free'd men, and flaves 'Gin to make head : there is one of Lentulns bawds Runs up and down the fhops, through every ftreet, With money to corrupt the artificers, And needy tradefmen, to their aid. Cetbegus Hath fent, too, to his fcrvants ; who are many, Chofen, and exercis'd in bold attemptings, That forthwith they ftiould arm themfelves, and prove His refcue \ All will be in inftant uproar, If you prevent it no V with prcfcnt counfels. We
Page 73

*C ATI LJ X 3. We have done what we can, to meet the fury, And will do more. Be you good to your felves. Cic. What is your pleafure, Fathers, ihall be done / Sytttnw, you are Cow//next defign'd. Your fcntence, of thefc men. Sy/.'Tis fhort, and this, Since they have fought to blot the name ofRomt, Out of the world ; and raze this glorious empire With her own hands, and arms, turn'd on her felf : I think it fit they die. And, could my breath Now execute 'hem, they (hould not enjoy An article of time, or eye of light, Longer, to poyfon this our common air. Sen. I think fo too. Sen. And I. Sen. And I. Sen* And I. C/c.Your Sentence,C*w# Ctfar. Ctf.Confcript Fath(r/ t In great affairs, and doubtful, it behoves. Men that are ask'd their fentence, to be free From either hate, or love, anger, or pitty : For, where the leaft of thefe do hinder, there The mind not eafily difcerrrs the truth. I fpeak this to you, in the name of Rente, For whom you (land j and to the prefent caufc : That this foul facl of Lmtultu, and the reft, Weigh not more with you then your dignity ; And you be more indulgent to your pamon, Then to your honour. If there could be found A pain, orpunifliment, equal to their crimes, I would devife, and help: but, if thegreatnefs Of what they ha' done, exceed all mans invention, I think it fit, toftay, where our laws do. Poor petty ftates may alter, upon humour, Where, if they offend with anger, few do know it, Bccaufc they are obfcure ; their fame, and fortune Is equal, and the fame. Butthe"y, that are Head of the world, and live in that feen height, All mankind knows their actions. So we fee, The greater fortune, hath the lefler licence. They muft nor favour,hat5e,andkaft be angry; For what with other* is call'd anger, there, Is cruelty, and pride. I know Syll*ntts y Who fpake before me, a juft, valiant man, A lover of the ftate, and one that would not In fucKa bufmefs, ufe or grace, or hatred ; I know too, well his manners, and modefty : Nor do I think his fentence cruel (for 4 'Gainft fuch delinquents what can be too bloody ? But that it is abhorring from our ftate } Since to a citizen of Rome, offendingj
Page 74

74 c A r i L i Our laws give exile, and not death. Why then Decrees he that ? Twere vain to think, for fear ; When, by the diligence of fo worthy a Ccnfil, All is made fafe and certain. Is 't for punifliment ? Why, death's the end of evils, and a reft. Rather then torment: It diflblvcs all griefs. And beyond that, is neither care, nor joy. You here., my fentenbe would not have 'hem -die. How then ? fet free, arfd increafe OatUmes army > So will they, being but banifVd. No, grave father^ I judge 'hero, firft, to have their itates confifcate,, Then, that their perfons remauvprifoners I! the free towns for dtij&Mfl&*) and.fcver'd : Where they might, nether have relation,.' Hereafter, tq the $**?, or -the people. Or, if they had, thofe towns,;then to be muldc^ As enemies to the ftate, that had therrjoard. Sen. Tis good and honourable, C^ffar, .hath uttcr'd^ Ctc. fathers, I, fee > our faces, and.your.Eycs All bent on me, to note of thfe two fenfurcs, Which I incline to. Either of'them. are grave, And anfwering the dignity of tbe fpc akcrs, The greatnefs of th 1 affair, . and both .evere. One urgeth death : and heiitey well remember Thisftate hath punifcYd teked citizens fo, The other bonds : and thofe perpetual, which He thinks found out for^he more Angular Plague, Decree, which you ftwH-jiKafe. You have a C onfnl, Not readier to obey, then to defend, What ever you (hall ad, for the republique - r And meet with wirHng fhoulders any burden, Or any fortune, with an. even face, Though it were death : whtch, to a valiant roan . Can never happen foul, nor to a Confal Be immatu-re, or to a wife man wretched. S>7. Fathers, I fpake, but as 1 thought : the needs O'th' commonwealth requited C*t. Excufe it not. Cic. Cat e. fpeak you your -fertfence.G*/. This it is You here difpute, on kinds of tjfcmiihment, And ftand confulting, what you flwuto decree ; Gainft thofe, of wh<ft^ou rather (hould beware, This mifchicf is not likernofecemmon fads. Which, when they.are d6rie> the'law&may profccute But this, ifyouprosid^no^ e're it happen, When it is happen'd, will not 1 wait your Judgement. Gopd Gains *]**> here, hath wywll, AlMl Q
Page 75

C A r I L I N B. * And fubtilly difcourf d of life, and death, As if he thought thofe things,, a.pietty fable, That are delivered us of hell, ami furies, Or of the divers way, that ill men go From good to filthy, dark, and ugly places And therefore, he would have there-live, and long to* But far from Rome, and in the fmall free towns, Leilj here, they might have re cu : As if men, Fit for fuch a<fts, were only in the City, .Xnd not threughout-all Italy ? or, thatboldnefs -Could do no more, where it fo.und leaft refinance? 'Tis a viin counfel, if he think them dangerous. Wftich, if he do not, but that he alone, In fo great fear of all inert, iland unfrightedj He give? mecaufe, and you, more to fear him. I am plain, Fathers. H :re you lo.ok.about, One at another, doubting what to do^; V Vkh faces at you trufted to the gods. That lill have r*vd you v and th >y can do't : But, They are nut wtfhings, or bafe womanilh prayers, Can draw their aids ^ but vigilance, counfel, avftion.* Which th^y wiH be afhamed to forfuk'e. 'Tis fl.-th they hate, and cowardife. Here you have The tray tors in your houfesyct, you (land, Fearing what to do with them ; Let them loofe, ^nd fend them hence with arms; too that your mercy May turn your mifery, as foon as't can. 0, but, they are great men and have offended, But, through ambition. We would fpare their honor : 1, if themfelves had fpared it, or their fame, Orrnodefty, or either god, or man: Then I would fpare them. But, as things now ftand, fathers, to fpare thefe men, were to commit ^greater wickednefs, then you would revengci If there had been but time, and place, for you, To have repaired this fault you fhould have made it ; It mould have been your punifhment, to have felt. Your tardy errour : but neceffity, Now, bids me fay, let them not live an hour, If you mean R me (houtd live a day. I have done. Sen. Cato hath fpoken, like an oracle. Cr*. Let it be fo decreed. Sen. We are fearful. Syl. ^4nd had been bafe, had not his vertue raifcd us. Sen Go forth, moft worthy Confnl, we' 1 aflityou*. O/. I am not yet changed in my fcntence, Fathers, Cat ,No matter. What be thofe?5tr Letters,for L 2
Page 76

7$ CATILINE. Cat. From whom? let 'hem be read in open Senate father s, they come from the confpirators. I crave to have 'hem read, for the republick. C*f. Cato, read you it. Tis a love letter From your dear filter, to me : though you hate me. Do not difcov,er it. Cat. Hold thee, drunkard. Cwfnl. Go forth, and confidently. C*f. You'l repent- This raflinefs, Cicero ,fr*. C&fars ihall repent it. Cic. Mold friends : Pr*. He's fcarce a friend unto the pubHck. Cic. No violence. Ctfar, be fafe. Lead on- : : Where are the pxiblick executioners ? Bid 'hem wait on us... On, to 5 pint hers houfe. Bring Lemulm forth. Here, you, the fad revengers- Of capital crimes, againft the publjck, take This man unto your Curtice : ftrangle him* Lev. Thou do'ft well, Cartful. 'Twas a caft at dice, In Fortunes hand, not long fince, that thy felf Should'll: have heard thefe, or other words as fatal. Cic. Lead on, to<.Quinttu Qernijiciitt houfe. Bring forth Cethegw. Take him tathe due Death, that hc.hathdeferved : and let it be Said, He was once. Ctt., A bead, or, what is worfey A flave, Cftheguf. Let that be the name For aU that is bafe, hereafter t That would let This worm pronounce on.him, and not have tramplecU His body into- Ha ! ^/rt thou-not moved ! Cc. Juflice is never angry : Take him hence, Cet. O, the whore -Fort we ! and her bawds the Fittest ' That put thcfe tricks on men, which knew the way To death by a fword. Strangle me, I may fleep : I (hall grow angry with the gods,.elfe. Cic. Lead To Caitu C<tf4r)iQt>Stati,lins. Bring him, and rude Gtbinius out. Here take thent To your cold hands, .and let them feel death from you Gab.l thank you,you do me a pleafurc.S/w. And me too. _ Cat. .So, Murcus TuUtut, thou mayeft now (land up, ,, ^nd call it happy Rome-, thou being Conful. Great parent of thy countrey, go, and let v The old mcn,-of the city, ere they die, Kifs thee ; the matrons dwell about thy neck; The youths, and maids, lay-up, againft they are old> What kind of rrwn thou wert, to tell theipnephews When, fucha year, they read, with in our Fafti y Thy Conful-fhip. y^ho's this, PretreinttCic. Welcome/ V Velcome renowned fouldier. V Vhates the news ?. HusJacc can bjing no-ill with't, unto Rome., Haw
Page 77

A T I I 1 X E. "77 How do's the worthy Griffi my colleague ? Pet. As well as vidory can make him ftr, He greets the Father *, and to me 'hath trufted The fad relation* of the civil ftrife : For, in fuch war, the conqueft ftill is black. Cic Shall we withdraw into the houfe of Comoro, ? Cat. No, happy Conful> here] let all ears take The benefit of this tale. If he had voice, To fpread unto the poles, and ftrike it through The centre, to-the ArijM? It would ask it. Pet. The ftraits, and needs of Cattlme being fuch, As he muft fight with orre of the two armies, That then had near enclos'd him. It pleas'd Fate , To make us th f objeA of his difperate chotfe, .-. Wherein the danger almoft poiz'd the honour : Ami as he rife, the day grew black with him; And- Fate defcended nearer to the earth, As if (he meant, to hide the name of things, Under her wings, and make the world her quarry. At this we rous'd, left one fmall minutes (lay Had left it to be enquir'd, what Rome was. And fas we ought) arnv'din the confidence Of our great caufe, inform of battle, ftood. Whilir Catiline came on, not with the face .: O any man, butofapublickruinet His count'nance was a civil War it fell.- . And all his hoi had (landing in their looks, The palenefs of the death, that was to come. Yet cried they out like vultures, and urgd orr, As if they would precipatc our fates Nor (laid we longer for 'hem ; but himfelt Strookthefirftftroke-.^ And, with it, fled a lite. 5 WWch cut, it feem'd a narrow neck ot land, Had broke between two mighty -leas v and either Fiow'd intoother ; for fodid the (laughter : And whirl'd about, as when two vrclent tid s - - Meet, and not yield. The Fane* ftood, on hills, , Circling the place, and trembled to fee men Do more, themhey : whilft piety left the field, Griev'd for that fide, that, in fo bad a caufe, They knew not, what a crime : their -valour was. The fun ftood ftill, and was, behind the cloud The battle made, feen fweating, to drive up H^ Sed horfe, whom ftill the noife drove backward. And now had fierce Enyo, Uke a flame. Confum'd all it could reach, and then it Wt , H;
Page 78

7 S CAT1L1NS. Had not the fortune of the Commonwealth Come PalUs-\\\&, to every. Rom*n thought. Which Catilint feeing, and that now his troops Cover'd thatearth,they had fought on,with their trunk*; Ambitious of great fame, toscrown his iU,, Collected all his fury, and ran in (Arm'd with a glory, high as his defpair) Into our battle, like a LybianfafOBf Upon his hunters, fcornful of our weapOHs, Carelcfs of wounds, Plucking down lives about hiiBj Till he had circled in himfelf with death .- Then fell he too, t* embrace it where it lay. And, as in that rebellion 'gainft the gods, Aftncrva holding forth Mtdufa's head, One of the gyant brethren felt himfelf Grow marble at the killing fight, and now, Almoft made ftone, began t'enquire, what flint, What rock it was, that crept through all his limbs, And, e're he could think more, was that hefear'd j So Catiline, at the fight of Rome in us, Became his tomb : yet did his look retain Some of his fiercenefs, and his hands ftill mov'd^ As if he labour'd, yet, to grafp the ftate, With thofe rebellious parts. Cat . A brave bad death. Had this been honeft now, and for his countrey, As 'twas againiUt, who had e re fallen greater ? Or. Honour'd Petrelm^ Row, not I, muft thank you. How modeftly ha's he fpoken of himfelf ! Cat. He did the more.Gc.Thanks to the immortal gods, Romans, I now am paid for all my labours, Mywatcbings, and my dangers. Here conclude Your praifes, triumphs, honours, and rewards, Decree'd to me : onely the memory Of this glad day, if I may know it lire Within your thoughts, fhall much affeft my confckncc^ Which I muft always ftudy before fame. Though both be good, the latter yet is worft. And ever is ill got, without the 6ft. The End.
Page Scan 93

THE EPILOGUE By the fame, N" 1 O Dance, no Song, no Farce ? His lofty Pen, How e're we like *>, doubtlefi Wrote to Atcn> Height way be his y as it was Babel's/*// ; There Bricklayers turnd to Linguifts^ rmndalL 1'de ne'refpoke this, had I not heard by many* He likit one filent Woman, above any : And again ft us hadfuch ftrange prejudice j For our Applaufe, hefcarnd to Write ami ft. For all this, he did us, like Wonders, fr .-*/;-. Not for our Sex , but when he, found its Wife. A Poet runs the Gantlet, and his flips. Are bare expos' d to regiments of Whips ; , Among thofe, he to Poetick Champions Writ } As We to gain the Infancy of Wit. Which if they prove the greatest Number, then The Houfe hath taufe to thankJfcH, more than BtBv. Our Author might per fer your praife^ perhaps, Weed rather haye your Money, that your Claps.
Page Scan 94



UNIVERSITY OF CALIFORNIA AT UOS ANGELES THE UNIVERSITY LIBRARY DEC 2 2 1949 REG'D DEC 8-1 DEC 1 EC'D 1FORNI LOS AT^ JJBRARY
Page Scan 101
