The old troop; or, Monsieur Raggou : As it is acted at the Theatre-Royal / By John Lacy, gent., . | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
The old troop; or, Monsieur Raggou : As it is acted at the Theatre-Royal / By John Lacy, gent., .
Author
Lacy, John, -1681.Lacy, John, -1681.
Published
London :Printed for William Crook and Thomas Dring,1672.
Description
[6], 62, [2] p. ;21 cm.
Rights
Public Domain, Google-digitized.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/osu.32435068321249

Table of Contents

    Front Cover
    Title Page
    Section 1 on page number 1
    Section 2 on page number 4
    Section 3 on page number 6
    Section 4 on page number 7
    Section 5 on page number 8
    Section 6 on page number 27
    Section 7 on page number 28
    Section 8 on page number 31
    Section 9 on page number 41

Book Text
Front Cover
Page Scan 1

Blank page

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 2

Wºzsº "Frº-Yº º | * = Aº A 52 s 4. |- º -3. ---- :. - --t-- Š ºrr t f º : - c ; ‘āfīo’sº -| | w: º § 5 º - - - º: --- - º : - - S0 º l Zººg r * ----n ---- ... r. º.º. cºrrain 5 º º º *sſ Sºś : | : {i; :







Page Scan 3

…… - - - - -.••••••• - … . -.• • • ••••• -- . - * - • • • • •--••• • •--~~~~~~ ·-- ~~~~-------------- … . .
Page Scan 4

Blank page
Page Scan 5

Blank page
Page Scan 6

Blank page

End of Front Cover. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Title Page
Page Scan 7

* . T H E OLD TROOP. Monſieur Raggou. - * As it was Aéted at the t" T H E A T R E-R or A L. By john Lacy, Gent. Lo Ndon, Printed for William Crook and Thoma, Dring, at the Green Dragon without Temple-Har, and at the White-Lyon next Chancery-Lane end in Fleetfireet, 1 6 7 2. :

Page Scan 8

- - & * - - - - - - - - * - : * * * ** : " - - - * - - - * - - - - - º : - -- - - - - - * --- - - - *- - - - - - - - .* * - * - - - - * - - - l - - - - - -- .* -- * - * * - - - - º, - - - - * * .. t * - - - - - - - - - - - * - - -* --- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - + - - - t - * * - - * * * , y * , , . . ." - - * w *. - *. ** º - - - - ---- -------------- i ... • - - - - - - - - - - - - * * * ... •. • *- - e. - *. - - - - - - - • * * • . - -- - - - - ... • - - - - - - - - + - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - * * * * * - - - - - - - - - --- - - - - • * * * * * * - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - : . - - - * - r - - - • , -" - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - r - - - - - - - - - - - - -- - t -- - - - - - 3. - - - * - - - - - ‘. . - - - * - - - - - J. * - " - - - r - - - --- - - * { } { - - - - - - - - - - - - - - º - - - - ~ - - - *
Page Scan 9

#################### T O The young PR N c e G E O R G E, Third. Son to her G R A C E, Dutcheſs of CLEVELAND. S I R, Acknowledge, that I am no leſs unworthy to ap- | pear before you, than I was before your Elder Bro- - ther, having in me the ſame duty and reverence for your high Bloud, and the ſame equal regard for your Perſon : Tet I come with confidence to you; for having found ſo affable and ſweet a Reception from your dear Brother, I ought not at all to doubt of yours : ſince his Great Bloud runs in your veins , you muft alſo retain his Vertues ; and in you they are juſtly called ſo, yet they are not ſo in all men ; for if ſlaves, and ſervantſ, and meaner men, prove affable and bum- ble, it is not Vertue in them, becauſe it iſ their duty : but in you, being adorned with all your Greatneſs, it , fiews ſo rich a Goodneſs in you, that all men are oblig'd to return you honour for it, which I do with my he trº, and all my facultieſ. I alſo preſent you, Sir, 2 - with :27.8488
Page Scan 10

The Epiſtle Dedicatory. with a poor French-man, Monſieur Raggou, being party perpale Trooper, and Cook: I tender him to you in hir own Equipage juſt as he landed, with not ſo much as a flirt to his back: But that is no new thing to the Eng- Iiſh Nation ; therefore, Sir, receive him as an objeći to exerciſe your Charity upon ; being naked cloath him ; let him but wear your Livery, and he will not only be received, but be made welcome to all men: Lay your protećiing hand upon him, and he is ſafe from the ma- lice of his Enemies : And, Sir, as I am bound, ſo I pray, that you may want no one Vertue that may maka you up a Miracle : May your Great Bloud appoint you to cut your own fortune out, and may you do it with. ſuch ſucceſ, and valour, that all men of courage may honour you, and the reſt of the World fear you. And this, Sir, ſhall always be the prayer - of your obliged and moſt obedientservant, * * * * john Lacy. THE.
Page Scan 11

********************* T H E EP I S T L E R E A D F R. iPiſtles ('tis true) are cuſtomary, but I think as , unneceſſary as Funeral Seymons, for they muſt Tº either infinuate and flatter groſly, or elſe ſay nothing to the purpoſe: For my part I cannot ima- gine, Reader, what to ſay to thee, unleſs like a raw Preacher I ſwerve from my Text 3 and inſtead of a modeſt Apology for my bold printings, tell thee a Tale of Maeſtricht being taken, or the Dutch bang'd at Sea; and to do that were to rob the Gazette,and ſo. be call-din queſtion for Intrenchments. What then. ſhall I ſay? ſhall I praiſe my Play to thee 2 No, that were to be a vain glorious Aſs; and in thy power, Reader, to prove me ſo: What then,ſhall I decry it? No, that were to break the Stationer, that perhaps has paid too dear for it: What then, ſhall I diſcover- the Plot and Intrigue of the Play to thee 2 No, to ſpeak of the Plot in the Epiſtle, were to fore- º * . . the
Page Scan 12

~ The Epiſtle to the Reader. the reading of the Play, and ſo dam the ſail of it. In- ftead then of an ingenious Epiſtle to divert, I beg a crafty Boon, Reader, that ſome one eminent leading Voice amongſt you, will be for once ſo kind,as to give an excellent Charaćter to the World of this my Play; and by that decoy people may be drawn in to buy it off: ſo that, as I have cozend the Stationer, by this means the Stationer may over-reach you; and in ſo doing, Reader, you will º -- Moſt highly oblige Your humble ſervant, * - john Lao. PRO-
Page Scan 13

P R O L O GUI E. - - To you that judges are i'th'publickſtreet, of Ballad withoutſence, or even feet; To you that laugh aloud with wide mouth'd grace, To ſee Jack Pudding, Cuſtard thrown in's face , To you I do addreſs ; for you I write, . From you I hope protećtion here to night. Defend me, 0friend, of th' upper Region, From the hard cenſure of this lower Legion. I war in hope, that Iſhould only ſee, My worthy Crew of th' upper Gallerie. What made you Wits ſo ſpightfully to come * To tell you true, I'd rather had your room ; , , Order there war, and that moſt ſtričily gin To keep out all that look d like Gentlemen 3 -ºº: º Tou have e'en brib'd the Door-keepers I doubt, - or elſe I'm ſure they would ha'kept you out : Tou muſt, nor cenſure Peet, nor his Play, , , , , For that's the work o' th' upper houſe to day. . . . . Deal you, Sirr, with your Match, your Dryden wit, Tour Poet Laureat both to Box and Pit, It is ſome conqueſt for to cenſure him That's fill'd with Wit, and judgement to the brim ; He is for your cenſure, and I'm for theirs, - Pray therefore meddle with your own affairs. Let Witſ, and Poets, keep their own ſtations 3. He writes to th Tearms, and I to th’ long Vacations. The -
Page Scan 14

The Perſon; Names. " f"Aptain Y Lieutenant - of the Troop. Cornet i Tom Tell-troth. Raggou. - - - Flyffint, Plunder-maſter General, -- - Captain Ferret-farm. - - Quarter-maſter Burn-dorp. Biddy, the Cornets Boy. - Dol Troop. - . . . . . . N Troopers. Conſtables. - . . . . Painter. - Carpenter. - - Servants. - Women and Children in abundance. Round-heads. overnour of a Garriſon. . . . . - . . . ; tºº. Captain Hold-forth. -, * : - *-* - Captain Tub-text; and, his two Holy Siſters. . . . . . . . º . . . . " - º º * * * * "... * ... • * * * * . . . . . . . . . . * * * - - * * ~ * - . . . - - - - - - * * * - - - - - - - - - - - ,- * * * - - * * * * * : y - Qi º 'º * - - * - 5 * - **. * > . . . v. k \, • ? • * * * w * * * t - - . . . " - * - 'i' t - - - * : " . . . - - * - - - . . . . . - - - - - - . . ". . . . . . ..., - -- ". . . * , t , , . ". . - --- . - - - - --- º * - - “... ii. - tº … ." . gº \º . . . . . ." * - * - - ... . - - * *-* - * A \ \ºv, º, º a tº tº ** * * - - - - - - - - - - - * - - - - - ; ~ * a - - l

End of Title Page. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 1
Page 1

(1) : \- . . . . . . - . . . . . . . . . ºp -> - - . . . . º } : . tº ºg - . $. $. º • - - #################### A N - OLD TROOP: -- - - * . . . -- - * - - e. Monſieur Raggou. - A CTuS 1. SC ENA I. - . . . . Tell-troth and Dol Troop. - Have heard your ſtory, and much pitie you; but, in truth, I am a wicked, very wicked woman: for I never did one good deed in all my life 5 and I doubt you're unluckie, that your fate direčts you to Inc. v - - . Tell. I find you have opportunity to do good, and will to ſerve me; † for reward, if that— º - | * Dol. Nay, y'are liberal enough, you underſtand the world; for money creates good and evil: and I, that never thought of doing good, will now heartity endeavour it. . Go to my - -- B . . . . . . . . quarters, * . . . . . . º - -

Page 2

(2) quarters, for I have a great deal of roguery to ačt for my ſelf, beſides the good I am to do for you. Tell, Inquire all you can into the laſt thing you ſpoke of for I confeſs that troubles me: if ſhe proves but honeſt, I'l forgive her wildneſs. Del. I’l do it, with all the craft I can. [Exeumt. Enter Lieutenant, Flea-flint, Ferret,and Burndorp. Flea. Good morrow, good morrow Lieutenant. Lieut. Precious Rogues! what brave Honours and Titles yeu have arriv'd at in the Wars,Raſcals 1 Plunder-maſter Ge- neral Flea-flint / what Prince can give thee ſo great a Title? a great credit for my Colonel, Rogue. Then, here's Captain Ferret-farm, an honourable:Gentleman; for always, when we are fighting, you are ferreting the Farms, and ſearching the women for Letters of intelligence, you damn'd Rogue. Then, héré's the Quarter-maſter Burndorp, a Rogue that, when we have brave large quarters aſſign'd, you ſell half of 'em, and then truſs us up nine or ten in one houſe together. A pox on you, Raſcal. Burm. But why are you thus cruel, Lieutenant 2 Lieut. Hang you dogs; did not I know you at firſt to be three tatter'd Muſquetiers, and by plundering a Mault-mill of three blind horſes, you then turn'd Dragooners, and ſo quartering in a Farm where a good team was, you chang'd your blind horſes for better, and then you commenc'd Troo- pers at Oxford, and when you had plunder'd your ſelves in- to good cloaths, you impudently calf'd your ſelves Major, and Captain, and Quarter-maſter, and then you ran away from your own Troop, and I entertain'd you for Reformado-Of- cers? you know I know this, and yet, you dull ungrateful Raſcals, you will not know why I am angry. . . . Ferret. Why are you angry 2. -- Flea, Why? I'l tell thee why: He wants twenty pounds, and a good gelding, Coxcomb; he muſt have it too, I know bim well enough. Burn. Is that it? he ſhall have it, and thank him too. Pray accept of this twenty Pound, Lieutenant. - Ferref. º
Page 3

(5) Ferret. And we have a good gelding for you, Lieutenant, as ever you laid leg over. - Lieut. Why ſo? Why will you put me tot to give you ill language? cannot you underſtand me without ſcurvie uſage 2 Ferret. I did not underſtand you, by my troth, Lieutenant. - Lieut. Pray underſtand me hereafter. Now are you three as honeſt, harmleſs fellows how doſt thou do? who dares ſay that thou wilt flea a flint 2 or he ſearch for Letters in a wenches Placket 2 or the Quarter-maſter burn a Town I'll ſet 'em by the heels that ſay it. Honeſt Robin, Tom and Dick, when ſhall we drinka tub of Ale together? Burw. When you pleaſe, worthy Lieutenant. Lieut. Get a Tub at one of your quarters, and I'l come to yeu. And pray underſtand met º hereafter: I believe I ſhall bevery angry within this week again; therefore pray take care to prevent it. . . . . - - [Exit. Flea. It were a good deed ne'er to plunder more. - Burn. Why, prythee? Flea. No thriving on't for theſe damn'd Officers. To put Exciſe and Cuſtom upon Plunderingſ to put Toll upon fleaing a Flint | I hold my own quarters to be my lawful Inheri. tance as much as any mans Land or Office, that is held by old Cuſtom, and Time out of mind. - * º, Terret. Nay, I hold my quarters to be ſo much my own, that the Wife,the Daughter, and Maid-ſervants, ought to be in my occupation. - - - Burm. I deny that 5 for the man of the houſe ought to have his wife himſelf, in caſe he have a daughter to furniſh you. Nay, the ſtrićtneſs of the Statute of Plundering ſays, that in caſe he has but barely a Maid-ſervant, you. ought not to med- dle with his wife, or indeed his daughter. - Flea. I am of the opinion of the Gentleman that ſpoke laſt; for Iaſyón my own quarter) Lord of the Mannor, and al Weſts and Strays are mine. , , , , - - - Burm. I'l ſay that for thee, a Maid cannot go a milking but thou mak’ſ a Weſt or a Stray of her. - - - * * *- - - - * - - - - - - º B. 2 --> sº ~... . . . 'Eºfer' *

End of Section 1. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 2
Page 4

t * º - * : * Emter Cornet. - " - \ - . . . . . . . . (4) - corn. Here's the faithful fraternity, a league of Knaves that's never to be broke. It is a joyful thing when Brethren plun- der together in unity. How d'ye, Plunder-maſter General 2 Flea, We have all arriv'd at excellent nick-names 3 to ſay truth, according to our ſeveral degrees and ways of Plun- dering : but you, Cornet, have a name that's proper for all Cornets to be calld by 5 for they are all Beardleſs boys in our Army: for the moſt part of our Horſe were rais'd thus, The honeſt Country Gentleman raiſes the Troop at his own charge, then he gets a Low-Country Lieutenant to fight his Troop ſafely, then ſends for hisſon from School to be his Cornet, and he puts off his Childs coat to put on a Buff-coat 5 and this is the conſtitution of our Army: So I ſalute you, Cornet Beard- leſs. Thou art call'd Ferret-farm, becauſe thou art ſo terrible valiant amongſt the Country-Bumpkins, and Aſpin becauſe thou ſhakeſt and trembleſt in a day of Battel. Ferret. Whoo pox, this is abſolute malice. Corm. There thou art out 5 for this is neither malice nor anger, but down-right truth. - - ... " Flea. You abuſe him iſfaith. I have ſeen him up to the chin in bloud. . . . . - - -. corn. 'Twas in a Saw-pit then: yet when the Armies meet (Il ſay that for him) he will draw up as confidently, as if he would take a General by the Beard ; and he will as confi- dently ride out of the Army before the Battel joyns: and if any man ask him whither he goes, he ſays he is ſent for Orders, ſo you hear of him no more 5 and the next day you find him. asſure in a Saw-pit. Ferret. Pray let the Saw-pit alone, and provoke me not: good men have done the like; therefore be not too bold with your betters. - Flea. Provoke him not ; for he's a Devil at a Sword; though he tremble at a Gun. Ferret. A Gun, I confeſs, is as terrible to me as Thunder and Łightning, they're out of my Element. Well, but leave this diſsourſe, and ſo you do not laugh at me, I'ltell you a ſtory. ., º' Flea.
Page 5

(5) Flea, What is't P * ... " ... . . . . . . . . . . \ Ferret. Why, faith our Dol's with child, and lays it to me. ... Burn, Pox on her, ſhe was with me this morning, and I com- pounded with her, for five pound. Terret. The whore had ſeven of me, by this light. . . → Corm. An excellent cunning quean!. She knows the family of the Flea-flints are ever themoney'd men of a Troop.I'ſ make uſe of my time too: give me ten pound to keep counſel, or I'l make you the laughing-ſtock o'th. Army. ; , Flea. Thou wilt not turn treacherous Rogue now ſure. . ; corn. 'Tis no treachery. Shºw me a Sauldier that will not take advantage. - - ... . • Flea. I, of the enemy.… . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Corm. For ten pound any man's my enemy or friend : there's another principle for you, and very fit for the Flea-flints to make uſe of. ‘. . . . . . . . . . . Burm. We ſcorn to compound 5 but we will lend you ſo much money, if you will mortgage the next freſh Quarters. L' Corm. I’l do’t. - Burm. Then there's your ten pound. - Corm. Now are you men of Inheritance, now.you have a good title to every mans goods and chattels 5 and for ten pound more I'l help you to a Lawyer ſhall plead it, and make it good to you and your Heirs for ever. - Enter Tell-troth. - Tell. God give you good morn, Sirs: I pray you which of - you is the Captain Commander 2 - . . . . . Flea. Why, friend, we, have ne'er a Captain here, he lyes Leiger at Oxford, to give the King intelligence when his Troop beats or is beaten. - - . . . Corm. There y’are a ſcandalous raſcal: ſome Captains,Icon- feſ, have that trick; but our Captain always fights his Troop himſelf; but we have a good Lieutenanthere,if that will ſerve your turn. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - : Burr. I, he's too good for us, I would the Devil had him. . . . Corm. What's thy buſineſs? ... " Tell. I'd be a Trooper. Ferrer.

End of Section 2. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 3
Page 6

ſº rii. An Hypocrite. . . . . rant you 5 and, in ſhort, this is my buſineſs hither. * * * * w (7) - - - Ferret. And canſt thou fight? . . . . Tell. Wilt thoutry ** - " -- . Ferret, No, faith, friend, I believe thee, Waſt' ever a Soul- dier? Tell. I, a Parliament one. * Plea. What, and did'ſt thou run away 2 . . . . . Tell. No, Iºwałk'd this pace: I ſcorn to run. - , * * - Burn. I believe this fellow's a Spy. . . . . . . . Tell. You lye; H am very honeſt. Now dare you fight? Burn, No, by my troth, not with thee. . . - - . # Then remember, if any body want the ly 1t lait. • , -- Flea, This is ſuch a fellow as I never met with. Yet why did'ſt thou leave the Parliament? . . . . . Tell. For the ſame cauſe that I believe I ſhall leave you. Flea. What's that? . . . . . . º. Tell. Becauſe I'lik'd'em not, tº oº & . ºv 2, you had • * - - - Ferret. Who was thy Captain * , º º ºr " … Tell. One Captain Perily Rett. . . . . . - * * Ferret. Of what Profeſſion was he " . . . . : Tell. Of every ones Profeſſion, I think. ... º. " Ferret. What's that? . . . . . . . . . - - - - . . . . . . . . . . . . ºrs, " . . . . . . . . . . . " t ; : - Burn. And doſt thou come out of love to the King? -- Tell. No 5 I come to ſee faſhions. - - Burn. But why did'ſt thou leave thy Captain? Tell. Becauſe he is an Hypocrite, a yea and may knave; he catinot endure to plunder, but (in a godly manner) he will take all he can lay his handson, Corm. But wilt thou fight for the King out of ſtark love and kindneſs. . . " . - - - - Tell. No; I'l fight for him as all men fight for Kings, partly for love, partly for my own ends. I'l fight bravely for a Bat- tel or two; then beg an old houſe to make a Garriſon of, grow rich, conſequently a coward, and then let the Dog bite the Bear, or the Bear the Dog, I’l make my own peace, I war- E//fºr

End of Section 3. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 4
Page 7

* . . ; ; c. . . . . . . Ewter Lieutenant. . . . . . . . . . g : Lieut. Where are you, Sirs? the Captain has brought Or- ders to march, but whither I know not 5 and better news than that, he has brought pay, Boys. . - - . . Flea. I hope you are not angry, Lieutenant. : Lieut. I am not yet 5 but I ſhall be very ſudde ly, there- fore provide againſt it: the next freſh quarter you will have advantage enough. I hope we underſtand of all hands. Flea. 'Tis #ºn. Lieutenant... . . . ... .” - - - - corn. But here's the ſtrangeſt fellow come to be a Trooper. ... Lieut. He’s welcome. Haſt thou a good Horſe, friend? Tell. No, but I've a bridle, and if you'l entertain me, I ſhall quickly have a horſe. Are you the Captain 2 £ient. I am but Lieutenant, friend. . - 11 º . . . Tºll. Ho, I thought you had all been Captains, Finſure you are all call’d ſovº, ºr 'º - * * ~ * * \º . . . . Enter Captain. . . . . . . Lieut. But here comes one that is ſo: this is a very Captain. Tell. I tell thee that's very much. What's his name?:, , Lieut. Captain Honor. . . ." § 90 of .45'ſ : Tell. I? have you ſuch a thing as Honoramongſt you? . . Capt., Lieutenant, get your Corporals, together, and give "em Orders to make ready for a march; and be ſure you charge *em to ſee every Horſe in their Squadrons ſhod, otherwiſe we -ſhall have 'em lye behind drinking and plundring, and then pretend they ſtay to ſhooe their, Horſes: let me hear no more on't. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Tell. 'Tis poſſible a very Captain may be honeſt. ... Lieut. But, Sir, before you do any thing, talk with this fel- kw: he would fain be a Trooper. . . . . . . . . . . .i Capt. Now, friend, would'ſt thoubea Souldier?, as º, Téll. Yes; if I could light of a good ſide: a right cauſe, and good men to manage it. . . . . - 3 . . . . . . . . . ; Capt. On my word, that's ſhrewdly put. Well, I'l promiſe thee a good cauſe, and ſome good men: in multitudes all are not vertuous, nor valiant. º. º. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . oi Telkiſhat's well ſaid: Ithink Iſhall begin to take a liking ** : - to
Page 8

(8) to you. But, Captain, I hear a man may learn to flea a flint amongſt you, to drink and plunder. Capt. D'ye hear that raſcals Pº - - - But where did'ſt thou hear this reportofus Tell. In a London-pulpit: but another ſort of people told me, they preach'd Intereſt more than Goſpel; ſo that a man knows not which ſide to take. . . . . . - . Capt. Nay, upon my word, thou art come to the right ſide, Tell, I gheſs as much; for you talk worſe than you do, and they do worſe ". ... ." . ., Capt. This is an odd kind of fellow, and I believe a dange- 'rous; Friend, withdraw, while I read my Orders to my Officers. . º . . . . . . . º . . . . . Tell. A word in your ear firſt, are you wonderful honeſt 2 * Capt. Thou art a ſtrange blunt fellow; yes, I am honeſt. Tell. But are you wiſe too? for elſe the want of wit to ma- nage your honeſty, may make you a knave. I know 'tis ſome mens caſes. . . . . . - - , , . . . . . . . . … . Capt. Thou doſt ſurpriſe me: ſure thou haſt moré buſineſs than to be a Trooper. . . . . . . tº . . . . . . Tell. I have ſo ; but I muſt ask you another queſtion ere you $now it. Are you ſtanch enough to keep a ſecret? Be not an- gry 3 many of your party cannot hold: for tell you news, and you fly, like lightning, to the next man to diſgorge it, and ſo it goes round till it comes to the Enemy 5 and thus you be- tray your buſineſs, and intendit not neither. Hiſ pº gº Capt. I have not heard ſo dangerous a man. Pray, friend, think me worthy to know your buſineſs. . . . . . . . . Tell. You ſhall. And to ſhew you that I have buſineſs, I know what your Orders are. * * * * * * capt. Why;’tis impoſſible. . . . . . º. º. . . . . . f"Tell. Nothing impoſſible: you are to remove your Troop to Cilſtow, there quarter till further Orders, but not to go to bed; for you are within three miles of a little houſe call'd Thiever-den. Garriſon, and you;are to expect a company of Foot to quarter with you: is this your Ordersº 2 tº . . . cºpi. You amazºº; how cameyºirisintelligence? *(x, Tekº,
Page 9

(9) ... Tell. It came to Thieves-dem houſe this morning, and ſo te me; I am their Confidant, and would fain be yours. capt. Do you not know who ſent it 2 - # No, nor they neither 5 there's the ſubtle carriage of the thing. * * * - capt. But pray, Sir, let me ask you who you are 2 . Tell. I am a plain, honeſt-meaning man, a neighbour to that Garriſon of Thieves-dem, and one that has .# into the bot- . tom of both your parties, and find that you have faults, but the other great wickedneſs.; Flea. I do not like this fellow, he had a fling againſt drink. Ferret. And plundering 5 but twenty to one he hath paid for’t. - Flea. He had a plaguy jerk at flaying offlints too. Capt. What if you went to Oxford with me? Tell. So I may be hang'd when I come home again 5 for they will know it asſure. Pray let me eat, and refreſh myſelf, and then conclude of ſomething. [Exehnt. - Enter Dol, and calls Lieutenant back, - Dol. Lieutenant, I’d ſpeak with you. - Lieut. Dol, I'l come to thee preſently. - [Exit. Dol. I cannot ſay I am with child, but with children 3 for here has been all Nations, and all Languages to boot: if the ſeveral Tongues ſhould work upwards now, and I ſpeak all Languages? why, I am not the firſt learned woman 3 but I believe the firſt that ever came by her learning that way. If I ſhould have for every man that has been dealing here a child, and if the children ſhould be born with every one a Back and Breſt on, as they were got? Bleſs me, what hard la- bour ſhould I have | But, for all this, I hope I do not go with a- bove a Squadron of children. But to my buſineſs. I mean to lay this great belly to every man that has but touch'd my Apron-ſtrings. I thank the Law, 'tis very favourable in this point; for when I have play'd the whore, the Law gives me leave to play the rogue, and lay it to whom I will. . . - - . . . . . . Enter Lieutenant. . . . . . . . Lieut. Why how now Dol; how go matters with you,good Dol 3 * - C T ' ' ' ' Do!. . . - ~ * -*
Page 10

(10) * pol. I deſire you ſtand my friend, Sir, you ſee my condi- tion. . . . . . . . . . Lieut. Thou wilt not lay thy child to my charge, I hope. Dol. No, Sir, I have more wit: my drift is to lay it to more than one man, or one Squadron : Sir, I underſtand there's a months pay in your hands; and I am reſolv'd to lay this great belly to every man round the Troop 3" ſome I have ſtruck already, and they have very fairly compounded with me; fome, I ſuppoſe, may buſtle and ſtand out, but if you will countenance me , then they muſt compound at our rates. . . . " - . . . . ; - * Lieut. But Dol, what benefit is this to me? for I profeſ; no friendſhip, but follow the general principle of mankind, Dol; which is to pick the money out of thy pocket to put it into mine. So, Dol, in plain terms what will you give me 2 Y Dol. Why, Lieutenant, you ſhall goſhips. . - * Lieut. Why, Dol, we are agreed; but after we have ſtruck the Troop round, who doſt thou pitch upon to father it 2 Dol. Why,faith, I did deſign to marry Monſieur Raggou, the French Cook, that rides in your Troop. * --- - * Lieut. Thou wilt never indure to live with him, 'tis ſuch a naſty ſlovenly rogue. . . . . . . ! -- . . . . pol. 'Tis no matter for living with him; I want a husband. Lieut. He ſtinks above ground: he has not had a ſhirt on's back time out of mind. w - Dol. That makes it a fit match 5 for, by my troth, I do not deſerve a man that's worth a ſhirt. Lieut. Well, Dol, upon the aforeſaid terms, you're ſure of me, play your game with all confidence. --- - - Dol. Well, I'l to work amongſt 'em preſently: or if I might. gain you to advance my greater deſires, which is my Cornet's Boy that waits on him; I am fooliſh, for I love him ſtrangely, deſperately. A hundred pounds, in plain terms, make him fill ſtC, - . . . . Lieut. But, Dol, where is this hundred pound 2 Dol. I have ſhark'd theſe four years, and made a ſhift to. £rape four hundred pounds together. - - - - J.icwt.
Page 11

(11) - Lieut. Still I ſay you're ſure of me, with ready money. … º, ºl. Enter Manſeur º and his Landlady. . . . . . Well, Dol, away 5 here comes Monſieur Raggou, ſtep aſide. Dol. O let him have his . if our Cornets Boy fail, FI have him, or he ſhall certainly keep the child. ..[Exit. Rag, Landlady, come, take a my Piſtol and lock in your Trunk very *. ... " ºf tº ºf ... . . . . - - : Land. Yes, Sir. • ... - - - - - Rag. Take heed, for begar you will be hang if my Piſtol run away. . * - , , , . . . * Land. O Lord, II take no charge on't. . . . . . ... . . rag. You roundhead whore, ſock it up, or me will kill ou, begar. . . . . . - - - • . y º iitake all the care I canon't, Sir. . . . [Éxit, Rag. So, me will ſteal my Piſtol from her trunk, and ſay ſhe carry it to de Enemy, and den me will ſo plundra de dam - - - ", ! whore. , . . . .” - - * - I. º. . . . . . Emter Bumpkin. . . . . - - Stand; who are you for, Bumpkin? … . . . T rum. O Lord, Sir, I am for to body. . . . . . . . . . : Hag. You Dog, bé you for de King, or de Parliamenta 2 ..., cºmm. Why I am for—pray, Sir, who are you for 2, ... . . . * Rag. Tank you for dat. Begar you be very fullwid cun- ning; you will be of my aſide,if me name my ſelf firſt. Speak, you dam Dog, who be you for 2 . . . . . . . . . " - Bum. Intruth it is not good manners to ſay who I am for.: your worſhip ought to ſpeak firſt. . . . . . . . . . . . , , *Rag. Pox take you, me be for de Parliament, you Dog. . Bum. O the Lord bleſs your worſhip, I am for the good Par- liament too. . . . . . . - - W Rag. Je'rny, Ham for de King, you'roundhead Dog: begar me will plundra you ſoul and body. . . . . . . . . . . . . * Bum. Q good Sir, ſpare me; I am for the King, . . . . Rag. Diable, me will plundra you for being jack of both ſides. Diantie, he have but one ſilling about his ſoul and bodee. Get you gone, you Dog. [Exit Bumpkin. Begar, me have no luck, zoun me plundra every day dis tre * , º C 2 years, / - -
Page 12

- (12) years, and begarmenevergetbut one ſilling or one ſix penne, . Ha! Monſieur Lieutenant, me hear very brave ting of you. • Lieut. What's that? Rag. Me hear you have ſome Largion for Monſieur La Soldier: pray how much will come to Monſieur Moy? Lieut. Faith, Monſieur, ſome three pounds. . - , Rag. How, tre pone? whar be detre pone? how much be tre pone? - - - Lieut. Why, here 'tis, Monſieur, ſo much as you ſee. . ... Rag. Begar, ſure you mock a de moy 3 begar me never ſee ſo much money togederin my life. Me will lye down and tum- ble in my money like de Dog dattumbla in de carrion, it isſo ſweet. O brave Capitain, O brave Lieutenant, Gad a bleſs de King of England, and de King of France too, when he give metrepone. Lieutenant, be to be mad a dangerous ting 2 Lieut. O, very dangerous. º Rag. Begardere be your tre pone again, it will make a me tark a mad 5 me no know vat me ſall do with all dis money: begar me admire tre pone of all ting in disvarle 5 it will make degreat Turk de Chriſtian, or de Chriſtian de Turks better den all de argument in de varle. Pray, Lieutenant, keep dis money formeone two treyear, till metake counſel of all my friend in France vat me ſall do wid dat. . . . . Iieut. Goto oxford, and buy ſome neceſſaries withit; you are ſo naſty, nobody is able to come near you; buy ſome ſhirts, to keep you ſweet and clean. - - Rag. Buy §: ſhart? Me love you very vell, Lieutenant, but you no underſtand: for vatſalſ me have ſome ſhart? Lieut. To keep your ſelf ſweet, and from being lowfie. . Rag. Who can ſee my ſhart 2 here be my, doublet come cloſe, my coat come over all dat, den who de devil ſee my fhart? For vat ſall me have a ſhart, when no body ſee my ſhart 2 , Lieut. But then you want ſtockins, and twenty neceſ. {aries. - - : - - - *- : - * * * . . . . A48.
Page 13

(13) ": Rag. Me pull up my boot, who ſee me have a ſtockin P’you will have a littel Engliſh tricka, and never underſtand: for vat vill you have more ting about you, den vat vill make a ſhew in de varle, and everybody can ſee? Pray let me lay out my. money to pleaſe my own fancee. Lieut. With all my heart. . . , T. ' ' '. tº Rag. Den me vill lay it out for my honor, and for de honor of de King, and my Lieutenant: So adieu. Buy ſhart? who ſee my ſhart P. [Exit. : … - - Enter Dol. . . - . . . . . Dol. Faith, Lieutenant, I’l at him, and ſome of the reſt pre- ſently; therefore leave me to work: I am aſham'd, I am ſuch a fool to doat on a Boy, but no remedy: remember, there- fore, and about it. - - - - - . * Lieut. Do you remember the hundred pound ; II work - him, fear not. [Exeumtſeverally. —T f _--T ºf Actus II. sc. ENA I. Enter Dol Troop. . Dol. ow to my buſineſs. My Flint-flayer compounded -- * with me very civilly, that I did fear would have out-witted me: I am afraid of nothing but anim- pudent rogue that has no ſhame in him, that will father the child rather than part with his money, and ſo ſpoil my com- }. with thereſt of the Troop. I'l be as wiſe as I can 5 have among 'em. . . " . . . . . - . . . . . . . . Enter a Trooper. . . . . . . . - Troop. What a pox makes ſhe here 2 f Dol. How d'ye, Mr. William # I'm come to tell you I am gone half my time, that you may provide 5 for I am quick. - * * > …, º 7.roop.
Page 14

(14) gº Troap...Art then?' faith, I'l be as quick as thou art, for I'l he in Holland (if the wind ſerve) to morrow. . . . . . [Exit. Dol. Slife, if they ſhould all boggle thus, I ſhould make a , thin Troop on't. . . - . - Emter Raggou. … " " ......" ºr Rag. O, Madam Do!! O dee, O dee? … ºf … . ' ' '. Dol. You fee how I do: I am near my time, I deſire you to provide. You ſwore a thouſand oaths to me you would Keep the child. . . . . . . . Rag. But me did but ſwearin French, Madam Dol, and dat wiłł no ſtand good in Engliſh Law, Madam Dol...!!... . . sc. Dol. Come, Sir, come; I'l make you father my child, or II ‘make you do worſe : will you compound? … . . . 'º'; Rag. Meſcorn to compone, and ſcorn to fader your ſhild 5 you be a dam whore, Madam Dol. " . . . . . . . . --> * Dol. You are a Raſcal, Mr. Monſieur, and I'l make you fa- ther the child in ſpite of your French teeth. lººp: Yºº lºgº.º. child but de May-pole in desirãº', ºdºº" get you w; pear, by goodvitteneſs, dàt me have to May-pole abouta me: Soadieu, Madam Babylon : Pox take you, me fader your dam ſon of a whore ſhild ! - - [Exit. Dol. You fickle Frenchman, I ſhall be reveng'd on thee: II marry thee, but I'l be reveng'd on thee., . - - - - . . * Enter cornet, Lieutenant and Biddy. . . . * * * But here comes my Cornet and his Boy, —and the intºm I ſee he is mindfill ºf my buſineſ. . . . . . . . [Exit. Licut. Cornet, I have an earneſt and (by my troth) a moſt pleaſant ſuit to you. . . . . ... . . . . . cor. You cannot miſs the grant of it. What is't 2 is tº Licut. But firſt, do you love money 2 º’ ºr dº cor. By my troth, I know not; for I never had a ſum worth loving in my life yet. fºº" " ' " " , "º Licut. Will fifty pound do any hurt?" * cor. But what muſt I do for it? betray the Troop to the ene- my, or ſome Garriſon 2 for under that I cannot ". fifty pound. - - Lieut.
Page 15

- (15) - vizieni. Towns dre, not ſo cheap yet: though Treaſonſbe v. plentiful, 'tis not grown a Drug. But to my ſuit: youaré to know that out Dol is deſperately in love; and with whom. : * '... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ." cor. Not with me? I find I muſt earn this fifty pound, ºf : Lieut. No ſuch matter: you have too great a conceit of our good face. - - ſº Rºll o Bid. Indeed you lye, Lieutenant: for he can neverthink too well of that face. . . . . . . . . [Aftile, v cer. Who is it ſhe is in love with ? ... I gºtº cº Tº | Lieut. By my troth with thy Boy here: deſperately in lové with thy Boy. º ...: C od in wººl Bid. The Devil take her for her pains. But why do I curſe her, that am ſo deſperately in love myſelf?... . . . . . [Aſide. º, Cor. Why, this ſtory is very pleaſant, if you knew all. : : Eid. O. Lord 3 you will not tell him what: I am, # hope P .L. tº ... .º.o. A ſlº. 2diziº, wºod cor. Lieutenant, I muſt deny your ſuit, for it muſt not be a match; for the Boy is, in plain terms, a Girl. . . . : Bid. The Devil take you for telling him. . . . . . . . . . * cor: Why ſo? my Lieutenant's very faithfuſ. ºf ºld Lieut. A Girl? Let me ſee your face. ...tº ſº, º iſ . lo Bid. O you unworthy man! Good'Sir, iforgive me; for I am even ready to ſcold. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Lieut. This is the pretty young daughter that belong'd to your Winter Quarters, and ſo came away for love? ºf , ...; Bid.:Yes, Sir 3 but if your Cornet had been true, I had been paſt Love by this time: I had been married. Cº-º', 'J Lieut. Why, are all marry'd people paſt love? . . . . Bid. Yes, Sir, of the mens fide eſpecially: but, Sir, I am na- turally very merry, and ſhall be, if you will but dome the favour to think me very honeſt.: ; ; ; c. 1: ... : ... . . . . .1 Lieut. I ſhall do you a great favour; if I do, for Inever thought any body ſo yet 5 but if it pleaſe you, I'itry your ho- neſty, and then .." my opinion. º Bid. Be not rude when you try me, if you be, you were better venture on a Maiden-Cat aimidnight; for Iſhall ſcratch . . . - - worſe,
Page 16

(16) worſe, and ſo mark you, not for my humble ſervant, but my humble Catterwauler... . . . . . . . . . ." . . .” Lieut. I could meet ſuch a creature o'th' houſe top, at any hour, and ſcratch, and ſqueak, and tumble down together, and get the prettyeſt Kitlings as we fall. . * * ... Bid, I am glad to ſee you merry, Sir 5 for merry people are likely honeſt. w ... *** : Lieut. Well, we'l try; but, if you love mirth, conſent to marry with this Dol: there's money for us all. [Exit. Bid. Content, i'faith. 'Twill be excellent ſport to marry her, for I loveroguery well enough; but, the Devil's in't, ſhe'l know me to be a Girl. Y . . . . . - Enter Dol, aloof. ... Cor. No, no 5 ſhe ſhall not come near you, nor touch you, till ſhe's brought to bed 5 then two to one but the Troop marchest away, and leaves her behind ; then I'm ſure the Country-Bumpkins will knock her oth head. - -- g Dol. There's a Cornet in grain, I'faith. - - Bid. Troth, you are very charitable. Well, ſince my hand's in at wearing Breeches, I'l do all the Offices of a man: I would I had wherewithal to perform; for, by my troth, I am weary : of our own Sex. -- - - ... Do!. She cryes, i'faith : I like that well. - - Cor. You little fool, you do not cry, I hope 2 º Bid. No, faith, that was but a tear by chance. You made me leave my friends (you know) when you talk'd of marriage to me; but not one word on't now you have made me your Be-de-Boy. ." … "...!! . . . . . . . . . . . ; Dol. I know not what to ſay to that. ... cor. We’l talk of thoſe things when we are ſettled. . . J Bid. By my troth, you have put me in ſuch a gog of mar- riage, that it will not out of my head; and yet Iſcorn: to ask you to marry me, and I ſcorn to crack a commandment with yeu: was not that baſely done of you to tempt me 2 but I ſhall ſcold, which is a thing I hate. O baſe fellow !you would be going oth' ſcore with me, for my Virginity P Faith, Sir, I'd have you know 'tis worth ready money. at any time f º - * - alth, * * * * * * . l
Page 17

(17) faith, I'Hºwear, it ſhall ne'er go under Matrimony. Dol. She is honeſt, i'faith : I love a vertuous wº I am none my ſelf; like him that lov'd the ſound of Greek, though he underſtood it not. She is righthoneſt, ifaith... Bid. Marry me, and then halloo Dog forthy, Silver coller.3 but till then, F1 gnaw my under-ſheet to the bed-cord, before ou ſhall have your will of me. I am ſometimes mad when I think how I left my friends: ſometimes I could ſcold, and ſometimes I could cry, and the Devil take that good face of yours, I can do neither for it. . . . . . . . . … . . ) Cor. Come,come,you truſt your perſon with me,and why not . your virginity ? How long do you think you can hold out at . this ſtanch rate. - - - , - Kid. Faith, Sir, I can hold out till it's fit for no body.: till I'm paſt the uſe of man, before thou ſhalt have it, ſhameleſs wretch. - - - ºf s \ . ; : Del. She is certainly honeſt, and that's half our work done. - " . . - r Cor. Come, prethee let's think of our mock-marriage with Dol, and after we'l be ſerious. . . .” ' ' '. Bid. Why, I'm for that too. 5 but yet I cannot chuſe but cry to ſee how falſe you are, and how they talk at home of me, ſhe's run away with a Souldier, and that raſcal will not marry her, O the Devil take you, I ſhall never recover that credit again! - º • €or. Come, we'P cozen’em all at laſt, tº ºf . , - tº Eid. Nay, I believe thou'lt cozen more than me; for what woman can forbear running away with thee, that ſees thoſe kering eyes, thoubewitching Devil, thou! . . . . . . . . : Cor. Oremember you hate ſcolding, Biddy.. . . . . . . . . Iid. I had forgot that, indeed...g. . . . . . . . . Cor. Nay, Pr'ythee no more of this ſtory. . . . * Fid., Well, I will not : but truly I grow weary of your unkindneſs; and I am ſerv'd well º for ſcorning a man that doated on me, ſº ºr j . . . . . . . . . . . Dal. Aha! I marry, that’s ſomewhat indeed, , , , , º Bid. But I ſee, a Cornet with his flying Colburs, and his
Page Scan 32

w (7) tº rant you; and, in ſhort, this is my buſineſs hither. “ Ferret.And canſt thou fight ' ' ' '. Tell. Wilt thoutry . . . . . . . . . . . . . Ferret, No, faith, friend, I believe thee, Waſt’ ever a Soul- dier * Tell. I, a Parliament one. * Plea. What, and did'ſt thou run away 2 . . . . . Tell. No, Iºwałk'd this pace: I ſcorn to run. . . . . - Burn. I believe this fellow's a Spy. . . . . . . . Tell. You lye 3 I am very honeſt. Now dare you fight? Burn, No, by my troth, not with thee. . . . . - . * Then remember, if anybody want the lye, you had 1t lalt. • . . . . . . . .-- Flea, This is ſuch a fellow as I never met with. Yet why did'ſt thou leave the Parliament? . . . . . . .) Tell. For the ſame cauſe that I believe I ſhall leave you, Flea. What's that? r º Tell. Becauſe I lik'd'em not. , tº "º 9 º' 'º º Ferret. Who was thy Captain * : * ~ * : * ~ * * * Tell. One Captain Perily Rett. … . . . . . Ferret. Of what Profeſſion was he Tell. Of every ones Profeſſion, I think. º ". . . . Ferret. What's that? . . . . . . . . . . . . . Tell. An Hypocrite. . . . . . . . . . . . . . it " . . . . Burm. And doſt thou come out of love to the King? -- Tell. No 5 I come to ſee faſhions. * - Burn. But why did'ſt thou leave thy Captain? Tell. Becauſe he is an Hypocrite, a yea and nay knave; he catinot endure to plunder, but (in a godly manner) he will take all he can lay his handson. . . . . . . - corn. But wilt thou fight for the King out of ſtark love and kindneſs. ; : y : . . - - - - Tell. No; Il fight for him as all men fight for Kings, partly for love, partly for my own ends. I'l fight bravely for a Bat- - ** - - - r - - tel or two; then beg an old houſe to make a Garriſon of, grow rich, conſequently a coward, and then let the Dog bite the Bear, or the Bear the Dog, I’l make my own peace, I war- E//fer
Page 7

G6) * . . . . . . . . . . . . Ewter Lieutenant. . . . . . . . . . . . . . g : Lieut. Where are you, Sirs? the Captain has brought Or- ders to march, but whither I know not 5 and better news than that, he has brought pay, Boys. . . v. º Flea. I hope you are not angry, Lieutenant. . . . . . . : Lieut. I am not yet 5 but I ſhall be very ſuddenly, there- fore provide againſt it: the next freſh quarter you will have advantage enough. I hope we underſtand of all hands. Flea. 'Tis ſufficient, Lieutenant. “ . . . corn. But here's the ſtrangeſt fellow come to be a Trooper. ... Lieut. He’s welcome. Haſt thou a good Horſe, friend? Tell. No, but I've a bridle, and if you'l entertain me, I ſhall quickly have a horſe. Are you the Captain 2 - £ient. I am but Lieutenant, friend. ... * * - -- ... ºv Tell. Ho, I thought you had all been Captains, Fm ſure you ‘. . . . . - , , . . . . . . . .\.T - are all call’d ſovº, ºr " * * * > . . . - . . . . . Enter Captain. . . . . Lieut. But here comes one that is ſo: this is a very Captain. Tell. Itell thee that's very much. What's his name?: , Lieut. Captain Honor. " . ." § 9d of ....' : Tell. I? have you ſuch a thing as Honoramongſt you? - - Capt. Lieutenant, get your Corporals, together, and give "em Orders to make ready for a march; and be ſure you charge *em to ſee every Horſe in their Squadrons ſhod, otherwiſe we {hall have 'em lye behind drinking and plundring, and then pretend they ſtay.toſhooe their Horſes: let me hear no more on't. . . . . . . . . . . . - . ºld Tell. 'Tis poſſible a very Captain may be honeſt. - ... Lieut. But, Sir, before you do any thing, talk with this fel- kw: he would fain be a Trooper. . . . . . . . . . [...i Capt. Now, friend, would'ſt thou be a Souldier?, 4.5 º, Téll. Yes; if I could light of a good ſide: a right cauſe, and good men to manage it. . . . . . . J … . . . . ; Capt. On my word, that's ſhrewdly put. Well, I'l promiſe theea good cauſe, and ſome good men: in multitudes all are not vertuous, nor valiant. ºf a ; ; , ; *... 19, 21... e. oi Telkiſhat's well ſaid: Ithink Iſhall begin to take aliking • 2 - to: --

End of Section 4. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 5
Page 8

..ſº ſ (8) to you. But, Captain, I hear a man may learn to flea a flint amongſt you, to drink and plunder. Capt. D'ye hear that raſcals 2 - - - But where § thou hear this reportofus 2 Tell. In a London-pulpit: but another ſort of people told me, they preach'd Intereſt more than Goſpel; ſo that a man {{nows not which ſide to take. I - - Capt. Nay, upon my word, thou art come to the right ſide. Tell, Igheſs as much; for you talk worſe than you do, and they do worſe than they talk. tº ... Capt. This is an odd kind of fellow, and I believe a dange- 'rous; Friend, withdraw, while I read my Orders to my Officers. : … . . . . . . ... " . . . . . . Tell. A word in your ear firſt, are you wonderful honeſt ? to Capt. Thou art a ſtrange blunt fellow; yes, I am honeſt. Tell. But are you wiſe too? for elſe the want of wit to ma- nage your honeſty, may make you a knave. I know 'tis ſome r **** mens caſes. . . - . . . . - - - - Capt. Thou doſt ſurpriſe me: ſure thou haſt moré buſineſs than to be a Trooper. . . . . . . . . . Tell. I have ſo ; but I muſt ask you another queſtion ere you . . . [...… . . . . ‘know it. Are you ſtanch enough to keep a ſecret P Be not an- gry 3 many of your party cannot hold: for tell you news, and you fly, like lightning, to the next man to diſgorge it, and ſo it goes round till it comes to the Enemy 5 and thus you be- tray your buſineſs, and intendit not neither. Fi pā, gº Capt. I have not heard ſo dangerous a man. Pray, friend, think me worthy to know your buſineſs. . . . . . . . . Tell. You ſhall. And to ſhew you that I have buſineſs, I know what your Orders are. . . . . . . . . . * -- capt. Why;’tis impoſſible. . . . . º. º.º. º. f"Tell. Nothing impoſſible: you are to remove your Troop to Cilſtow, there quarter till further Orders, but not to go to bed, for you are within three miles of a little houſe call’d Thiever-den Garriſon, and you; are to expect a company of Foot to quarter with you: is this your Ordersº. 2 º' … Tekſ. ºcºt. You amaze fle; how came yºu by thisintelligence? (, ,
Page 9

(9), ... Tell. It came to Thieves-den houſe this morning, and ſo te me; I am their Confidant, and would fain be yours. capt. Do you not know who ſent it 2 # No, nor they neither 5 there's the ſubtle carriage of the thing. - - capt. But pray, Sir, let me ask you who you are 2 - Tell. I am a plain, honeſt-meaning man, a neighbour to that Garriſon of Thieves-dem, and one that has div'd into the bot- . tom of both your parties, and find that you have faults, but the other great wickedneſs. . Flea, I do not like this fellow, he had a fling againſt drink. Ferret. And plundering 5 but twenty to one i. hath paid for’t. Flea. He had a plaguy jerk at flaying offlints too. Capt. What if you went to Oxford with me? Tell. So I may be hang'd when I come home again 5 for they will know it asſure. Pray let me eat, and refreſh myſelf, and then conclude of ſomething. [Exehnt. Enter Dol, and calls Lieutenant back. Dol. Lieutenant, I'd ſpeak with you. . Lieut. Dol, I'l come to thee preſently. [Exit. Dol. I cannot ſay I am with child, but with children 5 for here has been all Nations, and all Languages to boot: if the ſeveral Tongues ſhould work upwards now, and I ſpeak all Languages? why, I am not the firſt learned woman 3 but I believe the firſt that ever came by her learning that way. If I ſhould have for every man that has been dealing here a child, and if the children ſhould be born with every one a Back and Breſt on, as they were got? Bleſs me, what hard la- bour ſhould I have But, for all this, I hope I do not go with a- bove a Squadron of children. But to my buſineſs. I mean to lay this great belly to every man that has but touch'd my Apron-ſtrings. I thank the Law, 'tis very favourable in this point; for when I have play'd the whore, the Law gives me leave to play the rogue, and lay it to whom I will. . . - ... . . . . Enter Lieutenant. Lieut. Why how now Dol; how go matters with you,good Dol 3 - C T * ' ' ' ' Do!. -* * A - - \ r -
Page 10

(10) 4 * pol. I deſire you ſtand my friend, Sir, you ſee my condi- tion. . . . . . Lieut. Thou wilt not lay thy child to my charge, I hope. Dol. No, Sir, I have more wit 5 my drift is to lay it to more than one man, or one Squadron : Sir, I underſtand there's a months pay in your hands; and I am reſolv'd to lay this great belly to every man round the Troop 3" ſome I have ſtruck already, and they have very fairly compounded with me;. fome, I ſuppoſe, may buſtle and ſtand out, but if you - will countenance me , then they muſt compound at our - Licut. But Dol, what benefit is this to me? for I profeſ; no friendſhip, but follow the general principle of mankind, Dol; which is to pick the money out of thy pocket to put it into mine. So, Dol, in plain terms what will you give me? * Dol. Why, Lieutenant, you ſhall goſhips. . . . . . . . * Lieut. Why, Dol, we are agreed; but after we have ſtruck the Troop round, who doſt thou pitch upon to father it 2 Dol. Why,faith, I did deſign to marry Monſieur Raggou, the French Cook, that rides in your Troop. . . . . * Lieut. Thou wilt never indure to live with him, 'tis ſuch a naſty ſlovenly rogue. . . . . . . . . Dol. 'Tis no matter for living with him; I want a husband. Lieut. He ſtinks above ground: he has not had a ſhirt on's back time out of mind. Dol. That makes it a fit match 5 for, by my troth, I do not deſerve a man that's worth a ſhirt. - Lieut. Well, Dol, upon the aforeſaid terms, you're ſure of me, play your game with all confidence. bºl. Well, fito work amongſt empreſently: or if I might. gain you to advance my greater deſires, which is my Cornet's Boy that waits on him; I am fooliſh, for I love him ſtrangely, deſperately. A hundred pounds, in plain terms, make him mine, - - - Lieut. But, Dol, where is this hundred pound 2 Dol. I have ſhark'd theſe four years, and made a ſhift to. frape four hundredpounds together. JEichf.
Page 11

(11) • Lieut. Still I ſay you're ſure of me, with ready money. . . . . .e. Lieut. Still I ſay y ºd his Landlady. * * *... Enter Manſeur º - - - - - - well, Dol, away; here comes Monſieur Raggou, ſtep aſide: D. O' let him have his money : if our Cornets Boy fail, * FI have him, or he ſhall certainly keep the child. [Exit. Rag. indlady, come, take a my Piſtol and lock in your Trunk very ſafe... . . . . . . . tº ºf ... . . * - - : Land. Yes, Sir. " . . . . - - - -- Rag. Take heed, for begar you will be hang if my Piſtol run away. . . . **, *, . . . . . . tº Land. O Lord, I'l take no charge on't. . . . . . . ... ... Rag. You roundhead whore, lock it up, or me will kill you, begar. . . . . . - -- . Land. Titake all the care I canon't, Sir. . . . [Éxit, Ragºso, me will ſteal my Piſtol from her trunk, indſay ſhe carry it to de Enemy, and den me will ſo plundra de dam whore. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . * - I. º. - : i. Emter Bumpkin, º'- . . . Stand; who are you for, Bumpkin? . . . . . . . . . . . ." Eum, O Lord, Sir, I am for to body. - . . . . .” : Hag. You Dog, bé you for de King, or de Parliamenta ? ..., 2: Bam. Why I am for—pray, Sir, who are you for 2 m, , * Rag. Tank you for dat. Begar you be very fullwid cun- ning; you will be of my aſide ifmé name myſelf firſt. Speak, you dam Dog, who be you for 2 . . . º' - * Bum. Intruth it is not good manners to ſay who I am for.: your worſhip ought to ſpeak firſt. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . , , 1 Rag. Pox take you, me be for de Parliament, you Dog. Bum. O the Lord bleſs your worſhip, I am for the good Par- liament too. . . . . -- - W Rag. Je'rny, Ham for de King, you foundhead Dog: begar maiwill plundra you ſoul and body. . . . . . . . . . . . . . * Bum. Q good Sir, ſpare me; I am for the King, : . . .” Rag. Diable, me will plundra you for being jack of both), ſides. Diantie, he have but one ſilling about his ſoul and bodee. Get you gone, you Dog. [Exit Bumpkin. Begar, me have no luck, zoun me plundra every day dis tre ... .” 2 years, * - - -
Page 12

(12) years, and begarmeneverget but one ſilling or one ſix penne, begar. Ha! Monſieur Lieutenant, me hear very brave ting of you. - - }. What's that? Rag. Me hear you have ſome Largion for Monſieur La Soldier: pray how much will come to Monſieur Moy P Lieut. Faith, Monſieur, ſome three pounds. . * - *. , Rag. How, tre pone? whar be detre pone? how much be tre pone? - - - Lieut. Why, here 'tis, Monſieur, ſo much as you ſee. * , Rag. Begar, ſure you mock a de moy 3 begar me never ſee ſo much money togederin my life. Me will lye down and tum- ble in my money like de Dog dattumbla in de carrion, it isſo ſweet. O brave Capitain, O brave Lieutenant, Gad a bleſs de King of England, and de King of France too, when he give metre pone. Lieutenant, be to be mad a dangerous ting 2 Lieut. O, very dangerous. º Rag. Begardere be your tre pone again, it will make a me tark a mad 5 me no know vat me ſall do with all dis money: begar me admiretre pone of all ting in disvarle; it will make de great Turk de Chriſtian, or de Chriſtian de lurk, better den all de argument in de varle. Pray, Lieutenant, keep dis money form: one two treyear, till metake counſel of all my friend in France vat me ſall do wid dat. . . . . Lieut. Go to oxford, and buy ſome neceſſaries with 1t; you are ſo naſty, no body is able to come near you; buy ſome ſhirts, to keep you ſweet and clean. - - Rºg. Buy ſome ſhart? Me love you very yell, Lieutenant, but you no underſtand: for vatſalſ me have ſome ſhart? Lieut. To keep your ſelf ſweet, and from being lowfie. Rag. Who can ſee my ſhart 2 here be my, doublet come cloſe my coat come over all dat, den who de devil ſee my fhart? For vat ſall me have a ſhart, when nobody ſee my ſhart 2 . Lieut. But then you want ſtockins, and twenty neceſ. ſaries. - - . - - - * * - c. . - -- - - R45.
Page 13

(13) ": Rag. Me pull up my boot, who ſee me have a ſtockin P’you will have a littel Engliſh tricka, and never underſtand: for vat vill you have more ting about you, den vat vill make a ſhew in de varle, and every body can ſee? Pray let me lay out my. money to pleaſe my own fancee. Lieut. With all my heart. . . . . . . . . . . . i" Rag. Den me vill lay it out for my honor, and for de honor of de King, and my Lieutenant: Soadieu. Buy ſhart? who ſee my ſhart P. - LExit. : - Enter Dol. - - Dol. Faith, Lieutenant, I’l at him, and ſome of the reſt pre- ſently; therefore leave me to work: I am aſham’d, I am ſuch a fool to doat on a Boy, but no remedy: remember, there- fore, and about it. - - Lieut. Do you remember the hundred pound 3 II work him, fear not. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . [Exeumtſeverally. . . . . - _- - _-T ºf actus II. scien A 1. f — - Enter Dol Troop. Dol. ow to my buſineſs. My Flint-flayer compounded ...] N with me very civilly, that I did fear would have out-witted me: I am afraid of nothing but anim- pudent rogue that has no ſhame in him, that will father the child rather than part with his money, and ſo ſpoil my com- pounding with thereſt of the Troop. I'l be as wiſe as I can 5 ſo have among 'em. . . . . . . . . . . . . . - ... . . . . . . . . Enter a Trooper. - - - Troop. What a pox makes ſhe here 2 - . Dol. How d'ye, Mr. William # I'm come to tell you I am gone half my time, that you may provide 5 for I am quick. tre+.
Page 14

(14) gº Trºap...Art then?' faith, I'l be as quick as thou art, for I'l be in Holland (if the wind ſerve) to morrow, 2 . . . [Exit. * Dol. Slife, if they ſhould all boggle thus, I ſhould make a , thin Troop on't. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - Emter. Raggou..” “… . . . . . . . . . . . . Rag. O, Madam Do! / O dee, O dee? ºr ºf … . ' ' '. Dol. You ſee how I do: I am near my time, I deſire you to provide. You ſwore a thouſand oaths to me you would keep the child. . . . . . . . . Rag. But me did but ſwearin French, Madam Dol, and dat will no ſtand good in Engliſh Law, Madam pol: º, . . . sº. 1 poli. Come, Sir, come; I'l make you father my child, or I'l ‘make you do worſe : will you compound? … . . . . .” Rag. Meſcorn to compone, and ſcorn to fader your ſhild 5 you be a dam whore, Madam Dol. 3. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Dol. You are a Raſcal, Mr. Monſieur, and I'l make you fa- ther the child in ſpite of your French teeth. lººk ſºlº child but de May-pole in de Siran?'. ºnſ, ºan get you w; pear, by good vitteneſs, dàt me have to May-pole abouta me: Soadieu, Madam Babylon : Pox take you, me fader your dam ſon of a whore ſhild ! - [Exit. Dol. You fickle Frenchman, I ſhall be reveng'd on thee: I’l marry thee, but I'l be reveng'd on thee., . t . . . . fºr tº: and Biddy. º Aº, But here comes iny Cornet and his Boy, —and the ieutenant: I fee Hei mindfill bf my buſineſ. º,” “ . . [Exit. • Licut. Cornet, I have an earneſt and (by my troth) a moſt pleaſant ſuit to you. . . . . " ... . . . . . . cor. You cannot miſs the grant of it. What is't 2 ºf Licut. But firſt, do you love money 2 º’ ºr ºf cor. By my troth, I know not; for I never had a ſum worth º in my life yet. fºr Licut. Will fifty pound do any hurt?" º! cor. But what muſt I do for it?'betray the Troop to the ene- my, or ſome Garriſon 2 for under that I cannot deſerve fifty pound. - - Lieut. ºr ºf, t . - - , -º- a -* -
Page 15

- (15) - * Lieut. Towns are not ſo cheap yet: though Treaſondbe wº plentiful, 'tis not grown a Drug. . But to myſuit; youaré to know that out Dol is deſperately in love; and with whom. ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . cor. Not with me? I find I muſt earn this fifty pound, ºf ºtlieut. No ſuch matter: you have too great a conceit of your good face. ſº tº . Nº.'il o Bid. Indeed you lye, Lieutenant: for he can never think too well of that face. . . . . . . . . . ." [Aſide. v cer. Who is it ſhe is in love with ? ... ; ; ; ; º' Tº | Lieut. By my troth with thy Boy here: deſperately in love with thy Boy. - - ...: 33 tº ºur 1 Bid. The Devil take her for her pains. But why do I curſe her, that am ſo deſperately in love myſelf?... . . . . . [Aſide. “, cor. Why, this ſtory is very pleaſant, if you knew all. : : Eid. O. Lord's you will not tellſ him what: I am, i hope? ... . . . . . . .e. z º.º. 2diziº,' cºo cor. Lieutenant, I muſt deny your ſuit, for it muſt not be a match; for the Boy is, in plain terms, a Girl. + - Bid. The Devil take you for telling him. • , t * cor: Why ſo? my Lieutenant's very faithfuſ, ºr ºld : Lieut. A Girl? Let me ſee your face. .33% tº 1: ... }o Bid. O you unworthy man! Good'Sir, iforgive me; for I am even ready to ſcold. … . . . . . Lieut. This is the pretty young daughter that belong'd to your Winter Quarters, and ſo came away for love? ºf 2: …; Bid.:Yes, Sir 5 but if your Cornet had been true, I had been paſt Love by this time: I had been married. † -.' I Lieut. Why, are all marry'd people paſt love? - Bid. Yes, Sir, of the mens fide eſpecially: but, Sir, I am na- turally very merry, and ſhall be, if you will but dome the favour to think me very honeſt.… . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Lieut. I ſhall do you a great favour; if I do', for Inever thought any body ſo yet 5 but if it pleaſe you, Il try your ho- neſty, and then I'l give you my opinion, . . . . . Bid. Benot rude when you try me, if you be, you were: better venture on a Maiden-Cat at midnight; for Iſhall ſcratch - worſe,
Page 16

(16) worſe; and ſo mark you, not for my humble ſervant, but my humble Catterwauler..." . . . . . . . . . . . .” Lieut. I could meet ſuch a creature o'th' houſe top, at any hour, and ſcratch, and ſqueak, and tumble down together, and get the prettyeſt Kitlings as we fall. . * * Bid, I am glad to ſee you merry, Sir 5 for merry people are likely honeſt. w -, * * : Lieut. Well, we'l try; but, if you love mirth, conſent to marry with this Dol : there's money for us all. [Exit. Bid. Content, i'faith. Twill be excellent ſport to marry her, for I loveroguery well enough; but, the Devil's in't, ſhe'l know me to be a Girl. ºf , Enter Dol, aloof. - ... Cor. No, no; ſhe ſhall not come near you, nor touch you, till ſhe's brought to bed; then two to one but the Troop marches' away, and leaves her behind ; then I'm ſure the Country-Bumpkins will knock her oth head. * Dol. There's a Cornet in grain, I'faith. Bid. Troth, you are very charitable. Well, ſince my hand's in at wearing Breeches, I'l do all the Offices of a man: I would I had wherewithal to perform; for, by my troth, I am weary : of our own Sex. - - - ... Do!. She cryes, i'faith: I like that well. Cor. You little fool, you do not cry, I hope P - Bid. No, faith, that was but a tear by chance. You made me leave my friends (you know) when you talk'd of marriage to me; but not one word on't now you have made me your Be-de-Boy. . . . . . . . . . -- . . . . . : Dol. I know not what to ſay to that. cor. We’l talk of thoſe things when we are ſettled. & Eid. By my troth, you have put me in ſuch a gog of mar- riage, that it will not out of my head; and yet Iſcorn to ask you to marry me, and I ſcorn to crack a commandment with yeu: was not that baſely done of you to tempt me 2 but I ſhall ſcold, which is a thing I hate. O baſe fellow !you would be going oth' ſcore with me, for my Virginity P Faith, Sir, I'd have you know 'tis worth ready money. at any time; and . . . . * - faith, -
Page 17

(17) faith, I'l ſwear, it ſhall ne'er go under Matrimony. . . . . Dol. She is honeſt, i'faith : I love a vertuous wº I am none my ſelf; like him that lov'd the ſound of Greek, . though he underſtood it not. She is righthoneſt, ifaith... Bid. Marry me, and then halloo Dog forthy, Silver coller; but till then, Fl gnaw my under-ſheet to the bed-cord, before you ſhall have your will of me. I am ſometimes mad when I think how I left my friends: ſometimes I could ſcold, and ſometimes I could cry, and the Devil take that good face of yours, I can do neither for it. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - Cor. Come,come,you truſt your perſon with me,and why not your virginity ? How long do you think you can hold out at . this ſtanch rate. - - • •. - * , - Kid. Faith, Sir, I can hold out till it's fit for no body.: till I'm paſt the uſe of man, before thou ſhalt have it, ſhameleſs wretch. - - ! . . : Del. She is certainly honeſt, and that's half our work done. - - Cor. Come, prethee let's think of our mock-marriage with Dol, and after we'l be ſerious. . . . . .” . . . . . . ; Bid. Why, I'm for that too 5 but yet I cannot chuſe but cry to ſee how falſe you are, and how they talk at home of me, ſhe's run away with a Souldier, and that raſcal will not marry her... O the Devil take you, Iſhall never recover that credit again! : - * €or. ºvercºnºmialſ. ; : 1: . . . . Bid. Nay, I believe thou'lt cozen more than me; for what woman can forbear running away with thee, that ſees thoſe * Meering eyes, thoubewitching Devil, thou! . . . . . . . , : Cor. Oremember you hate ſcolding, Biddy.. . . . . . . . . Did. I had forgot that, indeed...g. . . . . . . . . . Cor. Nay, Prytheenomore of this ſtory. . . . - Fid., Well, I will not : but truly I grow weary of your unkindneſs; and I am ſerv'd well º for ſcorning a man that doated on me. His a …, Lal. Aha! I marty, that's ſomewhat indeed, , , , , . . . Bid. But I ſee, a Cornet with his flying Colburs, and his D. - word, * . .
Page 18

\ (18) word, Have at all, goes a great way with a virgin: who can reſiſt it? - - [Exeumt. - Enter Captain, Lieutenawt and Tell-troth. Capt. Lieutenant, ſtay and receive Orders. But, Sir, how many companies are there in Thieves-dew Garriſon? ... - Tell. Ne'er a Company; for not one of 'em will be called Captain of a Company, but Captain of a Congregation. One , is call’d Captain Holdforth, another, Captain Tubtext 3 Rogues mark'd at the Font for Rebellion. “ . . ; Capt. Rebellion is the firſt point of Reformation always. Tell. They are form'd to a new ſtamp of villany, the laſt Im- preſſion 5 that which put the Devil into a cold ſweat: take the wickedeſt and worſt-reputed men you have, and turn 'em looſe to Plunder, and Idefie’em to make the Tythe oth ſpoil theſe hypocrites have done. . . . . . . . . . . . capt. You are very bitter. . . . . . . ." Tell. Malice cannot lay 'em open: they Leóture it thrice a week, and ſummon the Country to come in : they that refuſe, they take their goods, and leave 'em ne'er a groat; and then they ſay, They took but their own, for the good creature is the inheritance of the people of Gad. . . . . . . . . . . . capt. It ſeems, every Captain is a Teacher, and his own Company is his Congregation; ſo that º: draw Religion among themſelves. No doubtmo blaſphemous vil- lains. - if c : " , º, t– Tell. Well, Sir, I'l home to night; march your Troop to Lavel to morrow 3 ſtay till I come to you: So fare you well; and I wiſh a bleſſing upon your good meaning. . . . . [Exit. capt. Lieutenant, be careful how you march to morrow, and take heed; I hear of no complaint. I'l to oxford in the morning, to give an account of this fellow. . . . . . . . . . - Lieut. I hope you’l allow us our old harmleſs Drolleries. cap. I, moſt freely. . . . . . i . . [Exit. -- - - . . Emier Cornet. . . . . . . . . . . .' Cor. Lieutenant, half the Troop will be gone: Dol has laid her child to 'em all, and they're for Horſe and away." Lieut. What ſhall we do?… * * …, , , , º, . ; tr. ºf - • * ** Cor.
Page 19

- (1 9) - cor. Indeavour to prevent it, that is all that's to * #. - --- ... º.º. occaſ Wife. Enter a Traoper with his Arque, and Aſºfteer Ragggu meets him. Rag. Ow dee, ow dee, Monſieur Lancaſhire * vat make yow have your arms.ſo late at night? is dere Alarm? be de enemy in de quarteer? . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 1 Troop. Worſe than the enemy, the Devil's in the Quar- ter: our Dol is with child,and would lay it to me; but I'l lay down my Arms, and go home. * { *.ſ.. . . . . . ) Rag. Begar, me villay down my Arms, and go home too; Hal begar, now itink, mehave no home. . . . [Exit, 1 Troop. Captain, Captain. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ...).; * Within...Who's there? what's the matter 2, ..., , , , , * I Troop. Thomas, 'tis I; the old Mutinier: tell the Captain . I muſt ſpeak with him, . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Within. He is but juſt laid down on the bed,to ſleep a little. Come i'th’ morning. . . . . . . . . tº orcy : ºriº's . ." ºroup. Fleſh dºublood, I will ſpeak with him. . . . . - - - - - - - i, º, . * * Captain above. . . . . . . . i : , ; c. 'i capt. What's the matter? an Alarm *, * , - 1 Troop. I marry is there, Captain; there will be a whoſe Squadron upon you preſently. tº gº 2:... . . . . Capt. 'Sdeath, my horſe, preſently. Esº i . . . 1 Troop. The Enemy Dolisſalminto our Lancaſhire quarters, ºr and has laid her Child to our Squadron: ſo here is your Back and your Breſt, Captain, and I'lgo home. - Enter four Troopers and Raggou. 3:2 Troop, Fleſh, we'l father no child, not we. . . . . . . . . ‘ Rag. Begar, mevil fader no ſhild too. Hey Monſieur Cap- tain, here be your one Piſtole. . . . . . . . 3 Troop. Captain, we have brought you ſome Lancaſhire Arms 3 here is ten or eleven Sowze Kidgiors for you. . . . ..., cap. Whatabevil ayls the fellows? [Aboue. ... ', Rag. Begar, Capitain,me vill keep noſhild: your dam Ma- dam Dol i. get us all jº. . . . . you d ... " w Capt. Run for the quean to come to me: I ſhall have all my Troop forſake me. Stay,ſº I'l come to you: imº - º well
Page 20

(20) well humour'em as be ſevere, or eſſenosouldiers. . . . . ) . . . . - * * - [Exit from above. --- #4. ve, me do know very vell how it ſall be my ſhild or no. * * * * *. 1. * - " - - - 2. > * 4 Troop. Well, Monſieur, and I have a mark to know whetherit be mine or no, as well as you. * * : * ~ * , 2 Troop. And ſo we have alſ. … . . . . . . . . . . . . : * : Enter captain and cornet. . . . . . . . . . . . Capt. My Maſters, you might have had ſo much manners to have held your complaints till morning; but however I have ſent for Dol, and I'ſ do you juſtice before Iſtir now. How now, Raggou; what are thy ſleeves ſtuff'd withal ſo 2 Rag. Begar, dis ſleeve be my Stabla, dere;be good Oata £er mine Arſe: 'ahd-dis ſleeve be my:Kitchin, dere be meat for my ſelf. Will you eat dis morning, Capitain?, ºf . . . ; - Capt. Foh, your ſleeves ſtink abominably. ºf . , º, a Rag. Zoun, do you call data ſtinka 2 'tis true, it have a lit- tle huggo: bāgar, dis ſleeve keep your Troop alive 5 dis - ſleeve is de Phyſician to all de Troop: When any man be ſick, fieſet on ſome hot vatera, dere let my fleeve boyſ one hour it it, and dat make de comfortable Pottage in de varle. Have - * - not mecure you all? . . . . . . . . tº gº º-º. . . 4 Troop. Yes, indeed, Captain, he has cur'd us twenty tiſints. . " . . . . . . º ºr 7... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . , Rag. Begar, Capitain, me have cure that dam whore Ma- dam Đol, and yet for all datſhe lay her ſhild a top upon me. . . • ‘’ ºl Enter Dol, v. 5 capt. O, here ſhe is: Now (you audacious quean) what makes you'Alarm theſe people thus? Who got you with child? ſpeak, and ſpeak truth I charge you. . . . o. º. . . . Doi why then I will ſpeak truth; an't pleaſe you : good Captain do not fright me." - . . . . . . . ; ; ; ; ; *. Capt. Well then. Is it his child?, did he get it?iº ºn **Doł. I cannot ſay abſolutely 'tis his, Captain, ºf . , ... capt. Why, is it this fellows? iſ dº. . . . . º. º' ºpol. I cannot ſay diretty’tis his neither. “ . . cpt. Is it Monſicuſ Aaggou's * * * * *.i. tº go - 1 & i: , ". * : º - r
Page 21

(21) : Dol. I cannot ſay (to ſpeak truth)'tis his in particular. capt. Death, (you abominable quean) ſay whoſe 'tis, or II ſlit your noſe. . . - - - ... dol. Why, truly, I cannot lay it to any one man; but Gad is my judge, 'tis the Troops child, Captain. ... . . . . . ºf capt. Was ever ſuch a ſlut heard ºf . s Dol. I deſire your worſhip to believe me in one thing: truly, Captain, and as Gad's my comfort, I have been as true and faithful a woman to the Troop, as ever wife was to a huſ: ‘band, Captain. - Tº dº areyouſº me tinknow,Madam pel, youare. de whore de Babylon 5 for one whole Troop may make a May- pole. - ... * - " " . . capt. Why this is ſome honeſty yet, that ſhe is true to the Troop. . . . . . . . . . … cº ºf 2. * . . . . Rºº. Ould, Capitain, for oughtame ſee dis ſhild beyour ſhild... . … ºc : *****! … . . . . . . . . . - , - Capt. How prove you that, Sir 2 * Rag. Begar, ſhe ſay de ſhild belong to de Troop, and you ſay de Troop belong to you 5 derefore de ſhild is your ſhild, begar. ; : . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . … . . . . . . . . . . . . ... Capt. But I'l make ſome of you father it. There is none * -- *- of you but have ſome private mark to know it (to be your own) by. - • ‘. . . . . . . . . . - - - - ... 4 Troop. Faith, Captain, if it be born with a Gauntlet and a Head-piece on, I'l own it. *~. . º } ." . . . ºf - . . . » 2 Troop. Troth, Captain, if it be born with a Bridle inits hand, and Boots and Spurs on, I'l own it, . . . . . . ... I Troop. Troth, Captain, I ne'er touch'd her; I was about it once; but the jade laid her ſelf ſo like a Conſtable ty'd neck and heels together, that I went to plunder her, and ſhe up and beat ºne like a Dog. . . . "gººd, by my oth, if it be born leading, horſe into the world, 'tis my child, Captain. . . *... Rag. Ould : you every one, have a mark to know your ſhild: Madam Dol, before my Capitain, if your ſhild be born widinevera ºrdin it be my ſhild; for mehave had no ſhart dis forty week. Fzzi Cº-
Page 22

(23) { - … tº: " : it." Enter Ferret-farm. . . . . . . . . 1. Ferrer. By your leave, Captain.” . . . ." . . . . . . Capt. What want you, Aſpin & . . . . . . . . . . Ferret. I come to free all theſe men, and to own the child, Captain. • *, - -- . pol. How, own my child? the Rogue never touch'd me in his life, Captain. . . . . . . . . ." . . . . Ferret, Ha, Doll Confeſs, confeſs. Will you have the truth; Captain? ºr . . . . . .” --- ~ * - Capt. I, §: my heart, *::Ferret. Why;then I muſt confeſs ſhe goes with two children: one Higot on the great 'trunks end, and the other on a ſtair. caſe, by my life, Captain. * T : * Cap. I never heard of ſtair-cafe children before. * Rag. But vat if de ſhild be born wid no ſhart? you ſalt be hang before you fader my ſhild. º. - Dol. Captain, if I were to dye to morrow, the rogue ne- wer º,getth - ode *c. - . . . . * Ferret. I’l cudget ther to deat tain. capt. Hold, hold. oguet * * . . * . . . . Rag. Let him come, Captain: me villkill him, begar. . . . . . . . . . [Draws and throws off his cºat. Capt. Hold Dol. I charge you to put up, Monſieur. * * Rag. Me will put up den. . . capt. Not one word more, I charge you, but all to your quarters. Be gone, Cornet, 'tis time to ſound to Horſe; and take heed I hear of no complaints. " . . . . . . . . . . . . . Rag, Begar, me never ſee all dat before 5 diable, me be Monſieur Raggou indeed: me vill put on my coat preſan, for begar if Monſieur Dung-hill-raker ſee me, begar he vill put The in his ſack. - r. [Exeumt. Enter twelve Troopers at ſek doors; two at a door. - 1. Troop, Pox of this French fool, what does he mean to give us all Ribbons? we do but laugh at him. - 3. Troop. His buſineſs is to be admir'd 5 I admire he has *ought him ne'eraſhirt. - ---- airwop. He islike the Hypocrites, that will not ſing Pſalms. . . becauſe:
Page 23

(23) (º becauſe they've ne'er a Room to the ſtreet, they cannot be heard. s - 4 Troop. And ſo hel have ne'er a ſhirt becauſe it cannot be feen. - - - Enter Lieutenant, Flea-flint, Ferret-farm, and Burndorp. Lieut. Come, to horſe, to horſe. - Flea, Lieutenant, pray let Monſieur Raggon ride before, and make the Quarters to night. - -- Ferret. Pray do, Sir : for every freſh quarter we know you exped, and therefore you muſt wink. … Lieut. But, Sirs, I dare not own you, for my Captain is ſo fevere, that proteſt hel hang any man that plunders; eſpe- cially you Flint-flayars, that he has forgiven ſo often. . . . Bumr. Why, Sir, we'l venture that, for we have a way to rome off. ºr a ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Lieut. Pray how for if the Country complain (and they diſcover you) the world cannot ſave you. . . . . . . . . . Flea, Why, Sir, you know Monſieur Raggou has a remarka- ble coat, with one ſleeve always fill of Meat for himſelf, and the other full of Oats for his horſe. -- " - - - - Lieut. Well, what then? º A" Flea, Why,I have ſuch a coat; and I will ſtuffup the ſleeves, and rob like him; I can ſpatter French, and have every thing ſo like him, that your ſelf cannot diſtinguiſh. . . . . . . Lieut. Well, and how rob thereſt?: 7 : . . . . . . . . . . Ferret. To ſatisfie you, in ſuch diſguiſes as the Devil can- not find us out in. B ºo: t , , ºf g º " . . . . . . . ... Lient. You'lldo well to keep in thoſe diſguiſes ſtill, for iſfaith he'l find you at the long run elſe. Well, if you will ven- ture, do; Pl aid you in what I can. … ... Burn. If the Country complain, they come direétly to you, Hieutenant. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Ferret. Then you bid 'em deſcribe the men, and without peradventure they fall upon the Frenchman, with his re- markable ſleeves. . . . . . . . . " " " ' " " ºf Lieut. But ſuppoſe he ſtand it out, and make it out where he was in the time of plundering & ... . . . . . . . . i. - ºłę4.
Page 24

- (24) * Flºa. That's ſhrewd, I conſeſ. . . . ." . , Lieut. Come, I'l help you...If the Country-men come in, and deſcribe him, I'l go directly to him, and tell him, I have Orders to ſeize him, for my Captain is reſolv'd to hang him: - ſo out of my kindneſs to him, I'l let him make his eſcape; and I'l warranthel away as if the Devil drove him. . . . • Ferret. But, ſuppoſe he will not go at that neither, for he's impudent enough. - - * * : Lieut. Ha! if he will not (let me ſee) I'l write a Letter and have it ready in my hand, and we'l pretend to ſearch him for ‘Letters of Intelligence, and ſo clap the Letter into his pocket, and pullit out again, which ſhall be as if itcame from the ene- my, and that (according to his promiſe, they hope) he will ‘betray the Troop. - - - " ; ' ' ' . . . Ferret. I marry, this is ſomething: needs muſt he go, that - - - º - - * * the Devil drives. . . . . . . . . . . ºr º 'º - ... Flea. Then much more muſt he go that the Lieutenant drives: Twarranthe goes to ſome purpoſe. . . . . . Ferret. Good 5 and when he is gone and fled fort d Lieut. The caſe is plain, he's guilty: none but he could O 1 tº : * I * -- … Burm. Why, this is Plot and Intrigue, laid, infaith.” “ . . . . . . . .” tº : Flea. Why then Eſperanza ºf". ** 1. --- - Ferret. What work we'l makel 1 ºr rºle . . . . . … . . . . . Enter Raggou and his Landlady. . Eieut. Here comes the poor rogue and his Landlady: he httle thinks of our Tragical defign againſt him. I'l ſtep aſide, and ſee what work he’lmake. º - - . [Exeunt, Rag. Come Ladlady, bring memy Piſtole, me muſt march. Land. I, Sir, I'l fetchityou: 'tis ſafe enough. . . . [Exit. Lieutenant, - bravely Rag. Begar, me have ſteal my Piſtole, me will make her be hieveſhe will be hang, and denſ ſhe vill endure plundering de betra. But (pox take her) me have ſearch, and ſhe have noting to plundra. . . . . . - - * . . . . ºf Enter Landlady. . “ . . . . Land. O Lord, what ſhall. Edo, Monſieur? your Piſtols. $ºns. - . . * Rag.
Page 25

(25) Rag, Hal . . . . . . Land. It is gone, it is ſtoln. • r Rag. Ha! you have º my Piſtole to de enemy (you dam whore) Begar, you ſall hang trepair of Stair higher den Hazmam. - Land. Truly I know not what's become on't: I hope you have it your ſelf. - - Rag. O, you dam whore, me vill plundra your houſe for iſlander a moy. - ~ Land. Good, Sir, I have nothing worth plundering, but a great Cheeſe. . . . . . . Rag. Give me your Sheeſe, you devil you. * . Land. Here it is, Sir, and all I have in the world. . . . Rag. Pox take you, give me one ſhilling for my Sheeſe. tº Land. With all my heart : truly it's all the money I have. " Rag. Now give me my Sheeſe agen, you dam whores Vatſall me do wid dis Sheeſe? it will not go into my Kitchin- !. Begar, for one ſhilling more you ſall have the Sheeſe -11] • * `-------' . . . . . . . . . . . . Land. You'l plunder it again? … . . . . . - Rag. Begar, it go agen my conſcience to take your Sheeſe, becauſe it will nogo in my Kitchinſleeve. . . . . . . . . . . : ; Land. I have not a peny to ſave my life. … º. . . . . . Rag. Begar, meſell it to your Neighbour. . . . . . .” º º Enter Neighbour. Vat vill you give me for my Sheeſe. Land. It's my Cheeſe. Rag. Begar ſhe lye, me plunder it very fair fiom her. Neighb. Then I hope I may buy plundred goods as well as other people. What's your price? . Rag. Begar, Dog-ſheap : one filling. … Neighb. There's your money. º Land. Will you offer to buy my Cheeſe? Neighb. 'Tis my Cheeſe. Land. I'l try that. [Fight & excunt, Rag. Begar, fight till de devil part you, ~ * * E Eºfeſſº
Page 26

(26) Enter Lieutenant, and all the Trooper. I - - " ... O Monſieur Lieutenant . . . . . . . . . Lieut. What doſt with that Cheeſe? r Rag. My Landlady love me vera dear, and ſhe give me dis Sheeſe as a token to wear for her ſake. . . . - - - Lieut. Raggou, you muſt needs go make the quarters for the *Troop. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ." , , ... ", - ** avu - f - - t Rag. Wid all minheart. But, Lieutenant, dere be a favour for you. . . . . . . . . . . [Gives him a knot of Ribbon. Lieut. But what is the meaning of this 2 . . . . . . Rag. Begar, it be for my honer: me have lay out all my tre pone in Ribbon, and give allide Troop my favour to wear in de Hat..: . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - . … Lieut. What, and is all thy, three pound gone in Ribbon, and bought never a ſhirt 2. ‘Tisºvery fine. . . -- r" . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ºfag. Regar, and ſo it be very fine. As me tell you before, who de devil ſeemy ſhart? all de varle ſee Monſieur Rasgow. in de Hat: every man will admire, and ask, who gave all that favour to de Troop * den dey-cry; Monſieur Raggou de French Cook; begar, datſall be more honer for me, den ever you ſall get by your ſhart.' . . . . . . . . . ºn 3 Lieut. Thou artia, right Frenchman, My horſe there, Groom.: Let's march away. . . . . . . . . . - - - - [Exeumt. - * - - - . . . . . . " ". . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .'; 3 ºf -, 4. - - - - t - " - . . . . . . . . . . . .." * . . . . . . . ." - - - --> --> f : . . " - - - : . . . . . . . . . . . . . ; itſ ºf “ . . . . . . . . ‘. . . . ." – -— --- - - * - - - … - - - - - - - - - - - - - * . - - - - - - * . . . tº . . . . . . . . .” - -- ºiſ.; , ; , : " : :"... tº . . . - * * * * - ---, -º-º: ‘. . . . . * * - - - - - ~~ . . . "tº ſº; ... ''{}^* . . . . . . . . . Y. ... " ! --> - - * - - * * - S. : . . 2: … 'ſtſ: " : , , , ‘. . . . . ; *ACTU 'o- - - - * - -- - - - - - - - * . º . . . . - , "I -- --- º - * C- | .* *_ - --- - - * * - * - T r : - t - --- --- -/ * - * - - - - - * º, --, - * * - + -- - Jºgº tºyºſ. -*** : J -> c. * c. ** , -- * w º, ** -

End of Section 5. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 6
Page 27

- ** - (27) "...a vºw 2:1 tº 20:52 : ...: tº ºr - - ". . . . . ‘. - J. : 1-3 - S - º Actus III, so ENA I. - - ' ' . . . . . . . . ". . . . ] i. -- , , enter Flea-flint, Ferret-farm, and Burndorp. º Burn. 'Tis like enough to delude the people with. . . L} +... Flea. I'l-rant and tear the ground, Boys. I will ſo plundra all de dam Bumpkin Dog. . . " Ferret. That will paſs: that's his word: 'tis like him. Flea. Be you pretty modeſt, Sirs, and let me play the de- - - - I *I* this like him as can be? . . villamong 'em. I will ſo terrifie 'em with French gibberiſh, . - that you ſhall appear no body amongſt 'em. . . . . . . . . . . . . Burm. Good: for the more ačtive and terrible thou art, I they will the more remember thee when they come to com- plain, and ſowe ſhall be ſure toſcape. iſ C . . . . Flea. Come away, Sirs 5 we muſt be quick, and ride hard I fort, i. 2; if I \tiº ſº. of woº tº . . . . [Exemºnt. Enter Raggou like Flea-flint. . . . . . º Rag. Begar; me have makaīmy ſelf, like Flea-flint, and me vill burn one two Town as megó to make a de Quarter, and me vill ſpeak Engliſh and me will call my ſelf Flea-flimt's let me; ſee: Come,where is this Conſtable? where are all theſe damn'd dery damn'd Rogues and Whores? I'l flay your very ſouls, it you beaſtly Bawds. Begar, all dat be very good Engliſh, and it be very much like Monſieur Flea-flint, and begar, me ho he will be taken and hangfordat, for begardme vill plundra de devel if me catch him. - [Exit. . . . * ºf , ºf I. Enteº, cºrnet and Biddy...ºd i, . . . . . Cor. Come, let me ſee, Biddy, how finely you'l court your . Miſtreſs now. . . . ::, ; W ºf . . . . . . . . . . . . .” Bid. I can court her as all men COllrt women; you ſhall, lendme two or three hundred gaths yout diſſembling * '**'. E 2 all

End of Section 6. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 7
Page 28

and your falſe heart, and then I cannot miſs the right way of wooing her. - - Cor. This comes very near ſcolding, Biddy, * - - " * [Taker her by the chim. Bid. You makeme forget my ſelf: look you now, would any honeſt man take a Maid ſo kindly by the chin, and yet not mean to marry her P. cor. Thou little fool, at that rate every man i'th Kingdom. would have ten thouſand wives: if you'l part with your Maiden-head, have at you Biddy. Come, come, you loving: worth, I know I ſhall have it at laſt. . . - . *Bid. Nay, o' my conſcience I believe thee 5, yet I have held. faſt hitherto. - - . . . - Cor. I am glad to hear that, i'faith. Bid. But I find I muſt look no more on thoſe eyes 3 if I do; i’ſaith I ſhall flutter ſo long about the Candle, that I ſhali . ſinge my Virgin wings-atlaſt: I will therefore now conclude; I am a man, and muſt go court my Miſtreſs. -- - - Enter Lieutenant and Dok - Cor. Here's the Lieutenant and Dol, now behave your ſelf like a man. * * : * : - " - . . . . . Bid. Could youſhew me how to behave my ſelflike an hor neſt man? that's out of your way I doubt...” Dol. Still better and better. This confirms me... . . . . Bid. Well, give me thy hand: I’m reſolv'd to be very ver... tuous, and very merry, and never think more of thee. cor, Well, Mrs. Dol, here's one has conſanted in part to, marry you, ". . . . . . . . . . . . ºf , . Dol. Pretty creature! . . . Eid. Ugly Toad... • Aſide. - * º; Well, and will yoube contenttoride beforeme loving- -a days 2 . . . . * . . • - y; I, and behind theetoo; ride thee all the points o'th." €ompaſs, wench, fear not. - Bid. O Lord, but is there ſo many ways of riding, Lieute-- hant? * , , *: , , Iicut. Haſtthouſiv'd to theſe years;and not known that yet?’ ... - ‘. . . Qars.
Page 29

- (29) Cor. Well, but when will you marry? … . . . . . . . . . , Eid. Nay, by my faith, let us woo firſt, and then marry: be- cauſe I believe there is more pleaſure in wooing than in the effects of it. . !cor. Why do you not begin and court her then * : . . Bid. Nay, by my faith, let her begin firſt. - - Lieut. That's not the mode for the woman to woo the man. Eid. That is, if the man love the woman 5 but that's not my caſe: for 'tis ſhe loves me, not I her. Lieut. O, but in complaiſance you muſt begin : . It is not civil to put a womau to't. . . . . . . . . . . .” Eid. Not I, faith: pray forſooth do you begin. Dol. Indeed it ſhall be yours. - . . . - Bid. I proteſt it ſhall be yours: therefore begin, or I. vow I'l break off the match. º Dol. Nay, rather than ſo, I'l begin, Sweet, Sir, Iain much, and greatly aſham'd. º, .." – … " ; Were you ever ſo before, Miſtreſs? at: Yes, truly, I have been aſham'd; but it is ſo long, ce - - * - , Bid, That you have forgot it, Iſuppoſe. But I diſturb you, forſooth. 7 - - sº º, 'i ... Dol. No diſturbance, ſweet Sir, (I want fine words to ex-- preſs my love in.) I am ſorry that the Cart-wheel of Fortune ſhould drive me into the Coach-box of your affection. Bid. Fortune will take it ſcurvily to call her wheela Cart- wheel: beſides, Coach-box and Cart-wheel did never agree in this world yet. - . . . . Dol. I am not able to expreſs my love as it deſerves 5 but I have four hundred pound in gold, if that will do it. Eid. By my faith you expreſs your ſelf very well, and I will woo you heartily for it. Madam, you have ſtruck me: with ſuch a deſperate Dart, from thoſe fair ſomewhat or other. that you have about you.- Are you ſure you have the gold you ſpoke of?: - Dol, Yes, my dear heart; very ſure. . . . - Aid. Then if I do not love you above all women-kind;.. . … - - * * periſh,
Page 30

(39) - & periſh me, and ſink me, refuſe me, rot me, and renéunce me, ºdorº Hold, hold, hold: do you call this wooing?!'" " - ºRid. Yes faith; I had a Siſter caſt away with the very ſame ſpeech, therefore do not interrupt me, for I know all man- * wooes thus." And, as I was ſwearing, Madam, the Devil talkC :... tº . . . . . . . . . . . ºn tº . . .” º ºut. Enough; enough, enough, enough. º Bid. But, Madam, are you ſatisfi'd? Tº . - Dol. I am, to the full ; and do believe you. . . . . . . . . . Bid. But, if you pleaſe, Madam, now my hand is in, to ac- cept of a hundred or two of oaths more. . . . .” - a . Dol. No, no, no 3 by no means: I believe you without 'em, and I am yours. . . . . . . . . . . . . Bid. I have not ſworn out halfmy Alphabet yet. . . . " Dol. You have done ſufficiently, indeed. . .” - , , , ºf 43rd. Well; givene your ji. yóu are the firſt wo- man certainly, that was ever gain'd with ſo little ſwearing. ** cor. Thouhaſt wooed her, and won her moſt bravely. Bid. Have I? why, then I'm thine. But hark you, Lieute-, nant and Cornet, we will be married privately, and in the dark, becauſe her face ſhall not turn my ſtomach. Madam, I. have one ill humor, I cannot abide a woman with a bare face'3" therefore, if I could buy you a maſque that would ſtiek to your face, and never come off. I believe I ſhould love you very : - well. - - -- - - - Dol. II have a Maſque, or what you pleaſe, my dear: * … Nextbour, thopé, will beiny turn to jeer.º. º. Lieut. Come, let's in, and viſit our new Quarters, º º (1: ! . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . [Exeumt. Emter Raggou making guarters, Conſtables and Neighbours. I Neighb I beſeech your worſhip do not quarter ſo thany up- on me: I'm but a poor man. . . . . . . ſº . . . . . 2 Neighb. Alas poor man!, you have over-char. 'd him. Rogue, he has more money than half the Town. . . . . . . . Kag. You be a dam Dög to betray your Neighbour; who would tink to find de devel in a Country-Bumpkinſ. Begar, me vill-make uſe of your develty,' , riſ C7) i i" i " . . . .” -º . . . I Neighb.

End of Section 7. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 8
Page 31

- (3) - w - & II Neighh. I pray'your worſhip take four horſe from ſnc.”.” Rag. You be a dam rich Dog: begar, you ſail have a Squadron upon you, if you no underſtand me. I Neighb. How ſhould I underſtand you? . . . . . . . . . Rag. You be a dam Dog: begar, me vill put twenty horſe upon your back till you underſtanda moy. Vat vill you give me, if I take all de horſe from you? . . . . . . . . . . . ... I Neighb. Indeed I'l pray for your worſhip. . . . - - Rag. O ho! be dat all 2 do you underſtand noting but prayer? Divel you fool vat be prayer to de Quarteer M.- - * * fter 2 but can you pray in French P : . . . . . . v. ºf I Neighb. Alas, # an’t pleaſe you. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Rag. Den, begar, your Engliſh prayer vill no ſave a French- man; you fall have ten Arſe more fo dat. - - - - *** 2. Neighb. An't pleaſe you, Monſieur, I underſtand you.…. Rag. Youſall have no Arſe upon you. . . . ; ; , , * * * * 3 Neighb. And Iunderſtand you very well; Sir. . . .” Rag. Begar, you have very muſh;a great deal of underſtand- *11191. -- - - - - - - - : " --> -- *: ". . . . * * * * * 3 Neighb. Here are more of our Neighbours that underſtand you, Sir. . . . . . . . . . . ." … . . . . . . sº Rag. Begar, den me underſtandi too: get all your money togedra, and put in myºpocket your ſelf den me can ſwear begar, menever take no peny of you, a hal, " . . . . . . 3 Neighb. We will do it gladly, Sir, and pray for you too.” i Rag. Begar, me no care for dat. But you dam Dog, that rounderſtania moy, fall quarteer all de Troops and den. look to your wife, for begar Flea-flint vill ſo get your ſhild for you. . . - " . . ... [Exeunt. Emter Flea-flint, Ferret-farm, Burn-dorp, Lieutenant, ... ºn Cornet, Raggou, and Dol.1: … . . º. a 'Burm. Lieutenant, we have done the Work. º' ...:” . Ferret. We have burnt ſeven Towns. £ºod, 2... zo: "Flea, We have raisdfourſcore pound. ºut." " . - Lieut. Y'are dextrous at your trade, you have made quick diſpatch.: but peace, we'lſhare anon... . . . [Aſide... i. ºf Now you're welcome. Come, where's the Boores o'th' houſe? ,” “º we'll
Page 32

(32) - * * we'ſ ſee what my quarters can afford. Where are you alſ? - ‘What houſe here, ho? . - Enter Woman and Maid. Womam. What want you, Sir P Zieut. Art thou the woman o'th' houſe? . Woman. Yes, Sir, a poor woman. * Lieut. Art thou poor 2 what a pox do I in ſuch a quarter? why, Quarter-maſt. Raggou, is this the beſt houſe in the Vil- ‘lage 2 - #. Zoun, hang'em, they're very rich Dog; but you ſall have no meat for your ſelf, no Oat foºyour Arſes, but her dam husband vill feaſt you all wid prayºor you. Lieut. Diable you Rotterdam whore, I'l make you bring out #. things: where's your Cowes, your Calves, and your ſheep? *... Alas, we have none, Sir. ºr . Cor. Haſt thou any drink, good woman? y - Woman. No, truly, we have none." - Flea, Nor haſt thou no wine, nor ſtrong-water, good wo. man? - - - - IWoman. No, indeed, we have none. Rag. Why den, a pax take you, good woman. * Lieut. No Hens, nor Turkies, nor Swine, nor nothing? - Rag. Hang her, begar ſhe hide every ting, when dey hear me come to make a de quarteer. . Ferret. Send to the Market Town, and buy proviſion, and be hang'd, or II ſet fire o' your houſe, you damn'd dery damn'd whore. * . . . . . . . . . . Rag. Zoun, dis dam coward, how he domineer over de Bumpkin woman! rº - - PWoman. Alas, we have no money, Sir, not we. . . Ferret. What doſ hou tremble and ſhake ſo for? what a pox ails thee? . . . . . . . . . cor. What ſhall we do? threatning will not ſerve the turn. Lieut. Do but ſecond me, and I'l make 'em bring out all they have, I warrant you: do but talk as if we us'd to eat children: . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . v. C. cºol Ferrei,
Page 33

(33) Ferret. 'Tis enough. Lieut. Why, look you, good woman, we do believe you are poor, ſo we'l make a ſhift with our old Dyet. You have children i'th' Town 2 - Woman. Why do you ask, Sir? . s - Licut. Only have two or three to Supper. Flea-flint, you have the beſt way of cooking children. . . . Flea. I can pouder'em, to make you taſte your liquor: I'm never without a dry'd childs tongue or ham. . Woman. O bleſs me ! : . Flea. Mine's but the ordinary way, but Ferret-farm is the man: he makes you the ſavourieſt pye of a childs chaldron that ever was eat l - - Lieut. A pox, all the world cannot cook a child like Mon- ſieur Raggou. - - - . . . . . Rag, Begar me tink ſo; for vat was me bred in de King of Mogul's kitchin for, tere ve kill twenty ſhild of a day? Take you one ſhild by both his two heels, and put his head between your two ; den take your great a knife and ſlice off all de buttack, ſo faſhion; begar, dat make a de beſt Scotts Collop in de varle. ... . . . . . . . - - Lieut. Ah! he makes the beſt Pottage of a childs head and purtenance! but you muſt boy] it with Bacon: woman, you muſt get Bacon. - -- Ferret. And then it muſt be very young. . . . . . * -- ... Lieut, Yes, yes. Good woman, it muſt be a fine ſquab - child, of half a year old : a man child, doſt here? Woman. O Lord! yes, Sir. . . . . . ~~ Rag. Do you hear 2 § me one ſhe-ſhild, a ſittel whore- ſhild, and ſave me all - º head whore ? . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Woman. I, Sir, I. O that ever I ſhould ſive to ſee ſuch men! . . - … º [Exit. Lieut. I warrant you it works ; if there be proviſion in the Country, we ſhall have it. • * r . . . * * - ; Flea. How the whore trembled for fear ! . - - - - F Cor. a • * de lamb-ſtone and ſweet-bread, and all de pig petty-toe of de ſhild: do you hear you round- * . , t -
Page 34

(34) cor. We ſhall have all the women in the Village about our ears: hide-bound whores! it's a queſtion whether they'l part with their meat of their children firſt. Lieut. This foolery will be nois'd about the Country, and • then the odium will never be taken off. . - "cor. Why,what can they make on tº allunderſtanding peo- Pl: will know it to be mirth. .. -- Lieut. I know they will; but the envious Prieſts will make fine talk on't, and make a great advantage on't too: though they know it to be nothing but mirth, they'l preach their Pa- riſhioners into a real belief of it,on purpoſe to make us odious. They’l preach againſt any thing: I heard a ſcandalous Ser- mon, of two hours long, againſt Prince Rupert's Dog. Cor. Come,’tis no matter what hypocrites preach: letus ſee what the event will be. - - - ... [Exeumt. Enter Women in a fright, alarm'd by their Neighbour. Woman. Look to your children; if ever you mean to ſee #. children alive, hide your children: they'l eat your chil- TCIT. I Neighb. Woe is me? what's the matter, Neighbour? Woman. I ſay, hide your children. - 2 Neighb. Ah! good Neighbour, what's the matter 2 Womam. Why, run away with your children. - 3 Neighb. Why,that ever we were born bºwhat's the matter? Woman. They will eat your children. - 4 Neighb."O,theſe bloudy Cavaliers ſhow, eat our chil- dren? - - ... ." Woman. They talk of boyling your children. , All. O ". on us! Woman. Androaſting your children. All O bloudy villains? * * > ... Woman. And baking your children. . . * Neighb. O Helliſh Cavaliering Devils 2. - Woman. There's nothing to be thought of, but hiding your children. - - - . I Neighb. I would mine were in my belly again. - Woman. That's not ſafe: they'l ſearch there in the firſt place, to be ſure. - 2. Neighb.
Page 35

(35) 2 Neighb. I'l hide mine in the ſtraw. - Womem. And ſo we ſhall have one of 'em lay you down a top of it, and ſmother one child whilſt he is getting another, I ſay, run away with your children. - 3 Night. O bloudy wretches I have heard much of their . . getting children 3, but never of their eating children before... * * 4 Neighb. Neighbour, their getting of children might be born with 5 but eating 'em was never heard of. woman. They have got a Cook from the great Mogull, on urpoſe to kill children : and they talk of roaſting their ſº and baking the chaldron, and broyling the chine. Maid. And making Pottage of the childs head and purte- Ilºilº C, - ſº All. O deliver our poor children. Woman. Do you ſtand whining and crying? Fetch out your Sheep, and your Calves, your Hens, your Pigs, and your Geeſe, and your Bacon 5 for there's no other way to ſave your children. - - All. I, with all our hearts: I Neighb. TI bring two fat Sheep. 2 Neighb. I'l bring Turkies and Hens. * 3 Neighb. I have a brave fat Calf worth eleven Nobles, by my troth I had as lieve part with one of my children. -- Woman. O you uncharitablebeaſt! go fetch your Calf. Run every body, and bring your things to my houſe, as faſt as you can drive. [Exeumt, Enter Lieutenant, Cornet, Flea-flint, Ferret-farm, Burn- . . . . . . . dorp and Raggou. Lieut. Meat, or Children, to ſupper for a wager, Gentle, men 2 - . . Cor. Meat, for a wager, if they have it. Lieut. I, without doubt 5 for never was women and chil- dren’ſo alarm'd in this world. . . Flea. When they were got together, and told their children would be eaten 5 they ſet up their throats, and made a more - horrid noiſe than a Welch Hubbub, or an Iriſh Dirge. , º -----> - ".. --, * f. - - “… * - F 2 Enfer _*
Page 36

(36) - s Enter Nurſe with two children. Ferret. How now! what think you if we be put to eat Chil- dren indeed? By this Hght, here's a woman with two Chil- dren. - - - - * Lieut. We ſhall be croſs-bit with theſe Country whores. what ſhall we do? . – ". * Rag. Begar, me vill help you off: you ſall eat no ſhildren. . Nurſe. By your leaves, your good worſhips : I make bold to bring you in ſome proviſions. . . Ferret. Proviſions ſ where, where is thy proviſions? Murſe. Here, an’t pleaſe you : I have brought you a couple of fine fleſhy Children. . . . º' - Cor. Was ever ſuch a horrid whore ſ what ſhall we do? • Nurſe. Truly, Gentlemen, they're as fine ſquab Children: , ſhall I turn 'em up? they have the braveſt brawny buttocks! - Lieut. No, no. But, woman, art thou not troubled to part with thy children P - - - - Nurſe. Alas, they are none of mine, Sir 3 they are but Nurſe- children P. - Rag. Dere be a dam whore for you. . Lieut. What a beaſt is this! Whoſe children are they * Nurſt. A Londoners, that owes me for a years nurſing. I hope they'l prove excellent meat: They're Twins too. -- tº Rag. A haſ but, begar, we never eat no Twin-ſhild; de Law forbiddat: but hark you, have any woman with ſhild in de Town?. - Nurſe. Yes, half a dozen, Rag, Lieutenant, it be de beſt meat in de varle: begar, a wóman with ſhild is better meat den one hen with egg at Shrove-tide. w : Enter Landlady, and women with proviſion. ! Lieut. How nowl what news, Landlady? - Woman. Here is a great many poor women that have brought in proviſions, in hope you’l-ſpare their children. . 1. Neighh.. We beſeech your worſhips ſpare our poor chil- dren, and you ſhall want for nothing our Country can afford. I./cut. Good woman, we are content to ſpare your chil- - * ' ' , dren, -
Page 37

' (37) dren, but you muſt get us ſome ſtrong drink. “ 2 Neighb. I, I 3 we'l get you every thing you want. ... Lieut. Why, then, go all home, and be contented 5 for we promiſe you, if we eat any children, it ſhall be the two Nurſe- children. - . . . . . . . . All. Ah, i-preſerve you all, Gentlemen. . . . Rag. Take ſome comfort 5 for if we ſhould eat your ſhil- dren, you ſall no be a loſer by dat: for look you, good woman, how many ſhildren we eat in a Pariſh, ſo many ſhild * bound to get before we leave it : dat is very fair. . . ... . . . . [Exeunt women. - Lieut. Why, is not this better than faſting 2 º' . . . Flea. Well, and what harm is there in all this? . Cor. None i'th' world. Come, let's in, and dreſs our ſupper, ... Rag. Me will go eat at my own quarteer. It be a brave ting to be in Office: begar de Clowns worſhip me, as if me. were dere great God Bumpkin. . . . . . . . . . . [Exeumt. - - - ... . . . 2 ... • * * - … . . . . : -- . . . . . . . .” - ... " " ? - - A CT us IV. s G E N A I. Lieutenant, Flea-flint, Ferret-farm and Burndorp, . . . . . . ...' . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Flea'. Ieutenant, here's all our Country crew that we plundred yeſterday. . . . . . - * . Ferret. But, our comfort is, they know us not; but cry out of a Frenchman, with two coat-ſleeves, ſtuffi like two Country bag-puddings. ** * : . ... i. º.º. . . . . . Lieut. This cunning rogue has º: you all: he has. been plundering as he went to make his Quarters, and in a Buff-coat too; for here is a dozen fellows at my Quarter; and they all deſcribe a rogue ſo like thee, that I proteſt thou wilt; ſuffer for it. Nay, the rogue call'd himſelf Flea-flint, too. Flea, Quns, what ſhall we do, Sir 2. . . . . . £iciº.
Page 38

(38) Lieut. Upon my word, this is no jeaſting buſineſs. Ferret. 'Sheart, over-reach'd thus ! . Lieut. You muſt e'en think of over-reaching him again. You muſt firſt think of ſtopping the clamor of the Bumpkins; that's your firſt point of ſecurity. º Flea. But,Lieutenant, how ſhould we dot? Faith, you muſt try your wits, and ſtick to us. Lieut. I knew you would venture ſo far, 'twould come to my turn to fetch you off at laſt,Rogues. . . • ?: Flea. Why, Sir, my man and his both ſhall ſwear Raggon borrow'd a Buff-coat of them. - Lieut. Let him be gone firſt, and then you may ſwear any thing. One of you go tell the Bumpkins, I am ſearching for the Rogue: the reſt go with me to Raggou. . - - - [Exit Ferret-farm. Burn. This is his †† - firm. This? Knock; it ſeems to be the beſt houſe ith: Town. [Knockſ. Maid. Who would you ſpeak with? [Within. Lieut. With Monſieur Raggou. - Maid, Sir, he gave us a ſtrićt charge to let no body ſpeak with him. - º Lieut. But I muſt, and will ſpeak with him. Maid. Indeed, Sir, he charg'd us, upon pain of his diſplea- fure, not to diſturb him. Lieut. Pain of his diſpleaſure? what an impudent rogue's this! Shew us, ſhew us." . . . * - . | | Raggou is diſcover'd in a Taffata bed, with a Back, Breſt and Head-piece on. - How now I what, in Tafſata Curtains? the impudent rogue makes me laugh. You, raſcal, Raggou 3-lookin his Head-piece to O. w * - ‘. . . -: Rag. Who de deveſ diſturb me? you dam whore you know vat me do to you laſt night 2 Lieut. Why, what was that you did to her laſt night? Rag. Begar me lye with her at three motion, as de Muſ, quetier ſhoot of his Gun; make ready, preſent, and give fire. - - Liemf.
Page 39

(39) - Heat. O' my word that’s good diſcipline. . . . . . . Rag. Begar, ſhe ſall make ready for you, if you will preſent and give fire. Lieut. But how came it that I had not this good Quarter P. ... Rag. Becauſe me knew me ſhould make a de Quarter but one night, and ſo, begar, me make a de beſt uſe of my time, as all . whole varle do too. Lieut. But what a Rogue art thou: why doſt thou lye in ſuch a bed in thy Arms? - Rag. For two gran reaſon, Sir. Firſt, becauſe my French louſeſall go great way about before he come to de clean ſheet: next, becauſe a de dam Engliſh flea ſhall not bite a my ſweet French body. Lieut. Well, Maid, go down: I muſt ſpeak with him. - - [Exit Maid. * Rag. Wat you have wid me, Lieutenant 2 . . . . Lieut. Faith, out of my love, I would ſavethee from hang- 1119ſ. - - *. Hang! for vat? begar, hang me if me deſerve, ſo you hang all dat deſerve a de hang; begar,dat is de whole Troop, - Lieutenant and all. . . . . - . Lieut. Here you plunder in one ſhape, and there in ano- ther: ſometimes, like Flea-flint, in Buff; ſometimes like your ſelf: that here is all the Country come in with ſuch horrid complaints. Nay, they ſay you raviſh women too. Rag. Lieutenant, begar, me never raviſh but one old wo- man, and ſhe give me five ſhilling for my pain. “ . . Lieut. Nay, here is worſe than all that, my Captain has in- telligence you're a dangerous man, and hold correſpondence with the enemy. Rag. Me ſall be hang, Lieutenant, if you tink ſo, • , Lieut. Nay, 'tis ſo; I have orders to ſearch you...— Put that in his Pocket, [affde], and pull it out again. . . . Rag. Ah, begar me have no long life before me be hang. Burm. O, Sir! are you good at that 2 he was going to con- vey Letters out on's pocket. . - -- - - - - . . . … . . . . " . . . * ~ * Rºg. * ... * * *
Page 40

(46) Rag. Begar, he tye Lieutenant, me have no Lettra; begar, hang a me; if me can write an read: de Horn-book be de He- brew to me, begar. Lieut. Search him, ſearch him. . - - [Search, and pulls a Letter out, and an Engine. Furn. Here's a Letter, Lieutenant 5 and an Engine, I think. Flea. What's this 2 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . * Lieut. O, you need not write and read if you have this : Tl be hang'd, if this be not the key of his charaćter he writes to the enemy with. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Rag. Dat make a de French Pye, and make a de Garniture for de Diſh, dat be all. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - Lieut. Let's ſee 5 the caſe is plain; he ſent his intelligence in charaćters of paſte. This verything will hang him: but let's read the Letter. Rag. Begar, me have no Lettra': de devel ſend it in my pocket. - - - - . . . . . . . . . . - . - Lieut. Reads. Monſieur Raggou 5 in hope that under this poor diſguiſe of a French Cook you will ſhew a rich faith— Rag. Vat he mean by fait? begar, me have no fait. . . . . Lieut. Reads. And when you have deliver'd up your Troop to us, the Parliament will own you as your ſelf, and give you the reſpects due to your great and honourable family. Rag. Devel, me have no honourable, nor family neider, begar. * . . . . . . . . . -ºilea. The caſe is plain, you are of ſome great family.... º. Rag. Lieutenant, meconfeſs me come of de King of France Kitchins of de; honourable family of de Turn-ſpit: Begar, me tell you true, dere beall my family, and my honourable to O. - . . . Burm. O, Sir, 'tis a very cunning fellow 5 my Captain ſends word heus'd to be converſant with the Round-heads, and pray with them. . . . . . .'; ºf . . . . . . . . . ;-- *- Rag. The Devel take a me, me never pray in my life, me ſwear altogedra in de King of France Kitchin. • Lieut. I love you ſo well, that I'd be loth to hangyou, Mon- ſieur 5 therefore I'm content to let you ſsape: but be ſure you be not taken. - Rag. *

End of Section 8. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 9
Page 41

. . . . . (4) . . . . . . . Rag, Begarden langamoy , ºr my Arſèvill no govery r. . . . . . . . . . . . . ." § 01, I.'". -º-º: St. A . . . Lieut. Well, º, be gone, and ſay you found a friend. Rag. Gadableſs you, Lieutenant : venme come in France, zoun, me vill ſo pray for you. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ºr : Ftea. And yet you ſay you never pray'd in your life. ºf go Rag. Begar, me tank Gad, me never have occaſion to pray. till juſt now. Adieu, adieu-a-Who ſendme'dat dam Lettrain my pocket?” ". . . . . . . . . . . . [Exit. . 1. Lieut. Well, now we muſt keep the Bumpkins here till heis. gone, and then give 'em orders to ſearch *cºlº föf. him. ...iſ sº tº "'. £urn. And that will whidle them,as well as if you had gi- venthem their money again. . . . . . . . . . [Exeunt. Enter Governor, captain Holdforth, Mr. Tell-troth, i. • ‘i () : . c.1.2d and captain Tub-text. e. ei 9.2:1 ºr Hold. Intruth, drinking is a harmleſs recreation, ſo we pro- ceed not to drunkenneſs. - . . . . . . . . .Y., Tub. Pray how far-forth may we proceed in drink? for I 2. take no more thanis fit to be taken with a ſafe con- CfICC." -- ºozell...Why, Captain'Tub-text, if thy belly were as large as thy conſcience, by that computation, the great Tun at Heidel- berg would be juſt thy mornings draught. ... . . . . . º. - Tub. Here is old Tom Tell-trath ; ha, ha, ha., ºi º * Hold. Intruth, if he were not very faithful, we ſhouldine- wer away with his boldneſsiºn ºf 23; º; … . . . … 3-3 Tub. Well ſaid, Captain Holdforth. But to the queſtion; how far may we proceedin drink? . . . . . . . . . . . Gºvern. As far as the innocent recreation of knocking one another down with Guſhions, come to 3 it is the exerciſe of OUIS ſuperiour Officers, ºr 2.1 ºf, ss... : 52% ºf . , ; ; *ç, Hold. I have obſervid, indeed, they do three-things toge- ther: they drink, then pračtiſe Pulpit-faces, , ;", * x * Tell. (To cheat the people with. ... tº . . ºf - Tub. Hashasha: in truth you hit ſo home.) . . . ; , , , Hold. And the third whovº of Cuſhions. The pračiſing ... i - aud -
Page 42

(43), - "diſſembling of holy looks, is of greatluſ; and deſign. *::: And drinking, and §: Cuſhions, a great #. ing to the body; ; ; ; *... . . . . . . . . . . - , Govern. As for Example. . . . [Throws a Cuſhion. Hold. Ha, ha, ha. I have ſeen our Grandee throw a Cuſhi- on at therhan with the great Thumb, and ſay, Colonel, wilt thou be a Cobler again? : ºn fº 44; ſºbrews a Cuſhion. tº Alliſ Ha;ha, ha. " : - - - --- （- ºr, Jr. º. . . - Tub. Come, here's to you, Governour, you Colonel Gold- ſuith, with a conſcience as dirty as a Black-ſmith : will you ſºil. Thimbles again? iſ ſº lºo ( , ) iſ throws a Cuſhion. All. Ha, ha, ha. - ºf . Hold. Noble Colonel,wilt thoubréw Ale again?[Throws,8&c. Whatan everlaſting cheat is Reformation and falſe Dočtrine! It has rais'd us from Coblers to Commanders.…. . . . Tub. There is no other way toraiſe Rebellion, but by Re- ligion.ºg Cº ... . . . . . . . .'; "tº fi : º '...'. . . . . . . . All. Ha, ha, ha. 11 º' cº - . . . . ) * Govern. I never knew the uſe of Religion before. . . . . . Tub. The women tickle like Trouts at it: ha, has ha. . . ; - - [All langh: zººſ. I believe the Country will findit ſo. For I hear of twenty wenches with child.º.º.º. ºf nº cº - ºri, • Govern. Intruth, I wonder at the witchcraft of it; for not- withſtanding the people have been bit through the chine-bone - ... that; before the old woundisheal’d, they are ready to run after the Lanthorn of new lights again tº has ha, hā, ºn tº or ºf . ºv, * 'tº riſ gº iſ jºi º ºil well, Sirs, fince you are in ſuch an ingenious way of gonfeſſing, tell me one thing, do not you wiſh your Garri- ſºn afireſbyou were at home,with all the wealth you've got?: Tub. Thought's free; but talk no more of that :, theſe are both treacherous Rogues, I dare not truſt'em!". " I "gº Tell. Well, you are merry, Sirs; but faith...be plain, Sirs: what ſays my ſeeming Saint that drinks by the conſcience 2 .." . . . . . . ." . . . . . . . . Y., , , , , , , - - dºr?" tº 2. "tºº ſo Agiºsiſ. : Ji. º * * * * * - - Doſt not wiſh thy ſelf at home, wallowing in thy plun- ºf * } - Hold.
Page 43

- , (4:3) º Hºld. You'mightfind a better name for it. :::Harkihyour ear: we are all ſuch treacherous Rogues, we dare not truſt one another; but we’l talk in private. " . . . . ** Goverm. But our Contribution-women will come in anon.) Hold. Ha, ha, ha: intruth, they edifie as one would have -'em, ºr tº &. ". . d or "...ſº lººſe" ...I .º.º. Tell. Well, now you ought to be ſerious, and conſider the enemies approaching. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ." Tub. Intruth a good occaſion to fetch in all the Goods and Chattels of the Country, upon pretence of ſecuring them, and ſo make conditions with the enemy to marchaway with them. I ſee we ſhall be raſcals to the laſt gaſp. º.o.º. 2d 13 Hold, And ſo we ſhall have proviſions for a long Siege. Govern. I'l make your Siege ſhort enough. --- . - ‘[Exit Govermour and one Captain. Tab. You are faithful; they are: Rogues: Read that, and telſ me whether you will undertake brino... . . . . ºº) - [Gives Tell-troth a Letter, & exif. Tell. How! very good. Ist poſſible! This is a greater Rogue in his own nature than the Devils invention tant make him :: he would not only betray his truſt, but deliverup all thereſt of the Garriſon to mercy. 3 conditionally that he may have all their wealth, and ſafé convoy to his own houſe. I need lay no Plot, 'tis done to my hand. I love the King well; yet my own ends are mingled, becauſe I have a Miſtreſs as imong’em, and cannot have her but by ſerving the King; and I believe moſt men have their reaſons for their Loyalty as well as I 3 ſo that, good King, whereſoe'er you ſeeme, truſt to your ſelf. Yet H will do ſomething. What if I betray'd this Rogue, and his Letter, to the Governout to ſecure my ſelf? but then, if they have a mind to deliver up the Garriſon, "twill make 'em ſhie of me, I find I have a hard taskon't. ...; a – , Enter Governour. . . . . . . . . . . . Govern. Q, Tell-troth, I came to ask thee a queſtion; and what think'ſt thou ? . . ." • . . . . ...iº a Tell. Troth, I know not. º' . . … ?" ..y-, * Govern. To know whether thoulov'ſt me truely, or no. ***.*.*. G 2 Tell,
Page 44

v ((44) Troyed. If you he ſerious, H could be angry with you, for †raiſing ſuch a doubt: to ſhew you that I love you (I do not . ſay your Cauſe, but you) read there 5 look you, one of your Gaptain. Rogues gave me that Letter, and the other gave me eanwhiſper to the ſame purpoſe too.… . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Govern. Is’t poſſible! What's to be done with theſe vil- claims?...ſigº lºg ºr ; , ºdº I dº ſº, y “. . . . . Tell. Something muſt be done, they'l betray you elſe. B: Goverw. .#j find it ſo, . . . . ...tºſell, Shall I ſpeak boldly? ſerve 'em in their own kind.… #1: Gavenn. Introth, I had it in my head, before to betray era, for the Rogues are rich. "I c. ºf , s 5 tº 7 tº tº Žell. Comé, let not you and HBeſhie of one another, do it - et. .." ... ." - - -- * : . . y Govern. Art thou in earneſt ? Łąśćlk. By my life; and I will put you in a way too..." Govern. Let's in 5 and conſider ſhow: had we beſt ſecure - - T - - - - t r ‘em. “ ºr - " ":- T - º Tell. No.: firſt command their two Companies out,then draw 'em into ſeveral parties, and then with your own Company diſarm 'em, and ſo clap them up and their Officers 5 then thew'em the reaſon (this Letter:) when that's done, ſend the Letter to the Parliament, and write how you have ſecur'd 'em : which will ſo ingratiate you with them, that you'l never be ſuſpected for betrayingon't your ſelf. - : Govern, My worthy, friend, ſhall I fall on my knees and worſhip thee? … . . . . . . . . ." . . . . . . fell. Let's be wiſe, and about our buſineſs, [Exeumt. ! º f : . Enter Cornet and two Troopers. - * cor. Where have you been, Sirs? - * - a 1 Troop. Why, we have been to take Fleaflint: my Cap- tain is reſolv'd to hanghim. . . . . . . . . . … - Cor. For what? . . . . . . . . . . . i 2 troop. For plundring, and ſo forth; but the Rogue has intelligence of it, and is gone : but he is in as bad a caſe. * Rºggvu 5 for we muſt ſend Huy and Cry after him. º sº, ºr ; ; ; ; ; ; ; ; ;... . . . . [Exeºnt. ºr - - a - JEA/jºr - - - * & =– * -
Page 45

(5) . . . . . . . . . Enter Raggou, º, ºr zºº . . French. To de Briſtol. - r - - r" " Rag. Ah, jam ſ: moy ; my Arſe can no carry me from de danger of dehang a de ſnoy 5 and yet me have ſpur two ſuch great hole in his rib, dat you may creep *...*.*.* Me muſt gº. coat, and mine hat, begar, me ſall beknown by at come here now * . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Enter French-man with a shew. What, come 2 . - ... - French. Come, who ſee my fine ſhite ? my rare ſhite, who ſee my fine ſhite? my rare ſhite. . . . . . . . . . . . . " Rag. }º. gowid your ſhite? - . . air, *::::::: . . . tº Rag. Dis French-man look as if he will be hang; begar, me vill put a de ſheat of dehang upon him. Monſieur, Be- gar me have de very fine ſhite too, and it vill come de Briſto! Fair too: it be de great vonder of de varle, it be de great fat Dromadory; you hear of dat? . . . . . . . . - French. Wee, wee: all de varle know defat Dromadory. Rag. Begar, you and me villjoyn partiner in de Fayr; be- cauſe you be my Country-man. . . . . . . . . . . . French. I, Monſieur, and tank you too. • Rag. We vill give out in de Bill of de two famous French- man; one inventra de ſhew of all Trade, and de oder make a de invent of defat Dromadory. . . . - ‘’French. Monſieur, wid all my heart. . . . . . - ... Rag. Vera good: you ſall go take a de beſt Houſe in de Town: dere be two piece, two jacoby for you 3, get ſome a ºvera good dinner. You ſhall take a my coat and de hat, and Ieave your ſhew wid me, for my waggon will come wid my Dromadory preſån. . . . º - - - - French. Thad good luck to light o' this French-man.[Affd. Rag, Begar, me have betra luck to light o' dis Frenchman. So, help me wid your waſt-coat: veragood. So, now make all de haſte in de varle. Adieu, adieu. [Exit French-maw. . So, now, begar, me be very ſafe.: but how de devil ſall me: ſhew mine ſhite? Begar, meforget to askvat language all de - - - • * - - - -Ti - -* - - - - --- - - Puppet: k Y!" -
Page 46

(46) Puppet in de ſhew ſpeak. Parla Francois Monſieur Puppey & Owieda. A haſ very good. . - - : Enter conſtables. . . . . . 1 Comſt. Sure we ſhall catch this fellow at laſt; for we hear 9f hiſ every where: º º º º------ * 2 Comſt. I; his two ſleeves ſtuffd,and his French Hat edge, with Ribbons will diſcover Eim.” * . * ſ: : edged - Rag, Diable , dere be de Conſtable and Mr. Huy-Cry come to catch a me--- Who ſee my ſhite, my rare ſhite, my fine ſhite 2 Begar, me ſall ſhite myſelf indeed. * : * 1 conſi. What a pox does he mean? . . . . . * * *- 2 conſt. He would have you ſee his ſhew." . . . . . 1 coſt. Come, faith let us...You fellow, come, let's ſee your ſhew. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Rag. How ſall me do now? begar, me muſt ſhew it as well aS mé Can. - . - “. - º º * { * * - . . . . . 2 conft. Sirrah, did not youſºe a French-man paſs by 2” . Rag. Frenchman * Vat have he upon him? " . . . ; 1 conft. Why, he has a greaſie coat with the ſleeves ſtuffd Out. - - * : * Rag. A pox take him, began he rob me juſt now of two piece, all me have in de varle, dat make ame cry. . . . . 2 Comſt. O'Rogue, Raſcal! alas to day ! give him a Crown, Church-warden, we are at the Pariſh charge. . . . . 1 Comſt. Come, do not cry, poor fellow; let's ſee thy ſhite; there's a crown for thee. . . . . . . . . . . . . Rag. A Gad bleſs you. Here be de brave ſhite of devarle: here be de King of Spain play on de Bag-pipe to his Privy- Council. Dat's a very good jeſt. Den dere be de King of Solomon, he give judgement upon deviſe ſhild. Dere is de firſt Aćt. Now put on your hat, and lookupon all de Lady. +am more cum povera blacumpovera, [Plays and ſings, am, jam, jam, jam Tomba nette, . . . . . jam jang Tombe mette equbla. ... a . . ~ 1... . - Now here be de Queen of swivºlºd, ſhe ſit in great Majeſty: - - her
Page 47

(47) her leg hangoyer de chair, vura full of temptation, make your chops watra,I; Vera good jeaſt. Den dere be de whore of Ba- bylon, ſhe make great love to de May-pole in de Stram. Se- cond Aët. ‘. . . . . - - - jam more cum povera, &c., it [Plays and ſings. < * ~1%. , ; , ". . . . . . . Dere be de King of Denmarks and Norway, learning to juggle of de Biſhop of Munſera. Dat's a vera good jeſt. Derebe de ſilent Miniſtra, he make a de long preach in de Play-houſe. Dere is tre Aét: datis all. . * - 2 conſt. I thought your Plays had always had five Aéts. Rag. They be de great Puppet have five Aét 5 de little Pup- pet have but tre, Will you go catch dis dam dog for me, and et a my money for me agen, my two jacoby & Begar, me undone, if you no catch dis dam dog for me. * . 1 conft. We’l away: we'l have him i warrant thee. ºil 'º'; … . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . [Exeumt. Rag. Begar, me be very fine ſheat, if it will hold out... But hold a 5 vat ifdey catch my Coat? Begar, den dey vill hang a my Coat: but dam dogvill confeſs me have his. Shew den 5. begar, meſall be hang wid mine Coat, Begar me will put a- way minè Shew. ..." **): . . . . . - - !' . . . Enter Flea-flint, with Huy and cry after him, . . . . . . Who de Devil is dat? - . Flea. A pox on't, I muſt be robbing alone, and without my Rieutenants advice! I muſt be careful, or ſuffer for it. . The Rogues follow me with Huy and Cry; I am not able to go further, I muſt change my cloaths. How now 2 what fel- low's this? 'Sheart, would I could perſwade him outof his Shew, and take my Cloak for it. - - Rag. Begar, would me could perſwade him to take my Shew, and give me de Cloak for dat. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Flea, Come hither, honeſt fellow. . . . . . Rag. Devil, it is Flea-flint. Ahme be povera demy, be- gar, me be halfhang already. Mevill no ſpeak French begar, den he will know me: me vill belch Dutch at him. Taiw, min heer. ... * , , , * - - Flea, -- -
Page 48

(48) - Flea, Come hither honeſt man: what's that, a Shew?ºl:3: Rag, raw min heer. Begar me vill ſlit my mouth from one ear to deodra, to ſpeakgood Dutch 5 and den, when me ſpeak French, begar me vill ſew it up again: dere's a vera good trick to ſave a my life. … . . . . . . . Flea. Fellow, wilt thou ſell thy Shew 2 Rag. raw min hear. Begar, dis Dutch make me vera ſick. Look! begar, every time me cry, raw min heer, dere come up a pickle Herring with it. Tam, look dere it go. Flea. Art thou a Dutchman? . . ..', Rag. raw verathticke. . . `... " Flea. Where hab you de meder Land, goºfton - Rag. Diable, vatſall me ſay? Begar me have no more Dutch. Flea, Hab you de meder Lands go weſt Lanceman & Rag. Ick habeu de Hoigh Dutch Lander gee weſton Lance- 2724/7. - ". . - tº . . . . . . . . . …] I Flea, Nay, it may be what Dutch it will, for I can ſpeakno ſºlore. . . . . *. ". . - ~ : ... “ Rag. Ick makem weel vander ſlapam can Helder Hought. Flea. But wilt thou ſell thy Shew 2 . . . . :- Rag, raw, raw, ick will van hundred Gilder habem. - . . . . . . Flea. That's ten pound 3 that's too much. I would Ihadity at any rate. . . . . . . " º: - - Rag. Begar, never fear, you ſall have it. Flea. Wilt thou take five pound 2 - - Rag. Neave ick: 1ck maken de Shew myſelf and ick maken! dat better as dis, and dat's better as dat, and dat's better as alli begott. • ... . . . . . . . . . . . . . ºf Flea, I hear'em coming : here's ten pound for thee, and I'll give thee my Cloak to boot and Hat. º Rag. Dere be my Shew and my Cap: me tankyou Lance- man. So, disdam Rogue never do no good in all his life be-, fore; and me hope, begar, he vill be hang for dat. ... [Exit. Flea. Now, what ſhall I do with this Shew.5 for I cannot ſhew it? why, if anybody would ſee it, I muſt ſay it's lock'd . 3 the key is gone before to Briſtol Fayr: that's all I have, or’t. . . . . . - - Emfer - - ; } - - - & ( : ... "
Page 49

- - (49) º, yº. ... : Enter conſtables looking for Flea-flint. . . . 4 conſt. Come, Sirs, we ſhall have him at laſt. ' ' ' ' ', 3 coſt. Stay, Sirs: what fellow's this 2 who areyou, Sir? Flea. A poorman, Maſter, going with my Shew to the Fayr, togetapeñy, and a Rogue has rob'd me of all I have, almoſt ten pound. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .” 4 coaft. O. damn'd Rogue Had he not a gray Cloak and "Hat - - - Flea. I, (wicked villain) the ſame, Maſter. . . . . 3 conſt. It's the ſame Rogue we are looking for, we ſhall have him i'th'Fayr, I warrant you. Let's away. [Exeunt Conſtables. Flea. This rogue thinks himſelf ſo ſafe now, and he'l be hang'd ſure enough if they catch him. - Enter the firſt conſtables with him that had Raggou's cloaths. I conſt. Look you, there's the notorious Rogue with the Shew : take him. • Flea, What would you have with me, Gentlemen? - French. Begar, the vill have my Shew from you. , Flea. Pox take you and your Shew 5: a damn'd Rogue that had it, has rob me often pound, and my Hat and Cloak. I conſt. Come, theſe are both Rogues: bring'em away. 1 Watch. Hold, it will do us no good to have them hang'd, what if we plunder them as they uſe to do us. - - conft. 'Tis a very good motion, do you hear, we are to ask you a queſtion, will3. be hang'd, or be plunder'd? ; Flea, I'l be hang'd before I part with my money.” ". . 2 Watch. Then let's hang him, we can take his money when he is dead. . . . . . . . . . . . t ... Cen. Then do you hang him. ; :: *.* tº: Y! ... " ... - 2 : . . [Enter Humpkin paſſing over the stage, 'i ºn . -- I Watch. Not I, I know not how to hang him. . . . . . ; lº" Troth hang him your ſelf, if you'l have him ng - - * ..." º: - - * -- Geºff. Doſt here brother Bumpkin Il give thee an Angel, and hang this fellow. " . . [conſtable calls to the Bumpkin. * , , is H- - - Bhmpk, 1 - - * * * * * * -- - - - - .* Ji', ' ', " . . . . . . . . . . • * ! . . . . -
Page 50

(50) Bumpk. It is not worth while for one, but PI take Angels' a piece to hangyou all. . . . . . . . . . . . & Conft. Hangyouraskal, comethere fall on boys, and plun- der him, . . [Plunder Flea-flint. ; Flta. Pray you, Gentlemen, give meſome money again to bear my charges home. -- " - - - - - - - - *:::: There's a Crown for thee, and farewel. - - [Exeumt all but Bumpkin. Bumpk, Heyday! this will prove a very wonder, - 1:...'. That Bumpkin ſhould a Souldier plunder. . . . . . . . . . * . . . . . . • - - - - r ACT us V. scien A 1. Enter a joyner, servant, and a painter at one door, and Raggou at another. Serv.TOyner, make haſte, and ſet your t'other Poſt up; and || Painter, fetch your Colours, your Pots and Pipkins, * and paint this Poſt in the mean time: it muſt be di. patch'd before the people are ſtirring. . . . Paint. My things are all ready, Sir, at the next houſe : we can ſcarce ſee to work yet. * , - serv. And be hang'd then go get ſome Ale to clear your eye-ſight: I’l warrant you'l ſee the bottom of the Pot well enough without day-light. " ... ." -- - - - - - - joym. Make what haſt you can, I'l bring my Poſt as ſoon as you'í be ready to paint it. . . . . . . * [Exit. paint. I'd laugh at that, ifaith.* Bºtfriend, what noiſe was § all night? I think the Watch was ſearching for ſome- - * - tº: , , º, I, I ; hark, you may hear 'em ſearching ſtill. Why, it ſeems ’tis a kind of out-landiſh French-man that they look for; he has a gray Hat, and a gray Cloak's but come, let º FIA|Ilº
Page 51

(51) mind our buſineſs, and make haſte, * : * . . . . f. Rag. Dat be me: dey ſlandra amoy, me be no out-lahdiſh French-man, begar me be a French French-man: Hark, dey come: vat ſall me do? Begar, me vill ſtand for de odra Poſt till de dam Bumpkin be gone ; a pox take 'em, de devel could not Huy and Cry me ſo cloſe. How ſall me do to be like a dat Poſt? Hark, dey come now. - ''{ Raggou gets upon the Poſt, and ſits in - - the poſture of the other Poſt. - - Enter Conſtable and Watch. conft. Pox o' this out-landiſh French-fellow for me; I'm as . dry as a Dog. . . . ; : . . . . . 1 Watch. So we are all; let's go and knock 'em up at an Ale-houſe, and eat and drink a little. a Watch. With all our hearts. - . . . ." Enter Painter. - º Honeſt Painter, can't tell where we may have a little Ale? Paint. I, ſure, two or three doors off you'l find 'em up, and a good fire, where you may toſtyour noſes, Boys. ſ conft. Thou date ſee an out-landiſh French-man this way 2 . •". tº . . . . . . t -- ‘. #in No. ſaw no French-man.[Exeunt º & Watch. Why, what a Devil, this Joyner has been here, and ſet up his Poſt, before I came : how timeſlips away at an Ale-houſel Rag. Begar, wou'd a good rope wou'd ſlip away you too. . Paint. Now to work, ~- ſº and paints him. Hag. He vill paint a me; vat ſall me do 2 -- As heftoopſ, Raggou throws a ſtone at him. Paint. A pox o' theſe roguing Prentices. Sirrah, I'I have you by the ears: a company of Rogues, a man cannot wor for you ! If you ſerve me ſuch another trick, I'l break al your Windows. " . . . . . . . . . . . . . Rag Depox break all your neck. . . . . . . . . . . - [Throws the Pipkin at him as heftoopſ. Paint. Why, you damn'd Rogue, you have broke my head; 'Sheart, I'l complain to your Maſter. Spoil'd all my Colours too! I'lnot endureit;I'l **** coſt me..[Exit. - 2 Rág. \
Page 52

- {(52) , R+: A pox dis Rogue; he murder mine face widthis dam paint. Now de coaſt be clear, me vill take a de Coat of Mon- fieur jack Painter and go; for begar dere be no ſtay in dis Town for moy. . . . . . . . . . Enter joyner with his poſt. - Hark, dere be ſometing: me muſt be de Poſt agen. A pox on dat. . . . . . . . . . . [He ſtands up for a Poſt again. joym., Why, how now? what a devil, another poſt, and • none of my work? 'Sheart, do you employ two men at once? II not be us’d thus; Il be paid for my work, and then let the - -- devil ſet up your Poſts. . . . [Exit. Rag. So, now begar, me vill take de Coat of de jack Pain- tra, and de Poſt of de jack Joyner, den no man vill ſuſped a moy. - . . . . . . . [effers to lift the Poſt. Diable, it is too much heavy for moy ; begår me betra be hangden have all dis dam Joyner ſit upon me. Diable, and would me vere in bed wid all de King of France Army, begar me vou'd fain ſee vat dam Engliſh § mpkin, Mr. Huy-Cry come fetch me from dem. . . . . . . . . . [Exit. Enter servant, Painter and joymer. seri. Why, whatafooliſh fellow art thou to be ſo angry ? I employ'd no Joyner but thy ſelf. . . ; - oyn., 'Sheart; there was two carv'd Poſts up, and rm ſure. I brought the third. . . - • * sero. Thou art mad, and ſo is this fool too, to complain of throwing ſtones at thee, when we have ne'er a Prentice, nor none within ſix doors of us. . . " - Paint. I'm ſure my Pipkin's broke, and my head too: pray look here. . . - * - - serv. Why, what's here 2. here's a broken Pipkin indeed, but where's the three carv'd Poſts? . - joym. There was two ſtood up when I came to the Houſe, and I ſet the third down here. Ounes, my Poſtand my Tools. and all's gone. . . w - Serv. I believe you are both drunk. . . ; : Faint. Heart man, I painted the Poſt that ſtood “, - - : " . - oyms w
Page 53

(53) joyn, Well, and heart man, I brought the t'other, an’you call it heart man, and all's gone you ſee. serv. My Maſters, go look after your things, and make an end of your work. - Paint.Let's go ſearch for this fellow that ſtole our goods here. - [Exeumt. • * Enter Tell-troth and Dol. Tell. O Dol, dye hear, put her off till your friend come as before you pretended, and ſay you'l marry when the Gar- riſon is deliver'd up. … " Dol. The Lieutenant and Cornet are very eager to have it diſpatch'd, that they may have the money I promis'd, and then they are reſolvd to laugh me to death. - - Tell. Well, but you know it will be our turn to laugh at them, if all be right you have told me. . - - - - - Dol. Upon my life I have been faithful in all points, and I find I ſhall take pride in doing good, ſince I have proſper'd ſo well in ſerving you. . . - Tell. Your reward ſhall anſwer your ſervice. I muſt to the Captain, and give him an account of all I undertook, which will meet his expectation. . Dal. Let me alone to manage my undertakings. . Enter Captain and Lieutenant. Tell. Here's the Captain; be you gone therefore: I would not beſeen with you, till I make him acquainted with every thing, [Exit cum Dord. Ilieut. But pray, Sir, why are you thus ſevere now, to baniſh. the Flint-fleyers 2 Capt. The Kings Honour and Intereſt is ſo abus'd with theſe ſcandalous fellows, that I'm reſolv'd to caſhier'em. ... Enter Tefl-troth. * - . . Qh, friend Tell-troth 1 look you Lieutenant, my opinion ſel- dom fails me. - - Tell. So, you had ſome diſpute then concerning me. Look, . you, Sir, it's now in my power to do more than e'er I hop'd for: you have a Foot Company 2. - . . . . . . Cap. Yes; they are now marching into th’ Quarter, Lieute- . . - * - nant.
Page 54

(54) nant, ſee they march fair, and do no wrong. [Exit Lieutenant. Tell. Read that: upon my life there is but three Compa- nies, and two of 'em are diſarm'd, and Priſoners, Officers and all. I laid no plot to do it, I found 'em all ready to betray one another to get the wealth 3 the manner how, hereafter. The Governour has commiſſion'd me to make his Conditions; which muſt be a Convoy, with all his wealth,to his own home. The Country bring in their plate and goods to ſecure 'em from your party, and he'l make conditions with you to march away with 'em, and ſo cheat the people: (precious Rogues!) beſides what they preach the women out of - - Capt. That muſt not be; for the King has Intelligence that they have great Treaſure there. - Tell. Does he know how they came by it? Capt. Yes, very well; with the cheat of preaching (I mean Tub-preaching, and Leótures.) The Leótures your wives read you, never aw'd you ſo. - Tell. But faith, Sir, give him his Conditions. Capt. I'l ſtorm it firſt. - Tell. I intend not to have you keep Conditions when you have made 'em. - . . Capt. That's baſe; I ſcorn that: my Honour is at ſtake. Tell. What, for breaking Articles with a Rebel?. Had it been a fair enemy,I grant you.Suppoſe you ſtorm it,and be bea- ten off? the King would give you littlethanks for the pundil- fio of your own private honour. Let your Lieutenant do it: the Captain may with his Honour break the Conditions that his Lieutenant makes. capt. I may approve of that ; I would not have my own hand appear againſt me. But I am glad to ſee you thus earneſt for the King : ſure you have ſome deſign. - - - - Tell. By my troth I have; but ſo ſmalla one, it is not worth this labour: you ſhall know it, for you muſt affiſt me." capt. With all faithfulneſs. - Tell. Come then, let's ſign Articles. So, march, and take poſſeſſion. - - [Exeumt. 11 . Eſºfº"
Page 55

(35) . . . . . . . . . Enter Raggou like an old woman; , - ... Rag. Mevill makeame noſe of wax, like de old woman,and vill go to Madam Dol, and tell her me come from Monſieur Raggou. Vera good. And if ſhe vill beg his pardon of de Capitain, he vill come and marry her, although her ſhild be born wid a ſhart and back and breſt too; for begar me find in mine conſcience me had betra marry a dam whore, dan be Enter Tell-troth, Captain, Lieutenant, Cornet, &c. * : with the Govermour Priſoner. . . . . Tell. Now, Sir, are you ſatisfi'd in my faith? capt. I am ſo 3 and I have found you a worthy perſon: command me to anything. - - Tell. Then I'l make you merry till I go about my deſign. Captain Tub-text, that got the two Siſters with child, is now in bed with them eating a Sack poſſet; and, that we may both ſhame and fright 'em, there are Bears i'th' Town, and other Shows that are going to Briſtol Fayr; now I'l ſpeak to the Bearward to muzzle a Bear, and turn him looſe into the room, and I'l bring you where you ſhall ſee the ſight. Capt. Content, for I am a great lover of ſports: let not the Shews go away, for I mean to celebrate Dol's wedding. Lieut. That's kindly done. You'l need no other ſport than to ſee Dol rant and tear when ſhe finds ſhe has married a Girl. - Capt. But the ſport will be, when you and the Cornet re- ceive your fifty pound a piece you told me of. Lieut. Yes, faith; we ſhall have it ſure enough. Capt. Yes, for 'tis depoſited in my hands. - Cor. Never was jade ſo deeply in love! but the jeſt is the Girl has made conditions with Dol, to put on a Maſque when ſhe is marrying 3 for her face is ſo bad ſhe cannot away with it, Capt. Give all the Troop favours; let 'em diſpatch, and bring them in to the bayting of the Sack-poſſet, and let the Country be ſummon din. [Exeumt. * * . . . - • * Tub-
Page 56

- (56) . . | Tub-text and his siſters are diſcover'd in bed, eating a &ack-poſſet : Enter Captain, Lieutenant, Cornet, Fer- ; ret-farm, above. - Tub. Here is this ſpoonful in remembrance of our ſweet Siſters precious fruit ſhe goes with. - [He puts a ſpoonful in each of their mouths. 1 Siſter. My tender, and moſt ſº thanks be return'd you. - - . . . . -- Tub. Now here is to the Maiden-fruits of this our weeping- Siſter. Wipe your tears; if they were Cavaliering burthens you went with, your caſe were mournful; but as they are my off-ſpring, repent not; for your Infants (be aſſured) will be Babes of Grace. º Capt. What a damn'd Rogue is this? 1 Siſter. Why then, it ſeems, we religious Lambs may play with one another, without ſinning? . capt. Was ever ſuch blaſphemous Rogues and Whores! I tremble to hear'em! Let in the Bear upon 'em. 1 Siſter. Here is to this our ſweet comforting man. 2 Siſter. I am over-joy'd to hear that religious Lambs may play, and yet not ſin. [Put their spoons in his mouth. Emter Bear. - Tub: What's here, a Bear? mercy upon us! All Help, help, help, help. Tub. Shift for your ſelves, ſweet Siſters. - . Capt. Now Bear, now Saint. º Lieut. HallooSaint, halloo Bear: I’l hold a- cor. Hundred pound of the Bear: thou Boy Bear. Lieut. A hundred pound of the Saint. So, now take off your Bear." Ferret. By my faith, wenuſt ſtave and tail him off for ought I ſee, Captain. I have been at many a Bear-bayting, but never at a Saint-bear-bayting before. [Exit Bear, &c. Capt. Now, Sir; is your name Tub-text 3 - Tub. Yea. - - capt. And do you think your two Whores are with shild with two babes of grace? Tub.
Page 57

(57) …I ub. Yea, foul mouth. . * . capt. What an audacious. Rogue is this! And doſt thou really believe thy ſelf in ſuch a degree of perfeótion, that thou canſt not ſin, and ſo, need no repentance? - - Tub. Yea, ſure, we are paſt repentance. Capt. Thou damn'd villain, I believe thee. Blaſphemous Rogue 1 how many poor ſouls haſt thou deluded? Sirrah, it were juſt to make thee marry theſe two women,and the n hang thee for having two wives. --> - Emter Ferret-farm. Ferret. Sir, our wedding folks are coming, and are ſo mer- ry, and ſo pleas'd 3 that, if their joy continue, the Example will make us all marry. - Enter Biddy as Bridegroom, Tell-troth in her hand dreſs'd in : Dol's cloathſ, and Do! in other cloaths, and Raggou * dreſſed like an old woman with a Mufler. . . Look you, here they are, pleas'd as you ſee. º - Do!. Now ſtand you here till I beg your pardon of my Cap- talſ. . . . . . . - - Bid. By your leave, Captain, I have made bold to eſpouſe your old hand-maid Dol; and give us leave to laugh 5 for faith my Lieutenant and Corflet has cheated her, Captain, for they have match'd her to a Girl: I am a very Girl, and yet I have not wrong'd you, for I told you before I could not get , your children. ~ * - - - - Tell. And we laugh, to think how we have cheated you ; for though you cannot get my children, if I can get yours, we ſhall do well enough. . . . . . . . . Bid. O Lord, what's that P that is not Dol's voice. . . Dol. Y'are i'th’ right; it is not Dol's voice, nor Dol that has marry'd you (keep the money, Captain)but your old love Tell- troth. Pray have your money, Lieutenant, before you laugh me to death. . . . . . . { - - : Bid. What, my old Lover Tell-troth ! • Tell. Now the laugh is on our fide, Gentlemen. Come, be not troubled, for I am the ſame honeſt lover Lover that e'er I Was, : ... . . . . . . . . . ;-- . . . . . . . \ I mid.
Page 58

(58) Bid. Nay, TI ſwear thou deſerv'ſt me, thou art a deſperate #over to venture on a wench that has troop'd ſo long under ſuch a handſome Cornet: but he's a fool too; for if he had follow'd his blow cloſe at one time, he had had all that. I could have given him. - - : Tell. I had ſpies upon you, and am well aſſur'd of your ho- neſty. Ask Dol. ". . . . . . - . . . . . . . . "I . . . . • * * - , Dol, Yes, faith, I watch'd your water at every turn. Do you remember he would have gone oth ſcore for your Maiden- head? but you cry'd 'twas worth ready money at any time 3 but marry me, and then halloo Dog for thy Silver Coller. You remember this? . . . . . . . .. . . . - Bid. I, to my ſhame I do. . . . . . . . . Tell. What, are you aſham'd that you are honeſt ? Eid. No , but I'm aſham'd that I loſt ſo much time; for I'm ſure thou wouldſt ha' had me honeſt or not honeſt. Tell. Come, be not troubled, I paſs by all. º. º. º.º. Eid, I love thee for thy confidence, give me thy hand, by my life I’m very honeſt; but I have had as much a do to keep my ſelf ſo, as ever poor wench i'th' world had. . . . . . . cor. But I hope, Biddy, you and I ſhall not loſe our acquain- tance? º º 2 " . . . . . . . . . . ; ; ; ; , , ; ; ; , ; ; ſº Lid. If my husbandwill have it ſo, I cannot help it. 'ſ Butſ: hope he has more wit than ever to let me ſee you again: if you have not, husband, in good faith, at your own peril. . . Tell. I'll have wit enough 5 fear not. - . . . . i.e. . . . . • * : *- . . . . . . Emter Ferret-farm. . . . º Ferret. Sir, here's the Country-Gentlemen come. . . . Capt. Pray let 'em come in. . . . . . . . - *... " . . . . . Enter Country-Gentlemen. - - Gentlemen, 'tis not unknown how publickly you have ap- pear'd againſt your Prince; and how ſecure you thought your ſºlves under the protection of theſe Hypocrites: but to ſhew. you what rogues they are 5 all the wealth that you brought hither to be ſecur'd from us, they would have made conditions to have march'd away with, and ſo cheated the whole Coun- try. Look you, there's their Articles: there's Reformation' $3ryoti. l L Gezi. -
Page 59

(39) * Gen. We are deceiv'd indeed in them 3 to have us’ s thus ! . capt. You muſt own, Gentlemen, that all the wealth, that's here, is juſtly forfeited to the King. • * :- - 2 Gent. We grant it, worthy Captain, and our lives to boot. . . . . . . . . . . ;-- * ~ * ºr -- ~~~~... . . . . capt. Although the wealth that's here be great, and the Kings wants require it 5 yet, to ſhew that he had rather have his É. hearts than money, he has Commiſſion'd me to return every man his own again. 1 Gent. Sir, this gratious act of the King, and your readi- neſs to perform it, ſhall turn us all faithful ſubjećts to the ex- tent of our lives and fortunes. . . . . - Capt. Now you deſerve his mercy. Dol. Sir, will you grant me a requeſt ? Poor Raggon has ſent me word, if I can beg his pardon of you, he'l marry IIl C. - ; Capt. Dol, you have been inſtrumental to our frend Tell- troth; I muſt grant you anything. * Dol. Then pray,Sir, let's make a littleſport with him: who do you think that old womanis? . . . - - - - A. : Capt. I know not. - ... Dol. Tis Raggou himſelf. "Pray fright him a little before you ſeal his pardon. - - . . ... Capt. What a Devil has he done to his face? . . . . . ..., pol. I know not ; I believe he has clap'd wax upon't. . . . Capt. Now, good woman, what would'ſt thou have 2, . . Rag. Mecome in de crowd, in hope to ſee a Souldier hang; it wou'd be great ſatisfaction to de Country, truly. º, Capt. Well, good woman, where doſt thou dwell? . . . . Rag, Begar me have no dwell: vatſall me ſay to him 2 Ilive at Briſtol Towns end, an’t pleaſe your worſhip. . . . º Capt. But, woman, if thou would'ſt tell me where to find a plundring French-man, call'd Raggou, the Country ſhould hang him with all my heart 5 for that's a notorious rogue, and he ſhall be hang'd if he live above ground. . . . . . . . . Rag. Begar he ſerve a mevera well to hang me: vat a º: … I 2 - make º 4-
Page 60

(60) make a me come here? dis be my vit: a pox on mine French wit. - - - [aſ dº o • Capt. Woman, find out that Raſcal for me, here is ten ſhil- lings in earneſt, and when thou takeſt him, I'l make it ten ‘pound. * * . . . . . . . . . . . . . - Rag. But will your worſhip ſecure me that I ſhall have no harm if I find him? * - . . . . - Capt. I upon my honour, before all this Company, thou ºfhalt have no harm.' . - . . . . Rag. Bear witneſs,gentlemen; now give me ten pound: for begar me be de man, me be Monſieur Raggolº. “ - A/. How! Monſieur Raggou ! . - - - Rag. Wie mafoy, ha, ha 5 me have ſheat a my Capitain of ten pound, and ſave a my life too 5 dere be de French vit! Be- arme honour my vit very much for dat. - Capt. Call the Marſhal. : Take him and hang him upon the next tree. - - . . . Rag. Hang a moy I did not you before witneſs engage your honour dat me ſall have no harm 2 Begår you vill dome great ... ... → * * * * - - -- - ‘deal wrong, if you hang me now. - - - - - - capt. I promis'd, indeed, that the old woman ſhould have no harm; but Raggou ſhall certainly be hang'd. ' ' ' * Rag. A haſ dere be a dam Engliſh trick will hang a French- man. But hold, hold : if you hang Raggou, how can you ſave de old woman 2 Dere be Law caſe for you! Let me have fair play for my life. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Capt. Take the old womans garments and lay them up ſafe, and then they have no harm ; then my honour is clear, and here is Raggou fairly to be hang'd. -- ~ f Aſarſ. Come, come away 5 'tis a plain caſe, you muſt hang or’t. . . . . . . . . . . . ... . . . * Dol. Why were you ſuch a fool as to come hither? Rig. For love of you, you dam whore you. - Dol. Why would you betray your ſelf for ten pound 2 Rºg. Dat be my cunning; de hangman ſall have de ten round becauſe he ſall no hurt a me when he hang me. But, Cºpitain, begar you can no hang me in juſtice 3 for de old wo- : º, . Dºłd Il;
Page 61

v - ' (61) man is Raggou, and Raggou is de old woman, and de Devil can no part us : ſo if you hang Raggou, you hang de óld woman, and you hang your own honour too, begar... . -- capt. Well, Sir, you have pleaded ſo well for yourſelf, that conditionally you will marry Dol, [l pardon you. . . . . . . . i Kag. If you tink it better to marry den to be hang, Capi- tain, me leave all to your judgement. . Capt. Why, then marry her. . . º º Rag. But who ſall keep de ſhild 2 Capt. The Troop ſhall keep it. Rag. Why may not de Troopa make one 2 dat's very fair me tinks. Capt. Nay, you may be hang'd yet if you will, , - [He takes the woman in one humal,and the halter in the other. Rag. Let a me ſee: here be whore, and here be halter 5 verafine ſhoice begar! me can no tell which to ſhuſe; but me vill e'en ſtan to mine fortune, and croſs and pile for it.' ' swell marry her, and me vill - capt. By my troth it ſhall be ſo, and take your choice; croſs or pile 2 - - - - - - - Lieut. Why, croſs he ſhall be hang'd, and pile he ſhall be married. - . . . . . . . . . . . ~ : ct-, -, - . . . . . . . . . . . º No, begar, it fill be croſsif me beharried, and pile if me be hang. - - - . . . . ." Lieut. Now it's an even lay whether this Farce be a Comedy or a Tragedy. . . - - ". . . . . . cor. Come, Gentlemen, whore or halter for a wager? Rieut. Whore for a wager. -- Cor. Halter for a wager. - Rag. Hold, hold: vat if it be nedra croſs nor pile? Capt. If it be neither croſs nor pile, thou ſhalt neither be married nor be hang'd, upon my Honour. Come, here is your fortune for you: ifaith, 'tis croſs, thou art to be married. Rag, Den dere be your halter again, and me tank you. *Capt. Come, take your beloved wife, and ſtrike a match. Rag. Den let her take me, and de Devil in hell give her good of me. - Capt. Then you have my pardon, and all is well. EA tº:
Page 62

\ (62) - * . . . . . . . . . . . Enter Ferret-farm; . . . . . . . . . "...Ferret. Sir, here are two of Queen Elizabeth, Tilters, go- ing to Briſtol Fayr, deſire to dance before you. Capt. With all my heart: call 'em in. - * A Dance of two hobby Horſes in Armour, and , jigg. , You have done well: where's my man? give 'em half a piece; you have done prettily indeed. Lieutenant,caſhier the Flint- fleyers: as for theſe Hypocrites I'l keep them priſoners till ºf the King diſpoſe of 'em, which will be but too mercifully I'm Fillre. - | ". . . . . . - Cor. I ſuppoſe, Governour, the Parliament will reward you with ſome Biſhops Lands for being ſo honourably pull'd by the ears out of your Garriſon. . . Capt. Come, upbraid 'em not; I hate that. To morrow, ; ſummon in the Country, and every man ſhall have his right. . . . . .. . . . . . . . º 'g'', God bleſs the King, and all his good Souldiers. . . . * ... Capt. You ſee, Lieutenant, how with good uſage the peo- ple return to their Loyalty: I know you are a brave fellow 5 but you have been to blame in the Country, and that dis- 'ſerves your Prince more than your courage can recompence. ... Lieut. Sir, you ſhall never have occaſion to ſay this again. Capt. I believe you: and I wiſh that the great Timber, the Pieces of State, that lye betwixt the King and Subjećts, * I wiſh that they would take a hint from hence - To keep the peoples hearts cloſe t v-- otheir Prince. . . - i. - - | Exehmf Ożnej, K. . . . . . . [Excumtom - - - - , \ . " . . - - - - . . . ºn \,--- ** * . . . - - * - º - * - * * - * - --- -- - - - - -- - I - : - - º ---- 3.” - - - cº: 1 * * * - - * . . - • * - --- - - , , , . . . . . ºf 10 ) .I. ºº' ſº 'º - † 29 . . ...l - - * : * ~ * i : … . . . º.º. ** • ‘7 : : : - - - - - - - - - - - * - - - - * - - - r x, ſº ºf:1 ; , "... . . . . . . . . . - 1 -- ~ 1. EP - - - - - - - - + ". - - i i - º º - - º - - - - 1. .-- - *. J +.
Page Scan 89

- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - e, E PILOG LI E. ..., ºn -- . . . ‘tº \ **...*.*.*.* - t - -- " - . . . . . . . * - Rologues, and Epilogueſ, ſhould ſomething fy - In order to th’ excuſing of a Play ; hº But things totb' purpoſe,being laid aftile, 1zzcº We ſhoot at random at leaſt ſix bows wide; . . . . Speaking of this or that, of Sea or Land, . . . . tº -- r : º, "" ; ; of any Matter but the thing in hand..., º º If men with ſuch faultſ, Poets do Commence, I may put in with my impertinence.” - - And though my dull Mafe cannot make y'a feaft, I'd fain be thought a Poet at the leaft: y \i. I find I am one, I can prove it plain, Both by my empty Purſe, and ſhallow Brinº -- I've other ſymptomſ to confirm it too, , , , , … I've great, and ſelf conceit, of all I do I have my little Cullies toºth"Town; *- Both to admire my workſ, and lend a Crown, My Poetſ day I morgage to ſome Citt, At leaſt ſix months before my Play is writ; And on that day awayyār Poet FITF, Tº Knowing full well, in ſholes, come all his dums. If theſe things make me not a perfeół Poet, He that haſ better Title let him ſhewit, sº. A y : * '3. ___ Books. --------------
Page Scan 90

- - - $$$$$$$33,3}{&#3%$&#333 tº: § sº #: ##3. * *** c. ****** - - Some Play; printed for Thomas Dring. - - - -- - - - "He Unfortunate Lovers. " * - - - -- - - - - The Amorous Prince: Or, Curious Husband. . . . Town-Shifts. * { . . . . . . . . . * - - - - - - - - -- - - - - - - The Six Days Adventure. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Albumazer. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ." The Changeling. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Love and Honour. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . School of Complements. * . . . º ‘. . º - * , º, . . * ... . . . . ." . . . . . . . . . . Aäed al the Duke. Theatre. * * * * * * - - - º - - * 6 7 -2. - º - º * - *** - - - - - - - - - - - º *** - º | He Dumb Lady :: Or, Farrier made Phyſician, º, . . . . . | The Rehearſal. . . . The Old Troop : Or, Monſieur Raggou. . . . . . . Afted at the Theatre Royal. . . . . . . . . . . ) \ * - ‘. . (, . - - - -- -- - - - - - - - - - - * -- - - - - - - y - - , ºt (,” -- -- - - - - - - - - * * * * * * - * * - - - - - - - º K - -- Playſ new Printed. It - * * * : - - - - - -- --- º * - 3. -> - - - - * -- - - - - tº . . . ºv'ſ - ... . - * * ----- --". -. --" " " . . . º * . -.' … * -- - º tº a ... º.º. * * **'''< * * . . . . . is " . . . . is : º **. -- - -- - ** - - - r - - - - - - - - “. . . . . . . " ... º. º. -ºº: - - - - - - - - - - - - -- - - - - - - * * - - - * --- - *- - ---" - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -- - - - - - - - - - - . . . -- - ºct

Page Scan 91

Blank page
Page Scan 92

Blank page
Page Scan 93

Blank page
Page Scan 94

-|- - - - - - - - ------------- * -- --------- ---------- --------- -------- ---- ----+---- |- ••• ----- -----
Page Scan 95

! RARE 300K RöOM *ES rºle cº- fāk FR35.711. CŞ |677

Page Scan 96

Blank page

This page contains an image.

End of Section 9. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents

End of text. Return to beginning.
