The rambling justice, or, The jealous husbands. With the humours of Sir John Twiford. As it is acted at the Theatre Royal ..., . | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
The rambling justice, or, The jealous husbands. With the humours of Sir John Twiford. As it is acted at the Theatre Royal ..., .
Author
Leanerd, John, fl. 1679.Leanerd, John, fl. 1679.
Published
London,Printed by E. F. for Thomas Orrell and James Vade,1678.
Description
[2], 69, [1] p.20 cm.
Rights
Public Domain, Google-digitized.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/hvd.32044086921277

Table of Contents

    Front Cover
    Section 1 on page number 3
    Section 2 on page number 21
    Section 3 on page number 25
    Section 4 on page number 31
    Section 5 on page number 63

Book Text
Front Cover
Page Scan 1

Blank page

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 2

Blank page
Page Scan 3

Blank page
Page Scan 4

Blank page
Page Scan 5

Blank page
Page Scan 6

Blank page
Page Scan 7

Blank page
Page Scan 8

Blank page
Page Scan 9

Blank page
Page Scan 10

Blank page
Page Scan 11

Blank page
Page Scan 12

PROLOGUE, spoken by Flora. WILL nothing take in these Vl-naiurd times .<? Neither low Farce nor great Heroics Rhines? 'Tis strange you fliould such SeQarics be grown, Thus to allow no DoUrine lnt your Own } And in the Pit as they in Pulpits rage, Preach up Rebellion to undoc the Stage. Like angry Fate you Damn without Confront, Ruine your Own, but not the Poets Soul. If Wit stould be the Substance of a Sparks Why is your Tall^fo Dull ^ your Sence so Dark.? Things much admird by Fops both great and smaly\~\ Are to be Drunks, keep Miss, and visit Bals$ C But the great Essence, Wit, few have at all. y Wit does in Plays to some Gay Fops appear. Like a New Mistress in their full Car ear} * All Ay re and Charming, till the Minute's past, And then you kick her out with all your hast, Tax'd with tf>e Crime ^ Damme fife's False you cry. Another Lord keeps her as well as I. This makes the Trade of Miss and Poet Dull, They care not how Debauch'd to please a Fo£l. But what's all this to me .<? Tve yet been true, But 'twos for want of Wit, like some of you. 'Sdeath who would be fa singularly kind, Toblige but One .<? Faith they're not of my mind. Tis Wit in Women to accept of AU, The Knight, the Squire, but Gold in General!. The more they swarm, the greater store comes in0 And 'twill be pleasure then to pay for Sin. But to be left in this unruly fort By yon the Great Pretenders of the Court, Would make a Saint, a Mistress ne're so true, Forget her Vows^ and prove as Falje as you; Turning her House, since you are grown so Fickle, As we must ours, into a Conventicle. There's no Redemption, thanks our daily Jars, The Men are all rejbh'd to go to Wars\ J '.. The Women thus grown out of Favour too%~ Must in Remotes begin and trade a new. A 2
Page Scan 13

Then if you chance to have the least Desire, And come though ovirchargd with Love and F, Perhaps wee I take your Guinnies and Retire. C heat you as neve with a Dull Lenten Play, And being Stock'd and Brisks sneaky quite axvay. Laugh at these Huffing Criticks of the Pit, Who come in Droves to feme this Monster Wit. vd FirtX *\ ire. y The Actors Names. Mr. Powell, Sir Arthur Twilight, A Lascivious old Knight. Mr. WHJbire. Sn Generall Amorous, A Gentleman of a tree Nature , a Generall Lover.. Mr. Disney, Contentious Surly, Of a morose Jealous Hu- mour. Mr. Perrin, Sir Geofry Jolt, A Country Justice, fond of all Women. Mr. Pome, John Twiford, A Gentleman of no For- tune, sometimes Lu- natick. Mr. g. Spywtff, Sir Generalls Man. Mr. Co~yfb. Bramble, Sir Arthurs Man. Mr.^ Mr. CoyJb9 Spyvaeff, Bramble. Mr. Coyjh, Bramble, Sir Arthurs Man. An Old man. Captain of the Gipsies, and other Gipsies Men and Women. A Drawer, and two Sedan-men. Women. Mrs. Farke, Eudoria, Mrs. Merchant, Petulant Easy, Mrs. Bates, Emelia, 1 Mrs.C<*>4.> Flora, J Wife to Sh Arthur. Wife to Surly. Daughters to Sir Arthur by a former Wife. ^ MR SCENE LONDON. 1 1 Time Twenty four hours •
Page 1

Blank page
Page 2

Blank page

End of Front Cover. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 3

The Jealous Husbands. ■ Gen. I long to see her then, for nothing in the world can more delight me than to see Beauty in a sit of madness, oh how they Charm! but is she often troubled > Art h. Once a Month, and then she looks so strangely. Gen. Las poor Soul, I fain would trespass Sir upon your Goodness, but the arguments you give me are so many I dare not plead against 'em. [Laughing xvitktn. Enter Bramble running. Brawl. Sir, Sir. Arth. The News with you } Bramb. My Lady Eudoria, and your Daughter Emilia are in such a sit of Laughter, that unless you come in to her assistance, and turn the source of their prodigious Mirth, I fear 'twill overcome 'em. Arth. My Wife Laughing? out you ly ing Varies, j Strides I him. Bramb. As I hope to be sav'd I saw her Sir, (lie laugh'd ex- treamly. Arth. Peace Hell-hound or Pox of the babling \,Afide. Dog, all's fpoil'd now —Alas Sir Amor out', my Man is Frantick, as mad as a March Hare : my Wife Laughing? she is the most melancholy Creature in Europe, she never Smiles nor Laughs, unless at Prayers, or at Church. Gen. Be not so angry Sir, he might mistake. Arth. A Pox of his Mistakes, I hate 'em Sir. (Frets up and I down. Gen. Come hither Bramble, is thy Mistress fick? Bramb. O law Sir. Æ 1 , is thy Mistress down. sick? Gen. Nay tell me, Sir Arthur shall be pleas'd, how does thy Lady? Bramb. Well Sir, well. Arth. Is she so Rascall? lStnk.es Bramble. Pardon me Sir Amorous. A man may have leave to jeast with his Friend, intruth he may, she is within, indeed she is, I did not intend to hinder her your Company, only to raise your Expectations to a pitch. Call in your Mistress, Rascall. Now shall I be made a Cuckold before my face, [Ex. Bramble. I know I shall, if I prevent it not—[^AJide.l I believe Mr. Aw- rom you take me for a Jealous man, a very Jealous sool l ie war- B 2 rant
Page 4

4 The Rambling Juflicc, or, rant you, siich another as Contentious Surly is. But i'faith you arc mistaken, for my Pigsny is too Virtuous to have the least: mistrust upon her, she is indeed. Gen. f mast confess Contentious Surly Rules more like a Mad- man than a Husband, and looks upon his Wife not with the ryes of Reason but of Rage, w ho is all Innocence and Cood- ueis, and \ dare (wear would rot wrong her Husband. Artl... Not tor a World, I know she would not. Alas poor Lady, this it is to have Chastity and Goodness lodg'd under a lealous Roof, I thank my Stars I am free from it. Ci\/.\ '[ ou are the Happier Man, Sir Art lar. Enter Eudcria, Emilia and Bramble. But yonder comes the Comfort of my Soul, who like a Glit tering Star points all its Beams this way. whilst I tire only Wretched of Mankind, dare but admire and ga/.c. Art/.: Sic Amorous be Complaisant, I prethec be, I am not Jealous, sack I am nor, what! look upon a Lady and not dani laJute her? Gen. Indeed I dare nor, my Oath has bound me from so great a Blessing. Arth. Nay if you have Sworn, I have done. Gen. However to oblige so good a Friend I will be perjur'ti once. [Goes to Eudoria,' Madam I hope my strangeness will not.appear Rude or Unman- nerlv, for in your Eyes I read a Happy Fate, and Glorious Blessings wait on every smile, but when they're Check d by the malign Aspect of such a dogged Planet, I must only with this Retire. [Kifes her Maud. End. Tis my 11l fortune Sir, to live a Stranger from the Licit society of man, and only Eat, and Drink and Sleep with an all.seeing Argus, who is I know not what. Gen. I can but pity for a time, then strive to get vour Free- dome. f, Kr fses her Hind again. Arth. Why that's well said, to her again Boy, to her again. Intruth she hath as good a Hand as any she in Europe. Enter Twisord.. Twif. Good Morrow Cousin Arthur, and you Cousin Eu- dorij, and you Cousin Emilia. I protest my Lady Cousins ac Court
Page 5

ealous tinsvanas. < * } Court are cxtreamly Well, Extraordinarily Jocolt and Pleasant, and my Lord had the Mighty Fortune just now to win a hun- dred Guinnics of the Eat ie my Cousin, and how fares my Lord AntnroHS .<? What, Dogged? Gen. No Mr. Trviford, so far from that, F ne're was better pleas'd. Tirif. Fle tell you my Lord th" effects or this day s Hunting. The Duke my Uncle, aud my Lord mv Extraordinary good Friend and Cousin, would needs take me in '.heir Coach to go a Hunting. Art h. flow! in their Coach Mr.Trrifinl.? Trvif. Yes, in their Coach Cousin Arthur. Alas tis the fashion now, all a Mode indeed; and being come to Hide Park, wt unbrae'd the Horses, put our Hats underneith for Saddles, and run the four mile Course Ib pleasantly : but by my Honour I beat 'cm a whole Coach length, Poal and all. Arih. I do believe you. Mr. Amorous mv new Friend and Lodger, welcome once more, come let's retire, the Morning A yi is bleak. Tiryf. It is indeed, mv Cousin Arthur advises well, and truly I am something weary, for I just novv came from Hampton Court. And upon mv word my Cousin is very well, and all the rest of the Lords and Ladies at Court, they are indeed. Arth. I am glad to hear it, come Sir Gcncr.il/. Trvif. Indeed Cousin you are very obliging, nay without Ce- remony my Lord. \_Exeuut. Spy well calls Bramble back,, Spyrv. Hark. How long have you lived here? Bramb. Too long by a fortnight, sixteen days. Spjrv. What, and weary of thy Service already? Bramb. The Devil cannot live Contentedly under my Ma- sters Roof, we are all Prisoners, and he the head Jay lour. Sometimes but very feldome I have the Keeping of my Lady. Spjn\ Whar, under Lock and Key? Bramb. Yes, and Bolts, and Barrs too .j he is as Jealous as he is Old, as Old as he is Crafty, and as Crafty as the Devil. No- thing can Cozen him. Spyrv. Nor Cuckold him neither? Brawl: I believe not, for all my Lady has a minjj to it. She (mil d upon me the other day, aud die Jealous Coxcomb brake my Head for't.
Page 6

6 The "Rambling fy slice, or, Spjtr Twjs ill done indeed. Here, canst thou be secret? \_Givcs him Money. Bramk Asa Churchwarden, let all the poors Money flip in- to my Pocket, and not declare it. Sp)ir. You are fit for my Mallers turn then: know, that Sir General/ Amorous was sent hither by Contentious Sur ley to Cuc- kold your Master, but he knowing no design could be brought about without the help of some Servant or other in the house, ordered me to make Choice of one, whom I lhould think Con- venient. Bram. 1 shall be glad to serve you Sir. Spin: 1 am not Unsenlible your Lady every Afternoon walks into the Garden, where over the purling Fountain stie mourns for the Lols she sustains in having only the Ruins of a Man. Bramb. True Sir. Spyw. She being entered, I would have you oblige me with the Key of the Garden Gate, that my Master may go in and out at pleasure. Brantb. It shall be done Sir. Spyrv. That's all at present, but fail not. Bramb. I will not Sir, I will not. This shall to my Master, perhaps he will reward me nobly for saving his honour, and keeping his Horns from Budding. [Exit. Spyrr. With this first Plot 1 11 try the hasty Servant, which if he spoil I value not, for nothing shall be acted I have told .him, but every Wheel move in another Frame. I've help'd Contentious to his Horns already, and it shall be hard if Twilight scape my Policy. [ Exit. Enter Surly and Petulant Easy. Easy. What have I done to merit your Disgrace! Easy. Have sin ought transgress d the Laws of Wedlock? Surly. Yes. Easy. With whom? Surly. One whom 1 to day remov'd, Sir General/ Amorous, have I not seen him gaze upon your Face, bask in the Sunshine of your Early favours, whilst you as wantonly as common Sin- ners exchang'd both Smiles and Glances? Easy. Surly. Enough. Easy. Have I in
Page 7

Blank page
Page 8

8 The Rambling Jujitce^r^^^^^ spect to her Lord and Master: a Husband is the Head, the very top Branch of the Family. Eas<. 1 look upon him so indeed. Geoff'. Again, again, Lord how this Duty Chaims me! let me Embrace you for an hour together. [_KiJses her again. Surly. How now! why I shall foster up another Snake to sting my Bosome, and one who through simplicity will do r before my Face. Easy. I hope my Wiscdome and Circumspection as he calls it, will make the top Branch of the Family a Buck of the first Head. ^ I Aside. Geoff. As I was going to lay, Mr. Surly, your Wife is a very Dutiful!, Religious, and by my Honour, a very obliging La- dy, your London Women kiss with such Air, and lo much Mag- nificence, that they almost slavish us Country Gentlemen: did you teach her that turn, and that thrust of the Lip ha? by 'Jove *ris most Delicious. Surly. No Sir. Geoff. Then the is Witty too, Lord how 1 admire a Witty Lady! learn that touch your self! let me be raviih'd quite. \_Embraces her again. Surly. Death and Confusion, this is worse than t'other, this is n meer Stallion, I (hall be the Branch 1 find it, he tops upon her still, and she Pvcceivcs it, Sir Geoffry. Geoff. I beg your Pardon Mr. Surly. I vow your Wife has such a Charming way of Kissing, and presses ft ib close, I had forgot my self. Surly. And Co She has 1 think, have you no stiamc, thou Impudent'st of Women? E'iJ}. Shame Sir! Surly. Yes shame. Easy. For what > Surly. To let the World behold your loose desires, you kiss with Art and Pleasure. Easy. You bid me use him kindly, bid me be Wise and Cir- cumspect, and said that you durst trust him with me, and truch/ if you dare venture that, I dare trust my self with him. Surly. Oh Impudence! Easy. You would have- me turn the Check and blusti when he comes near me, as if I were afraid his Beard would hurt me. No

Page 9

The Jealous Husbands. y « No Mr. Surly, I us'd him kindly out of respect to you: and a rhing once well done, is better than wice ill. Surly. Distraction seize her! get you to \ our Clumber. Eas'. Ym gone Sir, and from you for ever. !_ Exit Easy. Geoff". What, send your Wife away and nor give your Friend notice? 'twas unkindly done. Surly. Her business cal! d her. Geoff'. I'faith She kisses smartly. Sitrlv. I am glad to hear it. Geoff. And is all Air too, and for her breath Surly. No more of that Sir Gecffh, I am glad I have any- thing to pleasure you—Pox on him, I cannot forbid him the house for lhame, nor must he stay to plague me. [Aside. Geoff '. Come, come, come, I find you are melancholy, let s to a Tavern, a glals or two of Champain will make us kits and caper, and get us a stomach to our Dinners. [ Excto:t. Enter Sir Arthur and Bramble. Arth. My Wife made an Assignation to meet Amorous in the Garden? Bramb. It is nothing but truth I'll promise you, for his man SpyrteU gave me money not only to be a Confederate, but to steal the Key of the Garden gate, that he as well as my Lady might enter in and out at pleasure. Arth. Did he lb, did he so } Nay, then there is Treason plotting against my honour, I find there is, and did you get the Key for him Bramble / Bramb. Yes Sir. Arth. Did you so Rogue? out upon thee for a Villain, a Traytor, a meer foot Pad, a Setter, Devil j you gave him the. Key did you? I'll key you with a Pox. \_Beats Bramble. Bramb. Hold Sir, hold, you will make Mummy of me else. Arth. I will make a Devil of thee, what, my own Servant be a Traitor? Bramb. I thought no harm in it, as I hope to be . Arth. Beaten did you not? what,give the Key ot vour Masters Cabinet, his Jewclls, his all he has, and yet think no harm? However come along, conduct me to the place where I may see 'em both, or I will beat you swindgingly, nay, when 1 have seen 'em, I will make you beat the villain, and then C beat
Page 10

The Rambling Justice, or, beat you for rot beating him enough , come along Rascal!. [Exeunt, SCENE A Bedchamber. Sir General! Amorous, and Eudoria fitting as in Disc ourse, they rise and come ufoti the Stage. Gen. How dial! I make amends for this great blessing? if all the Services of Life, (which 111 devote to you) can make the feast, I vow to use 'em all; and spend no time but in the company of you, or your Idea which cannot be absent from a Lovers mind, when his Mistress is lb kind, so Charming, and so . Eud. Nay, do not flatter me, I am but as you see, my Face may pass, and those which love it not, let em seek out a bet- ter; I am no whining Lover, I hate those puling Fops, I love a man that gains me by Intrigue, a minute stoln is all the hap- piness of our mortality. Gen. We will have many then, revell in Joyg, and steal a ihousand pleasures, I have a Brain was never barren yet, espe- cially in any Love Projection. End, Thanks to your subtle Man, your vigilant Spjwel/, his Name was not giv'n him for nothing. - Gen. True Madam, I confess he has a ready Wit, but never >et durst undertake an Action, before the Mass was cast by me: he only works and thus divides the whole as our Occasions hap- pen, the drift of which is to obtain your Love. Eud. Which Purchas'd, will perhaps be aHfwer'd with a scorn. Gen. Never, O never Madam} it is impossible such glorious- Charms should meet the least neglect, you are all Goodness, and Entrance at every look my Soul. Eater SpywelUc ; . . Spjrr. Haste, or you're lost for ever, your Jealous Husband prompted by his Rage, comes first to search the Chamber, he is all fire and nothing can allay him. End. What (hall we doe? G.cn, Staad here and meet his Fury.
Page 11

The Jealom Husbands. 11 Spjrv. O by no means, is there no secret Chamber, no place os safety for you? End. Only one, this door leads to a Gallery which is as dark as night, from whence sometimes he fancies are groans heard,which he declares for Truth, and now and then relates v\ hat dreadfull Monsters, Ghosts and Devils he in hts Bed hath seen, all being only Fancies, idle Dreams; thither we will enter, and as we goe I'll give you a Disguise which I have alwaies ready, and if he chance to enter with a Light tumble both down to- gether. Spyw. It shall be done, scar not, haste, haste, I hear him coming. [ Exeunt. Enter Sir Arthur and Bramble, Bramble with a Light. Arth. On, on, you villain on, [Looks about the Room. not here by Heaven, nor here, [Breaks open one Door. nor here. [Brea^ open .mother. She is in the Garden that's certain, stay, stay, hold, hold, here is a Gallery, a Teneberian Gullet, which I dare not enter, but Bramble shall, in, in, in there Raicall, learch every place, nay every Corner, or meet my high displeasure. s Bramble Enters, is Tumbled down by Spy well, rowls \ out and is followed by Spywell as a Ghoji, Arthur \ feeing him, runs off crying the Devil, the Devil, See C and Bramble crawls off. Spyw. Come, come, you may venture to come out now. Enter Eudoria and Sir Generall Amorous. Gen. He's gone, as full of fear as Jelousy, Eudoria this plot was yours, and henceforth to you 1 11 own my Preservation. Spyw. This is no time to talk, Madam haste to your Bed, and there pretend a sleep, I know you want not sitting words t ex- cuse so small an absence if he should chance to search and find you. And you Sir, haste to your Chamber, 1 know that's the next Rendezvous after the Garden. Gen. Farewell, my Prayers and Love attend you. [Exeunt severally. SCENE
Page 12

12 The Rambling Justice, or, SCENE Iht Garden. Enter Twifbrd, Erael'ia and Flora. Tn.is. Nay, nay, come, come, come, mv pretty Coufins, up- on my honour and all that, you are both Beauties, but especi- ally Lady Cousin, you as the Eldest ought to have most praise, •ind i'faith you deserve it noblv, and when saw you my Lord 'John, and his Lady Miry, ha? Emel. I know 'em not. Twif. What, not my very good Friend and Honourable Con- fin my Lord John i that's strange indeed } why, he was my Fa- thers Cobler, but afterwards by Care and Prudence , good Custome and (6 forth, he became an Alderman, and then—— Enter Sir Arthur and Bramble. what, my Honourable Cousin Sir Arthur, I vow I am glad to lee you: my Lady Mary is very considerably well, and trucly I believe we shall have Affairs put into a very good order, and Cousin Arthur your two Daughters and I have been entertain- ing Discourse upon a very considerable lubject. Arth. Pox of your subjects. Ewelia, where is Ejtdoria .<? Emel. In her Chamber Sir. Arth. Tis false, all, all are Traytors, every one conspires my Ruine and Disgrace, but you shall pay for it Villain you shall, 1 11 sirk you i'faith, you must tell Lies with a Pox, get you from my sight you Varlet. [_ Beats Bramb. Eramb. So I will, and from your Service too j the Devil shall live with such a Master for me, farewell Sir, may the Pox and your own Horns choak you. [ Exit Bramble. Arth. Is he gone, is the Villain gone? Flor. Yes Sir. » Arth. What did he fay > Trvif. Something about Horns and Pox, but by my Honour Coz I believe he's Frantick, for what has a Clown to doe either with Pox or Horns? they are Ornaments only for Court and City. Arth. But Emclia, Flora, nay good Citles tell me where, where, where is Eudor/a, where is my new Lodger > EnicL
Page 13

The Jealous Husbands. 13 Emel. As for Sir Amorous I know nor, but for Eudoria I saw her in her Chamber. Flor. And so did 1 Sir Amorous. Arth. Nay then tis pretty well, 'tis pretty well: I am almost mad dear drles, this Peogue Bramble has Calhier'd my Wits, Pox of the Garden key, but tis no matter Emclia I have a Hus- band for you, a Rich and Understanding Husband. Emel. Nay, if he be but Rich I'll bate his Understanding, that is too troublesome a Companion for a Woman. Arth. All, all of the lame Brood by Heaven, not one Chast Woman in a Kingdom, it there be one 'tis a Miracle. QRv. .ill but Emel ia. I'.mcl. This is the Curse of Wedlock, hourly Jealousies and daily Troubles, if ever I many it lhall be one both Dea£ Dumb, Lame and Blind. They're all but Complements for hourly Strife, And with new Troubles cliily fill the Life Of her who's such a jot to be a Wife, [ Exit. The End of the First AB. ACT II. S. C E NT E S:. Jamess. Enter Sir General 1 Amorous. Gen. \ Æ Y Thoughts are all on sire, my Pulse beats (wist, and XVI every Motion uthers a new thought, I'm all Desire and Love, and fain would reap those pleasures are in View, oh Jelouly how dost thou wrong that Love might be enjoy *d without the least Sulpect, how many various waies do we Con- spire to blind his greedy Eyes! I wonder Bramble stayes so long, our hasty separation hindred a new Appointment, which I was fore'd to send by one I would not trust, did he not hate Sir Arthur. C 3 'Enter
Page 14

ie Rambling J up it Enter Bramble. Bramble the News? Bramb. The News Sir! Gen. Yes, how dorh Eudoria? Bramb. Soft, soft Sir, you think it is nothing to get News out of a l adies Chamber where her Husband is the Jay lor, 1 was there Sir. Gen. Well. Bramb. As you know a merry fellow may pals any where. Gen. So Sir, but what is this to the purpose? Bramb. Nay, it was nothing to the purpose that is certain. Gen. How wretched this Have makes me, did you not lee her > Br.imb. 1 law her. Gen. Well, and what laid she then? Bramb. Not a word Sir. Gen. How! not a Word? Bramb. Proves her the better temper'd, for Women should be seen more than they are heard. She was asleep Sir. Gen. You should have waked her then '-, such another oppor- nuity lost would be enough to ruine half a Kingdome. Br.imb. I durst not venture that Sir, for sear Sir Arthur should have heard me, and then you know what follows: but I stood ftill awhile, and presently I might perceive Endoria yawn, and stir, and rub her Eyes and then Gen. She spoke the kindest words, oh let me hear 'em. Bramb. Not one indeed Sir, and yet I know her mind as well as if I were in her Belly. Gen. You said but now she did not speak a word. Bramb. But she gave certain Signs, and that's as good. Gen. Can you conceive by Signs? Bramb. Ye* very well Sir, even from an Infant, did you ne're know that? I was the happiest Child in all our Country, I was born of a Dumb woman. Gen. How! Bramb. Stark Dumb Sir . my Father had a Rare bargain of her, a Rich penniworth, there would have been but too much money given for her, a Justice of Peace was about her, but my Father being then Constable carried her before him.
Page 15

The Jealous Husbands. Gen. What were the Signs she gave > Bramb. Many and good Sir. Imprimis, Hie first gap d, but that I guessd was done for want os Air; then she cast up her Eyes and wink'd, as who should say hid Sir Amorous come at twilight: then look d upon her Watch and twice she nod- ded, a>> who should lay, the hour will come, that I (hall make two Noddies of my Keepers. Gen. A Third of thee, is this your Mother Tongues my hope:, are much the wiser tor this Language, there ib no luch Curie in Love as an Arrant Als. Bnitub. O yes Sir, yes, an Arrant Whore's far worse. Gcrr. Eegone is this the good you do me? his Love. is wretch- ed and most distress, that mult make use of Fools. \_E\it. B\tmb. Fool to my Face from this, and he beaten by thco- ther? that's unreasonable 5 I will be a Knave one day for this trick, or it shall colt me a Fall, though it be from a Gibbet. I II be out of the Precincts of Fools it I live but two daics to an end, I will turn Kaseall presently, the bett fort of which are Gfljcis; for that is the high way to the daintiest Knave that ever Mothers son took journey to. O those dear Gipjejs they live the merriest Lives, eat sweet stoln Hens, pluck d over Pales and Hedges by a Twitch. They are never without a plump and lovely Goose, or dainty Sow pig, thole things I saw with my own Eyes to day, they call 'em Vanities and tri- fling Pilfries, oh they arc the Wittiest Thieves, 111 stay no longer, but go and steal something presently, and so bring my self acquainted with them. L^xit Bramble. , Eater Sir Generall Amorous. Gen. Nothing I fear so much as in the time of my dull ab- sence, and the idle Frenfie of my Metlenger, her Husband will come to know our Loves, and by secret threats and promises regain her Affection, there is the Mitchief, I have no Enemy like him, and though his Policy dissemble me a welcome, no mans hate can be greater than his to me. Enter Spy we ll. Spjw. Now is your only time t enjoy the freedonre Sir of Conversation. After Eitdorr.i parted to her Bed, I watched the jealous Hutband and dog'd him from the Garden to rWr Chatm. 'ber,
Page 16

16 The Rambling Justice, or, bcr, where when he found her he leapt for very Joy, then wept, and lcap'd again, at last he timeroully strove to wake her, which being done he fell upon his Knees anil beg'd her to forgive him } hung on her Neck and seem'd to be Transported. Gen. How can this quench thole Flames of Love I feel, or help me to Enjoyment? Spyrr. No sooner was his Pardon sign'd with Killes, but from her iight he thing to seek you out, that you might make it perfect. Gen. All this but ushers Torment, not Reliefc. Spjiv. He gone, I entered towards the fair Eudoria, and with Inch moving word* as l could utter, painted the Flame Sit of your vigorous Love} the lent a gentle Far to what I laid, and lighing bid you meet her in the Grove behind the Garden gate. Gc/t. Oh Happinets! Spjtv. Where Mask'd Sir, and dilguis'd like a Town GipJ) (he would attend your Pleasure. Gen. O let me hug you close, I could (methinks) squeeze you into my Soul, the News you've brought has made me all a Flame, rais'd my desires to such a mighty pitch, that as I'm fal- ling t'wards my Sea of plealure. I shall talt on the way all, all the bliss of Life. Enter Sir Arthur. Arth. Sir Gener.iU Amorous well met, well met i'faith, I vow I am glad to fee you; my Wife poor (Amorousjiwds I wel.imhol). What, angry man? come, come, I know the reason, I was a little jealous, Fack I was, but it is off again .., nay, now you are no true Friend, what, angry for a Continuando? Gen. I am not Sir, especially with you, yet who can shun the Crolses of the World, or help Arth. Help, what Crolles? I am the belt at helping of Cros- ses of any man in Europe} come tell me your Grievances, you shall, you shall. Gen. Sir, they are in my Power to tell, but not in your Will t'effect. . 3j Arth. Not in my Will t effect? by Eudorus honesty but it shall be in my Will, What is't? Gen
Page 17

e yen lorn tnuwaias. TT 1 Get?. By my frequent disappointments, and my many urgen1 occasions for mony, lam at this timeneceflitated fora hundred pound. Artb. Hum, hum, a hundred pound? 'tis a fwindging summe indeed, and out of my power not will to lend you ^ however heie's a Ring, a diamond Ring it is, and will go near to pawn for sifty Guinneys, take that, before you have spent it all, l Hull be furnished doubt not. Gen, Sir I accept your proffer, and for your security the Deeds of all my Lands shall be delivered, till then farewell. | Exit (um Spy Well. Arth. Shall be delivered? ay but when? l have done bravely now, lent fifty pound upon a shall be delivered} yet o'mycon- science he is an honest Gentleman .., he has honesty and civility writ on his face, he has indeed i he is not like our whoring, swearing Spai ks of the times, who make it their practice to dub Cuckolds, and then out ofcivility be the Child's Godfather. Enter S/r JeolTrey Jolthead and Contentious Surly. Geoff. Why, now Mr. Surly we look like men, methinks s could caper and leap, and kiss and play, and do every tiling with a Lady: oh this wine, this wine is a very pleasant element. Surly, It is indeed. Geoff. What Sir Arthur Tyvilighty and how does my pretty little Hearing Mistcs ha? can they kiss smartly and turn up the lip ha? QSurly pulls him by the Coat. si'riy. Pox of this Fool, he will proclaim my shame to all the World. '[Afde. Geoff. Can they Boy, can they? Artb. They can do every thing belongs to the Sex no doubt Sir Geoffrey. Geoff] I vow they are pretty Wags, I love em dearly; Hull I see 'em? ,r*2 • r^ftr j . ^« & Artb. Yes when you please Sir Geoffrey. Mr. Surly you look clouded: pox of sorrow I lay, it is enough for superannuated Cuckolds to be melancholy, not such as you and I, we are free from it. surly. I would I were. [Afide,~\ Sure he knows nothing ro the contrary.„ r, D Artb.
Page 18

ve ixamviing yx/tice, or, Arth. 'Tis a great torment to be jealous sure, to think a very shadow at Noon-day can do the act we dream of: to frown on all, even our best of friends ; turn off our Lodger?, cashier our Servant?, swear at our Maids, ("kinder our Children. [As sir Arthur / alks, Contentious Sur- |lv walks, Sir Arthur following him. Surly. Curse on this Ribaldry, what's this to me, am I ihc man you aim at? Arth. No, no Sir, no. Surly. Am I the mark you level all these arrows at? Arth. No Sir, no. Surly. Why do you bellow in my cars the name of Cuckold then? Arth. Because there is pleasure in it, methinks they are the prettiest old decrepit Creatures in Europe: but Mr. Surly I have done, come (hall's drink a glass of Wine together? let us be brisk and merry, shall we ha? Geoff. Well said Mr. Arthur^ you arc the same man frill, the merry man i'saith, and could I warrant you— but tis no matter, come Mr. Surly. Surly. I care Sir for no more, my business lies at home. Geoff. A pox of home, thou hast a Wife at home, that can l ie warrant you manage affairs without the help of Husbands come, come, you (hall go. Arth. Dodo, ifock, Mr. surl) you are good company, and I love good company with all my heart, come come, let's to the Tavern, and there talk ofour Wives. Surly. If I go, I bar that discourse. Anb. It shall, it shall, come, come, we will not name 'em, we will not name 'em. [Exeunt. SCENE Tke f ields. Enter Petulant Easy disguised 10$ a Gyfjte. • Easy. I'm happily eseap'd,not one pursues me, this shape s too cunning for em, and if I can but find Sir Generals then all my hopes are crown'd. This is the Gypsies place of meeting, I won- der they are not come yet, what will become of me in this shape without my strange Companions? if I know where to go In I
Page 19

The Jealous Husbands. I'm no dissembler, and I'denot lose that part of woman for such a trifle. Enter Bramble. Bramb. Oh excellent! by this light here's one of'em, by your leave Gypsie, pray how far ofFis your Company? Easy. Oh happiness, this is the merry fellow Sir Arthur Twi- light keeps, Tie send him speedily to Sir General with the news of my so strange and fortunate escape, and hee'l provide my safety at an instant. \,Afide.~\ Do you not serve Sir Arthur Twi- light? Bram. Who, I serve, Gypfie? I scorn your motion, and if the rest of your company give me no better words, I will hinder them the stealing of more Pullen then sifty Poulterers were ever worth, and prove a heavier enemy to all their Pig-Booties j they shall travail like Jews, and never get a Sow by the ear. I serve? I scorn to serve any body, I am more Gyplie-minded then lb, though my face look of a Christian colour, if my belly were ripp d up, you should sind my heart as black as any patch about ye: the truth is, I am as errand a thief as the proudest in the company, I will except none, I am run away from my Master in the state of a fool, and till I am a perfect knave I never mean to return again. Easy. 1 am never the happier for this fortune now, it did but mock me. Enter General Amorous. Bram. But here comes my last Master, I must not be seen. {Exit Bramble. Easy. Yonder's Sir Amorous, O happy hour, my blushes come apace to shrowd my shame, thus let me hide em from him. [Puts on her MasJ^ Gen. This is certainly she. Madam I am glad I have the hap- piness of this occasion to meet you here alone, far from the eyes of any Jealous Husband. Easy. I have long wish d it, and now I fear some strange mis- chance will cross us. Gen. Fear nothing Madam, but let's retire, the hasty Sun will soon withdraw its lustre, and leave us Lovers in a bed of darkness, where we shall be wrap'd in pleasures. \ExemU . D 2 Enter
Page 20

2 o The R ami ling Justice, or. Enter Bramble. Br im. Ha is he gone? vs hat, and the Gypfie too? then am I loft again. Enter Eudoiia d/Jguis'd like a Gjpfie. F.iulo. Who's that, Bramble ? then onymy flirowd and hide me horn his light. \J}nts on her Mask. Enter j company fffXjjpfer, men and women with booties of Hens, GV. dant h/g and singing rid/culoufly^ Bramble/cfw/ ovy. rjoj'd. Bram. O sweet, they deseive to be hang'd for so ravilh- ing os me. Eudo. What will become or me? if I seem fearsull now, or offer sudden flight, I (ball betray myself, I must do neither. C. G/p. Oulabell, Camcheteroon, Pulcatelion, Howfdrows. 2. G/p. Kurnbos Stiv.g. delion, alia Piskitch in lows Clows. Bra/n. Piskitch in sows Clov•s! I (hall never keep a good tongue in my bead till l get this Language. C. G/p. Umbra Fill, Kevoiiden, Magropie. [To. Eudoria* E/ulr I love your Language well but understand it not. C. G/p. Ha! End. I am but lately, turn'd to your profession, yet from my youth I ever lov'd it dearly 3 steal I can, it was a thing I ever was brought up to; my Father was aJI///A>; my Mother a Taj- ler's Widow. Bi.aw. She is 4 thief on both sides.. C. Gip. Give me thy hand, we have not a more true bred thief among jus. Brant, Pray take me into some graceamongst you, for though I claim no goodness from my Parents to help me into your society, I had two Uncles that were both hang'd for Robberies, and a brave Cut-punt; to my Cosen German: if Kindred will be ta- ken, I am as near of kin to a thief as any of you that had Fa- thers and Mothers. C. G/p. What is it thou required: noble Cofin } Colin? nay if we are ib near of kin already now we are sober, we ihall be sworn bnothers when we are drunk: the na- icd truchk I would be nude a Gipsie as fast as you could devise. C. Qfe

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 21

C. Gip. A Cipsic?

Brant. Yes with all the I peed you can sir, the very sight of those stoln Hens,eggs me forward notably. C.Gip. Stretch fbith thy hand Cu/, art thou fortunate? Bram. Nay I cannot tell ihat my self, I have sometimes found mony in old (hoes, but if I had not ftoln more then I found, I had had but a scurvy thin chcek'd fortune ot it. C. G/p. Here's a stir table. Bram. So hath many a man that hath given over house-keep- ing, a fair table when there is neither cloth nor meat uponit. C. G/p. What, a brave line of life is here! look Gipsies. {HhiiJl they el/jiourje, the G/p- \ (ies pick, his pocket. * Bram. I have known as brave a life end in an halter. C. G/p. But thou art born to precious fortune. Braw. Ha! am I si)? C. G/p. Bette Buckettos, Brunt. How! to beat.bucks? C. G/p. Stealee Bacons. Bran/. Oh to steal bacon, that is the better fortune of the two indeed. C. Gip. Thou wilt be shortly Captain of the Giplies. Br.iw. I would you'd make me Corporal in the mean time, or Standard-bearertothe womens Regiment. C. Gip. Much may be done for love. Bram. Nay here is some mony, I know an Office comes not all for love. {^Searches his pockets but fuels f/one. A pox of your lime-twigs you have it already. C. G/p. It lies but here in cash for thy own use boy. Bram. Nay if II lie there once,I shall hardly come to the singer- ing on't in hast, ytt make me an apt scholar, and I care not, teach me but so much Gipsie to steal as much from another, and Old Nick do you good with that. C. Gip. Thou (halt have all thy heart requires. First here's a Girl for thy dcsires.[G/7Jc/ him a wonuin Gipsre. Look you prove industrious dealers. To serve the Commonwealth with stealers, That th'unhous'd Race of Fortune-tellers, May never fail to cheat Town-dwellers.: D 3 Or
Page 22

~" 1 be H ambling Justice, cr, Or to our universal griefs Leave Country Fairs without a thief. This is all you have todoe, Save every hour a filch or two: Which hoping you'll observe, to trie thee, With Rusty Bacon thus I Gipsie-sie thee. [Blacks his face Bram. Do you use to doe it with Bacon? C. Gip. Evermore. Bram. By this light the Rats will take me now for some Hogs- cheek, and eat up my lace when I am aileep: I (hall have ne'i abit left by to morrow morning, and lying open mouth'd asl us'd to do, I shall look for all the world like a mouse-trap baited with^ucon. C. Gip. Why here's a face like thine so done, Only grain a in by the Sun. And this, and these. Bram. Faith then there is a company of Bacon-faces of us; we are a kind of conseionable people, and it was well thought upon to steal bacon and black our faces with it; tis like one that commits sin, and writes his faults in his forehead. C. Gip. VVit whither wilt thou? Bram. Marry to the next pocket I can come at, and if it be j Landlords, I wish a whole years rent in it: is this my In Docl out Nettle > what's Gipsie for her? C. Gip. Your Doxie she. Bram. Oh right, are you my Doxie, sirrah? Wo. Gip. I ll be thy Doxie and thy Dell, With thee I'll live, for thee I'll steal. From Fair to Fair, from Wake to Wake, 111 ramble still for thy sweet sake. Bram. Oh dainty fine Doxie, she speaks the Language as fa ^iliarly as if she were begot of a Canter. Woman Gipjie sings. Thus hand in hand let's htm him round, And dance a measure on the ground. We Ufrolick firsts then part from hence, Each rvith hisstocl^of impudence: ToTowns, to Cities, Fairs, and Fields, And fee what prosit each one yields. ^
Page 23

e yealom nnsvan Then to our Rendezvous rrec'lfly. Be brisk, be drunk,, be kind Jf>d die. rHere they dance. At the cud of the dame. Er/tcr \Contemious Surly, Sir Arthur Twilight, ik I ySV JeofTrey Jolthead,/& Gipsies feeing then^ n< ( off all hut Eudoru and Bramble. Art h. Iky day, hey day, what a surprize is this! QEudorta offers to go, *r kindred by Sir Arthi.j Nay, nay, Gipsie you shall not go, i'fack you (ball not, I long: to kits a Giplie, I do indeed i I am not so old yet but F can shake my leg under a hedge I II warrant you, come, comcy Gip- fie, pull off your false face, and tell me my fortune. [Tat(fJ her aside and jhoxcs his h ind. Geoff. And can you tell fomines sirrah? Braw. Culvario, legamuttanio. . Geoff. What a pox is that? Bran/. Shouldramaton, Katathumpton, Rob, bob, a Tum- brell. Geoff. That Tumbrell I understand being a Magistrate, on, fellow, on, what fry you to my hand? Bra/n. Chitteroon High Gulleroon , FHchcroon, purse Ful- leroon, Ousabcll Camchetcroon, iuscatclion Howsdrows. Geoff. What a devil is this? Br.im. Rumbos Straggadelion, alia piskitch in sows clowsum- bra sill KevollidenMagropie. Geoff. Pox on ye, (peak English, or I'll make you, tell me of Magropies? Brant. You arc J Starts in hk face, andalljhk whilepre- I tends to pi eights pocket,but ar discovered. Geoff. Ha Rogue, ha> is this your Piskitch in sows clows, and your Magropies? I'll Magropieyou with a pox. [Bedts him. Bram. As I hope tabe sav'd this is the first time, I am but a young Gipsie yet'-, alas I was Sir Arthurs Bramble till he beat me, and then I ran away, and entred my self amongst 'em. Geoff. I'll enter you as lam a Magistrate. \Bcatshtm again. Arth. I sack thou art a pretty Rogue, tells me all true by hea- ven: Oh I could eat your eyes out! On, on. Endo. Vare an insufficient decrepit whoremaster, and deserve Were I your wife to be . Arth. Chronicled, Ido indeed: but women may fay what they
Page 24

24 The li ambling yujttce3 or, they please, they may indeed. Come, come, let you and I re- tire, yonder t> a delicate hedge, where we will communicate all our pood Pans together, we will indeed. Fuel . What before you lee my face? A ih. No matter, no matter, you have good signs, good h inds, good hips, and I believe good everything; come, come, come, let Us lose no time, here's money before-hand, I gad rue- thinks lam a very vigorous Lover. End. But I hope, to lee my (ace, now you have lo generously expos'd voui gold, would be no trouble. Anh. None in the world: introth it would raise, it would elevate my spirits toa height, it would indeed,andthenl dial]—, End. What, Sir Arthur [Discovers her self, all are amazed. Be a perjur'd false dillembling Hypocrite! are these your daily •actions, these your haunts? could nothing but a Gipsie serve your turn? is age so hot, so fierce in his desires? have I with tears wept if you were but absent, mourn d like a turtle when my mate was h orn me, and all for this return? Surly. This is lbme nick, some trick upon my life, and ten to one my honour is concern d in'tj I'll after the Gipsies, perhaps my wise is amongst 'em, I ll fee, and search every man and wo- man in the company but I will sind her out. [Exit Surly. Rr.im. My Mistress a Gipfie? nay then there is hopes for me. End. Keep off, now I abhor you. [,Arthur seems tointreat. Arth. Nay dear Spouse, 'twas but a freak, a little freak indeed. Geoff. Come, come, forgive him Madam, 'troth I have done as much my self! Bra'/t. Pray Madam forgive him that Sir Geoff, may forgive me. Arth. Nay, nay, dear Chuck, what, be your Husband's mortal enemy? why, who would have taken you for a Gipfie? Nay, nav, come, you (hall forgive me. [Gives her a Ring. End. I do Sir, but have a care for the future. Arth. I will never look upon a woman besides thy self again, indeed I will not. Sir Geoffrey, you must forgive Bramble too, then all are friends. Geoff. With all my heart, but have a care hereafter. Bram. I'll warrant you Sir. Arth. Come S'wGeoff. you shall along with me and see Emelia. How more then happy is the marriage life, When man is bleji veith such a vert nous I Vise. [Exeunt. Finis AXus Secundi. ' A C T III

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 25

ACT III. SCENE A Groze. Enter as out of it, Sir General Amorous, and Easy mxsi^ck Gen. I " H I S is the greatest blessing Heav'n ( and you ) J could give me. How many minutes have we had of precious sweet delight! Oh let me dwell upon these hands a while, and breath my foul into each trilling Pore: thy melting lips have made me all a charm, and when I call my arms about thy neck,I thought I grasp'd a God j the darkness of the Covert could not (hade thy piercing beauty from me, tor through those thick and darksor.e Clouds of Night, I could behold the glances of thy Eyes, which Ihot fresh joys into my panting heart. Eajy. You're pleas'd to jest. "Gen. Not I by Heaven, all, all I lay is earnest} pull back that Cloud, and let me view your glories: let me behold you in the height of blushes, that I may fay you charm at every Action. [Easy pulis off her nusl^, Generous Jiarts. Ha! have I embrae'd a stale, a cast off Amoret, is this the hopes I had of fair Eudoria, have I bestow d a Ring of fifty pound upon I know not what? Easy. What ay le you Sir > Gen. Nothing Madam, nothing, onely the apprehension of the danger, and the mistrust your Husband will have of you when he shall find you absent, I must confess did something start my spirits, but now 'tis off again. But oh ! the Ring! Eas<. Name not that senseless thing again, a Husband ise'nea clog of life, I'm of a humour free, and unconfin'd, and court for pleasure in the man I love. Gen. True Madam, 'tis most sweet .■, when love and freedom meet, a Husband is a kind of dull Animal, created to bear the name of Father, whilest we happy men enjoy with freedom what he fondly thinks himself monopolizeth. . r Easy. Then they're so jealous too. They
Page 26

tng f*jttce, ar, Gen. They are indeed, and that first prompts their wives to new defires: I never yet knew a man jealous, but he had the just rewards his madness merited. Evtcr Contentious Surly. Heavens! here's your Husband coming, on, on with the mask, and haste home with all the speed you can before morning, ex- pert me to give" you freedom. tExil Easy, Surly going after her, lisjiop'cl by General Amorous. Mr. Surly your servant. I vow I am happy in finding you in this solitary place, my thoughts wanted companions. Surly. And so they are like still, I cannot stay. Gen. Were your haste requisite I would not stop you, but with your friend you might dispense some time. Surly. I cannot, nor I will not. Gen. Indeed you must fir. Surly. Must? Gen. Yes sir you must: I have not forgot how in your last frantick (it you pleas'd to stain rav honour, and with siich words. Surly. I have no leisure now. Gen. To fight I know you have not, nor never had i you wear a sword indeed, but for what use I know not, unless to fiighten fools, bully with cowards, or draw on every Link- boy. Surly. Prithee, I can stay no longer. 5 Forces from bint land Exit. Gen. He s gone as full of rage as jealousie, pray Heaven he overtake her not, but sure she has more wit then to go the di- rest path, which ac I'm sure will follow. Was ever man so chea- ted? how came I to mistake Evdoria, and light upon this Easy? it must needs be the treachery of Spywli, Enter Spywell. Spy. Was ever man so unfortunate } Gen. Was ever man so treacherous? Spy. To have an Assignation from a Lady, and shun the bles' sing of it. Gen. I am plain and do not speak in Hieroglyphicks, did not you send Petulant Easy disguis'd , as you told me En- doria
Page 27

The Jeatotts Husbands. 2 7 dori.t designs to be, to the place appointed for our meeting. Spy. Not I by Heaven. Grt'. Then the Devil did, that's certain j for I no sooner came to th' Rendezvous, but Easy habited and mask'd as you descri- bed Eudorta, with open Arms received me, and led me to this Grove? where after a few common ceremonies, love-toys, and the like, I presented her with a King I borrowed of Sir Arthur Twilight, still taking her for V.udona, but coming to the light, and the dark Cloud withdrawn, I found my strange mistake. Spy. The lame hapned to Eudorta, who full of love came to the place appointed, and there unfortunately met with Sir Arthur. Gen. Confusion! Spy. He mistaking her for a Gipsie, made a deal of ridiculous Love to her, which the accepted, but coming to the height of all his passion, and til I'd with a licentious kind of Dotage, the discovered her felt to the old Lecher, who was glad to make his peace on any terms. Gen. Oh I could grasp her now into my soul! (he is the most deserving of womenkind, but how to let her know the strange mistake, is past my power to imagine. Spy. Leave that to me, haste to Sir Arthur Twilight, and there pretend (as you may very well) a Journey out of Town, and by the way declare your love to Eajy, and hatred to Contenti- ous Surly, tell him you long to be reveng'd, and know no way but one, which is to take his Wise with you. Gen. Make him a Pander? Spy. Wee'l do't ne'er fear, he loves to view a Cuckold, but hates to fee himself; Come, let's be gone, I'll tell you as we walk, with what you must possess him: as for Eudorta, leave her to me, if I prepare her not may I never design again. Gen. Thou art a real servant, and lovest thy Master's plea- sure. How many various Charms round Women move! Each has some strange Intreague to make us Love. s Exeunt. E? SCENE
Page 28

e Rambling JuHice, or, SCENE Sir Arthur's House. Enter Sir GcofFry Jolthead, Emelia and Flora. G'.ff But what lay you Ladies, how could you affect my person } am I not all Air, ha? why, we Country Magistrates are such taking things, that you Londoners run almost stark mad of us. I am as sprightly as any bawdy Citizen of you all; [ can di ink, I can swear, I can roar, lean serenade, aud besides all that, I can but tis no matter. h/or. Nay there is no doubt Sir,but you are are all vigour,and methinks I could love a Country Gentleman with all my heart. Ewe. And so could 1, especially a Country Magistrate, they look with so much Grace, aud lit at the Bench just like— Geoff] We do so, we do so indeed, — just like what, mv Dear > Erne. A Baboon looking an Alderman's head. Geoff. Out upon thee wag, a Baboon is a beastly lascivious Creature:but goon, go on, you have leave to jeast. Flon. I am not of your mind Sister, I love a Magistrate, e- ipecially when he is asleep, he nods so prettily, and then he is ib quiet, unkis r.ow and then he snore out a learned Sen- tence. 'i*it Geoff. Still, still you are wags, nicer wags,i'siith }i but go on, go on, methinks 1 love to hear you. rohf U.*n«. I've done jeastingSir, alas rnv fit lasts but a little while, aud then lam so melancholy 3 aud yfct methinks I could love you, would you forbear that hard hearted trick of feeing wo- men whip'd at the House of Correction. . Gaff. I never use it, indeed I do not,but I know some of vour dare not speak before my Sister Could you love me Sir? Geoff. Beyond the world, why I coidd eat you Madam. E>»el. What and keep me like a Lady? Geoff] Oh like a Countesi, you shall have all, all that your heart desires, and live so pleasantly. ■ . Emel.
Page 29

The Jealous Husbands. ?y Emes. But would you never turn me off? Geoff. Never, never by this hand. Emel. Nor keep another } Gcnjf. Sooner a Devi], believe me Madam • This is the ytcldingest little Female I ever saw. [ Audi Emcl. I'm loth to try you though, you men are lode ceitfull. Geoff. Courtiers and Shopkeepers, I giant you, they fel- dome or nt ver keep their words, butwc Countrymen are astiuc a* steel. Emcl. How thai I we come together? G.off. How! as man and woman Ihould. Ewel. But by what means? Gcvff. Ay by what means, -I think some d'lguile- Etnel. You've thought upon it, habit your self like aQualgr. and come at twelve this night, vou'l lee a caudle in my window, hem twice,and I'll come down and let you in, the habit's grave and u ill keep off fulpicion. Geoff. It will indeed, oh let me kits your hand. Em J. Anon you shall enough, farewell. You shall be Mik'd Sir Gevffry, or I'll lole my aim. [ Exit Emelia. Gcvff. Was ever Country Magistrate so foitunate? lure ne- ver. I am an Adonis, that s certain. Ftor. My Sister and you have had a long discourse Sir. Geoff'. Something we did talk of, but not much. This Chicken has a mind to be doing tool find it. Aside. Alas she is all anger, and looks upon me as the Devil look'd o. ver Lincoln. Flor. I Ihould have been kinder had you made your addrestts to me , but her Chaims are Ib gr«.at, lo many, and lo powerful!, it was not in the power of man to stand against "em. Gccff. Your Sister is so, so, but i'faith you have twenty beauties to one of hers: methinks your Eyes are but tis no matter, 1 dare not look upon em, if you prove hard hearted bkeyour Sister. Flor. Tiy me Sir, I hope you'l find.me otherwise. Gicff. Then a woman I would not, for 'tis their glory to frown on all} but could I be so happy, to gain a place within ou loft affection, how would I stiiveto make me worthy ofyou. E 2 Flor. 1
Page 30

The Rambling Justice, Ftor. You are already, heigh ho [Sighs, Geoff. Come figh no more, I find you love me dearly. Flor. But will you not betray me? tell my Sister, and lay we open to her Scorn and Laughter? Geoff'. Not I by Heav'n, Pox I'll be hang'd and damn'd first. Flor. Nor forsake me? Geoff'. Never. Flor. Give me your hand, I am yours then '•, to morrow I will pretend a sickneis, and lend for you as a most learn'd lJhy- litian: but be secret. Geoff. As a Physitian ought, I'll warrant you. Flor. That done but tell no body. Geoff] Pox take me is I do. Flor. And the Room clear'd — but be silent as you respect my Honour. Geoff. Fear not, I have more respect to a Ladies honour than lb. Flor. I'll leave the rest to you: you are wise enough to manage Love affairs. Farewell. f_Ex. Flora. Geoff] If I fail, may I never have such fair Assignations again: a Quaker and a Doctor } two excellent disguises to get Maiden-heads in } I am Ravish'd, that's certain} a Quaker and a Doctor? oh excellent! [.Ex, Geoffry Jolthead. Enter Eudoria, reading a letter. Eud. Th' Excuse if fair, and founds like real! Truth} but what he prompts metds so full of dangerous hazards, I fear to undertake it. 1 Wait in the Garden MasJ(d [_ Reads. and in your Night-gown, and there expeSf th event What should it mean? What Plot's in aftion now? Why should I asi^that question, or doubt the firmness of it, vehen Love k chief Condudor? 1 will venture it, attend the hour, and wijh to fie th' Event; Love cannot injure Love, nor dare it think\on any cruell thought j or if it dare, I will be arnt'd against it. f_Ex. Eudoria. Enter
Page 31

Blank page
Page 31

Blank page

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 31

Enter as in discourse Sir Arthur Twilight and Sir Generall Amorous. Arth. Contentious Surl)S Wife ?. Gen. The fame Sir. Arth. In my Garden? Gen. Yes Sir, for Love has made her look for liich j thift to free her from his Tyrannous Jealousy, and I chose this courle before any othca, not only to make us sport, but to leap my wifh'd for Ends. Arth. A pierty and moss pleasant project! who would not friL.in a point of Neighbourhood for lnch a quaint device? 11! go retch her presently. Gm. How the Old villain joys in Villanj. ._Ex. Sir Arth. Enter Sir Arthur. Arth. Sir Generally Sir Generall, a rare Device. Gen. What vet again? what Stratcgcm have you now..' Arth. The best that ever was, I'll fetch my Wife's Gown which you may put upon Petulant Easy, that if he chance to meet her, he may not have the least suspect but take her for Eudoria. Gen. That I have done already, and Ib difguisd and mask'd she waits you in the Garden. Arth. I'U fitch her presently, Lord, Lord, how it pleases me to think upon Contentious, poor man ha, ha, ha, I laugh to think how he will rave,when he shall miss his Wife, a Cuckold, o law a Cuckold! ha, ha, ha. [Ex. Laughing. Gen. Now nothing sere can cross me, this night I Hull en- joy Eudoria and revcll in the pleasures of her Love, what will Sir Arthur fay u hen he shall miss his Wife? he can but vex or peihaps hang himself, let him doeither, all's one to me so I but enjoy his Wife. Enter Arthur, bringing in Eudoria in a Night- gown Masked. Arth. I have her, I sack Sir Generall I have} poor foul ho.v she shakes, come, come Madam fear nothing, Sir Generall is a pleasant Wag, he is indeed a very pleasant Wag 5 and I dare say loves you with his heart, truely he does, Lord lord, how flic tran- 1
Page 32

3 2 lUe AdiHUitKgyujtice, or, transports me! I am in love with her too , and methinks I could but let that alone, let that alone. Gctr. Pardon me Madam, the great desire I had to sec you hi fore I went from / ondon, made me lb importunate. Art h. You are not, indeed you are not, what importunate? no, no, no , Sir General! loves to Complement, he docs in- deed, hut conic let's goe, I sack we must drink before we Ger. N.n, now the Rascall's troublesome. Arth. Come Mr. Amorous, what at a stand? come follow me, I'll lead you to a Glass of the best Tent in London, I will indeed, a glals of that, and half a dozen Eggs will make me as vigorous av a Lover of Eighteen, it will indeed. [Exeunt. Enter Emelia .i»d Flora. En/e. W here is Sir Arthur? Flor. Gone out, but where, I know not. Ewe. If he stay abroad but long enough Vis well. Flor. Pray Sister what do you intend to doe with Sir Geojjry? Ewes. What? make an Ass of him. I'll help his zeal to a Mi- strifs, and (it him to a hair I'll warrant him. Flor. Whv, will you let him in } Ex/el. Yes, aud conduct him to our Masking Room, where by the help of the Trap-doors I doubt not to effect what I de- sire: I have already prepared our Scullion, who when the Can- dle isout, shall enter for a woman and perform my part, he is shaved on purpose, and I do not fear but he wist banter him bravely. Flor. He comes to me to morrow, if the affront you put up- on him dash not all his hopes. Ewel. That you must lalve again, by railing at me for the in- jury I did to Sir Geojsry; for his part he is lb good natur'd heel soon believe you. Elor. I would not lose the Opportunity for all ray hopes of marriage. Ewel. Sister it grows late, within this half hour I expect him. Flor. Let us part then. Pray Heaven the Lecher comes. Emel. Nothing more sore, be near to fee th event. Flor. 1ll warrant you. f Exeunt.
Page 33

lealou4 Husbands, SCENE A Tavern. Eater Sir General Amorous, and Sir Arthur Twilight, Leading Eudoria masl(d. Arth. Come, coine, Madam, you arc so melancholy, so a'! a rnort: Sir Genera!, pray come and comfort the Lady. Get/. Sir Arthur, I must beg you to officiate my place foi a minute, whilest I go down and dispatch a little bulinels. I lu//General Amorous. Arth. Blest Oppoitunity! she is right l 11 wariant her, or el(ii (lie would not leave her Husband to run away with a G •!'.. .«, but it is common i'sack, very common. Come Lady let us litdow n together, you look lo like my Wife that I could eat you, nay come, thisco) ness not becomes you.— [_Eudoria (its at i diji.ittt». Nearer a little, nearer yet, let me, let me feel your hand ;, a delicate (oft moist palm upon my w ord; very good symptoms indeed, let me see, good breasts too, Lord , Lord, how she. charms me! nearer yet dear Lady, she is a delicate Creature, and has all the symptoms of a Miss about her. Fray Madam off with your mask, that base injurious thing— ("Eudoria points to theCnndlc.~\ Ha! put out the Candle? I understand her mean- ing, i'sack I do. [Puts out the Candle. Eudoria fleals out. Now Madam I have perform'd your orders, I hope you will al- low me the honour of your Lip, your cherry Lip, your robe Cheeks, your dainty Teeth, your soft moist Palm, but here's enough of that 5 come dear Lady let us hug one another , nay you (hall not deny me, you know I know you, come little Wag, you know I do;, what, keep from your friend and servant) nay,, nay, if you arc tun into a cornet I'll after you, i'faith I will. [_ Gropes to find her out, and falls over the jiooles. Enter Petulant Easy. Easy. Thus far I have dogd Sir General, and was inform d be- low, he and a Lady were above together, which if I sind, and see apparent rallhood in the man I love^l'll study for revenge, and iii.his death blot oujtmy shame jjor ever.Ja; ib;;,V ".. .. . J .vv ': . ... " j _ >
Page 34

34 The Rambling Juftice, or, Arlh. Madam, dear Madam, nay now you arc unkind, indeed you arc Lady, dear Lady. 5 Gropes about, at length fit- l zes Petulant Easy. Ha, have I caught you Wap;, ha? come, come, let us solace our (llves, let us enjoy one another, come, come, I am ready again, I am indeed, the tall did not hindermuch. Eas'. What are you Sir? Arlh. A man, a man, a vigourous old man i sack , come, come, EjJ). You are mistaken in the woman lure. Arth. No but I am not, these soft moilt hands are agood sign, i'faith they are. Easy. A sign of what Sir? Arth. A stirring, brisk, airy, lively, sprightly woman } one that will kitsand hug, and hug and kiss, and kiss and hug to a miracle i'faith. Easy. Nay if you are rude Til leave you. Arth. But you shall not, come, come, be pliant, Sir Amorous will be here presently, and then our sport is spoil'd, come,come, dear Lady. \_Embrases her cbje. Enter Drawer with a Light. Draw. Shift for your self, or you're undone lor ever, Con- tentious Surly is below, m such a rage, as if the Spaxijh Devil Jealousy were dancing in his eyes * he swears he dog'd you hi- ther, and nothing can satisfie him but search the house he musL Arth. Surly below ? O law, what's to be done now> Draw. Here, here, into this Closet, if he should chance to rake you 'twill bebut as a jeast. Arth. Make hast, make hast, would it were over once. CEafy and Sir Arthur enter into the Closet, the (Drawer locks *be door and Exit. 'Enter Contentious Surly with a Light. Surly. Odamn'd Creature! can nothing keep her honest? [_ Lookt about the Stage. Not here, the jiking Quean has tricks, and shifts her shape a* often as a Witch, she's hereto certain, and must not scape my Inquisition. Breaks open the Closet. Ha!

Page 35

The Jealous Husbands. Ha! have I sound you Madam? and you lecherous Sir? come out ye pair of sinners, and let the world be witness of my flume. [Sir Arthur and Easy come out. E.isy. What shame, to be in a Closet with an old man alone? is that your wonder Sir? nay with such an old man as has no- thing but delire about him. Arth. Not I by Heaven, I am an Eunuch Sir. Surly. You are a Devil Sir, a Goatish Devil; and were it nor for the respect I have to your black souls, which I would not take so unprepared , Vac lend you both to Hell immedi- ately. Easy. Do hasty Husband, I dare you do your utmost '., strike, 'tis a woman bids you, where is your fury now? if you have any I'll raise it to a pitch, and leave you in the height on'r. Know I hate thee, and all thy surly humours, and will never be slave to a Jealous Husband more. Farewell, it you dare see the Monster, I will make you home to your Glass and view your self. f, Exit Easy. Surly. Brave, I am a Beast all over, a publick noted Beast, and she a Devil, howe're she shall not "scape me. [Exit Surly. Arthur. If this be the effects of whoring,! have done with it: pray Heaven Eudoria hear not of it. Enter Drawer. Where is Sir General Amorous .<? Draw. He and the Lady you brought in just now took Coach together. , Arth. The Lady, what Lady?! Draw. The Lady in the Night-gown. Arth. Was there a Lady besides EaJ) then? Draw. Yes, a delicate sweet Creature, much like your Wife. Arth. How? my Wife, my Wife? by Heaven it may be so in- deed! I have a strong suspicion for it, I shall run mad, mad, shirk mad 5 my Wife, my Wife, my Wise, I ama Cuckold, I am, lam, I am indeed, a damn d procuring Cuckold. s_ Exeunt. SCENE
Page 36

5 6 The R ambling Justice> or, SCENE Sir Arthur'* House. Enter Sir Geoffry Jolthcad, Iil^c a Qu.tkcr. Geoff. I nm transformed, I am another Creature, and have? the tore of the Brethren, pray Heaven I may have the success too, but not to be tols'd out of a Balcony :that is Emclias Chamber, I rind it by the Light, now to my sign, Hum, 1mm. Enter Emelia above. E/ml. Who's there? Geoff. Thy BrotherZachariah, who. desires to meet thee in the way of the FaithfurK \imcl. I will descend, thy presence is most gratefull. [, Exit Above. Gaff. Now fora night of pleasure, i'sairh it will fast trie swee- ter, because we act like Brethren: Oh those dear debnuch'd Bre- thren! how many merry nights they spend with a Go in, In- crease, and Multiply. Enter Emelia. Eme!. Enter Zachariahf thou hast a Sister's leave. Geoff. And I will perform the part of a Holy Brother. \_Exc/v;U Enter Sir Arthur Twilight. Arth. Eudoria, Wise Eudoria I fay, what out of doors at this time } where (hall I leek this Gad-fly? why Wife l fay : flits gone, stie's gone, a pox of the Salutation Tfveftr, flics gone with Sir Amorous, I rind-she is, a Coach, a Coach, a Coach, a hundred pound for a Coach. Enter SpywelJ. Spy. That was Sir Arthurs voice, now to my posture. Con- fusion take me if e're I serve again. [_ Runs against Sir Arthur. Arth. Who's there? Spy. One that resolves never to serve a Rambling man again.
Page 37

The Jealous kimi>ands. 5 Spy. Yes. a common Whoremaster? no longer agoe than this Evenina he run away with a very Worthy Centlcroans Wife. Arth. Ha! did he so, did he so, what Gentle-nan, friend? Spy. A very Worthy man indeed, one Sir Arthur Twilight. Arth. Confusion! I am the Cuckold then [_ Aside. Spy. But were 1 he, I w ould — Arth. What? Spy. In some disguise (larch out the Lecherous goat, and damn 'em both together. Arth. Ay, ay, but what disguise? Spy. They now are at the Role, drinking, carrowsing, and in a height of Jollity \ but would he goe guisa like an old tidler, and take his man in a strange habit with him , he might perhaps revenge, and keep himself fiom being made a Cuckold. Arth.. He might indeed, he stull about it (freight $ thanks. honest Friend, he thall about it presently. \_Ex. Sir Arthur. Spy. This will be Mirth to Admiration: I could cen hug my self to think upon the Credulous fool, I must not lose him though. The bliss of Life whilst Mars and Venus rules Is to project for Will-men, Cuckold Fools. [Exit. SCENE A Chamber. Sir Geossry jolthead and Emelia arc discovered unbracing. Eme. Nay, you arc too vigorous, ^ Brother. Gco f. My Zeal is hot, I am inflam'd, my Spirits are on fire. Enic. After our Ceremonies arc perform d, we will like holy Brethren meet and love together. y .aun H s' First with this Powder I'll perfume your Face, Then with this Band your tender Wrists Embrace. Well scented thus with all your Vigour move, Turn three times round, and then enjoy your Love*. < Blasts hi* Face, and tics his Hands behind kiw^ \ then puts oxt the Candle and.Exit. lExH. tits are on
Page 38

w JxamblitJg Jnjtice, or, Enter an Old man drejl about the head like a Woman. Geoff! I come, I come, I come, this is one of the prettiest devices in the whole Creation. Madam, Lady Emelia, what not answer me? Nay then i'faith have at you, I am old Dog at BufT; I could play at Blind-mans Buff sRunr againjt jome- naturally, ha, that was a fliroad Mistake. \ thing and breads Why Ladv, dear little Rogue } where \ the firing th.it are you^a? there I touch'd you;,faith have (bound his Hands. I got you, have I, have I? nay now I will make you kiss me, and hug me, and imbrace me, and O my dear little Rogue. C Having caught the Old man , he Kisses and < Embraces him till a Table with two Candles (_ upon it rises. Blek me! what have I got here? Old man. Nothing but an Old man indeed Sir. Geoff. An Old Devil are you not? begon Wizard or I'll make you j Kic^s the Old man off, returns again, and is let I down under the Stage. O Devil, Devil, Devil! Whither am I going now? help, help, help. SCENE Covent Garden. Enter Sir Arthur Twilight with a Cymball, and Bramble with a Violin, both difguis'd. Art h. Come Bramble, we shall find her anon I am sure ont. Bramb. Would we could Master, for I am half afraid to walk abroad to late. Arth. No danger, no danger Bramble: O that we could but sind em, I would Roguefy my Amorous Gentleman, i'fack I Would. \_MH$t\*nd a Noije of Singing as in the Streets. Bramb. Ha, the Roaring Boys are abroad Master, and if we stay here any longer we shall be kill'd for certain. [_ALi(uk and Singing again as nearer. Arth. They are coming indeed, they ave near us now, what shall we doe Branbk't O here's honest %we//. Enter

Page 39

The Jealow Husbands. 39 Enter Spy well n.ith a Light. Spy. So so you're well disguis'd. Now, now Sir is your time \ Sir Qencr.il/ Amorous and your Wife are enteredt here, therein that publiek Tavern, they've lent to lee for Muilck : now if you dare venture to pals amongst the Gang, I willconduct you to 'em. Arth. With all my heart, Oh I long to see 'em. Spy. Where taken for Musicians, you may stand unsuspected, and behold all their Transactions. Arth. Make hast, make hast, Ohow I long to lee 'em! [^Exeunt. Manet Spy we!!. Spy. Which you soall do, doubt nor, and fuller for v our Cu- riosity. Rats'd to a heights he from the top flj.ill fly To ferijh by his Rage and JealoHjy. The End of the Third AU. ACT IV. SCENE 7be Streets. Enter Sir Geoffry Johhead. GeoJs.T Am out again, thanks to my good fortune: if this be J Love and Enjoyment, the Devil take it for me; 'twas twenty to one I had not broke ray Neck when I fell into the Cellar, my Mistress Emclia was a little civill I confess to leave a Light below,, otherwise I might have slept amongst the hogsheads : I have lost all my stomach to Woman* flesti, and (hall never have a good opinion of the Sex as long as I live again. Enter Twisord. Tveis. My Lord your servant, I vow I am extream glad to you, your Honourable Cousins are all in good health, and

Page 40

40 The Rambling Jud ice, or, every thing poes extraordinarily well indeed. I just now came from Frante, and tnicly even' thing there is in a very good posture: his most Christian Majesty would tain have laid his Commands upon me to have been \ttsGcner.ililjimo, but I hear- ing the English Drums beat up tor Volunteers, came to pay my Rclpects to my very good Friend and Cousin, and to serve un- der the nol.1. Banner o£ England. Geoff. \\ hat a Pox i^ the meaning of this? . Tins. My ford I cannot but commend your meen and garb, upon my honour you are all over very charming, and look like one of the honourable family of the Soft-heads, I hope my Cou- sin Richard, and his extraordinary obliging friend Thomas are in parted health. Gnnl'. Yea Sir. What a pox ails he? \,Afidc. Tu rf And my Lady Grace, and Madam" Pru, and that ex- tream obliging Lady Madam Text, I vow I long to see e'm, but my extraordinary business in Town, has hindred me from their Society. W hy Ill tell you Cousin, I am just now going to serenade Madam Emclia, upon my honour she's sort ob- leigant. Geoff". She is all abomination, and musick is the wind-pipe of Lucifer. Twif. But mark you Cousin, mine is no wind musick, sirst, here is a Tin Pot, which besides its excellent vertucs of making a de- licious, sweet, charming, melodious sound, serves at a tnife to think out of; then hert is ah Extinguisher, and here a Drum- stick, all which meeting together, make an excellent harmonv^ you shall hear it Cousirt,s_^/j/J us on hisPot,andsings ridicvbujly. Geoff'. A vane Satan, these arc not the Devices of the Brethi en, be gone ivith your Gakmofry of Noises, or 1 shall rebuke thee, mark you s .• Tnrjf. How do you like the musick, ray Lord? Geoff} Be gone I say, you, disturb the ears of the faithfull. Trcrf. ButCousio. : :a i V ' , wV , Geoff. 1 will not heat thee, vanish thou fi<n us PetoLtfusl or look you, thus I will force? you. [ Pushes him off. Treif. But ray Lord, nay Cousin, my Lord, I fay-: [Exit.
Page 41

he fcaiom tnusuanas. 4* Enter Contentious Surly. Surly. She has seap'd my rage again, and unlcsi (he beat home I know not where to seek her. * f, Knock. y . Geoff. What lewd disturber is that > Surly. 'Sdeath hold thy tongue. f, Knocks again. Geoff. I lay thou hast evil intentions, and designest to rob the house of mv friend. Surly. Thy friend! who art thou? Geoff. A faithfull Brother, by Name Geeff.iu*, Zjchjrus Jolt. Surly. Strange! I should know that voice , are you Sir Geoffry j? Geoff. Yea, I am the man, now tell me, who art thou? Surly. My name's Contentious Surly. Geoff. The Devil it is? what my good Friend and Landlord 't i'faith I have been frolicking of it to night, I have i'faith : and how goes squares with thee, ha boy? Surly. Faith cross, extreamly cross, my Wife has given me two flips for a Teaster, and is run the Devil knows whither. Geoff That's sine i'faith 5 would I could meet her, flie kisses smartly, and has the Town ways to a hair i'faith. [Aside. Is she not at home t Surly. That's all the hope remains. Geoff. Let's knock and enter, if they refuse break open the doors. Surly. Agreed. C S\\x\y k*>ockj a good while, at \Jength breaks open the doors. Geoff. That's well said i'faith, enter and search, we shall sind her in a corner. {Exeunt. SCENE A Tavc Enter SirGeneral Amorous, Eudoria and Spy well. Gen. Is all prepar'd? Spy. All's in a readiness to entertain Sir Arthur, Gen. Then let in the Masquerading Ladies,and bid the Fidlers approach. f, Exit Spy well. G Come
Page 42

42 The K ambling jnjticey or, Come Madam, on with your Mask, to night we will enjoy our loves without disturbance, and smile upon the Jealous Fool thy Husband, whose curiosity shall lead him to his ruine. End. I fear hee l know me. Gen. Let him, he shall not dare to touch you, nor ga/e up- on you with the eyes of anger: to animate his rage chuse him out to Dance with you, I have ordered another to make choice of Bramble, who will also at the appointed time leave him with his Credulous Master, and both shall be convey'd Ib great a di- stance from us, that scarce his cries shall enter to disturb our joys. End. I'm too hard hearted to a jealous Husband. Gen. Would you be kind to him and mine me? would you destroy me on the virge of bliss, or kill what you have made > T Ihouldnot urge had you content at home, but being rob d of such a weighty blessing, and made a starveling to the joys of Wedlock, I come with real and hearty zeals, to give you those pleasures his Age and Impotence deny'd. Eutl. I'm too far entred now to make retreat without the lols of Honour, I must be yours for ever 5 but use me kindly, lest the strange surprize should kill my blooming hopes. Enter Spywell with Fidlers and Ladies, amongji whom are Sir Arthur, Bramble and Petulant Easy dijguis'd, all the men and women are maskjd but the Fidlers. Spy. Come, Come Gentlemen, strike up, and let the musick of the Sphcars speak loud, whilest they employ their feet in Dan- cing Measures. /-Eudoria and a Lady go to take out Sir Arthur \ ind Bramble, veho deny a great while, but at .I length yield and join with them. A Dance. All /Dance off but Sir Arthur, Spywell, Bramble, ^•and Easy, wheall continue dancing but Easy. Easy. Tis she, I know it5 persidious man you shall not scape my fury, must I be thus rewarded for my Favours, and not stu- dy a requital? rise up black revenge, and teach me to be cruel 3 teach me to act as bloody Nero did, that in my height of love and vengeance I may damn both, both their black fouls toge- ther. [Ex7* EaTy. They cease Dancing. Art h.'
Page 43

be Jealous Husbancls. Spy. Yes, yes Sir, come hither, both direct your eyes that way, and there behold what would confound a man not ai md with so much reason What see you Sir? Arth. Nothing. Spy. Nor you } Bram. Not I by Jove. Spy. Look, look, I see'em kissing, there, there, like wantoii Turtles they're billing both together. Arth. Where, where? (S/y. There, there, j Stamps, Sir Arthur and Bramble are let c down under the Stage, they cry help. Now you are safe enough, and sceur'd from all disturbance; and Sir General Amorous may now in peace enjoy the fair Endo- ria v all the reward I hope for is success. Projecting is my ge- nuine Mistress, and in my brain I lodge the loft Belovd, and treat her minutely with pleasing Embryo's, which by the mode- rate heat of smooth desires, are lull'd into perfections, which at once create and give me pleasures. These harmless plots perhaps may seem unjust, But when such loads you adde to one man's trust, Blame not projections if they onely prove A Servants care t'obtain a Masters love. [, Exit. SCENE A Be J. chamber. Sir General Amorous and Eudoria arc discovered fitting by the Bed fide. Gen. Come blush nomore, I am thy Husband now, and with a Passion more innate then his,I will exhilirate thy soul,and lead thy senses in a Sea of pleasures, where, arm in arm, wee'l wan- ton 'twixt the Waves, and every minute sind new pastimes our, revel in joys of uncontroul'd delights, and dwell forever in this bright Elysium. End. You've nam'd a word which bates me of my hopes, and dashes all those thoughts I just now dream't of Gen. It fliall be banish'd quite, orlikeafoyle stand still to heighten pleasure, what was't Endoria? End. Nothing but Husband Sir: that very word curbs all my joys, and prompts me to a sense, that all's imaginary. v~ G 2 Gctr.
Page 44

h Rambling Justice, or, Gen. What frown of fate can take you from my bosome, or rou me of the treasure I embrace > Enter Spy well. y%. Sir I have done the woik. Gen. Is he si se? Spy. As a thief in a mill, ne'r fear it } but here's one danger yet tmconciuer'd, the jealous Ei/)', who (*\t Items mistrusting you were here) came as a Mafquerader, and after the dance, followed you and Endorij, and had doubt left iurpriz'd you here, but that the Di\wtr by meer force kept her back. Gen. What, rr.ust I be prevented thtn? Spy. Sir you had bell go and appease her rage, perhaps file 1 near your reasons. Gen. 1 will, but v\ ith a curse able enough to damn her. f_ Exeunt. Minet Eudoria. Enter Petulant Eat).. Eisy. Where's this.unconstant man, and this false treacherous Woman? Oh let my anger meet 'em both, and in one breath confound 'em. End. What's this > E iJ). Nothing lascivious Lady but the force of love, and you if you had any grace might think it so, how durst you look upon that faithless man, or entertain the least thoughts of such a loose desire, and not tremble? I am all fury, and could shoot such killing glances on you, which would (but you're sopractis'd in the art already) reduce you to a heap of earth again. Bale treacherous woman! End. I understand you not. Ejjy. Then 111 be plainer, you are a End. Woman, and so are you, both married women too, and love Sir General both. Easy. Your Husband (hall know all. End. So stiall Contentions too: but talk is frivolous, and may perhaps hinder a new appointment. Farewell. QEa//Eudoria. Ejjy. Brave! the has impudence enough to stock the Sex in general. How shall I be reveng d? Ml haste to find Sir Arthur, tell him her crimes, and urge him to revenge. Thus to be slighted, now I all have giv'n, Calls tor confulion,and revenge from Heav'n.
Page 45

e sea km Husbands. 45 SCENE The Stnets. Enter Contentious Sui ly, and SirGcoffry Jolt. Geoff. Nay, nay, be patient man, what! set for the loss ofa woman } one that loves pleasure? pox on her let her go, let her go, you and I will to a Bawdy house, ar.d there solace our selves, ha ? lhall we boy, ha? Surly. No Sir. Ga ff. What not to a Bawdy house? let's to a Tavern then, drink and be drunk, and kiss every woman we meet. Surly. I am not given to the Flesh so much Sir. Geoff. Nor I neither, but I do it in revenge, f will lye with twenty women successively, and all to be reveng'd osone } but , thou hast a Wise. Surly. Damnation seize her, why should losall the world be made so wretched? why should mv sate be ib severe, so cruel? No one can lee I am a Cuckold, but I know I am, there, there s the plague on't. Enter Flora masked. Flo. I cannot sleep to night for thinking on Sir Geojjry, oh how I long to see him ! the great affront my Sister put upon him, I sear will keep him from me, which makes me venture at this un- seasonable hour to find him out, and wheadle him into a strange belief of my affection: ha !—yonder he is, now to be taken notice of f_ Puts on her m.ixI^, and pijfes over the Stage. Geoff. Ha! are you there, are you there i'faith i} blest Moon- shine! I have discovered a Lady, a Night-walker upon my life. I'll after her. . [ Exit Geosfry. Surly. How shall I find her out ? which way contrive to rcvc 1 in revenge? Sir General Amorous is the man that wrongs me, and on him 111 pour my indignation: but how the Devil came Sir Arthur and she lock'd up in the Closet together >. how? why she's common and sond of all the world : he, he shall suffer too, but in a different way, the one shall die, and the other be made as monstrous as I am. [Exit. ■ ■ C 3 Enter
Page 46

ne Hamming jujtice, or, Enter Flora massed. Sir Geoffry so Homing, seize t her. Geoff*. Nay little Rogue, i'faith you (hall not scape me; twould be unkindly clone to let you go alone, Ib early in the morning too, come, come, let me see you home to your lodg- ing little Wag. Flor. I beg your pardon Sir, I do not use it. Geoff. What! not your lodging Rogue? let's to a Tavern then, where weed drink and be lo merry, ib jocott and pleasant, and lulb and hug, and love one another. Flo. Who are you Sir } Geoff. A Country Magistrate, Lady, one that doats upon wo- man;; flesh, a very Cully, believe me Madam. Flo. You'l pawn me Sir. Geoff'. Not I by Jove, what, pawn a pretty Lady } that were unkind indeed; I may be frolickibme or so, but i'faith I will not pawn y"bn. Flo. I dare not venture to a Tavern Sir. Geoff. Let's to thy Lodging then , all's one to me , here, here's the tempting Angels, all this for a night* lodging I Gad: now lam all vigor, and (hall I, hah? little Rogue (hall I? Flo. If you l be kind. Geoff. As a Lover can be, thou (halt have Gloves, and Fans, ami Muffs, and Ribbands, and Flo. A Monky too. Geoff. Yes, yes, a great Baboon, come, come, let's go. Flo. You have such taking ways. Gaff'. Aud so have you i'faith. Here s one of my twenty that's certain. f, Exeunt. SCENE Covent Garden. Enter two Sedan-men bringing Sir Arthur Twilight in Bramble'/ cloaths, and Bramble in Sir Arthur'/ t haths, hound and gag d in a Sedan. 1. Sed. Pox on'em, they're cursed heavy. 2. Sed. Full of sin, full of sin Brother ^ but let's set em down here in the Piazza s, and go and take a cherishing cup this
Page 47

/ be Jealom tins bands. 47 . 1. Scd. Agreed, but I am afraid it is too early. 2. Scd. No, no, no, they are up at the King s-head T\\ war- rant you. [Exeunt Sedan-men. Sir Arthur dud Bramble come out of the Sedan. Enter Contentious Surly. Surly. Gone from thence too? She is a Necromancer that''• certain, and has a Legion of Devils to attend her. What have we here, Sir Arthur Twilights and his Honourable servant Bramble} they are in a pretty Posture too, and stand seasonably for a beating, which that old Lecher (hall not want \ this for Bellowing the name Cuckold in my Ears',—and all these for being lock'd up with my Wife. And 16 farewell Sir. [Beats Bramble and Exit. Enter Petulant Easy. E.ifi'. O that I could but sind Sir Arthur now to tell him all the story of his Wife, and pour into his Ears the strongest Venome that ever Poysoned man; and here he is, most happy opportunity. I'm sorry Sir, that I lhould be the Messenger ot liich ill news, as I am fore'd to tell you; but when a man is Married to a Wife, false* and unconstant, one all desires, and greedy after Pleasures, one that shall force a man to her Em- braces, and hug him with a Zeal what, not answer me? [_ Bramble makes a Noise. Alas Poor man, this was Eudorias Plot, her loose Contrivance, is t not enough to wrong her Husbands Bed, but slie must ieive him so, make him the Scoff, and Scorn of all the World? [sUn binds Bramble, he ungags himself Br.imb. Thank you Madam, this is the first kindness I ever, received of a Woman in my life. Easy. Are you not Sir Arthur then } Eramb. No, but I am his Man, and that's as good. Easy. Where is your Master? Qramb. There stands the Worshipfull Gentleman, you ma/ be kind and release him if you please : jEasy goes and unbinds this is the fruits of Eidling and Horn- \ Sir Arthur, hunting with a Pox, but if ever you take me in a Dilguilc again, I'll give you leave to hang me. Pox of Surlys blows, they
Page 48

j^anwiingyujtice, or, they were very unwelcome to me because they were meant to my Master. Arth. Madam, I can but thank you for my liberty: it was a severe Torment, it was indeed. Easy. But who transforms you thus? Arth. I'faith I know not. Bralf'!>. Two Devils I think, they were disguis'd I'm sure. Easy. Were I so injur'd, nothing should keep me from Re- venge. Arth. Ha! what said you there, Revenge? I'sack I long to be reveng'd, but how? Etsy. The Cure must needs be dangerous, when the Disease rages with so much violence you are not unsenlible you are a Cuckold } Arth. Ha> Eas<. Wonder not at it, for you're so that's certain, I saw 'cm both folded like Twins together, destilling Killes, inter- mixing Glances, and with a Rapture unexpreilible, dissolve into a show re. Arth. A Cuckold? Easy. I heard her boast, and glory in his Love, repeat the numbers of his Obligations, count o're his Charms in such a wanton Dialect, as would almost intice a Saint to fin. Arth. A Cuckold, O Confusion! EaJ). Then being tyr'd and glutted with Excess, repeat the pleasures of her stoln Delights, whilst her Lascivious Ears suck'd in the sound, that every Sense might have an equall share. Arth. No more, no more, no more. Death no more. Easy. Sometimes she'd with a scornfull smile call on your name, and say Alas poor Sir Arthur, poor decrepit Cuckold. Arth. Cuckold again! no more, no more, sweet Lady have you done? Easy. If it offend I have. Arth. Why, do you think it pleases, a Cuckold, a horrid, nay a known Cuckold too? I will be reveng'd that's certain, nay swindginly reveng'd, a Cuckold? O horrid! come along Bramble. [_Exennt, manet Easy. Easy. He's fir'd, and notliing sore can quench him, but the removall of his Wife Eudoria^ then I shall enjoy his Love in Peace, and fiar nc other Rivall j yet there's one danger still, a Jea-
Page 49

ealons tins bands. 49 a Jealous Husband, he shall bz remov'd tor>, they are not sir to live who hourly strive to curb a Worruns Joys, I will about it present! v. [Exit. Enter Twiford talking to tiro Eink^hoys. Tins. Truly every thing is very considerably well, and my Honourable Lord is in a delicate pleasing humour, and my Lady is—but as I was telling you my Lords, about the Play. J just now came from the Kings house, and truly every thing is very considerably well: and trnlv I doubt rot but to make .1 considerable advantage of the Comedy; for I have very conli. derably insinuated my self into the opinion of the Leading Wits, . and I have their \_The Linl{-boys sneak, off'. promise for applause, for indeed my Lord they know me for a Wit, and were extraordinarily pleas'd with my Heroick Poem call'd The Mm os Ncw.Mirl{ct, and lb forth; but let that pals, my Lords I see you do not regard me , and sleep is very neces fjry for a Poet, and so good night my Lords. < Enters into the 1 Sedan. Enter Petulant Easy. Easy. I am hem'd about on all sides, and cannot scape the Watch, what (hall I do for lhelter till the Day breaks or the Clutches of the Parish are rctir'd, ha ! what's there, a Sedan, and no body near it } [A Noise' as of the M jtch. Hark! the VVatch are coming, 1 11 enter there and secure my self, [ Noise again. There's a man in it, what shall I do now . [Noise again. I must enter were he a Devil, till the Watch is pair.. [Enters into the Sedan and fonts she door. Enter the two Sedan-men. 2. Sed. Pox on't, there's no Drink to be got, 1 think iis searce two. 1. Sed. Let it be scarce one an't will, I care not, for I am devilish dry. 2. Sed. So am I too, but come, let us up with our load, by that time we have drop't them in the Fields it will b^ day. f They talc up the Sedatt. Enter
Page 50

50 The Rambling Justice, or, Exler Contentious Surly, Constable and Watchmen. Const. Stand, who goes there? i. >SV.7. friends. tonst. V\ ho h ive von in vour Sedan? I . Ssd. No body, Mt. Co ■ftible. Surly. S...uch, rt.aich the Sedan, Mr. Cutrjhbk, \h twenty to ort. hut U r:x N'ght.walking Lady or other is in it. o../. i?;. \\ idi e.il our hearts, there it \ icaveh your Eyes out. s '■ I hist the;. .ire p/j. ng the Sedan, tic men % jnc.i/^ .nr.ij. The ^edan being opened dif- C covers Twiibid embracing Easy. C <?ll/?. What 16 close together? come out, come out I pray. (_ D&f/ r<ww cv.'/. .W/i. Death my Wife! and with a Mad.man loo, this is in- fuffcrablc} I am g!ad1 have found your Ladifliip, would your Honour be conducted home in a Sedan? you lhall be Sedan'd with a pox. Mr. Constable pray give me leave to secure this La- dy, upon my word the shall appear at the fhst summons. Const. Do you know her Sir? Surly. Too well, l wish 1 did not, (he IS my Wise. Const. You have Liberty. Surly. Come Minion will you walk? Ill secure you for gad- ding 111 warrant you. [^Pnfk's her out before him. Const. Stay, stay, what are you? [Twtfoxd offers to goe. Trvif. Truly my Honourable Lord is very well, and as I told you the flay will take. Const. What's all this to me? Who are you I fay? Trvif. As I was laying, Lewis the 14th. is a brave Prince, and a very considerable Souldier^ why look you Coz, this Ring was given me by Madam Buly, file is a very Honourable Lady, and takes much pains for the Publick. Const. Tell not me of Publicks, but give me an account, what are you? Tn.if. Very considerably well indeed, and every thing is in a very good method, and— ■ [_Sings Plays upon his Pots. Const. Watchmen away with him, he isa suspicious Person. Twist. Truly Cousin I know nothing of the matter. Const. What matter? Iwif, The very great Affairs of State , and Matters now in Question
Page 51

The Jealous Husbands. Question arc that the People os Stetin are a very Honourable People, and deserve to be a Conji. I care not what they deserve to be, who are you? whence came you > and whither are you going? Twif. Truly my Lord you are verv obliging , but I know nothing of the matter, but my Lord I'll tell you, his Honour— I must beg your pardon Cousin, the good Lord John is ju(t now come to town, and it will be accounted a great piece ot rudeness to be absent, and be so considerably well, your ser- vant Cousin. [ Runs oft. Conji. After him there and seize upon him, I will know what he is before he get his liberty. \,Exotni. SCENE A Bed-chamber. A Table with two Candles and some Books upon it jet upon the Stage. Enter Sir GcolFry Jolt and [. lora massed. Geoff. Now you are kind indeed, I'faith you are 5 come La- dy let us prepare, let us undress, O how I long to be in Bed dear Lady! Flor. Do you begin Sir, Ill but go in and dress my Head, and wait upon you presently. . [_Ex. Flora. Geoff. Pretty Rogue, an excellent Lodging this, this is no Mercenary Mistress. Lord, Lord, the Town Gallants are such conceited Animals, such Fops Alamode, they think no body has the happiness of Enjoying their Ladies but themselves. What's here, a Study? Arijtotlcs Problems, excellent, and here Leschole de Files, a pretty French book and here Annotations upon Aretines Pojlures, three Excellent Books for a Ladies Chamber $ but I am tardy, I stay too long, I should have been in Bed half an hour agoe} O for a week os Nights in One, that I might reap a Hecatoomb of Pleasures who the Devil would marry and run the danger ot being made a Cuckold, when he may live so freely? Come Lady, I am almost unready now, I am almost prepar'd, and could methinks Writer Emelia and Flora. Emel. Good Morrow tweet Sir Gecffry. Flor. Good Morrow credulous Sir Geoffry. H 2 Em.
Page 52

5 2 The Rambli>g Justice, or, Ewel. How did you like the Lady in the Mask.? Flor. Was she r.ot very charming, all Ayre and Convcr- saiion? Ewel. Had she not a sprightly way of Courtship? did she not work you to a height with Ait? F!or. Did flic not (igh, ami (wear she doated on you? long'd to betray her Hoi.our to your Woiship? (a.'//! Held Svrens hold, you've laid erough already. Emd. i\eu to a man ot Learning, a Courtly Magiftiate, one that would keep his Mistress like a Lad} , present her daily with soniL' Tov cn' other, as Muffs. F/or. Fans. Er/i!. Clows. Elor. Kibbandsv Eml. Neckdaces. f lor. Dogs. E.'.id. Nio/ike',«. E!or. And above al!, an Over-grown Baboon, just such ano- ther a; your lusty (Us. (•GeotfiyJpe.iks loud. srojj'. Peace I say, or by my Authority 1 will disturb the Houyc, raise.all the. Seivarts, flight the Watch, amaze the ^ei^hbouis, aid biing a Scandal on you both for ever. Ewes. Do, ar.d we'll declare' your Actions. Flor. Relate your Course of life. (Geoffry fops E'j/ul. Defame your Honour. ( his Ems. , F/or. Scandal your Learning. Em:l. And make your Name. an Antidote, against the plca- 'iugert Thoughts, the belt desiresithat ever Woman had. Qeojs. Have v ou done? have you done now? ye Pair of fte Devils. Elor. Yes, will you be pleas'd to walk Sir? Geojs. Any w here out of your Companies Ladies: may desire .ii.d the want of what you llight so now purlue you ever. h Ex. S/r Gcostiy Jolt. Ewel, Is he gone > Flor. Yes, with an intent never to come again III warrant him. Ewel. Then let's to Bed. t nperfi is Pleasures vebiljl in View they move, Are the Ingenious To)ls of hajiy Love. [ Exeunt. The End of the Fourth Act.
Page 53

The Jealous Hush am ACT V. S C E N E The Struts. Enter Sir General! Amorous, Eudoiia and Spywcll. £W.T"\ Ray H..wen we reach the House before Sii Arthur, I or else my Shame will kill me. Get!. This is the most: dangerous Adventure Love ere thought on, ar.d will J tear end in our ruins; for tis Impossible t' anticipate his hast. End. Fancy not storms before you fee 'cm riling: I am rc- sblv'd cither to save my Honour by this means, or meet my ruin quickly. ( Goes to the Door and unlocks it.'\ Thus far I'm safe, and make no question now but to succeed , farewell. Some two houis hence I ihall be glad to fee you. (Enters and hihj 1 the Door. Gen. What clogged Planet Reign'd at my Nativity! Saturn sure was Lord of the Ascendants I could not else be cioss'd as I have been: twice most willingly she gave Consent I stiould enjoy her Love, and still that Devil Jealousy frustrated all my hopes which like a man drove by one wave a shore, is by ano- ther hurried back again. To love, and not enjoy is but to gaze upon Delicious meat, and have no pow'r to touch it 5 I must goe on. Within this two houis I lhall be glad to fee you? that, that alone, had I not had sufficient Proot before, would have coiKitm'd an Angel. On then to Blijs which well in frivate meet, Where troulles paj} JlxilJ make it tajt more sweet. [ Exeunt. Enter Sir Arthur Twilight and Bramble. Arth. I am out of Breath with lunning, a pox of Matrimony is this be the fruits on't, was ever Gentleman made a Cuckold before? Bramb. Yes Sir, especially Citizens} 'tisan Hereditary posses- sion belonging to the Court of Aldermen, and scarce one scares it, if their W ives arc either Young or Handsome. H 3 Arlh.
Page 54

54 1 be Kamblmg yujrice, ory Art h. I would mine had been neither, I would she had not been a Woman, rather than 1 niould thus be made a Cuckold; but tis done, tis done, I am all over Horns that's certain, and shall be counted a greater Monster than the Elephant. Br.i/uk Tis something severe indeed, but the best is, you are not the first Citizen that has had his Wife run away with a Courtier. Arth. Am I not Sirrah ha? you make a mock of it, do you? Br.ital, No Sir no, I am in earnest. Arth. Are you so Villain, are you so? but on, on, knock at the Door, I long to be fully satisfied, y Bramble knocks at I the Door. Enter Eudoria above in her Night-gown. End. Whos there? Bramb. What's that to you? End. Who are you? Arth. A Friend, a Friend, one that should be Master os this Mouse. End. Who, my Dear Husband? my kind Sir Arthur j? where have you been to Night? Arth. Ha! where have I been to Night? rather Lady where have you been to Night? End. Here, here in my Chamber, rob'd of your sweet society, it was unkindly done.— Art h. It was indeed to run away from your Hu come, come, no more of that, open the Door Lady. End. I ll fly to do it, I am overjoy'd to fee you. f_ Arth. What is the meaning of this? ninth IV to think on't. Bnmb. Nor I neither, I am sure she was at the T Arth. But how came (lie home then? how in' undrest, ha? Bramb. Nay the Devil knows, and he is the best Counseller * Woman has, but this is some trick, some trick upon my life and ten to one Sir General! Amorous is with her. Arth. It is impossible, he went to the Salutation Tavern I am fare, 1 saw him, spoaktohim, and drank with him there. Bramb. All this may be, and yet he be in Bed with your Wife 5 to know which 1 11 go into the Street, some two or three
Page 55

The JealojK Hits bands. 5 5 three doors from the House, and cry, sire, fire, then go to your Back door and watch that, whilst you your His watch this. Arth. This will do, this will do, i'fack haste and about it streight. !,E.v. Bramble. Evtcr Eudoria. Etui. O mv dear Husb.ind! where have you been to Nig,}a' all night abioad at Taverns? rob me ot my Garments and tbt/i run away fiom rae? Alas is this seemly, for a man of your Credit? your Age? and Affection to your Wife? Arth. This is sine i'faith, miraculously fine. :_A'ide.~\ Was not I at home? call'd you like a l oiter? stood under your Window unregarded, was almost mad with fury, and all this but last night, ha? End. Yes Sir, the harmless sleep you broke, and my answer to you would have witue&'d it , if you had had the Patience to have stay'd one minute longer: but your so suddain retreat made me im.igine you were gone with Sir Genera// Amorous that common D. b.mche: keep him not company Dear, he is enough to ruine twenty Aldermen. Arth. Hey day! this is sine indeed: it is impossible she shou'd be honest } and yet the has not the looks of a Sinner neither. [, Bramble within, fire, fire, Sec. End. Ha Fire! I am undone tor ever then. Bram-

Eud. Dear Hulband let s go in iliall be lost for ever else. Arth. Not I by Heav'n, I'll stai Enter Sir Generall Ame Gen. From whence this Dismall Spyvf. I know not Sir. Get/. See it has rais'd my Woi Wsierc is the Fire Sir? Arth. Nay I know not.—Hey stranger still. re the Goods, we 1 to Morrow hist. 1 11 his Wife. day, hey day, stranger and [Aside. I Aside. E'itil
Page 56

56 The Rambling Justice, or, Enter Contentious Surly in a N/ght-goivn. Surly. Good morrow Sir Arthur, 3 0U are Alarm'd by the Noise I fee. Arth. Not much Mr. Surly, I am proof against sire, I am a mcer Salamander, and can live as we ll in the Flame as a Duck, in the Water, — sfoot I know not what to think of this— [Aride. Sir General/, Sir General/, you area Wag, i'sack you are': what stay abroad all Night? come, tell me where were you, indeed von Hull. Gen. Troth Sir at a Tavern about a Mile from hence, v-here after the pleasures of Wine and Mustek, I hoped to en- ioy the Charming Easy, but was hindred by that Jealous Devil . Surly. Anh. Did he hinder you ifack, did he come and take v ou } Gen. ]uft in the nick by Heav'n. Arth. It was ten thousand pities, it was indeed, you lost a delicate Night on e, i'fack I am sorry for it: what, hindred of a Night? Gen. 'Twas mv ill fortune Sir, but we Ihall meet again. Arth. I II do my best to help you, I will indeed, where's your Man? Gen. There Sir. Anh. He looks clouded methinks. Gen. A little Sir, for want of Rest, he's a most faithful] Ser- vant. Arth, A brave contriver I'll warrant him. Gen. How to get Drunk that's all : he roul'd last night just •ike a Bowl ill byas'd, and slept in every Corner. Arth. This is miraculous! I find I have abused my Wife al! r'iis while, and been Jealous for nothing? 1 am glad it is no worse though. O Villain! Monster that I was! how have 'abus'd my self! He with Eisy ? and his man asleep in every Coiner? this is strange indeed. [Aside. Pardon me Eudorix for leaving the Window so hastily, for my iuddain Jealousy transfer'd me 5 I will lay no more but this, \ will not indeed, Dear Wife I suspected thee. End. How, did you suspect me? Arth.
Page 57

The Jealous Husbands. Arth. Talknomore of it, I did indeed, and am asham'd to own it5 come, come, wee 1 in, and every morning on my knees I'll beg a pardon from thee. Enter Bramble. Brant. He is not come out Sir. Arth. No matter, no matter, all's well again, I cm Sir Arthur again, the brbk, bonny, and the merry Sir Arthur again, ha Surly. Where's the Fire Bramble? Bram. Fire? what Fire > was there any Fire? Gen. 1 heard em cry Fire. Surly. And so did I. End. And L Bram. Meer fancy, meer fancy, there is not a spark of fire in the whole City. Surly. Then I'll to Bed again, good morrow Sir Arthur. Arth. Nay Mr. Surly we will not part so, what, part with dry lips? out upon'r, come, come, wee'l go into my House, and drink a Glass or two, and then part to our Beds j come Sir Ge- neral. [ Exeunt. Enter Sir Geoffry Jolt Drunks Gcojs. Let it burn on, I have nothingto lay to fire or women, they are both out of my Element, Wine, precious Wine I am for, the bloud of the Grape shall be my Mistriss: I have been damnably affronted by a couple of Jilting Queans already, and it will be hard to bring me into a third Premunire. Where am I? O pretty near home, I find it, this 'tis to have good store of Wine in one s Head j a man reels to his Lodging so decently. [_ Exit Ruling. SCENE ABed-chamber. Easy. N av left t' Enter Petulant Easy. Now I am lost, and hope is fled for ever, there's no Way left t" accomplish my desire, nor how to bring about my wish'd for vengeance } I am a Pris'ner now, confin'd to one I hate above the World, and fore'd to love what I have cause to hate, the treacherous Amorou*, but he is gone, fled to E'nlorn s Bosome, and there is lodg'd a happy loving Guest. I • Enter
Page 58

58 The Rambling fustice, or, Enter Str Geossry Jolt. Geoff. Still, Rill in the reeling posture 5 what ne're leave me? ha, where .im l ? what, in my I. and ladies Chamber ? now if" I had not made .in Oath to the contrary, T would venture to ia- luu hu : pox rwas.i foolish Oath, and ought not to be kept by a person of Honour, (he kisses smartly, that's my comfort. By your leave LaJv, l must have a touch with you. [Tak$s hold of Etfy. Easy. What mean you Sir? G.'off. Nothing but honest) by my Sobriety, you have such a taking way with you, such a delicious turn of the lip, and lb charming a breath, that I am almost ravish d. [ Offers to kiss Easy, she refuses. Nay believe me Lady tis a favour, and ought to be taken so, nay come, come Lady. f_ Puffs Easy. Hi/}. Whither Sir? Geoff. To your Bed. it is a very convenient Utensil, and ought not to stand for a Cypher in a Ladies Chamber, these melting lips Nay by my Hondur, if you arc coy I shall be a De- vil, come, come, be as you should be, a delightful! yielding Female, I am found I'll promise you, you may venture, dear Rogue • R//j. Venture what Sir? Geoff. To add one horn more to your Husband's Forehead, come, come, I know you love to make him a Cuckold. Eas'. A Cuckold Sir? Geoff. Yes, yes a Cuckold , I have made him one my lelf. Easy. How? Geoff. In my sleep Lady, and there I thought you were Co brisk, lo airy, and so charmingj, and if you seem'd to bclb then, I am lin e you cannot chuse but be all pleasure noyv 5 come, dis- patch. Easy. I shall be fore'd to cry a Rape if you provoke me thus. Geoff. With all my heart, who would not venture on a Wo- man lor such a trifle? come along Lady, whilst you cry I'll acs, and then see yvho ll have the best on t. Offers to fora her. Easy. Help, help, a Rape, a Rape. Enter
Page 59

The Jcalom Husbands. Enter Surly. Geojf. Pox what need you baule Co loud, we shall disturb the Neighbours. f, Fere tug Easy jitli. Surly. What means this Rudeness Sir? Geoff. Nothing but Civility by my Honour: meer Pailion by Jove, and who can be angry at a Passion? Surly. It ill becomes you, especially in my House, S'nGcnJfrj. Geojf. Nay is vou are angry I have done, Good tnoriou l andlord, I'll goe to bed and sseep, and Dream, and so forth. [Rv//Gcofhv. Easy. Can you see this and not revenge the Injury? can you behold the honour of your Wise at stake, and not protect her; or at least, not offer todestrov the foul Abuser '* Surly. He's drunk, he's drunk, and knows not what he does. Eafjr. Were it Sir General/, or any other but this Goatilh Geejfrj, you would have entertained a strange Suspicion, and with a Jealousy as unrestrain'd as ever fury could invent, have hunted both to mine, but now Surly. Enough, enough, let this content you, that I ne're before did entertain so fair a thought of Woman as now I do of thee: my foolish Jealous}' still prompted me to think it was im- possible you could be honest , or stand the Tryall of the least Temptation; but now I sind thou hast a secret Virtue, which I will cherish ever: come let> retire. AU Jealous Pangs yon by this Ail remove, And now J st ill renew Dei .tying Love. [_ Exeunt. SCENE Sir Arthm's House. Enter as in a Pafpon Sir Grncrall Amorous, followed r" by Sir Arthur Twilight and Eudorw. Arth. Nay Sir General!, i'faith I am sorry, I am indeed \ what, leave your Friends house for a TriHe? nay sweet Sir Genctaff, 1 am not Jealous now, i flick I am not; dear Wise go to him, perswade the Gentleman, win him again, I shall be distracted if he leave me, to him Dear End. I know 'tis but in vain.
Page 60

60 The Rambling Justice, or, Art h. Nay, nay try him, 'tvvas but a small affront to say I doubted him, or to be Jealous, was it? nay dear sweet Wife perfvvadc him. End. I1l try my power Sir, but I fear th'event. Arth. That's well (aid, kili him into friendship, hug him, do any thing to win him, (but lye with him) and I am satisfy d. Fuel. Prepare a Banquet then to entertain him, and to it in- vite your Worthy friends 5 let it appear as costly as you can for such a little Warning , and I'll try if I can court him to it. Arth. Do, do my little Rogue, and see how I will love you, the Night will come and then,— but tis no matter, thou knowest my meaning [_Ex. Sir Arthur. Gen. Is he gone? End. Safe for an hour, I ll warrant him. Gen. How greedily he hunts his own Destruction, and with a Zeal as eager as our Loves, he strives to haste our Pleasures! End. Let us not lose that time by our neglect Heav'n has Co kindly given. Gen. 'Twere sin to flip the opportunity. Fortune now courts us to a World of Pleasure, and should we slight the Blessing she has given, we might for ever starve and long for Joys, but never more approach em. End. Where shall we goe? Gen. My Chamber is most safe; nay any where as you have chang d his humour, he would mistrust his Eyes I'm sore before you. End. Then let us goe, for fear we are prevented. {Exeunt. Enter Emelia and Flora. Eme. This is a strange alteration, but yesterday my Father was as Jealous as a Husband without Eyes, and as Waspish as an ill pleas'd Bride , and now he is all Mirth and Jollity. Pray Heaven it last. Flor. So fay I, for he just now proffered me a Husband: and if his Jealous Fitt should come again, I might chance to leade Apes in Hell; and that's a Curie too insufferable for me to bear. ryff• Erne. A Husband Flora / who was't? FUr.
Page 61

The Jealous Husbands. 61 Tlor. Mv degraded Magistrate, he tells me he is a man of Vigour, and loves me with an unspeakable flame. Eme. And can you fancy him } Flor. Best of all, for he's not a Wit I can tell you, and those soft headed Husbands are the easiest Creatures to work upon } a Woman may doe what flic pleases, keep a Gallant in Town, or maintain a comely Servant in the Country } who lhall be as proud to effect my Will, as I desirous to command him. Eme. There's danger in em though, besides restraint os Li- berty and Freedome, I hate to be mew'd up in a Country Ca- stle, give me the Matf, or Grays-Inn Walks; and now and then a Play, where a Woman mav receive as much Pleasure by ga- zing on the Gallants of the Town, as you in the Arms of" your Country Magistrate: were I to chule, I de have a General I Lover, one that Courts all, Doats little, aud Enjovs every where. Flor. They are so common, Sister. Ewe. Not as Country Squires: Alas there's a great difference in the men I speak of, One shall pretend he loves you mon- strously, and behind your back cry dam you. A Second court you with Letters, protest he doats upon you, and had rather gaze upon your Eyes, then any she in the whole World be- side 5 and yet the next minute run to a Bawdihouie. A Third comes with that taking Toy call'd Matrimony or Honourable Love, when his whole designe is but to Enjoy you, spend your Portion, and then leave you a Miserable Woman. Flor. You are well vers'd in the distinctions of Men, Sister. Erne. But above all, were I to chuse, give me Sir Genera// Amorous, his Business is writ here, here in his Face j and they are much deceiv'd who think he comes to marry 'em. Enter Sir Arthur Twilight and Bramble. Arth. Are all invited I Bramb. Yes Sir, all you gave order are. Arth. And will they come > Bramb. Doubtless, Sir, they are most there already: here's a Note of their Names. [ Gives Sir Arthur a Note. Arth. Let me see it, let me see it, [Reads. Sir John Twiford? what have I to doe with him? I want no Madmen Sirrah. I 3 Bramb.
Page 62

6 2 The Rambling Justice, or, Bramb. He will not come I'll warrant you, for I told him unless he could produce a new suite os Cloaths, and leave those greasy ones behind him, he could not enter here. Arth. That's pretty well, it is indeed, i sack I like the Jeast: Come Daughters let us go in, my Wife and Guests will stay for me, they will indeed, I long to be amongst em, for I shall be so merry, so Jocost and pleasant, come dear Cirles. [Exeunt. Scene draws and discovers fiated as at a Banquet, iVCenerall Amorous, Eudoria, Contentious Surly , Petulant Easy, and Sir GeotFry Jolt. Enter Sir Arthur Twilight, Emelia, Flora, and Bramble, all rife. Arth. Nay, nay sit down, sit down my Worthy Friends, 1 sack l joy to lee you, why this was kindly done to visit me upon so small a Warning. [Allsit down. Surly. You see we love you Sir. Arth. I hope you do so all, I should be loth to have the hate os any man, I'fack I should, come Gentlemen be merry, let's sing, and dance, and drink, and be jocost, ha? Geoff. Still the Old man by Jupiter, come here's a Health, sis but a frolick, to the most Superannuated Cuckold ia Europe. Arth. Let it go round ITack. End. Fy Sir, there's a Health? I blush to hear it. Arth. But you shall not: what, blush for a trifle? a Cuckold is a Christian, and so we are all I hope: Mr. Surly you are sul- len, dogged, moody, alamort ITack, come here's a Health to the Lord Mayor of London, ha, that was well thought upon ha, was it not, ha? Geoff. You are the lame man still, you are indeed Sir Arthur, I love a man that has no fense of his own Miseries: look, look, my Landlord's dogged, at that name Cuckold, down in the mouth by Jove, but you bear up briskly still ha, let me em- brace thee dear Rogue. [Embraces Sir Arthur. Arth. Look Sir Geoffry, mind that Girle, that little Wag Flora, would she not make a brisk she Magistrate ha, would i lie not ha? Geoff.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 63

Geoff. Yes Sir, yes, a delicate Magistrate. Arth. You shall see her Dance Sir Geoffry, believe me she has Excellent Parts, come Flora, I'fack flic shall be yours all over. Flora Dances a Jig. Arth. Excellent Girle i Tack, take her Sir Geoff.y, take her, 1 fay flie shall be yours, i'fack she shall. t Entertains Eudoria I m Dumb show. Geoff. The little Rogue has Charm'd me, the has won my heart again, come little Wag, what fay you to a Country Magistrate row ha, nay nay—I have forgot all the Abuses, all the Aihonts you and your Sister put upon me, I have upon my Honour. Flor. You are too hasty Sir Geoffry, you have my Fathers Consent I must confess, but mine is yet to get > and if you have me you must expect to be made a Geoff. Cuckold every day, I know it very well, tis Heredi- tary to the Family, but I'll venture that: come little Rogue. Enter Twiford drejl Ridiculously, with Slockjns of two several/ Colours, Breeches altogether out of Fashion, and a Coat quite different from all} and over this a Carpet rut Jo, that his Head and Arms may come through^ and the reji hang h^e a SeaaJors Gorrn. Tvpif. —Save you, —save you Ladies, and you my Ho- nourable Lords and very good Cousins, you see I keep my word, but upon my Honour it was something hard to put my self thus into the Fashion, I was at least with s score Lords and Ladies, all very considerable People, who were very conside- rably pleas'd with my new Play, andtruely I believe,it may do very honourably well, but my Lord [To Bramble,^] You arc a man of Wit, and I know understand in a very Extraordinary manner, I'll show you my Comedy 5 in the mean time pray Co/ oblige me with a Bottle of Wine, -and a considerable quantity of Meat 5 for mark you Coz I am a Wit, and a very hungry Wit, and between you and I thole are the best sort of Wits. , Bran/b. A Hungry Wit? I believe you: here Sir John, lu re is what Sir Arthur's Table affords. and Eat and Dr/nl^voj greedily. Arth.
Page 64

The Rambling Justice, or, Arth. Will he not yield yet, will he not be friends ha? The Devil is in the man I think. • \_Aside. kz.:id. He yet Sir is strangely averse to it, but I doubt not at another meeting to compleat the Work, and make you both friends again: and that's a very hard task, but for your fake 111 venture it. Arth. Dear Love, Night is a coming and then,— I fay no more, get Sir General! to your Chamber, work him, work him to a height of Good nature, and then bring me the happy ty- ciings, the joyfull news. Pud. Where shall I find you Sir > Arth. In my Study, in my Study Dear, I will make an excuse to the Company for my absence, and expect your Answer. Gentlemen, pardon me for leaving you so soon, a little busineis unt bought of before our meeting, just now came into my Head, and wants to be difbatch'd } be merry, drink and be merry, I'll wait upon you presently. Surly, You know your time Sir. Arth. Now will I steal into Eudorias's Chamber, and obscure my self that I may hear how my Wife works him j She has a notable Tongue, and can wheedle a man Delicately, she has indeed. Q^&.j [Ex. Sir Arth. Trvif. This is Delicate Food my Lord, have you any more > [To Bramble. Bramb. Truly Sir John no. Alas we live here amongst Canni- balls, within a short time after Dinner they will devour one another. Trvif. Truly your Cousins at r<Hare very Considerably well, and every thing is in a very decent Order, and they are all Ex- treamly brave and Gallant} why look you Cousin, I am going to get a Commission, I have already a Scarf, Sword and Belt, and such Appurtenancesindeed they are the fame I had at the Campain at Blacl^heath, but still they are very Genteele and rviodish.— {All thk while Sir Geoffry Entertains Flora \ in Dumb store. Geoff. What say you now little Rogue ha? Flor. I say I shall be the same I ever was, the fame jeasting, jeaiing, designing Woman. Geoff. With all my heart. Flor. t must must not be Curb'd. Geof.
Page 65

The Jealous Husbands. Geoff! You (hall not. Flor. Nor be hindred of my Pleasure. Geoff. You shall not. Flor. Nor be lock'd up in my Chamber. Geoff. Neither. Flor. Then give me your Hand I'm Yours. Geoff. Not as you was before, to Couzen me, I hope. Flor. The Minister shall confute you: but we (hall stay too long from the Company. Cthey go into the Scene and (it I down, the Scene closes. Ttfif. My Lord you are very obliging, and Madam Flora is very considerably in a good posture, as affairs stand now, and truly by the next month, at the opening of the Campain, she will be much bigger, and sit for a Considerable com- mand. Bramb. Shall we not have your Company, my Lord > Twif. Cousin, I will wait upon you, and be, my Lord, your most considerably Obliging Faithfull servant to command. f_ Exeunt. SCENE Eudoria's Chamber, Enter Sir Arthur Twilight. Art h. Now I shall be made the happiest Citizen in London, I shall indeed 5 let me see, where shall I hide my self to over- hear 'era, 1'fack under that Table, it is a Delicate privacy, and very sit for the purpose. [Creeps under the Table. Enter Sir Generall Amorous and Eudoria. Gen. Now Joy comes on apace, and every minute produces new Delights. We love without controle, and tread those paths are pointed out by your late Jealous Husband, and what before we studied for with care, is by Sir Arthur flung into our Arms. Art h. Ha! what means this? [Aside. End. Nothing's more sweet than oft repeated Bliss, especially to one whose Appetite has been so often dull'd by the Embra- cings of Old Age and Folly. K Arth.
Page 66

66 The Rambling Justice, or, Arth. Ha! is this the Effects? they arc reconcild, i'faith thev arc. [Aside. Gen. Poor Sencclefs man ! that has the impudence to think a Woman can be mew'd up alone, or feed upon a Sapless Tree: by Heaven a Nunnery is Paradise to such a Ladies Chamber. Anh. I can endure no longer, and yet I dare not stir. [Aside. End. Now we arc all desires, and reap each minute a World of New-born Pleasure?, whilst in that sordid thing a Feeble Hulband, we seed upon a wish, and only live by the imaginary parts os Bliss, Phantasms and Idle Dreams. Arth. O Devil, Devil, Devil, 1 shall be made a Cuckold, I lind I shall, and dare not offer to prevent it neither. [,A(ide. Gen. Let us be reall Lovers, and meet our Flames with vigour, I'm talk'd into an Exstaly, — and shall expire by gazing on your Charms. End. We talk away that time which should be spent in Pleasure. Arth. A Whore, a Whore, by Heaven a common whore, and I an Arrand Cuckold. [ Aside. Gen. I've been too tardy my Eiidoria, and will be so no more. [Spea^and move towards the Bed. Shoot down ye Gods, all, all jony Plagues above, Whtn I neglect the Critu\hour of Love. Arth. Confusion! a Pimp, a Pimp, a Pimp. [_ Falls into a fit ojCoHghing, they fit art. Gen. Ha! from whence that Noise? End. Under the Table I think. Gen. What Slave durst interrupt us? End. We are betray'd I fear. [, Looks under the Table. My Husband! I am lost for ever. Gen. Ha ! your Hulband? then Impudence assist me. [Draws. Come sortli ihou scorn of Mankind,, and take your Death with patience 5 look on your Fate, and with a Bsow serene, smile whilst I send thy Soul into another World : come out I Arth. Not I by Jove, if you will kill me do it in private, for I shall never indure to see it done, o'j Gen. Then blr [Ojsos to kill him. .vyfe? f.-5 I \ ij :, 'sv *' Arth.
Page 67

The Jealous Husbands. • Arth. "Nay sweet Sir Gcucrull hold, 'tis plague enough to be a Cuckold, but I'll forget I am one, if you II save my Lite; Ala^ I am not prepar'd to dye. Gen. So much the greater my Revenge. [Offers to kill htm agtin, Eudoria hmdring hint. Ei/J. Nay let me beg his Pardon Sir, alas the ran It was mine, I ought to suffer, ihed net the B!oud of such a harmless man, but if you must be crucll, iheath here your Sword, and let my Lire and shame end both together. Gen. Come out I fry. Arth. Not till you give me Life, I'faith I am sorry, very sorry I interrupted you, I am indeed. Gen. Come out, and 1 ll consider on t. | Comes from under the Table and k.nccls.-] How durst yc, thou base Jealous Do- tard, presume to think an evil! thought of us, much more di- sturb our Pleasures, skulk in our known Recesses,' and all to make you mad, horn mad? but to prevent your Lunacy thus I'll (Offers to k'U hint again, Eudoria Kneels and I seems to 11 ccp. End. Hold, on my Knees I beg you to forbear, look on his Age, his Innocence and Goodnels, look how submissively he bends for Pardon , and also look upon Eudorta's Tears : can they not win you yet, not bate your Fury? then on his Neck I'll hang and perish there, perish and Dye with my dear Lo- ving Husband. . [, Falls on his Nec^ and Weeps. Arth. Can you , can you strike now > can you kill Sir Ar- thur? your best Friend Sir Arthur? can you for all these Tears? for all the Tears of such a loving Wife? C Falls on Eudoria/ Necf^ at;d If eept. Gen. Rise, she has gain'd your Pardon: but on Condition that you never talk, nay not so much as think of what has happened, if you doe—. -,\ / Arth. Never, alas I will take it for a Dream, a mcer Dream, and when I am awake, put it out of my Memory.\: Gen. Forgive Eudoria then, and with a Zeal as hasty, as you went to Church together. Arth. I do, I'fack I do, wish all my Heart I doe. Arth.
Page 68

63 The Rambling Justice, or, Arth. I'm of your mind Sir Generall, I'fack I am, this 'tis to be Old and fearfull •■> but 'tis no matter, I'm not the first Cuc- kold, that's my comfort. fend. Now all my hopes are lost, quite lost for ever, and I must still be bound to one I hate. Enter Twiford Singing and Dinting. Trvifi Why, look you Coufins, every thing is Considerably well, and the Affair has been managed with a great deal of Prudence, and my Cousin Geoffry and his Wife Emelia, are migh1}' joeost and pleasant and every thing is in an extraordi- nary Good manner and Posture, and the way is mighty obli- ging I allure you, they did me the honour to employ me in this great Affair, which is to advertise you that all my good Lords and Ladies are in very Good health, and are— Enter Sir Geoffry, Emelia, Contentious Surly, Petulant Easy, Flora, Spy well and Bramble. Why look you Cousins, here are all my very good Lords and Ladies, and pray pardon me my Lords, if I leave your Compa- nies so soon, for my very Honourable Friend and Cousin, my Lord has sent for me, and I am to win a hundred Gtiin- nies to night, which is very considerable, my very good Lords, Ladies and Cousins, Adieu. [Ex. Twiford. Geojs. What, Alamort Sir Arthur .<? Come, come be merry and sing, I have got your Daughter, I'fack Boy. Arth. Tis Well, 'tis very well, she is a smart Rogue, and will make a good Wife I'll warrant her She is my Daughter, and I hope will make you a Cuckold too } that I may have a Son in law of the Family of the Wittalls. [AJtde. {AU this time Sir Generall Entertains Flora in Dumb Jhotv. Gen. Sir Arthur Twilight all anger being past and quite for- gotten, to bind my self for ever to you, and by a Bond that knits Intire Affections, with your Consent and to secure your peace, here will I plant my Love. Arth. With all my Heart, I care not what you doc, Marry whom you please, I can be but a Cuckold still. \_ Aside. Gen. What say s Emelia .<? Emel.
Page 69

The Jealous Husbands. 6y Entel. I would lay nothing Sir to Matrimony, is you men were not so deceitful], and yet methinks I long to know what 'tis. Gen. O tis a Pleasing Pain, a Heav'nly Blisi. Emel. Nay, tell me not on't before hand, I hate to have my Pleasures pai d by talking of 'em, give me your hand, for once I'll venture Marriage, but believe me, if it prove contrary to mv Expedtation, I'll run tbr't, go to Law lor alimony, and be Mistress to an Alderman. Artb. He shall be a Cuckold too, I'll perfwade my Daughter to be a Whore, and so be reveng'd on him. [Aside. Easy. Still he is False, and in the highest nature; I'll study for Revenge now I have lost him, and ruin both together. [ Aside. Surly. Sir General/ Amorous, I beg your Pardon for those foul suspicions I had of you and EaJ}t and hereafter Ill strive to (how my Love. Gen. My thanks shall not be wanting, nor my Rewards, to Spymell and to Bramble, both which have play'd the Parts of Faithfull Servants. Licentious Youth, taught by unruly Firest Each moment leads us to Unjuji Desires. The Jey once past, and the great Blessing tune j We grieve to thinl^it cannot come again. But here that Bliss we do in safety meet, And lay our Glories at the Vittors Feet. Where uncontr.ousd rve in our Chains enjoy Those Pleasures whish our Freedom would destroy. FINIS.
Page 70

E PI L O G U E, Spoken by Sir A RTHV R. Til E fate .of Writing is like Wedlock dark, J he Wife's Debauch'J by every Mod/sh Spa,k And though a Man Monopolr^tb lint He's sure to-have but little /bare of it. We City Culiies luy cur Wive's so Dear y And n itb such Pains indulge each Wantons Ears. Till they break.* ut, andyou Debauch 'em here,) Iberts scaice a Gallant but has jrepj supplies Of Love and Glances, from her Wanton Eyes, lie fate of Citt and Poet then are even, For sure both Fools and Cuckolds go to Heaven: How hapfy thens the Autbour oj this Play, ,* U'ho although Toung's as great a Fool as they? He fe ore he did not Write to flo.ow his Sence But his VnequaTd fleck of Impudence. For though you Raile and Daw, hehughs to fee Ton more mifiakfniu hi* Play the* he.
Page 71

Blank page
Page 72

Blank page
Page 73

Blank page
Page 74

Blank page
Page 75

I «
Page 76

This book should be returned to the Library on or before the last date stamped below. A fine of five cents a day is incurred by retaining it beyond the specified time. Please return promptly.

Page 77

Blank page

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents

End of text. Return to beginning.
