The history of Henry the Fifth : And The tragedy of Mustapha, son ov Solyman the Magnificent. As they were acted at His Highness, the Duke of York's theater / Written by the Right Honourable, the Earl of Orrery., . | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
The history of Henry the Fifth : And The tragedy of Mustapha, son ov Solyman the Magnificent. As they were acted at His Highness, the Duke of York's theater / Written by the Right Honourable, the Earl of Orrery., .
Author
Orrery, Roger Boyle, Earl of, 1621-1679.Orrery, Roger Boyle, Earl of, 1621-1679.
Published
London :Printed for H. Herringman,1668.
Description
124p. ;29cm.
Rights
Public Domain, Google-digitized.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/pst.000005294701

Table of Contents

    Front Cover
    Title Page
    Section 1 on page number 1
    Section 2 on page number 11
    Section 3 on page number 39
    Section 4 on page number 53
    Section 5 on page number 54
    Section 6 on page number 55
    Section 7 on page number 78
    Section 8 on page number 91
    Section 9 on page number 103
    Section 10 on page number 106

Book Text
Front Cover
Page Scan 1

-

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 2

Blank page
Page Scan 3

Blank page
Page Scan 4

Blank page
Page Scan 5

THE HISTORY OF HENRY THE FIFTH BY THE EARL OF ORRERY 1668 A FACSIMILE PUBLISHED BY CORN MARKET PRESS FROM THE COPY IN THE BIRMINGHAM SHAKESPEARE LIBRARY LONDON 1969
Page Scan 6

PUBLISHED BY CORNMARKET PRESS LIMITED 42/43 CONDUIT STREET LONDON WIR ONL PRINTED IN ENGLAND BY FLETCHER AND SON LIMITED NORWiCH SBN 7191 0131 x

End of Front Cover. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Title Page
Page Scan 7

Roger ºſ- oney THE H IS T O R Y Henry the Fifth. AND THE T R A G E D Y M U S T A D H A, Son of S 0 LT MAN the Magnificent. Asthey were Aāed at his Highneſs the Duke of Tork's T H E A T E R. Written by The Right Honourable the Earl of OR RER r. —i. 1.05 (T) 05WC, Printed for H. Herringman, at the Sign of the Blew Anchor in the Lower Walk of the New Exchange. I 668.
Page Scan 8

Blank page
Page Scan 9

The Perſons. King Henry the Fifth. Duke of Bedford, his Brother. Duke of Exeter, his Uncle. Earl of Warwick, Biſhop of Canterbury. Owen Tudor the King's Favourite. The Dauphin. Duke of Burgundy. Earl of Chareloys, his Son. Conſtable of France. De Chaſtel, the Dauphin's Creature. Biſhop of Arras. Count of Blamount. Monſieur Colemore. Queen of France. Princeſs Katherine, her Daughter. Princeſs Anne of Burgundy. The Counteſs of La Marr. French Ladies. Heralds. Guards. Mr. Harriſ. Mr. ‘Onderhill. Mr. Cogan. Mr. Aingel. Mr. Lylimſtol. Mr. Betterton. Mr. Toung. Mr. Smith. Mr. Cadiman. Mr.james N.oke Mr. Norrir. Mr. Samford. Mr. Medborne. Mr. Floyd. Mrs. Long. Mrs. Betterton. Mrs. Davir. Mrs. Norrir. H E NRY
Page Scan 10

Blank page

End of Title Page. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 1

Henry the Fifth. T H E FIRST ACT. Enter King Henry the 5", the Duke of Exeter, the Duke of Bed- ford, and Owen Tudor, with their Attendants. King. His is the day in which our Valour muſt Prove to the French,our claim to France is juſt; Since 'twill no other way be underſtood, It muſt be writin Charaćters of blood. By injuries they us to Battel call; Denying us our part, they forfeit all: * Tis fit in number they ſhould us exceed 5 That odds the French againſt the Engliſh need; That odds which both obliges them and me, Brings them to Fight, and us to Vićtory. Exeter. Heav'n left us purpoſely but few for fight, To ſhew the world, by your ſucceſs, your right. Bedford. They ſeem t'acknowledge Heav'n is not their Friend, Since on their boaſted numbers they depend 5 Which when their cauſe is reckon'd, we ſhould prize, As Heav'n accounts them, for a Sacrifiee. Enter Earl of Warwick. Exeter. The Earl of Warwick in his looks does bring Some News of high importance to the King. Warw. Arm Arm 1 Great Sir, the Foe is in our view, And has a Herauld ſent to challenge you. King. Tell him, I in this Field poſſeſs all France, From which l'le ne're retire, but may advance. In vain they threaten War, or promiſe Peace, They boaſt their numbers, which we wiſh not leſs; They are enow both to deſtroy and ſave 5 But were they more, they here might find a Grave. Take care the Herauld ſo rewarded be, That he may know his Meſſage pleaſes me. Under their Standards, as I order'd you, Are all my Troops fixt in the form I drew 2 Warm. They are, and like one face, all looks agree, Reſolving and fore-telling Vićtory. King. Who e're a room to other thoughts affords, Injures our Quarrel, and miſtakes our Swords. B Warp,
Page 2

(2) Warw. How ſhort a time and narrow ſpace of ground Is’t 'twixt your Conqueſt, and your being Crown'd? King. To make both ſhorter, I will ſtraight advance, And by two Titles wear the Crown of France. Uncle, to your command with ſpeed repair; The right wing, Brother, does expect your care; Both to the field of Battel lead the way, Whilſt but a moment I with Tudor ſtay. Exeumt Exeter, Bedford, Warwick, Oh my beſt Friend! thy ſadneſs I muſt blame, [Tudor appears. Canſt thou now think on anything but Fame? Tudor. When I refle&t how many dangers ſtill You muſt attempt, how many more you will----- King. Reflecton dangers which muſt glory win. Tudor. Excuſe me, if my duty makes me ſin : Since I no other way can grateful prove, I'le rather ſhew my fear, then hide my love. King. That I to thee may proofs of mine diſpence, I now ſtay here, though glory calls me hence: When Fame, when Life, and Empire are at ſtake, All thoughts of thoſe for thee I can forſake; Baniſh thy grief by thinking on that praiſe, Which ſhall thy name ſo high in Battel raiſe, That all my future favours men may ſay, Are not what I beſtow, but what I pay. Tudor. What you have ſaid and done brings merelief; This day I will deſerve your love or grief. King. Speak not of grief, but think on that applauſe Which Heav'n doth ſtill allow the juſter cauſe. Tudor. Why ſhould he be by too much courage loſt, Of whom alone this world has cauſe to boaſt 2 [Exehnt. Eater Dauphin, and De Chaſtel. Dauph. Let me deſpiſe what I can ne're obtain: I'll live retir’d ſince I'm deny'd to reign. My Mother, having got the Regency, Does either hate, or is afraid of me; But I perceive by my retirement here, I ſhun her malice, and ſuppreſs her fear 3 I ſhall (if I to Paris now return) Her hatred feel,or which is worſe,her ſcorn. De Chaft. But ſhall our Dauphin, the undoubted Heir, Sit idly peaceful in an ačtive War, And let his Enemy the Throne aſcend ? Dauph. He who my wrongs revenges, is my Friend, De Chaſtel, you have often heard me plead, That in this War I might the Army lead; O D
Page 3

( 3 ) On me ſo high a truſt ſhe'l not beſtow, And any other truſt I think too low : A Prince whoſe Soul as well as Birth is great, If he in glory cannot ſhine, ſhould ſet: From Courts I am condemn'd to Villages, From noble toyls of War t'ignoble eaſe ; Where undiſturb’d I'll for her hatred grieve, And honour makes me rather chuſe to live Equal with men not worth the Governing Then be at Court and there not be a King. De Chaft. Though I confeſs her uſage, Sir, has been Such as not fits a Mother or a Queen; Yet, Sir, conſider whilſt from her you flye, You more exalt the Duke of Burgundy. Dauph. That fatal name my fury doth advance : ‘Twas he who Murth’red Royal Orleance; And, though the Queen recover my eſteem, No Palace can have ſpace for me and him. De Chaſt. Return the ſooner to revenge that blood. No man has well his intereſt underſtood, Who to enjoy it ſcrupl’d at the way: He who builds high muſt low foundations lay. I by the Queen for your return am ſent, Her harſh behaviour ſhe does now repent: By kind ſubmiſſions you may rule her heart, And what's deny'd by kindneſs, gain by Art; With ſmall complyance you'l ſuppreſs her hate, When Nature's judge, and Duty advocate. Your abſence, Sir, has caſt your party down : Few follow thoſe on whom the Prince does frown. Dauph. Thou in all ſtorms haſt been my conſtant Friend, I'll on thy wiſdom and thy care depend 5 'Tis juſt I ſhould to thy advice ſubmit, For he who makes my fate, ſhould governit. De Chaſt. With this glad news I will out-ride the Poſt, And e're you come to Court, I'll clear the Coaſt. [Exeunt. Enter the Queen of France, Princeſs Katharine, Princeſs Anne of Burgundy, Duke of Burgundy, and their Train. gueen. This is the day Alanſon ſent us word, He would our Fate determine by the Sword; Which he has haſtned, hearing by his Spies The Plague had ſo impair'd our Enemies, That more delay would make our Princes dream They ſhould not come to kill, but bury them; And France would be oblig'd for her defence, Not to their Swords, but to that Peſtilence. Burgun.
Page 4

(4) Eurgun. Since from th’ Eternal Pow'r that rodisſent, Why from his hand take we the puniſhment 2 And this inſulting, Madam, makes me fear Our ruine rather then our triumph near : Thoſe Engliſh Swords on which he ſets no price, Lately cut down our Flower de Lucer twice; And to King Edward's Piety we owe The miracle that now again they grow. gºteem. France juſtly might the Engliſh Valour dread, Were it again by that Great Monarch led; We fear him leſs who now that Crown does wear, His wildneſs, not his courage, brings him here. Burgun. Whilſt his prodigious Father was alive, Some youthful ſigns of wildneſs he did give; But when he early on his Throne was plac'd, A Kingly Soul his Royal Title grac'd; And then whatever mis-becoming thing Liv'd in the Prince, was buried in the King 5 Nought ſhould in us low thoughts of him perſwade, Who does himſelf ſubdue, 2nd France invade. Enter a French Lady. Lady. The Count of Blamount from the Camp with news Does wait without, and for admittance ſues. gueen. Blamount ſo ſoon return'd? let him appear. Ill news is ſwifter then the wings of fear. Enter Bla- His looks to me a ſad account have given. II].Oults Where is Alanſon 2 Blam. Madam, he's in Heav'n : That glory cannot be to him deny'd, Who for his Country liv'd, and for it dy'd. gueen. The brave Alanſom Deadl by what miſchance? Blam. By the moſt ſignal that e're fell on France. gueen. Without diſguiſe the naked truth declare, Before my griefbe turn'd into deſpair. Blam. Laſt night both Camps ſonear each other lay, As we not more for triumph long'd then day 3 The mighty Martelled not braver men, When he at Tours ſubdu'd the Syracen, And with the blood waſh'd France, then did reſort To the unhappy fields of Agen-Court; Where many then with joyful ſhouts did greet The riſing Sun, who ne're ſhould ſee him ſet: A while both Armies on each other gaz'd, Both at th' intended ſlaughter ſeem amaz'd. gºueen. Could thoſe who oft have bloody Battels won, Stand long amaz'd at ills which muſt be done * Blam. Wars chearful Muſick now fills every Ear, Whilſt death more gaudy did then life appear. For
Page 5

(5) For various Enſigns did unfold ſuch Pride, That all ſeem'd Bridegrooms there, and Death the Bride; The noble order in each ſquadron ſeen 5 The many Warriours of a haughty meen; The prouder horſes chafing to be rid, Who breath'd the Combat as their Riders did 3 Made all confeſs that War gave Death a grace, And has its charms as well as beauty has, After a little pauſe they both advance, One to preſerve, th' other to conquer France: Thoſe who did proudly think the Foe would yield, Saw him draw up with order in the Field; And by a King advanc'd, whoſe hand and head, All the defečts fupply'd of thoſe he lead. Queen. How I did young Henry dare to meet you then 2 We heard diſeaſes had . his men. Blam. The courages of all the Engliſh dead, Were to thoſe few then living newly fled: So thin, ſo harraſt all his Squadrons were, As we did pity them we us’d to fear; For it is equally as ſtrange to ſay, That they durſt fight, as that they won the day: But Fame can want notheam when ſhe does ſing Of Engliſh Swords led by an Engliſh King 3 Nor was he only in the Battel known By his bright Armour, which like lightning ſhone; But did with nobler marks his Valour grace, Still being ſeen where foremoſt danger was. Alanſon, who obſerv'd this wondrous King, Courage to his, and fear to ours did bring; Made fighting ſingle with him his high aim, And in a Battel to a Duel came. gueen. By an attempt ſo noble and ſublime, He ſhow'd as much as I believ'd of him. Blam. Both Nations at a ſight ſo great and rare, Their bloody Swords ſuſpended in the Air, And by a general ſilence made it known, They in their Leaders fate would ſee their own : But though Alanſon did ſtupendious things, A Subjećts Sword could not reſiſt a Kings; Angels are Guardians of that Sacred name. Burgun. Yet by his death he got a deathleſs fame. Blam. That loſs invaded all to that degree, As we more fought for Death then Vićtory; For many Worthies waited on his fall, The Conſtable of France, the Admiral, The Duke of Brabant, and the Duke of Bar; Promiſcuous killing now diſgrac'd the War: C
Page 6

(6) Soglutted was the thirſty Vićtors Sword, As now the ſpacious world cannot afford, After ſo many Heroes drown'd in gore, Unleſs of Engliſh, one brave Worthy more. gueen. That Nation ſtill too highly you eſteem. Burg. Ourſelves we beſt excuſe in praiſing them. Blam. Now only horrour, death, confuſion reigns, And covers Agen-Courts unhappy plains; Here Corpſes lye, where Squadrons lately ſtood ; Standards and Enſigns there lye roll'd in blood ; Here woods of Lances o're the Fields are ſpread, And dying men lye groaning o're the dead. Queen. If truth conſents to what you now relate, From this black day France may her ruine date. Blam. This is not all the deſtiny of France ; The Dukes of Bourbon and of Orleance, The Lords of Domcourt, Humiere, Harcourt, Salt- Roy, Fauconbridge, Noel, and Beauſiquault, And many more of ſignal worth and race, The Conquerours Triumphal Chariot grace. But Bowdile, who this day firſt turn'd his back, In hopes to waſh away a ſtain ſo black, Aſſaulted with a loud and firious cry Th'unguarded baggage of the Enemy. The King ſuppos'd new Troops had took the field, And order'd ſtraight all Prisºners to be kill'd: What Bomdile thus at firſt and laſt did do, Made Henry happy, and yet cruel too; But 'twas a cruelty our ſelves did cauſe, And which his judgement took from ſafeties laws; For ſhameful was our Fate, the Pris'ners there Surpaſs'd in number thoſe who Vićtors were. &ueen. Could nothing, leſs then this, Heav'ns wrath abate 2 It made us Agents to our own dire Fate. Burg. The Deſtinies were never ſo ſevere, The fault, as well as loſs, they make us bear ; And by ſo ſtrange a ruine make us know, This Empire to one field her fall may owe. Were thoſe Renown'd Commanders now alive, They might the Fortune of loſt France revive, And by their Swords reſtore her dying Fame. Blam. All thoſe are living which I laſt did name: The King did rather hazard again'd field, Then ſuffer Chiefs ſo noble to be kill'd 5 And but with half his Army did advance, Twice in one day, to act the Fate of France, Leaving the reſt to guard them where they ſtocd. Burghn. His Valour ſheds, his Mercy ſpares cut blocd, Blaw,
Page 7

(7) Blam. Young Tudor, Madam, much renown'd you knows To whom all France her gratitude does owe 3 For he, when all did dangers face decline, Met it to ſerve the Princeſs Katherine; He gainſt my will this hated life did ſave, And when he heard thoſe orders Henry gave, Fearing their rigour might extend to me, Above my hope, or wiſh, did ſet me free; He told me as we parted that he knew, I had the honour to belong to you. Bowing to Princeſs Katherine. gºueen. "Tis Heav'n has ſtrucken us 5 and when we know That hand, who dares want patience for the blow * My Lord, 'tis needful I reſolve with ſpeed Who ſhall the fatal Conſtable ſucceed. Burg. And counſel needful is how far 'tis fit, After defeat to ſtruggle or ſubmit. gueen. Aſſemble ſtrait. Heav'n does occaſion give Of Mourning, yet allows no time to grieve. Exeunt Queen, Burgundy, Blamount, Lady. Prin. An. Madam, methought when Tudors name you heard, A new Vermilion in your face appear'd 5 That word did raiſe a trouble there as great, As you diſcover'd hearing our defeat: Though theſe are ſigns that Love does for him ſue, Yet to our friendſhip there is ſo much due, That from my height of faith I'll not deſcend, I'll rather blame my eyes then doubt my Friend, And think I ſaw not that which I did ſee, Rather then fear you hide your ſelf from me. Prin. Kat. Ah, how this ſoft concernment ſhews you juſt 1 For what can be too precious for your truſt? I muſt confeſs I bluſh'd when he was nam'd, But it was ſcorn, not love, my face inflam’d, That any but a King, and Crown'd with Bayes, Preſum’d ſo high as me his thoughts to raiſe; That ſecret now ſhall be to you reveal’d, Which only through your abſence was conceal’d: With ſo much grief I did your abſence mourn, When to your Fathers Court you did return, That the ſame day I to St. Germain went To give in that retreat my ſorrows vent 5 A ſtorm o're-took us as we thither paſt, Rain made the riſing Flood to ſwell ſo faſt, That of the bridge it did the maſtry get, An Arch was born away, and we with it. Prin. An. Madam, I heard that ev'n that ſad miſchance Did frighten you, leſs then it frighted France. Prin, Kath.
Page 8

(8) prin. Kath. Tudor, whom fortune led that way, deſcry'd What many more with vain compaſſionſpy'd; They at the horrour of my danger wept, He from the bridge into the River leapt, And ſtemm'd the raging Current, till he bore My breathleſs body to the neighbouringſhore; Him to the Court this timely ſervice brought, In whom ſo many Charms concurring wrought, As I can ſcarce without ſome bluſhes owne, , That I did grieve he ſat not on a Throne; For to a Princeſs, who like me would do, He who a Throne does want, wants all things too. Prim. An. Ah Madam I Love, if it be ſtrong and true, Levels the pow'rful down to thoſe that ſue; And, when by inclination we are ſteer'd, Only what that does ſpeak is fully heard. Prin. Kath. Tudor ſoon chang'd his chearful brow at Court 3 To unfrequented Groves he did reſort; Whilſt others did rejoyce, he fighing mourn'd, And all his freedom into bondage turn'd : This new diſtemper to a habit grew, His mirth was ever feign'd, his ſorrows true : The cauſe of this when I deſir'd to know, He made no anſwer, but did figh and bow 5 By no reply he would his ſilence break. Prin. As. In ſuch a ſilence he did more then ſpeak. Prin. Kath. Ah! ſo he did; but yet I muſt confeſs I knew not Love could ſpeak, yet hold its peace: I urg'd to beinform'd; he ſigh'd and then Look'd often on me, and look'd down agen; Then ſaid, you force me, Madam, to a ſtrait To diſobey you, or deſerve your hate: One of theſe evils does engage me now 5 Silence the firſt, ſpeaking the laſt will do ; But I implore you will not think it fit To force me unto ſpeech, then puniſhit. Prin. An. Againſt your juſtice, Madam, 'twas a crime To puniſh what you did conſtrain from him. Prim. Kath. Then he his paſſion for me did declare With words and geſtures, which ſo mournful were, As ſtrait I did, by my experience, prove, That pity was no way to bring in Love: A hundred things he ſaid, but I was ſo Offended with my ſelf, and with him too 5 Firſt, that his words I had conſtrain'd from him, Then that he could be guilty of that crime; As I forgot ev'n all he did relate But theſe few words, which Iſhall ne're forget 5 Love
Page 9

(9) Love, of a wondrous birth, cannot expire, Which ſtrangely in the water firſt took fire. Prin. An. None, Madam, but a Lover will believe That flames in water can their birth receive. Prin. Kath.'Tis true,but thoſe bold words which then he ſpoke, Did ſoon my indignation ſo provoke, That never any crime can raiſe it higher 5 Ibid him inſtantly from Court retire : "Twould grieve your patience if I ſhould declare All that he ſaid, his treſpaſs to repair 5 Let it ſuffice that after that black night I never did admit him to my ſight; Nor will I tell you how he ſought relief, And vainly ſince hath almoſt dy'd with grief. Prim. Am. Did you not give him then ſome ſighs by ſtealth, And wiſh his ſickly mind a little health? Prin.Kath. All that’t had been injuſtice to deny, Prin, Am. Sure that was Love? Prim. Kath. Oh! no, 'twas Charity. Love is a flame which nothing can controul; As ſouls to bodies are, Love's to the ſoul 5 A pow'r which does all other powers o'return, And cannot be conceal’d when it does burn. Had that been Love, which is miſtook by you, Tudor had ſeen, and I had felt it too; But term it what you pleaſe, it cannot be, Whilſt I have pow'r to rule it, Love in me. Prin. An. Love to his height oft by degrees does riſe, Sometimes it ſtorms a boſom by ſurprize; Love moves not ever in one conſtant road, Oft, like a Child, he aëts, then like a God; And, by your eaſie ruling him, you may Miſtake his power for what is but his play. Prin. Kath. I doubt you'd have methink I am in Love. Prim. An. I rather would my fear of it remove. Prin. Kath. No, though I were, ſo much I owe my fame That to my birth I would reſign my flame. Prim. Am. May I, with ſafety, build on what you ſay? Prim. Kath. If my own heart deceive me not, you may. Prim. An. Then I will tell you ſomething which, perhaps, If you are cur'd, will hinder your relapſe. When dreadful Henry to this War was bent, The Royal Bedford to my Father ſent Offers of power and treaſure,with deſign To make him in this laſt Invaſion join : My Father to his Burgundy retir’d, Having rejećted what the Duke deſir'd; D But
Page 10

( 10 ) But ſaid, ſince here unjuſtly we retain Anjou, Rich Normandy, and Aquitame, He would, if rendring theſe might Peace advance, Perſwade in England, and prevail in France. Prin. Kath. We then have done th injurious Henry wrong: Do all thºſe Provinces to him belong 2 Prin. Art. France can no other Title there pretend, But what, force having got, Arms muſt defend. Prin. Kath. My grief for our defeat ſhall then grow leſs; Since we want juſtice we ſhould want ſucceſs. Prin. Am. But ſince to me your ſecrets you declare, 'Tis equal you in mine ſhould have a ſhare. Ah Madam | do not wonder if my heart, Which was entirely yours when we did part, Is from that high and bleſt condition flown, I, bluſhing, ſay, 'tis now no more my own. The Duke of Bedford, by the nobleſt force That e're ſubdu'd a heart into remorſe, Did with ſuch joint ſucceſs ačt his deſign, That I took his, and then reſign'd him mine. Prim. Kath. Dear Princeſs, I ſhall now admire no more What you have mention'd of Loves art and power; Nor that ſo high in that diſcourſe you went, Since you but ſpoke your own experiment. Prim. Am. If, Mºdern, you had preſent been to ſee The ſoftneſs of thoſe Charms which conquer'd me : You'd wonder more that long I held the field, Then that at laſt I willingly did yield. Trim. Kath. The Engliſh Archers may vićtorious grow, Where Love begins the conqueſt with his bow. Prin. Am. After we had this ſacred friendſhip made, He told me, though his brother would invade This Kingdom, to regain what was his due, Yet the chief conqueſt he deſign'd, was you : He told me too, though England ſtill affords Beauties reſittleſ, as the Engliſh Swords, Yet none of them prevail'd, though ne're ſo bright, Like your vićtorious pićture at firſt ſight. Then he implor'd that when to you I came, I would prepare you to receive his flame 5 A flame which all things elſe muſt needs out-do, Since by him cheriſh'd and inſpir’d by you : This, Madam, was the cauſe why I have preſt To find if e're your heart were prepoſeſt; Let France, by you, be freed from her diſtreſs: This happy union will procure her peace. Prim. Kath. If me he lov'd, her blood he then would ſpare 3 Loves gentle voice is never heard in War. Prin,

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 11

(11) Prim. An. Yet, like a King to you he does pretend, Glory he makes his way, and Love his end. Prim. Kath. Where bloud does cry, can I a Lover hear? Prin. An. When glory pleads, what then can ſtop your Ear? Enter a Lady. Lady. Midam, the Council is aſſembled now, And ere it fis, the Queen would ſpeak with you. Prim. Kath. I come: too long by Love we have been ſtay-d; I will conſider all that you have ſaid. Prin. An. Madam, be pleas'd to think upon it ſo, That France to you may her redemption owe. LExehnt. T H E S E COND ACT. Enter the King, Duke of Exeter, Duke of Bedford, Earl of Warwick, and Tudor: King: Y Lord of Warwick, you may give to all The French of note the rites of Funeral; It is a debt which to the dead we pay, Rewarding Courage ev’n in thoſe we ſlay. Warwick. It ſhall be done. King. Brother it will be fit The Pris’ners you to ſtronger Guards commit 5 They ſhalla Court within our Army ſce; And in it nothing want but liberty. Bed. They ſhall be ſafe, yet have ſome freedom too. King. Uncle, the great requeſt I make to you, Is to preſ... we our wounded men with care 5 'Tis by their courage we vićtorious are. Exeter. They ſhall be ſerv'd with all they can deſire; We muſt that valour ſerve which you admire. Exeunt Exeter, Bedford, Warwick, Tudor. Though this great day, th' expecting world may ſee Your Title both to France and Vićtory; And though no Conquerour alive, or dead, With nobler wreaths did ever crown his head 5 Yet pardon me if I preſume to ſay, I ſee a ſadneſs miſ-becomes this day; This day, in which your friends and foes confeſs, Nothing can make you greater, nothing leſs; So fixt are Fortunes Wheels they cannot turn, Then, Sir, permit only the French to mourn; The loſs of Tork and Suffolk, though too great, Should not out-weigh your Enemies defeat : f I
Page 12

( 12 ) If, Sir, your Wars coſt not ſome lives, like theſe, You would not Conqueſts make, but miracles 5 Who in his Princes ſervice finds a Grave, Rather our envy than our grief ſhould have, And fighting in your fight, who for you dyes, Is bleſt enough without ſuch Obſequies: If to their death ſuch envy'd grief you give, You'l make us then repent that we do live : Sir, for the living's ſake your grief decline, And let your looks clear as your glories ſhine. King. So great a loſs as is above relief, Even on this day might juſtifiemy grief: He who of friendſhip knows the ſacred ties, Will value more his Friends than Vićtories; But that juſt ſorrow, which thou wouldſt remove, Is not a tribute paid to Death but Love 3 If Fame, or Power, only in me did ſway, I could not have been ſeen in Clouds to day; 'Tis Love's fierce Fire which does my heart devour 5 Leſs to be quench'd than heats of Fame or Power. Tudor. She muſt do more than Woman e're could do, Reſiſting ſuch a King and Conqu'rour too 5 You, though her eyes ſhould brighteſt beams emit, May ſafe in ſhades under your Laurels ſit. King. My Laurels might a ſafe refreſhment prove To any other heat but that of Love; Their ſacred force gainſt Thunder only lies, Not againſt lightningſhot from conqu'ring eyes; Whoſe pow'r, like that of lightning, I have felt; My breaſt they wound not, yet my heart they melt. Tudor. May I not know who does my King ſubdue # King. Saying I love, I need not tell thee who : VWho of the Planets ſpeaks of brighteſt beams, Need not ſay after, 'tis the Sun he means. Tudor. The Sun by all is mention'd at one rate, But Fancy alters beauties eſtimate; Were it not Fancy which that value gave, All Lovers then would but one Miſtreſs have. King. Such adoration Fancy cannot raiſe, As to this beauty ſight and reaſon pays; For he whoſe heart Love can to aſhes turn, Muſt feel her eyes alone have right to burn: But that this ignorance thou may'ſt decline, Know I adore the Princeſs Katherine : Loves Rebels by her eyes are kept in awe, She reigns in France ſpight of the salique Law. Tudor. Will not Loves heat make Glories flame expire * King. No, Tudor, it will rather raiſe it higher; F Or
Page 13

(13) For none ſhould aim at this exalted ſtate Who makes not glory firſt his Advocate. This was the cauſe when Charlº, her father, ſent Embaſſadours, my conqueſt to prevent; And this bright beauty offer'd for my Bride, But with her, as her Dowry, France deny'd; I ſhun'd the match, knowing her beauties were No price for Peace, but the reward of War; My vows and paſſion ſhe might juſtly ſcorn, Did I not Crown her Queen where ſhe was born; And raiſe her boundleſs beauties to ſupply What a rude Law does to her Sex deny. Tudor. Perhaps your flame had with more luſtre ſhone, Had you for it declin'd the Gallick Throne: For love of her to quit in France your right is more then 'tis to conquerit in fight 5 Nor can you hope her paſſions flame to raiſe When with her Countries blood you ſtain your Bays. King. Dear Tudor, I perceive becauſe thou art A Subjećt thou miſtak'ſt a Monarchs heart. Thoſe, who from Royal veins derive their blood, Find only in a Throne what's great and good; Sure Nature in her would much rather ſee Her Son then Brother rule this Monarchy. Tudor. A Love like this was never known before, The Father you'l depoſe, the Child adore. Your Love will be in proofs of hatred ſhown 5 You on her Countries ruines build her Throne; This ſtrange deſign, Sir, does my wonder raiſe. King. A Love like mine moves not in common waies: Such unexampl’d things I'le ſtrive to do, That when I reach to what I now purſue, When men name one who lov'd to a degree Ne're known before, they'l ſay he lov'd like me. Prepare thy ſelf to go within an hour To the French Court as my Embaſſadour; And let them know if they reſign up France, (Mine both by Conqueſt and Inheritance) They ſhun ſuch force as cannot be withſtood, They ſhew their juſtice, and they ſpare their blood. Succeſs now asks but what I ask'd before. Tudor. He that at firſt ask'd all can ask no more. Much is not in the proffer I ſhall make. King. Yes, it is much to ask what I can take, And to accept from them that Crown which I Have giv'n me from the hand of Vićtory. Tudor, in this they cannot but confeſs, I make my mercy hinder my ſº %dor.
Page 14

( 14 D Tudor. It might be then convenient that I try’d T'obtain with France the Princeſs for your Bride: Since you as well for her as France contend, Without her you'l not reach your nobleſt end. King. She juſtly, Tudor, might my paſſion hate If Love's high int’reſt I ſhould mix with ſtate. if I this great concern by Treaty move "Twill be below her Beauty and my Love. That bleſſing muſt in nobler ways be ſought: Though Heav'n may be beſtow'd, 'tis never bought. But that which chiefly makes me ſend thee now Is that my Friend ſhould let my Princeſs know My flames are ſuch as Martyr'd Saints ſuſtain; The glory of them takes away the pain. [Exeumſ. Tudor. Was ever ſuch a Curſe impos'd by Fate? His favour wounds much deeper then his hate. I muſt unworthy or elſe wretched prove, Be falſe to Honour or elſe falſe to Love: To which of both ſhall I precedence give * I'm kill'd by this, by that unfit to live; But ſtay ! why ſhould not I, even I alone, Raiſe Love and Honour to a height unknown If, for his ſake, my paſſion I forego, In that great A&I pay him all I owe : Who for his King againſt his Love does ačt Pays Debts much greater then he can contračt. Nor are theſe all th' advantages will flow From that great ačtion I intend to do. If I her right above my Love prefer In that, by loſing, H ſhall merither. And to obtain, not merit her, will prove Leſs then to loſe her and deſerve her Love. 'Tis worthy of my flame, and of her eyes, To make love be to love a ſacrifice. [Exeunt. Enter Queen, Duke of Burgundy, the Conſtable, Earl of Charaloys, Count de Chaſtel. gºueen. The fatal cauſe why we aſſemble now We by the worſt of ſad experience know. Heav'n does, at once, on this our Empire ſhowre All the fierce marks of anger and of power. The King, my Lord, whoſe head, and heart, and hand, Should be imploy'd our ruine to withſtand, Under his old diſeaſe ſtill worſer grows; Yields to his pain as France does to his Foes: Yet is he not unhappy in that ſtate Which makes him not to feel the wounds of Fate, Th G
Page 15

( 15) The Dauphin, whoſe green years make him unfit In ſuch a ſtorm at Empires helm to ſit, Yet for that great and dang'rous place does preſs; And, miſſing it, forſakes us in diſtreſs. As theſe two miſeries aſſault us here, So th' Engliſh late ſucceſs fills all with fear. Yet, France, ſurviving ſuch deſtrućtive blows, Ev’n in her ruine ſtill her greatneſs ſhows. By your wiſe help ſhe hopes yet to be freed; And on your breaſts ſhe leans her weary head. Shall we again by Battel try our Fate, Or with the Engliſh King Capitulate 2 Conft. Our ſhoulders but attend for heavier weight, If in the Field we ſhun to try our Fate. For doubtleſs, Madam, he leſs Vertue ſhows Who yields to, than who falls by fortunes blows. Rome, though ſhe loſt four Fields to Hannibal, Her valour rais'd ev’n in her Fortunes fall. Her ſteady vertue did all ſtorms ſuppreſs, And made her Etmpreſs of the Univerſe: I would not doubt but we at length ſhould find A Roman Fate, had we a Roman mind. pe chaft. Thoſe who too haſtily with Vićtors treat, Make them too proud who were before too great. Such condiſcention would to fear diſpoſe Your Subjećts hearts, and elevate your Foes. Let not Poſterity have cauſe to ſay, That you loſt France, and loſt her in one day. Comſt. The chance of Arms are ſtill alternative; Fortune one day does take, next day does give: And all the Engliſh fame will be o'rethrown Hſ we of twenty Fields can win but one. All thoughts of Treaties, Madam, then deſpiſe, Which but excuſes fear whilſt we ſeem wiſe. Burg. Madam, what the great Conſtable does ſay Becomes that place you rais'd him to this day: He, who the head of all your Armies is, Safe Counſels ſhould obey but not adviſe. If to my judgment you will pleaſe to truſt, Chuſe not what great appears, but what is jutt. Madam, it is alone by Arms you reign O're Anjom, Normandy, and Aquitame. Thoſe three, the nobleſt Provinces of France, Are th' Engliſh King's confeſt Inheritance. What-ever of preſcription Gown-men write, Yet length of time changes not wrong to right : Why ſhould you not, er'ethings are deſp'rate grown, By giving what is his, preſerve your own & Keeping
Page 16

( 16) Keeping thoſe Countries will at laſt be found A Gangreen ; the corrupt will eat the ſound. Ear.of char. Juſtice is more then but an empty word: Therefore, whilſt that aſſiſts the Engliſh Sword, Succeſs will alwaies to their ſide reſort 5 And every Field will be an Agin-Court. Eurg. Can Councils proſp'rous be or Armies ſtrong, Both aiming to perpetuate a wrong? If after this fair offer he purſue The War, our Swords will ačt what his does now. If he accepts it (as no doubt he muſt) You will be ſafe as ſoon as you are juſt. Purſue the Aéts of Juſtice; thoſe alone Have pow'r to ſave and to exalta Throne. Enter Blamount. Elam. Young Tudor is arriv'd, and craves to be With ſpeed admitted to your Majeſty. By thoſe few words which have between us paſt I find his meſſage does require ſome haſte. 2ueen. Know you what 'tis which does him hither bring f Blam. Some overtures of peace from th' Engliſh King. Blamount whiſpers in the Queens Ear. Queen. Yes, I conſent 5 and give her notice I Expect ſhe ſhould receive him civilly. [Exit Blamount, My Lords, I find your judgments various are 5 Two are for Treaty, th' other twofor War. Such reaſons you for both opinions give, That I, with reaſon, either may receive. But Tudor being come does ſurely bring Something important from the Engliſh King. 'Tis fit our reſolutions we defer Till I his bus'neſs in his meſſage hear. [Exehnt. Enter Princeſs Katherine, and Blamount. Blam!. Madam, what I have ſaid the Queen will owns Prim. Kath. What? That with Tudor I ſhould ſpeak alone # Blam. He for that honour, Madam, now does ſtay. Prim. Kath. Since by the Queen commanded, I obey. [Exit Blamount. Enter Tudor. Thdor. Though, Madam, this high honour does excel What deeds can merit, or what words can tell, It ſhall no cauſe of new preſumption be; I'le not repeat what you condemn'd in me. I then preſum'd to tell you of a Fire Your Eyes did ina Subjećts heart inſpire; But
Page 17

( 17) But, Madam, now th'aſſurance which I bring, Is that your beauties have ſubdu'd a King; A King renown'd by all the voice of Fame; The leaſt he has of Monarch is the name. He only Love and Glory does purſue; Which makes him Conquer France and yield to you. And by th’unhappi'ſt of his Subjects ſays, He at your feet his Heart and Laurel lays. Judge what his Vertues are, and what my Fate, Which makes his Rival turn his Advocate. Prin. Kath. Tudor what firſt you ſpoke made me not fear That Rival was a word I e're ſhould hear. For you in that repeat the paſt offence, Which made me lately baniſh you from hence. If, by his worth, your King claims my eſteem, Why grieve you that you plead to gain it him? Tudor. Ah, Madam, may I not your pardon crave For grieving when I part from all I have? A Father, when he ſees his only Son Condemn'd to death for what he could not ſhun (Though to the right of juſtice he ſubmit) May well be pardon'd if he mourns for it. By double Dićtates, Madam, I am led 5 My loſs makes melament, my juſtice plead. But all my ſorrows ſoon will loſe their name If you raiſe him for whom Iruin'dam. A Prince who only does, as his juſt due, Deſerve to love you, and belov'd by you. Prin. Kath. Has yet the Queen ought of this buſineſs known? Tudor. I had but leave to wait on you alone. Thoſe common paths of Kings mine will not tread, To ſee by Pićture and by proxy wed. He'l make his Court at an unuſual rate; His is a love of liking, not of ſtate. And ſays, he does not for a Miſtreſs ſue To France, but humbly begs yourſelf of you. Prin. Kath. Ibut by Pićture did to him appear. Tudor. Yes, he has ſeen you in my Character. 'Tis far above the labour'd art of man To draw a Miſtreſs as a Lover can. Your Pićture took his fight 5 but you will find My words alone did Captivate his mind. Though you may think the pencils pow'r is great; It aims to paint a fire, but not a heat; Much leſs a heat which does from Love ariſe, And which is kindled by his Miſtreſs eyes. The Pencil to my words reſign'd the place; Thoſe drew your Soul, that painted but your face. F Madam,
Page 18

( 18) Madam, 'twas I who told him how your mind With greater luſtre then your beauty ſhin'd 5 That from the Charms of your diſcourſe and ſhape Men could no more then from your eyes eſcape. And I may juſtly, Madam, be afraid He ſaw, in me, you ačted all I ſaid; And to revenge that which you call'd a crime I on this Embaſſy am ſent by him. Prin. Kath. Tudor, into a new relapſe you fall; You ſeem'd to mourn at your loves Funeral: And I on that aſſurance pardon'd you. Tudor. I told you what was then, not what is now. If other words have wander'd in my talk, The Ghoſt then of my murder'd love did walk : And like a Ghoſt to none it ſhall appear, But before you, who are the Murtherer. Prim. Kath. If you’l to my eſteem your ſelf reſtore, Let me, by it, be viſited no more. Tudor. Madam, I'le ſtrive t'obey you from this hour. But, ſince the dead have o're their Ghoſts no power, If mine again the treſpaſs ſhould commit, My laſt requeſt is that you'l pardon it; And to ſo ſad a love ſome ſorrow give, Which troubles you when dead, as when alive. But for my King I muſt my ſuit renew 5 And beg to know what I muſt ſay from you. If to accept his paſſion you incline, You'l make his happineſs your own and mine. Since you deny . for my ſelf I move, Let me, againſt my ſelf, ſucceſsful prove. Prim. Kath. You may acquaint the King all you have ſaid Have in my thoughts a fit impreſſion made: That I (as all who have but heard his name) Believe his merit has acquir’d his fame; Though I with paſſion wiſh that he had choſe To raiſe his glory on remoter Foes. I never more can his addreſs receive Till from the Queen he has procur'd me leave. Tudor. Why do you, Madam, words ſo cruel ſpeaks Make him not for you to another ſeek; Since, in that way, ſhould he ſucceſsful prove Twili rather ſhew you can obey then love. Only to you let him his bleſſings own. Prém. Kath. I have declar'd my reſolution. Tudor. To what then muſt the wretched Tudor truſt 2 Prin. Kath. To find his cure in what he grants is juſt. Tudor. How can that heal him which does make his wound? Yet to obey you, Madam, he is bound. Bu t
Page 19

( 19) But if hereafter you ſhould chance to hear Some dying fighs which may offend your Ear; Forc'd from him by the fierceſt griefs aſſault, Be pleas'd to pity, not condemn the fault. [Exit Tudor. Prim. Kath. Oh! why is Love call'd Natures higheſt Law, When Title, Man's invention, does it awe? But 'tis the ſtrength which reaſon does impart That makes my blood give rules thus to my heart. If Nature reaſon onus did beſtow, Love, Natures dićtate, 'twould not overthrow. But reaſon is a bright reſiſtleſs fire Which Heav'n, not Nature, does in us inſpire. It is not Natures Child, but Natures King; And o're loves height does us to glory bring. As bodies are below, and Souls above So much ſhould reaſon be preferr'd to Love: Since Glory is the Souls moſt proper Sphere, It does but wander when it moves not there. This makes that King, who Courts me, France ſubdue 3 And makes meflye what elſe I would purſue. T H E THR ID ACT, Enter King Henry, Tudori Tudor. Hat I have ſaid ſhews all that I have done; The Daughter by the Mother muſt be won. Thoſe, Sir, who, ſerving Heav'n, to Heav'n pretend, By others mediation reach that end. King. That obligation, Tudor, I'le decline. She ſhall be all her own that muſt be mine. 'Tis for her glory ſhe her ſelf ſhould give The greateſt gift that I can e're receive. If from her will I differ, can ſhe hate My being for her int'reſt obſtinate? [Tudor offers to ſpeak. Go! what I told thee, Tudor, muſt be done : He ne're meets Honour who does danger ſhun. Tudor. A Subjećt muſt not with his King contend. King. My Subjećt? thou art more; thou art my Friend! Make haſtel for I will only ſtay behind Till I have orders for the Treaty ſign'd. [Exeunt ſeveral ways. Enter
Page 20

(20 J Enter Duke of Burgundy, and Charaloys, Burg. No, Son, the Treaty muſt not ſo proceed, Leſt of my help the Queen ſhould have no need: That envy'd pow'r which makes me uſeful here Is the effect not of her Love, but fear 5 Whilſt things continue in their preſent ſtate I can diſpoſe of France and England's Fate. The greateſt skill that I would wiſh from Heav'n, Is in a War to keep the Scale ſo even As neither Party ever may prevail But by his help whoſe hand does hold the Scale. Whilſt theſe two mighty Kingdoms diſagree I keepin ſafety my own Burgundie. Char. Have you forgot that vow, Sir, which you made To th’Engliſh King when France he did invade? That vow is to your Honour ſtill a debt. Eurg. A States-man all but int'reſt may forget, And only ought in his own ſtrength to truſt: "Tis not a States-man Vertue to be juſt. Char. Thoſe words which lately you in Council ſaid, Have on my Breaſt a deep impreſſion made. You urg'd that Aéts of juſtice are alone What can preſerve or muſt exalta Throne. Is your own counſel by your ſelf deſpis'd? Burg. I then for others, not my ſelf, advis'd. Reaſon ſhould ſtill appoint us what to do. char. You'l find that Reaſon has Religion too, Which is by inter-change of juſtice ſhown, Doing to all what to your ſelf is done. Burg. You meaſure Reaſon with a crooked line. Char. High Reaſon to Religion does incline. Burg. I, Son, reaſon of Cloyſters, not of State : Pow'r ſeldom is Religious to that height. Religion too not Reaſon is, but Faith. Char. I fear, Sir, if ſuch dang'rous ways you chuſe, Inſtead of ruling both, you both will loſe. Burg. A harder game then this I twice have plaid; And though, by fortune, I was ſtill betray'd 5 Yet ſtill to greater pow'r I reach'd at length: Antaeus-like, by falling, I got ſtrength. Beſides, De Chaſtel, by much art and pain, Hasbrought the Dauphin back to Court again; Who offers, if I’le urge the Queen for War, We equally betwixt us two ſhall ſhare All Armies and all Governments in France, And he'l forget the death of Orleance. Charl.
Page 21

(21) charl. O'Sir, from ſuch an offer'd Friendſhip flye; What only int'reſt tyes it will untye. And I preſume though you reſtor'd him France He'le ne're . the death of Orleance. I wiſh Heav'n ſooner may forgive it you. Burg. Alas young man, if you but truly knew What pow'rful Charms on ſweet revenge do wait You would have ačted what you think you hate. Charl. Beware, Sir, I beſeech you then in time Leſt his revenge may ſeem as ſweet to him. Burg. Theſe tender thoughts are graceful in a Son | I have your int’reſt, you, your duty ſhown. I'le hear their offers, though I them refuſe: When allis offer'd I the beſt will chuſe. [Exeums. Enter Dauphin, De Chaſtel. De chaft. Sir, I believe you now no longer fear That on vain hopes I beg'd your preſence here. The Queen, while you retir'd, had by her Arts So rob'd you of your future Subjećts hearts, That’twas your preſence only could reſtore Them to that duty which they owe to Power. Sir, Fortune too begins to pay her debts 5 For the Burgundian with your Servant treats 5 And ſuch an Ear to my diſcourſe he lent As makes me more then hope a good event. And, as a proof, he lik'd what I did ſpeak : He vow'd he would the Engliſh Treaty break. Nor is this all 5 the Counteſs of La Marr (To whom your Siſter grows particular) I have entirely wrought to favour you : She told me, and th’ Intelligence is new, That Blamount from the Queen has gain’d free leave Your Siſter ſhall a ſingle audience give To one whom Henry ſent with privacy. Dauph. His Love for her will fatal be to me, Unleſs th' effects of it I ſoon prevent. De Chaft. I therefore have obtain'd La Marrs conſent That you, conceal’d, ſhall in that room remain Where ſhe this meſſenger will entertain. By that concealment you may clearly know The roots of their deſigns, and how they grow. Dauph. Heav'n' for my Mother's faults makes me amends In ſending me a Friend who gets me Friends. I fear'd my Siſters pride, my Mothers hate, The Engliſh Kings great Love, and greater Fate, G Heipt
Page 22

(22 D Helpt by the ſubtle head of Burgundy, Might by a fatal Marriage ruine me. But this permiſſion thou for me haſt got May teach me both to know and break the Plot, When does this Love-Embaſſadour appear? Dechaft. They every moment, Sir, expect him here. Dauph. Then it is fit I inſtantly repair To that concealment promis'd by La Marr. [Exeunt. Enter Queen, and Great Conſtable. gueen. Yes, I have ſeen the Dauphin, but methought Though he has humbler geſtures with him brought, Shaping his looks to what he gently ſaid, Yet old reſentments clearly he betray'd. But yet, perhaps, thoſe Charms which Courts attend May to ſome mildneſs his fierce nature bend. I will apply all that is taught by Art Or wiſer Nature to reclaim his heart. 'Tis fit you know, e're you begin to Treat, The King of Englands paſſion is ſo great For my un marry'd Daughter, that I hear He'l quit all he does claim, to marry her. That this is true the Duke does undertake; And you great uſe may of that paſſion make. Conſt. Madam ' 'tis ſtrange, for ſhe was then as fair When offer'd to him to prevent a War. &ueen. He that by rules can judge a Lover's heart, Hasbrought into the world an unknown Art. But, having heard me, you muſt now be gone: Should the Duke know we two had been alone (You having both tane ſolemn leave of me) It might in him create a jealouſie. [Exeuwt. Enter Princeſs Katherine, and King Henry Incognito. King. Madam, when firſt my King from Tudor heard That you your perſon to the Queen referr'd, He ſent me hither humbly to deſire You'd to your eyes be juſt and to his fire; And would believe this right to both is due, That he his Fate ſhould only learn from you. He'l but from you receive his deſtiny, Whether you’l make him live, or have him dye. Prin, Kath. That anſwer, which by Tudor you have known, Is, Sir, my final reſolution. Nothing cane're perſwade me to forſake Reſults which duty and my reaſon make. King.
Page 23

(23) King. Let him not be a double Sacrifice; You kill'd him with your Words, and with your Eyes. Heav'n meant that Beauty, Natures greateſt force, Having exceeding pow'r, ſhould have remorſe. Valour, and it, the world ſhould ſo enjoy As both might overcome, but not deſtroy. Prin. Kaih. He who in Fight has all the French o're-thrown Cannot be kill'd by words ſpoke but by one. King. Yet he who has in France a Conqu'ring pow'r With joy does own you as his Conquerour. And that you may not doubt that this is true He is in perſon come to tell it you! The King takes off his Diſguiſe. I was Loves Heretick till you I ſaw, In that which Tudor ſaid, and Art did draw 5 Now, like an Heretick, I treated am By Love, who has condemn'd me to the flame. Your Pićture to reſiſt I wanted skill; Tº oppoſe th’ Original I want the will : Believe what of my ſelf is told by me. Prin. Kath. The King of England 1 ſure it cannot bel King. Madam 1 by doubting adde not to his pain; You cannot but know him in whom you reign. Prin. Kath. Since he 'twixt France and all her ſafety ſtands, How dares he truſt his perſon in her hands? King. He who adores you, and dares tell you ſo, What is there after which he dare not do 2 Prin. Kath. To what a ſtreight, Sir, have you brought me too? I muſt be falſe to France, or falſe to you. The Dauphin diſcovers himſelf. Dauph. I will enlarge you though you wicked grow In calling that a ſtreight which was not ſo: For ſhe who doubts if evil ſhe ſhould ačt Does, in that very doubt, a guilt contračt. No wonder now that France is faln ſo low The Daughter of it treating thus our Foe. Prin. Kath. Brother l I nothing of his coming knew; His being here ſurpriz'd me more then you. Dauph. Siſter, when he reveal’d himſelf, your eyes Shew'd greater ſigns of liking then ſurprize: And, to convince me clearly of your crime, You doubted if you ſhould diſcover him. King. I ſhall want patience to attend this ſtorm 1 Prim. Kath. The only fault you ſhould in mereform Is that I doubted whether I ſhould do As it became the Siſter, Sir, of you. But to the King Heav'n will this truth averr, I ne're would have reveal’d his being here, My
Page 24

( 34 ) My Father's vertue to the world is known; Who to my falſhood would not owe his Throne. If ačts of Treachery he does not hate, What he now ſuffers he deſerves from Fate. Since, by fair War, France now aſſaulted is, Let her ſink lower, or by Vertue riſe. To abjećt deeds I'le never condeſcend, Nor make the means unworthy of the end. King. Vertue a higher pitch did never riſe; It has a luſtre which out-ſhines her Eyes. Madam, in ſaying what you pleas'd to ſay, You broke that ſilence my reſpects did pay. And now, Sir, ſomething I ſhall let you ſee To make you grant you injur'd her, and me. Dauph. Have you a Paſs-port then for coming here 8 King. This is my Paſs-port to go ev'ry where ! Pointing to Whoe're a Paſs-port ſuch as this can ſhow #: Sword. Will find all places ſafe, or make 'em ſo. And, Sir, it is by this that you muſt ſwear Not to reveal what you diſcover'd here: This muſt be ſworn, and ſworn without a pauſe. Dauph. You ſhould ſubdue mee're you give me Laws. Yet, I will ſwear; but 'tis that to this chance I owe the pow'r to pay my debts to France. Debts, which ſo weighty were as I did bow More under them then France does under you. Thoſe debts which by a cruel Mother'sſway Till now I to my Birth could never pay. Fortune 1 and Siſter here I pardon you, For all you did and all that you would do! Since through her Blindneſs, and your Treachery, My ſelf Iſingle in condition ſee To make our France ſuch a revenge receive As all her Swords in Battel could not give. I only grieve one falſe to France and me Should of that juſtice th' only witneſs be: But yet that cauſe of grief ſhould diſ-appear Since ſeeing of your death will puniſh her. King. Oh could I juſtly think my ſelfſo bleſt That what relates to me could touch her breaſt, Though Iſhould periſhin this preſent ſtrife, My death would be more happy then my life, But ſince noſervice I have paid her yet Can make me hope a happineſs ſo great, I'le ſtrive to merit that which you but fear, By now revenging what you ſaid to her f---- But yet, we ſhould not fight ſhe being by.---- Dauph. That is the reaſon why you here muſt dye. LDraws his Sword.T King.
Page 25

(25) King. Then, Madam, you'l forgive me, if I now [King draws. Defend that life which does belong to you.----- Prin. Kath. Oh Heavens ! whom ſhall I call? perhaps I may Saving my Brothers life the King betray. [Exit, and enters again with LaMarr. You broke your truſt. Think on the Kings high worth. La Marr. Blamount's without and ſtays to lead him forth ! King cloſes with him and diſarmes him. Prin. Kath. Go open ſtrait the Garden Gallery, Keep for the Kings eſcape the paſſage free.----- Firſt for my Brother in the Lobby ſtay.----- - La Marr. When he is gone I'le ſhut it with this key. - Exit La Marr, Prin. Kath. My Brother is diſ-arm'd what ſhall I do? King. Your life, young Prince, is at my mercy now. Prin. Kath. Sir, for my Brothers life let me implore; Nature ſpeaks now as Honour did beforel King. I to your pleaſure ever will ſubmit.----- 'Tis to your blood you owe my ſparing it.----- Your life I give you at the Princeſs word; And, for her ſake, I here reſtore your Sword. But, Sir, remember y'are oblig'd by me No more t'invade your Siſters privacy 3 Nor praćtiſe to obſtrućt that paſſions way Which is a debt ſo due as I muſt pay. Theſe not obſerving my revenge ſhall prove As ſtrong to you as ſhe ſhall find my love. But if in both your courteſie be ſhown, What here has paſt ſhall vaniſh as unknown. Dauph. Your Fortune, Sir, is great o're France and me; Great is your promiſe too of ſecreſie. But if I can myſelf with filence pleaſe, You may thank that, and not your Menaces. [Exit Dauphin. Prin. Kath. I'le follow him t'obſerve which way he takes, Whilſt, for the King, ſhe th'other paſſage makes. Sir, you ſhould ſtay a while ; I'le ſtraight return LExit. King. Oh Heavens ! why have I given her cauſe to mourn? Blamount, whoſe condućt did me hither bring Will ſurely with a Friend, and with a King, His promiſe keep 5 which was to ſee me out. I cannot his unblemiſh’d honour doubt. But I will ſtay to ſpeak with her though all The World were to be bury'd in my fall. [Enter Princeſs: Madam, Can you the cauſe in me forgive Which gave you terrours here and make you grieve? When you he injures not, much more then me, Your preſence will his Sanctuary be. H Priaº.
Page 26

( 26 ) Prim. Kath. I will forgive you, Sir, all terrours here, ff by your quick return you'l end my fear. To all your longer ſtay Alarms will give; My Brother's Nature is Vindicative: I fear from his revenge all that is ill, Here, where he wants no pow'r to ad his will, King. A greater ruine, Madam, I fore-ſee Then he, though in this place, can caſt on me 5 If I from hence ſhould to my Camp remove Before I know how you receive my love. Prim. Kath. The firſt day, Sir, you'l think it were unfit I ſhould do more then only know of it. Nor have you any reaſon to deſpair When for yopr ſafety I expreſs my care. King. Vérite may make you be my ſafeties friend; But to what's dearer to me I pretend. My ſafety lies not in my going hence But in that bleſſing you may here diſpence. I would not ſafety without that enjoy; And with it, nought my ſafety can deſtroy. Prin. Kath. I will ſay anything you'l have me ſay Rather then keep you here in ruines way. But yet, that what I ſpeak may not appear To be the dićtates only of my fear, If you were gone I'le to myſelf conſeſ, Such vertue and reſpect you did expreſs, That what I thought an Age had not the power To act in me, you acted in one hour. Now, Sir, you ſhould retire, and give a Maid The eaſe to bluſh alone for what ſhe ſaid. King. Madam, Igo: but go ſo charm'd from hence. Both by your eyes, and vertues influence, That 'tis impoſſible for me to know To which Imoſt of Adoration owe. But if the humbleſt duty, higheſt fire, Which man ere ſhew'd, or love did e're inſpire, Can be oblations fitting to be paid, You'lne're need bluſh for what you now have ſaid. Enter La Marr. La Marr. Sir, Elamount ſtays for you. This is your way ! Prin. Kath. She is your Guide, º: heed Sir of delay ! [Exewnt LaMarr, King Who can or Love or Reaſons Pow'r expreſs? One oft does more then th'other, often leſs, Reaſon makes me a Subjećts paſſion flye; Love o're a King gains ſuch a Vićtory. As
Page 27

( 27) As makes him venture life, and, what is far More great, his growing Glories of the War, That he his paſſion only might relate And from my lips might hear his doubtful Fate. Sure, to return ſome love for love ſo great, Is not to give a gift but pay a debt. [Exeumi, Enter Dauphin, and de Chaſtel. Dauph. Oh Friend, if I had kill'd him in that fight, My Glory I had rais'd to ſuch a height That, maugre all my Mothers arts and hate, I had reſtor'd, and I had rul'd the State. All their ſucceſſes had with him been dead; For he's his Armies Soul as well as head. Why did my Stars ſo fair a hope afford (Leaving, O France 1 thy Fortune to my Sword) Yet not to kill or periſh by my Foe; But both my Life and Sword I to him owe ? De chaft. Your mind, Sir, is too great to feel deſpair For one ill chance in Duel, or in War. Dauph. To be o'recome would be the greateſt curſe If to out-live that Fate were not a worſe. The firſt, perhaps, was Fortunes fault alone 5 But, Friend, the laſt too clearly is my own. Dechaft. If of that ſtain your heart has ſuch a ſenſe Let's waſh it offin's blood, e're he go hence. Dauph. Should the firſt ačt of life which he did give Meanly the Giver of his life deprive? Becauſe blind Fortune guilty is to me Shall I, to my own ſelf, more guilty be 2 No, my De Chaſtel; though he be my Foe, Yet he hath ſtill moſt gen'rouſly been ſo 3 And by no Aćts of mine he ne're ſhall dye Unleſs by ſuch as rais'd him up ſo high. De chaft. Let me then,ſingle, your revenge purſue. Dauph. Whoto a Crime conſents does act it too. If it were fit, the ačt it ſelf I'de do: And what's unfit, ſhall not be done by you. De chaft. I hope, Sir, then the Treaty I begun Will put you in ſo high a poſture ſoon That the diſgrace, which but a few now ſees, Shall in the Eyes of crowds of Witneſſes Be ſo waſh'd off as ſhall your ſorrow cure. Pauph. Thy hope's uncertain, my diſgrace is ſure, But what of good is meant for me by Fate Thou ought'ſt to haſten or 'twill come too late. [Exewmt. Eºfe;
Page 28

(28) Enter Warwick, and Tudor Diſgui,'d. Warw. Elamount deſir'd us to expect him here. Tudor. The King did never ſhew us how to fear, Elſe we ſhould tremble now at Blamount's ſtay. Warw. Would Love had led the King a ſafer way. Kings, in whoſe chances Nations fall or riſe, Hazard too much in private Gallantries 5 The odds againſt them checks their luck and skill. Tudor. "Tis true, but Loves great Gameſters reckon ſtill (Whilſt boldly they the ſtake that's faireſt chuſe) What they may win, and not what they may loſe. Enter Blamount. Blam. The King hath ſent for you. I'le bring you ſtraight Where he is ſafe out of the reach of Fate. You muſt to horſe. I'le tell you what has paſt. Tudor. You free us from a pain too great to laſt. [Exehni. Enter Princeſs Katherine, and Princeſs Anne. Prin. Kath. My fear did then my reaſon overthrow; I could ſcarce think, much leſs know what to do. Prim. An. Why did you not by poſitive commands Reſtrain at leaſt the King of England's hands? Prin. Kath. Should Iſo much my Brothers ſafety prize As to procure it by mean remedies? Ah! ſince’twas only Love brought Henry here, Should I have made his Love his Murderer? The Dauphin to the King injurious was : Heaven would not let thoſe wrongs unpuniſh'd paſs. Prin. An. His wrongs more then your own your anger move. Prin. Kath. That's what I owe my Vertue, not his Love. Prin. An. I doubt the Dauphin ſome raſh thing will do. Prin. Kath. La Marr was to attend our interview 5 Who did, corrupted by De Chaffel, bring The Dauphin to obſerve me with the King. I from the terrour of their Fight did flye And met her, who, to ſalve her Treachery, (Having a full command of all the keys) Diſpos'd their paſſage forth by ſev'ral ways. Alamount with all the Friends that he could get I have engag'd to ſecond his Retreat. Ihope my care in that will happy prove. Prin. Am. Where there is ſo much care there is ſome love, Prin, Kath. I know not whether it belove or no, But ſuch great things he did both ſay and do That
Page 29

(29) That I, dear friend, inſenſibly am led - To think that may be true which now you ſed. Who can, when ſuch a Vićtor will advance, Reſiſt that vertue which does conquer France # Prin. An. The proof he lately gave you of his flame, Madam, is ſuch as is above a name. All trodden ways in Love he does deſpiſe As things below his paſſion and your Eyes. Prin. Kath. Condemn not then my being in ſome pain Till I aſſurance of his ſafety gain: Which bleſſing that I may the ſooner know This proof of Friendſhip mine does beg of you, That we dividedly our ſelves concern Which of us firſt the welcom news ſhall learn. Prim. An. I'le ſtill obey what-ever you command, And, what I hear, you ſtraight ſhall underſtand. Prin. Kath, May Heaven ſo guide the King that I may hear He is beyond the proſpect of my fear ! [Exemnt. T H E F O U R T H A CT. The Curtain being drawn mp, The Duke of Burgundy, the Conſtable, Earl of Charaloys, and the Biſhop of Arras are ſeen ſitting at one ſide of a Table, attended by the French officers of state 5 on the other ſide, are ſeated the Duke of Exeter, Duke of Bedford, the Arch-Biſhop of Canterbury, and the Earl of Warwick, attended by the Engliſh. Burg. QInce all, my Lords, is done by usand you UWhich is, as previous to a Treaty, due 5 Delays in the affair ſhould be abhor'd 5 Thoſe impious are when peace may be reſtor'd: Therefore, my Lords, 'twere fit you would expreſs On what conditions you will grant a peace. Exet. Thoſe who our right and ſtrength well underſtand Need not be told, that we all France demand. Conſt. You would by meer demand a queſtion make 3 No Treaty gives all that ſucceſs can take. This high reſolve does more become the Field: Tis nobler all to loſe then all to yield. Bedf. And you'l confeſs it is more nobly done, By Arms then Treaty to regain a Throne; But yet my Brother thought a Treaty good That his French Subjećts might preſerve their blood. Arch-Biſh. That King proves well the juſtice of his claim Who, for his Subjećts ſakes, is deaf to Fame, I
Page 30

( 30 ) E. of char. Had we no Plea but what preſcription gives That were enough whilſt any French-man lives. Warw. In pleading ſo, my Lord, yourſelves you wrong; That can no Title be but to the ſtrong. For what can a protećtive aid afford Againſt the cleareſt Right, and ſharpeſt Sword £ Fiſh. of Ar. From what pretence ſoe're a claim you draw France knows no right above her Salique Law : A Law which is both rational, and old 5 It never was by time or force controul’d. Exet. You but imperfectly your ſtory know; Or ſpeaking thus, you hope that we do ſo. That Law (if made) was paſt on sala's banks; And was not made for France but for the Franck; ; A Germain people who in Camps were bred, And therefore ſtill renounc'd a Female head. Bedf. A Law, which only from arm'd Tumults roſe, And which Heaven's Law and Nature's does oppoſe. My Lord of Canterbury 'tis in you To ſpeak how France we challenge as our due. Arch-Biſh. Philip the Fourth, as your own ſtories tell, Had Lewis, Philip, Charles, and Iſabel 5 Edward the Second did his Daughter wed; His Sons did all to the French Crown ſucceed. Who, no Sons leaving, Philip, the Uncle's Son, Did from the Father's Daughter take the Crown; And kept it during injur'd Edward's life : To whom 'twas due, injuſtice, by his Wife. That Edward, dead, Edward the Third, his Son, Did, in his Mothers right, demand his Crown. Creſſy and Poiółiers to the World declare How Heav'neſteem'd his Sword in that juſt War, Death, Natures Conquerour, did him ſubdue ; And his great Son, the greater of the two. Soon after, Civil Wars our Iſle deſtroy'd: Our Swords againſt our ſelves were long imploy'd, Whilſt ſick with Civil War, Prides worſt diſeaſe, Webled in France, and loſt three Provinces. But, now when thoſe Inteſtine Wars are done, We come here to receive, or take our own. Bedf. You boaſt your Salique Law ſo juſt, and old, That it by time or force was ne're controul’d. But tell, I pray, what part of it decreed That Martelſhould King childerick ſucceed 2 Or how it could, if not by wreſted ſhift, Make Capet Succeſſour to Lewis the Fifth, When Charles of Lorrain ſhould have fill'd the place : The firſt Heir-male left of your Royal Race 2 - Exet,
Page 31

(31) Exet. 'Tis true, the States of France, by their decree, Did call King Capet to the Monarchie. Who wiſely then did Royal In'treſt ſave, Making them think that what they paid, they gave: For ſo to his juſt right he joyn'd their power, By which he vanquiſh'd his Competitor. Thus when by Arms the Salique Law was try’d Heaven judg'd the Title to the Female fide: For the chief right which Capet had to plead Was that he did King Lewis Siſter wed. Arch-Biſh. From this great Capet, who that Law repeal’d, All your ſucceeding Kings their Crowns have held. By which, my Lords, we think we clearly ſhow, If then his claim was good, ours now is ſo, Warw. Or, if you grant the States by their decree Can give to whom they will this Monarchie, If you their pow'r ſo highly will advance, We need but conquer to have right to France. Burg. Since you, my Lords, ſo pry into our right, How comes your Red-roſe now to rule your White * Blame not what France to that Duke Charles has done When a Lancaſtrian head does wear your Crown. What by both ſides may equally be ſed That neither, as his proper right, can plead. But if your Roſes Heav'n ſhouldere unite Then you may challenge France with better right. None of the preſent Line we will admit 5 The houſe of Tork can only plead for it. Exet. All of that houſe allow my Nephew's right 3 And, under him, they for this Empire fight. If Fate ſhould them to Englands Throne advance They ſhall poſſeſ, with it, the Throne of France: By them as Subjećts he is ſerv'd and fear'd. Burg. When they are Kings again they ſhall be heard, My Lords, that all this vain diſcourſe may ceaſe, What ſay you, if, t'advance you to a peace, We give your King the Princeſs Katherine, And with her ſuch vaſt Treaſure we aſſign, As may for ever all your Title buy To Anjou, Aquitain, and Normandy. Bedf. How came ſuch abjećt offers in your thought 3 One ought not to be ſold, north other bought. Burg. Then know, my Lords, the War you muſt purſue 5 The Sword muſt end what Treaty could not do. He riſes, and the reſt after him. Exet. "Tis to the Sword we muſt have our recourſe ! Where right's deny'd 'tis juſtice to uſe force. Redf.
Page 32

( 3.2 ) Bedf. Pippin and Capet ſuch ſharp Swords did draw As twice repeal'd this Pagan-Salique-Law. My Brother then may charge it as your crime If he preſume to do it the third time. His Sword you'l quickly feel as ſharp as theirs ; Since force muſt plead the right of Femal-heirs...[salutes the EI, My Lords, farewell we cannot here agree liſh Lords. But they'l begin th’euſuing War at Sea. Their Fleet's prepar'd 3 and, by this morning Poſt, Our Navy too does call me to the Coaſt. [Exemnt. Enter the Queen, and Counteſ of La Marr. La Marr. So far this Treaty has already gone That the Burgundian did aſſure your Son The Engliſh Treaty never ſhould ſucceed; Which with the Dauphin's paſſion ſo agreed As he has offer'd him to ſhare all France And to forget the Death of Orleance. This, Madam, but too clearly let's you ſee They mean to force you from the Regency: Which the falſe Duke ſoon after will cnjoy : Firſt he'l divide, and then your houſe deſtroy. ueen. This ſervice, my La Marr, is far above All Preſents I can make you, but my Love. I thought De chaſtel had ſo fierce a mind As he to Love could never have inclin'd 5 But in that thought I find I injure you : This conqueſt only to your Eyes is due. La Marr. Madam, 'twas only Love which could have preſt This fatal ſecret from De chaffel's breaſt. Nor would I e're to him have faithleſs been, But to ſave France, and to preſerve my Queen. gueen. Thy Queen, half loſt, thy Friendſhip does reſtore 3 And yet thy Friendſhip muſt oblige her more.---- Enter Burgundy, and Conſtable. The Queen caſts her eyes on Burgundy. That haughty Burgundy ſhall ſhortly Mourn.---- Kind Couſin! you have made a quick return.---- Burg. The Dukes of Bedford and of Exeter, Joyn'd with their talking Biſhop, did appear So much averſe to all that we could ſpeak As we in Duty did the Treaty break; Duty to you. We offer'd all you ſent, But only France can give their pride content. Queen. Since theſe bold Foes take pleaſure to make War (Proud that they dare do worſe then others dare, And
Page 33

(33) And prouder with ſucceſs) let us provide Tº advance our merit and debaſe their pride. Burg. Madam, in this juſt cauſe I ſhall afford Th' aſſiſtance of my Counſel and my Sword. een. It is on thoſe my chief dependance lies: For you, my Lord, both pow'rful are and wiſe. Prepare for Aétion, and let Treaties ceaſe: The wiſe may loſe by War, fools loſe by Peace. Burg. The better to obey what you deſire Excuſe me, Madam, if I now retire. [Exit. gaeen. He being gone, my Lord, I'le let you know What France, and I, do to this Lady owe. The Duke has broke the Engliſh Treaty now That to the Dauphin he may keep his Vow. And falſe De Chaſtel made 'em both agree Out of my hands to force the regency. And then between themſelves they are to ſhare The high employments both of Peace and War. coaſt. This Duke does all my faculties amaze: Yet ſtill he lov'd to walk in crooked ways. gºueen. They all ſhallſink and their own ruine find Within that depth which they for me deſign'd. My Secretary Perrot underſtands The Art of counterfeiting Seals and hands : I'le make him ſtraight write to the Engliſh King, As from the Duke, propoſing every thing Which falſe De chaſtel offer'd from my Son 5 Yet when all promis'd by the King is done, Though leſs then what my Son did e're propoſe Him he'l forſake, and with the Engliſh cloſe. La Marr ſhall entertain De Cheftelſo As of the Duke he may ſuſpicious grow. La Marr. Some doubts which ſeem perplex'd I will unfold; I'le ſay, he with the King does Treaty hold. &ueen. Which can no other way be brought to light But by thoſe Letters ta'ne which he may write : Theſe Letters ſhall, though forg'd, authentickſeem; And muſt be intercepted too by him. La Marr. This will between them raiſe a jealouſie. conſt. And when that ſeed is ſown'twill never dye. The Dauphins Soul I never underſtood If he revenge not this affront with blood. Queen. My Lord, withdraw, and write with inſtant care Exit Conſtable. The Letter for Du Perrot: you, La Marr, Shall ſooth De Chaſtel with your former Art, And ſubtly play your ſelf in all your part. [Exit La Marr. K Great
Page 34

(34) Great troubles to a Throne the way prepare 5 And greater troubles muſt preſerve us there. Yet the Ambitious envy thoſe who reign : They know the Pomp of Crowns, but not the pain. [Exit. The Princeſs Katherine, meeting Princeſs Anne. Prin. Kath. Madam, what News? Prin. An. The worſt that I could bring: They have diſſolv'd the Treaty with the King. Peace is quite fled, which did before but hide Her chearful face. The Sword muſt all decide. Thou forward hope, Wars voice has call'd thee back! Prin. Kath. I ne're could think ſuſpence was ſuch a rack. Prin. Am. Suſpence, in anything, a pain does prove; But turns a torment when 'tis mix’d with love. Enter La Marr in haſte. La Marr. Madam, I doubt the Queen and Duke have heard Of that diſguiſe in which the King appear'd. The buſie Whiſp'rers run from place to place 3 And fear, or news, is ſeen in every Face. Small Parties meet; then to a throng they grow, As Clouds unite before a ſtorm does blow. Enter Blamount. Blam. Madam, I left the Dauphin with the Queen; They have this morning in a Tempeſt been: Their meeting was both violent and ſhort : Your Brother inſtantly will leave the Court. He ſaid he would no longer vainly ſtrive, But boldly take what ſome deny to give. Safely the Duke th' event of this attends, And his apartment fills with Guards and Friends. Enter Earl Charelloys. E. of char. Madam, juſt now I from the Dauphin came: His Friends are kindled with his anger's flame. He is to ſudden Execution bent 5 To Deeds ſo ſwift as he'l too late repent. He puts on wings for what he will purſue; And ſays my Father does uſurp his due: And fierce De chaftel too (which all admire) Againſt his Nature ſtrives to quench this fire. Enter French Lady. Lady. Madam, you are expected by the Queen. Prim. Kath. This ſtorm will fall asſoon as it is ſeen. My Lord, I'le ſtrive to make the Queen apply To this diſtemper a quick remedy. harl Charl,
Page 35

(35) charl. I'le ſtill near my ſuſpicious Father ſtay 3 Too much ſuſpition does it ſelf betray. Prin. An. Brother, I’le follow / Madam, we in vain In ſtorms of Love of other ſtorms complain. Love's Queen did riſe from the Tempeſtuous Sea; Which ſhews that Love in ſtorms muſt ever be. [Exenat. Enter Tudor. Tudor. By what the King related I may ſee The Princeſs is for ever loſt to me. 'Tis evident ſhe has her Love reſign'd To his great Title and his greater mind. Why ſhould I thus, what ſhe has done deplore? She did but that which I had done before. But, Fate, thou art unjuſt in making me To quit the Love yet keep the jealouſie : Which is of Loves fair tree the fouleſt fruit 3 A Branch whoſe nouriſhment offends the root. Shall jealouſie a pow'r o're judgment gain Though it does only in the fancy reign 2 With knowledge thou art inconſiſtent ſtill; The minds foul Monſter whom fair truth does kill. Thy tyranny ſubverts even Natures Laws; For oft thou haſt effects without a cauſe. And, which thy ſtrength or weakneſs does detect, Thou often haſt a cauſe without effect. In all thou doſt, thou ever doſt amiſs, Seeſt what is not, or feeſt not that which is. Whilſt thou doſt live ſickneſs does thee purſue; And he who cures thee needs muſt kill thee too. Enter King. King. Tudor you muſt not think my Friendſhip rude Though it purſue you to your ſolitude. Some fatal ſorrow has your heart oppreſt: Divide it, and ſend half into my Breaſt. Tudor. What is it can invade me in exceſs, But joy, whilſt I your favour, Sir, poſſeſs 2 King. If my warm favour has your bleſſing made Why leave you then that Sunto ſeek this ſhade 2 Tudor. Sir, from your bounties I retire to ſhow I would prevent th’increaſe of what I owe. I ſtudy here to pay my former ſcore; And I avoid your making of it more. King. Tudor, I no ſuch anſwer will admit 3 I muſt be paid with truth and not with wit. The truth of Friendſhip has forſook the Earth : Thou doſt diſſemble thy accuſtom'd mirth.
Page 36

( 36 ) A ſudden figh does thy feign'd ſniles detect : Nature betrays more Art then I ſuſpect. Tuaor. Let me not, Sir, be for that ſhape deſpis'd In which I am ev'n to my ſelf, diſguis’d. King. Friendſhip above all tyes does bind the heart; And faith in Friendſhip is the nobleſt part. 'Tis ill, unaskt, not to have told your pain 5 But worſe, when askt, if you excuſes feign. Farewel, frail man; our Friendſhip here muſt end. You wrong your Honour, when you wrong a Friend. King offers to go out. Tudor. Stay, Sir, and to your vertue I'le unfold The ſaddeſt ſtory that was ever told. King. Why with thy King ſhould there ſuch trifling be; With Friendſhip too, which ſacred is as he? Tudor. My grief is yet cloſe pris'ner in my Breaſt; Whilſt there confin'd, 'twill only me moleſt 5 But may diſquiet you when got . home 5 Complaints, when paſt relief grow troubleſome. King. That grief does far all other griefs tranſcend Which greater grows when truſted to a Friend. Friendſhip in noble hearts would never reign If Friendſhips duty ſhould be Friendſhips pain. For eaſe of ſorrow Friends from Heaven were ſent. Tudor, diſpatch, and try th' experiment. Tudor. Why ſhould you preſs me Sir 2 it will not out.---- King. Thoſe fear their Cure who their Phyſicians doubt. Tudor. Force me not, Sir, to tell you what can be No eaſe to you, and yet a rack to me. King. Tell it I ſay I Tudor. I'letell it though I dye---- I am in Love. King. In Love 2 and ſo am I. Is this the ſtrangeſt ſtory e're was known 2 Tudor. Pray Heav'n you think not ſo e're it be done. King. Proceed. Tudor. She Sir, who does my heart ſubdue Is by my Friend ador'd with paſſion too: And, which is worſe, his paſſion he did tell To me, e're mine I durſt to him reveal. And, worſer yet, that Friend does me employ T'aſſiſt his Love whilſt Imy own deſtroy. I loſe my Miſtreſs if I condeſcend To this, not doing it I loſe my Friend. But, which is worſt of all, I'le not deny He does deſerve her ſo much more then I That ſhould ſhe, for my ſake, make him deſpair She muſt be more unjuſt then ſhe is fair. And
Page 37

(37) And, whilſt ſhe does admit of my addreſs, The wrong I do deſtroys my happineſs. King. 'Tis difficult. What haſt thou fixtupon 2 Tudor. What I thought juſt I have already done. King. Why thenis ſo much time in ſorrow ſpent 2 For what is juſtly done canſt thou repent £ Tudor. In what I did ſuch juſtice I have ſhown That I would do't again, were it undone. But, Sir, I cannot yet that grief remove Which ſprings from Friendſhip that conteſts with Love. As after ſtorms the Sea does troubled ſhow Though the fierce Winds, which mov’d it,ceaſe to blow. King. No wonder griefs wild Sea ſo high is wrought Since in your Breaſt Friendſhip and Love have fought. But tell me now thy Friends and Miſtreſs name For whom your ſelf you nobly overcame. He who you think deſerves much more then you I muſt conclude deſerves my Friendſhip too. Tudor. Oh, Sir! in that your pardon I implore : Too much is ſaid 5 force me to ſay no more. King. Tudor, that man muſt high in merit be For whom you'l do, more then you'l truſt with me, Tudor Tudor. Forgive me, Sir, if more I dare not ſay : #. Let me in ſilence mourn my Life away. King. Riſe, but no more I thee my Friend will call: For he's no Friend, if not a Friend in all. In part thouſhew'ſt me what I whole would ſee; A half Friend's worſe then a whole Enemy. Thy ſilence by a ſtrićter way I'le break. By thy Allegiance I command thee ſpeak! Tudor, Oh do not think my Soul is ſunk ſo low That ought can act what Friendſhip could not do. King. Thy want of it, this paſſion from me draws: Excuſe th’effects of which thou art the cauſe. No longer, Tudor, at this rate contend - - With him who is thy King,and more, thy Friend. [Embraces him. Tudor. The charming name of Friend will make me ſpeak When, even my King, could not my ſilence break. You are that Friend whoſe name I would conceal 5 Who is the Miſtreſs then I need not tell. Shee too did this revealment, Sir, conſtrain : What but my pain could have diſclos'd my pain? King. Oh why ſo late doſt thou this truth avow 2 Tudor. I fear too early I have told it now. King. Thus to have us’d thy Friendſhipbreeds a pain Which nothing can tranſcend but her diſdain. Tºdor. But had I told it ſooner, Sir, to you Could you have then done more then you can now 2 L Sinee
Page 38

(38) Since all I ask, for what you make me ſay, Is but your pardon that I durſt obey. King. My ignorance alone has made me do What Love itſelfcould not have forc'd me to. Tudor. Though, Sir, the Charms of Lovers hopes are ſweet, Yet mine I freely proſtrate at your feet. King. My Rival thus in Love thouſhun'ſt to be Yet thus in honour doſt out-rival me. I to no Monarch ere that glory gave 5 Much leſs my Subjećt ſhall that glory have. If, Tudor, you would now ſuppreſs your flame, To ſhew your Friendſhip, or exalt your fame, That ačt on neither ſcore I will allow ; For I'm in both, as nuch concern’d as you. So greatly, Tudor, thou haſt done for me As nought ca:, pay it but the ſame for thee. Tudor. I cannot, Sir, imagine your deſign. King. To be your Advocate as you were mine, And give you leave your paſſion to purſue. And, which is more, I do command you too. Tudor. Forgive me if this offer I refuſe. King. Reſolve to take it or thy King to loſe. Tudor. Then I'le embrace it, and diſpute no more. And give me leave a pardon to implore From all the better World who Lovers are, From all who ſhall be ſo, and all that were, That I againſt them did ſo guilty prove As to conſider ought in Love, but Love. King. Tudor, this gallantry obliges more Then all thy pleading for me did before. But, if I ever can attend again That Sov'raign Beauty which does o're us reign, I'legive her then ſuch Charaćters of thee As ſhall out-ſpeak what thou haſt ſaid of me. We then will be each others Advocate; And from her ſentence each receive his Fate. Tudor. Though this is more then I could hope 5 yet ſtill That which revives my hopes my hopes does kill. For when deſcribing me, you pleaſe to add All that you think is likely to perſwade, Even that a ſurer way will rather prove To ſhew your Vertue then advance my Love. King. Fear not, you may ſucceed; though drawing you I ſhall but Copy what for me you drew. Tudor. Yet thoſe will find, who juſtly ballance things, I only Subjects taught, but you teach Kings / [Exemnt. T H E

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 39

(39) THE FIFT H A CT. Enter the King, the Duke of Exeter, the Duke of Bedford, and Tudor. King. O'; R good ſucceſſes come together ſtill; And, as the good concur, ſo do the ill. I have obſerv'd it, Uncle, have not you? Exet. Tis, Sir, as worthy notice as 'tis true. King. This ſeems, methinks, t'accuſe their ignorance Who attribute our great events to chance: For though it may, when ſlowly one event Follows another, look like accident 5 Yet when together many ſwiftly joyn It ſhews a power which rules us by deſign. Whilſt we ſucceed at Land, to Heav'n we owe The Triumph of a Naval overthrow. Brother, your tongue may claim the right alone To tell what Heav'n by your brave hand has done. Bedf. But little fame, where many Conqu'rours were, Could juſtly fall to any ſingle ſhare. When we had ſail'd your Fleet in fight of France, From the Seins mouth the French did ſtrait advance t Their number pleas'd us whom it meant to fright; We joy'd at any thing that made them fight. But whilſt to gain the Wind both Navies ply'd, Both, to the Southward, a third Fleet deſcry'd. Whoſe courſe, by bearing, to our Fleet was bent : We thought to them, they fear'd to us,’twas ſent. When drawing near us, 'twas perceiv'd by all, Their Flags diſplay'd the Arms of Portugal. . That proſp’rous King, your Kinſman, and your Friend His Royal Navy to your aid did ſend, Hearing the French had rigg'da numerous Fleet. King. This ſhews his Friendſhip, like his virtue, great : I am oblig'd, and more I could not be Then by a Debt, great as your Vićtory. Bedf. The Valiant Bourbon, Admiral of France, Shrunk not at this, but ſwiftli'er did advance. That ſhout with which we did their Navy greet, Th'affrighted ſhore did Eccho to their Fleet. At the firſt ſhock, ſome ſhips we ſunk and burn'd : Our order ſoon was to a Chaos turn'd. The Portugal's ſtill like the Engliſh fought; Envying our Valour, or elſe by it taught.
Page 40

(40) A thouſand Deeds were worthy in that fight Though not, Sir, of your hands, yet of your ſight. But what the French perform'd, worthy your praiſe, Serv'd but the more your Glory, Sir, to raiſe. For your reſiſtleſs Genius there did reign, And madeus gather Laurels on the Main : As proſp'rous Stars, though abſent to the ſence, Bleſs thoſe they ſhine for by their influence. Five hundred Ships were ſunk or taken there Whoſe Flags ſeem Wreaths for you, the Conquerour. King. This high ſucceſs at Sea, which Heav'n has ſent, Has made me Maſter of that Element. When Monarchs have at Land a Battel loſt It may, to raiſe new Troops, ſome Treaſure coſt. But to repair loſt Fleets is not ſo cheap; Woods are a Crop which men but once can reap. That Prince, whoſe Flags are bow'd to on the Seas, Of all Kings ſhores keeps in his hand the Keys: No King can him, he may all Kings invade; And on his Will depends their Peace and Trade. Trade, which does Kings and Subjećts wealth increaſe; Trade, which more neceſſary is then Peace. Exet. If the Worlds trade may to our hand be brought Though purchas'd by a War 'tis cheaply bought. Tudor. He who an liland rules and not the Sea, Is not a King, and may a Pris'ner be. Bedf. In this Vićtorious Fleet your Parliament Have ſuch ſupplies of Men and Treaſure ſent That France will now in humble poſture ſeek The Treaty which her former Pride did break. King. Thoſe Royal Limbs will not their head forſake; My Glory they their own kind Int'reſt make. Their Love does with their Duty nobly ſtrive 3 And giving thus, unaskt, they doubly give.----- Oh Tudor! though my Sword at Land and Sea Docs conquer others, Love does conquer me. Whilſt under his reſiſtleſs pow'r I groan Fate cannot make me joyful with a Crown. Tudor. May ſtill the greatneſs of your fame increaſe; And, for your quiet, may your love grow leſs. Enter Warwick. Warw. From the French Court Count Blamount, Sir, is ſent And newly is alighted at your Tent. King. Admit him, but he ſoon may haſten home If from the falſe Burgundian he is come. [Exit Warwick: A Prince worthy of nothing but of hate; Early in promiſe, in performance late. H e
Page 41

(41) He cheaply rates my Honour with his own; And meanly thinks that I would ſell a Crown. In wronging his high Birth he injures me And gives my Sword a right to Burgundy. Enter Warwick, Blamount,Chareloys Diſguis'd. Blam. If a ſurprizing wonder may be news, Such as does joy and horrour too infuſe, Ibring it, Sir : for he, whoſe head and Sword Made War and Peace the Creaturés of his word; The Great Burgundian who in France did reign, Is by appointment of the Dauphin ſlain. King. Heaven's hand is ſure, though it the ſtroke defer. Blam. The face of France does full of change appear. King. This Murder ſudden was : but what late crime Could urge the Dauphin thus to Murder him? Blam. The Duke (who ſaid, Treaties would ne're advance That Peace with you which was deſir'd by France) Did therefore for the Dauphin's Friendſhip ſue. ſyon appointed was for interview 5 To which the Duke did inſtantly repair; There to reſolve how to contrive the War: The Dauphin met at the appointed time; But, whilſt the Duke humbly ſaluted him, De chaſtel, unprovok'd by decdor word, In the Dukes heart did ſheath his guilty Sword: And then the Dauphin publickly did own That this ſtrange ačt by his command was done 3 And ſaid it was a juſtice due to France Becauſe the Duke had Murder'd Orleance. King. Through what falſe Opticks domens paſſions look? In this wild juſtice he out-ſin'd the Duke: Blam. De chaſteltalk'd (though few did credit it) Of Letters taken which the Duke had writ, Th’ expreſs confeſt that they to you were meant, In which he offer'd (if you would conſent To what he there, Sir, did propoſe to you,) He would unthrone the King and Dauphin too. King. I by the Duke have been ſo courſly us'd That what he had propos'd I had refus'd. Will not the Son revenge the Fathers fall? [Chareloys pulls off his Diſguiſe. Charl. Yes, Sir, and does for your aſſiſtance call. The blood of Sov'raiga Princes baſely ſpilt Calls loud to Monarchs to revenge the Guilt. My reaſon, not my paſſion, makes me flye From a falſe Friend to a brave Enemy. If you'l revenge high blood, ignobly ſhed, The Crown .rance I'le ſettle on your head. And M Il
Page 42

( 4.2 ) And, when you wed the Princeſs Katherine, The States ſhall then entail it on your Line. Of thoſe moſt are my Friends and my Allies; And they are all ſo Noble and ſo Wiſe, That with one voice they will aloud diſdain The proud injuſtice of a Murd'rers reign. King. Your Father's faults I'le caſt into his Grave; And will revenge that blood I could not ſave. And ſince you are ſo generous and juſt, That, without Treaty, you my honour truſt, You ſhall, Sir, on a Kings unblemiſh'd word, Enjoy my Friendſhip, and engage my Sword. char. Where faith is wanting this would ſatisfie; On which, as on Truths Pillars, Irely. King. Th' example of your worth will make a Friend. But what, Sir, does the Dauphin now intend ? char. This fatal Murder, Sir, he did deſign Juſt when the Queen, the Princeſs Katherine, My Siſter Anne, and I, (t’ avoid the heat And noyſe of Paris) did to Meaux retreat : Some Troops to ſeize on us he thither ſent: One of their Leaders (as to Meaux they went, Being my private Friend) did by a Poſt Tell me, unleſs we fled, we all were loſt: And that we ſhould not then tow'rds Paris flye, For on that Road ſome other Troops did lye Tointercept us if we thither fled. King. This root of miſchief ſoon will ſhoot and ſpread. Charl. At this I found the Queens amazement great: For being now cut off from her retreat, Her wiſdom could not teach her what to do: I then propos'd we all ſhould flye to you, As the ſecureſt way to ſcape his rage 5 And ſo your Vertue by our truſt engage 5 Vertue ſo known as would her fears controul. King. Truſt is the ſtrongeſt Bond upon the Soul: That ſacred Tye has Vertue oftbegot; It binds where 'tis, and makes it where 'twas not. Charl. I ſaid ſhe might, to break her Son's deſign, Give you for Bride the Princeſs Katherine : And urge th’Eſtates t'entail the Crown on you: This to your right, that to your love is due. This done, what could reſiſt your Arms and mine # As ſhe conſider'd how ſhe ſhould incline Clermount came in, diſguis'd 5 in whoſe known care Her Wealth and Jewels lay 5 who did declare Her Treaſure was ſurpriz'd, by ſome who ſaid That they the Dauphin in that act obey'd 3
Page 43

(43) Who would employ that wealth, vilely procur'd, So as that France ſhould have her peace aſſur’d. King. The Dauphin, in his rage or want, has done What was below him as a Prince or Son. Charl. Though ſhe this wrong and loſs did calmly bear, Yet the high Dićtates of Revenge and Fear Made her reſolve immediately to do What I with reaſon firſt advis'd her to. And now at Troy, the Queen and Princeſs are 5 To which the Dauphin will Tranſport the War. A Garriſon of mine ſecures that Town, And ſince 'tis mine you know it is your owns King. 'Tis chiefly to your favour Imuſt owe My being bleſt in Love and Conqueſt too. Charl. "Twere fit, Sir, that you ſent ſome Troops of Horſe The Garriſon of Troy to re-inforce. King. I'le lead them, Sir, my ſelf: all that are mine In France, are but the Guards of Katherine : My Duty elſe ſhe might in queſtion bring. Charl. "Tis ſpoken like a Lover and a King. Blamount I'le ſend before that ſhe may know What Honour to her you intend to do. [Exit Blamounts When you to Troy are come it ſhall appear I will perform more then I promis'd here. King. You may augment my debt, as you thinkfit, But nothing can encreaſe my ſenſe of it, Unleſs your favour, Sir, I could incline To make my Brother's joys keep time with mine: His Love to Princeſs Anne wants your conſent. Charl. She made me in their Loves her confident: And in your Brother Iſhall think her bleſt. King. This, Sir, unites our bloods and intereſt. Bedf. This grant (great Prince) my happineſs ſecures. King. It makes my happineſs as much as yours. Now, Tudor, if our proſp'rous Stars deſign That we ſhall both ſee beauteous Katherine, I will performall that I promis'd thee: And when thy ſtory ſhe has heard from me (In which by all her truth I'le dothee right) We then our Supplications will unite, That ſhe (our Judge) will only him prefer Whom ſhe believes is leaſt unworthy her: Without regarding in the cauſe webring That thou my Subjećt art, or I thy King. Tador. In Vertue, Sir, ſo much you me out-ſhine That you all other Motives may decline. King. Brother, 'tisfit the Duke, with you and I, Should on the Princeſs wait immediately. Tudor's
Page 44

(44) Twdor's Brigade the Princeſs Guard ſhall be; And with the Army you muſt follow me. [Exeuwt. Enter Queen, Princeſs Katherine, Princeſs Anne, Counteſs La Marr. gºween. Our fins make us defenceleſs, and we flye For our protećtion to our Enemy. Thy Laws, Oh Heav'n I have I offended ſo That thou haſt made my Son my greateſt Foe & Into the World I have the Monſter brought 3 And now no ſuffrings can tranſcend that fault. Prin, Kath. Madam, you make, whilſt thus you bear his crime, Our grief more juſt for you then yours for him. La Marr. If he ſhould hear you grieve in this exceſs, The triumph of his malice would increaſe. Prin. An. My Duty has th' aſſault of grief withſtood; For ſince his fury ſhed my Fathers blood, That waſted time which you employ to grieve I, to deſign'd revenge, more juſtly give: Let all your ſorrow in ſuch thoughts expire. &ueen. Grief is the Fuel and Revenge the fire. Prim.4m. Think then on all the Crimes which he has done, And let thoſe thoughts cancel the name of Son. Queen. Since faln ſo low from what is great or good I hate his Crimes more then I love his blood. Enter Blamount. Blam!. Madam, my Duty has provok'd my ſpeed. The King and Duke moſt ſtrićtly are agreed 3 And both this night will wait upon you here. Queen. This happy news ſuppreſſes all my fear, And makes me hope, aſſiſted by their Fate, That I ſhall live to puniſh what I hate. slam. Thoſe Troops, now on their March, he does deſign As Guards t'attend the Princeſs Katherine: And therefore would not ſend, but leads them here, That his reſpečt and love may both appear. Queen. We were, when to this Monarch we did truſt, Kind to our ſelves and to his Vertue juſt. #lamount, for his reception ſtraight prepare All that can joy and our reſped declare. Daughter, you muſt a while retire with me; I have ſome Words which need your privacy, [Exeumt. Hºfer
Page 45

(45) Enter Conſtable, and Biſhop of Arras, Arras. Our Eccleſiaſtick States are all agreed: This day the Dauphin for his bloody deed Will ſummon'd be to anſwer what was done. conſt. I have the Peers to that concluſion won; And thoſe who repreſent the Commons too Will now not ſlowly yield to what we do. I'le loſe my judgment if he dares appear. Arras. He loſes his, and life, in coming here 5 This murder has incens'd them to the heighth. conft. All hate a Prince who violates his Faith. The peoples temper does occaſion give T’obey thoſe orders we did now receive. I find already that the moſt incline The King ſhould marry Princeſs Katherine; And on their Iſlue would the Crown entail. Arras. The Dauphin's crime will make that King prevail. Conſt. Rather thenbow beneath a Murd’rers pow'r Let's to the Throne advance our Conquerour : The Queen and Duke expect it at your hands. Arras. I never durſt obey unjuſt commands. Comſt. Do you then think that thoſe commands are ſuch Arras. If you think ſo, my Lord, you wrong me much. My judgement by a better guide was led When I our Annals and Records had read: For then I doubted that ſince Charls the Fair Our Kings inſenſibly Uſurpers were. The Crown (if truth did dićtate what I read) Belong'd to the Vićtorious Edward's head : Which no preſcription from his Line ſhould take. I'le therefore to this change no ſcruple make. But if the Dauphin were the rightful Heir You might of my obedience then deſpair; For Reaſon's Maxim I muſt ever own 5 No King can make a forfeit of his Crown. Much leſs can I admit the States Decree Has power to give away this Monarchie. Conſt. My juſtice ſhall, now I am taught by you, Perform what I reſolv'd revenge ſhould do. My Lord, let's go where all our Friends are met 3 And jointly pay to Heav'n this double debt. [Exeumt. Enter King, Princeſ; Katherine, Tudor. King. Madam, I have injurious been to him As far as ignorance could make a crime: N
Page 46

( 46 ) I did employ him in my ſuit to you; But knew not then, that he ador'd you too : But I declare (which ſome amends may be) That he, at leaſt, in all things equals me Unleſs in Title; but 'tis greater far A Crown to merit then a Crown to wear. Can Title in that Ballancee're prevail Where Love is Merit, and you hold the Scale & I wave whatever may your favour move Except the Title of the higheſt Love. Speak for thy ſelf if I have leſſen'd thee. Tudor. Only my ſilence, Sir, ſhould plead for me. King. Thy love, when I employ'd thee, was unknown : I minded no mans ſorrows but mine own; Nor where ſo many ſhafts were ſhot in me Could think, any before had wounded thee. Tudor. All, Sir, that in my cauſe is ſaid by you At once is for me, and againſt me too. Howe're, I'le rather ſpeak then quite deſpair 5 Since ſhe is juſt and you my Rival are: Yet, Sir, this diffrence to my caſe is due, You ſpeak for me, but I reſign for you. Prin. Kath. He who reſigns his Love, though for his King, Does, as he is a Lover, a low thing: But, as a Subjećt, a high Crime does do; Being at once, Subjećt and Rebel too: For, whilſt to Regal pow'r he does ſubmit, He caſts off Love, a greater pow'r then it. Tudor. I fear you now are glad of a pretence To puniſh what you cannot recompence. Elſe could you think Loves pow'r I do not know Becauſe my Love all others does out-go? If I by that ſeem guilty in your Eye, Oh bappy guilt which raiſes Love ſo highl For I but ſhew in what I now have done, That I your Int’reſt prize above my own. Prim. Kath. But juſtly I admirehow you can prove So true to Friendſhip, and ſo falſe to Love 5 Since inefle& they both are but the ſame, Only the Scx gives them a diff'rent name. Tudor. Yon Friendſhip tax for being too ſublime, And make its duty, ev'n to Love a Crime. Prim. Kath. Your King does give you a brave Rivals leave 5 But you ſeem loth that licenſe to reccive: Of theſe, which for my wonder is more fit 5 The leave he gave, or your not uſing it 2 Tudor. The Giver may ſuch gifts as theſe eſteem: I can, but by refuſing, sherit them: And,
Page 47

( 47) And, Madam, ſince 'tis evident that you Can never pay what to us both is due, Why will you call that ačt in me a crime By which we both may juſtice do to him 2 Nor blame me that my Friendſhip's debt I paid By thus reſigning what I never had. Let me my death without reproaches crave. Prin. Kath. At once you my diſdain, and pardon have. Tudor. But why ſhould you diſdain that which to you Obedience ſhews, to him my Duty too? Prim. Kath. It is a Duty he will not receive. Tudor. But you, to love you, have deny'd me leave. Prim. Kath. He who makes love at a true Lovers height Does ne're ask leave, but takes it as his right. Tudor. Have you deſign'd in what you'd have me do To make me loſe my King and Miſtreſs too? In loſing of the laſt I'm ſo accurſt As you'l in pity let me keep the firſt. Prin. Kath. I'de have you, Sir, in that which I intend Fxpreſs that you did merit ſuch a Friend: I would have had you too, to let him ſee That you were not unworthy to love me. But, making ſuch an ill Retreat, you ſeem No more to merit bravely me, or him. What greater thing or meaner could you do Then dare at once to love and quit me too? I would have had you like your ſelf appear, And not with Friendſhips name diſguiſe your fear. Nortell him he to your reſpećt does owe That which alone my juſtice does beſtow. I would have had you nobly fall by it, And not thus meanly, uncompell'd, ſubmit. Tudor. Madam, with you no longer I'le contend ; Since in the way we differ, not the end. Sir, though ſhe thinks my condemnation fit; Yet, without ſighs, I to her doom ſubmit : For one joys loſs another joy ſecures: What loſes me her favour, merits yours. King. Whilſt, Tudor, you for me your claim deny Igain the Field, and you the Vićtory: Your's is the Nobler, mine the happier ſhare, I'm the oblig'd, but you th’ obliger are. Prin. Kath. In leaving me, as worthy of your Friend, You to the utmoſt rate my worth commend. Whilſt with that value I to him am brought You ſhew a Friendſhip worthy to be ſought. Be but my Friend, as you to him have been, Letting out Love to keep your Friendſhip in, And
Page 48

(48) And make forſaken Love contented ſeem, Then ſºle your Friendſhip, Sir, like Love eſteem. Enter Queen, Chareloys, Duke of Bedford, and Princeſ; Anne. squeen. I'm come to tell you, Sir, that we have ſign'd All that can France to your protećtion bind. The States have judg’d to baniſhment my Son: And, as we promis'd, have entayl'd the Crown. Charl. And, Sir, in all their names, one from each State Attending both your Thrones, ſhall ſupplicate That they in publick their Decree may give, Which only from their juſtice you receive. gueen. That publick form, Sir, may a little war Till we our Nuptial Rites ſhall Celebrate 5 My thoughts are fully to my Daughter known. King. But from her ſelf would I might know her own. Prin. Kath. I of your Love ſhall too unworthy be When I deny that it has conquer'd me. King. He who the glory has to conquer you Does, without War, more then the World ſubduc. Bedf. Heav'n meant not you alone ſhould happy be, Behold, Sir, what it has reſerv'd for me. Confirm'd by her, and by her Brother too. charl. The gift is perfect when allow'd by you. King. I can but adde the Ceremonial part 5 You had the ſubſtance when you had the heart. Prin. Ann. I cannot adde to what I gave before, Unleſs in ſaying I could give no more. gueen. Crowds of impatient Subjećts wait within To ſee the Nuptials of their King and Queen: The Sacred Prelate in the Temple ſtays, And longs to mitºgle Myrtle with your Bays. It were offer.ſive to admit delay.---- She, Sir, will follow when I lead the way. [Exeunt. Enter the Dauphin. Dauph. Revenge and pride my reaſon have betray'd; And both have rul'd, what both ſhould have obey'd, This Duke did with his life his ſins reſign, Which, in his blood, are written down for mine. Revenge! of all thy Charms, Oh let me find But one t'appeaſe the Tempeſt of my mind. Let none to the ſucceſs of miſchief truſt : I'le rather be unhappy then unjuſt. Emfe?
Page 49

(49) Enter De Chaſtel haſtily. De chaft. You cannot your new Levies now employ To ſtorm or to beſiege the Queen in Troyé. Sir, to prevent our courage and her fear, The King of England is in perſon there. The Bride's prepard, the King and Duke agreed; The trembling States have treach'rouſly decreed, During your Fathers life the King ſhall be Admitted to a boundleſs Regencie. And, after his deceaſe their Law declares The Crown ſhall fall to Henry and his Heirs. The Queen (to whom they vaſt Revenues give) Will, quitting pow'r, rich and obſcurely live. Dauph. Can her revenge alone incline her to What right and nature could not make her do? Dechaft. Spend not that time in blaming what ſhe does Which fortune for a fair retreat allows. The Duke of Exeter with all his horſe Directly to your Camp now bends his courſe. Th' Alarm of ſuch a growing force ſo near Gave your new Troops a good excuſe for fear. O'retake your time before it runs too far. Sir, 'tis a granted principle in War That Chiefs, not ſtrong enough tº engage in fight, Should ſtill retire before the Foe's inſight. Of all Wars tasks the hardeſt is Retreat, Where fear does our worſt Foe, Diſorder, meet. Retire, Sir, leſt men ſay, we proudly ſtay'd Too long for thoſe of whom we were afraid. Daupé. Muſt the firſt Aét which I deſign'd to do Befoyl'd, and e're it is attempted too? De chaft. Let not one look of Fortune caſt you down : She were not fortune if ſhe ſtill did frown. Such as do braveli'eſt bear ber ſcorns a while Are thoſe on whom, at laſt, ſhe moſt wift ſmile. Dauph. Raiſe then the Camp! Fortune, that leads the way Of Time's whole progreſs, can give us a day. [Exchnt. The Curtain Fallr. Tiro Heraulds appear oppºſite to each other in the Balcomics near the stage. 1. Her. Herauld! What ſummons have you to proclaim * Whom would you ſummon now, and in whoſe name? 2. All that are Engliſh, all that are French appear ! 1. I am to ſummon thoſe Great Nations here. 2. And I muſt ſummon them to come before Iſenry the Fifth, both King and Conquerour, All O
Page 50

( 50 ) All that are Engliſh, all that are French appear ! 1. Behold your King and Queen' behold l and hear ! You Prelates of the Church are ſummon'd all And every Member Eccleſiaſtical. 2. And every Noble too, and Commoner 1. He that is French, or Engliſh, and not here, In perſon or in publique Deputie, Shall, though alive, in Law not living be. 2. Henry the Fifth is now to take the Crown Of France, not as if giv'n him, but his own. 1. That Crown ſhall ſtill deſcend to all his Line As Heirs, or not as Heirs, of Katherime. 2. He that is French, or Engliſh, now attend I. Or elſe he is no Leige-man, nor no Friend. The Curtain is drawn up. The Curtain being lifted up, there appear the King, Princeſs Kathe- rine, Queen Mother, Princeſs Anne, Chareloys, and all the Engliſh, and the French Nobility and officers of state; and other, according to their places. Burg. The Deputies, ſent by the three Eſtates, Wait for admittance at your Palace Gates. King. My Lord with all the publick forms of care Let all my Officers their way prepare. [All the officers deſign'd for that pur. poſe, then orderly go ont. Ifought this day my bleſſings could abate 'Tis that they are ill husbanded by Fate. For, Madam, I am now too happy grown By gaining in one day, you and a Throne. The firſt felicity I found ſo vaſt As takes away my relliſh of the laſt. Enter the Diffinä Trains of the Deputies from the three Eſtates, the Kings officers, and laſt of all the three Deputies, the Biſhop of Ar- ras for the Eccleſiaſtickſ, the Conſtable for the Peers, and Mon- ſieur Cole-more for the people. Biſh. of Ar. Great King, th' Eſtates of France have ſent us three To pay their Duties in this juſt Decree: Fixing the Crown on you, and on that Line, Which Heav'n, in favour, ſhall to both deſign. Who knows what wonders ſuch a Line may do As is from Beauties drawn and Conqu'rours too? In which, Heav'n all thoſe Princes will unite Who to this Empire have, or claim a right. We by the Dauphin's bloody deed did ſee That he but falſly claim'd what he would be. For
Page 51

(51) For we admir'd one born to fill his Throne Could ačthis crime, and then that crime could owne, But, ſearching our Records, we found at laſt That a long errour as a truth has paſt: For he who flyes, now juſtice does advance, Is Charles of Valoys, not the Son of France. From thoſe Records the Learned clearly tell Your Ancient Title by Queen Iſabel; By whom you to this Crown are lawful Heir : New rights we grant not, but the old declare. This juſt Decree, in which they pay that debt, We humbly proſtrate at your Royal Feet. I from the Clergy come to whom is given The laſting pow'r of Legates ſent from Heav'n, Their Pray'rs will make you conquer when you fight; And, in their voice, Heav'n does allow you right, Comſt. I from the Nobles come, who ſtill ar. born To ſave their Monarchs, and their Courts adorn 5 And ſtill are certain of th’ inceſſant care Of Pallaces and dangers of the War. They in their Sphear ſhould ſtill continue bright Since they from Kings derive their borrow'd light. Mounſ. Cole. Ifrom the people come, who always are The Hands,as Nobles are the heads of War. And when the glorious toyls of Warſhall ceaſe Their hands are no leſs uſeful, Sir, in Peace. B. of Ar. And all the three do with one voice confeſs They in their Duty find their happineſs. [They give the Parchment. King. Th' Eſtates I hope, my Lords, ſhalíne're repent What I receive, and they have freely ſent. Engliſh and French now but one people are: And both ſhall have iny equal love and care. Bnt Charleſ of Paloy, we ſhall ſoon deſtroy; And, by his ruine, France ſhall Peace enjoy. Since now gainſt ſo much guilt we are to fight We may depend on Conqueſt as our right. Sur Swords ſhould ºnly Miracles produce Now we have joyn'd the Croſs and Fleur de Luce. Twere ſin the help of Fortune to implore To Crown that head your hands have Crown'd before. [Exehnt Ommer. F I N I S.
Page 52

Blank page

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 53

T H E T R A G E D Y Must ApHA, The S O N of S O L Y M A N T H E Magnificent. Written by The Right Honourable the Earl of OR RERT. L O N Do N, Printed for H. Herringman, at the Sign of the Blew Anchor in the Lower Walk of the New Exchange. I 668.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 54

The Perſons, Solyman the Magnificent. }H. Sons. Muſtapha, and Zanger. Ruſtan, and Pyrrhus. Haly, and Achmat The King of Hungary an Infant. The Cardinal of Veradium. huricuſ. and - T 3 a }Hugrim Lords. Viche. Roxolana, Solymans Wife. Queen of Hungary. Zarma, and Mirza. }.izier Baſaws. $Eunuch Baſaws. 3rown. Women Mr. Betterton. Mr. Harris. Mr. Smith. Mr. Samford. Mr. Norriſ. Mr. Cadiman. Mr. james Noke. Mr. Toung. Mr. Medborn. Mr. Aingel. Mrs. Betterton, Mrs. Daviſ. Mrs. Long. Mrs. Norriſ. Cleora,Queen of Hungary's Woman Mrs. Shadwel. The Sultan'ſ Guards. Mutes. Pages. And other Attendants. MU STA-

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 55

(55) Muſtapha. T H E FIRST ACT. - Solymans Camp and his Pavillion. Enter Solyman, Ruſtan, Pyrrhus, and the Sultans Guards. Ruſt. Hat Influence, Mighty Sultan, rules the day, And ſtops your courſe where glory leads the way? Th’ Hungarian Armies haſten from the Field, And Buda waits for your approach to yield; Yet you ſeem doubtful what you are to do, And turn from Triumphs when they follow you. Pyrrh...We at the Suns one moments reſt ſhould more Admire then at his glorious courſe before. Glory, like Time, progreſſion does require, When it does ceaſe t'advance, it does expire. soly. You both miſtake; my glory is the cauſe That in my Conqueſt I have made this pauſe; Whilſt Hungary did pow'rful Foes afford, I thought her Ruine worthy of mySword; But now the War does ſeem too low a thing, Againſt a Mourning Queen, and Infant King ; Pyrrhus, it will unequal ſeem in me To Conquer, and then bluſh at Vićtory. Ruft. None but the Conquer'd ſhould have ſence of ſhamcº Shall ſhows of Vertue darken your bright Fame : Succeſs does cover all the crimes of War, And Fame and Vertue ſtill conſiſtent are. In lazie peace let Chriſtian Monarchs ruſt, Who think no War, but what's defenſive, juſt, Our Valiant Prophet did by ſlaughter riſe : Conqueſt a part of our Religion is. Pyrrh. He in his Holy War ſounds no retreat, Accounting none Religious but the great; His Martyrs, not by yielding, glory gain; They th' other World, by Conquering this, obtain. Soly. To Rome I will my dreadful Enſignes lead, Rome which was once the univerſal head, Which ſtill the worlds important part controuls; Once ſhe gave Laws to Kingdoms, now to Souls; To
Page 56

(56) To that great Conqueſt my deſigns Ibend, This Kingdom is my way and not my end, Which now, ſince too much ſcar'd by my Alarms, Seems worthier of my pity then my Arms. Ruſt. Since Rome did oncetheuniverſe ſubdue, 'Tis now the only Conqueſt fit for you; But he who Conqueſts wiſely has deſign'd, Does never leave an Enemy behind. Though all that Heav'n ere finiſh'd in a Man, Is now in you, yet Heaven's Great Agent can Proceed but as the Inſtrument of Fate, To work out Conqueſts, not at once Create ; Beginnings ſhould to th’ end ſtill uſeful be; 'Tis more to uſe then gain a Vićtory. Pyrrh. The Sword muſtend what Valour has begun, Elſeyou diſgrace what is already done; Your Foes would think if you ſhould now relent, That you of Conqueſts as of Crimes repent. When your bright Creſcents are to Buda ſhown, 'Tis but a ſtep to the Hungarian Crown ; Your preſence lower then their knees will bring Th: Hungarian Prieſts to offer up their King. When by that proofyour Conqueſt is confeſt, Diſpoſe of him by rules of Intereſt. soly. Bear then my Standard before Buda's Walls I ſhould not ſtop my Ears when glory calls; Since there the Foe all his reſerves does make, In taking Buda I the Kingdom take. Call the Divan, let them conſult with you, What with the Infant King is fit to do. [Extunt the two Baſhas. Divans like Common-wealths regard not fame, Disdaining honour they can feel noſhame; Each does, for what the publick ſafety call, Venture his Vertue in behalf of all, Doing by pow'r what Nature does forbid, Each hoping, amongſt all, that he is hid, Hiddenbecauſe they on each other wink, When they dare act what Monarchs ſcorne to think. [Exit. Enter Iſabella Queen of Hungaria in Mourning, Cleora, Thuricas, Wiche, and Attendants. Thur. In the Hungarian Council does appear Diſorder vary'd in all ſhapes of fear. Piche. And in their looks too clearly I deſcry, They'l rather tamely yield thenbravely dye. ..Queen. But yet the remedy by Death remains, When that may free them will they carry Chains - Theif
Page 57

(57) Their Souls are with their Armies overcome, They who the Bulwark were of Chriſtendom, Shall now be made at once their ſcorn and ſhame: 'Tis leſs to loſe their Countrey than their Fame. But though the frighted States ſhould yield the Town, I am reſolv'd ne're to reſign the Crown: My care of that, and my neglect of Life, Areſigns that I have been your Monarchs Wife. Thur. The death of that Great King for whom you Mourn, Didour advancing Empire backward turn 5 The Turks may now the Chriſtian world out-brave, Since all our hearts lie buri'd in his grave. ſ Enter the Cardi- Card. The Sultan's Army covers Budas hills, U ral of Veradium. Which our Conſulting States with terlour fills, Who hearing he to ſuch has mercy ſhown, As, timely yielding, did his wrath atone; They will a ſudden preſent to him bring, Worth more than all their lives, our Infant King. 2ueen. Give up the King! in that reſolve I ſee Th’ Hungarians now are ripe for ſlavery; The Prince, who from your King his birth did take, Shall not a part of Turkiſh triumph make; Death may, but fear ſhall never caſt me down: Who yields, does ne'ie deſerve to wear a Crown; Death ſhall us both in the firſt breach relieve, We'ldie, ſince in the Throne we cannot live. Thur. Ah Madam, that which you have now deſign'd, Does more become your fortune than your mind; Let not your Vertue teach you cruelty. 2ueen, 'Tis worſe to merit death than’tis to die: A Queen who does reſign her Son and State, Does uſe her ſelf, worſe than ſhe'sus'd by Fate. Card. Since now the States your broken Armies pay, The orders of the States they will obey; And what they have reſolvd, they ſoon will do, Therefore my Counſel, Madam, pray purſue; Since they have prov’d ſo falſe and ſo unjuſt, Turn what they make neceſſity to truſt; Send the Crown-Jewels, and the Infant King To Roxolana as an Offering; Subdue that Beauty which the Vićtor ſways, With what the Great are ſooneſt conquer'd, Praiſe: Extol her Vertue, and her Mercy move, By all the Charms of pity and of love; In gaining her you make the Sultan ſure, A deſperate ill can have no common cure. Whilſt with applauſe high minds you higherraiſe, You make them vertuous to make good your praiſe. 2&tem.
Page 58

(58) 2ueen. The States, not I, this Counſel may eſteem, 'Twill make me do what I abhorr'd in them ; If by their Cowardice I am deſtroy'd, I'le bravely meet what I in vain avoid: Ah 'tis enough my fate to undergo, Muſt Ithe Patient be , and Agent too? 'Tis Hazardous on th’Empreſs to relie, I by the Sultan's Conqueſt can but die; And 'twill leſs glory to my death afford, To periſh by her ſentence then his ſword: By my own way I but to death ſubmit, But if I folk,w yours I merit it; For whena Monarch is ſubdu'd by fear, What he does ſuffer he deſerves to bear. Card. My way, the worſt that can befal our King, Is to become his peoples offering; Of the two ills, which will the worſer be, To die for them, or by their Treachery: Thus he’l afflićt whom he canne're reclaim, For ſure the ſharpèſt puniſhment is ſhame: The worſe they are, his fate the betterſeems, When thoſe who him deſtroy he thus redeems; Religion too makes it a greater thing, To die a Martyr then to live a King. ..Queen. My Lord, your pious ſeaſons make me yield, Nature to Vertue ſhould reſign the fields Bring me, Cleora, my unhappy Son, And with him all the Jewels of the Crown ; | Exit Cleofa, You Thuracus on Embaſſy ſhall go To Roxolana's Tent, and lether know How much the common voice of Fame I truſt. Which renders her compaſſionate and juſt ; Whilſt others ſay ſhe all her ſex exceeds, They ſhew their Faith by words, but I by deeds ; I by ſo ſtrange a truſt may find relief, If ſhe has vertue equal to my grief. Piche. Madam, ſhe will not now by one meanaët, A future ſtain on her paſt fame contract. Thur. Honour will make her value what Ibring: 'Tis more to ſave then to deſtroy a King. Enter Cleora with the young King, and a Casket of £ewells, with Attendants. .Queen. Ah! wou'd thy Cradle had been made thy Grave. Since born to beat once a King and Slave; In bonds thy fatal Reign thou doſt begin, And thou art puniſh'd e're thouknow'ſt to ſin. Card. You feedyourſorrow when you thus complain; Think not of loſs, but count what you may gain; - Fortune
Page 59

(59) Fortune who leads him hence will bring him back, And long preſerve what you a while forſake. 2ueen. My Lord, my ſorrow ſeeks not your relief, You are not fit to judge a Mothers grief; You have no Child for an untimely grave, Nor can you loſe, what I deſire to have. card. He'l be reſtor'd unleſs you hazard him, By loſing time which none could ere redeem. 2ueen. I'l now ſeal up the heart which I muſt ſend In thee, to thy new-Mother and my Friend. [ Kiſſes him. Ch Heav'n perſwade her that ſhe both may prove, And that her power be equall'd by her love; Let me but ſeal't agen ere it does go : Two Seals th’ importance of Diſpatches ſhow. [ Kiſſes him agen. Card. Madam, we muſt by ſtealth our paſſage get: Our Guards are ſtrićt, and th’ Ev’ning Watch is ſet. ..Queen. Beyou his Nurſe, Cleora, teach him how, He ſhould to Heav'n with early homage bow; Teach him to ſooth the Empreſs, and to be, A pretty ſupplyant for himſelf and me. [Exeunt ſeveral ways, the Queen ſtill turning her Eyes towards her Son, and weeping, Enter Muſtapha, Zanger, Attendants. Muſt. Sure, my dear Zanger, thoſe who heretofore, The envy'd Crown of this Great Empire wore; Nere knew the charms which Friendſhip do attend, Orin a Brother never had a Friend; Since he who Friendſhips ſacred power has known, Rather than kill a Friend, would loſe a Throne: Your Friendſhip at ſo juſta rate I prize, As I for that this Empire can deſpiſe. Zang. That jealous care which on this Throne atteads, Thinks thoſe too great who merit to be Friends; None but an equal ſhould in Friendſhip ſhare, And Sultans of their equals jealous are : They think the proof of wiſdom is diſtruſt, And thenbelieve, what ere is ſafe is juſt; Their fatal maximes made our Sultans ſtill. As ſoon as they were Crown'd, their Brothers kill. Muſt. How can that wiſdom in our Sultans be, Which of itſelf is fear and cruelty? If titles change th' intention of the Faët, Then juſtice weighs the Aćtor, not the Aét; And who would not a Monarchy refuſe, When, to gain pow'r, he muſt his nature loſe, ;:
Page 60

( 6o ) The vertue of that man was never ſtrong, Who fear'd not more to do then ſuffer wrong. By our great Prophet ſolemnly I ſwear, If I the Turkiſh Crown doever wear, Our bloody cuſtom I will overthrow ; That debt I both to you and juſtice owe. zang. And here Ivow by all that's good and high, I'le not out-live the day in which you die; This which my Friendſhip makes me promiſe now, My grief will then enable me to do. Muſt. My vow is ſeal’d. Zing. Mine Friendſhip ſhall make good. [They embrace. Muff. Friendſhip's a ſtronger tye than that of blood. Enter Haly. Ha'). Sir, the Divan in ſecret Council ſit; The Sultan to their Judgment does remit The Summons or Aſſault of this proud Town, Or to demand the lnfant with his Crown. Zang. If the Divan may of this Realm diſpoſe, Th’ Hungarians will have ſcarce enough to loſe. *:: Councils dare do worſethan their Monarchs dare; Fol where in evil many bear a ſhare, They hardly count, when they divide the guilt, A drop for each, though ſtreams of blood were ſpilt. [Extunt, Enter Roxolana with her Train, Cleora, Thuracus with the young King, and a Casket of Penels. Rox. She thinks that my compaſſion may be bought : You had the King without theſe Jewels brought, If ſhe had held me worthy to have ſhown, That I without reward could ſave a Crown: She does at once what generous ſeems and low, What her truſt builds, her gifts do overthrow. Bear back the remnants of her ruin’d State, And leave the Infant to expect his Fate. Thur. Great Roxolana cannot but excuſe Thoſe errors which our Queens reſpects produce; She makes for her offence no ill amends, When ſhe dares truſt that Vertue ſhe offends; Nor has ſhe cauſe that error to deplore, Which gives you power to ſhew your mercy more. 'Tis not below your fame, nor yet your ſtate, To pardon faults your Glory does create; For if your Glory had been leſs ſublime, You could not take her Préſent for a crime. Theſe gliſt ring Ornaments of Regal State, Become the Proſprous, not th’Unfortunate. Ah
Page 61

(61) Ah! to her errour, Madam, be more kind; The wrong ſhe meant not, ſhe the truſt deſign'd. Rox. What I reſolve, I change not through miſtake ; Leave here your King, but bear your Preſents back. Cleora. This anſwer makes us both rejoyce and mourn; The greater gift you keep, the leſs return; Yet your protećtion cannot be deny'd: Honour and mercy ever were ally’d. [Excunt Thuracus, Cleora, Roxolana, Lady carries amaſ the Infant. Enter Zarma. Zarm. From the Divan, Ruſtan is hither ſent, Who humbly begs tº attend youin your Tent. Rex. Admit him; this muſt of importance be; [Exit Zarma. He is a Cloud between the Sun and me. Achm. Your beams exhal'd what they may ſoon diſpel; He'll ſhrink in leſſer time then he did ſwell. Rox. He's now the Sultans, but I rais'd him firſt, And poyſon'd him with power to make him burſt. Enter Haly, Ruſtan. Ruſt. From the Divan, Great Empreſs, I am come; They have pronounc'd the Royal Infants doom ; And now their Mutes at your Pavilion Gate, For execution on your pleaſure wait. Rox. Can they conteſt with what they ſhould deſpiſe: Or are they in ſuchwant of Enemies, As to purſue an Infant to my Tent : Reft. 'Tis ſaid that he is here for refuge ſent. Rox. Deſignof refuge ſanctifies this place: Weakneſs purſu'd, ſhews ſtrong purſuers baſe; The priviledge of refuge I'll maintain, And they not breaking it will honour gain. Ruſt. States may by honourloſe, if they comply With miſchiefs, becauſe weak, or when they flye; They rootup Infant Danger when it ſprings: None can fore-tell the height of growing Kings. Rox. The grave Divan inruining their Foes, Are not concern'd when they may honour loſe; Becauſe it moſt refle&son future fame, But they ſeek preſent ſafety though with ſhame. Great Solyman, who has for honour fought, Does wiſely prize what with his blood he bought; And what he values, I muſt value too; Doing like him, how can I betterdo: But the Divan and Iſhallvainly ſtrive, Since from the Sultan they that power derive; By which for bloody int'reſt they contend, And by his power, my honour Idefend. R Raft.
Page 62

(6.2 ) Ruſt. Your beauty keeps all humane pow'r in awe: What can reſiſt it, but our Prophets Law: The wiſe Divan, arm'd with Religious force, Conteſts not with your pow'r, but your remorſe, Rox. Religion now does many faces bear, And all reſemble thoſe, who Copy her; You States-men in your own reſemblance draw Her ſhape, by which you keep the world in awe, Ruſt. Fair Empreſs, when Religion does oppoſe What cuſtom plants, or in our nature grows; We are incens'd, and yet we then forbear Tº accuſe the Law, but tax th’Interpreter; As men refrain to quarrel with the ſtrong, But wrongs pretend from thoſe whom they may wrong; Our Law offends them by their own miſtake, Whilſt what is merciful, they cruel make: This Infants blood will quench the flames of War; Millions of lives weby his dying ſpare. Rox. But can Religion with ſuch ill diſpence As harm prevents, by harming innocence. Raft. Shall true Religion (which muſt ſtill declare Againſtall falſe Religions open War) Beleſs provided for offence then thoſe, VVho pračtice policy as well as blows: Rox. Ruſtan, I did not think Camps could have bred One, whoſe Religion might in Temples plead For all that Heav'n enjoynes, and Hell reſiſts: Ruſtan might lead an Army made of Prieſts. Ruſt. They fight forth other World,and yield up this . Would I could lead them all to Paradiſe: But Madam, the Hungarian Child, to ſave, Conteſting Armies from a publick grave, Should dye, if with his death you would diſpence, Rox. I have ſome pity of his innocence. Ruſt. His early dying may his Soul prefer To th' other World, and may ſecule us here. Thoſe, Madam, may rejoyce who upward go, And ought to pity us who ſtay below. Rox. Ah Ruſtan you by ſoaring Vertue reach, Thoſe heights of which our Prieſts can only Preach; My pity you correót, and then Seſtroy, In pleading what the dead, by death enjoy; And now, to ſhow I prize what you eſteem, Call in my Mutes and bid them ſtrangle him. [Pointing to Ruſtan, Ruſt. 'Tis much to ſay it, can you mean it too: [Exit Mitza. Rox. I'le not diſſemble as you Viziers do. Enter Mitza and A Viziers power is but ſubordinate, the Mutes. He's but the chief diſſembler of the State; And
Page 63

(63) And oft for publick int’reſt lies ; but I, The partner of Supreme Authority, Do ever mean the utmoſt that I ſay; Diſpatch, he's ſuch a Saint as needs not pray. Haly. Hold, hold. Rox. How Haly, by command from you? Hall. 'Tis but for leave that I may humbly ſue. I can leſs doubt the juſtice of your will, Then that you here have priviledge to kill; The greatneſs of his crime none will ſuſpect, Becauſe he came t' invade,what you protećt, But for that height of treſpaſs let him live, Leſt you ſhould ſeem unable to forgive. Achm. You only mortal pow'r by killing ſhow; But by forgiving it does Heav'nly grow: Th’ Offender more your frowns, then dying fears. Ruſt. To me your anger, worſe then death appears. Rox. Live, ſince my wrath does fear of death tranſcend, Live to continue, what thy death will end. Exit Ruſtanbowing low. Extunt Mutes another way. Haly. He's gone to ſtudy what revenge can do; But, Madam, 'tis more ſafe for us that you Haveleft a Vizier living to complain, Then that the Sultan ſhould have found him ſlain. - Rox. Can you your ſafety doubt whilſt you are mine? Achm. You and the Sun warm all things where you ſhine. Haly. Some flowers ſeem more then others to rely On the Suns favour, ſuch as with his Eye Open and ſhut, and with his Noon grow ſtrong, We like to thoſe may flouriſh, but not long. Achm. The Sultan will not chideyour violence, But make our knowing of it an offence ; And we ſhall certain be of puniſhment, For knowing that which we could ne're prevent. Haly. He'l on your errours wink, as on his own, And think them puniſh'd in but being known. Enter Solyman. Achm. Our ſtorm's already coming, would twere paſt. Haly. Before it falls,letus to ſhelter haſte. Extunt Achmat, Haly. Solº. Weinour Camp want pow'r to check your will, Andyour Pavilion is your Cittadil; Which you with Dwarfs, and Mutes, and Eunuchs, man, Tohold out ſiege againſt the whole Divan ; This wonder ſam told, if it be true, We muſt leave Buda to beleaguer you. - Rox. Ithoughtingainingyou,Igain'd the Field, And therefore would not to your Subječts yield, - Sº";
Page 64

( 64) soly. Fortune does bluſh at the bold minds of thoſe, Who, what is long in gaining, raſhly loſe. Rox. Your Vizier is a moſt impatient Saint: He cannot ſuffer wrong without complaint. Soly. You would be terrible, yet pleaſant too, And in gay humour when you miſchief do; Can you, when ſullengrown, bechearful made With no leſs ſport then death in paſquerade? My Vizier, on whoſe office Irely, Whoſe pow'r ſhould advers Nations terrifie; You, for your Eunuchs. and your Dwarfs delight, To try his Valour,with Death's vizard fright. Rox. Had you not taught me, I had never known All Pow'r to be Phantaſtick, but your own. Sely. I'll teach you now that Death's a ſerious thing. Call for your Mutes, and for your little King ! Rox. What is your meaning Sultan: Zarma ſtay! soly. Ha! Is ſhe doubtful whom ſhe ſhould obey? Rox. You rule enough, ruling the world and me 3 Pray let my Women, my own Subjećts be. Soly. Your Subjećts are not ſafe obeying you: They l make my Mutes do more then yours ſhould do. Rox. Your looks are chang'd, and many dangers there Aſſemble like black Clouds when ſtorms are neare: Ah Sultan what ſhould Roxolana do, If, like your looks, your heart were alter'd too? Is it your pleaſure that my VVomen bring, For your Diverſion, Sir, the Infant King? Soly. Your queſtion breeds delay, let him be brought. Your Women ſure are Mutes, and only taught To know your ſigns for what they ſhould not do; I'll ſend my Mutes tº inſtrućt them when to go. The Women Rox. Alas, their fear did make themloth to move : #. 04ſ, They fear your anger, but I truſt your love. Enter the Women with the young King. Soly. Is this the thing that you would keep alive; For whom the Croſs does with the Creſſent ſtrive; Nay, bring him near, his motion has a grace; And I perceive a promiſe in his face, That he'l perform what he declares in ſhow, If deſtiny will give him leave to grow; His eyes do with a diff'rent luſtré move, They threaten veng'ance, and they promiſe love. Rox. Pray look, methinks his features are not ill---- But cruel Ruſtan, thinks I have no skill---- Toor Infant,none dareſpeak in thy defence, And thou want'ſt words to plead thy innocence. Soly. You are too fond, betender of your own: They'l quit his company to get his Crown;
Page 65

(6; ) If this ſeems ſtrange Tll put you out of doubt; Zarma go call my Mutes, they wait without. Rox. Stay ! Zarma ſtay ! If this, Sir, beyonr doom, Send me too where the cruel never come; - I'll bind him to me with my Arms and Hair, Then try, Sir, if your Mutes or Viziers dare Enforce him from the refuge of my Breſt. - Soly. Though withſtrange valour you are now poſſeſt, Yet ſurely, Empreſs, the Divan, and ſ, May charge with the moſt deſp'rate Enemy: Your heart will yield after this raging fit. Rox. It may e'relong, when you have broken it. [Weeps. Soly. Come, come ! My Mutes, ending an Infants life, Which ſeems but new begun, will end out ſtrife. Rox. The light of this new kindl d life ſhall ſhine, Till thoſe who put it out extinguiſh mine; Your Mutes may tremble and your Viziers too, Knowing what I have done, and ſtill dare do. Soſy. You will not ſure with them and me contend. Rox. Againſt th' oppoſing world I will defend The life which in protećtion Ireceive; Sultan I'lldo't —— If you will give me leave. Soly. You, Roxolana, are the Conquerour. What ſtormis notallay’d by ſuch aſhowre: I only try’d whether your Vertue were Above my anger, and your ſexes fear : Since over both it does ſo nobly riſe, It ſhall be more Triumphant thenyour eyes. Rox. By yielding you prevail, and your remorſe Gains more then other Vićtors get by force. soly. Your ſhowre of Tears will make my Laurels ſpring, And growth does promiſe to this Infant King; He ſhallapplaudyourgentle Vićtory, For your remorſe ſaves him and Conquersme. Exennt. The young King, being led out between Solyman and Roxolana. [Wept. S T H E
Page 66

(66) *--------------------------- - T H E S E C O N D A C T. Enter Roxolana, Zanger, Haly, Zarma, Achmat, and Attendants to them. Achm. Hree Chriſtian Ladies, who from Buda come, Wait for admittance in the outward room. Rox, Sure they are ſent from the Hungarian Queen. Her fears have made her reſtleſs: bring them in. Zanger, your looks muſt now ſereneappear; Ruſtan muſt find no more foul weather here; He has endeavour'd to deſerve his peace, Therefore your frowns muſt with my anger ceaſe. Zang. The Vizier gains ſo much of your eſteem, That I e're long may wiſh good looks from him. Enter the Queen of Hungaria, and two Ladies attending her. 2ueen. Madam, your favours have ſo proſp'rous been, And ſo obliging to th' Hungarian Queen (Still riſing like your vertue and your power) That ſhe does find her ſenſe of it is more, Then ſhe dares truſt another to expreſs, Therefore is now her own Embaſſadreſs. That high Compaſſion, Madam, by which you The Infant ſav'd, has brought the Mother too; As the afflićted with Devotion run To Altars, where great Miracles are done. Rox. In this you truſt my vertue, not my power; And whilſt you are oblig'd, oblige memore. Queen. Thoſe who at Altars bleſfings crave, may bring, There where they begging come, an offering; Which if they offer as a recompence For what they then implore, were an offence. But, Ma'am, I ſhal now a Preſent make. O; what I ought to give, and you may take: Buda, for your acceptance, Madam, waits: Your vertue, by a Charm, unlocks her Gates: Buda, willbow toyou; though it the pow'r Proudly withſtood of every Conquerour; By force ne're aw'd, nor ſtratagem beguil'd: Bnda, the Virgin Town; which has been ſtil'd (When every Vićtor courted her to yield) The Miſtreſs of the Maſter of the Field. Zang. Haly, we grow too great, Heav'nmake us leſs, Since Conqueſts bring ſuch beauties to diſtreſs, Methinks
Page 67

(67) Methinks my Mother ſhould more tendergrow. Haly. You feel that pity, Sir, which ſhe will ſhow. seen. I to your vertue now a Preſent make Of what the Sultans power could never take; Somuch your powerful vertue does oblige, That it does take what he can but beſiege. Rox. Whilſt thus you ſtrive to make my vertue known, Madam, you ſhow a greater of your own; And what I did, you now reward ſo well, As makes the recompence the Deed excel; Yet but a little vertue were in me, If I ſhould now let yours, your ruine be. 2ueen. How can my gratitude my ruine bring, Truſting a Kingdom, where I truſt a King? Pardon me, Madam, if I come to you, As all to Altars with ſelf-intereſt do; Hoping they mighty bleſſings ſhall receive, For what they there in little offerings give: I give an Infant King whom all forſake, And of a Town beſieg'd, a Preſent make; But you adopting him reſtore a Crown, And give a Kingdom, when you take a Town. The Sultan may his Armies valour ſpare, You by your ſingle vertueend the War. Rox. Your vertue has a greater wonderwrought, It Conquers where it but protećtion ſought; Above this height, Honour can neverget, For it does Conquer, whilſt it does ſubmit. Madam, 'tis only Solyman and you Canboaſt they Roxolana did ſubdue ; And that your triumph may themore appear, You in this very Camp have Conquer'd her: But you are now my Gueſt, and you ſhall ſtay, Till you at leaſt believe that I'll repay What you with more then gratitude have done: Madam, I know you long to ſee your Son. zanger, attend the Queen, and let her be, By finding your reſpects, aſſur’d of me. Exeunt ſeveral wayes, Zanger leading out the 2ueen, Enter Ruſtan, Pyrrhus, Ruſtan. Sheo're his heart ſtill more vićtorious grows. And faſter Conquers him, then he his Foes. Pyrrh. Your dark deſigns are all in vapour gone, They are but Clouds, her beauty is theSun. Great Fav'rites ſeldom their reſentments hide; Revenge ſhows not their anger, but their pride;
Page 68

(68) She'l be reveng'd that you her power may ſee. Ruſt. "Twill her leaſt miſchief ſeem to ruine me: She with the wind and tide of favour flows. Pyrrh. Row with that ſtream which ſtrength cannot oppoſe: Swell up her Sails with praiſe and flattery. Ruſt. Thoſe are low Courtſhips for a Soulſo high; Such common fawning ſhe'l deſpiſeor hate, She muſt be tempted with a ſubtler bait: I muſt engage her by ſomebold deſign, In which her Int’reſt with great crimes may joyn The Great can never love, becauſe too high kor that which Love allows, equality; But they to thoſe they fear will favour ſhow, And they fear thoſe, who their great miſchiefs know : Knowing her guilt, I may her favour find; Guilt next to Love, above all ties do bind: Her heightn'd mind and nature much diſdain, That Muſtapha ſhould over Zanger raign 5 I can aſſault her only on that ſide, Making her vertue vaſlal to her pride. Pyrrh. Advance, Sir, this deſign e're ſhe can know, What for her ſake you flave begun to do; Honour or craft may make herelſe to ſhun The ſin deſign'd, which ſhe'll applaud when done. Ruſt. And, Pyrrhus, 'twere no little mark of skill To make her think, when I oppos'd her will, 'Twas only that I might the Sultan blind, More ſafely to effect what I deſign'd ; My faults to her ſhall ſuch deſerts appear, As ſhe ſhall thank me that I injur'd her. Pyrrh. If ſhe diſcerns you not through your diſguiſe, She who has caught the Sultan, is your prize. Ruſt. I ſhould her Friendſhip wiſh, were Friendſhip more Then a meer name 'twixt thoſe who covet power; You ſhall but Eccho what I have begun, To make the Father jealous of the Son. I with the Sultan durſt at firſt proceed, Only ſofar as might attention breed; Laſt night ſome words Iartfully did ſay, From Fame, not from myſelf, of Maffapha, Which might the Sultan's jealous anger raiſe, Not words of accuſation, but of praiſe; For nothing can old Monarchs more offend, Then when their Succeſſors we much commend: Iquickly found that he was loth to hear, Therefore by pauſe and parcelin his Ear, Did civilly that poyſon, Praiſe, infuſe, As men unwilling ſeem to tell ill news. Pyrrh
Page 69

(69) Pyrrh. His firſt Diſeaſe is fixt, what canremove Thé Jealouſie of Empire, or of Love? Ruſt. Now I that fatal ſeed have own, 'tisfit That I attend on time to ripen it. Pyrrh. When fancy to that fruitful weed does give But any root, 'twill grow whilſt it does live. Enter Zanger, and Achmat, at diſtance from him. zang. Warm me, and quench me, for I freeze and burn, And at one objećt both rejoyce and mourn: What mean'ſt thou Nature,isit bad or good, Which makes this April-weather in my blood & Achm. I fear he has with two much paſſion ſeen The charming eyes of the Hungarian Queen; I ſaw him gaze on her with ſuch review, As if he fear'd the objećt were not true: Somiracles are ſeen by faithleſs men, Who ſtay and fain would ſee them o're agen. zang. Oh Achmat ſomething does my heart purſue I wander from myſelf, and flye from you. Achm. This, Sir, ſeems one of Loves great extaſies, zang. I would I knew what 'tis not, or what 'tiss Love to my breaſt hath ſtill aſtranger been; And yet that ſtranger may be gotten in. Achm. Ah Prince 1 the ſecret paſſage of Loves flight Is as unſeen by day, as 'tis by night. Though Buda ſhould her Walls like Mountains rear, And Solyman could never enter there, No notwith Armed Crowds the Out-works win, Yet Love un-arm'd would by ſurprize getin. Zang. Love is a god, and carinot be withſtood: Achm. Yet he's agod only to fleſh and blood: For thoſe whoſe Souls are a&tive and ſublime, Reſiſt his power,and ſo prove gods to him. Zang. Ah! talk not of reſiſtance of his force, Whom nothing Conquers but his own remorſe: Irather would, if e're he Conquer'd you, Be told how firſt he did your heart ſubdue. Achm. As quietly as day does vanquiſh night, I heard nonoiſe, but ſaw reſiſtleſslight. Zang. He does, alas ! with quiet force begin, But Oh! What does he do, when enter'd in: l Achm. My waking thoughts I ſtill for dreams did take; And whilſt I dream't, I thought I was awake: With equal view, in darkneſs as in light, Ciara's image entertain'd my fight:
Page 70

(70) If ſhe was abſent, ſorrow made me pale; If ſhe appear'd, thenbluſhes did prevail: What her concern'd, did me more meerly touch. zang. I know toolittle, and I hear too much: Oh Achmat ceaſe and inſtantly retire, Your words are more than fuel to my fire. Fxrant ſeveral waies. EnterSolyman, followed at diſtance by Ruſtaº, Pyrrhus, Soly. Ruſtan does know much more then Idare hear: Can Ia Monſter breed, which I can fear? I find ſuſpition a ſufficient pain, Fear is a torment, which I ſhould diſdain: Herobs my heart of all the Calms of reſt: I'le tear the dire uſurper fom my breaſt: Ruffan is full of try’d integrity, And ſervants often, more then Parents ſee. 1 yrrh. He has more thoughts then he has skill to uſe, Ruff. The poyſon of my whiſper does infuſe. O's curſed Court 1 where not to be the moſt In ſight and eminent, is to be loſt; Where ſtill the weary by falſe ſteps muſt climb, And yet their falling is eſteem'd a crime. Soly. Raffan, my privacy you now invade. Ruff. Sir, it is ſelf-invaſion to be ſad. Soly. Have you a Cure; you brought the malady: I ſay you brought it. Ruſt. Heav'n defend me ! I? Soly. Do you ſº ſpect the truth of what I ſaid : Ruft. Would I had been unborn, or worſe then ticºi, Rather then e're have caus'd a gifinyou, To w! on the comforts of both worlds are due. Soly. You talk'd to me, and took my ſleep away. Ruſt. Could in words, too much my duty pay : "Twere better I ſhould periſh in deſpair, Then you ſhould grieve one moment. | Soly. So it were. Ruff. Sir, you but heard what I was bound to ſay. soly. What was it that you ſpake of Muſapha f Reft. I did with joy acquaint you, that your Son Nobly the hearts of allyour Army won: Your dreaded anger I had juſtly rais'd, If I your deareſt pledge had falſly prais'd, To ſooth you with fićtitious flattery; Put Pyrrhus knows it true, as well as I. Pyrrh. 'Tis true, that he is generous and good; He will ſucceed by vertue, as by blood, Fiſ.
Page 71

(71) º This, Sir ſhould cauſe your joy, and not your grief, Soly. Canſt thou believemy painwill find relief In that which ſhows the juſtice of my fears: Did I in Winter Camps ſpend forty years; Out-wear the Weather, and out-face the Sun, When the Wild Herds did to their Coverts run, Out-watch the Jealous, and the Lunatick 2 Out-faſt the Penitential, and the Sick; Out-wait long Patience, and out-ſuffer Fear, Out-marches the Pilgrim, and the Wanderer: And there, where laſt years Ice was not unthaw'd, (When in thick Furs, Bears durſt not look abroad) Iwith cold Armour cover'd, did maintain Life againſt ſhowres of Arrows, and of Rain: Have I made Towns immur'd with Mountains yield, Sent haughty Nations bluſhing from the Field? And muſt I, at one caſt, all that I forego, For which ſo oft I deſperately did throw a They ſteal my Laurels to adorn my Son; Who can but dream of Fields that I have won: [Ehter Roxoland, Rox. What valiant power can be ſecure from fear When, Sultan, we your voice of anger hear? Who dates that anger raiſe, and hope to live: Sol). If Muſtapha uſurps, ſhall I forgiver Rox. He is your Son, and is your eldeſt too; And may ſhow faults, which others muſt not do: Nature will tell you,Sir, how farr in him You ought to pardon any gallant crime. Solº. Naturemay yield when I my power out-live; For when I cannot puniſh, I forgive. Rºx. His youth, Sir, has not only time to mend, But has ſome licenſe alſo to offend; And ſince too apt for errours being young, Some may advantage take to do him wrong; And, whilſt they Jealous of your glory ſeem’, Aſſume a priviledge to darken him. Soly. He Courts my Armies to uſurp their love. Rox. Canthat your Jealoufie toanger move: Their love you purchas'd,whenyou bravely fought; Let him inherit what for him you bought: They ſhow their love to youin loving him. $ol). They loving him too ſoon, make love a crime: He knows by ſtudy of uſurpers Arts, - That he commands their hands, who gains their hearts: Him whom they love, they ſtill moſt worthy deem. ... Rex. You have more pow'r ore him, then he ore them 5 He will confine that pow'r which lovedóes get. Solº, Pow'r never to its ſelf could limits ſet #
Page 72

(72 ) It never thinks it lives, but whilſt it grows, And what it can perform, it ever does. Ruſt. Our Sultans have their ripe Succeſſours ſent Toſome remote and quiet Government; Why ſince that rule is ſafe, and ancient too, Should it for Muſtaphabe broke by you? soly. I did it out of tender care to breed His youth, and make him worthy to ſucceed. Ruſt. But if, when popular, he does expreſs A ſlow requital of your tenderneſs; Which Heav'n forbid, then you may ſoon remove His perſon, till you can reclaim his love. Rox. Sure, Ruſtan, you with too much vigilance. Turn to deſign, and purpoſe, things of chance ; And, over-watchful with the eyes of fear, Draw little objećts, from wide diſtance, near; And ſee them double, whilſt you ſeem to make All that, which is your malice, yourmiſtake; But do not faſly, as a Spy, prevail, Becauſe a Son may in his duty fail. Ruſt. Madam, I cannot over-watchful be In what concerns the Sultan more than me: I humbly take the priviledge to ſay, That you connive too much at †. And have of late beenſlow and negligent, In what your care could not too ſoon prevent : And, Madam, this perhaps you wiſely do, Tº avoid report, grown publick, though not true; Which is, that with a Byas ſtill you run To follow Zanger, your neglected Son. Soly. No more, theſe are the riſing miſts that make Tiëſ. ſtormy winds, that keep me ſtill awake [Exit Solyman, Rox. Ruſtan, you muſt by freſh intelligence -- Charge Muſtapha, and with ſome new offence. Ruſt. Madam, I am engag'd paſt all retreat. Rox. Go and attend me when the Watch is ſet: Extunt Ru- Theſe little Arts great Nature will forgive: ſtan, Pyrrhus. Dye Muſtapha, elſe Zanger cannot live Pardon, oh Solyman, thy troubl’d Wife; Who muſt her dutyloſe, to ſave a Life; A Husband venture to preſerve a Son; Oh! that's the fatal rock that I would ſhun; For Solyman, muſt Muſtapha deprive, Of that lov'd Life, by which himſelf does live : And Muſtapha, to his untimely grave Muſt haſten, that his death may Zanger ſave, Oh cruel Empire that does thus ordain Of Royal Race the youngeſt to be ſlain, That
Page 73

(73) That ſo the eldeſt may ſecurely Reign; Making th’Imperial Motherever mourn, For all her Infants in ſucceſſion born: Excuſe, oh Nature, what by me is done, If it be cruel to preſerve a Son | [ Exit, Enter Muſtapha, Zanger. Muſt. If it be Love, and you againſt it ſtrive, Then greater ſtrength you to your torment give. Love may all hearts under his Empire bring, Since to reſiſt,and yield, is the ſame thing. Ev’n Reaſons power is uſeleſs againſt Love, For when he enters, reaſon does remove ; And from your force of anger he is free, Since none with what they love can angry be: In vain you this unequal War abide, When allyour aids turn to your Conqu'rours ſide. Zang. I do not, Sir, to Love, but grief ſubmit, Muff. Your grief I know not, yet Iſhare init: A friend is griefs Phyſitian, and may heal Your pain, if you the cauſe of it reveal; But you, by hiding that which ſhould be known, Give meatorment greater than your own; And do ev'n worſe then when you ſhunrelief; For you kill him who comes to cure your grief. . . . Zang. Ah Prince 1 ſince I the weight of grief deplore, You are unkind in loading me with more. Muſt. But you tranſgreſs againſtall Friendſhips Laws, Shewing effects, when you conceal the cauſe; When thoſe you cannot hide, theſe ſhould be told; Thoſe ſhow themſelves, but you muſt theſe unfold. Zang. Your Enemy much rather than your Friend, Shou'd tell you griefs which you can never end. Muff. Friendſhip will nothing like reſerves endure, But loves to ſhare in griefs it cannot cure. zang. Then will Ithrow my vain defence away, And, though obedience uſeleſs be, obey. You know what by my Mother has been done For the Hungarian Queens abandon'd Son. Muff. Yes, and the Deed was for her greatneſs fit. Zang. The Queen herſelfis come t'acknowledge it: And that her gratitude may clearer ſhine, She does ſtrong Buda, as a gift reſign. *:: They may, by vertueurg'd, for honour ſtrive ; But why ſhould this make Noble Zanger grieve? Zang. Canfate bring greater grief to me or you Then now, when the ſubdu'd dous ſubdue? V WY e
Page 74

(74) We have by Arms th Hungarian Kingdom won. And by their Queen in honour are out-done: A Crown reſign'd my Mother ought to quit, Since ſhe by keeping does not merit it: Can you my ſorrow for my Mother blame, Who now muſt leſſen in her Pow'r or Fame: Muff. In ſuch a choice ſhe cannot chuſe amiſs; But, Zanger, there is in it more then this. Zang. Ah Prince much more indeed, for had you ſeen The griefs and beauties of the Chriſtian Queen, You would have felt the trouble which I had; Theſe did to pity, thoſe to love perſwade: They help'd each other to perform their part, Grief ſoftn'd, and her beauty ſeal'd my heart; Through all her blacks the luſtre of her eyes Shew'd like the Sun when it from night does riſe: But I want words for what I ſhould commend. Muff. Howſoon from liking we to love aſcend! Zang. When ſhe her Royal Infant did embrace, Her Eyes ſuch floods of Tears ſhow'd on her face, That then, oh Muſtapha I did admire How ſo much Water ſprang from ſo much Fire: And, to increaſe the miracle, I found At the ſame time my heart both burnt and drown'd. Muff. What you have told, ſeems miracles to me. Zang. You will ſee greaterwhen the Queen you ſee. Muft. Tome no miracle can greater prove Then ſeeing Friendſhips right reſign'd to love: Your Heart onceloſt your Friendſhip too muſt end. Zang. Sure I may have a Miſtreſs and a Friend. The Soul, dear Muſtapha, is Friendſhips part, And Love for his does challengebut the heart? Muſt. That's a diſtinction made by couz'ning Art; Can I your Friendſhip have, and not your Heart: Such Lovers Logick is too low for you; What love a Captive, and a Chriſtian too : Zang. How ill the name of Captive does befit A mind that conquers whenit does ſubmit: Her abjećt fate who would not undergo That ſhe might Vertue in ſuch Triumph ſhow? Muff. Though Friendſhip may injuſt perſwaſion fail, Yet, Zanger, your Religion ſhould prevail. Zang. Since Nature no Religion knows but Love, He that loves moſt, does moſt Religious prove: Religions true deſign in Love conſiſts, Heav'n owns not that which States-men teach our Prieſts. I love, but when I on the Queen reflect, The cauſe will more than juſtifieth' effect.
Page 75

(75 ) Muff. Py ſeeing of your ſhipwrack I'll grow wiſe. Zang. How can Iſhipwrack’t be on Paradiſe 2 Muſt. Something in your concern I hope to do: Farewels I muſt condemn and love you too. [Exeunt ſeverally. Enter the Cardinal with Papers in his hand, Viche, and an Hungarian Gentleman. Card. This for the Governour with your firſt ſpeed, This for Count trick, this for 1/lfinſhed, Theſe are the Bills which will be paid at fight. Gent. Isit your pleaſure I returnat night : Card. You muſt, and learn who of the Garriſon Form'd the revolt: be careful, and be gone. [Exit Gentleman, Wiche. Fortune's before you wherefoe're you Come; You ! happy be ev’n out of Chriſtendom. Card. I ſhall be, if ſhe end as ſhe begun. Wiche. You are for Roxolana's darling Son. The glorious Zanger has a Meſſage ſent, Which ſays, he means to find you in your Tent; He whom our Queens bright beauty did ſurprize. Card. A Lover ſpeaks at firſt but with his eyes; But if he now hath found his tongue, he'l ſay Something which I perhaps am to convey. Wiche. Their happy interview may raiſe us all: Men may look up . to the bottom fall. card. My Lord,his viſit ſeems deſign'd inhaſte, And to receive him I'll prepare as faſt: You muſt not go to Buda; you ſhall ſtay And wait for our ſucceſs: d: Mirtle may (Which does a forward Spring already ſhow) Even in a Camp where all things wither, grow: In fames records twill no great wonder prove, If we, who fell by hatred, riſe by love., [Exeunt ſeveral wayes. Enter Muſtapha and the Queen. Muff. Madam, your fortune would malicious be, And make your beauty your worſt Enemy. Iknow with reaſon, Madam, you depend On Roxolana, as your potent Friend; But whilſt ſhelabours to reſtore your Throne, Your beauty makes a Captive of her Son; When ſhe does thatunhappy Conqueſt know, Your kind Protećtreſs will become your Foe. Whilſt fateagainſt your beauty does conſpire, I grieve at the perfection I admire. 2stem.
Page 76

(76) Queen. Donot believe, Great Prince, your Brother will submit to eyes where grief inhabits ſtill; To eyes in which there nothing now appears To move a heart, unleſs it be their tears; You but miſtake his pity for his love. Muff. Thy paſſion, Zanger, why did Ireprove : [Aſide, Madam, where grief and beauty ſo excel, Pity and love may both together dwell; They both are but his duties ſacrifice, This to your fate is due, that toyour eyes. ..Queen. Your Vertue which does thus my fatelament, May all the malice of that fate prevent; Conqu ring a fortune ſo perverſe as mine, Will makeyoubrighter than in Battel ſhine. Muff. Oh Heav'n ' Ifeel my own ſubjećtion near, Even then when ſhe would have mereſcue her. .9qeen. Fortunein this has made her laſt aſſault, She'd have mebear what is aloneher fault, And make the Empreſs think that Ideſign What cannot be her trouble more than mine. Believe me, Gen'rous Muſtapha, theſe eyes Which made the laſt Hungarian King their prize, Deſerve more griefthan to his urn they pay, When they do ought but weep themſelves away. Muff. Whilſt § ſhin'd out, who could reſiſt their pow'r, VWhich, through griefs clouds, crowns you a Conquerour? 2ueen. Your Brother, when his paſſion ſeeks relief, May owe his Cure to reaſon and my grief; It will a blemiſh to his Vertue be, If he with fortune join to ruine me; And Roxolana's fame he much neglects, In making her deſtroy whom ſhe protećts: This you may tell him, Sir; and tell him too, I had not ſent him Counſel but by you. Muſt. How, Madam, with your Counſel can you truſt One whom already you have made unjuſt? For I ſhall give to Zanger, for your ſake, Counſel which I myſelf can never take. 2ueen. Were you unjuſt when you did well expreſs The danger I incurr'd by his addreſs, And counſell'd me t'adviſe him to refrain From love, which would his Mothers hatred gain : The Counſel is not alter'd, but the ſame. Muſt. But I am alterd'd ſince Ihither came. 2ueen. It is not fit you ſhould be underſtood, I know you cannot change from what is good; My caſe with pity ſhould your heart inſpire. Muff. Ah! who can pity what he does admite? Your
Page 77

(77) Your pity to my caſe is rather due: How can I give that which Ineed from you ? Madam, Ibut in vain ſtrive to conceal A ſº. which my vanquiſh'd eyes reveal; Inſtruct me how my ſelf Iſhould reclaim, Before Izanger for his paſſion blame; Or rather teach us both how to endure That wound, which you declareyou cannot cure; And do not truſt our reaſon to ſubdue A love, which reaſon does invite us to. 2ueen. Oh Heav'n' in what wild Ocean am I loſt? The Tempeſt riſes and Iſee no Coaſt. Muff. Zanger,mot you, may taxmeof a crime; Icame to counſel you from love of him; But you, when you avoid my love, prevent All he could wiſh me for a puniſhment; Your int’reſtbrought mehere to keep you free From ſuch a love as might your ruine be; Let me, when gone, at leaſt your pity have, Dying for you whom I did come to ſave. 2ueen. You cannot be ſo cruel as you ſeem: Why do you break that heart which youeſteem : Leave me, you muſt not love, and ſhould not hate One cruel made by rigour of her fate. Maff. Youſhould not of your deſtiny complain, You are depos'd but with more power to reign. 2ueen. Fate of this little beauty took a care, Only by that to heighten my deſpair. Since you reſolve to ſtay, Imuſt begone, True grief endures not any looker on; And mine I feel to ſuch a height does riſe, That 'twill I hope revenge me of my eyes. [Exit. Muſt. She is as tyrannous as ſhe is fair, Born to breed love, and to beget deſpair; I did lament her fortune, but I ſee One much more cruel is reſerv'd forme. Can Zanger, for my love, my friendſhip blame, When the ſame fire does usalike inflame: My weakneſs cannot forfeit his eſteem, Since I but yield to that which conquer'd him; Tolove whom he firſt lov’d, can be no more Then if I hate whom he did hate before. [Exit. X T H E

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 78

(78) THE T H I R D A C T. Enter Muſtapha, Ruſtan, Pyrrhus. *T*: the Sultans will to have it ſo. Muſt. Toward's Syria! and tomorrow muſt I got The order is ſevere, and I am ſent, Not to a fair retreat, but baniſhment. My memory is ill if I have done Ought that ſhould make a Father hate a Son. Ruff. Great Sir, take heed leſt you his kindneſs blame, He ſends you not to exile, but to fame; His Aſian Armies will beled by you: whilſt he the Weſt, you muſt the Eaſt ſubdue: Since for high valour and for condućt too, The publick voice allows that each of you Is for the ſpacious worlds whole Conqueſt fit, Why here ſhould both ſubdue but part of it? Muff. You hold me up too high when I am prais'd, I like a Meteor waſte by being rais'd; I am already by my Friends undone, Praiſing the little Battels I have won ; And I the Perſians ſhould ſubdue in vain, Loſing a Father when I Perſia gain. Pyrrh. Your Father this diſtemper ſhould approve, Since you but jealous are of him you love. Ruft. If his diſpleaſure haſtensyou away, Do not increaſe it by deſire to ſtay; Or if his jealous love ſent this command, Yet do not inconvenient love withſtand. Pyrrh. Which way ſoever you conſider it, You ſhould approve his orders and ſubmit. Muſt. I'm debter to you both; leave me a while That I may grief and duty reconcile. Ruſt. You'l be defended againſtall offence, Adding but patience to your innocence, Exeunt Ruſtan, Pyrrhus. Enter Zanger obſerving him, Muff. Fortune did never in one day deſign For any heart, four torments great as mine; I to my Friend and Brother Rival am; She, who did kindle, would put out my flames
Page 79

(79) I from my Fathers anger muſt remove, And that does baniſh me from her I love; If, of theſe Four, the leaſt a burden be, Oh how ſhall I ſupport the other three: Zang. Can my dear Muſtapha a grief admit, And not let Zanger know the cauſe of it? Muff. I having Zangers Friendſhip how could Fate Deſtroy my peace but by my Fathers hate: Time does too long with the afflićted laſt, But now in my afflićtion moves too faſt; Tomorrow from to day will quickly grow, And I to morrow muſt tow’rds Syria go, Unleſs your pow'r with Roxolana can Revoke the order ſent by Solyman. Zang. Depart tomorrow ! no, let time tun on My Mother ſtays, and you are yet not gone. Sir, are you not of Zangers friendſhip ſure : And can you mourn for ills which he may cure • But why do you aloud your grief deplore, When ſam ſilent, though I ſuffer more : If by your foes you are to Syria ſent, You'l there in Armies gain by Baniſhment: Perſia, not you, th' event of this ſhould fear, Since by that hatred which does ſend youthere You will prevail as Vićtor of the field; But Love ſtays me, where like his ſlave I yield. Muſt. The higheſt glory conqueſt can beſtow I would not purchaſe by my leaving you. Zang. To any Deity, but Love, men come With open glory to their Martyrdom; But I muſt periſh and conceal my flame, Asif to be his Martyr were a ſhame. Muff. Yet no afflićtion, Zanger, can tranſcend The grief of being baniſh'd from a Friend. Zang. My grief much greateris, whilſt I remain Near her I love, and am not lov'd again. Oh my dear Muſtapha when you have ſeen The Tears and Beauties of th: Hungarian Queen; Her Tears forbidding whom her Eyes invite, Whilſt ſhe appears the joy and grief of fight; Whilſt empty hope does riſe but to decline; Then you will think your ſorrows leſs then mine, Muſt. Alas! you ſaw not more then I did ſee; She who did conquer you, ha's conquer'd me; And now I may my grief to yours prefer, Since I am baniſh'd both from you and her. Zang. Ha! Did you ſee her, Sir, and ſee her ſo, That from my friend you did thy Rival grow & ‘roº
Page 80

(8o) You made your viſit in a fatal hour. Muſt. You know her eyes, and can you doubt their powe: In blaming me you will detract from them; As thoſe who do the conquer'd much condemn, Do then diſparage him who overcame ; Since all may yield to Worthies without ſhame. None could her forcer, ſiſt, and how could I Then chuſe but yield: for none can from her flye. Zang. Though we but ſeldom the ſubdu'd condemn When we the Vićtors condućtmucheſteem; Yet they are leſs excus'd if they did know, From others haims, the forces of the Foe. Muff. If, Zanger, freedom of confeſſion may The anger due to an offence allay, Then I acknowledge I my viſit made, That from your Love I might the Queen diſſvade; Yet 'twas in fear, leſt whilſt you did purſue Your Love your Mother might abandon you: But if you had beheld that breaking light, Which like a ſudden dawn ſurpriz'd my ſight, Love would have ſeem'd'gainſt friendſhip a leſs ſin, Then not to love againſt her eyes had been; Iſtuggld much e're I his Fetters wore; But that reſiſtance ſhow'd her power the more; And where reſiſtance could not conqueſt ſtay, It was diſcretion quickly to obey. Zang. Yet we may juſt to one another prove; You are the Heir to Empire, I to Love; Youts the Eldeſt may the Scepter bear, You firſt the world did ſee, I firſt ſaw her; And as I no invaſion would deſign Againſt your right, ſo you ſhould leave me mine. Muff. If by meer ſight we may poſſeſſion take, How vain is that long Love which Lovers make : None but the ſleepy can their fortune doubt ; Men need but riſebetimes and look about : But ſhe muſt be by merits claim poſſeſt, And he who loves her moſt, deſerves her beſt. Zang. Deſerves her This all injuries exceeds; Her, by your words you wrong, me by your deeds ; He of her Love unworthy does appear, Who does but think that he can merit her; It may of her, ev'n as of Heaven be ſaid, Which, though attain'd, is never merited; If loving her can any merit be, Who is the man that dares contend with me : Muſt. I am the man who ſilence all that boaſt How much they love ; for I love more and moſt; And
Page 81

(81) And will not ſuch a wretched Lover be, As meerly to depend oncourteſie, He who declares that he no merit has, Then when heloves, does heedleſly diſgrace Her whom he thinks he highly does prefer, By ſaying, that no Love can merit her; As if her Vertue could not ſoon improve To her own value all that dare make Love. Love makes both ſexes equal and but one: A Cottage-Lovel may deſerve a Throne. Love is, like Valour, ſtill improv’d by praiſe, And whilſt Ithus Love's merit highly raiſe : I would not the rewards of it deſtroy; The beauty whom I love I muſt enjoy. zang. Did ever Love aſſume a ſhape like this 2 Or Paſſion talk with ſuch an Emphaſis: Yourſence of Baniſhment does dang'rous grow, It ſends your reaſon from you e're you go. Muſt. Zanger, you may my Beniſhment approve, Becauſe my abſence may promote your Love. zang. Afflićtion makes men wiſe, but ſeldom vain. You fear your abſence more than her diſdain. The Empreſs ſtrait ſtill in your cauſe appear, And get you Licenſe to continue here; And ſince you height of Love as merit boaſt. Make good your claim by daring to love moſt. Muſt. What deſtiny ordain'd me to contend Againſt ſobrave a Rival and a Friend? And yet my paſſion I muſt ſtill purſue: Let Love which makes my fault, excuſe it too. Exeant ſeveral wayes, Enter Solyman, Ruſtan, Pyrrhus. soly. Were my Commands with ſuch ſurprize receiv'dº Pyrrh. He ſeem'd as much amaz'd as he was griev'd. Ruſt. Wonder and grief did his condition fit, Thougheach did ſeem to th’other oppoſite; Wonder inferr'd he knew not his offence, But ſo much grief diſgrac'd his innocence. Pyrrh. Yet grieving for a puniſhment from you, He does but pay that ſorrow which is due. Ruſt. When your diſlike does up to anger climb. You reach too high for an intended crime; Such grief as his no fićtion could admit. Soly. I may believe he did not counterfeit; For having on my ſtage begun his part, Icall'd him offe're he could ſhow his Art. Y Åuff, -
Page 82

(82 ) Ruff. Canhe, who is ſo highly born and bred, Walk underground, and be by 1 raytorsled? soly. From hamleſs Child-hood I with tender care Did breed him up to all the harms of War ; I taught him, that unguarded innocence Serv'd but to tempt the powerful to offence; That none are ſafe from wrongs, but when ſo ſtrong As alwaies to be able to do wrong; That only valouris true faith, and thoſe Domoſt truſt Heav'n who alwaies life expoſes I taught him Vertue,and to love her ſo As time Philoſophers duſt never do ; Enduring for her ſake the pangs of power, And all the toyls that make a Conquerour: Fo none but Chiefs who firmly theſe endure, Can reach ſuch pow'r as may the good ſecure: I taught him ſuch a greatneſs as might be From all the yokes of Subjects counſel free: None but our Prophet Fmpire underſtood, Which, when’tis bounded, ceaſs to be good; His Sword did two Ulſurping Saints devour; Forbidding ev'n the Saints to ſhare his power: He bleſt Heav'ns King who Monarchy firſt made, And prais'd him cauſe he no companion had. All this I taught my Son; but when we give Our young Succeſſouls counſel how to live, They are in haſte, thinking we do them wrong, And we their lives miſ-ſpend when we live long. Enter Roxoland. Rox. Forgive me, Sultan, if I boldly ſue In Natures cauſe between your Son and you ; Thoſe orders which to Muſtapha you ſent, His filial kindneſs takes for Baniſhment. When you your Succeſſours ſofar remove, Reaſon may make him jealous of your Love; I’le anſwer for the kindneſs of his grief, And you'l want pity if he wants relief. Saly. Alas! 'tis far above a Womans art To reach the height of an aſpiring heart: He who by craft, my Aimies love procures, Can never want the cunning to gain yours. Rox. Seduce your Armies love! no humane skill Can do it, and, I hope, he wants the will. Soly. The Nations whom Ilead will not ſeem ſtrange. If they, like other Nations long for change; For men of what they have ſoon weary grow, When they the utmoſt value of it know; And
Page 83

(83) And long to change plain things, which they poſſeſs; For that which hope does gild with promiſes. Rox. Be to your ſelf and to your Army juſt: You ſhould their love and your own merit truſt. Prodigious jealouſie, how can it ſhoot And ſpring to ſuch a height without a root: Soly. It may a whlebe hidden from your eye; Forroots are deepeſt where the trees are high. Ruſtan and Pyrrhus can direct your ſight; But they a 3. draw before the light. Rox. Perhaps they find what they are loth to ſees Vertue in others may offenſive be To ſome, who when it is to luſtre grown Are jealous that it may Eclipſe their own. Sultan, no Curtain can be drawn ſo wide, That it the Suncan from the people hide : The world is full of Muſtapha's renown. Ruſt. Yet we offendin telling what is known. Rox. You injure him whoſe vertues you conceal. Ruſt. We need not ſhew what does it ſelf reveal, Soly. I tax them not that they his Vertue hide, But they concealthedanger of #. pride : His race of glory is too ſoon begun. Rox. None blame the early riſing of the Sun, Nor wiſh for Clouds his luſtre to diſgrace. Soly. But if he ſhines too fully in myface, Ile draw a Curtain and his luſtre hide; His glory ſhall not makeme turn aſide. The ſhining Muſtapha muſt change his Sphear; He threatens me worſe than a Comet here. Rox. Can Solyman by thoſe forſaken be Whom he ſo often led to Vićtory : Soly. They by the many Battels I have won, Think all the ſtock of my ſucceſs is gone: Though fortune often grac'd me in the field, And many favours hung upon my ſhield; Yet now cold looks men to my winter bring, Whilſt they rejoyce at my Succeſſour's ſpring: Fortune they think is to his youth indebt, And what ſhe pays to him they hope to get. Rox. Thoughglory may awhile his youth miſ-guide, Yet he has duty to correóthis pride. Nature does give him counſel againſt this. Soly. Pride is more natural then duty is: Duty is only taught by care and Art, Pride is by nature planted in the heart: He who to Empire hºſtily aſpires, Is only counſell'd by his own deſires; Ar. r.
Page 84

(84) And thinks all crimes which help him to a Crown Are then abſolv’d when he does put it on. Rox. Ifear you have diſcover'd more then I Diſcend, who on your judgement muſt rely; Therefore, in care of you, I beg he may For a few dayes haveliberty to ſtay : That licenſe is to narrow time confin'd: lf he has any publick crime deſign'd, He muſt by many hands aſſiſted be: Crouds are inconſtant and want ſecreſie: If guilty, why ſhould you his death delay: If innocent, he then may ſafely ſtay: Your anger ought to kill where it does touch ; His Exile is too little or too much. Pyrrh. When in few dayes this ſecret ſhall lookout, Puniſh his crime, or elſe ſuppreſs his doubt. Ruſt. Be pleas'd t” allow what th' Empreſs does adviſe, And ſeem to wink, whilſt we imploy our Spies; Your doubts will juſt appear, or quickly ceaſe, Excuſe your anger, or reſtore your peace: Let not the Prince, whilſt thus ſuſpected flie Beyond the reach and terrour of your eye. Soly. Go, I'le conſidere’re I change his doom; I'le reckon what is paſt, and what may come. Excunt Ru- Oh Rexolana | Fate in vain beſtows ſtan, Pyrrhus. Continual Conqueſts o're my open Foes; Whilſt it a tumult raiſes in my breſt, Fiercer than all thoſe Wais I have ſuppreſt. Juſtice perſwades what nature fain would ſhun. Pity a father who muſt hate his Son. [Exéunt. Enter the Queen and Zanger. Zang. He who can all his love contain in words, Has ſuch a heart as littlelove affords, Queen. He has too much for thoſe who none return: You know my ſorrow, and for whom Imourn: From ſuch a guilty perſon you ſhould flie As does the duty want by grief to die. Zang. I would not in my wiſhes covet more Then to change fates with him whom you deplore: You crown'd him with your love when he did live, And to his death your life in ſorrow give. But, Madam, why will you ſo highly grieve, For one more happy dead, than I who live? You are in this unjuſter then your Fate, Waſting your ſorrows on the fortunate. Heav'n
Page 85

(85) Heav'n did his death deſign to make it known That you a bleſſing are too great for one. The Chriſtian world did to your beauty bow, Which o're our larger world muſt govern now. ..Queen. In pity and in prudence, Sir, forbear, To ſpeak what my diſcretion ſhould not hear. Zang. Lovers high thoughts to wonders are inclind; Andboundleſs thoughts ſuit not with ſpeech confin'd. I wonder much how he, whom you bemoan, Having your love, could not defend your Throne; And how by any force he was ſuppreſt, Whilſt with the influence of your favour bleſt. But, Madam, now his loſſes you repair, For you revenge all his defeats in War; Fate did deny his Sword ſucceſs in fight, Only by that to do your beauty right. #. Yout raiſing me by your depreſſing him, May find my hapredſeekingmyeſteem. Enter Muſtapha. Zang. Ha! I employ'd my Mother for his ſtay, And Rival-like he haſlens me away; But I'm paſt hope, and need no Rival fear. Muſt. This viſit without leave may rudeappear: Yet, Madam, when you ſhall vouchſafe to know That Itomorrow muſt tow'rds Syria go; Th’opininion of my rudeneſs you'l re-call: I muſt attend you now or not at all. Thinkona Lovers ſorrow, who removes Fiom ſeeing and from ſerving what he loves; Whilſt he ſuſpects thoſebleſſings are deſign'd For a more happy Rival left behind; Do but allow your pity to allay That ſorrow which your love might take away. Zang. Madam, if this requeſt ſucceſsful be Then Iſhall need your pity more than he: I am deſtroy'd if this be not deny'd, For pity is to love too near ally'd, Loves wounds are ſaſe when of your pity ſure; The wounds you pity you deſire to cure. Muff. Your love does make you cruel when you plead Againſt that pity which your Friend does need. Zang. Your Love in high injuſtice does delight, Pleading to get your Friend's and Brother's right. Muff. You have declar'd that Love no right can ſhow But what a Miſtreſs freely does beſtow. Zang. As of the fair new world he claim'daright Who chanc'd to have it firſt within his ſight; Z So
Page 86

(86) So, ſince to me ſhe did the firſt appear, I claim the right of a Diſcoverer. - Muff. The firſt Diſcov’rer only ſaw the ſhore; The ſecond claim'd poſſeſſion ſeeing more. In your firſt ſeeing, and then loving her, The favour of your fortune did appear, Not greatneſs of your love; for all, like you, Having but eyes to ſee, would love her too. You but the beauty of her face did find; I made the rich diſcovery of her mind. You of the borders of Elizium boaſt, Her mind is all the Inland to that Coaſt. I by a ſecond voyage finding more Of beauty then was ever found before; More in it to be lov'd and worſhipp'd too, Muſt therefore love her more then you can do. zang. Amongſt the Prieſts of Love there Caſuiſts be, Who Love's Religion vex with Sophyſtry; But I for ſacrifice bling ſuch a heart As Nature offers in diſdain of Art. Queen. Princes no more. You both but vainly ſtrive To be poſſeſt of what I ſhould not give; That which I ſhould not give, you ſhould not take, Nor prize my Love when Duty I forſake: it is in me impiety to ſtay. Detain not whom the dead does call away. She effers to go out, Zanger ſays her, Zang. Stay, Madam. When the Clouds of grief are gone, Which cannot darken long ſobright a Sun, Let Zanger in his love ſo happy be That none may happier prove in yours then he: If you to any others ſuit incline Then my Succeſſous Love diſgraces mine. This is not envy, but does rather ſhow I prize my love becauſe 't's given to you. Muff. True Friendſhip, Madam, cannot yield to this; If you reječt my Love, accept of his ; Next to your Love the bleſfing I would chuſe Is that my Fiend may gain what I muſt loſe. Zang. I am amaz'd at what you ſeem to do : Let me not bear Loves wounds and Friendſhips too. Muſt. Only thoſe Lovers ſhould be counted true Who Beauties intºreſt, not their own purſue; Who nobly would, when by their fortune croſt, Have others get what to themſelves is loſt. None but the Fiends can wiſh Heav'n empty were Becauſe they cannot get poſſeſſion there. Zang. This gallantry does reconcile in you The utmoſt of revenge and friendſhip too; Re-
Page 87

(87) Revenge appears moſt ſenſible and high In placing favours on an Enemy. Forgive me if that ſtyle I undergo; He who a Rival is, is then a Foe. Friendſhip till now did ne're ſo high aſcend As to endure a Rival in a Friend. In one bright Sphear we may together move. Whilſt you excel in Friendſhip, I in Love. But having paid what to my Love was due, Let me diſcharge my debt of Friendſhip too, Midam, I thus would expiate my crime; That which he beg'd for me I beg for him. Tracing his ſteps how can I ſurer tread? l'le follow Vertue which I ſhould have led. .Queen. This which you Beauty call ſo much offends, When it does Rivals make of two ſuch friends, That I, by drowning it, will give relief - To your unequall'd Friendſhip and my grief. She Hºfs. Zang. Againſt that Beauty why ſhould yourepine Which makes our Friendſhip with ſuch luſtre ſhine? Muff. You wrong the world when you your beauty wrong; That and the Sun to all the world belong. Queen. My grief is greater then I ſhould endure; I'le flye from wounds l make and cannot cure. Exit, and they gaze after her. Muſt. Oh, Zanger, look not after her ſo long 1 Through all her clouds her luſtre is too ſtrong. Zang. As courage of weakTowns, in their defence Againſt ſtrong Armies, is held inſolence, So I, reſiſting Fate in this aſſault, May make ev’n fortitude become a fault. Enter Achmat, and whiſpers Zanger. Achm. The Empreſs, Sir, commanded me to ſay She has prevail'd, and Muſtapha ſhall ſtay. Zang. Leave us, we ſhall her pleaſure ſtrait a tend. [Exit. Achmat. Muff. What froward meſſage does my fortune ſend ? zang. Sir, you are timely eas'd of half your fear. My Mother ſays that you ſhall tary here. Since I have this procur'd you may allow Your ſelf to think that I will keep my vow. I have in Friendſhip vow’d not to ſurvive The fatal day on which you ceaſe to live. And 'tis a work more difficult and high To help a Rival then it is to dye. Muff. I know you'l keep your vow; and I ſome ſign Have giv'n that I ſhall faithful prove to mine,
Page 88

(88) I vow'd, if by ſucceſſion I ſhould gain Th’ Imperial Scepter.you ſhould with mereign. And ſince in Love's nice int’reſt I comply (Whoſe Empire is ſecur'd by jealouſie, And where each Lover ſtrives torule alone) I can admit a Rival in my Throne. [They Embrace, Extant. Enter Thuracus, Viche, Cleora. riche. Ha! Will ſhe leave the Camp: who can prepare Counſel for changes which ſo ſudden are : Thur. My Lord, her reſolution muſt ſeem ſtrange 5 But, as 'tis ſudden, ſo it ſoon may change: She did by me a ſecond offer make; urging the Empreſs inſtantly to take The keys of Buda, our revolting Town; Hoping by quitting that to keep the Crown. Wiche. What was the anſwer which the Empreſs made * Thur. She ſummon'd all the glory that ſhe had 3 Then ſaid, ſhe would not from the &: receive A Preſent till ſhe could a greater give. And then declard, her Sultan ought and muſt Eſteem that faith which did his honour truſt; That he by conqueſt ſhould proceed no more; And what his glory took it ſhould reſtore. Enter Cardinal, and Queen, cleora. The Cardinal ſeems thoughtful, and the Queen Does feel more ſorrow then ſhe would have ſeen. Exeunt Thuracus, Viche, Cleofa, Card. But when purſu'd will you from refuge run, And Sanétuaries ſlut againſt your Son? Your Infant whilſt from proffer'd love you flye, Muſt meet the hatred of your Enemy. Ruſtan has long your Royal houſe abhorr'd : And he is now to former pow'r reſtor'd: The ſtorm which from the Empreſs he endur'd Has his foundation try’d and ſtrength ſecurd. ..Qaeen. When you the Princes proffer'd loves commend You ſeem to Fmpire, not to me, a Friend: And when your King I in his Grave forſake, I loſe more love then you would have metake. Card. Be taught by Nature; ſhe forſakes the Dead; Your precious Tears you but on aſhes ſhed, Which now an urn keeps ſacred, but they muſt By wand'ring Winds be blown with common duſt. Nature does turn her looks from Death's ill Face; Where ruine does not Natures ſtrength diſgrace, But
Page 89

(89) But by theſlightneſs of man's Fabrick ſhows (which time evºn with a touch ſoon overthrows) That ſhe made flown's intending they ſhould fade 3 And Mourners erre when Nature they upbraid. It is at once Idolatry and Pride To place on Altars what ſhe throws aſide. Lovecnly to the living does belong: Loving the dead you all the living wrong : And both betray and loſelove's int’reſt when You love the dead who cannot love agen. 2ueen. But is there to the dead no ſorrow due: card. What uſeful is grows only fit for you. Grieve not for one made uſeleſs being gone; But favour thoſe who may reſtore your Throne. Queen. Since both the Princes do alike pretend, VVäich to my favour will you moſt commend ? If Imuſt Love, and ſhall be taught by you, I cannot, ſure, be counſell'd to love two. card. But you may favour both, and may diſguiſe Orſhew your Love as int’reſt ſhall adviſe. Queen. I cannot int’reſt by ſuch arts improve, Seeming to favour whom I do not Love: Nor with two Faces ſeverally invite From both what I in neither can requite. card. Yet do not both for want of loving loſe; But ſuddenly conſider which to chuſe. Ingaining Zanger you the Empreſs gain; But Muſtapha muſt by ſucceſſion reign. 2ueen. Each is ſufficient to reſtore my Throne. But, whilſt for Empire you are ſtudious grown, Younothing for the other world prepare. My Lord, take Heav'nalittle in your care. How can Iought of Love from Princes hear, VVho ſcorn thoſe Altars where I kneel with fear? card. They their Religion did by Conqueſt make; And will no Rules but from their Conqu'rors take. If they, till taught, can never truth diſcern They muſt be conquer'd to be made to learn: And ſince no Pow'r but Love can them ſubdue, Madam, they muſt be overcome by you. But ſhe who will o'recome in Love's fair field Muſt by her yielding make her Lover yield. ..Queen. My Lord, your Purple Robe has ſtudy'd well, Muſt I this way convent an Infidel? card. Love is perſwaſive and will ſooneſt teach. 2ueen. They both can to the top of Empire reach, But cannot ſoar to our Religions height. card. By truſting Muftapha you'l teach him Faith. A 2 Jºmfºr
Page 90

(90) Enter Cleora. Cteora. My Lord, ſince Muſtapha is in your Tent. Card. Madam, my thoughts are with true duty bent To ſerve your Throne. Do not kind Fortune loſe When ſhe preſents you two great Lottstochuſe. [Exit Cardinal. 24een. Without a Clue I'm in alabrynth left: And where even Hope is of her Eyesbereft. With Noble Zanger Maſtapha contends, They ſtrive as Rivals and they yield as Friends: I injure one if I the other chuſe; And keeping either I the Sultan loſe. Flying fiom both I from my refuge run; And by my ſtaying ſhall deſtroy my Son. Them for their falſe Religion I eſchew Though I have found their Vertue ever true. And when Religion ſends my thoughts above, This Card'nal calls them down and talks of Love: And ſimple Love (which does as little know State-int'reſt as Religion ought to do) He would, bold with Ambition, lead through all The daik and crooked walks where Serpentscrawl. His Prieſts to what he counſels gravely bow; Whilſt other Prieſts condemn what thoſe allow: Thoſe would by Pious craft r, ſtore our loſs; Theſe ſcorn the Creſcent ſhould redeem the Croſs. Zealagainſt Policy maintains debate; Heav'n gets the betternow,and now the State. The Learned do by turns the Learn'd confute, Yet all depart unalter'd by diſpute. The Prieſtly Office cannot be deny'd; It wears Heav'ns Liv'ry and is made out Guide. But why ſhould we be puniſh'd if we ſtray, When allour Guides diſpute which is the way? T H E

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 91

( 91 ) T H E F O UIR T H A C T. Enter the Queen, and Cleora. Queen. TYIſpatch, Cleora, leſt we ſhould be ſeen. - Lay my diſguiſe beneath the Couch within, You ſhould have ſent to call the Cardinal: I have forgot my Letters. Burn them all. Here, take the Key I make up my Jewels ſtrait. You ſhallattend me at the Eaſtern Gate: But burn my Letters in the inner Tent. cleora. Ifear you will this haſte too ſoon repent. 2ueen. Fortune, with thy diſtempers I muſt ſtrive; And from a crime will not my curederive. Thoſe who by policy their actions ſteer Faint when they faults as well as loſſes bear; But thoſe who on firm vertue ſtill relie May boldly periſh when they guiltleſs die. Cleora. "Twere want of neceſſary Faith in me To think your virtue can ſucceſsleſs be. All your commands I'leinſtantly obey. 2ueen. Our flight, Cleora, cannot brook delay; Nor can Iany pauſe to fear allow. Enter Roxolana. Rox. You were my Gueſt, but are my Prisºner now. Doyounot tremble ſeeing me appear? .Queen. None but the guilty ſhould have ſenſe offear. Rox. Diſmiſs Cleora ! we muſt be alone To reckon both what I and you have done. 2ueen. Retire | Th’intentions of my flight are all Betray'd by her, or by the Cardinal. [ Exit Cleora, Rox. To make the Audit of my actions true I'le briefly take their Regiſter from you. Did I not ſtruggle in your Sons defence, When with no Armour but his innocence The reſcue of his Crown I undertook, Whom all his Nation, being arm’d, forſook : ..Queen. Madam, of what you did this is the leaſt. Rox. No Bird, new fledg'd, and frighted from his Neſt, Could, more then he, be of his home bereft, Or more to Natures caſual mercy left. Did I not boldly his weak cauſe maintain Againſt the Vizier and the whole Divan, Though from their number I did need defence: For number has a proſp’rous impudence, Which
Page 92

(92 ) Which more prevails in Courts then in the Field, Making by clamour ſingle Fav'rites yield. And I was forc'd, when charg’d by the Divan, To my laſt ſtrength, the love of Solyman. 2ueen. Your Enemies could not but many be, You having then all that were ſo to me. Rox. When, without leave, you did adventure here, And, by the right of War, my Prisºner were, Did not then my favours ſo extend That you became no Prisºner but my Friend?, When Buda you did offer to reſign, I)id I not conſtantly the gift decline, And in your cauſe the Sultan did implore That what his Sword had gain’d he would reſtore? Queen. All bounties, Madam, muſt to yours ſubmit, Which nothing equa's but my ſenſe of it. Rox. Having confeſt my allegations true, Maik what returns his ſince been made by you. For more than hope of what you wiſht to be, For your protection and your liberty, For all I did, and purpos'd to hºv. 'one, You, in requital, have enſlav'd my Son. A Son, who never yet my will controul’d Till he your fatal beauty did belold: But now, with that inchanted, is no more By his own regſon rul’d, not by my pow'r, What my deſigns have built, you have ovel thrown ; And I, in Zanger's ruine, feel my own. - My patience has not ſtrength for this aſſult. 2ueen. Oh do not make my miſery my fault, You now confirm all my Prophetick fears; I did employ my Reaſon, Pray'rs, and Tears, To make the Prince his Fatal Hove decline; I knew you would reſent his fault as mine: But I, alas ! found my diſſwaſions vain. Rox. Why did you not betimes to me complain : ..Queen. Who to a Mother could accuſe a on, Orlead you to that grief which you would ſhun: When l perceiv'd his Love was fixt ſo ſure That 'twos above my Tears and Reaſons cure, I did reſolve in a diſguiſe to flie Where I unknown might in a Cloiſter die. And, leſt you might ſuſpect what I deſign'd. r This Letter I did mean to leave behind. | Give; her 4 Letter. Which begs your pardon, and informs you too My flight was but in thankfulneſs to you. Nor can I doubt your mercy to my Son, When I, to keep your Love, from Zanger's ſun, Rox.
Page 93

(93) [Roxolanareads the Letter to herſelf. Rox. In taxing you, who now ſo juſt appear, I am more guilty then I thought you were. Nor can you your revenge more cruel make Then when you ſhew the guilt of my miſtake, 2ueen. Of what is paſt you ſhew too great a ſenſe; Thereparation does exceedth' offence. Agenyou'lwound me if you treat meſo; I only meant my innocence to ſhow; You, ſeeing that, make me obtain my end. Rox. You muſt my pardon ſeal, and be my Friend. [Kiſſes her. And that I may deſerve what I requeſt I'le lodge my greateſt ſecret in your breaſt. I know you will be ever kind and juſt. [Kiſſes her agen. 2seen. No obligation binds ſo much as truſt. Rox.The Friendſhip plac'd by my unhappy Son On Muſtapha, is not to you unknown. 2geen.To that high Friendſhip Inoſtranger am: A nobler never yet was told by Fame. Rox. Ah Queen from that dire friendſhip Ireceive The deepeſt wound which Fate did ever give. You know the bloody cuſtom of this Crown; Nought but the Sultan's life ſecures my Son. For when the Eldeſt does the Throne enjoy, He muſt the Younger by our Laws deſtroy. 2ueen. That cuſtom he by friendſhip will reclaim. Rox. Friendſhip, to Love and Pow'r, ſeems but a name. Though Muſtapha has Virtue and Renown Fit to poſſeſs and dignifie a Crown: (For never }. did any Sultan's Son Perform and promiſe more than he has done) Yet when he ſhall th’ Imperial Scepterbear He muſt become my Zanger's Murderer. For that is made a righteous Law by time, Which Law at firſt did judge the higheſt Crime. 2ueen. Pow'rs private ſafety is the publick good; It lives in health by letting others blood. Rox. The Sultan's love gives me a pow'r ſo high That I to this could give aremedy If Zanger did not ſecret Friendſhip ; Even with Religious Rites, to Muftapha. All my deſigns fond Zanger does oppoſe, Who ſaving Muſtapha himſelf will loſe, ..Queen. Your Fate againſt your Vertue does conſpire. Rox. Alas I muſt deſtroy what I admire. In this attempt I ſhall your aid implore: And, ſince your beauty they do both adore, You
Page 94

(94) You muſt love Muſtapha, and ſlight my Son; Deſpair may dowhat reaſon ſhould have done: For Friendſhip never yet could climb above The high reſentments of neglected love. 2ueen. Madam, the weight you on my boſom lay I cannot bear, nor your commands obey. Prince Muſtapha my love can never have 5. My King and Love are bury'd in one Grave. Rox. If Muſtapha cannot your love obtain, It may ſuffice when you affection feign. ..Queen. But Honour, Madam, quickly will fo: ge: And loſe it ſelf whilſt it does counterfeit; As men a little us’d to ſpeak untrue The juſt remembrance loſe of what they knew. Till their firſt ſhapes grow to themſelves unknown. Rox. Can this be ſaid by you who wear a Crown When from your heart your looks do diff'rent ſhow, Love does but change the weather of your Brow; Which ſhould no more a conſtant meaning bear Then th’ outward face of Heav'n ſhould ſtill be clear. The Great ſhould in their Thrones myſterious be; Diſſembling is no worſe then myſtery. Obſcurity is that which terrour moves; The gods moſt awful ſeem'd in ſhady Groves. And our wiſe Prophet's Text a rev'ience bears Where it is hard and needs Interpreters. ..Queen. I ever was without diſſembling bred, And in my open Brow my thoughts were read: None but the guilty keep themſelves unkown. Rox. No wonder we ſo ſoon ſubdu'd your Throne; When wiſe Diſſimulation, which ſhould guard Chief Pow'r and make th' approaches to it hard, Was baniſh'd from your Court to Rebell-ſtates, To Conclaves, Councills, and ſmall Magiſtrates : Theſe ſtronger grow then Monarchs who refuſe The cloſe falſe-Armour which their Subjects uſe. ..Queen. Madam, you teach what Chriſtians 4:e not taught, And ſeem to ſoar as high in flights of thought As now your Empire wide incompaſs ſwells. Rox. Sure Chriſtian Kings live not in Courts but Cº.'s That is un-countly-ill-bred innocence Which cannot with diſſembled love diſpence, You muſt diſſemble love to Muff pha, And make him think by what you often fly, That you for Love can mournand languiſh too, .Queen. Madam, I ſhall need counſel what to do. Rox. How, Madam : you may counſel take of me, But ſhould from Subječts counſel ſtill be free. -
Page 95

(95) We, but in asking it from Subjećts, give Much more of value then we can receive. We give our ſecrets to them, which, when known, May make their int’reſt greater then our own. By counſel men perſwade or elſe direct; Direction like appointment we ſuſpect: Andeven perſwaſion does the Throne invade; For ſlaves may govern whom they can perſwade. Adviſe your ſelf and boldly then proceed; Counſel muſt yield to courage and to ſpeed. 2seen. When I ſhall counſelask, I'le none reveal; I can adviſe myſelf what to conceal. Rox. I'le preſs you now no farther, but retire. Madam, improve what Honour ſhall inſpire If that which I requeſt may not be done Youruineme, and Zanger, and your Son. But,e're I go, aſſure me of your ſtay. 2ueen. In this, becauſe I can, I will obey. ſ F2: Roxolaña. No Fortune aims at more than ſhe can do: She takes my Crown then tempts my Vertue too. I am for Muſtapha's true love indebt, Which I will never pay with counterfeit. Enter Cardinal. Card. Madam, laſt night I did adviſe your ſtay, But now I come to haſten you away. Time has been ačtive ſince Iſaw you laſt. 2ueen. Shall I truſt Councils which can change ſofaſ, card. By various wayes wenay our end purſue. Councils ſhould alter as their cauſes do. Phyſicians, Madam, will not thinkit ſtrange If I change Med'cines when Diſeaſes change. The Pilot, of moſt firm and conſtant mind, Muſt ſhift his courſe and turn with ev'ry wind. Enter Thuracus, Viche. Thur. The Sultan's Troops, more ſwift then in Akins, Are, without orders, running to their Arms. º Miche. Raftan does now in ſev'ral ſhapes appear; For he is often alter'd by his fear. card. The Army is ſo bent to Mutiny That Muſtapha does counſel you to flye. Madam, we all are to your flight inclin'd. Queen. But, to this place, my Lord, Iain confin'd; And by a tye which has ſuch influence That I will rather dye then flyefrom hence. - A Mutinous noiſe is heard card. Their anger is grown loud! Madam, 'tis fir That you ſend out to know the cauſe of it: 2stem,
Page 96

(96) 2ueen. Make haſte my Lords, and ſev'rally inquire If thoſe who rais'd this ſtorm can raiſe it higher; And when you have the danger of it learn'd Obſerve how far the Princes are concern'd. [Exeunt Thuricus, Viche, Enter Cleora at another door, and whiſpers the Queen. cleor. Zarma has haſtily a whiſper brought Which ſays, that means for your eſcape is wrought. This Tempeſt Muſtapha would have you ſhun; And ſhe will help to ſend away your Son. Queen. O how am Iperplext: ſecure him Heav'n' [Aſide, I have my Faith to Roxolana given Tº aſſure her of my ſtay, by which mySon May in my Fortunes equal hazard run. [Whiſpers Cleora. Goſtrait to Roxolana's Tent, and there Obſerve what change does in her looks appear. [Exit Cleora. card. Madam, you ſaid you would not flye from hence: 'Tis a reſolve of fatal conſequence. ueen. The cauſe of that reſolve Imuſt conceal; But will a ſecret of more uſe reveal, The Prince has by his Preſents Zarma won, Who will contrive to ſend away my Son. This is a bus'neſs worthy your debate. card. Unhappy is the Miniſter of State Whom for ſucceſsleſs counſelyou deſpiſe Yet that conceal by which he ſhould adviſe. His fate and not his skill you ought to blame Who plays the Cards yet muſt not ſee the Game. If I but hold the Cards which you will play, I throw your judgment not my own away. .Queen. But this which needs your counſel open lies, Card. To what you have reveal’d I thus adviſe. Your Son, to Buda flying, will redeem By his ownloſs thoſe who abandon'd him. You truſt the Conquer'd who were falſe before And by diſtruſt provoke the Cônquerour. How can your Son by flight advantag’d be Who quits the Port to meet a ſtorm at Sea? And doubtleſs, Madam, you by ſtaying here The whole revenge of his eſcape muſt bear. Theſe are the dangers which attend his flight; But he is ſafe in Roxolana's ſight. For, till her growing pow'r you can ſuſpect, Doubt not his ſafety whom ſhe does protect. Queen. Your reaſons urging his continuance here, Like Rays of light, are ſudden, ſtrong, and clear. My Lord, as theſe convince me for his ſtay So let my counſel haſtenyou away. The
Page 97

(97) The Mutinous, who now in tumult riſe, Hate our Religion, and your Robedeſpiſe. This ſtorm you may in Buda ſafely ſee. card. Madam, it will no more my wonder be That you, not truſting me, diſguis'd appear Sinceyou ſuſpect I am ſo faint with fear As to forſake my Queen in her diſtreſs. But, Madam, walk in Clouds and truſt me leſs: Though but in partyour mind you will declare Yet in your whole misfortunes I will ſhare: And though my counſels may defeótive ſeem Ileby my ſuffrings merityour eſteem. [ Fººt 2ueen. Our greateſt Councºlours think we are unjuſt - VWhen our leaſt thoughts are hidden from their truſt; And till (by knowing th' utmoſt that we know) Thoſe reſtleſs Councºlours may our Rulers grow, They do not love us, and they ſullenſeem; But after care not though we love not them. [ Exit Enter Solyman, Ruſtan, ºu. Shouts are heard from within. soly. What Shouts are theſe ? Ruft. Shouts which your Souldiers pay, Hearing Prince Muſtapha has leave to ſtay. Pyrrh. About his Tents the joyful Soldiers crowd. soly. There was no need their joy ſhould be ſo loud. Their ſhouts of Triumph never roſeſohigh. Raft. It ſhews they love him more than Vićtory. And when theſe ſhouts they in your preſence make It is a ſign they love him for your ſake. soly. How long can they the Father love,who run VWith ſuch aguilty kindneſs to the Son: 'Tis much to do it, more to ſhow it ſo, Pyrrh.. Men never fear to pay the debts they owe. soly. He takes that love which does belong to me, And lets mereign but by his courteſie: His early acquiſition ſhews his skill In ruling, and his pow'r declares his will. Ruſt. Suſpicion's good unleſs it ſtart too ſoon And then does faſter then th'offender tun. If he purſues, too early and too faſt, Your Armies love, he errs but in his haſte. Your jealouſie and his deſire to gain That love from which he ſhould a while abſtain, Maybe excus'd; for neither is a crime But as you both may erre in point of time. - GS c Pyrrh.
Page 98

(98) Pyrrh. Why ſhould your Armies kindneſs be his fault: Saly. They love or hate but ſo as they are taught. By fear uſurpers ſhould their pow'r ſuſtain; But a true Prince chiefly by love ſhould reign. Whilſt, in looſe knots, fear but the body binds, We ſtrongly rule by love our Subjećts minds. Ruſt. Yet wiſeſt Monarchs by ſucceſs have prov'd That it is ſafe to be fear'd than lov’d. For Subjećts, as they pleaſe, their love diſpenſe, But alwayes fear as it does pleaſe the Prince. A King ſhould more the ruling pow'reſteem Plac'd in himſelf then when 'tis lodg'd in them. Soy. That errour is deſtructive to a ſtate: For whomſoe're the people fear they hate. This is in me and in my Subjećts true: For fearing Muſtapha I hate him too. And he, even in my Camp, my pow'r controuls; I ruling but their Bodies, he their Souls. Pyrrh. By his firſt deeds heſeem'd to ſtudy you: And of your ſtory a fair Copy drew. Can he deface the Virtue he has ſhown And on his fathers Ruine build his Throne: Soly. Since on Ambition's wings he means to riſe He willboth hate and ſlight all Natures Ties, A Fathers name cannot his Nature fright From Glory when it does his youth invite. Th’inchanting ſound of Pow'r ſo Charms his Ear, That he will now no other Muſick hear. Newſhouts are heard, at which Solyman ſtarts. This inſolence is loud enough to wake Revenge from duller º then death can make. Ruſt. Perhaps not underſtanding their offence, They deem this duty which is inſolence. And think they not offend in what they do. Soly. My Army then is bravely taught by you, Canany ignorant of Treaſon be Who ſhout for ought but vićtory and me? Ruſt. Yet do not, Sir, decline what I adviſe. Repentance is a noble Sacrifice. But if, when taught, their crime they ſhould purſue, 'Twill juſtifie what you intend to do. Pyrrh. When but a few into offences run, Juſtice may ſafely puniſh what is done. But when whole Camps are kindled to a flame, Pe:ſwaſ on then, not force, muſt them reclaim. Ruffam. Revenge, which to the injur'd does belong, Can be ſucceſsful only to the ſtrong. Yout
Page 99

(99) Your Foes you ſummone're their Towns you ſtorm: If toyour Army now you leſs perform They all in Arms for Muſtapha will riſe Becauſe you uſe them worſe then Enemies. Soly. I yield to your advice, goboth, and try - To make them in their joys more mannerly. Exeunt Ruſtan, My race of Glory did proceed too faſt. Pyrrhus, My Armies now grow weary of my haſte. And yet, though tir'd, they ſhout and gladly run To ſee me over-taken by my Son: All in this Race are ſtopt when overtook 3 And I, whom all did follow, amforſook: Forſook by him whom I begot and bred: I'm left behind by thoſe whom I haveled. Muſt I, like Conquiring Fleets,whenſtorms begin, Take all my glorious Flags and Streamers in: Though Muſtapha by Heavens decree was ſent Towarn great Monarchs by my puniſhment Yet he does Heav'n offend, offending me. What means our Prophet by this miſtery: My Son's ordain'd to what he ſhould not do And Ito bear what I ſhould puniſh too. [Exit. Enter Muſtapha, Zanger. Muſtapha ſeems very penſive. Zang. Ah Prince! you wrong your love whilſt you admit Another Paſſion thus to reign with it. Muff, Zanger, my grief maywell my heart ſubdue Since’tis too great to be reveal'd to you. Pity that Fate with which I now contend; It makes me hide my dange from my Friend. Zang. What canyou ſeem unwilling to declare, After confeſſing you my Rival are: Or of that Friendſhip are younot ſecure Which did, unſhaken, ſuch a proof endure : Muſt. Let what Iheard be ſilenc'd as untrue, Since my believing it may troubleyou: And yet my ſpeaking it may pardon'd be Since your not hearing it may ruine me. Zang. What can Imore an injury eſteem Then when by ſilence you diſtruſtful ſeem : Muſt. Alas! you know not that you are unjuſt VWhen thus you take my kindneſs for diſtruſt. Beloth to hear what I ſhall ſpeak with pain. Zang. I torment feelin that which youretain. Muff. Your Mother with the Wizier is agreed: And ſhe hath ſecretly my death decreed. Zang.
Page 100

( i oo) zang. Youwong me, Brother, and yout ſelf deceive: And I wrong nature when I this believe, . Muff. I’le rather periſh by your miſ-belief Then give you evidence t'íncieaſe your grief. Farewe!! the duty of a Son retain. You'l hear your Brother, and your Friend is ſlain. Zang. Twere cruel, Sir, to leave mewith this wound. - Muff. You are toogood to ſee what I have found. [Going out. Zang. Stay, Sir, I cannot nature much offend, Doubting a Mother to preſerve a Friend. Our Friendſhip does the minds allyance ſhow. Let me the utmoſt of this ſecret know. Muff. It comes from one who does not prudence lack, Nor his intelligence from Rumour take; One to whom Zarma does with truſt diſcloſe (Chaim'd by his love) all that herboſom knows. This bloody miſchief is with art deſign'd, The ſecret, cautiouſly, to few confind; Which by ſuch cloſe contraćtion is made ſtrong, And ſtill you Mother abler to do wrong. Zang. Perhaps ſhe is thus cruel ſince I grow As cruelin believing ſhe is ſo. Yet then ſhe with her ſelf does diſagree, Knowing I die in you and ſhe in me. Atuff. This Junto could not ſo ſucceſsful be Were not the Sultan wrought to jealouſie That I, affecting popular eſteem, Follow thoſe Crouds which have ſorſaken him ; And that I aim'd not, by my Battels won, To conquer Perſia but uſurp his Throne. Theſe falſe ſuggeſtions I might ſoon remove Were Iadmitted to implore his Love; But oh that rigid form which us bereaves Of all approach without our Father's leaves | That rigid cuſtom which does bring no leſs Then death when we, unſent for, ſeek acceſs But, Zanger, if I could admittance gain, I muſt not where your Mother rules complain. Zang. If they have rais'd the Sultan's wrath ſo high, You muſt, to ſave your life, vouchſafe to flie. Your ſtay makes life depend upon his breath ; Your flight prevents his guſt and your own death. Whom he ſuſpects he does but ſeldom ſave; A Princes Priſon is a Princes Grave. Muff. Twere better, Zangºr, that my blood were ſpilt Then ſav'd by Flight; Flight is itſelf a guilt Since ſtill my duty did my actions ſteer I'le not diſgrace my innocence by fear, Leaſt
Page 101

(1 or ) Leſt I the ſaving of my life repent. l'le rather bear then merit puniſhment. zang. When Pris'ner made 'twill be a new offence Tº accuſe his wrath by pleading innocence. Your death he'l then decree tº avoid complaint; Pow'r oft by death does juſtifiereſtraint: And, when incens'd, into two faults will run Rather then own that it has aéted one. We ſhall by your retreat gain time to learn Thoſe dangers which our haſte cannot diſcern. You then may make that innocence appear Which yet his paſſion will not let him hear. Muff. The ſooner yield my perſon to his pow: Then be held guilty by him but one hour. By flight my fear and ſhame will equal be: And fear or ſhame is worſe then death to me. zang. I doubt your vertue will your life betrays But ſince ſo nobly you reſolve to ſtay, I'letomy Mother ſtrait, and ſhe ſhall know Th’ important ſecret of our mutual vow. It will divert the hope of her deſign, When ſhe's aſſur'd yout ruine muſt be mine. Muff. Friendſhip like this whoever did enjoy, Which Rival’d-love nor death cannot deſtroyº Oh Zanger! If you knew how much I ſtrove To make my Friendſhip overcome my Love (Though in that ſtrife I could not Vićtor be) You would both envy then and pity me. Zang. I'm glad in that deſign you miſt your end , Who quits his Miſtreſs may forſake his Friend. Andnone of Friendſhip ſhould a proof admit Which may occaſion fear of loſing it. For he who can break off your Conqu'rours chain Has ſuch wild ſtrength as nothing can reſtrain. Muſt. Hah! ſtay! methinks I'm on a ſudden brought Tolight's laſt glimps, and to a ſtop of thought! Methinks, ſomething prophetick in my Breaſt Bids me make haſte and in Fame's Templereſt. And as men dying leave chief Legacies To thoſe whoſe Friendſhip they did deareſt prize, So, Zanger, I, as to your merit due, Bequeath the Queen, my life's laſt gift, to you. Zang. Ourſecret Sympathy your Fate ſecures: If bad, my Breaſt would feel't asſoon as yours, And ſince you but bequeath a Legacy, Which cannot be poſſeſt before you dye, You ſafely give what I ſhall ne're receive Becauſe I cannot Muſtapha out-live. Mºſº,
Page 102

( 102 ) Muff. How poorly ſome in Friendſhip take a pride - Which nºver yet was by Love's int’reſt try’d: To ours alone the perfeót praiſe is due - At once of being Friends and Rivals too. [Exeunt Fmbracing, Enter Ruſtan, Pirrhus. Pirrh. Complyance now muſt ſerve us more then force Since th' European and the Aſian Horſe Refuſe our orders and in publick ſay Th t we conſpir'd to baniſh Muſtapha. Ruſt. No prideſo dang'rous is as being proud Of pioſp’rous Mutiny. They threaten loud Who usd but in their whiſpels to complain. Pirrh. If they the £anizaries Aga gain We are, beyond repairs of Coult, undone. ſuff. The force we dare not meet we ought to ſhun. Pirrh. The Empreſs feels remoiſe, or finds her fear. Ruſt. We ſhall be call'd, Zarma expects us here. § Enter Ach- Achmat, the Aſian Horſe have long been led lmat, Haly. By you, and by your great example bred. This Monſter-mutiny will all devour. You might oblidge the Sultan with your pow'r If you could quell this Monſter. Ach. May be ſo. But you had better trye what you can do. Ruff. The deed is noble and belongs to you : I would not take what is to Achmat due. Ach. Indeed you ever, with a tender hand, Touch'd what another Baſſa ſhould command. - Your Juſtice (which knows when, and whom to ſtrike) uſurps no buſineſs which you do not like. Pirrh. Haly, this doubtful language ſtrange appears. Haly. You'l in the Army find Interpreters. Ruſt. Haly it ſeems does liſten to the Crowd. Haly. Men need not liſten where Complaints are loud. Pirrh. The people rail to exerciſe their Tonguês. Haly. Their patience firſt is exercis'd with wrongs. Pirrh. They, wanting judgment, ſhould ſubmit to Laws, And cannot Judges be in their own cauſe, ºut to their Rulers gently ſhould appeal. Ach. Men their own judges are of what they feel. Ruſt. This is not meant in Friendſhip nor for ſport. Sure, Pirrhus, they are angry with the Court, And having found, none for their anger care, Strive out of malice to be popular. F ºf ºr

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 103

(1c3) .*.* Enter Zarma who whiſpers Ruſtan. Zarma. You muſt bring Pyrrhus, and may have acceſs. Exeunt with Zarma. Ruſtan and Pirrhus, ſmiling ſcorn- fully on the other two, and they on them, Achm. Methinks we were ill-natur'd to expreſs Somuch contempt of Greatneſs in diſtreſs. Haly. When ſhining Fav'rites grow with greatneſs proud All men rejoyce to ſee them in a Cloud. If this ill nature be, ’tis not confin'd Tous alone, but is in all mankind. - And whilſt weblame our ſelves we injureali: Nothing's ill natur'd that is natural. Achm. I muſt confeſs, in thus inſulting, you Dobut as States-men to each other do. Haly. When they are more afflićted we will ſeem To mourn with their few Friends who pity then: ; But ſecretly we will their Foes inſence And then, in haſte, bring them intelligence Of miſchiefs which they never can avoid; And ſo be thankt by thoſewe have deſtroy'd, {Extant, Enter Roxolana, Buſtan, Pytilus, Rox. My favour to the Sultan you implore Only for Governments you ſought before. Youſue for Egypt, you for Babylon; If I could theſe procure you would be gone. Ruſt. In theſe from ſudden Foes we diſtant are; No Mutiny can laſt to march ſo far: And we, by abſence, may perhaps abate The rage contračted by this Armies hate. Pirrh. This Armies temper, well conſider'd, ſhows You are not ſafe when we our ſafety loſe. But 'twill in vain with your deſigns conteſt When in our hands you ſhall poſſeſs the Eaſt. Rox. Men who to high deſigns, like this, are bºat Should leſs fear death then not to ſee th' event. Reft. The Camp to Muſtapha ſuch love has ſhown That weſhall haſten by his death our own. Pirrh. That which does lead your hope the ſureſt way Brings us to certain ruine if we ſtay. Rox. You vow'd (ſtriving my favour to regain) That Zanger after Solyman ſhould reign. And, that I might no mark of horrour bear, You ſaid, I ſtill againſt it ſhould appear. Pirrh. But, Madam, neither of us promis'd we The Princes Executioners would be. Aft
Page 104

(IO4) All but the Mutes will that black office ſhun; And all things elſe are near perfeótion done. Rox. None here the fatal Orders will obey, If in this juncture you ſhould flye away. You both muſt ſtay, and what you plotted, ačt : I'le not the guilt of your deſigns contraćt. Ruſt. In ſtaying we the Princes fate partake; We who are guilty only for your ſake. So guilty none did ever yet appear. Rox. You only guilty are becauſe you fea; But fear in States-men is the higheſt crime. Thoſe who to Empires upper ſtations climbe Are not ſouſeful by their being wiſe As they may hurtful be by cowardiſe. For they, fearing to act what they ſhould do, Make with themſelves the valiant uſeleſs too. Ruff. Provoke not thoſe who with your ruine may Save both themſelves and injur'd Muſtapha. Pirrh. This, were we Cowards, we could quickly do. Rox. Am I forſken,and then threatn'd too e You doing this will your beſt viſage wear. Falſhood in States-men is leſs vile then feat. Go to the Sultan, go and th’ int’reſt tiy Of crafty Art: On Nature I'le rely. You are whole States-men and his Triends in pa, t . States-men, like States, are but the works of Alt. When in both ſhapes your wiſdoms have appeard, Weak Wives and Miſtreſſes may chance be heard. You with your blood muſt for your miſchiefs pay 5 Put a few tears will waſh my guilt away. What you deſign'd, Ambition made you do; I did but that which Nature cali'd me to. You did the Plot contrive to kill his Son; At which I but conniv'd to ſave my own. Go then, and by your deaths the diffrence pove Twixt thoſe whom Kings but truſt, and whom they love, Ruſt. Our Treaſon againſt you would be a fault Greater then ever enter d in our thought. Pardon our Paſſion ſince you did deny The ſute we made with ſhapeſt injury. Pirrh. Too much your loyal ſervants you deſpiſe When you their care impute to Cowardiſe. Rox. Care does unworthy of it ſelf appea: When it the ugly vizard wears of Fear. lf, as you ſaid, the deed is almoſt done, Stay but one day to end what you begun. The Souldiers fury, which you would decline, If well improv'd will perfect your deſign. Their
Page 105

( I c.3) Their love to Muſtapha is turn'd to rage; Which nothing but his blood can now aſſwage. Go then and make my Son the Empires Heir : Leave your preferments to my ſudden care. Ruff. We in your cauſe all dangers will deſpiſe. Pyrrh. And with your fortune quickly fallor riſe. Ruſt. We will the Sultan inſtantly attend: The Princes ling'ting Fate in death ſhallend. [Extunt Ruſtan, Pyrrhus. Enter Zarma. Zarma. Madam, Prince 2anger, much impatient, ſays Within, and humbly for admittance prays. Rox. I gueſs the bus'neſs which has brought him here: His fatal Friendſhip gives me grief and fear: Finding the Sultan does his Brother hate He would employ me as his Advocate. Say I am cloſe at my Devotion, go! Say I'm retit'd ; make haſte and tell him ſo. Admit him not though much he will pretend. zarms. He is too much a Brother and a Friend. [Aſia. - [Exit Zarma, Rex. Whatſin of mine, oh Heaven incenſes thee: Thou mak’ſ mySon his own worſt Enemy. What by my care and Art he mightenjoy He does himſelf contribute to deſtroy. And I, in my perplext condition, muſt Become unnatural, or elſe unjuſt: Muſt leave a Son to Empires cruelty, Or to agen'rous Prince inhumanebe. My Husband, whom I Love, I cruel make, Even againſt Nature, yet for Natures ſake. His Son, by my contrivance, he muſt kill; Whilſt I preſerve my own againſt his will. The blood Iſave muſt anſwer for my guilt And waſh away the ſtains of what is ſpilt. E e T H E

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 106

(106) T H E FIFTH A C T. Enter Solyman, Roxolana, Pyrrhus, Ruſtan, soly. I Will not ſtay to ſee him in my Throne: I I yet can reach him and will take him down, Ruſtan has now my orders: he ſhall die. Rox. Exceſs of Juſtice turns to cruelty. soly. Whilſt but ſuſpition did my breaſt invade Your mediation could my wrath diſſwade; But now his Treaſon is ſo certain grown That I muſt take his life, or loſe my own. The name of Muſtapha infects your breath. Thoſe who deſire his life, deſign my death. Rox. Then, Sir, my interceſſion is unfit. Yet pardon me if I with grief ſubmit : For it does too much cauſe of grief afford, When Juſtice againſt Nature draws her Sword. Soly. His death is but deferr'd, becauſe I ſtay To ſend him to his Grave the ſafeſt way. Ruſt. Since you by Achmat did the Prince adviſe That if he either loyal were or wiſe He fom the Camp ſhould ſecretly retire, And by his abſence quench his raging fire. It were convenient to you Achmat ſent With kindneſs to invite him to your Tent; Pretending 'tis your will he ſhould receive Your counſel e're he does the Army leave. Fut, Sir, ſince for your ſufety he muſt die It ſhould be done with ſpeed and ſecreſie. Pyrrh. Elſe they may reſcue him by open force, His Train and Guards are Thirty Thouſand Horſe : And he ſo much your Souldiers rules that they Will ſcarce, but in your preſence, you obey. Soly. Already his dark evening is begun: I le ſhall be ſure to ſet before the Sun; And never more ſhill riſe to be ador'd, But part in an Eclipſe and be abhorr'd. Sºnd Achmat hither to avoid delay. [Exeunt Ruſtan, Pyrrhus. Fox. Fate riſes in your Brow ! I dare not ſtay To hear the bloody ſentence you muſt gives Horrour and pity in my boſome ſtrive, Remembring what to Muſtapha is due, And not to puniſh him would ruine you, Exit. Sa'y.
Page 107

(1 oz) Soly. We our compaſſion rather ſhould extend To ſtrangers than to Sons when they offend: With wrongsfrom ſtrangers we may well diſpence Who nothing have receiv'd to recompence: Theyonely are by common juſtice bound: None are ingrate who have no favour found. But Muſtapha (unthankful for that care Which bred him to deſerve the Wreaths of War; Whom all the Bonds of Nature could not tie) Shall now, for Natures ſake, unpity'd die. L Exit, Enter Muſtapha, Zanger. Muſt. This counſel Achmat from the Saltan brought, Whoſe favour I have now by Achmat ſought; Begging I may attend him e're I go, And fully my ſuppos'd offences know. If to this juſt requeſt he does conſent, I may avoid my fatal Baniſhment, And be deliver'd from a double grief Whilſt Ito Love and Friendſhip give relief. Zang. I fear in yourrequeſt by Achmat made You have but ſought the means to be betray'd. And ſince againſt your ſelfyounow conſpire Who will oppoſe that Fate which you deſire? My Mother, indenying me acceſs, Does raſhly your determin'd death confeſs. Muſt. Since only guilty minds have cauſe offert It does tome more probably appear That even my Foes are likeli'er to abhor Their miſchiefs paſt then to conſult of more. Enter Achmat. Achm. The joys of conqueſt ever fill your breaſt, The Mighty Sultan yields to your requeſt; Believes your love is in your meſſage ſent;. He truſts that love, and thinks you innocent. His Cloud is vaniſh'dand his Brow ſo clear That you may plainly read a Father there: Sir, he does ſtraight expect you in his Tent: Improve his kindneſs whilſt he does relent. Muff. How like you now the way l did purſue : [To Zanger Zang. Ithink the change too ſudden to be true. Muſt. If falſe, I then am but of life bereav'd: 'Tis worth my dying to be undeceiv'd. And who would with a Father be in ſtrife: Rather then duty loſe I'le loſe my life. Zanger, farewel ! I leave, in leaving you, The beſt of Friends and beſt of Brothers too. Yet
Page 108

( 108) Yet I ſhall take ſome glory in my death Counting the worth of what Ican bequeath. And, to confirm my Legacy, I now Freely releaſe the rigour of your vow. For ifin th' upper world we ought can know Of things which thoſe we love tranſaćt below, I ſhall rejoyce when I am thither gone, That you poſſeſs my Miſtriſs and my Throne. zang. Can you ſuch gifts to one ſo worthleſs give As after you will be content to live: Ah Prince . If this diſcourſe you ſhould purſue, Sorrow to me would kinder prove then you. Muff. If in my Fate, Dear Zanger, you ſhould ſhare, Who of the Queens conce.ns will take a care: Think it her ſute, not mine, which you deny. zang. When you are dead, Honour will make me die. Muff. I ſhall be ſtrong enough formy defence, Where nature pleads the cauſe of innocence. zang. Methinksboth theſe ſhould all things overcome ; Yet Hope finds in my breaſt but littleroom. Muff. I muſt not your Prophetickſorrows hear: 'Tis only Friendſhip which createsyour fear. [Extunt. Enter the Queen, Zarma. Zarma. One whom I lov'd enjoyn'd me to obey, With faithful ſervice, you and Maſtapha, And, Madam, I attend you now you are Alone that all I know I may declare. .94een. I'le not ungrateful be for what you do: Ile ſerve you in rewards and Friendſhip too. Zarma. I ſtill have fear'd that Roxolana's love To Zanger would his Brothers ruine prove; But many proofs do now my thoughts convince That ſhe deſigns to ſave and ſerve the Prince : For that effect ſhe's to the Sultan gone; But firſt commanded me to tell her Son That he this evening in her Tent ſhould ſtay To ſpeak with her concerning Muſtapha. The tumult in the Campbegins to ceaſe, And all put on the chearful looks of Peace. Queen. You tell mewhat I moſt deſir'd to hear: Which ſoon will free me from my grief and fear. Zarma. Since all things move to meet with your deſire Your Son has no occaſion to retire. .9aeen. By your advice I may ſucceſsful grow. Zarma. Still what Ihear you inſtantly ſhall know. [Exit Zarma, A. ºffer
Page 109

(109) EnterCardinal, Thuracus, Viche, Cleora, 2geºn. My Lords, by Zarma (who is newlygone) I hear the Sultan ſmiles upon his Son: The Empreſs nobly has procur'd his peace: The Chiefs of factions from their tumults ceaſe, And now for favour to her Tent reſort. Card. I doubt all this is but a turn of Court. Think not the Empreſs will her pow'r employ Tº eſtabliſh him who muſt her Sondeſtroy. .9seen. Honour has inherSoul the higheſt place. Card. Nature has greater pow'r then Honour has, But, Madam, whilſt this ſeeming calm does laſt You, with the Infant, ſhould to Buda haſte; Which, now diſloyal grown, will ſcarce withſtand The worſt of all your Foes, King Ferdinand. For whilſt the Turk invadesus from the Eaſt, Th'un-chriſtian King aſſaults usin the Weſt. With craft and wealth he has advan'd his pow'r, Thur. Madam, wenow came from the Governour; Who bad us tellyouthat he has ſurpriz'd Three of King Ferd'nand's Officers diſguis’d. Wiche. With theſe there have beenblank Commiſſions found: Some of their faction we in Fetters bound. 2seen. Before this danger does reſiſtleſs grow You muſt, with both theſe Lords, to Buda 90. Card. Your preſence, Madam, will be needful there. 2seen. My promiſe will a while detain me here. Card. You'ſ then be left afflićted and alone. 24een. You leave me for my ſafety not your own. Whilſt I the rage of fortune here withſtand We may be ruin'd there by Ferdinand. Imuſt not be deny'd. Your being there Will free me from a moſt important care. Card, Madam, my ſtrict obedience makes me 90. All that does happen you ſhall hourly know. [***Sueen and Cleora one way, the Cardinal and Lords at the other door. Enter Muſtaphº. The Guards and others, paſsingly him ſhake their head, with ſorrowful # gby him, Muff, All ſhake their penſive heads in paſſing by As if they did diſlike my deſtiny. Let him diſpatch whom he intends to kill: 'Tis leſs to ſuffer death then fear it ſtill. Nor is the worſt of deaths ſo bad a Fate As ſtill to live under a Fathers hate. F f My
Page 110

( 1 Io) My torments are ſo many and ſo high That only death can be my remedy. Death will my Fathers jealouſie remove And free me ever from neglected love; Whilſt to my greateſt guilt it puts an end Of being Rival to ſobrave a Friend. But even that comfort brings me ſorrow too; Fordeath will then more then my Friendſhip do. And if his kindneſs makes him keep his vow He, dying, will the greater Friendſhip ſhow. He'l freely, for my ſake, quitt life and love; But cruel force does me from both remove. In death his friendſhip will ſo clearly ſhine That when Idye, he'l ſee the faults of mine: For I, by Rivalſhip, was faulty grown And death reſignswhat friendſhip ſhould have done. *nter ſix Matts, one of them advances before the reſt and kneel, down, delivers Muſtapha a black Box with a Parchment, the Sultan. Great Seal hanging ºf it in a black, Ribond. Then he hold, up 4. Bow-ſtring and makes ſigns that he ſhould kneel and ſubmit the Sultan's ſentence. Jubmit to Theſe are to addenew wings to my laſt hour. I underſtand your ſigns and ſee your power. Stand off. I with your bus'neſs can diſpence, But your officious haſt is an offence. I will conſider what Iought to do, And dye to ſatisfie myſelf, not you. They retire to the fur- Can Imy duty ſhow when Idoill, {{... end ºf the Sfaze. unjuſtly yielding to a Fathers will? - Sure we, by Natures gift, the right enjoy oſtrive with thoſe who would our lives deſtroy. And when Itamely dye, without defence, I teach the world to doubt my innocence. But with my Father why ſhould I debate 2 My death he wiſhes and my life I hate. Why ſhould I make his anger higher riſe By ſtriving to preſerve what I deſpiſe : [ He beckens to the Mutes to come near him, and they advance. Before I dye I'le to the Sultan ſhow My injur'd innocence, that he may know My death will to the judging world proclaim He is more guilty then he thinks Iam. When I have told him what I ought to ſay, Then what he does command I will obey.---- [They all ſhake their head; inſign of denyal. Hoºv
Page 111

(111) How, Slaves 1 am Irefus'd: I will not dye Till I have firſt obtain'd what you deny. [The Mutes draw their scemitars and aſſault him; he draws too and Kills two of them, Enter Solyman. saly. O Traytor! art thou ſuch an Enemy To thy high Blood, which is deriv'd from me, That now, enforc’d by this new crime, I muſt With my own hand mix it with commonduſt? Againſt my pow'r thoudying art at ſtrife, Tomake thy death as guilty as thy life. At the firſt hearing of Solyman's voice the Mutes give over fighting, and 4? ſ end of Solyman's ſpeech, Muſtapha, kneeling, lays % .. at the Sultan's feet. Maſt. The cauſe of my defence from their aſſault Was that from you I might have learnt my fault. Alas, what iſt I with that life ſhould do Which, Sir, is hated and proſcrib'd by you ? All I endeavour’d by my life's defence Was to gain time to ſhew my innocence. Iſhun not dying, Sir, but to be held Guilty, is dying after I am kill'd, Loſing the life of Fame when I am dead, Soly. A mancondemn'd is not allow'd to plead. I’le hear no more, [Muſtapha riſes, Muſt. Then, Sir, to death I'lego. I am too guilty ſince you think meſo. May not my ſervants do what muſt be done? Let not your meaneſt Slaves deſtroy your Son. Soly. Though juſtice takes that life which he muſt loſe [Aſiae. Yet Nature cannot this requeſt refuſe. Go, lead him in, and let his Servants do [To the Mutes. That ſuddenjuſtice which I left to you. Muff. That cheerfulneſs with which to death Igo Some proof, Sir, of my innocence does ſhow. And ſince by death Iwould your hate remove What would I not have done to gain your love : [Extunt Muſtapha, and Mutes, Solyman looking after Muſtapha whilſt he is inſight. soly. What I have now decreed does juſt appear: But againſt Nature who can ſtop his Ear Though ſhe againſt the right of Juſtice ſtands? My Heart does figh for what my Tongue commands, [Exit. Enfty
Page 112

( 1 12 ) Enter Roxolana. Rox. Now the great deed is doing, or elſe done, I have been cruel to preſerve mySon. That cruel deed which makes him th' Empires Heir Heav'n, ſure, forgives ſince it rewards my care. And nothing now can ever make me grieve But for his death by which my Son does live. Enter Zarma. zarma. Madam, the Guards are doubled ev'ry where. Rox. If Guards can make you ſafe what need you fear : Zarma. Your ſervants hide their looks, and fear to ſhow The griefs they feel, and dangers which they know. Rox. Zarma, be deaf to what you ſhould not hear; Or uſe your ſtrength to what you ought to bear. Eaſing your ſelf, when you of grief complain, To many others you transfer your pain. [Enter Haly weeping. By your amazement and the tears you ſhed, [To Haly. You ſeem to tell me Maſtapha is dead. Haly. Yes, and ſo dy'd, that the moſt fortunate Would gladly for his Fame have had his Fate. But, Madam, be ſuffic'd that he is dead. Rox. No, Idare hear both what he did and ſaid. Haly. The Sultan his laſt ſuit could not deny; Which was, that by his ſervants he might dye. And each of thoſe declar'd it a leſs crime To kill himſelf then 'twas to Murder him. Rox. It ſhews he was with higheſt love eſteem'd When none would kill whom Solyman condemn'd. Haly. It turn'd our blood to tears when he did pray To all, in vain, to take his life away. He ſaid aloud, can Iſo wretched prove That your denyals muſt declare your love? See what your guilty kindneſs drives meto; Worſe then my Father did, 'twill make me do. One, whom he guilty thought, to death he ſent; But you will make me kill the innocent. 'Tis you have made your Prince unfortunate, Who finds your lovemore cruel then his hate. And now (afraid of nothing but delay) He flowning ſaid, unfriended Muftapha Muſt be beholding to himſelf for death: Then ſnatcht a Sword which ſtraight he did unſheath, Morat cry'd out, the Murd’rer's part I'ledo; 'Tis fitter I ſhould bear that guilt then you,
Page 113

(113) The Prince about his neck his Arms did ſpread Inſign of gratitude, and ſmiling ſaid, Is it not fit my wretched life ſhould end When he who kills me Ieſteem my Friend: Rex. He could not give more ornament to death Then when ſo calmly he reſign'd his breath. - Hay. When griev'd Morat the fatal deed had done (Which kindneſsmade him do and others ſhun) With haſte he ſaid, no Tears can be ſo good To ſhed for ſuch a kyſs as Tears of blood. His hand then acts the ſecond Tragick part Soon his own, as on his Maſters heart. But grief had wounded him ſo much before, That ſcarce his Cemiter could wound him more, Rox. This was at once a duty and a crime. Haly. It madeus pity firſt, then envy him. Rox, Call Zanger hither and return with ſpeed: But keep him ignorant of this diredeed. [Exit Haly. Brave Prince, if now thy Mother were alive, She, by my ſorrow, might be taught to grieve, How ſoon thy death a miracle has done? It makes meweep for what preſerves my Son. [ Exeant Roxolana, Zarm2. Enter Solyman, Soly. Forgot are now thoſe Fields his Valour won, Which did too ſoon his Head with Laurel crown! His Virtue with his Foes he overthrew ; For, growing great, he ſtraightgrew guilty too. Enter Zanger, who kneel; ; Solymau ſteps to him, and takes him up. ſ: I come at your command, by Achmat ſent; Who ſaid, I ſhould attend youin your Tent. Soly. Zanger, l, now did for your judgement ſend: Youare my minds Phyſician, Son, and Friend. Tellme, can Mortal-Monarchs alwaies keep The watch o're Empire ſet without ſome ſleep: Zang. Noman can live whom ſleep does not repair; Muchleſs can Monarchs who are borntb care. Soly. Behold then therevenge which I did take On him who kept me many Months awake. Zang. My Brother dead: you have the world bereft Of much more Virtue then is in it left 'Twas Jealouſie, not he (Oh diremiſtake 1) Which did ſomany Months keep youawake; G g Aa3
Page 114

(114) And it was juſt that you, who in your Breaſt Would jealouſie admit ſhould take no reſt. My ſpeech is by this obječt overcome: No grief is well expreſt till it is dumbſ Zangef goes to- Ah Loyal Prince 1 till death does cloſemy Eyes, l wards Muſtapha. Accept theſe Tears, my Friendſhips Sacrifice! Soly. Traytor, doſt weep for one condemn'd by me? This ſhews that thou as guilty art as he. Deſiſt, or thou ſhalt ſhare in his juſt fate. Zang. That, Sir, willrather ſhew your love than hate. Death is the only bleſſing I can find: - You think it juſt, and Iſhall think it kind. I will his worth to all the world declare. Soly. He did aſpire and grew too popular. Zang. Ruſtan, and Tyrrhus did his life purſue: We their contrivance of this Murder knew: And I deſir'd him from your wrath to flie; But in obedience he would ſtay to die. For, but one day when baniſh’d from your ſight, VVas worſe to him than Death's eternal night. If in himſelf he any guilt had known, He, with your leave, to Syria might have gone. He told me ſtill what he deſign'd or knew. Soly. His black deſigns he did conceal from you. Zang. Nothing could more his truſt of Friendſhip prove Then that we both th' Hungarian Queen did love: And though he then my firſt pretenſions knew, Yet freely he confeſthe lov'd her too: And when a Rival does his love reveal, What can his cunning after that conceal: How could you his unblemiſht Vertue doubt? Soly. Have Inot often heard my Armies ſhout When he appeat'd, and with applauſe ſo high As if his preſence brought them Vićtory: Zang. In that their errour and not his appeard; He with moregrief then you their gladneſs heard. By all the duty to a Father due, And to our Prophet, Muſtapha was true; True as you Viziers have been falſe and wrought You into wrong ſuggeſtions of his fault. Soly. Oh Heaven! my guilt now makes it an offence To hear untimely of his innocence. This truth (which now I may my torment call) You ſhould have ſooner told, or not at all. zang. Who could, without offending you, have thought (When your kind meſſage was by Achmat brought) That’twas a train laid for my Brothers life? And yet my doubt with duty was at ſtrife : And
Page 115

(115) And doubt prevail'd, for ſev'ral waies I try’d To get admittance but was ſtill deny'd. Swly. Zanger, to eaſe our griefs, let us agree Tº impute his Fate to our ill deſtinie. Thoſe who to death have made me ſend mySon, Shallinſtantly in torture meet their own. Let wiſdom check your ſorrow, and prepare To be this day proclaim'd my Empire's Heir. Zang. But, Sir, religiouſly to me he ſwore That, if the Turkiſh Crown he ever wore, He to our bloody Law an end would give, And I ſhould ſafely in his boſome live. Myſelf I then by ſacred promiſe ty'd Not to out-live the day on which he dy’d. Andas I knew he nobly did deſign To keep his vow, ſo I remember mine. [He turns to Muſtapha, ‘Twas only love had ſtrength enough t'invade That mutual Friendſhip which we ſacred made: But now o're love I have the conqueſt got; Though Love divided us, yet death ſhall not.-- [Zanger ſtabs himſelf and falls at Muſtapha's Feet, Solyman runs to him. Soly. Hold, Zanger hold ! Zang. The happy wound is given Which ſends my Soul to Muſtapha and Heaven. Soly. Friendſhip and cruelty alike have done; For each of them has rob'd me of a Son. Zang. When, Sir, you have forgiv'n me for my death, Grant what I ask with my departing breath: Your dying Zanger begs th' Hungarian Crown For th’injur'd Queen and for her guiltleſs Son. Soly. Shall I ſolittle give for Zanger's ſake, Whoſe mighty mind would not my Empire take : Zang. Sir, for your gift in thankfulneſs I bend; I Bows to him. Indeath Iſerve my Miſtreſs and my Friend. He'llive in your eſteem, ſhe in her Throne. Now all I had to do on Earth is done. [Turns againto Muſtapha, Loat your Feet, dear Friend, your Brother lies; And where he took delight to live — he dies. [Zanger dies, Soly. Fame in her Temple will adorn thy ſhrine. No Roman Glory ever equall'd thine. Zanger, in height of Youth, for Friendſhips ſake, Did rather die then proffer'd Empire take. I would die too, but by revenge am ſtaid Due for you both, which ſhall be doubly paid. My Piziers ſhall be firſt your ſacrifice. Nor is ſhe ſafe who in my boſom lies, f Ot
Page 116

(116) For they, without her intfeſt in the deed, Durſt not at laſt have urg'd me to proceed. [Turns to Muſtapha. Oh Muſtapha! the worthy may in thee The dang'rous ſtate even of great vertue ſee. Thine was to all the height and compaſs grown That vertue e're could reach to get renown: And the reward of it pernicious prov’d, For I did puniſh thee for being lov’d. Thy Mother was the firſt thate’repoſeſt By Conqueſt the Dominion of my Breaſt: And had thymind been blotted and as black As vertue would paint vice, yet for her ſake, (The brighteſt Beauty, and the ſofteſt Wife) Imight, alas, at leaſt have ſav'd thy life. But I ſhallmourn toolong; for whilſt Iſtay, To count thy wrongs, Ithy revenge delay. [ Exit. Enter Roxolana, Haly. Rox. How Haly! are you certain that mySon Is to the Sultan's Great Paviliongone? Haly. Achmat was for him by the Sultan ſent; And you will find him in the inner Tent. Rox. You ſhould have brought him to conſult with me E’re he had known his Brothers deſtinie. Haly. I humbly beg, this maybe rather thought Your ſervants great misfortune then his fault. Fox. Waitinmy name, on the Hungarian Queen: Tell her, that thoſerude Tumults ſhe his ſeen May ſtill increaſe, and may nenew her fear; And therefore I would fain ſecure her here, But ſomething, from yourſelf, you ought to ſay, She having heard too much of Muſtapha. [Exit Haly. Roxolana goes towards the Scene, where ſhe ſees Mu- ſtapha, and Zanger with his Dagger in his hand, and then ſhe ſtarts back. Both dead! O horrour ! Zanger does appear Arm'd gainſt himſelf as his own Murderer. This deed Friendſhip and pity made thee do. But was not I thy Friend and Mother too: That Friendſhip againſt Nature was a crime Which paid menothing and too much to him. Though Friendſhip to a Friend thou might'ſ aſſign, Yet, ſince I lent thee life, that life was mine. Unjuſt to Nature, though to Friendſhip true, In paying Friendſhips debt with Natures due. 1s
Page 117

( i 17) Is this the laſt reward of all the pain I felt,ſaving thy life to make thee reign : Thou haſtreveng'd (O Heav'n) what [have done With ſo much guilty kindneſs for my Son! Enter the Queen. Queen. What voice of ſorrow is alone ſo loud, As if the cauſe had made the mourner proud : For after noble Muſtapha is ſlain Who can enough, without my help complain? Rox. Ah Queen! add to your grief by looking there. Zanger is dead, and his own Murderer. 2seen. Zanger 1 I did not think Fate could have ſhown (After it took away my King and Throne) Another loſs which could a grief impoſe To make me weep as juſtly as for thoſe. Why did not zanger fatal vertue lack Since it did higheſt Friendſlip cruel make : Grief grows too hard for our complaints alone When the Worlds loſs is greater then our own. Rox. Ah Muſtapha Ihither came to grieve [Aſia. That by thy death Imademy Zanger live; But he tooſoon for my offence has paid; And I, thy Traytor, amby him betraid. -- Madam, your tears will now injurious be; [Turns to the Queen. In grief, as honour, you out-rival me. Żueen. You Zanger lov'd, then do not mereprove Grieving for two who had no fault but love. Enter Haly. Rox. Haly! If you come nearer you'l deſpiſe All Glory and repent that you have Eyes. Haly. The Sultan, full of horrour, did relate A Tragick ſtory of ſuch diſmal fate As keeps me from approaching out of fear To ſee what it was cruelty to hear. But theſe high ſorrows are accompany'd With others which compaſſion fain would hide. Rox. VVill Heav'n more weight on our afflićtion lay f Haly. Madam, the Guards and Train of Muſtapha Aſſault the Camp with their united Force, And are aſſiſted by Prince Zanger's Horſe. The Sultan, arm'd againſt this ſudden rage, Is now advanc'd their fury to aſſwage. Rox. O fatal ſtrife where Vićtors nothing gain Haly. The Viziers by his order are both ſlain. Madam, to you, as Regent for your Son, [Turns to the Queen. The Saltan does preſent th' Hungarian Crown. The old Moravian Troops areby command, Prepai'd to march againſt King Ferdinand. H h Yeu,
Page 118

( 1 18 ) You, with your Son, may now to Budago To meet your Friends and to purſue your Foe. Your Reſtoration he before deſign'd When firſt the Empreſs with his purpoſe joyn'd : Put this diſpatch he juſtly has confeſt Is the effect of Zanger's laſt requeſt. ..Queen. The looks of gratitude ſhould chearful be ; But, Zanger, I am ſo oblig'd by thee, As it occaſion gives to make me mourn That to the dead I nothing can return. Rox. Madam, the Sultan's bounty ſtrait receive; And, in your abſence, truſt me here to grieve. 2ueen. Madam, I'le with my Son to Buda go And my laſt duty to his Father ſhow: Then in a ſhady Cloiſter will remain, And, as a fatal Mourner, ſtill complain Of that which here both you and I have loſt, Where death does over love in triumph boaſt. I ſhall undo my Son if I look back On thoſe whom I unwillingly forſake; I'm more concern'd in what I leave behind Tſien in the joys he ſhall in Buda find. Rox. Go, Madam, go, and haſten to your Throne Live to find Zanger's Friendſhip in your Son. Be with much pow'r more happy then I prov'd; Live to be feard, and yet continue lov’d. ..Queen. I'le flye from pow'r 5 but yours to the diſtreſt Has been arefuge and ſhould be increaſt, Till (when you weary grow ) your ſuppliants ſue That Heav'n may be a refuge then to you. [They Embrace, [Exeunt Queen, and Haly. Fnter Zarma at the other door, Zarma. The Mufty is within, and bad me ſay That he is ſent to counſel you to pray, Rox. Why doſt thou weep? I do not dying fear: Thougriev'ſt becauſe Grief's remedy is near. Tie meet the Mufty, and for death prepare: Lead me this way, for I would ſhun deſpair. [She looks backwards towards the dead Bodies and goes from them. Excunt. The Scene changes. Enter Achmat, Haly, Achmat. The tortur'd Wiziers did their guilt confeſs; And, e're they dy'd, accus’d the Sultantſ: Włº
Page 119

(119) Who to their firſt propoſal did encline : But by ambitious Ruffan the deſign (In hope to gain her favour) was begun; And was purſu'd by her to ſave her Son. Haly. The Guards and noble Train of Muſtaphs Have got renown though they have loſt the day. Achm. Till Solyman in perſon did appear They, in their fierce aſſault, Vićtorious were. With Thirty Thouſand Horſe they brav'd the Field : Of which Five Hundred are not left unkil’d. He pardon'd thoſe and pitty'd their offence ; But they ſo hated life and lov'd the Prince That it was harder to preſerve thoſe few Then 'twas t’o recome the many whom we ſlew. VWhen rumour (ſwift, though it flies low) had ſpread Through all our Camp that Muftapha was dead, And that his Friends, who had that battel fought, VVere only for his ſafety hitherbrought. Then the Vićtorious threw their Arms away, And wept for thoſe whom they did lately ſlay. Some, who had kill'd their Sons, more tears did ſhed For their own guilt, then that their Sons were dead 5 Guilt wrought by Fate, which had their valour mov’d Againſt that Prince whom they for valour lov’d. Enter Solyman, Zarma. Hall. His Brows are full of Clouds, his Eyes of Fire; There's dang'rous Thunder near: let us retire. - [Extunt Achmar, Hly. A Table, with Staandiſh,and a chair upon the Stage. Sol. VVell, call her in ; and do as I command. You, with her VVomen, muſt be ſtill at hand. The Mufty is of uſe; let him attend." [Exit Zarma. Thy progreſs, Love, was long, but it ſhallend. By Beauty (which does even the wiſe delude) The valiant ever ſooneſt are ſubdu'd. 'Tis nature's ſnare, and in defiancelaid; For whenleaſt hidden we are moſt betray'd. Beau ies fair hand has many a mighty name Too foully blotted in the Book of Fame. Accurſed Beauty 'tis at laſt to thee That Famous Chiefs have ow'd their infamie. Oh what? has it not done, and may do ſtill. Enter Roxolana. Rox. Icome to know Heav'ns pleaſure in yout will. Sol;
Page 120

(I2O) soly. Diawnearer then 1 Alas! be not afraid When 'tis too late to fear. Speak, have you pray'd? For you have much to loſe, but more to ſave. Have you been Penitent : Rex. Sultan, I have. Soly. You needed many Tears to waſh away The ſtains which have defil'd this bloody day. Brave Muſtapha,and Zanger too is dead; Theſe have deſerv'd more Tears than you can ſhed, Since all in Honour's liſt they did excel: But in their cauſe full Thirty Thouſand fell; And twice that number were in Battel kill’d By thoſe who did deſerve to gain the Field. Rox. Oh, Sultan, do not give me leave to ſpeak ; But give that Heart, which loves you, leave to break! Soly. Let it intire a while, for my ſake, laſt. I would not now havemention'd what is paſt But that 'tis juſtice and ſome kindneſs too Toſhew ſufficient cauſe for what Ido, Which elſemight cruel ſeem ; for you muſt dye. Rox. When you bring death I will not ask you, why • Soly. It ſhews the civil greatneſs of your mind When to your Puniſher you can be kind': But 'twill oblige me and become you too, More then your fatal beauty ere did do, If you ſo gracefully depart from life As fits our Childrens Mother and my Wife. Rox. Perhaps Iliv'd unworthy of your fame, Put none ſhall Roxolana's dying blame: Yet I muſt grieve ſo as Iought to do When I, by leaving life, depart from you. Swly. You may your little debts of kindneſs pay; But I muſt be oblig'danother way, Which will be firſt by your confeſſion ſhown: Confeſſing not what you, but I have done. Rox. Ah, Sir! moſt willingly I will confeſs You found me in the Region of diſtreſs ; A Flow'r but newly ſprung, and in the ſhade. My growth I from your ſhining favour had. Soly. This, is not the confeſſion I would hear, It ſhews untimely gratitude or fear; And makes meguilty of upbraiding you With what Love's ſecret pow'r did make me do. I aim not to be told what I have done By loves perſwäfive force, and but to one ; For when you lov'd me too that debt was paid, And debts, diſcharg’d, none juſtly can upbraid. Mox.
Page 121

(12 I) Rox. Ah do not, Sir, forbid my thankfulneſs soly. You quite miſtake the thing you ſhould confeſs, 'Tis not what Love but Honour made me do For all yout Sex, and not alone for you. Though the ſtrićt Laws of ottoman's high Race Did not allow our Sultans e're ſhould grace The Mothers of their Sons with priviledge Of Marriage, yet your Sex I did oblige, And lifted you above the ſcorns of life, When I, by ſacred forms, made you my Wife. Rox. This is butmention'd to augment theſence, Which you ſuſpect I want, of my offence. Or elſe you ſhew me that I uſeleſs grow Whilſt Iconfeſs but what the people know. soly. If what I did was then by Honour done Let me that Honour keep when you are gone, Let me the favour of your Sex retain: Which ſince Ijuſtly did by Marriage gain I would not loſe it now by Deaths divorce, Whilſt they unjuſtly think I want remorſe; And that my juſtice is but cruelty, Becauſe my Wife does by myſentence die. Rox. Do but inſtruct me, Sultan, how I may, In death, for all my life's offences pay? Soly. It is not fit our Prieſthood or Divan Should fit to judge the Wife of Suffman. But yet the blood by your ambition ſpilt, Cries out ſoloud'gainſt your audacious guilt, That now my People, Armies, and the State, Behold your Beauty with malicious hate: And no expedient e're can ſatisfie The juſtice they expect unleſs you die. You only can to Heav'n for mercy truſt. Rox. Sir, I will die,that they may find you juſt, Soly. But, that your Sex may ever think me ſo, You muſt a form of proceſs undergo Which ſtrićt neceſſity does make me uſe. You muſt, under your hand, your ſelf accuſe: Which, as a true Record, may reſcue me From falſe opinions of my crueltie. Rox. Ah Sultan This proceeding is ſevere! Soly. You nobly ſhould your own impeachment bear Leaſt you a ruder from our Baſhaws hear. Go, Roxolana, ſit, and write it down. Rox. I, with my crime, ſhallmake my duty known. [Lead; her to the Table, soly. Bebrief and clear. Poſterity ſhould know The hidden root which made your miſchief grow. I i When
Page 122

(122) When the firſt cauſes we of ills diſcern We ſafely and with eaſe preventionlearn. You had your aids in the conſpiracy; My Viziers elſe had not been i. to die. [He ſteps to her whilſt What form do you in your confeſſion uſe: ſhe is mriting. Rox. Sultan I wholly do myſelfaccuſe. - - Andyet the dying, ſure, may blame the Dead Who ſafely are by Death from danger freed: Beſides both they and I ſhall ſtraight appear Where Heaven's juſt Monarch will the injur'd hear. Soly. Accuſe your ſelf and let their guilt alone, Rox. If the contrivance was by them begun May Inot make of Truth peculiar uſe And crimes extenuate when Iſhun excuſe: Sol). Already is your whole contritionſpent. Leave off if you unwillingly repent. [He offers to take up the Taper, She riſes and hold; it aſide. Rox. Forgive, me Sultan, and I will proceed. Sol). Oh Heav'n 1 when ſhe ſo *f does pardon need Can ideny it and endure to live? I cannot be forgiv'n, if I forgive, So much her crime all mercy does exceed; For Muſtapha and Zanger too is dead. Make haſte writefully your ambition down In changing the ſucceſſion of my Crown. Rox Pardon the Tears Ion the Paper ſhed If I have written what you cannot read. Sely. Forgive her Heav'n here take my Handkercher Diſpatch why do you pauſe : Fox. I'le haſten, Sir. [She riſes again. But whilſt Inow my crimeat fullexpreſs - Let me a little ſpeak in much diſtreſs. soly. Your time forbids the tediouſneſs of grief; Complain not when you cannot have relief. Yet you may ſpeak. Take courage, but be brief. Rox. Sir, this confeſſion a Record muſt be To ſave you from imputed cruelty. Heav'n give you, Sir, an everlaſting fame, And Heav'n perſwadeyou to prevent my ſhame. I have but little through ambition done; Nature did more, and’twas to ſave my Son. Soly. What did myſterious nature make you do? Could you at once be kind and cruel too: Farewel, you are relaps'd, worſe then before. • Rox. Sultan, Ile write, and I will ſpeak no more. [She ſits down again. Enter
Page 123

(123) Enter Haly, Hall. Sultan, Iſhew my Duty in my haſte; For with new Clouds your Camp is over-caſt: The Bloody bus'neſs of this fatal day Grows bloodi'r ſince the death of Muſtapha. The Janizaries, by their Agaled, Accuſe the Empreſs, and demand her Head. Roxolana riſes and They have their grievance by their Agaſent, } ſeems diſorder'd. And he attends at th' entrance of your Tent. soly. They truſt my yielding but ſhall feel my force. Bid Achmat face them with my Syrian Horſe. You muſt your beſt diſguiſe of Friendſhip wear, And meet the Aga with the looks of fear, Call him to Council, and diſorder'd ſeem ; And when he is admitted, ſtrangle him. [Exit Haly. Theſe threatning Tumults only dang'rous are To Monarchs who dare leſs then Subjects dare, Goes to Rox- Sit down! is your confeſſion finiſh'd yet? olana. Rox. Sultan, it is. soly. I'le read what you have writ. she kneeling zºº Rox. Sir, now I feel thetorments of true fear, l him the Paper. Becauſe your dangers great as mine appear. Give to rude hands the life which I muſt loſe, If you defend it you your own expoſe. Soly, No, Roxolana, you ſhall calmly die. You ſhall find juſtice, but no cruelty. Your Women waitwithout; the Mufty too: What muſt be done they decently ſhall do. Enter Haly and kneels. Haly. The ſudden Tempeſt ſuddenly is paſt, [she riſ ;. No Clouds canlong before yourluſtre laſt. - With Tears the Janizaries now implore That favour which their rage diſdain'd before. Sir, Achmat for the Aga's life doesſue; Which he repriev'd to have it ſav'd by you: It will a Triumph to the Army give Who are with grief ſubdu'd. soly. Go, let him live. - Rox. Ah Solyman I ſhall ſhe who heretofore, Still with ſucceſs, for others did implore Be now deni’d when for her ſelf ſhe ſues? Ibeg not what Iought, Sir, to refuſe If it were granted, your conſent to live. Oh take my life, but my offenceforgive. soly. Oh why did Heav'n ſuch perfeółbeauty make Yet let ſuch beauteous things perfeótion lack? [Exit Haly, Love
Page 124

( 1.24) Love againſt Juſtice in my boſom ſtrives. Let Juſtice pardon Love what Love forgives. [He takes her up. Riſe, Roxolana, you ſhall mercy find. Eut as when you were cruel you were kind, So I willdeeds by your Example do; For I will now be kind and cruel too. Rox. Heav'n which begins to take your Clouds away, Will from departing night make break of day. Soly. I give you life, and I forgive your crime; Yet in this kindneſs I ſhall cruel ſeem. Rox. Oh ſtay, Sir, and but hear what Ile implore. Sol). Your doom is ſeal’d. I'lenever ſee you more. Rox. Ah, Sir, you gave what I can ne're enjoy; What you preſerv'd you inſtantly deſtroy. Soly. Zarma 1 call all to look on my remorſe; And then be witneſſes of our divorce. Enter Zarma, four of Roxolana's Ladies, Achmat, Haly, the three Attendants of Muſtapha and Zanger, eight of the Guard, and ſix Pages. The number on #. Stage being now twenty four. w Take with your life perpetual Baniſhment. Long may you live that you may much repent: But fom my fight be ſtill ſo far remov’d, As I may quite forget Iever lov’d. Rox. Ah, Sultan, do but hearwhat Ican ſay ! Soly. Oh cruelty, you kill me if you ſtay. Rox. I'le but forgiveneſs beg for love and grief Since both offend you when they ſeek relief. soly. Oh Heav'n ſtill will you ſpeak: Rox. Sir, I'le depart, And at yoºr feet leave a forſaken heart. [Exit. Saly. Farewel for ever, and to Love farewell I’le lock my Boſom up where Love did dwell; I will to beauty ever ſhut my eyes, And be no more a Captive by ſurprize: But Oh, how little I eſteem a Throne When Love, the Ornament of Pow'r is gone! Extant Omnes. F I N I S.
Page Scan 135

Blank page
Page Scan 136

Blank page
Page Scan 137

Blank page
Page Scan 138

||||||||||| ADDDDD.5254701 Y-KS go) O 4– —, |\º | C 33 c
Page Scan 139

Blank page
Page Scan 140

|||||| |

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents

End of text. Return to beginning.
