Pompey. A tragoedy, [Ornament], . | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
Pompey. A tragoedy, [Ornament], .
Author
Corneille, Pierre, 1606-1684.Corneille, Pierre, 1606-1684.
Published
Dvblin,Printed by J. Crooke, for S. Dancer,1663.
Description
3 p. L., 80 p., 1 L.22cm.
Rights
Public Domain.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015094339739

Table of Contents

    Front Cover
    Title Page
    Section 1 on page number 1
    Section 2 on page number 8
    Section 3 on page number 20
    Section 4 on page number 32
    Section 5 on page number 36
    Section 6 on page number 52
    Section 7 on page number 55
    Section 8 on page number 58
    Section 9 on page number 60
    Section 10 on page number 62
    Section 11 on page number 77
    Section 12

Book Text
Front Cover
Page Scan 1

// , , , 2%. º Zºº

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 2

->- r z º. f* . º & º Q} {}} \}º.º. Kº ººººººººººº!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!！！!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!!！!!!!！!!!!!!!!！!!!！!!!!!!！!!!!!!！!!！ ，SÌ∞∞∞§################################ Ř®ſ$ſ;[][] ' '， SSR （NÅºſºſſŒ œ £7 E! E: &#&@A.S.; Vſ. Sº Aºy. JºJº º M.J. Q. ºf Sº, ºffſ Re： | ĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪífffffffffffff ĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪĪ



This page contains an image.
Page Scan 3

RA*E SOOk gºod M.
Page Scan 4

Blank page

End of Front Cover. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Title Page
Page Scan 5

º - D'O B L IN, * Printed by john Crooke, Printer to the Kings Moſt Excellent Majeſty, for Samuel - Dancer, next Door to the Bear - and Ragged-ſtaff in Caſtle- - - - - ſtreet, 1663. . .

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 6

º -- º *ae ſ - - - - --- - - º º ---- ------ ！！！ |-|-ſae ，，… ：（ ！ |-ſä ！ ！！ ！！ --" ------- W bris º - -- º ºil- - - ſº tº









This page contains an image.
Page Scan 7

- -- ºº: -- -º tºº The Printer to the ºf Hope you expetino Eloquence from a Printer, nor Regularity in a 1 Preface, which hath nothing to ſay to you, but that Pompey being a Tranſlation out of the French of Mon- feur Corneille, the hand that did it is reſponſible for nothing but the Engliſh, and the Songſ between the Atif, which were added only to lengthen the Play,and make it fitterfor the Stage, when thoſe that could not be reſiſted were reſolved to have it ačied; and that no abuſer of Tranſcribers ( though they were nume- rous ) could have prevail'd to ſend it to the Preſ, if the Perſon moſt con- cern d had not fºur'd to diſobey an excel- lent Lady, who commanded this pub- lication, more than the ſeverity of the World Cenſure. A 2 The 20% ºf"/3 º -





This page contains an image.
Page Scan 8

- The Perſons of the Play. julius Caeſar. Marcus Antonius. Lepidus. º Ptolomy, King of Ægypt. Cleopatra, His Siſter. Photinus, His Governour. Achillas, His Lieutenant General. - Septimius, A Roman in the Ægyptian Kings Army. º Achoreus, Cleopatra's Gentleman Uſher. Charmion, Cleopatra's Maid of Honour. Cornelia, Pompey's Widdow. Philip, Pompey's Freedman. Romans and Ægyptians. The Scene Ptolomey's Pallace in Alexandria. PRO.



This page contains an image.
Page Scan 9

testsegºttests: $$$$$$$$$$$$$$$. PRO LO GUIE, Earl of Roſcomon, - ( Rage He mighty Rivals, whoſe deſtrućfive Did the whole World in Civil Armeſ en- 40 & Are now agreed, and make it both their ci. To have their Fates determin’d by your Voice. Caeſar from mone but You, will hear his Doom, He hateſ th’ obſequious Flatteries of Rome: He ſcornſ, where once he rul’d, now to be try’d, And he hath rul’d in all the World beſide. Jºhen he the Thames, the Danube,and the Nile Hadſtain'd with Blood, Peace flouriſhed in this - º (Iſle; Audyon alone may Boaft, you never ſaw Caeſar 'till now, and now ean give him Law: Great Pompey too, comeſ aſ a ſuppliant here, But ſaye. He cannot now begin to fear. - - - - For the Theatre at Dublin, written by the y- tº







This page contains an image.
Page Scan 10

He knewer your equal juſtice, and (to tell A Roman #. ) He knower himſelf too well. Succeſ, tir true, waited on Caeſar'sſide, But Pompey think; he conquer'd when he dy'd. His Fortune when ſhe prov'd the moſt unkind, Chang'd his Condition, but not Cato's Mind. Then of what Doubt can Pompey's Cauſe ad- Since here ſo many Cato's judging fit. (mit, To the La But you bright Nymphº.give Caeſar leave to dies, The greateſt Wonder of the world but you.(woo. - And hear a Muſe, who has that Hero taught To ſpeak as gen’rouſly, aſ ere he fought. " JWhoſe Eloquence from ſuch a Theme deterſ All Tongue, but Engliſh,and all pen, but Hers. By the juſt Fates your Sex is doubly bleſt, Tou Conquer’d Caeſar,and you praiſe him beft. To the And Ton ( Illuſtriouſ Sir J receive as due, Lerd *A Preſent Deſtiny reſerval for You. (here, tenant. Rome, France and England joyn their Forces To make a Poem worthy of your Ear. - - Accept it them, and on that Pompey's Brow Who gave ſo many Crowns,befton, one now.



This page contains an image.

End of Title Page. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 1

-- - - - --". ºf . º ºn ſolºbºſ bººb atti'ſ - --- -- --- . * —º ºf , , . . º Hºbsºlo fºol - H--------------- ------------ --- tº ºilº ºn. --- º. º S. º.º. --- º-º-º: --- - - v. ºv 2. --- a . -- " - * -º . Ağ tº Seen º # silº bºoſt ºf º, it rid ſº, º, sº º º blº º: gº Ptoljiney ; : Ae hillis , Photiºſ, Septiºnſ. ºn dº no loº ºisie P TO L'OM Yºlº ºbſº *Ate hath. º: Th"Intrigue of the great Rivals Beſtiny: Tº That quarrel which did all theºodsdivide, Pharſalia hath the Honour to decide. +. Whôſe Rivers ſwelling with new blººdy (Sent thither from ſo many Particides), "( Tides The Horrow of tºrn Enfigh, Chariots, Shiºds, spread in Confuſion o're th' infected'Fields;" Thoſe Slaughter'd heaps whoſe ſhades no reſt ob- By Nature to their own revenge conſtrain'd,(tain'd (Their Putrefactions ſeeming to Revive º' T The War, with thoſe that do remain alive; ) ". Are Dreadful rules by which the Sword thinks fit, Pompey to caſt, and Caſar to acquit, ºli. - A That









This page contains an image.
Page 2

( 2) -- That diſtreſs'd Leader of the Juſter Side, . Whoſe wearied Fortune hath all Help deni'd, A terrible Example will create - To future Times, of the Extreams of Fate: i. He flies, whoſe happy Couragehad, till now, Confind the Bay to his Victorious Brow: He in our Ports chooſes his laſt Retreat 3 And wanting Refuge from a Foe ſo Great, His bold Misfortune ſeeks it in Abodes, ". Which from the Titans once preſerv'd the Gods 3 And from ſo fam'd a Climate, doth expect That it ſhould Earth as well as Heav'n protećt 5 And lending his Deſpair a kinde Effort, It ſhould the ſtaggering Univerſe ſupport: Yes, the World's Fortune Pompey with him brings, And hopes a Land whoſe Fame ſuch Wonder ſings, A Prop or Tomb might to her Freedom give, And Pompey's Fall Attend, if not Releive. ... This, Friends, the Subject is of our debate 5 - Qur Triumphs he, or Ruine will create; , He hazards me, who did my Father ſave, And does expoſe that Memphis which he gave: We muſt now haſtensor prevent his fate, ºr ------ ------ * * - * ſºil 1. . - His Ruine hinder or precipitate : º, º ****) . ." --ºl. 1 • *-**** * * * - º That is unſafe, and this Ignoble is , , , , I dread injuſtice, or unhappineſs; ſº And angry fortune each way offers me Either much danger, or much infamy; sº It is my part to chooſe, yours to adviſe, º, ºf 1.3 sº 1 "lººn ** 1 - " - r * * * * * * * What you believe to be inoſt ſafe and wiſe; Pompey's Concern'd; nay, we the fame ſhall get, Caeſar's ſucceſs to trouble, or compleat; • * * *. º º - º - - -- --- iºſi º A. And º º



This page contains an image.
Page 3

( 3 % tº º º º r: ". -- º And never Monarchs Fortune, did afford." " So great a Subječt, for a Councel Board. * * ... '" ºf * * * * * ºt

- tº ºf PHoT IN us. - abº dº * , , -º-º-º-º- When things, Sir, are determind by the ſword, - Juſtice is nothing, but an empty word 5 - And he who then Affairs would rightly weigh Muſt not his Reaſons, but his power obey: - View your own Strength, let Pompey be ſurvey'd, Whoſe Fortune Droop's, and Valour is betray'd; Who not from ceſar only takes his flight, But from the Senates juſt Reproach and ſight, (Whoſe greater part, were cheaply left a Prey To the Keen Vultures of Pharſalia ) He flies loſt Rome, and every Roman now 5 Who muſt to his defeat their Fetters owe. He flies thoſe Kings who would chaſtiſe his Guilt, Of all the blood that in his cauſe was ſpilt. Their Kingdoms now of Men and Mony void, Their broken Scepters and their Thrones deſtroy'd, As Author of all Woes, abhor'd by all, He flies the whole Worldy ſhatter'd by his Fall. Can you alone reſiſt ſo many Foes? His ſafety he did in himſelf Repoſe : º He falls, and You may yield without a Bluſh To ſuch a weight as Rome her ſelf does Cruſh 5 A weight which hath the Univerſe preſt down, And the yet greater Pompey, overthrown. He that will ſave, whom Heaven will have wrack’t, By too much Juſtice may a Guilt Contračt.

A 2 And

This page contains an image.
Page 4

(4)

- - - - - * * * - - And a fidelity ſo indiſcreet ºn May a ſhort Fame, but long Repentance meet: He but a more Illuſtrious wound will have, Which will not ſmart the leſs for being brave : Do not for Egypt Thunderbolts provide, But chooſe with Fortune, and the Gods to ſide. Believe not they can an Injuſtice do, But where they favour, pay your Homage too. Whatever they decree for them declare, And think it Impious where they frown to ſpare, With Divine Anger, Pompey now beſet, Comes to involve you too, in his Defeat. His Head for which both Gods and Men do call Already ſhakes, and ſeeks but where to fall: His coming hither an Offence does ſeem And ſhew's his Hatred rather then eſteem. He would his ſafety with Your Ruine,buy, And can you Doubt, if he deſerve to dye & Had he fulfill'd what we both wiſht and thought,

And a Vićtorious Navy hither brought, sº We then ſhould him a Joyful welcom ſhew, ºr Who muſt the Gods blame for his uſage now. I of his Fortune, not of him Complain, But with Regret Ağt what the Gods Ordain, And the ſame Ponyard, once for Ceſar meant Shall with a figh to Pompey's Heart be ſent. Nor can you at a leſs rate then his Head Secure Your Own, and ſhun the ſtorm You Dread, Let this be thought a Crime, if ſoit muſt, - 'Tis not a States-man's Virtue to be Juſt. When Right and Wrong are in the Ballance lay'd, The Intereſt of Kingdoms is betray'd, E - . X- ---

This page contains an image.
Page 5

- - -- -- - ( ; ) - -- Extreameſt Rigour is the Right of Kings, * When Timorous Equity their Ruine brings, ". Who fears a Crime ſhall ever be affraid, " But hee'ſ rule all, who all things dares invade, Who Dangerous Virtue, as Diſgrace, does ſhun, And to an Uſeful Crime as ſwiftly run. This is my Thought Sir, but Achillas may, Or elſe Septimius, chooſe ſome other way. But this I know.whatever others like, (ſtrike. They fear no Conquerour, who the Conquer'd A C H I L L A S. . Photim ſayes true Sir,but though Pompey we Deveſted of his former Grandeur ſee, Yet that Blood Pretious does to me appear Which the Gods did in Theſſaly revere. Not that a Crime of State ſhould be refrain'd, But 'tis not lawful, till it be coaſtrain'd : " And what need is there of ſuch Rigour here £ Who quits the Conquerºd, needs no Conquerour You may be Neuter.as You were before : (fear. And Caeſar may, if him you muſt adore; But though you treat him as a Power Divine, This is too great an Offring for his Shrine. To Mars himſelf ſhould this Head offer'd be, 'Twould fix on Yours too black an Infamy: Let him not be Aſſiſted nor Deſtroyid, And ſuch a Condućt will all blame avoid. - You owe him much Sir, for Rome, mov’d by him, Help'd our laſt King his Scépter to redeem, But

This page contains an image.
Page 6

* - (6) But Gratitude and Hoſpitality, ºn In Monarchs Breſts muſt regulated be, Nor can a King Contračt ſo great a Debt, . But that his Subjećts claim a greater yet. And all Engagements are to Princes void, ºilº - To Cancel which,their Blood muſt be Imploy'd : º Conſider too, what Pompey did expoſe, - When he your Father help'd againſt his Foes : By that he made his Power the greater ſeem, And rais'd his own Fame, by reſtoring him : He did in ſerving him but language ſpend 5 But Caeſar's Purſe appear'd the better Friend, - Had we not Caeſar; thouſand Talents ſeen, Pompey's Orations had ſmall ſuccours been. Let him not then his Verbal merits boaſt, For Caſar's Actions have Oblig'd You moſt. But if a benefit to Him be due, Speak now for Him, as he did once for You : His kindneſs ſafely thus requite you may 5 But here receiv'd, He will your Scepter ſway : This Conquer'd Roman yet a King will brave, And in your own Dominions you enſlave. Refuſe him Welcom then, but ſpare his Head 5 But ift muſt fall, this arme ſhall ſtrike him dead: I can obey (Sir J and ſhould Jealous grow, if any Hand but mine ſhould ſtrike the blow. - , S E PT IMI U. S. Sir, I'm a Roman, and theſe Hero's know Pompey needs aid, and from you ſeeks it now ; * - - | You

This page contains an image.
Page 7

(7) - - You are his fate, may his loſt hopes revive, Baniſh, or Kill, or give him up alive: - The firſt would coſt you much too dear a Rate, I'le only then the other three debate. In ºn His exile draws on You enraged Pow'r, tº And does but half oblige the Conquerour 5 º' Since to a long ſuſpenſe you will him leave, What fate his future battles ſhall receive 5 And both on you Revenge, when weary grown The Ills, which but for You, they had not known. To render him to Caeſar were the ſame, Who muſt forgive him, to Augment his Fame: He will a brav'ry on himſelf impoſe, And ſwell in that falſe mercy he beſtowes; Glad if that way, he Pompey can o'recome, And in the ſame Aét pleaſe ſubjećted Rome : But whilſt you him to this neceſſitate, You'l purchaſe his, as well as Pompey's hate: His danger and diſhonour then prevent, Both make him great, and keep him Innocent; Whilſt Pompey's Faëtion, you, in him deſtroy, Let Caeſar, at your coſt, the Fruit enjoy: By this advice, which you’l I hope allow, You'l gain a Friend, and need not fear a Foe 5 But if Achillas unſafe courſe you chooſe, You neither gain, but both their Friendſhips looſe. - º PTO LO M. Y., ºniº aſ Let us no more debate what's Juſt and fit, But to the Worlds viciſſitude ſubmit. -º-º-º-º: - Your

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 8

Your Major votes do with my Thoughts agree Who in ſo great a change would active be, Rome hath too long made an Injurious Claim That all Men ſhould adore the Roman Name: Her lofty Freedom let us now throw down, And all Her ſcorn in Pompey's Blood lets drown. Cutting the Root by which that Pride does live, To the Worlds Tyrants, let's a Tyrant give; Now fate would chain an Arrogance, ſo fierce, a £et's help her to revenge the Univerſe. ºil Rome,thou ſhalt ſerve, & Kings which alwayes yet, Th' haſt dar'd with ſo much Inſolence to treat, Will Caeſar now, with leſs Regret, obey Since thou ſhalt be enſlav'd as well as they. Achillas and ſeptimius looſe no time, But make us Deathleſs by this glorious Crime, nº Of Heavens Reſentment I’le the hazard run, . Who ſent him hither ſure to be undone. . º ºn tº ºut ºld A C H I L L.A.S. ºn tº ºf sº ºn |- ſº A Kings Command muſt no diſpute endure. ºn ºn P TO LO M.Y. . . . ºf - - - - --- -- ºn º º * Go then, the Scepter which I bear, ſecure 5 For you by this Commiſſion are become The Deſtinies of Egypt and of Rome. - - - - ºil ºre-º-; tº +. tº ºſº jºi º 'º ºf , , - - - - - - ---------- - ºf Scen, 2.

This page contains an image.
Page 9

(9). - º - - --- '9. ' Tº #Ir, - irºſ tº: Bº,” Q: boºſ, ºr tº ſº ºv, *... º. - - tº º º : ; sº º º º ºf 5 -: ; : ~, - bºoij}ººl º: ºf ºil-fill -- - - - º - - - - º, º ºr ºf tº ſºlº a Scen. 2. Iº e II* * º ſºliº. - - -- - Ptolomy, Photinus. -* º -- - º PTO L O MY. I am miſtaken photim, or by this My Siſter will her expectation miſs, ºn Pompey roy Fathers Will having ſecur'd, Her Coronation ſhe believes aſſur’d. And ſhe her ſelf the Miſtreſs does eſteem, º Of that divided Scepter left by him. / - Their Antient Friendſhip ſhe depends upon, And inwardly already ſhares my Throne. Whence her Ambition is become ſo vain, That from its Aſhes it revives again. PHoTINus. Sir, 'Twas a motive I did not debate, And yet which ought to haſten Pompey's Fate. He your Pretentions doubtleſs will decide, , , And by your Fathers Will your Claims Divide. sº To which great Truſt of Friendſhip being true, You know how much he diſobliges you. Nor that by this Diſcourſe, I would remove The Sacred Ciment of a Brothers Love, I baniſh her not from your Heart, but Throne, For he Reigns not, that does not Reign alone. £ Divided * *

This page contains an image.
Page 10

(10) Divided Empire all wiſe Kings avoid, For Pow'r Communicated is Deſtroy'd ; And Policy.—But, Sir, ſhe does appear. Scen. 3. tº Ptolomy, Cleopatra, Photinus. CLEOPATR A. Pompey is come (Sir) and can you be here, Jº P TO LO M. Y. º That mighty Warriour I at home attend, And him Achillas and Septimius ſend. . . . . CLEOPATR A. º. º. What? ſuch Embaſſadours as thoſe to him? ºf P TO LO M.Y. You may go too, if they too little ſeem. C L E O PAT R. A. Is your own meeting him, too great a thing 2 P TO LO M. Y. " I muſt remember, that I am a King. CLEOPAT R.A. Can you refle&t on that, and yet be ſlow To kiſs the hand of him, that made you ſo *. And pay your homage to a Man ſo great? ºn enº PTO LO M. Y. - - - Did he that Title in Tharſalia get? CLEQ PATRA, . . . . . Though none did his misfortunes help afford, Hee's ſtill that Pompey who your Crown reſtor'd. . . . . . - ----- --- - º ſº PTOLOMY. y -- -- - - - º * -

This page contains an image.
Page 11

- - - - º 6% 3.14 - *... . P+ #6M3. * fluºrºo'ſ Rather his ſhade, and biºmyºther Crowfia, By whoſegiºjºſº. Let him, attéfid'his ſ: ind, e'éðatent""" To receive Thanks, from his cold M nument.ie EijäßRA." Hath ſuch a Benefit ſuch uſage met? . . ) PTOL O MY: , , , I both remember it and º ºn tº 2 -- "GLEQ PATRA - You do indeed but with a cornfull Pride; is ...? ...........}}}.9Mº... i.e., Time is the Ständard by which thiugs are Tryºd; * … ', 1.2.2]º 2.0 ---...-- is a -------- º ****** You, that ſº priz; hinſhay Higréâtneſs Court, A But know, Hè y t Fº in the F 'Ort- ºfioſ, - º CL E. PATR A... son ºf . , J What, may his Shipwrack in the Port, arrive? And have you dar'd his Ruine to contrive. ºp T. O. L. O. M. Y.” ºn ºrdſ: i , "º tº " ". . . . , I have done ºnly whât the Gods inſpirid, sº l And what the ſafety of my State requird-, i. º. C LEOPATRA. . . . . ºluoil I know but too much;P hotin, and his Crew. Aºi Have with their wicked Councels, oyſon'd, you . Souls that are but of Natures ſº " . PHOTINUIS. ... º. The Councel, Madam, will not be diſclaim’d, i.rº ſºº", ºr 'r- - “A rººt º' ---------- -- - " - ...CL E Q PA T.R.A. ſº brº. 'Tis the Kingſthain'ſ diſcuſs with now; Stay then, till'ſ deſcend to talketoyou. . . . © 2 - PTOLOMY. ººV





This page contains an image.
Page 12

(12) - § PT O LO M. Y. You muſt a little with her ſcorn diſpenſe, I know her hatred, and your innocences But ſhe's my Siſter, give her humour vent. - CLEOPATR A. Sir,"If too late it be not to repent, Shake off at length, a Yoke that is ſo vile, And call your Virtue back from her exile: That magnanimity ſo great, and good, Which is convey'd to Princes, with their Blood. PTO LO M. Y. Swell'd with a hope, in vain by you foreſeen, You ſpeak to me of Pompey, like a Queen: Through your falſe zeal, flaſhes of Pride eſcape 3 And Intereſt does ačt in Virtues ſhape: Confeſsit then, you had been ſilent ſtill, Were it not for the King our Fathers Will; You know who kept it? . CLEOPATR A. And you ſhall Know too, Virtue alone prompts me to what I do. - - - -1, *** * - For if I did my own advantage ſeek, I ſhould for Ceſar, not for Pompey ſpeak: , , , Receive a ſecret I conceal’d before, And after that, never reproach me more. , When nonethat bold Rebellion could withſtand, Which rob'd our Father, of his Crown and Land, The injur'd King forſook his Native ſhoar, And Rºme great Senate did for Aid Implore, ºr With him we went, their pitty to engage, 'º - ſº tº , . 1: . . . ; ºr ; -- --- tº ºf wº You very Young; but I was in an Age," " ' " -- º º º -- • * * * * * *-* * * - - When

This page contains an image.
Page 13

(13) . When Nature had ſupply'd my Eyes with Darts, Already A&ive in ſubduing hearts. caſar receiv'd,or elſe pretended love, And by his A&tions, would his Paſſion prove. But ſince the Senat's Pique to him he knew, He their lov'd Pompey, to our party drew. Whoſe high concern for us, on Ceſar's ſcore, Was the laſt fruit their Friendſhip ever bore. Of this you do inherit the event. - But ſuch a Lover not with it content, When by th' aſſiſtance of ſo great a Man, In our behalf the Roman ſuffrage ran, Reſolving further Kindneſs to impart, _* He gave his Treaſure to attend his Heart: And from the bounty of his growing flame, Theſe ſinews both of War and Power came: Thoſe thouſands Talents which we owe him yet, Forc'd our revolted Egypt to ſubmit. On this the King reflecting, when he dy’d Betwixt us did his Dignity divide 3 And by his Sovereign Right, on me beſtow'd A part of what, he to my Beauty ow'd: Whilſt you, who this great reaſon never knew, Thought that his Favour, which was but my due; And Your dread Father, partiall dar'd to calls Who gave me half, when yet he ow'd me all. P TO LO M. Y. - This Story, you with Art enough contrive. CLEOPAT R. A. I am aſſur'd, Caeſar will ſoon arrive. And a few hours will ſuch a change effect, As your Dark Policy did leaſt expect. A * - nel

This page contains an image.
Page 14

(14) And ſhew you why I ſpoke ſo like a Queen, ºv, Who the loath’d Objećt of your ſcorn have been. You in the Throne, uſurp'd my equal ſeat, ºn And as a Slaye you did your Siſter Treat 3 ºr biº Till I was forc’d to ſhun a ruder Fate, ºn tº To ſtoop and Court your Miniſters of State. º Pompey or Caeſar will ſecure me now 5 p. º: And whatſoe're your Sycophants Ordain, ºr 10 º Whoſe ſteel or poyſon, I ſtill fear'd : but Know I now am ſure my Scepter to obtain : º Till when my Pride ſhall leave you, to divine In this Conteſt, what could be my deſign. ºn --- --- ſºil ºf i-l in - - - - - º - f º - Tx . . . --- - º - ------ º Ptolomy, Photin. Tº ºf arº º - - - 'º º bº. ºn 2 PTO LoMY. ºn ºf . ... What think you Photin, of this lofty Mind 2. - PHOT IN. a. º My ſpirit, Sir, to wonder is reſign'd, iſ nº And nothing but amazement can expreſs sº At ſuch a ſecret as I nere could gueſs, My thoughts are ſo unquiet and confus'd, - I ſcarce know what expedient ſhould be us'd, i. º - : º P HO TI-N. ſºlº º Had you that decreed, Yet it were now convenient he ſhould bleed. . . Your Siſter hates you, ſhe is fair and fierce, And if ſhe ſuch Victorious Charmes diſperſe; Shall we ſave Pompey & sº ºn tº ſº. ºf ºn a PTO LO M.Y. ºn º The head of Pompey only, can ſuffice iº To win the heart of Caeſar from her Eyes. ill PTOLOMY. - - -

This page contains an image.
Page 15

(15) º º PTO LOMYºº This dangerous woman hath a buſie wit. - N PHOT IN. But ſuch a ſervice will out-ballance it. º PTO LO M.Y. But what if ceſar ſtill her Pow'r Obey & - PHOT IN. - Then flatter her, yet mind not what I ſay, Till firſt you ask, in an affair ſo Nice, Achillas and Septimius beſt advice. P TO L O M Y. Lets from the Tow'r ſee them ačt Pompey's doom, And this Debate at their return, reſume. After the firſt A&t of Pompey, The King and Photin ſhould be diſcovered, fitting and hearkning to this ſong. S” affairs of the State, are already decreed, k Make room for Affairs of the Court, Employment, and Pleaſure each other ſucceed, Becauſe they each other ſupport. Were Princes confind From ſlackening their Mind, when by care it is rufted and Curl’d, A Crown would appear Too heavy to wear And mo Maz, would govern the World. - - - - - If the Gods themſelves who have power enough, In diverſions are various, and oft". Since the buſineſ of Kings is angry and rough, Their Intervals ought to be ſoft. - Were Princes confin'd, &c. To -

This page contains an image.
Page 16

\ ( 16 J To our. Menarch we ºwe, whatſoer'e we enjoy: And no grateful Subječs were thoſe , - Who wonld not the ſafety, he gives them, employ To contribute to his repoſe. ºf Were Princes confin'd, &c. . . . . . . . . ºil - - - - - After which an Antick dance * * * ... -- " " --------- tº "vº, "º 1 - ... . . . . . . of Gypſies ſhould be preſented. . - - - ----- ----------------- Ağ. 2. Scen. I. -------------, --- -- . Cleopatra, Charmion. C L E O PATR A. | Love him, but a Flame ſo much refin'd, ! How bright ſoever, dazles not my mind: For Virtue makes my inclination know, What Caeſars Miſtreſs does to Pompey owe : And none dares own a paſſion ſo ſublime, But ſhe that ſcorn's the ſhaddow of a crime. I ſhould but ſmal Reſpect to Caeſar pay, To ſeek his love in an unhandſom way. - C H A R M I O N. Can you love Caſar, Madam, and adviſe That Egypt ſhould in Armes againſt him riſe? That they ſhould Pompey againſt him Protećt, And his Pharſalian Triumphs ſhould be checkt, Sure Love in you does little Empire ſhew. CLEOPATR A. This to their high extraćtion Princes owe, - That

This page contains an image.
Page 17

* * * That by th’ Aſſiſtance, of their Royal Blood;’ Their Paſſions are more eaſily ſubdu'd, "º Their honour ſtill the Vićtory will have, And whilſt they truſt themſelves, they ſtill are All the Diſorders, which in Kings we ſee, (brave: To others Counceſs muſt imp ited be.”" . This I the cauſe of Pompey's ruine Deemſ; ſº, cº The King would help, but Photin murthers him.” Whoſe Councel hath his Maſters faith orethrown, Which ſtill had ſway’d, had he obſervd his own: * C H A RM 1 O Nº º ". Youthen who cefar love, and yet oppoſe.” CíEOPATRA: “ lºº The Love I cheriſh no diſhonour knows," " º But worthy him. º - º º ſ *º º - - C H A R M I O N. Modi opiniº riſ C. Are you of his ſecur'd? - C L E O PATR A. . . . I think I am. º gº ºl º * - . º CHA RM IO N. ºººººº º º But are you well aſſur’d £º C L E O PAT R A. Know that a Princeſs by her glory mov’d, | No Love confeſſes till ſhe be belov’d." Nor the moſt noble paſſion ever ſhows, When it ſhall her to a Contempt expoſe, tºº At Rome, I firſt did Caeſars Heart invade, Where he the firſt expreſſion of it made ; And ever ſince, he did to me renew, The Tribute of his Vows and Laurels too. . . . . He march'd through Italy,through Gaule and Spain, With Lovein's Breſt,and fortune in his Train N C Ol' - l ------- -------- - * ,



This page contains an image.
Page 18

/ - (18) - - Nor did he ever make ſobrave a Prize, º, … ºr But hepayd Homāge for it tº theſe Eyes, ". . With the ſame hand, which did that weapon quit, With Blood of Pompey's party recking yet, He writ complaints, and ºut my fetterson, ſº £ºinthéºdºnewly won. " Yes from Pharſilia his ſub - -" - it his ſubmiſſions came, º And if his ſpeed be equal to his flame, Or rather, if the Sea befriend his Fleet, #. ſee himſhortly at my feet. ecomes my Charmion, and from me alone, Seeks the reward of all that he hath done. And all his glory, to my Shrine he brings, With the ſame hand:which gives the law to Kings. So that ev’n in his Triumphs, my diſdain Can make the Man, that rules the World.complain. CH A R M I O N. Yet Idare ſwear, your charmes a pow'r enjoy Which though they boaſt of they will n'ere employ. And the great Caeſar ſhall no trouble know, If it can only from your rigour grow. But what can you expeºt from Ceſars flames, Wherein ſuch right another Woman claims, L. His freedom he by marriage hath reſign'd, ºn And only to Calpêhrmia is confin'd. Tº -- - - iſ ºn - - - CLEOPATR A. -- But a Divorce, at Rome ſo common now, May remove her, and my deſires allow. - - Ceſar's experience him to that may lead, Since 'twas calphurnia's Paſſage to his bed. CHARMION.



This page contains an image.
Page 19

( 19 ) ~ CHA RM IO N. - But the ſame way, may you at length remove, - hº. C LEQP ATR AºA) Perhaps I better ſhall ſecure his love, Perhaps my paſſion may find out an Art Better to manage that Illuſtrious Heart. ºf Bütlét's to Heaven leave what may afrive, ºw Añd this Aliyance (if we can) contrive. Were it but one day, 'twere enough for me, One day, the Miſtreſs of the World to be, ºbº I have Ambition, and bee’t good or ill, oil ſº It is the only Soveraign of my Will. º r - ºil And 'tis this Noble paſſion ſure, or none, ºil A Princeſs may without a Blemiſh own. ºn be But yet with Glory I would it enflame, ºr ºf Nor would buy greatneſs with the loſs of Fame, For I the brighteſt Crown can ſcorn to touch, When 'tis attended with the leaſt Reproach.: sº Wonder not then, that I ſo much purſue oºoº Yº - Pompey's defence, and would my Duty doe: tº His injur’d virtue, ſince I cannot right : º My ſecret Wiſhes muſt invoke his flight...º. That ſome kind ſtorm may ſo his Ships diſperſe, As may preſerve him from his Murtherers, tºº But faithfull Achoreus comes,and he tº nº º Will quickly tell us Pompey's Deſtiny, biº º - tº or º- - - - sºoris wº, º º - - º - º --- º ------ . hº ed ºlºniº ºl. cºil - º - cº º - - - - - - - * Lºº, º sº...". * * : C 3 Scen, 2.

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 20

o) (2. ºf C. M. º. º. ºO Scen, 2 º --- º, - - Cleopatra, Charmion, Achoreur. ºrrºr, irrºr". ~ - ---ſº -- º q gº cle o PATRA: "º What,is it done,and hath ſome Treacherous hand With that Rich blood ſtain’d our unhappy ſtrand 8 ºn A C H OR EU. S. . . . . . . By your commands; I to the ſhore did run, And ſaw this Treaſon, in its Horrour done. º I ſaw the greateſt Mortal looſe his Breath, And though a ſad, I ſaw a glorious Death. And ſince a ſtory you require from me, . . . So much his Honour, and our Infamy : Hear then his fate, and wonder, and bewail, ". ... His three Ships in the Harbour ſtriking ſail, When to our ready Gallies he approach'd, - - - nº sºlº arº º º He thought the King,with his misfortunes touch'd2 By noble ſenſe of Honour, did intend ºº'ſ With all his Court to meet ſo brave a friend.º.º. But when he only ſaw a ſquiffe prepard,' " . And that too fill'd with Ruffians of hi S guard : º Th ingrateful Treachery did then appear;" | And gave him ſome approaches of a fear; º ſº But ſeeing Arm'd Menon our Ships and Shoar," He bluſh'd his Apprehenſions were ſo Poor 5 º' And when the Danger, was ſo near him brought, He only on Cornelia's ſafety thought. “Let's but expoſe, ſayes he, this ſingle head “To a Reception we may ſo much dread. * But

This page contains an image.
Page 21

(21) “But whilſt I only do the ſhocke ſuſtain, * Haſten thy Flight, and my revenge obtain. “King juba is more gen’rouſly inclin'd, “Where thou thy Father, and my Sons ſhalt find: “But if their Deaths ſhould thee of them deprive, “Never Deſpair while cato is alive. . . . . . º While their conteſt on this, was ſad and kind ; ; Achillas fatal boat their Veſſel Joyn'd : &eptimius then, to get him in his Pow'r, Ith Roman Language call'd him Emperour 5 And as deputed from th’ Egyptian Prince, Let, Sir, ſayes he, this barke convey you hence ; The Shelfs and Sands, which under water lye, To greater Veſſels an Acceſs deny. - The Hero ſaw , and ſmil'd at this abuſe 5 He then receiv'd his Wifes and Friends adieus, Their ſtay commanded, and to death did go With the ſame look, as he did Crown's beſtow : '.. With the ſame Majeſty writ in his Brow, sº He ſat unmov’d among his Murtherers now : His ſtedfaſt Courage, did his Condućt ſeem, Philip his Freed-man only follow'd him, - Of whom, what I have told you I did learn, But ſaw the reſt my ſelf with ſad eoncern: tº And think, (ſo mournful it to me appears.) ſº I Caſar himſelf could not refuſe it Tears. ºf - CLEOPAT R. A. - - *. º º • --- º But ſpare not mine, nor let them intercept * A ſtory, which I have already wept. ºil ºf . sº - ºf º ---- ºr t- ºf sh tº ºn. J ----- - º - - - in ºf ºn ACHORELIS, /



This page contains an image.
Page 22

(22 J * * * * * - * A CHOR EU.S. Whilſt toward Land they brought him, not a word To the unhappy Pompey they afford : ºngº In which contempt, he did foreſee his end. iiºdº At length arriv'd, they ask him to deſcend, ſº He Riſing, as Achillas ſtood behind gº iſ . . Drawing his Sword, for what they had deſign'd, Septimius, and three Romans more embrew’d, º Their Guilty hand in that Heroick Blood, ºld Till ev'n Achillas was with horrour ſtrook, bº Upon a Rage ſo Barbarous to look. CLEOPATR A. . . You Gods, who Nations do chaſtiſe with War , i. When you Revenge this Death, our Cities ſpare I And not the place, but Aétors look upon, nº The crime of Egypt was by Romans done. But tell me what this Worthy ſaid, and did. In ſº - º - - -- --- - ºr 3 - - -- ºr lºº º º º A C H OR ELI S. º ". º With his Robes border he his viſage hid, ºn Blindly his cruel Deſtiny obey'd; And would not ſee that Heav'n which him betray'd: Leaſt any look of his, in ſuch a ſtroak, sº pº Should its aſſiſtance, or Revenge invoke: ... tº Not the leaſt poor complaint fell from his Tongue, Or ought that ſpoke him worthy of his wrong: But that deſpiſing made his laſt Retreat ºn To all that in his Life, was good or great :, ºn And held the treaſon,which the King had wrought, Too much below him to imploy his thought. - His



This page contains an image.
Page 23

-- - - - - -- - - - ------> -------------------. (23). , His Virtue, by their crime more brightly ſhone, dº And his laſt Gaſpe, was an Illuſtrious one. ºf . This great Soul fled, his Body did expoſe ºf . To th’ greedy Eyes, of his inhumane Foes : ºO His Head, which tumbled on the bluſhing Deck, A (By vile Septimius ſever'd from his neck.) ºr ºf Upon Achillas lance we fixed ſee, ſº º As after Battles Trophyes uſe to be: And to conclude a Deſtiny ſo ſad, The Sea was all the Sepulcher he had. To fortune now, his ſlaughter'd Corps reſign'd, Floats at the Pleaſure of the Wave and Winde. - The Poor Cornelia at the Dreadfull view. CLEOPATRA. O Gods ! What could ſhe either ſay or do A C H O R. E. Ui S. By dreadful ſhrieks, ſhe try’d his Life to ſhield, Then hopeleſs up to Heav'n her hands ſhe held : And by her mighty ſorrow overthrown, Fell either dead, or in a deadly ſwoon. In this Diſtreſs, her Ships imploy their Oars To gain the Sea, and quit thoſe horrid Shoars. But infamous Septimius having thought ºn Cornelia's flight, rob'd him of half his fault: lº Has with ſix Ships haſten’d to her purſuit, And the dead Pompey ſtill does perſecute. - But whilſt to th’ King Achillas brings the Prize, a The trembling People turn'd away their eyes. ºº One does with horror on the guilt refle&t, lº And a Revenging Earthquake does expect: - This

This page contains an image.
Page 24

(24) This hears it Thunder, and that does believe Nature a Revolution muſt receive. - Their Reaſon, troubled by the Crimes extent, Cannot but dread as vaſt a Puniſhment. Philip mean while ſhews on the River ſide, º - That his mean fortune a brave ſoul did hide. . . He curiouſly examines every wave, º ſº For that rich Pledge,which Treaſon to them gave: That thoſe lov'd Bones he piouſly might burn, - - - • * * - - º' -- And give him one, though an inglorious Urne.' * * - And with a little Duſt, a Tomb ere&t º To him, who did the Univerſe ſubječt. But whilſt Cornelia they one way purſue, Another we might Caeſars coming view, A Navy which can hardly Reckon'd be: C L E O P A T R A. Ne're Doubt it, Achoreus, it is he 5 Tremble bad Men, at your approaching Doom, My Breath is now your Deſtiny become. - Caeſar's come, I'm a Queen, Pompey's reveng'd, Tyranny ruind, and the times are chang'd. “But let's with wonder on the Great reflect; * Pity their Fortune, and our own ſuſpect: He who we thought ev'n Fate her ſelf had ſway’d, Who rul’d a Senate which the World obey'd : Whom his own Rome ſaw ( almoſt Deifi'd ) Over the World's three Parts in Triumph ride; o - - And who in the laſt hazards of his Fate, Saw both the Conſuls on his Standards wait : As ſoon as Fortune one unkindneſs ſhows, Egyptian Monſters of his Life diſpoſe: ºf - And - >

This page contains an image.
Page 25

- - - º - ºr (25 ) C. - º - - * *... ." - - - - - And a Photinus, or septimius, can Govern the Deſtiny of ſuch a Man. A King who ow's him, ev'n the Crown he wears, . Expoſing him to thoſe baſe Flatterers. - - | So fell the mighty Pompey, and ſo may - caſar himſelf perhaps another day. O may the Gods the Augury diſprove And make his Fortune conſtant as my Love. ºch ARM ſo N. The King comes Madam, who may overhear. --> -- - -- ------------ ºffi Gºliº - - - - - L º - -- . - - - - - - . . Scen. 3. - .* -- --- ". - º - - \ . J. : lº bº º jº Ptolomy, Cleopatra. sº bº ------ - - - --- -------- - - - º - P TO LO M. Y. ºl. ii ". . ºf . Know you what happineſs is Drawing near ºn tº C LEO PAT R.A. Yes I have heard it,the great Caeſar's come : ºn And Photin ſhall no more pronounce my Doom : sº a cººp TO LO M.Y. º. - That faithful Subjećt you could ne're endure. A C L E O P.A.T. R. A. errº ºr No, but am from his Projećts now ſecure. º ºº: P T O LO M. Y. Which of his Plots could you ſo much offend ? . º - Bºº ºn C LEO PATR A. ºn tº * I've much endurd, and more may apprehend tº For ſuch a Polititian is not Nice, - And you are alwayes ſteer'd by his Advice. D PTOLOMY.



This page contains an image.
Page 26

(26), * PTOR.S.M.X., .º.º.º. in If I believe him, Ihis prūdéhéé ſee. º ... CLEOPATR.A., And I who fear him, Know his cruelty. ' --- P TO LOMY. - * * º º

º ------ F ---, - ſº For a Crown's ſafety all things juſt appear. , CLEO PATRA. Tº That kind of equity creates my fear, My ſhare of Power hath been by it loſt, " And now it has the head of Pompey coſt. - PTO LO M. Y. * * * * * Never a game of State was more advis'd, tº For elſe by Caſar we had been ſurpris'd : You ſee his ſpeed, and we had been ſubdu'd, Before we could in our defence have ſtood. But now I to a Conquerour ſo great, Your Heart may offer, and my Royal ſeat. C L E O PAT R. A. Make your own Preſents, I'le diſpoſe of mine, Nor others Intereſts with Yours combine. tº ºut PTOLOMY. O Our Blood's the ſame, uniting meland you. . . ºr C L E O PA. T. R. A. º, it. You might have ſaid, our Rank unites us too. ... We both are Soveraigns, yet 'twill be confeſt," ºf . There is ſome Difference in our Intereſt. -- Sº P TO LO M.Y. ºn tº ºn ºf Yes, Siſter, for my Heart is well content Only with Egypt, narrow Continent. ii ººlºº But now your Beauty, cefari Heart does wound, Tagus and Ganges muſt your Empire bound.º.º.

r ------ ºr ºf jon ºf ſºlºis ºf --- ---, ----- ----- i. " * ºil ºn tºº CLEOPATRA, . . . . . . . . . - C

This page contains an image.
Page 27

º - º (27 ) ºlºfi Iliºſ sús ** . . . ºnº C LEºPATRA..." º I have Ambition, but it is confin'd, * It may ſurprize my Soul, but never blind. Tº upbraid me with thoſe bounds there is no need, I know my Reach, and ſhall not that exceed. - PT O LO M. Y. - - - Your Fortune ſmiles and you th' advantage uſe. C L E O P A T R A. You may revile mel, if I that abuſe. PTO LO M. Y. . . . . I hope the beſt, Love no ill Fruit can bear. Cºl E O PA TR.A. - You ſeem to hope, what really you fear. . But though the Gods my juſt pretentions Crown, You need not doube I'leask, but what's my own. You ne're ſhall, Anger from your Siſter find, "..." Though you’r a Cruel Brother, I'le be kind. a is a PTO LO M.Y. " ſº ºn But yet methinks you do diſcover Pride. ejº inº ºf CL EO P A TRA. º * -º Time is the Standard whereby things are try’d. º P T O LO M. Y. IT Your preſent carriage that doth plainly ſhew. tº C LEO PAT-R. A. - º - º - - * - º Ceſar is come and you've a Maſter, now. º tº º ºri. P. T. O EOM Y. º - " - I made him mine who the Worlds Maſter is. C L E O PAT R.A. - Pay him your Homage, while I look for his, In this Addreſs you may your ſelf be ſeen, But Ile remember that I am a Queen. ºr ºil ºf - D 2 Photin



This page contains an image.
Page 28

(28) - Phetin will help you to receive him now, Adviſe with him, heel tell you what's to do. - - -- Aćt. 2. Scen. 4. .." º 'º - º * , - Ptolomy, Photinus PTO L O MY. lºt I have obſerv'd thy Counſel, but find ſince To flatter her, but ſwells her inſolence. For with her Pride ſhe did affront me ſo, That I at laſt fell into Paſſion too. 1 ºf This Arme enrag’d by her, could ſcarce forbear (Without a Thought that Caeſar was ſo near) Diſpatching her (as ſafe as ſhe does ſeem ) o have complain'd to Pompey, not to him. She talks already at that haughty rate; That if great ceſar pleaſe her Pride and Hate, And ſhe o're him her boaſted Empire have, Her Brother and her King muſt be her Slave. No, no, we needs muſt Fruſtrate that intent, Nor poorly wait the Ills we may prevent. Let's ſpoile her of her Power to diſdain, º And break thoſe Charmes whereby ſhe hopes to Nor after ſuch indignities, let's brook, (reign : That ſhe ſhould buy my Scepter with a look. º- -- ~~ º -º- P HO T I NU S, º ºn Do not for Ceſar, Sir, pretence provideº ºil That Egypt ſhould be to his Triumphs Ty'd : - - --- - . . For , , A-1 - º

This page contains an image.
Page 29

(2.9) - For this Ambitious Man which through the world, Hath War and Slavery together hurl’d 5 Swell'd with his Conqueſt, and a Rage ſo ſmart, As ſuch a loſs, writes in a Lovers Heart: - Though you but ačt, what Equity approves, . Will thence ground his revenge for what he loves: As for a crime, Heel you to Bondage bring, Though you did only what became a King, P TO LO M. Y. If Cleopatra ſees him ſhee's a Queen. PHOT IN U.S. But if ſhe dye your Ruine is foreſeen. P TO LO M. Y. Who ruines me ſhould on my fall attend. | To ruine her you muſt your ſelf befriend. - P TO L O M Y. What? muſt my Crown upon her Temples ſhine * No, if my Scepter I muſt needs reſign, The Conquerour ſhall rather it command. P HO TI NUIS. You'l ſooner force it from a Siſters hand. How great ſoever now his flames appear, He muſt be gone, and leave You Maſter here. Love in ſuch Men, ſeldon that room can find, Which to their Intereſt will not be reſign'd. With juba, Scipio, and with Pompey; Sons, - | Spain, to Revenge, he knows, with Affrick runs: And while that Party are not yet o'rethrown, He cannot ſafely call the World his own. Ceſar's too great a Captain, to o'reſee . The Purſuit of pharſalia's Vićtory: tº A. And



This page contains an image.
Page 30

(3o ) And leave ſuch fierce Hearts on revenge intent, *To riſe from their ſolate Aſtoniſhment. If he his ends Obtain, and them o'recom, Lº He his gain'd Empire muſt ſecure at Romeº And there the fruit of his ſucceſs enjoy, fºodſ Whilſt he at pleaſure does her laws Deſtroy. Judge in that time,what great things you may do, See Caſar then,and ſtrive to pleaſe him too. Reſign him all,but yet this Rule intend, That future things on accidents Depend.º.º. Your Throne and Scepter give into his hand, And without murmur yeild to his Command : He will believe that Juſtice he ſhall do If he your Fathers Teſtament purſue 5 aſ Beſides this ſignal ſervice you have done 5 - Will give you ſtill ſome Title to your Throne. Entire ſubmiſſion to his Orders ſhew, Applaud his Judgment, but then let him go. . . That time for our Revenge will be moſt fit ºf When we can Aćt, as well as think of it. --- With temper let theſe Paſſions then be born, Which were excited by your Siſters ſcorn. Boaſts are but Air, and he revenges beſt, Who Aéts his braver Thoughts,yet talks the leaſt. - -- ---------- - P TO L O M Y. O thy Advice my greateſt Comfort brings, A Prudent Counſellour's the bliſs of Kings. Come dear Supporter of my Throne, let's go, And to ſave all, on Ceſar all beſtow. His Pride let's flatter with an empty State, And with our whole Fleet on him hither W.; - After

This page contains an image.
Page 31

(31) After the ſecond Aët, this song is to be ſung by tº two Egyptian Pricſts on the Stage. - EE how Vićtorious Caeſar's Pride J Does Neptune's Boſom ſweep ! Aud with Theſſalian Forfume ride In Triumph o're the Deep. 2. - What Rizal of the God is this - Who dare's do more them they 2 Whoſe Feet the Fates themſelves do kiſs And Sea, and Land obey. I. mhat can the Fortunate withſtand? For this reſºftleſ. He, Rivers of Blood brings on the Land, And Bulwarks on the sea. ** 2. Since Gods as well as Aſem ſubmit, ºr º And Caſar's favour woe, - Virtue her ſelf, may think it fit That Egypt court him too. --- - ºf tº I. But Pompey's Head's a rate to dear, For by that impious price The Godleſ. Noble will appear * Than do's the Sacrifice. ſºlº 2. f A - , ººº-

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 32

(32 2. If juſtice be a thing divine, º º . The Gods ſhould it maintain, For us tº attempt what they decline, - Would be as raſh as vain. º º º . . . . . º º - Chorus. - Bow deſperate is our Princes Fate & What hazzard doe's he run & He muſt be wicked to be great, Or to be juſt, undone. - - * - ". lºº º º ----- Aët. 3. Scen. 1. - - - " * -- * * ------ - Charmion, Achoreus. . . . . . . . . - CHA RMI ON. - --> ". . . . . . . Es, whilſt the King himſelf is gone to meet Ceſar, and lay his Scepter at his Feet. To her Appartment cleopatra went, - And there unmov’d expects his Complement. What words have you to cloath this Humour in 2 º' A CHOR EU S. 'Tis Noble Pride and worthy of a Queen. Who with Heroick courage does make good The Honour of her Rank, and of her Blood. - º - - May -



This page contains an image.
Page 33

- - (33) ) * - May I ſpeak to Her ? ºri º yº ºf gº ºf r: * --- - - ºf No, but ſhe hath ſent Me to enquire this meetings great event. | How caſar on this Gift himſelf explain'd, Whether it were acknowledg'd or diſdain'd. If he the fierce takes, or the gentler way, And what he to our Murtherers could ſay. - A CHORE us. The head of Pempey hath already coſt, More than they will have any cauſe to boaſt : For whether Ceſar be or ſeem ſevere, Yet I for them have ground enough to fear. | If they lov'd Ptolemy, they ſerv'd him ill, You ſaw him part, and I purſu'd him ſtill. When from the City his well order'd Fleet, |Advanc'd a League, that they might Caeſar meet. He with ſpread Sails arriv'd, and as in Wars | He ſtill had been the Favourite of Mars - -, * --- - - - --- ^ **, * 1 - --- - * So Neptune to his Navy was ſo kind , . . . . . . . His Fortune was not fairer than his wind. Our Prince was ſo Aſtoniſh’d when they met, As if he did his Crowned Head forget. ..., Through his falſe Joy his Terrour he Confeſs'd, And all his Aëtions his low Thoughts czpreſs'd, I my ſelf bluſh'd as at a ſhamefull #." There to ſee Ptolomy, but not the King; º º º €eſar who ſaw his Courage thus expire, In pitty flatter'd him to raiſe it higher. A He with low voice offering his Fatal gift, “Now Sir, ſayes he you have no Rival left...º | rº -- E * ' ' " ' " cº What -- ~ -->







This page contains an image.
Page 34

- - - - - - -

(34) º “What in Theſſalia, not the Gods could do, ſº “I give you Pompey and Cornelia too. - “Here's one, and though the other flight did take, . “Six Ships of mine will quickly bring her back. Achillas then the great Head did expoſe, Which ſtill to ſpeak it ſelf ſeem'd to diſpoſe. . . At this new injury ſome warm Remain º º Did in imperfect groans ſeem to complain. " " ' I thought his open mouth and ghaſtly look, Recall'd the Soul which ſcarce her leave had took; And his laſt anger ſeem'd with dying Breath, To charge the Gods with his Defeat and Death. Ceſar ſeem'd Thunder ſtricken at this view, º As not reſolv’d what to believe or do. º Immoveably on that ſad Objećt ty'd ; ; He long from us his inward thought did hide, º And I would ſay if I durſt make a gº, º By what our Nature uſes to expreſs : ...º. Some ſuch malignant Pleaſure he enjoyd, º' º As his offended honour ſcarce deſtroy’d. º. º. That the whole World now in his Power lies, º Could not but bring ſome flattering ſurpr Žeº But though a while this conflićt he endurd, hº Yet his great Soul it ſelfſoon re-aſſurd. * * Though he loves Power, yet he Treaſon hates, Himſelf he Judges, on himſelf debates; ºº, Each Joy and Grief at reaſons bar appears, º At length reſolv’d, he firſt let fall ſome Tears. His Virtues Empire he by force regains, º And Nobleſt Thoughts by that weak ſignexplains. The horrid preſent from his fight expell'd,” pH His Eyes and Hands he up to Heaven Held, gº º I- In

This page contains an image.
Page 35

* *-- In a few words their inſolence repreſs'd, And after did in Penſive ſilence reſt. Nor even to his Romans could reply, º But with a heavy ſigh and furious Eye. ". Sº At laſt with Thirty Cohorts come to Land, To ſeize the Gates and Ports he does command. The Guards he ſet, and ſecret Orders ſent, Shew his Diſtruſt, as well as Diſcontent. Egypt he ſpeaks of, as a Province won, And now calls Pompey not a Foe, but Son. This I obſerv’d. --- a ch A RMI on. * Juſt Oſiris to her Vows inclin'd : * º Whilºt with this happy News to her I fly, Do you preſerve her your Fidelity, \,. A CHORE us. - Ne're doubt it 5 but here ceſar comes, go then Deſcribe the Conſternation of our Men: And whatſoever proves to be their Fate 5 Ile firſt obſerve, and then to her Relate. - - - - ſuit ºn tº - - -* º, ſº - *** - tº º -- --- - - --- - - - - - --- - - - º - - - - - - - - - -- - - - - - º º 2 nº Scen, 2. - º ---------- - - - - ----- -º-º-º-º: --- --- - - - - --- --- - - - - - - -- - - -- --- - --- -- --- --- - º - ºil º º intº ºil - ** 2

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 36

(36) lºº º º Scen, 2. Ceſar, Ptolomy, Lepidus, Photinus, 4 choreus, Roman and Egyptian Souldiers. º tº º PT O LO M. Y. Great Sir, aſcend the Throne, and govern Us. tº *-C AES A R. - º | / Do you Know ceſar, and ſpeak to him thus * / What worſe could envious Fortune offer me & Who alike hate a Crown, and Infamy. . . . . This to accept, would all my Boaſt confute, . That Rome did me unjuſtly Perſecute : (where, Rome; who both ſcorns, and gives Crowns every And nothing ſees in Kings, to love or fear 3 Nay, at our Birth, does all our Souls enflame, To ſlight the Ranke, and to abhor the Name. This truth you might have learn'd from Pompey, If he ſuch Offers lik'd,could ſhun them too. (who Both Throne and King had honour’d been,t' afford Service to him who had them both reſtor'd : So glorious had been even ill ſucceſs, In ſuch a Cauſe, that Triumphs had been leſs : And if your Fortune ſafety had deny'd, ..To have beſtow'd it, had been Caeſars Pride : But though you would not own ſo brave a ſtrife What right had you to that Illuſtrious Life 2 Who



This page contains an image.
Page 37

º Who that rich Blood ºff your hands allow'd, That to the meaneſt Roman ſhould have bow'd 3 Was it for you, Pharſalia's Field I won 3 Wherein ſo many Nations were undone? 'º. - And did I purchaſe at ſo high a Rate, ſº That you ſhould be the Arbiters of Fate?º . If I in Pompey that could ne're admit, Shall you eſcape, o're him aſſuming it 2 - - How much is my Succeſs abus’d by you, º, Who attempt more then ever I durſt do? ºr What Name, think you, will ſuch a blow become, Which has uſurp'd the Soveraignty of Rome 2 And in one Perſon did affront her more, Then could the Aſian Maſſacre before, ºbº Do you imagine I ſhall e're agree nº sº gº You would have been more ſcrupulous for me 3 No, had you Pompey here Vićtorious ſeen, My Head to him had ſuch a Preſent been : I to my Conqueſt your Submiſſions owe, ºn tº When all Wrongs had purſu'd my Overthrow. You do adore the Conquerour, not me 5 º I but enjoy it by Felicity. Dangerous Friendſhip ! Kindneſs to be fear'd l Which turnes with Fortune, and by her is ſteer'd. But ſpeak; this Silence does encreaſe your Sin * º, ºn º º PT O L O M Y. Never hath my Confuſion greater been 5 ºn And I believe, Sir, you’l allow it me, ºn Since I, a King born, now a Maſter ſee: o, .2 Where at my frown, each Mandid tremblingſtand, - And every Word of mine, was a Command 5 . . MOJO’iº . I

This page contains an image.
Page 38

-- (38.) - 'I ſee a New Court, and Another ſway, sº And I have nothing left, but to obey: ºn Your very Look abates my Spirits force 5 º' And can it be regain'd by your Diſcourſe? ºr Judge how I can from ſuch a Trouble ceaſe, A. Which my Reſpects create; and Fears encreaſe: And what can an aſtoniſht Prince expreſs, a Who Anger ſees in that Majeſtique Dreſs 2 And whoſe Amazement,do his Soul ſubdue, That Pompey's Death ſhould be reveng'd by You. Yet I muſt ſay, whatever he beſtow'd, We owe you more, then ever him we ow'd : Your Favour was the firſt to us expreſt, And all he did, was done at your Requeſt 5 s He did the Senate move for injur'd Kings ºn And them that Paayer to our Aſſiſtance brings But all that He for Egypt could obtain, ºr Without your Mony, Sir, had been in vain: By that his Rebels our late King ſubdu'd, And you have Right to all our Gratitude :- We Pompey as your Friend and Son rever'd, But when he your Competitour appear'd, When of your Fortune he ſuſpicious grew, sº Tyranny ſought and dar'd to fight with you------- tº ºvoº gº tº fºllº, º C E SAR. Forbear, your hatreds Thirſt his Blood ſupplies, Touch not his Glory, let his Life ſuffice; Say nothing here that Rome ſtill dares deny, But plead your Cauſe without a Calumny.



PTOLOMY.

This page contains an image.
Page 39

(39); * -- * * sºng 2 giºiºſº dº ſº of ºil bº 3. viº, P TO LOM Y. ºn ſaid toº º Then let the Gods be judges of his Thought 3- º I only ſay, That in the Wars laſt fought, To which ſo many Wrongs did you perſwade, Our Vows for your ſucceſs were only made: ". And ſince he ever ſought your Blood to ſpill, I thought his Death a neceſſary Ill. " For as his groundleſs Hatred daily grew, º He would, by all wayes, the Diſpute renew 5. Or if at length, he fell into your Hand (ſtand: We fear'd your Mercy would your Right with." For to that Pitch your ſenſe of Honour flies, As would to Fame your Safety Sacrifice; Which made me Judge, in ſo extream an Ill, We ought to ſerve you, Sir, againſt your will;" My forward Zealth occaſion did embrace, º Without your leave, and to my own diſgrace : And this you as a Crime in me diſclaim, º But nothing done for you deſerves that Name: Iſtain'd my Hands, your Danger to remove, Which Aët you may enjoy, and diſapprove 3 Nay by my Guilt, my Merit higher growes; Since I my Glory gave for your Repoſe And by that greateſt Vićtim have procur'd tº Your Glory and your Power to be aſſurd. ed sº ºncºſ', ºi nº ºn tº ... Bºlº'ſ CAESAR. an ºn nº º You employ, Ptelomy, ſuch Crafty Words, And weak Excuſes as your Cauſe affords; º' . Your Zeal was falſe, if twere affraid "to ſee gº º what all Manūrābegåøfiegod, mould "...a º And, - -- -

This page contains an image.
Page 40

- - º - O ) / And did to you ſuch ſubtilties Convey, As ſtole the Fruit of all my Wars away; Where Honour me engagd, and where the end iſ Was of a Foe ſubdu'd, to make a Friend; Where the worſt Enemies that I have met, - When they are conquer d, I as Brother Treat : And my Ambition only, this Deſign'd o lº To Kill their Hate, and force them to be kind 5 How bleſt a Period of the War ’t had been, sº If the glad World had in one Chariot ſeen brown º Pompey and Ceſar at once to have ſate ºf ºf 10. Triumphant over all their former Hate! gº º Theſe were the Dangers you fear'd ſhould befali 5.4 O fear Ridiculous! and Criminal lºgº ºf 'oºz A. You fear'd my Mercy,but that trouble quit, ſºlº And, wiſh it rather 5 you have need of it, sº sº, For I am ſureſtić ſuffice would conſent iwi. I ſhould appeaſe Rome with your puniſhment. Miſſºſ Not your Reſpečis, nor your Repentance now; a No nor your Ranke, preſerves you from that Blow: Ev’n on your Throne I would revenge your Guilt, But cleopatra's Blood muſt not be ſpilt: º, ºn Wherefore your Flatterers only I condemn 5 ºf And muſt expect you'l dome Right on them: tº For what in this I ſhall obſerve you do, sº *4 pº Muſt be the Rule of my Eſteem for you : oº lºor To the great Pompey Altars now erect, And to him pay, as to the Gods, Reſpect. By Sacrifices your Qffenſe expell; ... º. ºf But have a Qare you chooſe your Vićtims well...na Go then, and whilſt you do for this prepare, squoy I muſt ſtay here about another Care. M., ºw briſ, - - Scen. 3.

This page contains an image.
Page 41

- - - - - - ---, -, ----------- --- - - ºf --- - ºgild coſº S.r.º., ºn tº itſ ºr ºn - ºf ºceh, 3. . - - -, -, -, -º - º, ºr ºn tº - º º --- - . ſººn sº ºf º º º wo * º zºº, #. A º. L º d º º - º Cºſº, ntoniſtſ, Lépiduſ. - º -- º * - - - - - lºº-º- A CAES A R. Antonius, have you this bright Princeſs ſeen? ANT ON I U.S. Yes, Sir, I have, and ſhee's a matchleſs Queen; With ſuch proportion Heaven never yet - All Beauties both of Minde and Body knit 5 So ſweet a Greatneſs in her Face does ſhine, The Nobleſt Courage muſt to it reſign 5 º' Her Looks and Language with ſuch eaſe ſubdue, If I were caſar, I ſhould love her too. ººlºº, º - ºdºº gº C AES A R. ºilº Jºli How was the Offer of my Love receiv'd £º A N T ON I U. S. As doubted, and yet inwardly believ'd : She modeſtly declin'd her higheſt aims, ºil And thinks ſhe Merits, what ſhe moſt diſclaims..., - ºf CAESA R. o But can I hope her love 3 A N TO N I UI S. - Can ſhe have yours? As that your Joyes, ſo this her Crown ſecures. To gain that Heart can you believe it hard, Whoſe kindneſs you with Empire can reward : Then let your Paſſion all its Doubts disband, For what can Pompey's Conquerour withſtand 2 - * * * **, *, * --- , ºº, - - -- - - --- - - - is ºl. Yº F But

This page contains an image.
Page 42

(42) But yet her Fear to her remembrance brings, How little Rome hath ever valu'd Kings 3 And more then that, ſhe dreads Calphurnia's Love; But both theſe Rubs your preſence will remove, And your ſuccesfull Hope all Miſts will break, If you vouchſafe but for your Self to ſpeak. CAE S A. R. Let's go then, and theſe needleſs ſcruples quit, Shewing my Heart to Her that wounded it: Come let us ſtay no longer. A N T ON IUI S. - But firſt know, €ormelia is within your Power now : Septimius brings her, boaſting of his Fault, And thinks by that, he hath your Favour bought. But once aſhoar your Guards (by Orders taught) No notice took, but hither both have brought. CAES A R. º Then let her enter : Ah unwelcome News Which my Impatience does ſo roughly uſe ! O Heaven l and am I not allow'd to pay My Love this ſmall remainder of one day?… nº Scen, 4.

This page contains an image.
Page 43

- (43) - Scen. 4. Caſar, Cornelia, Antonius, Lepidus, Septimiur. -- -- ------- - º - - - - --- SEPTIMI U. S. CAE S A. R. Go Septimius for your Maſter look, Caeſar a Traytors preſence cannot Brook 3 A Roman, who to ſerve a King could be Content, when he had Pompey ſerv'd, and me. - [Exit Septimiu, CORN ELIA, - Ceſar, that envious Fate which I can brave, Makes me thy Priſoner, but not thy Slave: Expect not then my Heart ſhould ere afford To pay thee Homage, or to call thee Lord: How rude ſoever Fortune makes her Blow 5 I Craſſus Widow once, and Pompey's now 5 - Great Scipio's Daughter, (and what's higher yet) A Roman, have a Courage ſtill more great 3 And of all Stroaks her Cruelty can give, Nothing can make me bluſh, but that I live, And have net follow'd Pompey, when he dy'd 3 For though the Means to do it were deny'd, And Cruel Pity would not let me have The quick aſſiſtance of a Steel or Wave, Yet I’m aſham'd, that after ſuch a Woe, Grief had not done as much as they could do : F 2 Death Sir.



This page contains an image.
Page 44

- - - Death had been glorious, and had ſet me free As from my Sorrow then, ſo now from Thee. Yet I muſt thank the Gods, though ſo ſevere, That ſince I muſt come hither, Thou art here: That Ceſar reigns here, and not Ptolomy 3 And yet, O Heaven what Stars do governme? That ſome faint kind of ſatisfačtion'tis, To meet here with my greateſt Enemies 3 And into their Hands that I rather fall, Then into His that ow'd my Husband all. . . . But of thy Conqueſt, Ceſar, make no boaſt, Which to my ſingle Deſtiny thou ow'ſt 5 I both my Husbands Fortunes have defac'd, And twice have caus’d th' whole World to be diſ. My Nuptial Knot twice ominouſly ty'd, (grac'd 5 Baniſh'd the Gods from the Uprighter Side; Happy in miſery I had been, if it, . For Romes advantage, had with Thee been Knit 3 And on thy Houſe that I could ſo diſpenſe All my own Stars malignant influence: For never think my Hatred can grow leſs, Since I the Roman Conſtancy profeſs; And though thy Captive, yet a Heart like mine, Can never ſtoop to hope for ought from Thine: Command, but think not to ſubjećt my Will, Remember this, I am cornelia ſtill. CAESAR. O Worthy Widow of a Man ſo brave Whoſe Courage, Wonder, Fate does pity crave; Your generous Thoughtsdo quickly make us know To whom your Birth;to whom your Love you owe; And, º

This page contains an image.
Page 45

(45) And we may find, by : Hearts glorious frame, Both to, and from what Families you came 5 ºn 1 Young craſſus Soul, and noble Pompey's too, Whoſe Virtues Fortune cheated of their due 5 The scipio's Blood, who ſav'd our Deities, Speak in your Tongue, and ſparkle in your Eyes; And Rome her ſelf hath not an ancient Stem,(them: Whoſe Wife or Daughter, hath more honour’d Would to thoſe Gods your Anceſtors once ſav'd, When Hannibal them at their Altars brav'd, That your dear Hero had declin'd this Port, And better known a falſe Barbarians Court; And had not his uncertain Honour try’d, But rather on our Ancient love rely’d 5 That he had ſuffered my ſuccesfull Arms, Only to vanquiſh his unjuſt Allarms; tº Then he, without deſtruſting me, had ſtay'd Till he had heard what Ceſar could have ſaid 5 And I, in ſpight of all our former ſtrife, Would then have beg'd him to accept of Life; Forget my Conqueſt, and that Rival love, Who fought, but that I might his Equal prove : Then I, with a content entirely great, Had Pray'd the Gods to Pardon his Defeat 3 And giving me his Friendſhip to poſſeſs, He had pray'd Home to É; {ucceſs. But ſince Fate, ſo Ambitious to deſtroy, Hath rob'd the World, and Us, of ſo much Joy, Ceſar muſt ſtrive tº acquit himſelf to you, - Of what was your Illuſtrious Husbands due: Enjoy your ſelf then with all freedom here. Only two dayes my Priſoner appear ; ; And ¥11

This page contains an image.
Page 46

46.) - And witneſs be, how after our Debate, a tº I ſhall revere his Name, revenge his Fate; You this Account to Italy may yield, What Pride I borrow from Theſſalia's Field, I leave you to your ſelf, and ſhall Retire 5 - - º º- Lepidus, furniſh her to her deſire; As Roman Ladies have reſpected been, So Honour her, (that is, ) above a Queen. Madam, command 5 all ſhall your Orders wait. --- lººk ºf O Gods how many Virtues muſt I hate º, sº tº --- After the third Aët, to Cornelia aſleep on a Couch, Pompey's Ghoſt ſings this in Recitative Air.º. º º - -- - - - From laſting and unclouded Day, From joys refin’d above Allay, And from a ſpring without decay. - - ---- --- º I come, by Cynthia's borrow'd Beams º To viſit my Cornelia's Dreams, And give them yet ſublimer Theams. ºutlºº º º Behold the Man, thou lov’dſt before, Pure ſtreams have waſh'd away his Gore, tº And Pompey now ſhall bleed no more. ------ ----- º º º - By Death my Glory I reſume 5. … For twowld have been a harſher Boom . . Tº outlive the Liberty of Rome. º By -. CoRN ELIA.

This page contains an image.
Page 47

- - - - ... (47) º - --- - - ºilº, º ºf vºllº ºn tº . . . . . -- By me her ºft. fortune try’d, - Falling, bequeaths my Fame this Pride, I for it liv'd, and with it Dy'd. º º, º ºr, - --- a --- . . ." ºnor ſhall my Wengeance be withſtood º -- - - - - º, Orumattended with a Flood, of Roman and Egyptian Blood. * Caeſar himſelf it ſhall purſue, His dayes ſhall troubled be, and few, And he ſhall fall by Treaſon too. He, by ſeverity Divine - shall be an offering at my Shrine 5 As I was his, he muſt be mine. Thy ſtormie Life regret no more, For Fate ſhall waft thee ſoon a ſhoar, º ºn And to thy Pompey thee reſtore. lºſt ºf º º -: -- - - inhere paſt the fears of ſad removes º * We'l entertain our ſpotleſ: Leves, - l, lºſºl ºf ſº, .ºr jºº "º *I* beauteau; , and Immortal Groves, ſº ".. ºil; ºiſi Cºº ſº ſº ſº. ººliº There mone a Guilty grown ſhall wear, Nor Czſar be Dićtator there. Nor ſhall Cornelia ſhed a Tear. : ºº hiſtº ºbº (miºſ ºn tº ºf wººid dº no wº tº hiſ gº ºlding ºn tº gº -- - After º - - - - -- - -



This page contains an image.
Page 48

(48); After this a Military Dance, as the continuance. of her Dream, and then cornella ſtarts up, as waken'd in amazement, ſaying, sº - sº sº ". **** ". --> º * * * - º º - º, º . . . . ". - What have I ſeen 3 and whether is it gone How great the viſion 1 and how quickly done! Tet if in Dreams me future things can ſee, There's ſtill ſome joy, aid up in Fate for ms. "Y- º ºx, ...", it. -º-º: º º º, - º º º .." iº º Exºt ... º. - - * * * - - --> tº º, . ºººººººº. - - ------ - - - --- - ---. -- - - - º -- º --- º ----- cº, tº tº ºn --- ºAği. 4. Scén. Lºº. - .nº º ºxº º º *** * * *- Ptolomy, Achillas, Photinuſ. . º, º 'º º P T O LO MY. *** * * * ºvº, "º", * * * ******A* or º, . . - * * * * * * (which had W Hat 2 with that Hand, and with that Sword A Vićtim of th’ unhappy Pompey made, Saw yºu &eptimius, fled from Ceſar; hate, Give ſuch a bloody Period to his Fate?’ ºwa CHILLAs.ºr ..º. º.º.º. tº vº. He's Dead, Sir, and by that you may collect, What ſhame (foreſeen by him) you muſt expect: Caeſar you may by this ſlow anger know, The violent does quickly come and go: --------- T --- - º A. - But

This page contains an image.
Page 49

- º 3) But the conſider'd Indignation grows Stronger by Age, and gives the fiercer Blows; - - In vain you hope his Fury to aſſwage, or ºf .25 ſ Who now ſecure, does Politickly rage 3 iſ ſº cººl He ſafely for his Fame concern'd appears, Eſkº Pompey, alive, abhor'd; he dead reveres: ºº ºff tº And of his Slaughter by this Art doth chooſe, º ºſ. To act the vengeance, and yet make the uſe. * * -- ºn ºf ºilº tº P TO LO M.Y. ºn tº Had I believ’d Thee, I had never known vºw ºf T A Maſter here, nor been without a Throne: oº “But ſtill with this Imprudence Kings are curſt, “To hear too much Advice,and chooſe the worſt; “At the Pits brinke Fate does their Reaſon blind; “Or if ſome hint,they of their Danger find, “Yet that falſe Light amiſs their Judgment ſteer's, “Plunges them in,and then it diſappears. - -- ºn PHOT IN U.S. A dº I muſt confeſs I caſar did miſtake," º º Since ſuch a Service he a Crime does make: ; But yet his ſide hath ſtreams, and thoſe alone º' Canexpiate your fault, and fix your Throne. I no more ſay, you filently ſhould bear, sº . And your Revenge, till he be gone, defer tº º No, I a better Remedy eſteem. . . " ". To juſtifie his Rivals Death, on him.º.º. When you the Firſt Aćt, by the laſt make good, -- And céſar's ſhed, as well as Pompey's Blood, º Rome will no difference in her Tyrants' know, But will to you, from both, her Freedom owe. - º G PTOLOMY. º -



This page contains an image.
Page 50



O * * * ...? * bºugh ºn tº ºld, PT Ó LO M.Y. ºn Yes, Yes, to this all Reaſons do perſwade; Let's fear no more the Greatneſs we have made : Caeſar ſhall ſtill from Us receive his Doom, ºn And twice in one day weel diſpoſe of Rome 5 ºn As Bondage firſt, let's Freedom next beſtow ; - Let not thy Aëtions, Caſar, ſwell Thee ſo 5 But call to mind what thou haſt ſeen me doe; Pompey was Mortal, and ſo thou art too 5 Thou envy'dſt him, for his exceeding thee, And I think, thou haſt no more Lives, then he 3 Thy own Compaſſion for his Fate, does ſhew That thy Heart may be Penetrable too: Then let thy Juſtice threaten as it pleaſe, 'Tis I, muſt with thy Ruine, Rome appeaſe; iº And of that Cruel Mercy Vengeance take, ºf . Which ſpares a King, but for his Siſters ſake. My Life and Power ſhall not expoſed be To her Reſentment, or thy Levity 3 Leaſt thou, to morrow, ſhould ſtat, ſuch a Rate in Reward her Love, or elſe revenge her Hate: º More noble Maximes ſhall my Fears expell 5 Thou bad'ſt me once to chooſe my Victims well, And my Obedience thou in this ſhalt ſee, ºn on Who know no Vićtim worthier then thee, ºr bun North Immolation of whoſe Blood,will draw dº Better Acceptance from thy Son in law. . . But vainly, Friends, we this foment our Rage, Unleſs we knew, what Strength we could engages, All this may be unprofitable heat, his entiºn The Tyrants Forces being herefogreat; ſº Yº ſº º, But

This page contains an image.
Page 51

- (51) But of our Power let us be firſt agreed, And in what time and me 6d to proceed. . tº hºliº ºil of it iſ sº tºo tigii: A CHILL AS.5 iſſon ºnomi, We may do much; Sir, in out preſent State,º Two miles from hence fix thouſand Souldiers wait; Which I, foreſeeing ſome new Diſcontents, º Have kept in fºliº; s, for all Events'; 'º Ceſar with all his Af s, could not foreſee º; That underneath this ſown a vault ſhould be; By which this night we to the Palla emay º Our Men with Eiſe, and without Noiſe convey; Tº aſſault his Life by open force alone, 'º r- Would be the only way to looſe § #9Wn;º We muſt ſurprizé him, and #& 6trºdeſign, º' when he iºfunk with pleafire Lovčá wine. The People are all ours; for when he made His entry, Horrour did their Soulsinyades,V, oº When with a Pomp ſo arrogantly grave, His Faſces did our Royal Enſigns brave 5 I mark'd what Rage at that Injurious view, From their incenſed Eyes, like ſparkles, flew ; And they ſo much did with their füry ſtrive, That your leaſt Countenance may it revive. septimius Souldiers fill'd with greater hate, Struckwith the Terrour of their Leaders Fate, Seek nothing but revenge on him, who them nº Did, in their Captains Perſon, ſo contemn. biºp TOL O MY...a blºod ºf But what way to approach him can be found ! Ifat the Feaſt his Guards do him ſurround 3 r G 2 PHOTINUIS.

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 52

bestºs .…............ oºoººººº. gººd º 'º','!' … ºbº cornelia's Men, who have already known Among your Romans Kindred of their own, Seem. ... us they would help afford To Sacrifice their Tyrant, to their Lord; C - L. Lºw - - - - - > - Nay have aſſurd it, and much better mayº Then we, to Caeſar the firſt ſtabs convey 5 ºil His Clemency ( not only falſe but vain) ºn Which Courts Cornelia, that He Home may gain, Will to his Perſon, give them ſuch acceſs, As may aſſure our Plot of a ſucceſs. Mºo But Gleºpatra comes 3 to Her appear, ºn I eſs'd with Weakneſs, and with Fear ºf w aw Sir, for you know that we ºf Are Objećts,ſhe will much abhor to ſee. , , ºr º T.I., z TT T. --- - ºf a PTO LO M.Y. ºn Go wait me.--— ſº bibºriotº it. - º ºgºgº ºn tº sºciº Scen: 2.11no bibºº cit ºf gººgº ºn 3 - º, ſº º P º º - - i. s: Ptolomy, Cleopatra. ºn tº !y, º lº it. 4. ºf bº º, , , , , , , , , , ), tº lººd C LE OP A.T.R.A.. º * * * * * r ... . . . :---- - lºº , - Brother, I have ceſar ſeen, And have to him your Interceſſour been. ºp TO E. O MY." Tºſi, ſº biºl I never could expect an Aćt leſs kind From, you who bear ſo generous a Mind... ºn - ºn mºſt º aid * But … iſ CHSJ gº tº - . - - - ------ ſºº'ſ º





This page contains an image.
Page 53

-- 53) - - But your great 1.4 *, from you went. C L E O PA T.R. A. Twas to the Town, tº appeaſe ſome diſcontent, Which he was told had newly raiſed been Betwixt the Souldier and the Citizen : Whilſt I with Joyfull haſt come to aſſure You, that your Life and Kingdom were ſecure ; Th’ Illuſtrious Cæſar on the Courſe you took, - Does with leſs anger then Compaſſion look, He pitties you, who ſuch vile States-men heard, - As make their Kings not to be lov’d, but fear'd : Whoſe Souls the baſeneſs of their Birth confeſs, And who in vain great Dignities poſſeſs: For Slaviſh Spirits cannot guide the Helm 3 Thoſe too much Power would quickly overwhelm. - That hand, whoſe Crimes alone do purchaſe Fear, Will ſoon let fall a Weight it cannot bear. - P TO LO M. Y. Thoſe Truths, and my ill Fate do me perſwade How bad a choice of Counſellours I made : For had I ačted Honourable things, I had as Glorious been, as other Kings 5. And better merited the Love you bear A Brother, ſo unworthy of your Care 5 Caſar and Pompey had been here agreed, And the Worlds Peace in Egypt been decreed 5 - - Who her own Prince a friend to both had ſeen; - Nay, he perhaps, an Arbiter had been. - But ſince to call this back is paſt our Art, Let me diſcharge to you my Troubled heart 3 You, that for all the Wrongs that I have done, Could yet Preſerve me both my Life and Crown; - Be --~~ - s º

This page contains an image.
Page 54

(54) º - - - - - -- º º - Be truly great and vanquiſh all your Hate, By changing Photin's and Achilla's Fate. -- For their offending you, their Death is due, But that my Glory ſuffers in it to 3 ºn tº If for their Kings Crimes they ſhould puniſh'd be, The Infamy would wholy light on me; Caeſar through them wounds me, their's is my Pain For my ſake, therefore, your Juſt Hate conſtrain : Your heart is Noble, and what pleaſure then Is th’ abjećt Blood of two unhappy Men Pº º Let me owe all to you, who Caſar charme, And, with a Look, his Anger can diſarm. - º ºf tº º tº C L E O PA TR. A. ººl Were but their Life and Death in me to give, My ſcorn is great enough to let them live : But I with Caeſar little can prevail, º When Pompey's Blood lyes in the other ſcale; I boaſt no Power to Diſpoſe his will, tº toº For I have ſpoke, and he hath ſhun'd it ſtill, wº And turning quickly to ſome new Affair, º He neither does refuſe, nor grant my Prayer: Yet Ile once more on that harſh Theam proceed, In hope a New attempt may better ſpeed sº A And Ile believe.— ºn º tº º º, - ſº. ºn tº PTO LO M. Y. * - nº - - T-- º He comes, let me be gone, º' Leaſt I ſhould chance to draw his anger on 5 'º'; . My preſence may enflame what twould make leſs, And you alone, may ačt with more ſucceſs. * * - ſº ". . . . . - tº oil -- -- º --- - Scen. 3.

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 55

(55) - scen: 3. Ceſar, Cleopatra, Antoniuſ, Lepidus, Charmion, Achoreus, and Romans. CAE S A. R. The City now is quiet, Beauteous Queen, Which had alarm'd with little reaſon been 5 Nor need they fear the troubleſome event Of Souldiers Pride, or Peoples Diſcontent : But O great Gods.! when abſent from your Eyes, A greater Tumult did within me Riſe 5 - When theſe unwelcom Cares ſnatcht me from you, My heart, ev'n with my Grandeur, angry grew 5 And I my own Renown began to hate, Since it my parting did neceſſitate : Put I forgave all to the ſingle Thought How much advantage to my Love it brought : For tis to that, I owe the noble Hope Which to my Flame does give ſo fair a ſcope, And perſwades Caſar that his Heart may prove Not utterly unworthy of your Love, And that he may pretend to that, ſince he Nothing above him, but the Gods, can ſee. Yes Queen; if in the World a Man there were That with more glory could your fetters bear Or if there were a Throne, wherein you might By Conquering its King, appear more bright. - Leſs

This page contains an image.
Page 56

- 56 Leſs for his Throne wº R. Man purſue, Then to diſpute the Right of ſerving you. 'Twas to acquire that valuable Right, That my Ambitious Arm did alwayes fight, ºs. And in Pharſalia rather my Sword drew To Preſerve that, then Pompey to ſubdue. I Conquer’d, and the God of Battles, leſs Then your bright Eys, afforded me ſucceſs. They rais'd my Courage, and my hand did ſway, And I owe them that memorable day. As the effect of heat by them inſpir'd, tº For when your beauties had my paſſion fir’d, That a return might your great Soul become, They made me Maſter of the World and Rome. I would ennoble that high ſtile I wear, * - / 'By the Addition of your Priſoner. º, And ſhall moſt happy be, if you think fit º' That Title to eſteem, and this permit. C L E O P A T R A. I know how much I to my fortune owe, " . Which this exceſs of Honour does beſtow. " Nor will from you my inward thoughts conceal Since I know both, you, and my ſelf ſo well. -- Your Love did in my earlieſt Youth appear, ºt And I my Scepter as your Preſent wear’: ºº I twice receiv'd my Kingdom from your Hand, And after that, can I your Love withſtand 2 No, Sir, my Heart cannot reſiſt your ſiege, Whoſo much merit, and ſo much Oblige. . . But yet my Birth, my Ranke, and the Command Which I have now regain'd in Egypt, Land, T - - he

This page contains an image.
Page 57

(57 ) The Scepter, by your Hand reſtor'd to mine, Do all againſt my innocent Hopes combine 5 . To my deſires injurious they have been, And leſſen me, by making me a Queen: , , For if Rome ſtill be as ſhe was before, T. aſcenda Throne, will but debaſe me more 5 Theſe Marks of Honour will be but my Shame : And Ruine my Pretences to your Flame : But yet, methinks, the Power you enjoy, º Might all my Fears with eaſe enough deſtroy, And I would hope, that ſuch a Man as you, May juſtly Romes Capriciouſneſs ſubdue, And her unjuſt averſion for a Throne ºf She might ſee cauſe, for your ſake, to diſown : I know that you can greater things effect, And from your Promiſe Wonders I expect 5 You in Pharſalia did much greater do, And I invoke 1103 other Gods but You. --- -- CAE SAR. There's nothing humane can my Love withſtand; 'Tis but the overrunning Affrick Land, To ſhew my Standards to the reſt of thoſe, Who did me with ſo ill a Fate oppoſe 3 And when Rome can no more of them Advance, She will be forc'd to ſtudy Complaiſance: And you ſhall ſee her with a ſolemn State, At your Feet ſacrifice her Pride and Hate : Nay I muſt have her, at your Royal Seat, In my behalf, your Favour to entreat 3 And with ſo much Reſpečt theſe Beauties view, That ſhe young Ceſars ſhall requeſt from yº ſ - H - This - -

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 58

(58) This is the only Fortune I deſire, And all to which my Lawrels do aſpire: How bleſt were my Condition, if I might - Obtain thoſe Wreaths, and ſtill enjoy your ſight ! But yet my Paſſion its own harm procures, For I muſt quit you, if I will be yours; While there are flying Foes, 1 muſt purſue, That I may them defeat, and merit you. To bear that abſence therefore, ſuffer me . To take ſuch Courage from the Charmes I ſee, That frighted Nations may, at Ceſars name, Say, He but came, and ſaw, and overcame. CLEOPATR A. This is too much 5 but if I this abuſe, The fault which you create you muſt excuſe: You did my Crown, and perhaps Life reſtore, And yet your Love (I truſt) will grant me more; And I Conjure you, by its ſtrongeſt Charms, By that great Fortune which attends your Arms, By all my hopes, and all your high Deſert, Dip not in Blood the Bounties you impart 3 Great Sir, forgive thoſe that have Guilty been, Or elſe by that, let me appear a Queen 5 Achillas and Photimus blood diſdain, For they endure enough, to ſee mereign; And their Offenſe tº GAESA R. - - Ah! by ſome other way Aſſure your ſelf how much my Will you ſway º - . 3 As

This page contains an image.
Page 59

(59) As you Rule me, if I might you requeſt, You better ſhould imploy your Intereſt 5 Govern your Céſar, as a lawfull Queen, And make him not Partaker of their Sin: For your ſake only, I the King durſt ſpare; 'Twas love alone that— Scen. 4. To them Cornelia. C OR N E L I A. Caeſar, have a Care. - For Traytors have againſt thy Life Combin'd, And ſworn thy Head ſhall be to Pompey's Joyn'd. If to prevent them thou ſhouldſt be remiſs, Thy Blood will ſpeedily be mixt with his. If thou my Slaves examine, thou may'ſt know, The Author, Order, and the Aétor too. I yield them thee 3 CAESA R. O truly Roman Heart! And Worthy him, of whom you were a part 1 His Soul, which ſees from its exalted State, How I endeavour to Revenge his fate, Forgets his hate, and is become ſo kind, To ſave my Life, by what he left behind. Whatever Treaſon could to Pompey do, Yet he does ſtill ſubſiſt, and ačt in you: And prompts you to a thing ſo brave, that he May vanquiſh me in generoſity. H 2 CORNELIA,

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 60

cºs) º º - CO R N E L I A. Ceſar, thou art deceived in my intent, If you think'ſt Hate yields to acknowledgment: No, Pompey's blood muſt all commerce deny, Betwixt his Widow and his Enemy. And I thy offer'd Freedom would enjoy, That to thy Ruine I might it employ. Nay, I ſhall make new buſineſs for thy Sword, If thou dra'st be ſo Juſt to keep thy word. But though ſo much on thy Deſtruction bent, Yet I thy Murther would as much prevent. I have thy Death, with too much Juſtice ſought, That it ſhould now, be with a Treaſon bought. Who knows and ſuffers, does partake the guilt : Nor ſhould thy blood be infamouſly ſpilt. But when my Husbands Sons, and Kindred do Attempt thy death, then I ſhall wiſh it too. And that ſome brave Arm, which I ſhall excite, May in the Field, and in thy Armies ſight, Offer thee Nobly to that Hero's Ghoſt, In whoſe Revenge thou ſo much zeal beſtoweſt ? My reſtleſs thirſt for ſuch a day as this, By thy untimely fall its end would miſs. But whatſoe're hopes from abroad I may Receive, yet I am Rack'd by their delay. * For diſtant ſatisfaction is half loſt : “And long expected Joys too dearly coſt. I ſhall not wander on the Affrick Strands 5 To ſeek the vengeance ready in thy hands, Which does the head it Threatens beſt befit: For I could thine have had inſtead of it; * - - , , --, -- But tº º - --

This page contains an image.
Page 61

(61). gº) But that my hatred ſaw the difference great, Betwixt my Husbands murther and defeat : And I an earlier Puniſhment would ſee On their Preſumption, then thy Vićtory. This is Romer wiſh, Whoſe Venerable Brow To this affront, too juſt a Bluſh would owe : If her two Nobleſt heads ſhould ( after all Her Triumphs ) with ſo much diſhonour fall. Shee, upon whom thou never couldſt impoſe, Would ſooner Puniſh Criminals, then foes. Her Liberty, would a misformune grow, If upon Tiber Nile ſhould it beſtow. None but a Roman could her Maſter be, - And but a Roman none ſhould ſet her free. Here thou wouldſt fall to her unſacrific'd : And wouldſt be murther'd ſo, but not chaſtis'd. Nof would ſucceeding Tyrants frighted be, For the Example too, would dye with Thee. f Revenge her thou, on Egypt, wrong, and I Will her revenge upon Pharſalia try. . . . Adieu, no time in this ſhould waſted be, Go then, and boaſt I once made vows for thee. , - - º º -- \ - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - --- - - " . -- - ! --- -º ºr - - - * - --- - - - - - - - --- -- - º -- - º - - - -- - - - - -------- - - - - - - - --- - - - --- ----- - - - -- º - - º - - -- ------ - - - -- - -- - - - - - - º - - º - º --- -- - - - - - - - - - * º --- -- - - - - - -- - - ----, -º tº tº . - - is '. --- - º ------ - - - - o - - - - --- - - - - t - --- - "- -- - - - - ----------- --- - ------ - - - * - ºil ſº º ºiſ; ----- ºf * . - - - - º - -- - - -- - - -- - - - - - - - - --- -- --- - ---- Y \, , , , , f*. - - * , , , , ſºil. - - - - -- A ---tº-r - A Cº. - - - - --- -- *-* --" - - - - - - - - - - -- - - - - - - -

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 62

- - (6.2 ) - 2 -** - - ------ .* - - ------4--- ſº º º-ºº- ------- º -- ºn. º º: ºlº J tºº "ººl tº ºth ºl- -- --- - ºn Scen, 5, ---" - ºn sºr ºf ºur intº Ceſar, Cleopatra, Antonius, Lepidus, A º - ºf "Tºº *- choreus, Charmion. CAE's A R. Her Virtue, and their Crime, alike amaze, , , , Queen, you perceive for whom your goodneſs’ - ºº: º (prayes. CLEOPATR A. ' That, now, no more againſt your Juſtice fights Go (Sir)Revenge all violated rights * . . . My Ruine, they much more then yours deſire: The Traytors do againſt my Right Conſpire. . . As my ſupport, againſt you they deſign: ... " And by your death.would make their way to mine. But though all this be to my anger known, ſº Yes 'tis my Brother ſtill, that leads them on. ... Do you know that Sir, and may I obtain, It your deſerved fury may reſtrain f --- CAE SA R. Yes, Ile remember, your heart is ſo great, That for his Births ſake, you his Crime forget. Adieu, fear nothing, for theſe are not foes, That can the fortune of my Arms oppoſe. Them, and their Party, I ſhall quickly rout, When I to them but Whips and Racks bring out: They ſhall not Souldiers, but Tormentors ſee, And now my Axes ſhall my Enſigns be. Exit. Caeſar. -- CLEOPATRA. 3 ºn tº

This page contains an image.
Page 63

- - r * * - - - - _* ºf tº . . . ( *… ...º.º. tº - CLEOPATRA,” - - --- --- - - - - - º - º Dear Achoreus, after cefar go, With him prevent my Threatned overthrow. And when he puniſhes our worthleſs Foes, Make him remember what his promiſe ows. Obſerve the King, when he in fight appears, And ſpare his blood, that you may ſpare my tears. A CHOR ELIS. Madam, his fortune ſhall no ſorrow need, If all my Care and ſervice can ſucceed. - º - After the fourth Aćt, Cleopatra ſits hearkening to this Song. * * * ºr º i. * º -- Dº Mom wº of Royal puſ / Do not your old Foundations ſhake & And labour to reſign their truſt . . . For ſure your mighty Gueſts ſhould wake. Now their own Memphis lies at stake. º . .º.º. ºººººº, Alas ! in vain our Dangers calls. They care not for our Deštiny, Nor will they be comcern’d at all - - If Egyyt mow enſlav'd, or free, - A Kingdom or a Province be. - What is become of all they did £ And what of all they had deſign'd, 's Now death the buſie Sceme hath hid; Where but in ſtory ſhall we find Thoſe great diſturbers of Mankind? When



This page contains an image.
Page 64

( 64) When Men their quiet Minutes ſpent Where Mirtle; grew and Fountains purl’d, As ſafe as they were Innocent sº * What angry God among them hurl’d º Ambition tº undoe theherº tº Pº a woºd tº dº ºil sºlº & What if the charm of being Greats º º * Which oft is gain’d and loft with Sim, ‘’ - Or if nº attain a Royal ſeat, - With Guiltle 3 #eps what do we win, , , º if Love and Honour fight within.” ºf ſlºº Cººl I -- --- - ---- - tº 2 ſº lº i. Honour the Brightneſs of the Mind! And love her nobleft extaffe : That does our ſelves, this others himdº" Hºhen yºu great Paiſall diſagree h hat caſhift can the Umpire be. --- -- º º - Though Love does all the heart ſubdue, * * With gentle, but refiftleſ; ſway º ----- -- --~~ * Yet Honour muſt that govern too: And when the Honour win; the Day, * - -------- **** - --- - - * Love ºvercomes the braveft way. tº º º, "...º. ºn º º º \ , º, ºn ºf tº º º sº tº ºvº, º 'º º * - - - - \ º " - - ** * - - - - § sº tº º, º sº º * * - " * * - - - ºlº tºº - --- " " … º, ... . . . . . - - Ağ. --- -º A. ºn , º, º, ø, º º, ºn tº J * ...º. -- º - - * ... " - º º tº sº, sº . º º --- - - - - º * nº ºn. -º-º-º-º-º-º º ºn tº --

This page contains an image.
Page 65

(65) tº , sosing iſ ºdd vſ. tº ºbo'ſ sºciºtº º ºbºni sºvº viºleº T T- ºf ººº- it. º º: º, º i lºſiº º - --- - Aćt. 5. Scen. I. ºn *-ºſ º-º... º. ººr, ſº - ºr-- ºriº ºf ºut ºſt ºf sº ſº tº Cornelia with a little Urne in her hand -i. ** . . ." ſº - and Philip. - ºil º 19 ºn tº tº CORN E E. I. Alºi º ºil ſº nº ºbſºn; sº wild hoººººººº lºſſ º --- - - Ay I believe my Eyes 2 or does this fight Mà. me, with chimera's of the Night? Do I behold Thee Philip 3 and didſt Thou Funeral rites to my lov'd Lord allow #5 wºod His Aſhes does this Urne contain 2 O view nº At once ſo terrible and tender too !" ºn tº Eternal Food of Sorrow and of Hate, ſº All of Great Pompey that is ſpar'd by fate. a Expect not I a Tear to you ſhould pay, dº nº hº For Great Souls, eaſe their Griefs another way.º Shallow Afflićtions, by Complaints are fed : And who laments, would fain be Comforted. But I have ſworn by all that we Adore 3 ºr ºl And by your ſelf (ſad Obječt ) which is more: gº (For my griev'd Heart does more to you ſubmit, Then to thoſe Gods who ſo ill-guarded it. ) By you I ſwear it then (Mournfull remain, ºn My only Deity, now he is ſlain), nº nº ºn That no extinétion or decay, ſhall be sº- In that revenge which muſt enoble me. ºf º l, ºr I - To

This page contains an image.
Page 66

(66) as , To ceſar, Ptolomy, by baſe ſurprize, Rome, of thy Pompey, made a Sacrifice. And I, thy injur'd walls will never ſee, Till Prieſt, and God, to him ſhall offer'd be. Put me in mind, and my juſt hate ſuſtain, - Q Aſhes!, now my hopé as well as Pāin, sº ºn And to aſſiſt me in that great deſign, Shed in all Hearts, what now is felt by mine. But Thou, who on ſo infamous a ſhoar, Gav'ſt him a flame, ſo Pious, though ſo Poor: Tell me, what God thy Fortune made ſo great, To pay to ſuch a Hero ſuch a Debt? º 1. PHILIP. ºº, ſºlº Cover'd with Blood,and much more dead then he: When I had curs'd the Royal Treachery, ſº My wandring Feet were by my grief convey'd, Where yet the Wind upon the Water plaid : After long ſearch, I on a Rock did ſtand, And ſaw the Headleſs Trunk approach the Sandº Where th' angry Wave, a . ſeem'd to take To caſt it off, and then to ſhatch it back: ººlºº I to it leap'd, and thruſt it to the banks; ºf . Then gathering a heap of Shipwrack'd Planks, An haſty, artleſs Pile, 1 to him rais'd, ſº Such as ſcould, and ſuch as Fortune pleas'd. . . . ‘Twas hardly kindled, when Heaven grew ſo kind To ſend me help, in what I had deſign'd. todru', an Ancient Roman, who lives here, sº Returning from the City, ſpy'd methere. ºf . And when he did a headleſs Carkaſs view, sº ºf By that ſad mark alone he Pompey knew : Th - en

This page contains an image.
Page 67

( {67) Then Weeping ſaid, *** thou art? To whom the Gods ſuch honours do impart." Thy fortune's greater then thou doſt believe, i. Thou ſhalt rewards, not Puniſhments receive." £eſar's in Egypt and Revenge declares.º. º. For him to whom thou pay ſt.theſe Pious Cares, Theſe Aſhes to his Widow thou mayſt bear In Alexandria, for now ſhe is there. By Pompey; Conquerour ſo entertain'd, o' C. As by a God it would not be diſdain'd.º.º.d'ſ Go on till I return, this ſaid, he went, ſº wº And quickly brought me this ſmall Monument. Then we, betwixt us, into it convey'd, That Hero's Aſhes which the fire had made º ºn Cof NELIA, With what great Praiſesſhould this act be crown'd? PHILIP, Entring the Town I great diſorders found.º. A numerous People to the Port did flye, ºol Which they believ'd the King would fortifie. The eager Romans fiercely theſe purſu'd, - Rage in their cys,their hands with blood imbrew’d. When Ceſar with brave Juſtice did Command, Photim to periſh by a Hangmans hand. On me appearing, he vouchſaf'd to look, And with theſe words my Maſters Aſhes took. Remainders of a Demigod whoſe Name I ſcarce can equal Conquerour as I am. Behold guilt puniſh'd and till Altars call, For other Vićtims let theſe Traytors fall.

I 2 Greater

This page contains an image.
Page 68

(68) . . . . -- oleºntº 3. Court go thou, º, On Pompey's Widow this from me beſtow. º! And whilſt with it ſhe makes with grief ſome truce, Tell her how Caſar her Revenge purſues. º. That great Man, ſighing, then from me did turn, & And humbly kiſſing did reſtore the Urne, º' mºst º 'º tº º ºſ º º A. sº COR NE LIA.º. O Formal Grief! how eaſie is that Tear, That's ſhed for Foes whom we no longer fear ! How ſºon revenge for others fills that breſt, º Which to it, is, by its own danger preſt 2 º' And when the Carewe take to right the dead. Secures our Life and does our glory ſpread.* Caeſar is generous 'tis true, but, he . By the King wrong'd, and from his Rival free, , Might in an envious mind a doubt revive," What he would do were Pompey yet alive. His courage, his own ſafety does provide, s Which does the Beauty of his ačtions hide." Love is conceridin't too, and he does fight In Pompey; Cauſe for €leopatra's Right. tº So many Int’reſts with my Husband's met, Might to his Virtue takeaway my debt. º. But as Great Hearts judge: by themſelves alone, I chooſe to gueſs his honour by my own, sº And think we only make his fury ſuch, ºn tº Since in his Fortune I ſhould do as much. ºº - - .* . º ------- - º -- º -- --- ------ º erºſ ºoſiº ºn tº it to gº - º … …" ºr -- ~ *-**** rtiſ, 25 fºotººººoº lººp: dº ºiº Hºo zººl A. Iſiſ ºf fliriºg tº biºlº -- - -º - - - - - * ". * ºr " - - - r º, a gººd sº ºn 1 - - - ---, * * - - f S - - º CCI1. 2.

This page contains an image.
Page 69

(69) * * * * * . . . . - " * º ºlº --- * * " , Scen. 2. t - º - - - Cleopatra, Charmion, Cornelia, Philip. º ºf ºl º ºlº ºf : , - - - * > . ~~ : - --- --- C L E O PATR A. ºlº -- - - --- ------ --- ...º. --- º --- I come not to diſturb a grief ſo due To that afflićtion which hath wounded you. But thoſe remains tº adore, which from the wave, A faithfull freed-man did ſo lately ſave. To mourn your fortune, Madam, and to ſwear, You'd ſtill enjoy, a Man ſo juſtly Dear If Heaven which does perſecute you ſtill, - Had made my Power equal to my will. Yet if to what that Heaven ſends you now, Your Grief can any Room for Joy allow : If any ſweetneſs in revenge there be, Receive the certainty of yours from me. The falſe Photimus. But you may have heard. CORN ELI.A. Yes, Princeſs that he hath his Juſt reward. CLEOPAT R.A. Have you no comfort in that news diſcern'd? C OR N E LIA. C. If there be any you are moſt concern'd. C L E O PA TRA. All hearts with Joy receive a wiſh'd Event. C O R N E L IA. ---. Our thoughts are, as our Int’reſts, different. Though

This page contains an image.
Page 70

- (760) - Though ceſar add Achillas Death twill be, To you a ſatisfaction, not to me. For nobler rites to Pompey's Ghoſt belong, Theſe are too mean to expiate his wrong. No reparation by ſuch Blood is made, ------ Either to my grief, or his injur'd ſhade, And the Revenge which does my Soul enflame, Till it hath Caeſar, Ptolomy doth claim; Who though ſo much unfit to reign or live, Ceſar Pknow will for his ſafety ſtrive. * - But though his Love hath dar'd to promiſe it, Yet juſter Heaven dares it not permit. And if the Gods an Ear to me afford, They ſhall both periſh by each others Sword. Such an event would my Hearts grief deſtroy, Which now is ſuch a Stranger grown to. Joy. But if ye Gods think this too great a thing, And but one fall, O let it be the King ! C L E O P A T R. A. Heaven does not govern as our Wills direct. - C OR N E L I A. - - But Gods, what Cauſes promiſe, will effect And do the guilty with revenge purſue. C L E O P A T R A. - - As they have Juſtice they have Mercy too. . . C O RN E L I.A. But we may Judge as here events have paſt, They now the firſt will ačt and not the laſt. CLEOPATRA: Their Merey oft does through their Juſtice break. CC) R N E LIA. Queen, you as Siſter, I as Widow ſpeak. Each - -

This page contains an image.
Page 71

(71) Each hath her cauſe of kindnes and of hate, And both concern’d are in this Princes fate." But by the Blood which hath to day been ſhed, We ſhall perceive whoſe vows have better ſped. Behold your Achoreus. • *---- º -- ºf H Q tº Scen. 3. To them Achoreur. C L E O PA TR. A. - But alas, I read no good preſages in his Face 3 Speak Achoreus, let us freely hear What yet deſerves my ſorrow, or my fear. A C Ho RE us. Aſſoon as Caeſar did the Treaſon know: C L E O PA TRA. 'Tis not his Condućt I enquire of now, I know he cut and ſtopt that ſecret vault Which to him ſhould the Murtherers have brought, That to ſecure the ſtreets his men he ſent, Where Phot in did receive his Puniſhment: Whoſe ſudden fall Achill's ſo amaz'd, That on th' Abandon'd Port he quickly ſeiz'd; Whom the King follow'd, and that, to the land Antoniº all his Souldiers did command. Where Ceſar joyn'd him, and I thence do gueſsº, Achillas Puniſhment, and his ſucceſs.” " --- * . - ACHORELIS. º in º

This page contains an image.
Page 72

(72) A CHOR, E U S 2 ºr His uſual Fortune her Aſſiſtance gave. ºn -- º C L E OP A T R. A. º: ºi º But tell me if he did my Brother ſave, nº And kept his Promiſe. A C H O R. E.U. S. Yes, with all his Might. C L E O P A T R A. That's all the News I wiſh'd you to recite. Madam, You ſee the Gods my wiſhes heard. - C O R N E L I A They only have his Puniſhment deferr'd. C L E O P A T R A. You wiſh’d it now ; but they have him ſecur'd : f º A C H O RE U. S. º. Or ceſar had, if he had life endur'd. * C L E O P A T R. A. What ſaid you laſt? Or did I rightly hear? Oh! Quickly your obſcure Diſcourſes clear. A C H O R EU. S. Neither your cares nor ours could ſave him, who Would die in ſpight of Ceſar, and of You : But Madam, in the nobleſt way he dy'd That ever falling Monarch dignify'd. tº º irtue did his Birth make good, lºº And to the Romans dearly ſold his blood. º He fought Antonius with ſuch noble heat, ºl That on him. He did ſome advantage get: º Eut Ceſars coming alter'd the event 5 tº ºt Achillas thereafter Photimus went. Cºlº But ſo as him did too much Honour bring tº With Sword in hand he periſh'd for his King. - : -º N.º -

This page contains an image.
Page 73

O ſpare the King'; º the Conquerour cry’d; To him no Hope but Terrouritimply'd.º.º. Bº For frighted, he thought cºfar did intend ºf But to reſerve him to a ſhameful end. tº ºf He charg’d, and broke our Ranks, bravely to ſhew What Virtue armed by Deſpair can do. º. ºº By this miſtake his vexed ſoul abus'd, ... . . . Still ſought the Death which ſtill was him refus'd. Breathleſs at laſt, with having fought and bled, Encompaſs'd round, and his beſt Souldiers dead, Into a Veſſel which was near he leaps, ſº tº And follow’d was by ſuch tumultuous heaps, dº As by their number, overpreſt, the Ship º With all its fraight was ſwallow'd in the Deep. This Death recovers all his loſt Renown, Gives ceſar Fame, and You th’Agyptian Crown. You were proclaim'd, and though no Roman ſword Had touch'd the Life ſo much by you deplor’d." Caeſar extreamly did concern'd appear 5". " He fighs, and he complains: but ſee him here, Who better can’then I his Gliefs relate,” For the unhappy Kings reſiſtleſs Fate º º ºr or- ºr pº - - tº IX ºf Cººl ºr not ºn tº Scen, 4, º - - - - - - - - ºf ºººººº... . º. ºº ºf - - I O them zerº ºf -- - - *** , , , -

ºr ºil a wºol. ºrº. . . . ºº iſ Ceſar, Antoniuſ, Lepidus, coRNE LIA. Caeſar be juſt, and me my Gallies yield, , , , , Achillas and Photinº both are kill'd 5 - º K Nor º ---

This page contains an image.
Page 74

# --- ; :º And Pompey here, no more revenge • ******* * * ~ *-*******.*.*-****** \ (74). No could thyſoſtned heart their Maſterſºve, no - ". -- - havcº º This fatal ſhoare nothing does me preſent, But th' Image of their horrible Attempt, And thy new Conqueſt, with the giddy noiſe Of People who in change of Kings rejoyce: , , But what afflićts me moſt, is ſtill to ſee . . . . . Such an obliging Enemy in Thee, ºn ºn tº Releaſe me then from thisinglorious pain, And ſet my Hate at liberty again, in ºn But yet before I go, I muſt requeſt nº The Head of Pompey with his Bones may reſt, ºn Give it me then, as that alone, which yet yº / I can with Honour at thy hands intreat. In ſº º CAESAR. º ſº ºil tº lººd, º iſ ſº lºſiº. " ...Yº, O ºf , You may ſojuſtly that Remainder claim, , , That to deny it would be Caſar's ſhamef, But it is fit, after ſo many Woes, , , , , ... That we ſhould give his wandring Shade repoſe, And that a Pile which You and Iºnflame, ſº From the firſt mean one reſcue Pompey's name, That he ſhould be appeas'd our §. view; And that an Urn more worthy him and you May (the Pomp done, and fire extinét again ) His reunited Aſhes entertain. I' This Arm, which did ſo long with him debate, Shall Altars to his Vertue dedicate 3 º, Offer him Vows, Incenſe and Vićtims too, And yet ſhall give him nothing but his Due. fººt ºn lºº - - * \º- I but to morrow for theſe Rites require, - - - - ºr tº -tºrr 1-y - - ---- º º Refuſe me not the Favour. I deſire; ººº- /. But



This page contains an image.
Page 75

--- /

- -, - - -_ _ _ " - "Lºſ - W - 5) ºriº Aiº tº {{ is ºr ºf But ſtay till theſe **** ... And then you may reſume your eager haſte." Bring to . ; : . fö great, . º That Relique bear ºne º --- “. . . . , tº CORN E L I A. - º Not thither Ceſar yet..., Till firſt thy ruine, granted me by Fate, To theſe lov’d Aſhes ſhallunlock the Gates, And thither (though as Dear to Rome as me) They come not till Triumphant over thee. To Affrick I muſt this rich burthen bear, in Where Pompey's ;: i.e., Who'll finde'ſ hope, (with a brave King ally'd) Fortune as well as Júſtice on their ſide: And thou ſhalt ſee, there with new fury hurl’d, Pharſalia's Ruines arme another World. . . . . . From Rank to Ränk theſe Aſhes I'll expoſe

- Mixt with my Tears, tº exaſperate thy Foes. . . . A." . . . . . . .”" . . . My Hate ſhall guide them too, and they ſhall fight With urns, inſtead of Eagles in their fights That ſuch ſad Obječis may make them intent Thou to this Hero now devout art grown, But, raiſing his Name, doſt exalt thy own. . . . I muſt be Witneſs too ! and I ſubmit5, , , , , But thou canſ never movemy Heart with it. My Loſs can never be repaird by Fate, tº Nor is it poſſible t'exhauſt my Hate. i - This ‘Hate ſhall be my Pompey now, and I In his Revenge will live, and with it die. K 2 But

This page contains an image.
Page 76

‘76.) But as a Roman, though my Hate be ſuch, ºn tº I muſt confeſs, º thee eſteem as much. ºº. Both theſe extreams. Juſtice can well allow: ºl This does my Virtue, that my Duty ſhow. ºr My ſenſe of Honour does the firſt command, Concern, the laſt, and they are both conſtraind. And as thy Virtue, whom none can betray, Where I ſhould hate, makes me ſuch value pay : My Duty ſo my Anger does create, sº º And Pompey's Widdow makes cornelia hate. But I from hence ſhall haſten, and know then, I'll raiſe againſt thee Gods, as well as Men. Thoſe Gods that flatter'd thee and me abus'd, / And in Pharſalia Pompey's Cauſe refus’d 5 Who at his Death could Thunderbolts refrain, To expiate that, will his Revenge maintain: If not his Soul will give my Zeal ſuch heat, As I without their help ſhall thee defeat. But ſhould all my Endeavours proſperill, , , What I can not do, Cleopatra will. . . . . I know thy flame, and that tº obey its force Thou from Calphurnia ſtudy'ſt a Divorce: ...ſº Now blinded, thou wouldſt this Alliance make,..., And there's no Law of Rome thou darſt not break. But know, the Roman Youth think it no ſin ſº To fight againſt the Husband of a Queen. a And thy offended Friends will at the Price. Of thy beſt Blºod revenge their ſcorn’d Advice. I check thy Rhine if heck thy Love ...". Adieu's tomorrow will thy Honour prove, ſº ſº tºº ºr -ºº -- * ". . . . . --, - - * . . . . - - - º, ºr ºf ſºv º, tº J # 2i; r: oil, at , irº bººtlºw −3 ºr "tº º - Scen. 5 º - • p 3::: Q ºf

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 77

(77) -** º Scen. 5. tºº ; : ; ºf - - - - - - - - - - --- ºf , ºr rºtº, º żº ºf ºil , " - Ceſar, Cleopatra, Charmion, Antoniur, Lepiduſ, Achoreuſ. CLEO PAT R A. Rather then You to this expos'd ſhould be, With my own Ruine I would ſet you free. Sacrifice me, Sir, to your Happineſs; For that's the greateſt that I can poſſeſs. Though far unworthy to be º Bride, Yet He'll remember one that for him Dy'd. . .C AF S A. R. Thoſe empty projećts, Queen, are all now left To a great Heart of other Help bereft ; Whoſe keen deſires her want of Strength confeſs, Could ſhe perform more, ſhe would wiſh it leſs. The Gods will theſe vain Auguries diſprove, Nor can they my Felicitie remove. If your Love ſtronger then your Grief appears, And will for Ceſars ſake dry up your Tears 5 And that a Brother, who deſerv'd them not, tº May for a Faithful Lover be forgot. ºn You may have heard, with what Regret of mine His Safety to Deſpair he did reſigne. How much I ſought his Reaſon to redeem From thoſe vain Terrors that ſurrounded him, Which he diſputed to his lateſt Breath, And caſt away his Life for fear of Death. O ſhame for Ceſar! Who ſo eminent And ſo follicitous for your Content ºf i - - - Yet

This page contains an image.
Page 78



(78) Yet by the Cruel Fortune of this Day . Could not the Firſt of your Commands Obey: But vainly we reſiſt the Gºds, who will tº Their Juſt Decrees on guilty men fulfill. And yet his Fall your Happineſs procures, Since by his Death Ægypt is wholly Yours. ºf C LE O PATR A. tº ºn, I know I gain another Diadem, ºn tº For which none can be blam'd but Heav'n and Him; But as the Fate of humane things is ſuch, That Joy and Trouble do each other touch, ºl Excuſe me, if the Crown conferr'd by You nº ºf As it obliges, Does afflićt me too. And if to ſee a Brother juſtly kill'd , nº To Nature I as well as Reaſon yield. No ſooner on my Grandeur I reflect, , , , , , , But my Ambition by my Blood is checkt. , , , I meet my Fortune with a ſecret Groan, Nor dare without Regret aſcend the Throne. AC HORELIS., , , , , The Court is full, Sir, People crowding in, Who with great ſhouts demand to ſee their Queen, And many ſignes of their Impatience give, , , , That ſuch a Bleſſing they ſo late receive. . . . ſº I tº. ..º.º. º ºr ºf tº ºn CAESA R. | | .." Let them ſo juſt a Happineſs obtain, ºr (reign, And by that Goodneſs, Queen, commence your O may the Gods ſo favour my Deſire, tº That in their Joy your Sorrow may expire 30, i. * _º 2t

This page contains an image.
Page 79

(79)

That no Idea in your Soul may be, But of the Wounds which you have given me : Whilſt my Attendants and your Courtiers may Prepare to morrow for a glorious day. When all ſuch Noble Offices may owne, Pompey t” appeaſe, and Cleopatra Crown. ... To her a Throne, to him let's Altars Build, And to them both Immortal Honours yield. Exehººt.

- afier the Fifth Aét by two Egyptian Prieſts as af. ter the ſecond. - --- -- --- - Scend a Throme Great Queen 1 to you By Nature, and by Fortune due 3 ***And let the World adore

º º One who ambition could withſtand, subdue revenge, and Love command, * * * * On Honour. ſingle ſcore. - Te mighty Roman ſhades, permit That Pompey ſhould above you fit, He muſt be Deifiºd. --- --- * . . . -



º --- ºn For who like him, e're fought or fell 2. What Hero, ever liv'd ſº well, Cºlº Or who ſo greatly dy'd? - - 1. On ºil | º irhat cannot Glorious Cæſar do º jº º How nobly does he fight and woe 1 º' . On Crowns how does he tread!', ºuco º Wha? ------ - - - &

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 90

- - - - - - ºdºº lººd tº ſº on Jºº What mercie to the weak, he ſhews, sº loº How fierce if he to living Foer, º/, ºn ſiliº - How pious to the dead? & º, - --- º ------------ - tº 2... . . . . . º Cornelia yet, would challenge Tears, But that the ſorrow which ſhe wears, ºn A So charming is, and brave. That it exalts her Honour more, ºne. Then if ſhe all the Scepters bore, ºu lºº Her Generous Husband gave. - - * - - º -- º Chorus. . . . . . Then after all the Blood that's ſhed, Let's right the living and the dead: Temples to Pompey raiſe; sº º * . set Cleopatra on the Throme; Let Cæſar keep the World h has won 5 And ſing Cornelia's praiſe. º 'º ºf a º - tº . After which a Grand Maſque is Danc'd before Ceſar and Cleopatra, made (as well as the other Dances and the Tunes to them) by Mr. john - sº, ſº tºº sº, tº Ogill, • º º, ºn tº º * - - - - - - ----- -- ----- - --------- º 'º º, º 'º','º', º º, - EPILOGUE

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page Scan 91

ſº stettestetti $$$$$$$$$$$. E P I L O G UI E. Written by Sir Edward Dering Baronet. ( fit, Leas'd or diſpleas'd, cenſure as you think The Aétion,Plot,the language or the wit: But we're ſecure, no Bolder thought can tax Theſe ſcenes of Blemiſh to the bluſhing Sex. Nor Envy with her hundred Eyes eſpie One line ſevereſt Virtue need to flye: As Chaſt the words, as harmleſs is the ſence, As the firſt ſmiles of Infant Innocence. Yet at your Feet, Caeſar's Content to bow, And Pompey, never truly Great till now: Who does your Praiſe and kinder Votes pre- ls Before th' applauſe of his own Theatre: (fer | Where fifty Thouſand Romans daily bleſt The Gods and him, for all that they poſſeſt. The ſad Cornelia ſayes,your gentler breath Will force a ſmile,ev’n after Pompey, Death. - She - Nº. º º º











This page contains an image.
Page Scan 92

- * - - -- - *- But flattering hopes and trembling fears re- Undone in Egypt, Theſſaly and Rome, (turn: She yet in Ireland hopes a milder Doom: Nor from Iberian Shoars, or Libian Sands Expe&ts relief, but only from you hands. Ev’n Cleopatra, not content to have The univerſe,and Caeſar too her Slave: (low; Forbears her Throne, till you her right al- (ſed you. - - - - - - - --- --- - - --- - - º *** **** º - - - - º - - - * º º - - º, - * > 1 - F- __ ** - - - - - - -- - - - -- -- -- - - F I N I S. - - - --- - - - - - -*. º - - --- ------------ Tº ... " - - -. - -- * --> - * - -- - - - --- º - * - -- 3 * - - - - -º- She thought all Paſſions bury'd in his EIrre, Tis leſs t have rul'd the World,then plea-

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 93

Blank page
Page Scan 94

Blank page
Page Scan 95

*Nºv. frº wors, JAN $ 1910
Page Scan 96

º º º -

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents

End of text. Return to beginning.
