Argalus and Parthenia. Written by Fra. Quarles., ---. | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
Argalus and Parthenia. Written by Fra. Quarles., ---.
Author
Quarles, Francis, 1592-1644.Quarles, Francis, 1592-1644.
Edition
The last ed.
Published
London,Printed by J. Redmayne for T. Rooks,1677.
Description
3 p. l., 215 p. incl. 29 pl.front. (port.)21 cm.
Rights
Public Domain, Google-digitized.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/nyp.33433112025238

Table of Contents

    Front Cover
    Title Page
    Section 1 on page number 1
    Section 2 on page number 10
    Section 3 on page number 20
    Section 4 on page number 29
    Section 5 on page number 33
    Section 6 on page number 47
    Section 7 on page number 59
    Section 8 on page number 68
    Section 9 on page number 73
    Section 10 on page number 81
    Section 11 on page number 84
    Section 12 on page number 87
    Section 13 on page number 106
    Section 14 on page number 113
    Section 15 on page number 129
    Section 16 on page number 145
    Section 17 on page number 146
    Section 18 on page number 149
    Section 19 on page number 152
    Section 20 on page number 177
    Section 21 on page number 189
    Section 22 on page number 192
    Section 23 on page number 197
    Section 24 on page number 208
    Section 25
    Section 26

Book Text
Front Cover
Page Scan 1

NYPL RESEARCH LIBRARIE |||||||| 3 3 1 iii. 5238 433 1120 |

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 2

|------ - - - - ----- _- ----- «- - -- - - - -|- |-|-- - - · |- |-----|----- |-|- ~|- |- ·. -- |-|-|-|-|- |-|-|- |-|- |-|-|-|-|- ----|- |-|-|-|-|-|- |-- - |- |-----|-|- ·|-|- |-· |- |-|-|-|-|- |-|-|--|- |-·|-·|- -|-|-|- |- ·|-|-|-|- |- |-|- |-· |- -|-|-|- |-|-·|- |-|- → |-|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|- |-|-|- |-|-|-|-|-|- |-|-·|-|- |-- -， |-，|- ！|- |-- ：|-|-|- |-|- -- |-· |-|-|-· ··|-- -- |-|-|-----|-|- |-- · - ·|- |-|- -|-|-|-|- |-|- |- ----- -- ·-|- |-|-* .|-|- |-|-|-|-|- |-~----|- |- - |- - ·|-|-|- ·· ·-· |-* . |--|-|- ·----• • -- · · · -· |-· ， ,|- -|-|- ·• … .|-, ！|-|-|-|- ·|- |-|-|- *, ！|-|-|- |-|- |-|-|-|-|- |- · – |-|- |- -|-- - · - |-• |-- - |- -|- - -||- ----|- |-|-|-|- - --~|-|- |-· |-|- :|-- |-||- |- |- |- |-·---- |-|- - |-|-|-|- ^|-|-|-· |- |- |-|- - |-|-|-|-|- |- |- |-|-|-|- ----|- |-|-· ·|-|- ·|-· · ··|-| |-|- |- |-|-|- |- -|-|- ·|- · |--|-|- |-|-|-|-|- |- |-|-|- |-||-|- |-|-|-|-|- |- ·|-|- ~ |-|- |-|-|-|- |--- " |-·|- |-|- -< |-|- |- |-|- |-· · |- º |- |-· - - -|-|----- « ·|- · · |-|-|- |- ----|-|-|- |-|-|-|-|×|- · ---- |-<！--· …|- ----|- |-|- ·|-|-|- |-|-|- ~ ！（ --- |- （ ） - - |-|- |- |-|-|- |-|- |-|-|- |-|-- - -|-|- |-|-|- |-|-· · · - ， ， |-|- |-|-, ！|-· · |- |-|-|- |-|-· · ·|-|-|-|- -|- -|- · · |- · - ·|-|-|-|- |-|- |-|- |-|- |- |-|- |-|- · · |-|-|- ----·|- ---- . |-|- |-|- |- |-|- |-· | ·|- |- · |-|- -









Page Scan 3

· |- · · -|- |- |-· |-|-|- |-|-|-|-|- · · · |-|- |- |- |-·· * - * .|- |- |- · ·|- ·- - |-|- |-|- |-|-· - - · · ·|- |-|-|-|- |-|-|- ·|-·? ----|-|- - - |- →---- |- .* -|- |-' ' ， ！ |- |- --|- |- · -- |-|- |- - --- |- |- |- |-|- |- · - |-|- |- - |- |- · |-|- - -|- |- …|- ， ， , |-|×|--- |-|-|-· · |- |-- - |-|- ， ，|- |- |-|- |- ·|- - - -|- |-|- |-|- |- |-|- |-|-|- ， ！|- ----* |- |----- |- ！ |-|- |-|-|- |-|- |- |-|-|-…"|- ae ： ， ！ ，|-|-- - -|-|-- |-|-|-|… |-|- |- |-|- |- . |-·|- |-!|-|- |-|-|-|- |-|- · · · |- |-|-|- -|-|- |-|- · - -|- +|- º -











































Page Scan 4

Blank page
Page Scan 5

Blank page
Page Scan 6

Blank page
Page Scan 7

** - ; : * i --, -, (" ",
Page Scan 8

!, |

End of Front Cover. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Title Page
Page Scan 9

ſ ARGALUS . . * * * ‘. . . . . . *— —i------— - - º, “ , :# Written by Fra. Quarles, - -- - * - "y" - * -***** The laſt Edition Correàed, Amended, ILLust RATED with 36. FIGuREs - . Relating to the . ... " w . . º s To R Y - - £ o N p o N, - Printed by 7. Redmayne, for Tho. Kooks, at the Lamb - and Ink-Bottle in Newgate-ſtreet, who makes and ſells the beſt Ink, MDCLXXVII.
Page Scan 10

A*TOR, 1 Ency Ana Til DEN Egunſ. A rows The Mind of the Frontiſpiece. R. behindth ſilenfrontſiae bes - The Argument of our Book: which to your Eyes our Muſe (for ſerious cauſes, and beft known itnto her ſelf) cºmmand, ſhould be unſhown: And therefore, to that end ſhe hath thoughtfr To draw this curtain 'twixt your eye and it. 3.A. sº. £e sº - º ################ - * - º 2



Page Scan 11

-, -- -- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - ~. - - - - - - * . * - - - - * -- - - * - - º - --> * ... -- * - - * * * * - -- * * * * - * - - - *** - - º -- - - - * - - - - - - - - - º - - * - - º -- - - .* , - . . * e. - - - - - - - - - - - - - - … - r ~ - - - -



Page Scan 12

GALVS and PARTHENLA e Z11°g 11111 e 11t O e Hiſtory N- J771-42 Cºtto11–. Fs. f * -- - ºS--- º 42.4% zºnº. 4aze ºf Azczz.ºreet rº, 2 . * -- - - - - 22 - - • * * - - | §: TBazz/ºr M *cºmarzazá.3.4 & .*. - r

Page Scan 13

(, -- | ######### READER. Reader, - sº Preſent thee here with a Hiſtory of Argalus and § Parthenia, the fruits of broken hours. It was a Ciens taken out of the Orchard of Sir Philip - Sidney, of precious memory, which I have lately graffed upon a crab-ſtock, in mine own. It hath brought forth many leaves, and promiſes º if malevolent eyes blaſt it not in the bud. This Book differs from my former, as a Courtier,from a churchman: Bºt if anythink it unfit fºr one to play both parts, I have preſidents for it; And let ſuch know, that I have taken but one Play-day in ſix: However, 1. fhould beſhrew that hand that binds them all together to make one Volume. In this diſcourſe, I have not affected to ſet thy underſtanding on the Rack, by the tyranny of #rong Lines, which (as they fabulouſly report of China diſhes)are made for the third generation to make uſe of, and are the meer itch of wit: under the colour of which, many have ventured truſting to the Oedipean conceit of their ingenious Reader)to write non-ſence, and felloniouſly father the created expoſitions of 0. ther men;not unlike ſome Painters,who firſt make the piſture, then, from the opinion of betterjudgments, conclude whom it reſembles. Theſe lines are ſtrong enough for my purpoſe: If . not for thine, yet read them, and yet underſtandings may be magnified *** -

Page Scan 14

`-- --— To the Reader. magnified by their weaknefºreader thouſhall in the progreſs - of this Story, meet with a ſeeming Soloeciſm, which is this ; Demagoras his ſº foula aeed perpetrated upon the fair Par- thenia, is fully j. ; and yet, the revenge thereofpaşţ o- ºver in ſilence; wherein (as I conceive) I have not dealt un- juſtly. When Prometheus ſtole fireſ. Heaven to animate and quicken his artificial bodies, the ſeverer gods fºr puniſh- ment of ſo high a ſatriledº, ſtruck him nºt head with a ſudden Thunder-bolt, but(to be more deeply avenged)et him live, to be tormented with Pultures continually gnawing on his Liver. The ſame kind of torture had Ixion; ſº had Siſyphus; ſº had Tantalus: Did then Demagoras fault equal (if not ex- eeed) theirs, and ſhould his puniſhment be leſ; 2 Had my pen. delivered him dead in your hands, what could you have had more? His accurſed memory had ſºon rotted with his baſer name, and there had been an end of him : In which reſpeši, I bave ſuffered him to live, that he may ſtand like a Jack a Lent,or a Shroving Cock, for every one to ſpenda Cudgilat, to the worlds end. Ladies, (for in your ſilken laps I know this 'Book willchuſe to lie,which being far-fetched if the Stationer £e pie, will be moſt fit for you)my ſuit is, That you would be tea ed to give the fair Parthenia your noble entertainment: Shº hath croſſ the seas for your acquaintance, and tº come to /ºr and die with you; to whoſe gentle hand, I recºmmend her, and kiſs them. - Dublin, this 4. - - of March, FR. QUARLEs. 1621. Argalud.

End of Title Page. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 1

As great a ſharer in the Daphnean Tree, - §§ Sé $$$. :- ############ tº: --------- ############, *******************ssss ALuS A N D PARTHENIA. THE F I Rs T Boo K. Kºſthin the limits of th’Arcadian Land, Sºſ/ whoſegrateful bounty hathinrichtthelland §ºof many a Shepherd Swain,whoſe ruralArt ºuntaught togloze, or with a double heart ßTo vow diſſembled Love) did build to Fams Eternal Trophies of a Paſtoral name: . . . . . - That fºreet Arcadia; which, in antick days, , Was wont to warble out her well-tun'd lays To all the World; and, with her Oaten Reed, Did ſing her love whilſt her proud flocks did feed: Arcadii, whoſe deſarts did claim to be As



Page 2

*Targalus and partinia. Tº Ashis, whoſe louder AEmead proudly ſings - Heroick conqueſts of vićtorious Kings: There (ifth'exuberance of a word may ſwell So high, that Angels may be ſaid to dwell) There dwelt that Virgin, that Arcadian glory, Whoſe rare compoſure did abſtract the ſtory Oftrue Perfection, modellizing forth The height of beauty, and admired worth; Her name Parthenia, whoſe unnam'd deſcent, Can ſerve but as a needleſs complement, To gild Perfection: She ſhall boaſt, alone, What bounteous Art, and Nature makes her own, Her Mother was a Lady, whom deep age More fill'd with honor, then diſeaſes; ſage, A modeſt Matron, ſtrict, reſerv'd, auſtere, Sparing in Speech, but libral of her Ear; Fierce to her foes, and violent where ſhe likes; Wedded to what her own opinionſtrikes: Frequent in Alms, and charitable Deeds, Of mighty ſpirit, conſtant to her Beads, Wiſely ſuſpicious; but what need we other Then this 2 She was the fair Partheniaes Mother, That rare Parthenia, in whoſe Heavenly eye Sits Maiden mildneſs, mixt with Majeſty; Whoſe ſecret power hath a double skill, By frowns or ſmiles to make alive, or kill; Her Cheeks are like to Banks of faireſt Flowers, Inricht with ſweetneſs from the Twilight ſhowers, Whereon thoſe jars, which were ſo often bred, Compoſed were, betwixt the white and red : Her Hair wrought down beneath her Ivory Knees, As if that Nature, to ſo rare a piece * , Had - ſ
Page 3

—-r -- Book Zirgalus and parthtnia. 3. Had meant a ſhadow ; laboring to ſhow, And boaſt the utmoſt that her hand could do: Like ſmalleſt Flax appear'd her Nymph-like Hair, Butonely Flax was not ſo ſmall, ſo fair: Her Lips like Rubies, and you'd think, within, Inſtead of Teeth, that orient Pearls had been: The whiteneſs of her dainty Neck you know, If ever you beheld the new-faln Snow; Her Swan-like Breſts were like two little sphears, Wherein, each azure line in view appears, Which, were they obvious but to every eye, All liberal Arts would turn Affronomy: - Her ſlender waſte, her Lilly-hands, her Arms - - - Idare not ſet to view; becauſe all Charms Forbidden are: my baſhful Muſe deſcends No lower ſtep : Here her Commiſſion ends, And by another Virtue doth enjoyn My Pen to treat Perfection more divine. . The chaſte Diana, and her Virgin crew Was but a Type of one that ſhould enſue In after-ages, which we find expreſt, And herefulfill'd in chaſte Parthenia's Breſt; True vertue was the obječt of her will; She could no ill, becauſe ſhe knew no ill; w Her thoughts were noble, and her words not laviſh Yet free, but wiſely weigh'd; more apt to raviſh, Then to entice; leſsbeautified with Art, Then natural ſweetneſs: In her gentle Heart Judgment tranſcended; from her milder Breſt Paſſion was not exiled, but repreſt: - Her voice excel'd; nay, had you heard her voice But warble forth, you might have had the choice, To \ . - - - -
Page 4

s == | . Žirgaing and partijenia. To take her for ſome ſmooth-facdcherubin, Or elſe ſome glorious Angel, that had been A treble ſharer in th’eternal joys, Such was her voice, ſuch was her heavenly voice: Merry, yet modeſt; witty, and yet wiſe; Not apt to toy, and yet not too too nice; Quick, but not raſh; Courteous, and yet not common; Not too familiar, and yet ſcorning no man: In brief, who would relate her praiſes well, Muſt firſt bethink himſelf, what’t is tº excel. Book I. . When theſe Perfections had enhaunc'd the name Ofrare Parthenia, nimble-winged Fame Grew great with honor, ſpreads her haſty Wings, Advanc'd her Trumpet, and away ſhe ſprings, Th'unmated glory of Parthenia's name: Who now but fair Parthenia 2 What report Can find admittance in th’Arcadian Court But fair Partheniaes: Every ſolemn Feaſt Muſt now be ſweetned, honor'd, and poſſeſt With high diſcourſes of Partheniaes glory, And every mouth muſt breath Partheniaes ſtory. The poet ſummons now his amorous Quill, And ſcorns aſſiſtance from the Sacred Hill: The ſweet-lipt Orator takes in hand to raiſe His prouder ſtile, to ſpeak Partheniaes praiſe. Thc curious Painter wiſely doth diſplace Fair Venus, ſets Parthenia in her place. The pleader burns his Books, diſdains the Law, And falls in love with whom his eyes neºr ſaw. Healthstothe fair Parthenia fly about At every board, whil'ſt others, more devout, / * And with her full-mouth'd blaſt ſhe doth proclaim
Page 5

Book I. Žirgalug, and parturnia, 3 Fire-balls of Lightning hurl’d by angry five, Build Idols to her, and adore the ſame, And Parrets learn to prate Partheniaes name: Some truſt to fame, ſome ſecretly diſprize Her worth ; ſome emulates, and ſome envies: Some doubt, ſome fear leſt laviſh Fame belie her, Andall that dare believe report, admire her. upon the borders of the Arcadian Land Dwelt a Laconian Lord: Of proud command, Lord of much people, youthful, and of fame, More great than good, Demagora, his name: Of ſtature tall, his body ſpare and meager, Thick ſhouldred, hollow cheek'd, and viſage eager, His gaſhful countenance ſwarthy, long and thin, And downeach ſide of his reverted Chin A lock of black neglected Hair ( befriended With Warts too ugly to be ſeen) deſcended; His rouling eyes were deeply ſunk, and hiewid Like fire: 'Tis ſaid, they bliſter'd where they view'd, upon his ſhoulders from his fruitful Crown. Arugged crop of Elf-locks dangled down: His hide all hairy; gariſh his attire, And his Complexion meerly Earth and Fire; Perverſe to all; extenuating what - Another did, becauſe he did it not: Maligning all mens ačtions but his own, - Not loving any and belov'd of none: - Revengeful, envious, deſperately ſtout, And in a word, to paint him fully out, That had the Monopoly, to fulfil All vice, the Hieroglyphick of all ill. He view’d Partheniae; face. As from above, Co3.
Page 6

6 2ſtgalus and pattlenia. Bookl Confound th' unarm'd beholder at a blow, And leave him ruin’d in the place; Even ſo The Peerleſs Beauty of Partheniaes eyes, . At the firſt ſight did conquer and ſurprize - The laviſhthoughts of this amazed lover, Who void of ſtrength to hide, or to diſcover The tyrannous ſcorching of his ſecretfires, - > Prompted by Paſſion, with himſelf conſpires: Accurs'd Demagoras | Into what a Feaver Hath one lookſtruck thy ſoul? O never, never To be recur'd 1 If I had done amiſ, - Hath Heaven no eaſier Plagues in ſtore, but this a Prometheus paints are not ſº ſharp as theſe, Ourſins yet labor'd both of one diſeaſe; Ourfaults are equal: Both ſtole fire from Heaven; Our faults alike, Why are our Plagues uneven a Be juſt, O make not ſuch º: Of equalſins: Be juſt, or elſe no gods: mhy ſend ye down ſuch Angels to the Earth, To mock poor mortals 2 or of mortal birth If ſuch a Heaven-like Paragon may be, Why do ye not wound her as well as me 2 But why do I implore your aids in vain, That are the higheſt Agents in my pain f Poor mretch! What hope of help can ye aſſure me, when omely ſhe that made the wound, can cure me 3 Divine Parthenia, Earths unvalued?ewel: ſpould thouhadſ been leſs glorious, or leſs cruel: mhen firſt thine eyes did to theſe eyes appear, I read the hiſtory of my ruin there, - Aſyneceſſary ruine: Heaven, nor Hell - Cin ſalve myſores, by help of Prayer or spell; . . - God's
Page 7

Book I. Žitgāiuš and Partbenia. 7 At firſt (unentred) findesaliveleſ; damp, Gods are uhjuſt 3 and if, with Charms, I haunt her, Her eyes are Counter-charms, to inchant th' enchanter: mhy do Ithus exulcerare my diſeaſe 2 By adding torments, hope Itofinde eaſe 2 Is not her cruelty enough, alone But mº' (bring freſh terments of my own 2 Chear “PDemagºras: 'Tis a wiſe mans part Not to loſe all, if his unpratīiºd art Servº not to gain; 4 Gameſter may not chaſe His change: It is ſome conqueſt, not to loſe. Look to thyſelf: Let no injurious blaſt - of cold deſpair chill thy green wound; too faſt For time to cure : Q, hope for no remiſºn of pain, till Cupidſendthee a phyſtian. She is a Woman ; if a Woman, then My title's good: Women were madefor men. She #4%man, though her heavenly brow - Write Angel, and may ſtoop, although not now. Women, by looks, will not be underāood Włntil their hearts adviſe with fleſh and blood. She is a Woman, There's no reaſºn why, But ſhe (perchance) may burn as well as 1. *e then, Demagoras, let Parthenia know The ſtrength of her own beauty, in thy wo: Fear not, what thou adorſº; begin to move, Chrº-ºroſ fºreruns the Aſphabetoflove. Tº halfperfeifed, what is once begun; 'She is a mºman, and ſhe muſt be ºn. - Like as a Swain, whoſe handshave made a vow, And ſworn alleageance to the peaceful Plow, * Preſt out for ſervice in the Martial Cam Bcleag’ring
Page 8

3 3rgains and partinia. rºi. . Beleag’ring every joynt, as often ſwounds . . . As here he views his Sword, or thinks of wounds, At length (not finding any means for flying, ". . . Switcht and ſpur'd on with deſpirate fear of dying) He hews, he hacks, and in the midſt he goes, And freſhly deals about his frantick blows; Even ſo Demagora, whoſe unbred faſhion. . … Had never yet ſubſcrib'd to loves ſweet paſſion, Being call'd a Combatant to Cupids field, Trembles, and ſecretly reſolves to yield The day without a parley, till at length, Fiercely tranſported by th’untutor'd ſtrength Of his own paſſion, he himſelf aſſures, That deſpirate torments muſt have deſp'rate cures: And thus to the divine Partheniaes ears Applies his Speech, devoid of doubts and fears, (1) Faireſ of Creatures, if my ruder Tongue, To right it ſelf, ſhould do your patience wrong, And lawleſ, paſſion makes it too too free, O blame your heavenly beauty and not me : It was thoſe eyes, thoſe precious eyes thatſº Enforc'd my Tongue to ſpeak, or Heart to burſt: From thoſe dear eyes I firſt receiv'd that wound, Which ſeeks for cure, and cannot be made ſound, But by the hand that ſtruck: To you alone, 1ſue for help, that elſe muſt hºpe for none: Then crown my joys, thou Kºś deſpair, And be as merciful as thou art fair ; Nature, t|
Page 9

- -- - - \ - ~ - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - ſ - - - - - - º * * - i º - - - : -- | - | - - - * - - | - - | - - - - - - - - - - - º - - - | - - -- * - - - - - - • - - - - - º ~, - - t - e - - - - - sº -- - "I ----- - ..~~~ -- .* ***::::: * ~ * ~ - t - | - - - - - * *

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 10

- - - - - - - - º - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - * -- - - - - - -- - - - - - - - - - * - . \ - - - - - - - t - - - - - - - - - * - - - - - - * - - - - - - - - - 1. - - - - -- - r - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - º l - - - - - - ** - * - - - - - - - - -- - - - - - - - - - -- - *- - º * f * – º – -- - - - - * -- - - - • *- - - - - - -- - r - -- - r - - - - - - - - - - - - -- *.*. - - - ----- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - * * * . - - .-: - - - - - - - - -- *...* - - - - º z - - - - - -* - - - - - - - * - rº. - -- w - - - * - "… -- w - --- w - * . - ---. . º. is - - # , - - :- - - t - -- - ** * *** -- - - - - - **- : * ~ * - -- - - *. - - - - * . . . ºn.". - - - - - - ", a º -- - - - - - - - - - - ... " *. - - - - - y i-" , - - - - - - - - ; : " ' -- - º - - - - - - - - - - ~ - - - - - - - * * * - - * -- - - f º `. - - - - - - * . - - - - - - - - . - *- - - - - r -- - - - - - - - -- - * - º - -- º - * * - - - º -- - - - - - * , - * - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - w --- * - - - - - i - -- - - r - * , - - - ------- - - ------ * * - - - - - - * - - - - - s … ----- º - - - * - - - -º-º: - -- - - - -- - - ** - - - - - - - - - - - - - * - - - - - - - - * : * ~ * - - - - - - * - -- - - - * - | - - - - | o - ~ -- - - - - * - - -- - - - - --- -- º - - - - - - ~ --- l - , - - - - - , “ - - - - - - _ - - - - * - - - - ſ - . - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - * - - - - - - - * -- -, * * - - - - - *~ * -- - - - - - * > - “... *-i- - | - - - * - ** ** - - - - - - - - * - - *

Page 11

- - - - t - bookſ. 2ſtgalug and parthenia. Tº } Nature, (the bounty of whoſe liberal hand - - Made thee the jewel of the Arcadian Land) - Intended in ſº rare a prize, to boaſt Her maſter-piece : Hid jewels are but lºſt; Shine them, and rob not Nature of her due, But honor her, as ſhe hath honor'd you. Let not the beſt of all her works lie dead . Inthe nice Casket of a Maidenhead: What ſhe would have reveal’d, O do not ſmother; Th'art made in vain, unleſs thou make another: Give me thy heart, and for that gift of thine, Left thou ſºft want a heart, I'll give thee mine; - As richly fraught with love, and laſting duty, n As thou with Wirtue, or thine eyes with beauty. - Why doſt thoufrown 2 Why does that Heavenly brow, AVof ºff, wrinkles, ſhew a wrinklemon: . Send forth thy brighter Sun-ſhine, and th: while, O lend me but the twilight of a ſmile : . Give me one amorous glance ; why ſtandſ; thou mute f Diſcloſe thoſe ruby Lips, and grant my ſuit: Speak (love, ) or if thy doubtful mind be bent To ſilence, let that ſilence be conſent: '. Norbeg I love of alms, although in part, My words may ſeem tº emplead my own deſert. Diſdain me not, although my thºughts deſcend Below themſelves, tº enjoy ſo fair a friend. I, that have oft with tears been ſºught tº, ſke : And Queens have been his ſervants, that ſerves yon: The beauties of all Greece have been at ſtrife | To win the name of great Demagoras wife, And been deſpi’sd, not worthy to obtain So high an honor; what they ſought (in vain) B 2. M
Page 12

I 2 ºrgatus and 49artbenia. Bookſ Ihere preſent thee with, as thine on’m due, º It being an honor fit for none but you: speak then (my ſove) and let my Lips make known That I am either thine, or not mine own., Have you beheld when freſh Aurora's eye Sºnds forth her early beams, and by and by . Withdraws the glory of her face, and ſhrowds Her cheeks behind a ruddy Mask of Clouds, Which, who believe in Erra Pater ſay, Preſages wind, and bluſtry ſtorms that day. Such were Partheniae; looks: In whoſe fair face Roſes and Lillies, late had equal place, But now, 'twixt Maidenbaſhfulneſs, and ſpleen, Roſes appear'd, and Lillies were not ſeen: She paus’d a while, till at the laſt, ſhe breaks Her long kept angry ſilence, thus, and ſpeaks. ſ My Lord, Had your ſtrong Oratory but the art, To make me coaſtious of ſo great deſert, - - As you perſivade, Iſhould be bound in duty To praiſe your Rhet’rick a you praiſe my beauty: Or if the frailty of my judgment could * Flatter my thoughts ſo groſly, as to hold rour words for currant, you might boldly dare Count me a fooliſh, as you term me fair. If yots vie Courtſhip, Fortune knows that I Hiſ e not ſo ſtrong a game, to ſee the vie: V. Ala, my skill durff ze: er undertake - -- To play the game, where hºarts be ſet at ſtake : Nº dº ºff the loſs he great, mbea ſuch have bin sel om 'ſerv'd to ſave themſelves that win :
Page 13

Book I, 24rgalug and Patti).cnta. 13 A Tou crave my Heart, my Lord, you crave withal, Too great a miſchief: My poor heart's too ſmall To fill the concave of ſo great a breſt, Whoſe thoughts can ſcorn the amorous requeſt Of love-ſick Queens, and can requite the vain, And fačious ſuits of Ladies with diſdain: Stoop not ſo low beneath your Self'(great Lord) To love Parthenia: Shall ſo poor a word stain your fair lips, whoſe merits do proclaim A more tranſcendent Fortune, than that name Cangive 2 Call down Jove's winged Purſuivant, Andgive his tongue the power to inchant Some eaſie Goddeſs in your name, and treat A marriage fitting ſo ſublime, ſo great A mind as yours, andfill the fruitful Earth • WithHeroes, ſprung from ſo divine a birth: - Partheniaesheart could never yet aſpire So high : Her home-bred thoughts durſt ne'r deſire Sofond an honor matcht with ſo great pride, To hºpefor that, which ...}. been deny'd. Be wiſe, my Lord 5 vouchſafe not to repeat S’anſit a ſuit : Be miſe as you are great : Advance your noble thoughts, hazard no more To mrack your fortunes on ſo fleet a ſhore, That to the wiſer world, it may be known, The leſ; y are mine, the more you are your own. Like as a guilty priſoner, upon whom Offended Juſtice lately paſther doom, Stands trembling by, and hopeleſs to prevail, Bauls not for mercy: but to the loath'd Jail -" Drags his ſad Irons, and from thence commends "-- A haſty ſuit to his ſeleśted friends, B 3 That
Page 14

Targalus and partººnia. Bookſ. That by the virtue of a quick Reprieve, The wretch might have ſome few days more to live: Even ſo Demagoras, whoſe rewounded heart º Had newly felt the unexpected ſmart And ſecret burthen of a deſperate doom, Replies not, takes no leave, but quits the room, And in his diſcontented minde, revolves . . . Ten thouſand thoughts, and at the laſt reſolves What courſe to run, relying on no other But the aſſiſtance of Partheniaes Mother. Forthwith his fierce miſguided paſſion drove His wandring ſteps to the next neighboring grove, Akeen Steletto in his trembling hand . . . . . He rudely grip'd ; upon his Lips did ſtand - A milk-white froth ; his eyes like flames; ſometimes He curſes Heaven; himſelf; and then the times; Rails at the proud Parthenia; raves; deſpairs; , And from his head rends off his tangled hairs; Curſes the womb that bare him; bans the Fates, And drunk with Spleen, he thus deliberates: . . * Why dy'ſ thou not, Demagoras, when as death Lends thee a weapon? Can the whining breath Of diſcontents and paſſion, ſend relief To thy diſtrađion, or aſſivage thy grief? why mov'ſ thou not the god; 2 or, rather, why • Do'ſ not tontemn, and ſcorn their power, and die 2 But ſtay ! Of whom doff thou complain P. A woman. To whºm (fºnd man) doff thou complain *, A woman. And ſhall a womans frownshave power to grieve theef Orſhall a womans iranton ſmile relieve thee f : ..., Fie, fir, Demagoras, ſhall a womans eye Prevail, to make the flout Demagoras die, Aad
Page 15

Bºi. Targains and parthenia, v. ºf * 2 l And leave to after times an entred name Ith calender of fools?, Rouze up for ſhame Thy waſtedſpirits ; whet thy ſpleen, and live To be reveng’d: She, ſhe, that would not give Admittance to thyºft. love, muſt drink The potion of thy hate: Stir then the ſink of all thypaſſion ; where thou canſ not gain By fairer language, Tarquin like conſtrain. r But holdthy hand, Demagoras, and adviſe ; Art gives advantage oft where force denies: #. thy fury: Make Partheniaes Mother -- The means: One Adamant willcut another: Sweeten thy Lips with amorous Oratory; Affett her tender heart with the ſad #ory of thydear love: Extol Partheniaes beauty: But moſt of all, urge that deſerved duty Thou ow'ſ her virtue, and make that the ground of thy firſt love, that gave thy heart the wound: AMingle thy words with ſighs; and it is meet, If thou canſ force a tear, to let her ſee’t, Againſt thy will. Let thyfalſe tongue forbear No vows, and though thou beeſtforſworn, yet ſwear: Ifere thy barren Lips ſhall chance to pauſe, For want of words; Parthenia is the cauſe, who hath benum'd thy heart; if ere they go Beyond their lifts, Parthenia made them ſo : withal, be ſure, when ere thouſhalt advance The daughters virtues, let the glory glance ſupon the prudent Mother: Women care not To hear too much of virtue, if they ſhare not. When thus thouhaft prepar'd her melting ear To ſºft attention, cloſely, in the rear B 4 of -
Page 16

#6 ºrgalus and Partbenta. Book i. of thy diſcourſe, prefer thy ſad Petition %;#.%; the condition of a diſtreſſed lover, andafford. In thy behalf, a Mothers timely word; . . . . . . So ſhalt thou wreak thy vengeance by a wile, And make the Mother Baud to her own child. . . . " He pauſed not ; but like a raſh Projector (Whoſe frantick Paſſion was ſupream Director) Fixthis firſt thoughts, impatient of the ſecond, Which might been bettered by advice, and reckon'd All time but loſt, which he beſtowed not On th’execution of his hopeful plot: Forthwith his nimble paces he divided Towards the Summer-Palace, where reſided The fair Partheniaes Mother ; boldly enters, And after mutual complement adventers . To break the Ice of his diſſembled grief: Thus he complains, and thus he begs relief. (2) Madam, - - The hopeful thriving of my ſuit depends 1/pon yourgeodneſs, and it recommends It ſelf unto your favor, from whoſe hand It muſt have ſentence," or to fall, or ſtand: - Thrice Three times hath the Sovereign of the might, Rºpair’d her empty horns with borrored light, Since theſe ſad eyes, theſe beauty-liſted eyes, if ere firicken by a light that did ariſe y - - - - Frnºr
Page 17

–––––– ·- -~ |- |-！ |--|- |-|-|-*|- ·！* |- | |-|- |- : · |- * * |-|- % |-· · ·} | ? *… # ·# ſı - - - º · · * ： , ! · -|- · , ！ |- … *· |-, ， |-|-* - *v |- -

Page 18

- THE N ºr K PUBLIC iſ CRAR - -- - - | Aston, Lenox ans : Thi-ºn roundaTorº. -- -
Page 19

Book. 2irgalug and parthtnia. 12 º Fromyour bleft womb, whoſe maſwagedſmart Hathpierc'd my Soul, and wounded my poor Heart: It is the fair Parthenia, whoſe divine Andglorious virtueled theſe eyes of mine To their own ruin: Like a wantom Flie, Idallied with the flame of her bright eye, Till Ihave burn'd my wings. O, if to love Be held a ſin, the guilty gods above - (Being fellow-ſimmers with us, and commit The ſelfſame crimes) may easily pardon it. o thrice divine Parthenia, that haſ got Aſacred priviledg which the Gods have not, . If thouhaft doom'd that Iſhall be bereaven of my loath'd life, yet let me die forgiven; And welcome death that with one happy blow Gives me more eaſe, than life could ever do. Madam, to whom ſhould my ſad words appeal But you? Ala, to whom ſhould I reveal , My dying thoughts, but unto you that gave Being to her, that hath the power to ſave My waſted life; the language of a Mother Moves more than tears, that trickle from another. With that a well-diſſembled drop did ſlide From his falſe eyes. The Lady thus reply'd; My Honorable Lord, If my untimely anſwer hath prevented Some farther words, yourpaſſion would have vented, Pardon my hafte: which in a ruder faſhion - Sought onely to divide you from your pºſion : The love you bear Parthenia, muſt claim 7 he priviledge of mine ear, and in her name, : (Though

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 20

º - zo 3rgalug and 19artbenia. Book I. (Though from an abſent mind, as yet unknown) Return Ithanks with intereſt of mine own. The little judgment, that the gods have lent Her downy years (though in a ſmallextent) Does challenge the whole freedom of her choice, In the reſignment of a Mothers voice: The ſprightly fancies of a Virgins mind Enter themſelves, and hate to be confind: - The hidden Embers of a lovers fire Deſire no bellows, but their own deſire; And like to Dedalus his Forge, if blown, Burns dim and dies; blazes, if let alone: Lovers affect without adviſement, that which being moſt perſuaded to, they hate. My Lord, adjourn your paſſion, and refer The fortune of your ſuit to time, and her. Like to a Pinace is a lovers mind, The ſail his fancie is ; a ſtorm of wind His uncontrouled Paſſion ; The Stears - His Reaſon ; Rocks and Sands, are doubts and fears: - rour ſtorm being great, like a wiſe Pilot bear But little Sail, and ſtoutly plie the Stear: Leave then the violence of your thoughts to me, My Lord, too haſty gameſters over ſee. - Go, move Parthenia; and Juno's bleſſing w Attend your hopeful ſuit, in the ſuppreſſing - Loves common evils ; and if her warm deſire Shen, but a ſpark, leave me to blow the fire. Go, loſe no time: Lovers muſt be laborious ; * ~ * { Aſy Lord, go proſperous, and return vićtorious. With that, femagoras, (proſtrate on the ground, As if his ears had heard that bleſſed ſound, Where-

Page 21

Book I Tzirgalus and particnia, 2, w Wherewith the Delphian Oracle acquites The accepted ſacrifice) performs the Rites Of quick devotion, to that heavenly voice, Which fed his Soul with the malignant joys Of vow’d revenge, up from the floor he ſtarts, Bleſſes the tongue that bleſt him, and departs. ~~ By this time, had the Heaven-ſurrounding Steeds . Quell'd their proud courage, turn'd their fainting heads Into the lower Hemiſphere, to cool - Their flaming Noſtrils in the Weſtern Pool, When as the dainty and mollitious Air Had bid the Lady of the Palace, ſhare In her refined pleaſures, and invited Her gentle ſtepts, fully to be delighted ~ In thoſe ſweet walks, where Floras liberal hand. Had given more freely, than to all the Land. There walked ſhe ; and in her various mind, Projects and caſts about which way to find The progreſs of the young Partheniaes heart; - Likes this way: Then a ſecond thought does thwart The firſt ; likes that way; then a third the ſecond: One while ſhe likes the match, and then ſhe reckon'd? Demagoras virtues: Now her fear entices -" Her thoughts to alter; then ſhe counts his vices: Sometimes ſhe calls his vows and oathsto minds . . . . Another while,thinks oaths and words but wind. She likes,diſlikes, her doubtful thoughts do vary: Reſolves, and then reſolves the quite contrary. - - One while ſhe fears that his malign aſpect Will give the Virgin cauſe to diſaffect: . And then propounds to her ambitious thoughts His wealth, the Golden cover of all faults : --
Page 22

22. 2[tgalug and patrºnia. - Book. And, from the Chaos of her doubt, digeſts Her fears; creates a word of wealth; and reſts. With that, ſhe ſtrait unfixther faſtned eyes From off the ground; and looking up, eſpies The fair Parthenia, in a lonely bowre, Spending thetreaſure of an Evening hour: There ſate ſhe, reading the ſweet ſad diſcourſes Ofcariclea's love; the entercourſes Of whoſe mixt fortunes taught her tender heart To feel the ſelf-ſame joy, the ſelf ſame ſmart: She read, ſhe wept; and,as ſhe wept,ſhe ſmil'd, Asif her equal eyes had reconcil'd i. Th’extreams of joy and grief: She clos'd the Book, Then open'd it, and with a milder look, She pities lovers ; muſing then a while, She teaches-ſmiles to weep, and tears to ſmile : At length,her broken thoughts ſhe thus diſcovers. wnconſtant ſtate of poor distreſſed lovers Is all extream in love? No mean at all: No draughts indiff'rent : Either Honey or Gall? Hath Cupids univerſe no tempºrate Zone 2 Either a torrid, or a frozen one : Alas, alas, poor Lovers I As ſhe ſpake - Thoſewords from her diſcloſed Lips, there brake Agentle ſigh; and after that another With that, ſteps in her unexpected Mother. Haveye beheld, when Titans luſtful head Hath newly div'd into the Sea-green Bed Of Thetis, how the baſhful Horizon (Enforc’d to ſee what ſhould be ſeen by none) Looks red for ſhame, and bluſhes to diſcover Th’inceſtuous pleaſures of the Heaven-born lover: Se \
Page 23

Bookſ, argăluş and Parthenia. 23 solook'd Parthenia, when the ſudden eye of her unwelcome Mother did deſcry Her ſecret paſſion: The Mothers ſmile Brought forth the Daughtersbluſh;and levelcoyL They ſmild and bluſht; one ſmile begat another: The Daughter bluſht, becauſe the jealous Mother Smild on her; and the filent Mother ſmil'd To ſee the conſcious bluſhing of her child: - At length grown great with words, ſhe did awake Her forced ſilence, and ſhe thus beſpake. Bluſh not, my faireſt Daughter; 'tis moſhame To pity lovers, or lament that flame, , , , which worth and beauty kindles in the breš; *Tis charity to ſuccor the diffreſt. v The diffuſition of a generous heart Mak's every grief her own; at leaſt, bears part. what Marble, ah what Adamantime ear E’re heard the flames of Troy, without a tear : - º Much more the ſcorching of a lovers fire, \ (mhoſe deſperate feweli, his own deſire) Mayboldly challenge every gentle heart ro be joynt tenant in his ſecret ſmart. why doſ; thou bluſh 2 why did thoſe pearly tears ... Slide down f Fear mot: This arbor hath no ears : • Here’s mone but we ; ſpeak then : It is noſhame To ſhed a tear; thy Mother did the ſame : . Say, hath the winged wanton, with his dirt, Sent ere a meſſage to thy wounded heart 2 Steak,in the name of Hymen, I conjure thee: If ſo, I have a balſam ſhall recure thee, Ifear,I fear,the young Laconian Lord Hath lately left ſome indigeited word
Page 24

34 2irgalug and 12áttúenia. Book1. In thy coldſtomack; which, for want of art " ' " " ` 1 doubt, I doubt, lies heavy at thy heart. . . . . . . . . . . iſ that be all, revealing brings relief; Silence in love, but ; a grief; i . . . . . . . . . . Hid Sorrow's deſperate, not to beenāur'd, -- - mhich being but diſclos'd, is eaſly cur'd: ... . . . . . . Perchance thou lºft Demagoras, and would?ſmother Thy cloſe affeifion from thy angry Mother, . . . . . Andreap the dainty fruits of love unſeen : . ." . I did the like, or thou hadſ; never been. . " " " ' ". . Stoln goods are ſweeteſt... if it be thy mind . To love in ſecret, I will be as blind As he that wounded thee; or if thou dare Acquaint thy Mother, then a Mothers care shall be redoubled, till thy thoughts acquire The ſweet fraition of thy choice deſire: . . . . . . Thou lov'ſ Demagoras: If thy Lips deny... . . . . Thy conſtious Heart muſt give thy £ips the lie : . . And if thy liking countermand my will, º Thy puniſhment ſhall be to love him ſtill: Then love him ſtill, and let his hopes inherit The crown belonging to ſº fair a merit; . . . . . . His thoughts are noble, and his fame appears . . . To ſpeak, at leaſt, an age above his years: The blood of his increaſing honor ſprings From the high ſtock of the Arcadian Kings. The gods have bleſt him with a liberal hand, Enricht him with the prime of all the Land: Honor and wealth attend his Gates, and what . . . . Can he command that he poſſeſſes not : All which, and more, (if Mothers can divine) The fortune of thy beauty hath made thine; - - - - -- - - - * , , , - - • * Aſe ‘. . . . . . . . . . . .
Page 25

fºr Targaingº partººnia. 25 He is thy Captive, and thy conquering eies Have took him priſoner; he ſubmits, and /ies At thy dear mercy, hoping ne'r to be . . . . . . . Ranſºm'd from death, by any price, but thee. . - Wrong not thy ſelf, in being too too mite, , , . . . . . And what(perchance)may not be profer'd twice, Accept at first : It is a fooliſh mind , sº To be too coy: Occaſion's bald behind. .. 'Tis not the common work of every day \ T'afford ſuch offers; take them while you may, Times alter: routh and Beauty are but blaſts, uſe then thy time,whill youth and beauty laſts: For if that loath’ā and infamous reproach Of a ſtald Maid, but offer to incroach , lipon opinion, th’art in eſtimation, Like garments kept till they be out of fiſhion: Thy worth,thy wit,thy virtues all muſt ſtand Like goods at out-cries, priº’d at ſecond hand; Reſolve thee then, t'enlarge thy firgin-life With th' honorable freedom of a ſºft : And let the fruits of that bleſ; marriage be A living pledge betwixt my child and ºve. \ So ſaid, the fair Parthenia (in whoſe heart Her ſtrong affection yet had got the ſtart Of her obedience) makes a ſudden pauſe, Strives with her thoughts 3 objects the binding laws Offilial duty to her beſt affection, Sometimes ſubmits unto her oxvil cieótion, Sometimes unto her Mothers: thus divided In her diſtraćted fancy, ſometimes guided By one deſire, and ſometimes by ancther, She thus reply'd to her attentive Mother: - . C - Aſadam, *
Page 26

as Tāzgalug and partinia. Tººl |- Aſadam, - Think not Parthenia,under a pretence º of ſilence, ſtudies diſobedience: or by the crafty ſlowneſs of reply, Borrows a quick advantage to deny: It lies not in your power, to command - Beyond my will; unto your tender hand I here ſurrender up that little All rougave me, freely to diſpoſe withall: The gods forbid, Parthenia ſhould reſiſt mhat you command, command you what you lift : But pardon me, the young Laconian Lord . . Hath made aſſault, but neveryet could board This heart of mime: I wept, I wept indeed, But my miſèonſtrued ſtreams did ne'r proceed From Cupids ſpring: This blubber’d Book makes known Whoſe grief; I wept, I wept not for mime omn; My lºwly thoughts durff neveryet aſpire The leaſt degree tomards the proud deſirº Of ſo great honor, to be call'd his wife, - For whom ambitious Queens have been at ſtrife: He ſu'd fºr love, and ſtrongly did importune My heart, more pleaſed with a meaner fortune : A4, breaft pas marble, and my heart forgot All pitty, for indeed, I lov’d him not : But Madam, you, to mhoſe more wiſe direétions I bend the ſtouteſ of my raſh affeitons, roº have commandeil, and your will ſhall be The ſquare ºf my uneven deſires, and me: Ple pračiſe duty, and my deedſball ſhow it: , , A ſe pračiſe love, though Cupid never know it. When
Page 27

Bookſ. 2ſtgalug and Pattituta. 27 When great Baſilius (he whoſe Princely hand - Nouriſht long peace in the Arcadian Land) With triumph brought to his rendunedCourt His new eſpouſed Queen, was great reſort Of Foreign States, and Princes, to behold The truth,that unbeliev'd report hath told Offair Gynecia's worth: Thither repair'd The Cyprian Nobles, richly all prepard - In warlike furniture, and well addreſt, With ſolemn Jouſts to glorifie the Feaſt Of Marriage Royal, lately paſt between . Th’Arcadian King, and his thrice noble Queen, The fair Gynecia, in whoſe fice and breſt, Nature, and curious art had done their beſt, To ſum that rare perfeótion, which (in brief) ; Tranſcends the power of a ſtrong belief: Her Syre was the Cyprian King, whoſe fame Receiv'd more honor from her honor'd name; Than if he had with his vićtórious hand, Unſceptred half the Princes in the Land: To tell the glory of this Royal Feaſt, The Bridegrooms ſtate, and how the Bride was dreſt; The princely ſervice, and the rare delights; The ſeveral names and worth of Lords and Knights; The quaint Impreſa's, their deviſeful ſhows; - Their Martial ſports, their oft redoubled blows 3 The courage of this Lord, cr that proud Horſe, Who ran, who got the Letter, who the worſe, Is not my task; not lies it in my way, To make relation of it: Heraulds may : Yet fame and honor have ſelečted one From that illuſtrious crue; and him alone ... " C 2 Have
Page 28

as 2irgalug and 49atthenia. Book I. Have recommended to my careful Quill, Forbidding that his honor ſhould lie ſtill Among the reſt, whom fortune and his ſpirit . . . . That day,had crowned with a vićtor's merit: . His name was Argales, in Cyprus born: And (if what is not ours, may adorn Our proper fortunes) his Blood Royal ſprings : His out-ſide had enough to ſatisfie º . . .", The expectation of a curious eye; ºl * * ºn - - r - Nature was too too prodigal of her beauty, ºi, , , From th’ancient ſtock of the great Cyprian Kings; wº - To make him halfſofair whom fame and duty He ought to honor, call’d ſo often forth, T’approve the excellence of his manly worth: … His mind, was richful furniſht with the treaſure Of Moral knowledge,in ſoliberal meaſure, Not to be proud: So valiant and ſo ſtrong Of noble courage, not to dare a wrong: Friendly to all men.iriyard but with few; Faſt to his old friends, and unapt for new : Lord of his word,and maſter of his paſſion, Serious in buſineſs, choice in recreation; Not too miſtruſtful, and yet wiſely wary; Hard to reſolve, and then as hard to vary: And to conclude, the world could hardly find So rare a body with ſo rare a mind. Thrice

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 29

- - - - - -- - - - - - - \ - - - -- - - º ... * * -- - * * * ----- - - • * * - * - - - - - - - \ - ... ** - -- -**** * * * * - - - - - * -- - - - * --> -->. - - - - - - - f -- --------- - * … *, * * * - - º - - - - - * * * ~ * ** * - -- ---- - - - - - - - -- - - -----, 2-rº- ºr - - * * - * * --- --- ** . - f - -- º **** - - - -- - - - - - - - - - * * * - . . * * - - - - ** *** - - sº ºf * *s -- * - ~ * s, a - - - *:: - **- - - - a º - - --- . . . . . . . - - - - ** ** - - º * - - - * * - - - - * - - --> - - - - --- --> - - -- - --- - - - -> - - - * * , - * --> *- - - - - - ------ - * - - - º - - *. - - - t - - - -- - - - - - -- - - . - - \ - -* x - - - -

Page 30

*w-º º § ~~~~~~ --> --&S-Sº --~~E---> º º º _-

Page 31

Book. 2:rgalus and 19artbenia. 3 I (3) - - - - - - --- I º Thrice had the bright ſurveyer of the Heaven Divided out the days and nights by even tº And equal hours, ſince this child of fame . . (Invited by the glory of her name, ) , ..., Firſt view’d Parthenias face, whoſe mutual eye Shot equal flames, and with the ſecrettye, Of undiſclos'd affection, joyn'd together . . Their yieldinghearts, their loves unknown to eitfier: - Both dearly lov’d; the more they ſtrove to hide , , , Their love, affection they the more deſcry’d. It lies beyond the power of art to ſmother º Affektion, where one virtue findes another.' . One was their thoughts, and their deſires one, And yet both lov'dunknown; belov'dunknown: . One was the Dart, that at the ſelf-ſame time Was ſent, that wounded her,that wounded him, , , , , Both hop'd, both fear'd alike, both joy'd, both griev'd; Yet, where they both could help, was none reliev'd; Two lov’d, and two beloved were, yet none But two in all, and yet that all but one, By this time had their barren Lips betray'd Their timorous ſilence; now they had diſplay'd Loves ſanguine colours, whilſt the winged Child Sate in a Tree, and clapt his hands, and ſmil'd To ſee the combat of two wounded friends. He ſtrikes and wounds himſelf, while ſhe defends That would be wounded, for her pain proceeds, And flows from his, and from his wound ſhe bleeds ; C 4 - She -
Page 32

*Târgălug and partmenta. Trogi. She plays at him, and aiming at his breſt, Pierc'd her own heart: And when his hand addreſt The blow to her fair boſom, there it found His own dear heart, and gave that heart the wound: At length both conquer'd and yet both did yield, - Both loſt the : , and yet both won the field: . . . . ; And as the warfare of their tongues did ceaſe, irº; ºr, Their Lips gave earneſt of a joyful peace.” tº fºr . . But O the hideous chances that attend 2: . . . . A lovers pro reſs to his journies end iſ . . . . How many deſp'rate rubs, and #" wait.'..cº.i..., , , Each minute on his miſerable ſtateſ , , , , º, . . . ») : His hopes do build, what ſtraight his fears deſtroy:. . . ; Sometimes he ſurfeits with exceſs offey: Yat fivº Sometimes deſpairing eye to find relief, tº . . . . He roars beneath the tyranny of grief; º:: * * * * And when loves current runs with greateſt force; zºº ºf Some obvio's miſchief ſtill diſturbs the courſe : 19, is: '. Forlo, no ſooner the diſcoyered flame . . . . . . . . . . . " Of theſe new parted lovers did proclaim . . . . . . . Loves ſacred Jubilee,but the Virgin Mother - ºr (The poſture of whoſe viſagedid diſcover - Some ſerious matter, harbºring in her breſt) ... : : Enters the room: Half angry, half injeſt, ... o. - She thus began: Aſy deareſt child, this might, Jºhen as the ſilent dirkneſs did invite. , ſº - º i -- , , f' ſ :

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 33

: - - - ~ - - - ...” *… - ºr , , -> - wº -- .** - - - - - - - - --- --- -- - **** º * > * - * * * * wº - - - -- - --- - * = --- - - -a- --- : * **** - ------ - --- - - - … w - -** -- - - w - - e - -- * * * t - - - - ** - - - - - - - - - * *. -- - - - * * - - r - - - - - - - - - -- - - - - - - - - - * * * * * * - - - - - - - * * ---> * -** ** - - ºr . * ** * . º - - t - º - - / - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - º - - - - t - * - - - e / - -

Page 34

： ， ！ ， ， ， ----- ---- ------ ----+---------- - - - - • ••••••••••• • • • • • • • • • • • • ---- - ---

Page 35

--- → \ Boºk 3rgalus and partbtuſa. 3% º * * . (4) - - - y Mine e es to ſlumber, fundry thoughts poſſeſ My ... mind, and robb’d *:::::::3 * Iſlept not, till the early Bugle-horn º t of Chaunticlere had ſummon'd in the morn. . . 7° attend the light, and nurſe the new born Day. At laſt, when Morpheus, with his Leaden Key Hadlock'd myſenſes, and inlarg'ath power of my Heav'n-guided fancy, for an hºr Iſlumbred; and before my ſlumbring eyes, - One,and the #ſame *::::::::thrice; Iwak'd; and being frighted at the priſon, , , . Perceiv'd the god, had made an Apparition. AMy dream mathi:; Me thought I ſaw theefitting Dreſt like a Princely Bride, with Robes befitting The State of Majeſty; thy Nymph-like Hair . . . . . — Edeſly diſhevel’d, and thy Brows did bear 4 Cypreſs wreaths and (thrice three moneths expir'd) Thy pregnant Womb grew heavy, and requir’d … . . . Lucina's aid; with that me thought I ſaw A team of harneſt Peacocks fiercely draw º A fiery chariot from theffiting skie, , , , , , º wherein there ſat the glorious Majeſty ...” Of great Saturnia, on whoſe train attended - 4 hoſt of goddeſſes; Juno deſcended sº . . . From out the flaming Chariot, and bleſ? : … Thy painful Womb; Thy pains a while increaft, At lengthſhe laid her gentle palms upon Thy fruitful flank, and there was born a ſon. She
Page 36

36 24rgalug and Pattijtnía. Book I. She made thee Mother of a ſmiling Boy, And after, bleſ thee with a dſothers joy, She kift the Babe, whoſe fortune ſhe foretold; For on his head ſhe ſet a crown of gold; Forthwith,as if the Heavens had clºven infunder, º, ºr Methought I heard the *::::::: of thunder : \ . . . . . The hail ſtorm'd down, and yet the skie was clear, º, . . . . Some Hailſtones that deſcended did appear, ºr iſ t v. As Orient Pearls, ſome like refined Gold, . . . . . . . . . . . . whereat the goddeſs turn'd, and ſaid, Behºld,'..." . . . . Great fove hath ſent a gift 3 goforth, and take'?: . . . . Thus having ſpoke, ſtºvaniſht, and I wak'd :'': º, . . 1 wak'd, and waking trembled; for I knew : ' ' '. They were no idle paſſages, that grew . . . . . . . . From my diffempered thoughts: 'twas not a vain . . . . . Deluſion roving from a troubled hrain. A "...º.º.º. It was a viſion, and the gods foreſpake . . . . . . . º.º. tº Partheniaesfortune? Gods cannot miſtake. y.º.º.º. I lik'd the dream, wherein the Heavens foretold ºn A Thy joyful Marriage, and the ſhower of Gold ºn . . . . Betakened wealth: The Infants Golden Crown, ºn tº 3 - Enſuing honor: Juno's coming down; *...*.*.*.*.*.*, * * A ſafe deliverance; and the ſmiling Bºy', " . . . . . . . Sum'd up the total of a Mothers joy: * * * * *** * * *. But what the wreath of Cypreſs(that was ſº -**) tº upon thy nuptial Brows) preſig'd, as yet.' . . . . . º.º.º. The gods keep from me: If that ſecret do. . . . .” - sº Portend and evil,Heav'n keep it from thee too. ' ' " . . - Adviſe Parthenia: Seek not to withſtand The plot wherein the gods vouchſafea hand: Submit thy will to theirs ; what they injoym, Mºſt be ; nor lies it in my power, or thine To .*
Page 37

Bºokſ ºrgalus; and battpºnia, 37 Tºontradiº Endeavor to fulfil . . . -º-º: * ~ * , , ºr , What elſe maſſ come to paſt againſt thy will; ... ºt . Noſy #. filial duty thou # .. ſº The gods and me, or ifº, elſe more dear, Canforce obedience; as t ---------- - - - - - - At the gods hands, in greateſ time of need; By Heaven, by Hell, by all the powers above, There conjure Parthenia to remove - All fond conceits, that labor to disjoym r - - "... "...",".. . . - ‘. . . * * mhat, Heaven hath knit, Demagoras heart and thine The gods are faithful; and their viſãomskº mhat's better for us mortals, than we do: ". Doubt not(my child) the gods cannot deceiv What Heaven does offer, fear not to receive.”" with thankful hands, paſs not ſº ſlightly over The dear affe:#ion off true a lover : . . . . . . Pity his flames, relieve his tortur’d breſ, That findes abroad nojoy, at home no reſt: º But, like a wounded Hart before the Hounds, That flies with Cupid's javelin in his wound; ; stir up thyrak'd up embers of deſire; The gods will bring in fewel and blow the fire; - - - - - - ‘. . . Begentle; let thy cordial ſmiles revive . . . . His waſted ſpirits, that onely cares to live To do thee honor: It was Cupid’s will, The Dart he ſent, ſhould onely wound, not kill ; rield them : and let the engº'd gods pour doivº Their fromis'd blºffing; on thy head, and crown Thy youth with joys ; and maſſ thou after be . As bleſt in thine, & I am blºft in thee. . . . . So ſaid; the fair Parthenia, to whoſe heart Her fixt deſires had taught th'uſi willing Art - * of ---- -** * - & * , < * * * º ºve . £ºsi. ... At sº tº º ei, ". - * . . . . , i. *hºp'ſ to ſpeed. . . . . . - - - - * - *** * lºſi tº - --- , - . . £ 3 º' -- --> *
Page 38

is Tāzgalugand partººnia. Boºl * Of diſobedience, calls her judgment in, ** And, of two evils, determines it a ſin More venial, by a reſolute denial, To prove undutiful, than be diſloyal . . . To him, whoſe heart a ſacred Vow had tied - So faſt to hers; and (weeping) thus replied. || Madam, h l ſ * º The angry gods have late conſpir'd to ſhow | The :::::::: inraged ; coulddo, - | And having laid afte all mercy, ſtretch . . . Their power, to make one miſerable wretch, - | whoſe curſ and tortur’d ſoul muſtomely be | The ſubject of their wrath ; and Iamſhe. Hard is the caſe 1 My dear deſires muſt fail, ... . . My vows muſt crack, my plighted faith befrail; , , or elſe affection muſt be ſº exil'd .#: A Mothers heart, that ſhe renounce her child. And as ſhe ſpake that word, a flowing tide Oftears guſhtout, whoſe violence deny'd Th’intended paſſage of her doublingtongue; She ſtopt a while, then on the floor ſhe flung Her proſtrate body, while her hands did tear (Not knowing what they did) her dainty hair : Sometimes ſhe ſtruck the ground, ſometimes herbreſt; Began ſome words, and then wept out the reſt: At laſt, her liveleſs hands did, by degrees, Raiſe her caſt body on her feeble knees, , Andhumbly rearing her ſad eyes upon Her Mothers frowning viſage, thus went on. upon theſe knees, theſe knees that me’r were bent, To you in vain; that never didpreſent - - Their
Page 39

* Book. Argalus and patibºnia, ºf | Their unrewarded duty: never roſe, sº "Yº YY without a Mothers bleſſing; upon thoſe, . tº \l. upon thoſe naked knees I recommend . . . . . . . º ºx Tº your dear thoughts, thoſe torments that attend º.º. rour poor Parthenia, whoſe unknown diſtreſs, ºr craves rather death, than language to expreſs "...º. what ſhall I do? Demagoras and death. . . . . .sº sound both alike to theſe ſad ears; that breath º º That mames the one, does nominate the other: , , , , No, mo, I cannot love him, my dear Mother. ºv command Parthenia now to undergo . . . . what death youpleaſe, and theſe quick hands.ſhallſhow tº The ſeal of my obedience in my heart: . . . . * * * * , The gods themſelves, that have a ſecret art To force affection, cannot violate * . . . The Law of Nature, j the courſe of Fate. can Earthforgether burthen, and aſtend? or can th'aſpiringflames be taught to tend . . To the Earth? Iffire deſtend, and Earth affire, Earth were no longer Earth, nor Fire, Fire: Even ſo, by Nature,' 'tis all one to me, To love Demagorasand not to be: No, no, the Heavens can do no ač that’s greater; Than (having made ſº) to preſerve their creature: And think you that the righteous Gods willfill me With ſuch falſe joys, as (if injoyd) would kill me a I know that they are merciful, what they Command, they give a pomer to obey: -- * - . The joyful Piſion that your ſlumbring eyes - t of late beheld, did promiſe and compriſe - A fairer fortune, than the Heavens can ſhare The poor Partheniaesmerit; whom deſpair Hath

Page 40

so 2ſtgains and Partútnia. Book. - | Hath ſwallow'd : rour prophetick dream deſtry'd.º.º. ºr A Royal Marriage; pointed out the Bride : . . . . . . Her ſafe deliverance; and her ſmilingſon; , , Honor and wealth; and after all was dome, . . . . . . . There wants a Bridegroom: Him, th’ Heavens have ſeal’d within my Breit, by me, to be reveal’d; - - which if yourpatience ſhall vouchſafe to hear,. . . . . . . aſy Lipsſhall recommend unto your ear. when as Bafilius (may whoſe royal hand Longſway the Scepter of th’Arcadian Land) - - From Cyprus brought his more than Princely Bride, The fair Gynecia, (whom as Greece deny'd An equal; ſo the world acknowledg’d none As her ſuperior imperfeition :) . . . . . . . Ilpon this Ladies royal train, and ſtate & - Agreat concourſe of Nobles did await, - - r And Cyprian Princes, with their Princely port, “ . . . . Tº ſee her crown'd in the Arcadian Court: Illuſtrious Princes were they ; but, as far . . . . . . . As midnight Phoebe out-ſhines a twinkling ſtar; . . . . , So far, amongſt this rout of Princes, one . . . . Surpaſt the reſt, in honor and renown : . - - - Whoſe perfeif virtue findes more admiration In the Arcadian Court, than imitation: In th’ ex'llence of his outward parts, and feature, - The world conceives, the tarious hand of Nature - Out-went itſelf; which being richly fraught ...And furniſht with tranſcendent worth, is thought To be the choſen fortreſ for protećtion - - Of all the Arts, and fore-houſe of Perfeółion : The Cyprus ſtºck did nºr till now,bring forth So rare a Branch, whoſe undervalued worth - Brings
Page 41

BºITârgălug and patibania. Tº * Brings greaterglary to the Arcadian Land, , , Than can the dull Arcadians underſtand : - His name is Argalus: " . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . He (Madam) was that Cypreſs wreath, that crown'd . My nuptialbrows: And now the Bridegroom'sſº - cleath'd in the myſºry of that Cypreſs wreath 5. #hich, ſince the better gods have pleaſ'd to breath Into my ſoul, O may / ceaſe to bet ... . . . fought but death º: and me: . . . ret does myſafe obedience hot withſtand . . What you deſire, or what the gods command; For what the gods command iſ four deſire Parthenia ſhould obey, and not reſpire . . . . . Againſt their ſacred ::ſ. or #. . . . The plot, wherein they havévouchſf'dahand? . we muffſhbmit our wills; what they enjoyn Mait be nor lies it in your power or mine, To croſs: We muſt endeavor tofulfil - at elſe muſt time to paſsagiințour will; My vans areſº and ſecond Heavens decree, - Nothing ſha § my Árgalusand me. ... So ſaid; th’impatient Mothers kindſed eye (Halfèloſed with a hurtherous frown) let #. - - Aſcotching Fire-ball, from whence was ſhed. Some dropsoſcholer; ſtefnly ſhakes her head; , , With trembling hands unlocks the door, and flecs; }...; of her aking knees: And as ſhe fled, her fury thus began To open, Ahd is Argalis the man : , , , , But there ſhe ſtops, and ſtriving to expreſs Whatrage had prompted, could do nothingleſ. * # all * 1
Page 42

42 2ſtgalug and 33attijºnia. Book I, All you whoſe dear affections have been toſ; In Cupid's Blanket, and unjuſtly croft . . . . . By wilful Parents, whoſe extream command , , , , Hath made you groan beneath their tyrannou, hand, * That take a furious pleaſure to divorce - Tour ſouls from your beſt thoughts, (nay, whiti. worſe | f Than torture)force our fancies to reſpett, .* I W … And dearly love, whom moſt goa diſaffe:#; *. Draw near, and comfort the diſtreſſed heart of poor Parthenia; let your eyes impart ( One drop at # : And whoſº'er thou be H That readſ theſe Lines, may thy deſires ſee . . . p The like ſucceſs, if reading, thou forbear, E To wet this very Paper with a tear. . . . . / T , Behold (poor Lady) how an hours time H Hinºdifiefdºm hºprime, Who like an unregarded ruine, lies, & With deaths untimely image in her eyes: . . . . a She, ſhe, whom hopeful thoughts had newly crown. With promis'd joys, liesgrov'ling on the ground; u , Her weary hand ſuſtains her drooping head; A (Too ſºft a Pillow for ſº hard a Bed). . . . . T Her eyes ſwoln up, as loth to ſee the light, l That would diſcover ſo forlorn a ſight: . . . . . T The flaxen wreath of her neglected hairs . . . l Stick faſt to her pale Cheeks with dried tears; A And at firſt bluſh, ſhe ſeems, as if it were N Some curious ſtatue on a Sepulchre : . . . ... }} Sometimes her briny Lips would whiſper thus, i. 44, Argalus, Aſy deareſt Argalus : ". D And then they clos'd again, as if the one - u Had kiſt the other, for that ſervice done, 4
Page 43

º pººl. .3ttgalus and partººnia. As * º º - | º wn the decºgniffalºm, miſeries, "Ziad Î not ſº this water from mine eyes ; * - Innaming Argala : Sometimes oppreſt . . With a deep figh, ſhe gave her fainting breſt Aſidden ſtroke; and after that another, , , Crying, Hardfortune, Q hard-hearted mother . And ſick with her own thoughts, her paſſion ſtrove * . . Betwixt the two extreams of grief and lové i t - The more ſhe griev'd, the more her love abounded: - “. The more ſhe lov’d, the more her heart was wounded With deſprate grief; at length, the tyrannous force Of love and grief, ſent forth this ſelf diſcourſe. . . . How art thoughang’a (Parthenia) how hath paſſion. . . Exil'd thy little judgement, and betray'd thee . . . . To thine own ſºft How nothing hath it made thee How is thy weather-beaten ſoul oppreſ; g, , , , mith;forms and tempeſts #lown from the North-eaſt ºf cold deſpair? which, longere this, had found ºrnal reſt; had been o'erwhelm'd and drown'd My Argalus; 9 where, owhere art thou?. . . . Thou little thinkſ thy pour Parthenia now Is tortur'd fºr thyſake; alas, (dear heart 1) Thom knoweft not th'unſufferable ſmart . . . fundergo fºr thee: Theºdºſ not keep ſº. A Regifter ºf theſe ſad tear; I weep, , , No, no, thou diffhot. . . . . . . . . . . . Well, well; from henceforth, Fortune, do not ſpare To dathe worſt thyačić miſthief dare; - - - Deviſe new torments, or repeat the old, *...* … itntil thou burſt; or Icºmplain Behold, As bitter; I diſdain thy *f; thy power; : * : * ~ * º- º ---- *-

Page 44

44 2ſtgaltig and partútnia. Book. who's level'd with the Earth, can fall no lower; Do; ſpit thy venome forth, and temper all ºr . . . . Thy ſtudied aftions with the #. of gall; … :--- ºr Thy pračis'd malice can no charm deviſe º' tº Too ſure for Argalus to exerciſe: ºf ºº His love ſhall ſweeten death, and make torture ". . . . -- Myſportful paſtime, to make hours ſhorter : * ~ *- : His love ſhall fill my heart, and leave no room 9 ºf mherein your rage may pračiſe Martyrdom. º, . But ere that word could uſher out another, itſ cºcº º The tender Virgins marble-hearted mother, sº ºr Enters the Chamber; with a chang'd aſpect Beholds Parthenia; &#: * . . Salutes her child, and (having clos'd the door) ºr - Her helpful arm removes her from the floor -º º: "º Whereon ſhe lay, and being ſet together, ºr º In gentle terms, ſhe thus did commune withher ** * * ... . . . . . . . . . " … A : \\\\ \º Perverſe Parthenia, is thy heart ſoſworn. º, sº To Argalus his love, that it muſt ſtorm, º Demagºras P are your ſouls enjoyh'dſ cloſe, . ºciº º That my entreaty may not interpoſe: ** º * * * * If ſo, what help? yet let a Mothers care. Sº sº wº Be not contemn'd, that bids her child beware. * * º - - - - - --- The Sickle that's too early, cannot reap ºvº- A fruitful Harveſt; look before you leap. ; “º Adjourn your thoughts, and make a wiſe delay, º ºsº. rol, cannot meaſure virtue in a day; sº Pirtues appear, but Pices balk the light; . . . . . . . . 'Tis hard to read a vice at the firſt ſight.” Falſe are thoſe joys that are not mixt with doubt, tº . Fire eaſily kindled, will not eaſily out: . . . . . . . . . . . * * * * . . Divide -- º \"", tº \\ , , , - - - - - - - - - - |
Page 45

Bookſ 2itgalug and £artbrnia, 45 Divide that love, which thou beſtow'd on one, Twixt two; try both, then take the beſt or none: Conſult with time; for time beivrays, diſcovers; The faith, the love, the conſtancy of lovers. Afts done in haſt, by leiſure are repented, And things, ſoon paſt, are off too late lamented. With that Parthenia riſing from her place, And bowing with incomparable grace, Made this reply: Aſadam, each ſeveral day Since firſt you gave this body being, may Write a large volume of your tender care, mhoſe ; goodneſs, if it ſhould compare With my deſerts, alas, the world would ſhow Too great a ſum for one poor heart to owe. I muſt confeſ; my heart is not ſo ſworn To Argalus his merit, as to ſcorn Demagoras; nor yet ſo looſly tide, That I can ſlip the knot, and ſº divide Entire affeſſion, which muſt not be ſever'd, Nor ever can le (but in vain) endeavor’d: My heart is one, and by one power guided: One is no number, cannot be divided: And Cupid’s learned Schoolmen have reſolvd, That love divided, is but love diſſolvd: . But yet, what plighted faith and honor may .. - Not new undo, your counſelſhall delay. . . . . . Aſadam, Partheniaes hand is not ſo greedy, To reap her cºrn, befºre her corn be ready:. . . Her unadviſed ſickleſhall not thruſt -- Into her hºpeful Harveſt, ere needs muſt: . . . . To yours, Parthenia ſhall ſubmit her skill, whoſe ſeaſon ſhall be ſeaſon'd by your will: - - -----. - | * - - - - - - i. . . . . . .
Page 46

46 3rgăluş and 12artbenia. Bookſ. Her time of Harveſt ſhall admit no meaſure, “ . But oneſy what's proportioned by your . So ended ſhe'; but till that darkneſs got The maſtºry of the light, they parted not : The Mother pleads for the Laconian Lord; The daughter (whoſe impatience hadābhorrº His very name, had nother Mother ſpok’t) - She pleads her vow, which cannot be revok’t: Yet ſtill the Mother pleads, and does omit º' . Noway untry'd, that a hard-hearted wit Knows to deviſe; perſwades, allures, intreats, , Mingles her words with ſmiles, with tears, with threats; Commands, conjures, tries one way, tries another, Does thºutmoſt that a marble-breſted Mother: , . . . Can do; and yet the more ſhe did apply, ºr The more ſhe taught Parthenia todény; The more ſhe did aſſault, the more contend, The more ſhe taught the Virgin to defend: At laſt, deſpairing (for herwords did find More hopes to move a Mountain than her mind) She ſpake no more: but from herchair ſhe ſtarted, Ånd ſpir theſe words, Go peeviſh girl, and parted: Away ſhe flings, and finding hoſucceſs. . . . . . In her loſt words, her fury did addreſs Her raging thoughts to a new ſtudied plot: Aćtions muſt now enforce, what words could not. Treaſon is in her thoughts: her furious breath F. Can whiſper how no language under death: : Poor Argala muſt die, and his remove . . Muſt make the paſſage to Demagora, love: And till that bar be broken; or put by, Schºpe to ſpeed: Poot Argalus muſt die. isv i. i* . . . . . . ; ; : . . . . .” -; ‘. : R. ''{ ºf , , , -, * * * * . . . . . Thaºtago?” Atº ºf ºf S t

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 47

s s w | | TITNE w Yoº PUſ.) IC LINPARY As Tor, lººsa Ana Tuºtº ºuslyx º - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - -- - - - * - - - º - - - - - - - - * - - - º -
Page 48

**** | ||||| |||| ---- - - - ---- | | | | | | | | | ----|-

Page 49

B.Târgălug and partººnia.T - ~~~~ * * (; ) Demagºra iscaldtocounſel now, Conſults, conſents, and after mutual vow, Reſolving on the ait, they both conſpire which way to execute their cloſe deſire: , , Drawing his keensteletto from his ſide, , , , Madam (ſaid he ) this medicine well apply'd To Argalus his boſºm, will give reſt. . . . To him and me: the ſudden way is b My Lord: your trembling ;ſhe) may miſ, The mark, and then yºur ſelfin danger is Of out-cry; or perchance his own #. : Attempts are dangerous, at ſº ſmall a diſtance: A Drug's the better weapon, which does breath Deaths ſecret errand, carries ſudden death clos'd up in ſweetneſs : Come, a Drugſtrikes ſure, And works our ends; and yet we ſleep ſecure: My Lord, bethink no other : ſet your reſt upon theſe Cards: the ſureſ way it beft: Leave me to manage our ſucceſsfal Plot, And if theſe ſtudious brows contrive it not Tooſure for art of Magick to prevent, Ne’r traft a womans wit when fully bent To take revenge: Re gone, my Lord, Repoſe The truſt in me: onely be wife, be cloſe. , That night, when as the univerſal ſhade Of the unſpangled Heaven and Earth, had made An utter darkneſs; (darkneſs apt to further The horridenterpriſe of rapes andmurther) She,
Page 50

3o 2irgalus and partijenia. BookL She, ſhe, that now lacks nothing to procure A full revenge, ſhe calls Athleia to her, (Partheniae handmaid) whom ſhe thus beſpake: Athleia, dare thy private thoughts partake with mine? Canff thou be ſecret f Hathy heart A lock, that none campick by theeviſh art, or break by force? tell me, eamſ; thou digeſt A ſecret, º: to thyfaithful Breſt? Madam (ſaid ſhe) Let me never be true To my own thoughts, if ever falſe to you: Speak what youpleaſe; Athleiaſhall conceal; - Torments may make me roar, but ne'r reveal. - Reply'd the Lady then: Athleia knows How much, how much my dear affection ows . Partheniaesheart, whoſe welfare is the crown of all my joys, which now is overthrown, And *::: buried inforgotten duff, If thou betray the ſecret of mytruſt; It lieth in thy power to remove Approaching evils: Parthenia is in love: Her waſted ſpirits languiſh in her breſt - Andnought, but look'd for death, can give her reſt: ... 'Tis Argalus ſhe loves ; who with #. Requites her love, not loving her again; - - He ſlights her tears; the more that he negleifs: The more entirely ſhe (poor ſºul) affeits. She groans beneath the burthenofaeſpair, And with herſgh ſhe clays the idle air: - Thou art acquainted with her private fears, And you, ſº oftexchanging tongues and tears, Muft know to much, for one poor heart t'endure; . But deſperate's the wound admits no cure: º it
Page 51

A- -- ** * * . mammº- ºf 2ſtgatuš and eartbºnia. * It lies in thee to help : Athleiafay, ºº will thou aſſiſt me, if ifnd the wayºgº tº . Madam, my forcedignorance#all be º: sufficient earneſt or Žiž; ºº:: **** rººps have utter’ānothing that intº To Athleia’s ears; alas, it is too trae: *. º, sº zong, longere this, yourſervant had reveal’d - ..Th;fame to you, had not theſe Lips beenſtard: But if my beft endeavors may extend...... - To bring my Ladiet fºrrows to an endº tºº. ºb ºilſ Let allih enraged Deities allot º'º", * tº bilº To me worſe torment, if I do it wet : * º, º * * º My life's too poor to hazard fºr herºeſe: , , , , \ºv %dºm, rild’t, command me what youtleaſe, So ſaid: the treacherous Lady ſtept aſide, - Into her ſerious cloſet ; and appli’d Her haſty, and perfidious hands, to frame This forged Letter, in Partheniae, name. To her faithful Argale. lthough the malice of a Mother \ Does yet enfºrce my tongue to ſmother *hiſ my deſire is ſhouldflame 3 ret Parthenia’s the ſame. Although my fire be hid a while, w 'Tis but fireſlak’d withoyl: Beforeſeven Suns ſhall riſe andfall, It ſhall burn, and blaze withal. -- - . . . . . . what
Page 52

*Targains and partinia. EEI. what Iſend thee, drink with ſpeed. . . . Elſe lef my Argalus take heedº. . . . . . . wnleſs thy providence withſtand, , . . . . There is treaſºn near at hand: ". . . . . Drink a thou lov’ſºme, and it ſhall ſecure thee . From future dangers, or from paſt, recure thee, º:* - , , , º, . This done, and ſeal’d, ſhe op'd her private door, Call'd in Athleia, and ſaid, For every fore - The gods provide a ſalve; force muſt prevail, mhere fighs and tears, and deep entreaties fail. - .* tº . . . . . . . . . . * .**** - - - - - - , . . . . <-- *** *** - * - - * * * * - - - ! . . . - - . . . . ; . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - * 21: , , ; ; (; ; ; *... . . . . . . . . . . . - ** *** - - - - - - ** - * * * * * * * * * : *, *, • * ~ * . . . . \ « » * . . . . * -- - *** - * - - *~ * , - - * -* - 4. - - * - - - *
Page 53

- -- - y - º - - - - - - - - - a -- - º - ** - *-*.*.*.*.*.*.*.*.. - - - - w - - - -- ~ * . .” *. ~ * : sº º - - - - * - - * * . • * * - , , ºr - - - - - - * * w ** ** - - --> - - - - - # , * * *. * : - - - - - -*. * - - > * -- ºr -- - - - -- - - * - -- º - - -- - - - - -- - - - - - -- r - -- - ~ - - - - -- -- - * -- - ** - - - - - - s - - -- --> - - ---- - - - - - - - - - - - * - - - - - * . - - - - º - - w w -- - - - | - * . - - - f - | - - - - i. “ - r - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - º - - - - : t - t -- - \ - ...------ - - - - - - - - --- - - - - - - - - - º - - ** w - - --- - w - - - - - - - ------ - - -- * * - - - - w > - - - - - - - - - - t - -- - - * f - / - - - - - - ~ - - - - - - w - ... " - - - \ - ºn - -- - - - - - - - - * -- - - - w - -- - - - - * * ~ - - - - - - ~ - - - - - - r - - º r -- - - - - - t - --- - - - - C ºr 7 - - * > - - 4. º - - * r - * -- º ** - - -> - a º R - | - | - - i. - - - - - - - Y - - - -- - - - - - -- … • - -- - - -- t * - - - - * , *** wº - - - - -- ſ — , - º - w * -- - - - - - a Tion • * • * * - --- - w -- -- º- *- * - *** - - - - * * - - - -- º: **. - - - - * - - - - - *** ... • - - * * - - - - - - - * -a --- - --- - - - -- * - - - - - r * - * . º - - - w | - -- * * > - - - - - - - - - -- es. - - ". * - - - - - - - - - - - * - - - - - --- - - º … * *. -> • *-* - * . º - * -- * --- * - - - - - - *- * - - - - * * - - - - - ." * - - - - - - - *-* * - v.” . . . - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - * - s º - - - - - - º -- - - - -- - .* * A - - -- - - - - -- - t º - - - -- - - a - - - - w * - - * * - - - º - * - - • - - --- - - - - - w - * - w - -- ! - - - * - - -- - - * - - - - - - - t - - - - - - - - º - : - *





Page 54

Blank page
Page 55

pºſſ 2irgalug and partienia. - 55 (6) Forthwith, from out her Cabinet ſhe took - A little glaſs, and ſaid, Athleia; look, within theſe ſlender walls, theſe glazed lifts, - Partheniae happineſs, and life conſiſts; It is Nepenthe; which the factious Gods . Do uſe to drink, when ere they be at ods; -- Whoſe ſecret virtue (ſº infus’d by Jove) . . Does turn deep hatred, into deareſt love; . . . . It makes the proudeſt lover whime and baul, And ſuch to dote, as never lov’d at all: | Here, take this glaſs, and recommend the ſame To Argalus in his Partheniaes name, . . . | And to his hand, to his own hand commit This Letter; between º: and it." - " . \ º e - Let no Eye come: Be ſure thyſpeed prevent :* - The riſing Sun ; and ſo heavens crown th’event. . . . . By this, the feather'd Belman of the night * > ...,' Sent forth his midnight ſummons, to invite - All eyes to ſlumber: when they both addreſt sº º Their thoughtful mindes, to takeadoubtful reſt, º O Heavens, and you, O you celeſtial powers, ". . .” That never ſlumber, but imploy al/hours º In mans protection ; ſtillpreſerving; keeping ºr . Otºy ſouls from obvious dangers, making, ſleeping, º º O, can your all diſcerning eyes behold -- . . . . . | Such impious aftions proſper uncontrouſ dº - O can your hearts, your tenderhearts endure To ſee your ſervant (that now ſleeps ſecure, “... * - - 1/24r2.’d, - * * *
Page 56

36 2/rgalug and partbenia. Book I. unarm'd, wmwarm’d, and having no defence, But your protećtion, and his innocence) Betray'd and murther'd, drawing at one breath His own prepar'd deſtruction, his own death: And º ſuffer's f he that is the crown of prized virtue, honor and renown; The flower of Arts; the Cyprian livingſtory; Arcadia's Garland, and great Greece's glory; The Earth; new wonder, and the morld; example, Muff die betray'd ; Treaſon and Death muſt trample Mpon his life 3 and in the duſt muſt lie - As much admir’d perfeółion, as can die. No, Argalus, the coward hand of death, Durſt me'raſſault thee, if not underneath The mask of love: Thou art above the reach of open wrongs; mans force could ne'r make breach Into thy life : No, Death could ne'rumcaſe Thy ſoul, had ſhe appeared fact tº face. - Dream, Argalus, and let thy thoughts be troubled m’ith murthers, treaſons, let thy dreams be doubled; , , And what thyfighted famcy ſhall perceive, - Be wiſely ſuperftitious, and believe. . . . . O, that my lines could wake thee now, and ſever Thoſe eye-lids, that ere long muſt ſleep for ever: Wake now or never Argalus, and withſtand Thy danger: Wake, the Murthereſ is at hand: Parthenia, o Parthenia, who ſhall weep . . º Thy wºrld'ſ tears canſ thou, o canſ; thuſleep: will thy dull Genius give thee leave to ſlumber 2 Does nothing trouble thee : no dream incumber Thy frighted thoughts, and Argalus'ſ near His late:f hour: Not one dreaming tear?
Page 57

Book I. zirgalus and partºnia. - JZ -*. sleep on ; and when thy flattering ſlumber's paſt, Perchance, thine eyes will learn to weep as faſt: His death is plotted; and this morning ſight Muſt ſend him down, into etermal night: Nay, what is worſe than worſt; his dying treath Will cenſure thee, as Agent to his death. By this, the broad fac’d Quirifter of night , Surceas'd her ſcreeching note, and took her flight , To the next neighboring Ivy: Birds and Beaſts Forſake the warm protection of their Neſts, And nightly Dens, whilſt darkneſs did diſplay Her ſable Curtains to let in the day; - When ſad Athleia's dream had unbenighted Her ſlumbring eies, her buſie thoughts were frighted 3 She roſe, and trembled; and being half diſtraught With her prophetick fears, ſhe thus bethought what ails the gods thus to disturb my reș, And make ſuch Earth-quakes in my troubled breſ 2 Nothing but death, andmurthers? Grates and Bells, Frightning my fancy, with their hourly Knels : 'Twas nothing but a dream 3 and dreams, they ſay, Expound themſelves the clean contrary way: w The Riddle's read; and now I underſtand My dreams intent: Some marriage is at hand: For Death interpreted is nothing elſe But Marriage; and the melancholly Be!'s Is mirth and muſick: By the Grave, if read The joyful, joyful, joyful marriage bed: J, it is plain; and now, methinks, 't yº 1 That my prophetick dream foretold ſhould die. If this be death, Death exerciſe thy porer, And let Athleia die within this hour ; }, £ia.
Page 58

3 ºrgains and partººnia. Book. 120, do thy worff, Athleia’s faithful breath - Shall prayfor nothing more than ſudden death. . . . *ut ſay, Athleia, the too forward day to Begins to gild the Eaſt; amay, anay. - - So having ſaid, the nimble fingered Laſs Took the forg'd Letter, and the amorous glaſs: And to her early progreſs ſhe appliesher: Departs, and towards Argalus ſhe hies her; But every ſtep ſhe took, her mind enforc’d New thoughts, and with her ſelf ſhe thus diſcours'd: Hon frail’s the mature of a womans will Hºp croſs | The thing that's moſt forbidden, ſtill They more deſire ; and leaſt inclin'd to do, What they are moſt of all perſivaded to: Hid not (ala) my Lady bound theſe hands, Athleia ne'r had ſtrugled with her bands : I ºff not taše it ! Had ſhe not injoyn'd 137 lips from taſting it, Athleia’s mind Had never theught oz't ; now methinks I long; Deſires, if once confin'd, become too ſtrong Fºr romans conquer’d reaſon to reſt: 24 vonºans reaſon's meaſur’d by her liff. I Áng to tañes yet was there nothing did Aſoº’e my deſire, but that I was forbid. - - * - - - With

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 59

a. ~~ ， ！！ .*{ ſ. * + + + |-|-· |-|- ---- , ！ |----- • • • - -- * |- |-|- |-|- · ：- （） |- r - |- |-|- |- |-|- → - ！ * |-|- *|- |- -|- |-|-|-· |- |-|-|- |- |-|-|-|- |-|-----|- |- |-|- ·|- |- |-|- |-^ .-|-|- ·|-|-|-|- |-----|- |-|-|- |-|- |- |- |- |-|- |- |- |-|- |-|- |-|- /** . . |-|- |-·- |- ·.*/-· |-|-- - .|- |--|-|-|- ----·- .·*~ ·|-· - |- |-|-+· -- ： |-|-·！ ---- - -- : * *·, ，|- --|-• • • •---- · |- |-|-|-|-· ·|- |- -\ |-|-|- ·|- · *|- |-|- ·|- *·|- ---- <|-|- |- |-|-|- →… • |-|- |- -'. |- |-|-|- |-·|- ·|-|- |-|-· |-… |-|- |-|-· |-|-|-- |-|-|- |-~|- |-· ！·|-|- ; ·> |-|-|-- |- |-+ ''|-·|- |-·|-|- ·; ··|- ·|--- |-|- |- · - |-· …|-



Page 60

------- - -** ！



Page 61

x \ . . . - - \ - 4 Book I. 24tgalug and partijenia, (7) . . *> s With that ſhe ſtaid her weary ſteps, and haſted Tºunty the glaſs; lift up her arm, and taſted; - . That done (and having now attain'd, almoſt, *, * , Her journeys end) the little time ſhe loſt, - .* * New ſpeed regains: The nimble ground ſhe traces . . . . With double haſt, and quick redoubled paces, . . . . . . All on a ſudden ſhe begins to faint: - * * * Her bowels gripe, her breath begins to taint: Her bliſtred tongue grows hot, her liver glows: Her veins do boil, her colour comes and goes, She ſtaggers, falls, and on the ground ſhe lies : . Swells like a bladder, roars, and burſts, and dies. . . . Thus from her ruine Argalus derives - - His longer life, and by her death he lives; Live Argalus, and let the gods allot - Such morning-draughts, to thoſe that love thee not. Live long, and let the righteous Powers above, That hath preſerv'd thee for Partheniae; love, Crown all thy hopes, and fortunes with event Too ſure, for ſecond treaſons to prevent. By this time, did the laviſh breath of Fame Give language to her Trumpet, and proclaim Athleiaes death, the current of which news Truth’s warrant, had forbidden to abuſe Deceived ears: Which when the lady heard Whoſe treacherous heart was greedily prepar'd To entertain a murther, ſhe aroſe And with rudeviolence deſperately throws E 3 - 1 - Her



Page 62

- Book I. * 3rgalus and particaä. --- º ºf Her trembling body on the naked floor, But what ſhe ſaid, and did, I will deplore, Not utter; but with forced ſilence ſmother, Becauſe ſhe was the fair Partheniaes Mother: May it ſuffice, that the extreams of ſhame, And unreſiſted ſorrow overcame . . . . . Her diſappointed malice, leſs lamenting - The treaſon, than ſucceſs; and more repenting Of what ſhe fail'd to do, than what ſhe did, ` Her ſullen ſoul deſpairs; her thoughts forbid What reaſon wants the pºwer to perſwade; * And griefs being grown too deep for her to wade”, “ . . She ex, * # inks; and with a hollow figh ſhe cried, , . SA welcome thou eaſer of all evils, and died. . . *; Now tongues begin to walk; and every ear º *::::Hath got the Saturyafts to bear . . . This tragick Scene: the breath of Fame growsbold, Fears no repulſe, and ſcorns to be control'd : " : " - t # Whilſt loud report (whoſe tender Lips, before, e Durſtonely whiſper) now begins to roar; Theletter found in dead Athleiaes breſt, . A Bewray'd the plot, and what (before) was gueſt, Is now confirm'd and clear'd : for all men knew Whoſe hand it was, and whepee the malice grew. But have we loſt ; In what Iſle s of endleſs ſorrow lurks ſhe all this while?' " Sweet Reader, urge me not to tell, for fear Thy heart diſſolve, and mels into a tear : Excuſe my ſilence ; if my lines ſhould ſpeak, Such marblehearts, as could not melt, would break, No, leave her tº her ſelf; it is not fit "... . - 7 - - ! . ...a..”.' • *f; ; : * * - * To write, what leing rºad, yºu a Iriſh unwrit:- * - ºr - -- - * 2 * * º ſ
Page 63

Booki. 2ſtgalug and 12attberta. 63 I leave this task to thoſe, that take delight, To ſee poor Ladies tortur'd in deſpight of all remorſe; whoſe hearts are ſtill at ſtrife To paint a torment to the very life; º I leave that task to ſuch, as have theſ: To weep, and ſmile again within an hour: To thoſe whoſe flinty hearts are more contented - Tolima% than pity the tormented: * - H +ºğ. remov’d, and loves wide Ocean now t. Let it ſuffice, that had not Heaven prote:fed : Her Argalus, #. whereof corrested That firious grief, which paſſion recommended _To hºſtãºhoughts, her ſtory here had ended. ſheartmethe enemy of Éame had clos'd leſſºbling Lips, and gently had compos'd arthºniae; ſorrows, raiſing from the ground ſºdy ſpent with grief, and almoſt drown'd her own tears, along expected Scean º * - - *(g erfortune enters in, to drean - #: her ſtormy night of tears ſt; a welcome day of joy appears. Gives room enough; looks with a milder brow. Reader, forget thy ſorrows; Let thine ear’ Welcome the tidings thouſo longſt to hear: Alqvers diet'sſweet commixt with ſowre; His Helland Heaven ofttimesdivides an hour. .* E. 4. - Now -

Page 64

64 2ſtgalug and 49artbenia. Book" -— º (8) Now Argilus can find a fair acceſs , , - - - To his Parthenia: Now fears nothing leſs, º Than ears and eyes; and now Partheniae; heart - Can give her tongue the freedom to impart His louder welcome, whilſt her greedy eye Can look her fill, and fear no ſtander by: - - She's not Parthenia, he not preſent with her; . . . . . And he not Argalur, if not together: . . . . . *. - - - Their cheeks are filſ'd with ſmiles;their tongues with chat; Now, this they make their ſubject; and now that:". One while they laugh, and laughing, wrangle tooyº And jar, as jealous lovers uſe to do: - ". . . . . And then a kiſs muſt make them friends again : . . . Faith, one’s too little; Lovers muſt have twain: Two brings in ten, Ten multiplies to twenty: - That, to a hundred: then becauſe the plenty Grows troubleſom to count, and does incumber Their Lips, their Lipsgave kiſſes without number: . . Their thoughts run back to former times: they told: Of all lovespaſſages they had ofold: ... " * Of this thing done, the time, the place, and why? . { The manner how, and who were preſent by: ' ' ' ' The Mothers craft, her undeceiv'd ſuſpicion: Her baited words, her marble diſpoſition: His pining thoughts, and her projećting fears: | His ſoliloquies, and her ſecret tears; º " | Where firſt they met, th’occaſion of their meeting: ( Their complement, the manner of their greeting: Hi . - - - is / |
Page 65

-***** |- ae * ： · |-||- |- |-· ---- .y «. ！, |- }; ·|- |-|- · * -1 -|- |- |- |- · -· · ·1 |--· * ·· |-i · |-|- |- · |--|-, -|-·|- |-|-· |- |- |-. ^|--|--" - |-|-|-|-|- |-|-|- - - --_-. --|-|-|-

Page 66

w --- : y w - --- - | -- - - - *

Page 67

p.Târgălug and particula. Tº His danger, his deliverance, and the reaſon That firſt induc’d the Agents to the Treaſon. Thus by the priviledge of time and leaſure Their ſweet diſcourſes (crown'd with mutual pleaſure Commixt with grief) they equal with the light, And after, grumble at the envious night, Which bids them part too ſoon what day deny'd In words, in thoughts the tedious night ſupply'd, Which blam'd the Fates for doing Lovers wrong, To make the day ſo ſhort, the night ſo long. But now the little winged-god repented That he had laugh’d ſo much, his heart relented, His very ſoul grew ſad, his blinded eye - Began to weep at his own tyranny : : Laments their ſorrows: findes a ſecret way, To make the night as pleaſing as the day: Calls Hymen in, and in his ear diſcovers The lingring torments of theſe wounded Lovers: Gives him a charge, no longer to defer, T’ingroſs their names within his Regiſter. And now Partheniaes harveſt draweth near: (The dearly purchas'd price of many a tear) Her joy ſhall reap, what a world of grief hath ſown: The time’s appointed, and the day’s ſet down, Wherein ſweet Hymen, with his nuptial bands, Shall joyn together their cſpouſed hands. . . Here ſtop my Muſe; retire thy ſelf and ſtay, To gather breath againſt the Marriage day. w Reader, the joyful Bride ſalute; we all, In her behalf, if any have let fall A tºxder tear, to thoſe ſhe makes requeſt, That they’ll be pleas'd to grace her ºf irrige Feaſ. Arg: 'us

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 68

38Tºgalug and partijenia. Book II, ARGALUS PARTHE NIA. The Second Part. | Ailgentle Pinnace: Now the Heavens are clear, slº The Winds blow fair : Behold the Harbor's near Tridented Neptune hath forgot to frown, The Rocks are paſt: The ſtorm is over-blown. łlp weather-beaten Voyagers, and rouzeye, Forſake your loathed Cabbins: Up and louze ye t!pon the open Decks, and ſmell the Land: Chear up, the welcome Shore is nigh at hand: Stilgentle Pinnace, with a proſperous gale, To th’ Iſle of Peace : Sail, gentle Pinnace, ſail: Foztume condućt thee Let thy keel divide The Silver ſtreams, that thou maiſt ſafely ſlide Into the boſome of thy quiet Key, And quit thee fairly of th’injurious Sea. Great Sea-born Queen, thy birth-right gives thee power T'aſſ'ſ poor ſuppliants, grant one happy hour: o, let theſe rºunded Lover; he poſſeſ, .it length, of theirſ lºng deſired reſ. *{xv, now theio, ful marriage-day draws on : the Bride is buſie, and the Bridegroom's gone - - TO \ l |

Page 69

BºſTirgains and partººnia. Tº To call his fellow Princes to the feaſt: , The Garland's made : The Bridal Chamber's dreſt: The Muſes have conſulted with the Graces, To crown the day, and honor their embraces With ſhadow’d Epithalms : their warbling tongues Are perfect in their new made Lyrick ſongs: Hymen begins to grumble at delay, And Bacchus inji. upon the day; The virgin-tapers, and what other rights IXo ºf. to Nuptial delights Are all prepard, whereby may be expreſt The joyful triumph of this marriage-feaſt. But ſtay ! who lends me now an Iron Pen, T'engrave within the Marble-hearts of Men A Tragick Scene? Which whoſo'erſhallread, His eyes may ſpare to weep, and learn to bleed Carnatian tears: If time ſhall not allow His death-prevented eyes to weep enow, Then let his dying language recommend What's left to his poſterity to end. . . . . . . . Thouſaddeſt of all muſes, come, afford Thy ſtudious help, that each confounding word May rend a heart (at leaſt) that every Line May pickle up a Kingdom in the Brine - - - of #. own tears: O teach me how textračí The ſpirit of grief, whoſe virtue may diſtrađ Thoſe breafts, which ſorrow knows not how to kill: Inſpire, O, inſpire my melting quill ; - * ºff; like ſad $.". ſº. - - * . . . That cannot melt, be turn'd into a ſtone : - Teach me to paint an oft-repeatedſigh * * . so to the life, that whoſº'er be migh, -
Page 70

7. 2itgatus and Partbenia. Tºkſi. | Mayhear it breath, and learn to do the like By imitation, till true paſon ſtrike - - Their bleeding hearts: Let ſuch as ſhall rehearſe . . . This ſtory, houllike Iriſh at a Hearſe. - . . . . Th' event ſtill crowns the aët: Let no man ſay, Before the evening's come, ’tis a fairday : For when the Kalends of this Bridalfeaſt Were entred in, and every º breaſt Waxt great with expectation, and alleyes. (Prepar'd for entertaining novelties) Were grown impatient now, to be ſuffic’d With that, which Art and Honor had devis'd Tº adorn the times withal, and to diſplay Their bounty, and the glory of that day : The rare Parthenia, taking ſweet occaſion To bleſs her buſie thoughts, with contemplation Of abſent Argalus, whoſe too long ſtay - Made minutes ſeem as days, and every day A meaſur'd age, into her ſecret bower Betook her weary ſteps, where every hour Her greedyears expect to hear the ſum Of all her hopes, that Argalus is come. She hopes, ſhe fears at once; and ſtill ſhe muſes . . What makes him ſtay ſo long; ſhe chides, excuſes; She queſtions, anſwers, and ſhe makes reply, And talks, as if her Argalus were by: Why com’ſ thou not 2, Can Argalus forget His languiſhing Parthenia? What not yet : But as ſhe ſpake that word, ſhe heard a noiſe, * Which ſeem’d, as if it were the whiſpring voice Of cloſe conſpiracy: She began to fear She knew not what, till her deceived ear - (Inſtruſted - l
Page 71

BookII. Žitgalug and Partútnia. 7: (Inſtructed by her hopes) had fingled out The voice of Argalus from all the rout; - Whoſe ſteps (as ſhe ſuppoſed) did prepare, a By ſtealth to ſeize upon her unaware: . She gave advantage to the thriving plot, Hearing the noiſe, as if ſhe heard it not : Like as young Doves, (which ne'r had yet forſaken The warm protection of their neſt, or taken upon themſelves, a ſelf-providing care, To ſhift for food, but with paternal fare º Grow fat and plump)thinkevery noiſe they hear, Their full cropt-parents are at hand to chear Their craving ſtomacks; whilſt th’impatient fiſt Of the falſe Cater, rifling where it liſt, Inevery hole, ſurpriſes them, and ſheds Their guiltleſs blood, and parts their gaſping heads From their vain ſtrugling bodies; ſo, even ſo, Our poor deceiv'd Parthenia, (that did owe Too much to her own hopes) the whilſt her eyes Were ſet to welcome the unvalued prize Of all her joys, her deareſt Argalus, - Stept in Demagoras, and ſalutes her thus: Baſe Trull, Demagoras comes to let thee ſee, * . How much he ſcorns thy painted face, and thee: * Foul sorcereſ; 1 could thy proſperous actions think Toſcape revenge, becauſe the gods did wink At thy deſigns? Think'if thou thy Mothers blood Cryes in a language, not to be underſfood? Hadſ thou no cloſer ſtratagem, to further Thy pamper'd luft, but by the ſavage murther of thine own aged parent, whoſe ſad death * AZaft give a freedom to the whiff'ring breath r
Page 72

7, 2Irgalug and partútnia. Book II. of thy enjoy’d Adulterer? who (they ſay) # %: #, whoredom with a ºday : - - Nay ſtruggle not, here's none that can reprieve such pounded beafts : It is in vain to ſtrive, or roar for help 3 mby º not rather weep - That I may laugh? fº ance, if thou wilt creep Mpon thy wanton Belly, and confeſs - Thyſelf a true repentant Murthereſt, . Myſinful Page may play the fool, and gather Thy early fruit into his Barn, andfather The new got Cyprian Baſtard, if that he Behalf ſo wiſe, that got it, but to flee : Hah! doſt thou weep? or do falſe miffs but mock Abuſed eyes 2 from ſº obdure a Rock can water flow: Weeping will make thee fair; weep till thy marriage-day; that mho repair To grace thy feaſt, may fall a weeping too, And, in a mirror, ſee what tears can do. Wile strumpet I did thy flattering thoughts e'er wrong Thy judgment ſo ; to think, Demagoras tongue Could ſo defile his honor, as to ſhe - For ſerious love? ſo baſe a thing as you (Methinks) ſhould rather fix your wanton eyes 1/pom ſome eaſie Groom, that hopes to riſe Into his Maſter's favor for your ſake: 1, this had been preferment, like to make - A hopeful fortune: Thou preſumptuºus traſh What was my courtſhip, but the minutes daſh of youthful paſon, to allay the duº Of my deſires, and exuberous lift : 1ſtorm thee to the ſºul, and here Iſland - Bound for revenge, whercio 1 ſet my hind, | * With

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 73

|- ----|-|- |- |-|-|- |- ·|- |-|- ， , ··|- -|- |-|-|-|-|-|-• .|-|- --------- - -|-• • • • • • • • • • • • • •！ ----- |-|- |-|- -* * · * |-•|- |-|-·---- ·-|-·|- ---- |-•|-· -|-·|- |-•|- |- |-;|----- |-|-|- |-·|-|- |-|- |-|-·|- |-·|-|-|-|-|- |-|-|-|- ·|-|-·· ·|-|-|-|-|- |-|- |-|-* --· · · · · ·|- |-- :----|- |-|-|- |-- |-|-|-|--|-|- |--|-* …·|-. » *-|-• • • |-|- |-|- -|-|- |-{:|-|-|-|-|- |- |- |-|-|-·· |-|-|-- -·v |- |-*|-|----- |-|-|--|-- -|- |-|-|- -|-|-|- |-|-|-- ·· |-|-----·|- +------------+|-|-|-|- |-· · ·-|- ^x>=|-- |-· -|-+|-|- |-•|- |-ºr Cr?----|-|- |-Úſ* •·|- ·----·|--|- |-|-|- * （ < ）.z ·- ·- -|-|- …...***|-|- ·**|- |-·· ·· · -|- |-|- |-|-… --|- +…* •·+> ~~|-|-|- |- ---- |-， ， |-…|-|-|-|- |-·-----í！ -|-|- -|-|- |-·|-|-|-|- - →|-|-|-|- |-·|-\|-- * .|-|-·|- ·！ - |-* , , ，·，· · · ·：|-|- · · · -·----|-- |-|-|-|-|- -…º---- |-|-- ·|-|-|-|-|-|- * * · ·-|-|-|-· |-|-|-|-|-|-~~|- ·|- |-|- |--·|-·（ ）|-/r. |-|- …-|-|----- |-|-|-|--|-|--|-|- ·|-|-|-|-· º|-|-|-|-|- ·|-|-|-|-~---|- |-· |-·|-|- |-- - |-|- |-|-！|-|-|-|-|- |-• |-|- |-r. |-- |-· • • ·<|-|-“… :） |-|- -|-· - |-/- - - |-|-|--|- - -→ ·|-|-|- |-- -* ----|-|-|-|-|-|-|-|- |- ·-|- |-|-|-|-|- |-|- |-; ;“. |-·-|- |-|-|-|-|-|-- |-|-----|-|-|-|-|-|- |-|-|-|--|- - -. »|-|-|-|-\ |-|-|- |--|- |-|-*· |-|-- |-|-· ·|-|-|-|- · |-|-|-|-|- * … |-|-|×---- |-·---- |-•|- |-|- ·-|-…* .|- |-…’|- • |-----· ·|- |-··|-· · · ·|-|-· ·-|-|- |-|-·|×|-|-· |- |-…" · |-|-! · \） |-|-|-· |· - * *





Page 74

- -

Page 75

Book II. 21cqalug and Barth.cnta. 75 - (9) With that, be grip'd her rudely by the fair And bounteous treaſure of her Nymph-like hair: And, by it, drag'd her on the duſty floor: He ſtopt her mouth, for fear ſhe ſhould implore An aid from Heaven: ſhe wouning in the place, His ſalvage hands beſmear'd her liveleſs face . . . With horrid poyſon, thinking ſhe was dead, - He left her breathleſs, and away he fled, Come, come ye Furies, you'malignant ſpirits, Infernal Harpies, or whit elſe inherits. The Land of darkneſs; you that ſtill converſe h'ith damned ſouls; you, you that can rehearſ? The horridfaths of villains, and can tell Howevery Hellhound looks that roars in Heſſ, Survey them all; and, then inform my Pea, To dran in one, the monster of all Men: Teach me to limb a villain, and to paint, With dextrous art, the baſeſt Sycºphant That ere the mouth of inſolent diſdain Pouchſafīd to ſpit upon : The putrid Blain Of all diſeaſed humors, fit for none But Dogs to lift their haſty legs upon : So clear men's eyes, that whoſº'er ſhall ſee The type of baſemeſ, may cry, this is he Let his reproach be a perpetual blot In Honors Book: Let his remembrance rot In algood mindes : Let mone but villains caſt His Bºg-bear name to memory, where withall F.2 Tº
Page 76

76 ºrgains and eartbenia, Bookſ. - To fright their bauling Baſtards : Let no ſpell Befouma more potent, to prevail in Hell, Than the mime Letters of his charm-like name: Which, let our baſhful Chris-croſs-row diſt/aim - To the worlds end, not worthy to be ſet . . . ; In any but the jewiſh Alphabet. rq ft. . But hark Am I deceiv'd: Or do I hear f The voice of Arg’lus ſounding in mine ear? He calls Parthenia: No, that tongue can be No counterfeit : He's come: 'Tis he, 'tis he. ' Welcome too late, that are now come too ſoon : Hadſt thou been here, this deed had ne're been done. Alas! when loverslinger, and out-go Their promis'd Date,they know not what they do: Men fondly ſay, That women are too fond At parting; to require ſo ſtrićt a Bond For quick return: Poor ſouls 'Tis they endure Oft-times the danger of the forfeiture : I blame them not: For miſchief ſtill attends Upon the too long abſence of true friends. Well, Argalus is come, and ſeeks about In every room to find Parthenia out: He asks, inquires, but all Lips are ſparing To be the Authors of ill news, not daring To ſpeak the truth: they all amazed ſtand: And now my Lord's as fearful to demand; Dares not enquire her health, left his ſad ear * Should hear ſuch words, as he's afraid to hear: Aiſlips are bolted with a Linnen Bar, And every eye does, like a Blazing-Star, Portend ſome evil; no Language findes a Leak: The leſs they ſpeak, the more he fears to ſpeak. Faces
Page 77

Book II. ºrgaſus and pattºrnia. 77" z- Faces grow ſad, and every private ear Is turn’d a Cloſet for the whiſperer : º He walks the room; and like an unknown ſtranger, They eye him : from each eye, he picksadanger. At laſt his Lips not daring t'importune What none dare tell him, unexpected Fortune Leads his raſh ſteps into a dark’ned room, A place more black than night: Noſooner come, , But he was welcom'd with a figh, as deep, As a ſpent heart can give : He heard one weep, And by the noiſe of groans and ſobs, was led (Having no other guide) to the ſad Bed. Who is't (ſaid he] that calls untimely might To hide thoſe grief; that thus abjure the light a With that, as if her heart had rent in two, She paſt a ſigh, and ſaid, O ask not who 1/rge not my tongue to make a forc’d Reply Toyour demand! Alas! It is not I. Not I (ſaid he 2 ) What Language do I hear? Darkneſs may #op mine eye, but not mine ear : It is my dear Partheniaes voice, Ah me ! And can Parthenia, not Parthenia be? - inhat means this word, (Alas! It is not I?) it hat ſudden ill hath taught thee to deny Thyſelf? or what can Argalus then claim, If his Parthenia be not the ſame . She was 2 Alas, it ſeems to me all one º To ſay, Thouart not hers, that’s not her own : can hills forget their pondrous bulk, and flie Like wandring Atoms, in the empty skie : Or can the Heavens (grown idle ) not fulfil Their certain revolutions, but ſtand ſºil, - . - F 3 - - A*3
Page 78

is ºrgalus and parturnia. Bºii. And leave their conſtant motion for the wind Tº inherit: can Parthenia change her mind? . Heav'n ſoonerſhall ſtandſtill, and Earth remove, E’ermy Parthenia falſifie her love: - 1łnfºld thy riddle then ; and tell me, mby t Thoſe Lips ſhould ſay, (Alas ! It is not II) Whereto ſhe thus reply'd : o do not thou So mrong thy noble thoughts, as once t'allow, That curſed name a room withia thy breſt, Let ...!foul a prodigy be bleſt, with thy loſt breath: Let it be held a ſin, Too great for pardon, e'er to name’t agen: Iet darkneſ, hide it in etermal might: May it be clad with horror to affright A deſpirate conſcience: He that knows not how To mouth a curſe, O let him pračiſe mov Alfon this name: Let him that mould contračí The body of all miſchief, or extraff - The quint'ſſence of a ſorrow, omely claim A ſecret priviledge to uſe that name: Far be it from thy language, to commit Sofoul a ſin, as once to mention it : Itve happy Arg’lus; do not thou partake An theſe my miſeries: Oforbear to make My burden greater, by thy tender ſorrow: Alas, my heart is ſtrong, and needs not borrow Thy needleſ help: o be thou not ſº cruel, To feed my flaming fires with thy fuel: why doff thouſgh? O wherefore ſhould thy heart : *1ſurp my ſtage, and aff Parthenia's part : * Žt is my proper task: what, doff thou mean, Without my Licence, to intrude my scene: * : * : * : . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Alts
Page 79

ºil. Tºgalus and parturnia. 72 Alas ! thy ſorrows eaſe not my diſtreſs; \ God knows, 1 weep not onepoor tear the leſs: My Pateni's ſign'd and paſt, whereby appears. That I have got the Monopoly of tears, In me let each mans torment find an end: i I am that Sea, to which all Rivers tend : Let all ſpent mourners, that can weep no more, -1: Take tears on truſt, and ſet them on my ſtore. :* And as ſhe ſpake that word, his heart notable To bear alanguage ſo unſufferable, , , But being ſwoln ſo big, muſt either break, Or vent; his conquer'd reaſon grew to weak Toppoſe his quickned paſſion (like a man Tranſported from himſelf) he thus began: Accurſed darkneſ; : Thou ſad type of leath ! 3 Infernal Hag, whoſe dwelling is beneath! What means thy boldneſs to aſſurp this room, And force a might, before the might be come : Get, get thee down, and keep within thy lifts : Go revel there; and hurl thy hideous miſts Before thoſe citrſed eyes, that take delight In utter darkneſs, and abhor the light; Return thee to thy Dungeon, whence thou came, And hide thoſe faces, whoſe infernal flame Ca'lls for more darkneſs, and whoſe fortur’d ſºuls Crave the protećtion of th’obſcureſt holes, Toſcape ſome laſhes, and avoid thoſe ſtrič And horridplagues, the Furies do inflić: But if thou needs muſt ramble here, above, Go to ſome other climate, and remove Thy ugly preſence from our darkned eyes, Th. thate thy tyranny: Go exerciſe - F 4 Thy
Page 80

* 3rgalug and eartbenia. Bookſ: Thy power in Groves, and ſolitary ſprings, *here Bats are ſubjeńs, andwhere Owls are Kings: Go to the Graves, andfill thoſe empty rooms, That ſuch as ſlumber in their ſilent tombs May bleſ; thy welcomeſhades, and lie poſſeſ; Ofundiffurbed and eternal reſt: . . . . . . . k \ Or if thy more ambitious fogs deſire . . . . . - To haunt the living, haft thee, and retire Into ſome Cloyſter, and there ſtand between ... . The light, and thoſe that fain would ſin, unſeen : , , . . . Affift them there; and let thy ugly#. ‘. . . . - -, * * Count'nance cloſe treaſons, and inceſtuous rapes: . . . . . . Benight thoſe rooms; and aid all ſuch as fear º, . " The Eye of Heaven: Go, cloſe thy Curtains there, . . . . . We need thee not, (foul Witch) anay, anay; . . . Thou hid'ſt more beauty than the noon of day . . . . . . . Can give ; othou, that haft ſo rudely hurl’d . . . . . . on this dark bed the glory of the world. . . . . . . . . . . So ſaid, abruptly be the room departs . . . . . . . His cheeks look pale, his curled hair upſtarts Like quills of Porcupines, and from his eye. . . . . Quick flaſhes like the flames of Lightning flie: - He calls for light; the light no ſooner come, But his own hand conveys it to the room , ; From whence he came, and as he entred in He bleſt himſelf; he bleſt himſelf again, Thrice did he bleſs himſelf, and after ſaid, Foul witch be gone, and let thy diſmalſhade, Forſake this place : Let thy dark fogs obey . Great Vulcans charge; in Vulcans name, anay; br if thyſłout rebellion ſhall diſclaim - . His ſoveraignty, in my Parthenia's name 7 tº º

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 81

- - - - - - - - - w º - - - - - - - - - - - - - - * w - - - - & - - - ~ * - - - - - - - - - -r - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - + ... -- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - ----- - - - - - f - - - -- - - - - - *. - - - - - *. º - - - - - --, - - -- - - - -- - --- - -." - - - .. - - * - -- - - - - - - - - - - - -- - - -- - - - - - - º - - - - - - - - - - - - - - º - - - º - - - “. - - -- - - - * - - 2 *-

Page 82

l i i

Page 83

º- - . f. Book II. zirgalugand 49artbtuta. 83 —- I charm thee hence. And as that word flew out, He ſtept to that ſad bed, where round about, Clos'd were the Curtains, as if darkneſs did Command that ſuch a Jewelſhould behid, ( 10 ) His left hand held the taper, and his right Enforc'd the Curtains, to abſolve the light: Which done, appeará befºre his wºi, eye The trueſt portraitof deformity, , , . . . . As ere the Sunbeheld: that lovely face That was of late the model of all grace H And peerleſs beauty, whoſe imperious eyes . H Raviſht where ere they lookt, and did ſurprize H The very ſouls of men, ſhe, ſhe, of whom Nature her ſelf was proud, is now become Soloath'd an objećt, ſo deformid, diſguis'd, , , As darkneſs, for mans ſake, was well advis'd To cloath in miſts, leſt any were incited, To ſee that face, and ſo départ affrighted. . . ~ All this when Argalus beheld, and found . . . - It was no dream, he fell upon the ground, Andrav'd, and roſe again, ſtood ſtill, and gaz'd; At firſt he ſtartled, then he ſtood amaz'd : Looks now upon the light, and now on her, One while his tired fancy does refer - * His thoughts to ſilence; as his thoughts increaſe, His paſſion ſtrives for vent, and breaks that peace * Which conquer'd Reaſon had of late concluded, | And thus began: Are theſe falſe eyes deluded ? Or -º-















End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 84

W. X- º * & Argalug and partienia. Bºii. or have inchanted miſts ſtept in between My abuſed eyes, and what my eyes have ſeem : No, miſchief cannot ačf ſo fair a part, Taffright in jeſt; it goes beyond the art Of all black Books, to mask with ſuch diſguiſe So ſweet a face: I know that theſe are eyes, And this a light: Falſe miſts could never be Betwixt my poor Parthenia, and me." _ Accurſed Taper what infernal ſpright Breath'd in thyface: what fury gave thee light 2 Thou imp of Phlegeton; who let thee in Toforce a day, before the day begin: mho brought thee hither? I did I? From whom, ºr What lean-chapt Fury did Iſmatch thee from : :* When as this curſed %. did go about - To bring thee in, why went not theſe eyes out : | Be all ſuch Tapers curſed for thy ſake; | Ne’rſhine, but at ſome Vigil, or ſad Wake; Be never ſeem, but when as ſorrow calls Thy needful help to nightly funerals; Be as a May-game for th’amazed Bat To ſport about ; and Only to wonder at : Still haunt the chancels at a midnight-knell, v To fright the Sextonfrom his paſſing Bell: % Give light to mone but treaſons, and be hid. In their dark lanthorns: Let all mirth forbid , Thy treacherous flames the room; and if that none Shaldaign to put thee out, go out alone: - Attend ſome Miſer's table, and then waſte Too ſºon, that he may curſe thee for thy haſte; Burn dim for ever: Let that flatt’ring light Thou feedſ, conſume thy ſtock: be baniſht quite From
Page 85

Bº: II. 2ſtgalug and 42attl)&nta. 85 From Cupids Court: When lovers go about Their ſtolen pleaſures, let your flames go out : Henceforth be uſeful to no other end, But onely to burn day-light, or attend - - The midnight Cups of ſuch as ſhall reſign With uſury their undigeſted ſpine: - Why doſt thou burn ſo clear: Alas ! theſe eyes Diſcern too much ; thy wanton blaze doth riſe Too bigh a pitch:thou burn'ſ too bright for ſuch Asſee no comfort : O thouſhin'ſ too much: * Why doff thouvex me? Is thy flameſ ſtout º Tendure my breath: this breath ſhallpuff thee out: Thus, thus my joys are quite 2. 726 Jęy To be reviv'd : Thus gone, thus § ever, With that, tranſported with a furious haſte, He blew it out: but mark, that very blaſt (As if it meant on purpoſe, to diſclaim - His deſpirate thoughts) reviv'd th’extinguiſht flame, He ſtandsamaz'd; and, having mus’d a while, Beholds the Taper, and begins to ſmile. ‘And can the gods themſelves (ſaid he) contrive 4 way for hope & Can my paſt joys revive, Like %. 2.É. ; ºft, do, - Fle curſe my lips (bright Lamp)for curſing you. . . . Eternal Fates deal fairly; dally not : - - If your hid bounties have reſerv'd a lot # Beyand my reamed hope, be it expreſt In open view; make haſte, and do your beſt : But if your juſtice be determin'd ſo - ~~ To excerciſe your vengeance on my wo, a . Strengthen not mhat at length you mean to burſt; Strike home betimes; diſpatch, and do your wºrſt : h - That * *
Page 86

36 Targains and parthenia. Bookſ. * That burthen is too great for him to bear, ſ That's evenly poiſed betwixt hope and fear. { And there he ſtopt; as fearing to moleſt The ſilent peace of her diſſembled reſt. t He gaz'd upon her; ſtood as in a trance: | Sometimes her liveleſs hand he would advance | To his ſad Lips; then ſteal it down agen: - Sometimes, a tear would fall upon’t, and then f Aſgh muſt dry it; every kiſsdid bear , º A figh, and every figh begat a tear: - I. He kiſt, he §, he wept, and, for a ſpace; | He fixthis eye upon her wounded face, º And in a whiſpering language, he disburs'd - * Hisyarious thoughts; thus, with himſelf diſcours'd, And were the Sun-beams of thoſe eies too fierce & For mortal view: or did thoſe fires diſperſe X. t Flames two conſuming for th'amaz'd beholder f Or did thy youth . treaſon e'er the bolder - To ſtain that brow; and by a midnight theft, To ſteal more beauty than the day had left? or did that blind, that childiſh god deſcry A kind of twilight from that heavenly eie, . which, over-bright, he ſought to make more dinº By blurring that, which elſe had blaſted him : Or did the Sea-born goddeſs Queen repine To ſee her Star out-ſhone ſº much by thine : Andfill'd with rage, and envious deſpight, X. Sent down a cloud tº eclipſe ſº fair a % 2 - or did the wiſer Deities foreſte - This likely danger; that when men ſhould ſee So bright a Lamp; fearing they ſhould commit Such ſweet idolatry, benighted it : - Ul

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 87

º: ºf ºrgālūETPastºnia. A Tor did the too too careful gods cºnſpire . . . . . . . #ſº: , And knoWingſºch an eie too bright for any, x. gave it a wound, #. it ſhould round too many? . . . . . fſ, they meant, they might have been more kind ſo ſave that beautie, and have ſtruck us blind. . . . Before the ſound of his laſt breath was gone Her ſpeech being marſhal'd with a powerful groan Through the rudeconfluence,and amazed thron # her diſtracted thoughts) her feeble tongue Wept forth theſe . Thus fleet, thus tranſtory 's mans delight, and all thatpainted glory. . . . °oor Earth can give : Nor wealth, nar blood, nor heaktie, ſam quit the debt, that meceſſary dutie - They on to Change and Time; but like a flowr, They flouriſh now, andfade within an hour: The morld’s compos'd of change, there's nothing ſtaies At the ſame point ; all alters, all decaies: The world is like a Play, where every age ºx. Concludes her Scene, and ſo departs the ſtage; º And when Times haſty hour-glaſs is run, - Change ſtrikes theEpilogue,andallthe Play is dome. ...}{ Who afts the King to day, by chance of lot, Perchance to morrow begs, and bluſhes not : Whoſe beautie was ador'do'er night, next morning * * * * - - - -: - & & May find a face, like mine, not worth the ſcorning : * , Zook where we lift, there’s nothing to the eie Seems truly conſtant, but Inconſtancy. Azoft dear Parthenia, (Argalus repli’d) .X. Had thy deceived eie but ſtept aſide, b And ſockt upon thy Argalus his bre; ; I know, I &nvº, thy (anguage had profeſt º × - Another - -

Page 88

sº Târgains and partººnia.T.Boºk. 'ſ Anotherfaith: Thy Lips had nºr let flie, At unawares, ſo great an Hereſie : " . . 'Tis not the change of favor, that can change My heart; nor Time, nor Fortune can eſtrange My beft affeitions, ſo for ever fixt on thee, nothing but death can come betwixt My ſºul and thine: If I had lov'd thy face, - Thyface alone; my fancie had given place, ºff. to freſh %. and #. Mpon new fortunes; and the old had ended. If I had lov'd thee for thy heavenly eye, º I might have courted the bright Majeſty of Titan: if thy curious Lips had ſnar'd - My lickriſh thoughts, I might have ſoon prepar’d A bluſhing Corral, or ſºme fullripe Cherry, Andpleas'd my Lips, until my Lips were weary; Or if the ſmoothneſs of thy whiter brow Had charm'd mine eyes, and made my fancie bow To outward objećts, poliſht Marble might - Have given as much content, as much delight 3 In brief, had Argalus his flatter'd eye Been plex'd with beauties bare Epitomy, - Thy curious piſture might have then ſuppli’d My wants, more full, than all the world beſide : No, no ; 'Twas neither brow, nor lip, nor eye, Nor any outward ex'lence urg'd me, why * fo love Parthenia: 'twathy better part, 2% y p Øſhich miſchiefcould not wrong) ſurpris'd my heart? *Thy beauty was but like a Chryſtal caſe, Through which, the jewel of admired grace Tranſparent was, whoſe hidden worth did make . Me love the Casket for the jewels ſake: ~5 * A. - º -
Page 89

Book II. ". Argalug and parthenia. 89 We, mo, my mell adviſed eye pierc't in Beyond the film; ſunk deeper than the skin ; Elſe had I now been chang'd, and that firm duty * I ovemy Voys, had faded with thy beauty : • Nay, neep not my Parthenia; let thoſe tears Me'r nail that loſs which a few after years Had claim’d as due; chear up, thouhaft forſaken But that, which ſickneſs would (perchance) have taken, With greater diſadvantage; or elſe age, . . . . * That common evil, which art cannot aſſwage ; Beauty’s but bare opinion : White and Red - - Piave no more priviledge than what is bred . . . . . . By humane fancy, which was ne’re confin'd . . . . . To certain bounds, but varies like the wind : - What one man likes, another diſreſpects, x And what a third moſt hates, a fourth affèës : The Negro's eye thinks black beyond compare, y | And what willfright as moſt, they count moſt fair. % - If then opinion be the touch, whereby . . . All beauty’s tried ; Parthenia in my eye, > * . . Out-ſhines fair Helen, or who elſe ſhe be . . . . . . That is more rich in beauty's wealth than ſhe. . . . Chear up : the ſoveraignty of thy worth infranches Thy captive beauty; and thy vertue blanches #% eſtains offortune: come, it matters not What others think: a letter’s but a blot - Toſuch as cannot read; but, who have skill, . . . . . . Canknow the fair º: of a quil, From groſs and heedleſs blurs; and ſuch canthink No paper foul, that’s fairly writ with Ink: - What others hold a blemiſh in thy face, Myskilful eyes read charaćfers of grace: . A G ** º - - -- " * : - * * * * z What

Page 90

90 ºtgalug and Partbenia. Book II. M'hat hinders then, but that without delay, Triumph may celebrate our nuptial day 2 She that hath only vertue to her guide, Though wanting beauty is the faireſt bride. * A Bride! (ſaid ſhe) ſuch Brides as I, can have No fitter bridal chamber then a Grave: Death is my Bridegroome; and to welcom Death, My loyal heart ſhallplight aſecond Faith: .. Andwhen that dayſhalloome, that joyful day Wherein tranſcendant pleaſures ſhall allay The heat of all my ſorrows, and conjoym - Mypale-fac’d Bridegroom's lingring handwith mine, Theſe Ceremonies and theſe Triumphs ſhall Attend the day to grace that day withall. Time with his empty Hour-glaſſhallead The triumph on, his winged hoofſhall tread Slowpaces ; After him thereſhallenſue . The chaft Diana with her Virgin crew, All crown'd with Cypreſs garlands : after whom In rahk, th’ impartial Deſtiniesſhall come: . . . Then in aſableChariotfaintly drawn With harneſt Virginsvail'd with pureſ lawn, . The Bride ſhalft; Diſpair and Griefſhall ſtand Like heartleſs Bridemaids upon either hand: Wºon the Chariot top, thereſhall be plat'd The little winged god with arm unbrac'd, And Bow umbent; his drooping wings muſt hide . . . His makedknees, his Quiver by his ſide - Muſt be unarm’d, and either hand muſt hold A Banner, wherewith Charaćters of gold Shall be decipher'd (fit for every eye - To read that runs JFaith, Love, and continº. - - €3:f
Page 91

- Book II. atgalus and partbenia 9. Mext after, hope, in a diſcoloured weed Shallſadly march alone: Aſlender Reed . - Shalguide her feeble ſteps, and in her hand + A broken Anchor all beſmear'd with ſand. - And after all, the Bridegroom ſhall appear : Like Joves Liuetenant, and bring up the rear, He ſhall be mounted on a Coal-black Steed, - His handſhak hold a Dart, on whichſhallbleed . A pierced heart, wherein a former wound Which Cupids Javelin enter’d, ſhall be found. . When as the Triumphs ſhall adorn our feaſt, Let Argulus be my invited gueſt, And let him bid me nuptial Joy, from whom Ionce expeºfed almyjoys ſhould come. º With that, as ifhiscount'nance had thought good To wear death colours, or as if his blood * - Had been imployed to condole the ſmart And torment of his poor afflićted heart, He thus beſpake: "Unhappieſt of allmen, - Why do Ilive? is Death my Rival them? # Tºnequal chance 1 Had it been flºſh and blood I could have grapled, and (perchance)withſtood Some ſtout incounters: had an armed hoſt Of mortal Rivals ventur'd to have croft * My beſt deſires; my Partheniaes eye ad given mepower to make that army fly Likefrighted Lambs before the Wolfe; but thou Before whoſe preſence all muſt ſtoop and bow ... Their ſervile necks; what weapon; ſhall I hold Againſt thy hand that will not be controuſ'd? :}: Greatenemy: whoſe Kingdom's in the duſt • And darkſome Cavés; I know that thou art juſt ; G 2 Eſſe º º
Page 92

92 3rgalug and 49attbcilia. Book II. Elſe had the Gods ne’re truſted to thy hand So great a priviledge, ſo large command A: And juriſdićtion ore the lives of men, To kill and ſave even mhom they pleaſe, and when : O, ſuffer mot Parthenia's tempting tears. To move thy heart; let thy hard-hearted ears Be deaf to all her ſuits: if ſhe profeſs - Afféétion to thee, believe nothing lºſs: She’s my betrothed Spouſe, and Hymen's bands, Have firmly joyn’d our hearts, though not our hands ; Where plighted Faith, and Sacro-ſančtious vow Hathgiven poſſeſſion, diſpoſſeſ; not thou: Be juſt ; and though herbriny lips bewail * Her grief with tears, let not thoſe tears prevail. PWhom Heavens havejoyn'd, thy bands may not disjoyn, I am Parthenia’s, and Parthenia’s mine; ~4las ! me are but one ; then thou muſt either x: Refuſeus both; or elſe, take both together. - My dear Parthenia, let no cloudy paſſion Ofdul deſpair moleft thee; or unfaffon Thy better thoughts, to make thy troubled mind Either %; or thy ſelf unkind: \, . Starve not my pining hopes withlonger ſtay : . . . . . . My Love hath wings, and brooks no long delay; . . . It hovers *p and down, and cannot reſt . . . . . . . |Antil it light, and perch upon thybreſt. ..., Torment not him within theſe lingringfires, . . . " That’s rack’t already on his own ; : . . . . . . . . Seal and deliver as thy deed, that band, - - - Wheretothy promit’d faith hathſet her hand ; Andwhat our plighted hearts and mutual vow Have ſo long ſince begun, O finiſh now ; -* º . . . . - -
Page 93

Book II. Argalug and partbenis. 93 That our imperfeół, and half pleaſures may Receive perfeółion by a marriage day. - Whereto, ſhe thus : Had the pleas'd Gods above Forgiven my faults, and made me fit for Jove To blºſ at large; had all the powers of haven (To boaſt the utmoſt of their bounty) given As great addition to myſlender fortune As they could give, or covetoſe mind importune, I von to heaven, and all thoſe heavenly powers, They ſhould no longer be made mine, but yours; May, had any fortunes ſtay’d but at the rate They were ; had Iremained in that ſtate I was (although at firſt unworthy far Of ſuch a peerleſs bleſſing as you are) My dear acceptance ſhould have fill'd my heart As full of joys as now it is of ſmart. Aſ But, as I am, let angry Jove them vent On me his plagues, till all his plagues be ſpent : And when I roar, let heaven my painsAeride, When I match Argalus to ſuch a Bride : Live happy Argalus, let thy ſoul receive H'hat blºſings poor Parthenia cannot have : Live happy: may thy joys be mever done, But let one blºſing draw another on : & O may thy better Angel watch and ward Thy ſoul, and pitch an everlaffing guard About the Portals of thy tender heart And ſhorer damn blºffags whereſo'ere thoſ, art: Let althy joys be as the Month of May, :* Andall thy days beas a Marriage day : - Let ſorror, ſickneſs, and a troubled mid Beftrangers to thee, let them never find * . w -
Page 94

94 3rgalus and parthenia. Bookſ. Thy heart at home: let Fortune ſtill allot Such larlºſs gueſts to thoſe that love thee not : And let thoſe blºſings, which ſhall wanting be To ſuch as merit none, alight on thee. That mutual faith betwixt us, that of late Hath paſt, I give thee freedom to tranſlate Opon the merits of ſomefitter Spouſe; I give thee leave, and freely qiut thy vows: Icall the Gods to witneſs, nothing ſhall More bleſ; my ſoul, no comfort can befall More truly welcome to me, than to ſee My Argalus (what ere become of me) Solinſ’t in wedlock, as ſha/moſt augment His greater honoºr, and his true comtent. With that, a ſudden and tempeſtuous tyde Qftears orewhelm’d her language, and deny’d A paſſage; but when paſſions flood was ſpent, She thus proceeds : Tou Gods, if you are bent To aſſ my Tragedy, why do you mrong Our patienceſo, to make the Play ſo long 2 Tour Scenes are tedious ; gainſt the Rules of art, Tou dwell too long, too long upon omepart. Be brief, and take advantage of your odds, 3: One ſimple Maidamongſ ſo many Gods, - And not be conquer'd yet 2 conjoymyour might, And ſend her Soul into eternal Night, That livertoo long a day: I’ll not reſiſt; Provided you ſtrike home, ſtrike where yelift : Accurſed be that day, wherein theſe eyes . . Firſt ſaw the light ; let deſprate ſouls deviſe . A curſe ſuffeient for it: let the Sun We're ſhine upon it; and what ere's begun
Page 95

Book II. 3tgalug and 42ättbcuià. 95 Tpon that fatal day, let heaven forbid it Succeſs; if not t'enſnare the hand that did it. Why was I born ? Or, being born, O why Did not my fonder Wurſes Lullaby (Even whil'ſ my Lips were hanging on her breſ) Sing her poor Babe to everlaſting reſt ? & Othen my Infant ſoul had never known This world of grief, beneath whoſe weight Igrown : Aſo, no, it had not ; he that dies in's prime, - Speeds a long buſineſs in a little time, - - But Argala, (whoſe more extream deſire, Ulnapt to yield, like water-ſprinkled fire, Did blaze the more) impatient ofdenial, Gave thus an on-ſet to a further tryal : Life of my ſoul; by whom, .ext heaven, I breath: Excepting mhom, I have no friend but Death: How can thy wiſhes eaſe my grief, or ſtand My miſery in #ead, when as thy hand, Andnothing but thy helping hand can give me Relief, and yet refuſes to relieve me? Strange kind of charity, when being afflićfed, Iffnd beſt wiſhes, yet am interdiffed Of thoſe best wiſhes, and muſt be remov’d From loves injoyment; why? becauſe belov’d. ...Alas! alas ! %. can my wiſhes be A bleſſing to me, ifumbleft in thee 2 Thy beauty's gone, (thou ſay’ſ) why, let it go ; He loves but ill, that loves but for aſhow; Zhy beauty isſupply'd in my affection, That neveryet masſlave to a complexion. Shall every day, wherein the earth doth lack The Sun's reflex, b’expell'd the Almanack? G 4 Or º - Y
Page 96

96 3tgălug and 42attbenia. Book II. Orſhall thy over-curious ſteps forbear •v. A Garden 'cauſe there are mo Roſes there? X Orſhall the Sun-ſet of Parthenia's beauty Enforce my judgment to negle&# that duty, The which my beſt advis'd affeifion ows Her ſacred vertue, and my ſolemn vows 2 No, no; it lies not in the power of Fate To make Parthenia too unfortunate For Argulus to love. It is as eaſe for Parthenia's heart To prove leſs vertuous, as for me to ſtart - From my firm faith; the flame that honours breat, Hath blonn, nothing hathpower to quench but death; Thougav’ſ me leave to choſe a fitter Spouſe, - And freedom to recall, to quit thoſe vows I took: who gave thee licenſe to diſpenſe With ſuch falſe tongues as offer violence Toplighted faith? ala I thou can'ſ not free Thyſelf, much leſs hadſ; power to licenſeme. Vows can admit no change, they ſtillperſever ...Againſt all change; they bind for ever: Avon's a holy thing, no common breath : The limits of a vow is Heaven and Death: A vow that’s paſt, is like a bird that’s flown From out thy hand, can be recall’d by mome; It dies not, like a time-beguiling Jeſt, Asſoon as verred; lives not in thybreſt, # When atter d ºnce, but is a ſacred word Straight entrea'im the ſtrić and cloſe Record Of Heaven; it is not like a Jugler’s knot, - - Orff, or looſe, a pleaſes u, or not. Since º
Page 97

Book II. ºrgalug and pattbenia. 97 -- Since then thy vows can find no diſpenſation, Aud may not be recal’d, recal thy paſtou; , , Perform, perform what now it is too late, . T’unniſh againe, too ſoon to violate: ºek not to quit, what Heaven denyes to free Perform thy vows to Heaven, thy vows to me. 3 #rice dearer then my ſoul,(ſhe thus repli’d) Had my on a pampered fancy been the guide ſo ºff ºoº, I had condeſcended. . . * this, to year regueſt, which had befreinded º 'ºft deſires top: I lov’d not thee . . . . . ºr ºyowa pleaſure in that baſe degree, A gluttons do their diet, who diſpenſe MWith univaſh't hands, (left they ſhould give offence # To their grip’d ſtomacks, when a minutes ſta * . Will make them curſe occaſion all the day) Ilov’d not ſo; my firſt deſires did ſpring . . . From thy own worth ; and as a ſacred thing, I always view'd thee, whom my zeal commands Me not prophane whith theſe defiled hands: Tis true; performauce is a debt we owe To Vows,and nothing’s dearer than avoir; Tet when the Gods do raviſh from our hand, The means to keep it, 'tis a countermand. He that hath vow'd to ſacrifice each day, . At Juno's altars bound, and muſt obey: But if (being under voiv) the Gods do pleaſe . To ſtrike him with a leprous diſeaſe, X Orfoul infection; which is better now, Prophane the Altar, or to breake the von 2 The caſe is mine; where then the Gods diſpence, We may be bold, yet tender no offence. . . . - - Admit
Page 98

98 3tyalus and parthenia. Book II. l Admit it were an evil; 'tis our beſt, Of neceſſary ills, to chuſe the leaſt. The Gods aregood; theſtrić recogniſance Of vows, is only taken to advance - The good of man; now if that goodprove ill, We may refuſe, our vow’s intire ſtill. Ivow a marriage; why? becauſe I do Entirely effect that man my Vows are to ; But if ſome foul diſeaſeſhould interpoſe Betwixt our promis'd marriage, and our von's . The ſtričíperformance of theſe vows muſt prove A wrong; and therefore love not, whom I love. Then urgenomore: Let my denial be Apledge ſufficient’twixt my love, and thee. So ended ſhe . But vehement deſire (That can be quencht with No,no more then fire Withoyl ; and can ſubmit to no condition) Lends him new breath: Love makes a Rhetorician; He ſpeaks; ſhe anſwers: He, afreſh, replies; He ſtoutly ſues; as ſtoutly ſhe denyes. He begs in vain; and ſhe denies in vain : For ſhe denies again: He begs again. Atlaſt, both weary, he his ſuit adjourns; For Lovers days are good, and bad by turns. He bids farewel; as if the heart of either Gave but one motion, they both ſigh’d together. She bids farewel; and yet ſhe bids it ſo, As if her farewelended, ifhego; He bids farewel; but ſo, as if delay Had promis'd better farewels to his ſtay. She bids farewel, but holds his hand ſo faſt, Asifthat farewel had not been the laſt. …” t Both
Page 99

Book II. Žtgalug and pattºrnia. 99 Both figh'd, both wept, and both being heavy hearted, She bids farewel, he bids farewel, and garted. - Soparted they : Now Argalus is gone? And now Parthenia's weeping all alone, And like the widdow'd turtle ſhe bewails - The abſence of her mate: Paſſion prevails ... - Above her ſtrength : Now her poor heart can tell What's Heaven by wanting Heaven: and what's Hell By her own torments : Sorrow now does play. The Tyrants part, Affečtion muſt obey; - And like a weathercock her various mind Is chang'd and turn'd with every blaſt of wind. In deſp'rate language ſhe deplores her ſtate ; She fain would wiſh, but then ſhe knows not what: Reſolves of this, of that, and then of neither, - She fain would flee: but then ſhe knows not whither: . . At length (conſulting with the heartleſs pair 2

Page 100

Blank page
Page 101

Book II. 3rgalug and 42atthenia. 101 s (11) ofalladviſors,Sorrow and Diſpair) Reſolves to take th'advantage of that night, To ſteal away, and ſeek for death by flight : | A Pilgrim’s weed her liveleſslimbs addreſt i s From head to foot: a thong of leather bleſt . . . . . Her waſted loyns; her feeble feet were ſhod With ſandals: In her hand a Pilgrims rod. . . . . . . When asth illuſtrious Soveraign of the day Had now begun his circuit to ſurvey His lower Kingdom, having newly lent The upper world to Cynthia's Government, Forth went Parthenia, and begins tattend . . . . o The progreſs now, which only death can end. . . . . . Go hapleſs Virgin? Fortunebe thy guide, And thy own vertues; and what elſe beſide, . . . . That may be proſperous; may thy merits find a . More happineſs than thy diſtreſſed mind . . . . . " Can hope: Live, and to after ages prove , º, . , Af The great example of true Faith and Love: . . . . Gone, gone ſhe is ; but whither ſhe is gone, . . . . . The Gods and Fortune can reſolve alone : . . . . . . Pardon my Quill, that is inforc’t to ſtray . . . . . . . From a poor Lady in an unknownway. . . . . . . . . To number forth her weary ſteps, or tell ' ' ' ' Thoſe obvious dangers that ſo oftbefell . . . . . Our poor. Parthenia in her pilgrimage, Or bring her miſeries on the open ſtage, Her broken ſlumbers, her diſtraćted care : Her hourly fears and frights, her hungry fare; Her dayly perils, and her nightly’ſ apes From ravenous beaſts, and from attempted rapes, I - - $ &
Page 102

1oz 3rgalug and £arthenia. Bookſ. º Is not my task; who care not to incite My Readers paſſion to an appetite. We leave Parthenia now; and our diſcourſe Muſt caſt an eye, and bend her ſettled courſe To Argalus. 2. When Argalus (returning To viſit his Partheina the next morning) Perceived ſhe was fled, not knowing whither, He makes no ſtay; conſults not with the Weather; Stays not to think, but claps his haſty knees To his fleet Courſer, and away he flees; His haſte enquires no way, (he needs not fear # Toloſe the Road,that goes he knows not where : ) One while he pricks upon the fruitful plains; And now he gently ſlacks his prouder reins And climbs the barrenhills: with freſh careers He tries the right handway; and when heveres His courſe upon the left: One while he likes This path, when by and by his fancy ſtrikes llpon another track. Sometime he roves: Among the Springs and ſolitary Groves, Where, on the tender barks of ſundry trees, Hengraves Parthenia's name with his, then flees To the wild champian: his proud Steed removes The hopeful fallows, with his horned hooves: He baulks no way, rides over Rock and Mountain, When led by Fortune to Diana's Fountain, (12). He ſtraight diſmounts his Steed, begins to His thirſty i. ;and after that,to drench (quench His fainting limbs, in that ſweet ſtream, wherein Parthenia’sdainty fingersoft had been. The
Page 103

---- ----- ~~ ~~~~ |-№ Sèèè） 22%

Page 104

104. 3rgalug and 42atthenia. Book 11. --> The Fountain was upon a ſteep deſcent Whoſe gliding current nature gave a vent Through a firm rock, which art (to make it known To after ages) wall'd and rooft with ſtone : Above the Chryſtal Fountain's head was plac'd Diana’s Image (though of late defac’d:) Beneath, a rocky Ciſterſ; did retain * . The water, ſliding through the Cocks of Cane, Whoſecurious current the world's greater eye Ne'review’d, but in his mid-day Majeſty: It was that Fountain, were in elder times Poor Corydon compos'd his rural rimes. And left them cloſely hid, for his unkind 4. And marble hearted Philida to find. - All rites perform’d, he re-amounts his Steed, Redeems his loſſe of time with a new ſpeed: And with a freſh ſupply, his ſtrength renews His progreſs, God knows whether: He purſues Hisvow’d adventure, brooking no delay, And (with a mind as doubtful as the way) He journeyson; he left no courſe unthought: No traveller unaskt; no place unſought. To makea Journal of each circumſtance; His change of fortunes, or each obvious chance … Befel his tedious travel : to relate * The brave attempt of this exploit, or that; His rare atchievements, and their fair ſucceſs; His noble courage, in extream diſtreſs; His deſp'ratedangers, his deliverance: º His higheſteem with men, which did enhance His meaneſt ačtions to the throne of jove: And what he ſuffer'd for Parthenia's love, Would
Page 105

* Book II ºrgalus and particula. Tros | Would make our Volume endleſſe,apt to trie The utmoſt patience of a ſtudious eye: All which the bounty of free conceit May ſooner reach to, then my pen relate. But till bright Cynthiae; head had three times thrice Repair'd her empty horns, and fill'd the eyes Ofgazing mortals, with her globe of light, This reſtleſſe Lover ceas'd not, day and night To wander, in a ſolitary queſt For her, whoſe love had taught him to digeſt The dregs of ſorrow, and to countall joyes. But follies (wheigh’d with her) at leaſt, but toyes: It hapned now, that twice ſix moneths had run Since wandring Argalus had firſt begun . . Histoilſome progreſs; who, in vain had ſpent An year of hours, and yet no event, When fortune brought him to a goodly ſeat, (Wall’d round about with hills) yet not ſo great As pleaſant; and leſs curious to the fight, Then ſtrong, yetyeilding even as much delight As ſtrength: whoſe only out-ſide did declare The Maſters judgment, and the builders care. - Around the Caſtle, Nature had laid out - The bounty of her treaſure; roundabout - Well fenced Meadows (filſ'd with Summers pride) Promis'd proviſion for the Wintertide: , , Near which the neighb'ring hills (well ſtockt& ſlo.’d With milk-white flocks) did ſeverally afford Their fruitful bleſſings, and deſerv’d increaſe To painful Husbandry, the child of Peace: It was Kalanders ſeat, who was the brother of oil Parthenia; late deceaſed Mother. He

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 106

----------- - - · - -· …------------！----- （i. | Tſji T |-~ ! * ，！ • •·|- × × × ·|-^^ lae ---- |-- …” （ ） · * ----- ！•. w |-·|- ! ----- |º G , · · -··|- |- |---- « ！|- ||- ---+ …- } |- |-*|-|- ·|- · · |- |- · |-. -- |------ ----|-|-|-|-- -- -|-|- |- ---- |-•|-|- |-·|- - |-|-· |-- |-

Page 107

Book II. 3tgalug and 49attijemiá. I O 7 He was a Gentleman, whom vain ambition Ne’r taught to undervalue the condition Ofprivate Gentry; who preferr'd the love - | Of his reſpected neighbours, far above tº - The apiſh Congies of th’unconſtant Court Ambitous of a good, not great report: . . Beloved of his Prince, yet not depending - Upon his favours ſo, as to be tending . . . . . . llpon his Perſon: and, in brief, too ſtrong - - t Within himſelf, for fortune's hand to wrong : • , . - ( I 3. ) - - . Thither came wandring Argalus, & receiv'd - As great content, as one that was bereav'd . . . Of all hisjoyes, could take; or who would ſtrive T’expreſſe a welcom to the life, could give. His richly furniſht Table more expreſt . . A common bounty, then a curious feaſt; . . . . Whereat the choice of precious wines were proffe'rd In liberal ſort; not urg’d but freely offer'd : - |. The careful ſervants did attend the room: | No need to bid them either go or come: . . . . . . Each knew his place, his office, and could ſpie : " . . . | His Maſters pleaſure in his Maſterseye. . . . . But what can reliſh pleaſing to a taſt . That is diſtemper’df Can a ſweet repaſt } Pleaſe a ſickpalate? No, there's no content Can enter Argalus, whoſe ſoul is bent . . . . . . . To tire on his own thoughts: Kalanders love . . (That other times would raviſh) cannot move . . . * That fixed heart, which paſſion now incites T” abjure all pleaſures, and forſwear delights. • . - H 2 - - ſt ... }, + -- * *

Page 108

CŞ 3tgalug and 49atthenia. Book II. It fortun'd, on a day, that dinner ending, Kalander and his noble gueſts intending T’exchange their pleaſures in the open air, A Meſſenger came in, and did repair Llnto Kalander, told him, that the end Of his imployment, was to recommend A noble Lady to him (near alli’d, Tofair Qeen Hellen) whoſe unskilful guide: Had ſo miſled, that ſhe does make requeſt, This Night to be his bold and unknown gueſt: : And by his help to be inform'd the way, * To find tomorrow, what ſhe loſt to day: §. (the extent of whoſe ambition as to expreſs the bounteous diſpoſition Ofa free heart, as glad of ſuch occaſion To entertain) return'd the ſalutation - Of an unknown Servant; and withal profeſt A promis'd welcome to ſo fair a gueſt. Forthwith Kalander and his noble friends, (All but poor Argalus, who recommends His thoughts to private uſes, and confines His ſecret fancy to his own deſigns) Mounting their praunſing Steeds, to give a meeting, To his fairgueſt: they met, but at firſt greeting. (14) Kalanderſtood amaz'd, (for he ſuppos'd it was Parthenia) and thus his thoughts diſclos'd : Madam (ſaid he ) if theſe mine aged eyes Retain that wonted ſtrength, which age denies To many of my years, I ſhould be bold . . - * (In viewing you, ) to ſay, I do behold My | - * → - - - - - - º

Page 109

| | U|||||||||| \!



Page 110

to 3tgalug and 42attbellia. Book II. My Neece Parthenia’s face : Nor can I be Perſivaded (by your leave) but you areſhe. Thrice noble Sir (ſhe thus reply'd) your tongue (Perchance) hath done the fair Parthenia wrong, In your miſtake, and too much honour'd me, That (in my judgment) was more fit to be Herfoil than picture ; yet hath many an eye Given the like ſentence, ſhe not being by; Nay, more: I have been told, that my own mother Fait'd often to diſtinguiſh 'tone from 'tother. Said then Kalander: If my raſh conceit Hath made a fault, mine errour ſhall await ºpon your gratious pardon : I alone Was nºt deceiv'd ; for never any one - That view’d Parthenia's viſage, but would make As great an errour by as great miſtake. But (Madam) for her ſake, and for your own, (Whoſe worth may challange to itſelf alone, AMore ſervice than Kalander can expreſ; ) 1’ are truly welcome: enter and poſſeſ; This Caſtle as your own ; which can be bleſ: In mothing more than in ſo fair a Gueſt. - Whereto the Lady (entring) thus repli'd : Let everlaſting joys be multipli’d Within theſe gentlegates, and let them ſtand As laſting monuments in th’Arcadian Land, Ofrare and bounteous hoſpitality To after times. Let ſtrangers paſſing by Bleſs their ſucceeding heirs as ſhall deſcend From ſuch a Lord, from ſuch a noble Friend. When as a little reſpite had repair’d Her weary Limbs, which Travel had impair’d, The freeneſs of occaſion did preſent New
Page 111

Book II. 3tgălug and 43attijcilia. 11 : -> New ſubjećts to diſcourſe; wherein they ſpent Nolittle time: among the reſt befel . Kalander (often ſtopt with tears) to tell Of Argalus and loſt Parthenia's love, Whoſe undiſſembled paſſion did move A general grief; the more that they attended To his ſad tale, the more they wiſht it ended. Madam (ſaid he] although your viſage be Like hers, yet may your Fortunes diſagree; - Poor Girl; and as he ſpake that word, his eyes Let fall a tear. The Lady thus replies. My Soul doth ſuffer for Parthenia’s ſake : But tell me, Sir, Did Argalus forſake - His poor Parthenia whom he lov’d ſo dear 2 Hon hath he ſpent his days ere ſince, and where? Madam (ſaid he] when as their marriage-day Drew near; miſchief, that now was bent to play Opon the ſtage, her ſtudied maſter-prize, With ugly leproſe did ſo diſguiſe Her beauteous face, that ſhe #. 4 terror To her own ſelf: But Argalus the mirror Of trueſt conſtancy, (whoſe loyal heart, Mot guided by his eyes, diſdain'd ſº From his paſt vows) did in deſpight offortune, Purſue his fixt deſires, and importune Tº intended marriage ne’rtheleſs; but ſhe Whom reaſon now had taught to diſagree With her diſtraffed thoughts,ſtands deaf and mute, And at the laſt, t'avoid his furtherſute; , Mot making any private to herflight, , , She quits the houſe, and ſteals amay by night: But Madam, when as Argalusperceiv'd - That ſhe was fled,and being quite bereav'd - ef
Page 112

sº 3tgalug and 42atthenia Bookſ: -- Of his loſt hope, poor Lover, he aſſays . By toilſome Pilgrimage to end his days, Or find her out : Non twice ſix months have run Their tedious courſes, ſince he firſt begun His fruitleſ, journey, ranging far and near, Suffering as many Sorrows as a year - Could ſend, and made by th’extreams of weather, Tºnapt for Travel; fortunebrought him hither, Where he as yet remains, till timeſhall make His waſted body fit to undertake His diſcontinued progreſs, and renew His great inqueſt for her, who at firſt view, Madam you ſeem'd to be. - So ſaid, the Lady, from whoſe tender eyes Some drops did ſlide, whoſe heart did ſympathize With both their ſorrows; ſaid, And is there then Such unexpected conſtancy in men? [Moſt Noble Sir : I If the too raſh deſires of a ſtranger - May de diſpens'd withal without the danger Of too great boldneſs, I ſhould make requeſt To ſee this noble Lord, in whoſe rare breſt (By your report) more honour doth reſide Than in all Greece; nay, all the World beſide : I have a meſſage to him, and am loath To do it, were Inot ingag’d by Oath. Whereat Kalander not in breath, but ačtion, Applies himſelf to give a ſatisfačtion To her propounded wiſh: protraćtion waſtes No time, but up to Argalus he haſtes: (15) Arg’le comesdown, and after ſalutation ... Given and recciv'd, ſhe accoſts him on this faſhion % My

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 113

/ / -， //77 // | //// // |%ſ. /////| // // d >− ar ſráC# ! ， ， ,# * | ----!， ,|-|- {{Q !× × × |-+- Cº|- *-|-× ， , ~~ ~~… -> º z! ！ !----? ! *---- |-* ，~ ~ - -·… •9.* … ' + ' } ）; ----, ，|-* … ~~~~~ ~ ！ ---------|- ·|- |-- ----· --•••- - - ----- · · *|- ••

Page 114

1 I4 3tgalug and 42attbcuta. Pook II. My Noble Lord, Whereas the loud reſounding trump of fame Hathmois'd your worth, and gloriff'd yourname Above all others, let yourgoodneſs now Make good that fair report ; that I may know By true experience, what my joyful ear Pład but as yet the happineſs to hear, And if thefrailty of a Woman’s wit Should chance t'offend ; be noble, and remit. Then know (moſt noble Lord) my native place Is Corinth ; of the ſelfſame blood and race Withfair Queen Hellen, in whoſe princely Court I had my birth, my breeding; to be ſhort, Thither, not many days ago, there came Disguis’d and chang'd in all things but her name The rare Parthenia, ſo in ſhape transford'd, In feature alter'd, and in face deform’d, That (in my judgment) all this Region could Not ſhelva thing more ugly to behold. Long was it ere her oft repeated Vows And ſolemn Proteſtations could rouze . . CMy over dull belief: till at the laſt, - Some paſſages that heretofore had paſt Inſecret 'twixt Parthenia and me, Gave full aſſurance’t could be mone but ſhe ; Abundant welcome, (as a ſoul ſo ſad As mine, and hers, could give or take) ſhe had: So like we were in face, in ſpeech, in growth, That whoſoeverſaw the one, ſaw both; Tet were we not alike in our Complexions So much as in our Loves, in our affections : One ſorrow ſerv'd us both, and one relief Could --- &
Page 115

Eºok IT 3tgalug and 49artbcnia. - I I 5 ! (jouldeaſe us both,being partners in onegrief: Much private time we joyntly ſpent ; and neither Eouldfada true content, if not together. he ſtrange occurrents of her dire misfortue She oft diſcours’t, which ſtrongly didtmportune A world of tears from theſe ſuffuſed eyes, The true Partakers of her miſeries. And as ſhe ſpake, the accent of her ſtory Would always point upon the eternal glory . Of your rare conſtancy, which whoſoere In after ages ſhal/preſume to hear And not admire, let him beproclaim'd A rebel to a/virtue, and (defam'd In his beſt ačions) let his leprous Mame . Or die diſhonour’d, or ſurvive with ſhame. But ah! what Simples can the hand of art Find out to ſtanch a Lovers bleeding heart? Or what (alas !) can humane skull apply, To turn the Courſe of Lov’s Phlebotomy? Love is a ſecret fire, inſpir’d and blown Fyfate, which wanting hopes tofeed upon, Pi/orkſ on the very ſoul, and does torment The univerſe of man : which being ſpent And waſted in the conflić, often ſhrinks - Beneath the burthen : and ſo conquer’d, ſinks : All which yourp or Parthenia knew too well, Whoſe bed-rid hopes not having power to quell Th’ imperious fury of extream diſpair, . $he languiſh't : not being able to contraire . . The will of her vićforious paſſion; cryed, .) My deareſt Argalus farewel, and died: - My Lord, not long before her lateſt breath - * . .* Pład



Page 116

*6 3tgalug and 32atthenia. Book\; º \ Had freely paid the full arrears to death, She call dºme to her ; in her dying hand Sheſtrained mine, whil'ſ in her eyes did ſtand Aſhower of tears unwept, and in mineear She wiſper’dſo, as all the Room might hear: - Siſter (ſaid ſhe) (that title paſt between us,. Not undſerv'd, for all that ere had ſeen us ºº Miſtook usſo, at leaſt) the lateſt ſand . Of my ſpent hour-glaſs is now at hand: Thoſe joys which heaven appointed out for me, t . I here bequeath to bepoſeſt by thee; And whenſiveet deathſhall clariffe my thoughts, And drain them from the dregs of all º, Enjoy them thou, wherewith (beingſ, refin'd . From all their droſs)fullfraught thy conſtant mind: And let thy proſp’rous voyage be addreſt | To the fairport of Argalus his breſt, . i As whom the eye of Woon didne’r diſcover - So loyal, ſo removn'd, ſo rare a Lover; Caſt anchor there; for by this dying breath, Nothing campleaſe myſoul more, after death, And make my joys more perfeit, than to ſee • 4 Marriage’twixt my Argalus and thee; This Ring, thepledge betwixt his heart and mine, As freely as he gave me, Imake thine: With it untothy faithful heart I tender Myſacred vows, with it I here ſurrender . All Right and title that I had, or have In ſuch a bleſſing as Inow muſt leave ; Goto him, and conjure him in my name, What love he bareto me, the very ſame, That he transfer on thee : take no denial, which /

Page 117

BookII. Targalug and parturnia. Tº Which granted, live then happy, conſtant, loyal; And as ſhe ſpake that word, her voice did alter, - Her breath grew cold, herſpeech began to falter ; Fain would ſhe utter more, but her ſpent tongue (Not able to go further) fail'd and clung To her dry roof: a while, & in a trance She lay, and on a ſudden did advance Her forced language to the height, and cryed, Farewel, my deareſt Argalus; and dyed. And now, my Lord, although this office be º Mnſuitable to my Sex, and diſagree - * º Too much, perchance, mith the too mean condition - Of my poor ſtate, more like to find deriffon * Than ſatisfadłion; yet, my gratious Lord, Extr'ordinary merits do afford . . . - Extr'ordinary means, and can excuſe The breach of Cuſtome, or the common uſe : Wherefore incited by che dear direétions : Of dead Parthenia, by my own affečtions, And by the exc'lence of your high deſert, I here preſent you with a faithful heart; Aheart to you devoted, which affures Itſelf no happineſ, but in being yours. Pardon my boldneſs, they that ſhall reprove This as a fault, reprove a faulti love : And why ſhould €uſtome do our Sex that wrong, To take away the priviledge of our tongue? If nature give us freedom to affèë, . Why then ſhould Cuſtomebarus, to deteå The gift of nature f ſhe that is in pain, Hath a ſufficient warramt to complain. . . Then give me leave, (my Lord) to re-inforce

Page 118

1 18 Argalug and 12artbenia. Book II A Virgins ſuit, and (thinking ne’r the worſe of proffer'd love) let my dºſires thrive, And freely accept what Iſo freely give. So ending, ſilence did enlarge her ear, (Prepar'd with quick attention) to hear - His gratious words: But Argalus, whoſe Paſſion Had puthis amorous Courtſhip out of faſhion, Return’d no anſwer, till histrickling eyes Had given an earneſt of ſuch Obſequiès, As his adjourned Sorrow had intended To do at full, and therefore recommended To privacy; true grief abhors the Light, Who grieves without a witneſs, grieves aright. His paſſion thus ſuſpended for a while, - (And yet not ſo, but that it did recoil - Strong fighs) he wip'd his tear bedeved eyes, . . And turningro the Lady, thus replies ; ~ * Madam, - Tour no leſs rare than noble favours ſhow How much you merit, and how much I owe Tour great deſert, which claims more thankfulneſs Than ſuch a dearth of Language can expreſs: But moſt of all, Iſtand for ever bound . . . To that your Goodneſs, my Parthenia found In her diſtreſs, for which reſpeš (in duty As I am ty’dy poor Arg’lus ſhall repute ye The flower of noble courteſe, and proclaim. Tour high deſervings. Lady, as I am, A poor unhappy wretch, the very ſcorn Of all proſperity, diſtreſs, forlorn, Tºnworthy the leaſt favour you can give, I am your ſlave, your Beedſman will I live;
Page 119

Book II. 3tgalug and 43atthenia. 119 But for this weighty matter youpropound, Although Iſee hon much it would redound To my great happineſs, yet heaven knows (Moſt exc'lent Lady) I cannot diſpoſe Of my own thoughts, nor have Ipomer to do, What elſe you needed not perſwade me to ; For truſt me, were this heart of mine my own, To carve according to my pleaſure, none But you ſhould challenge it ; but while I live, It is Parthenia's, and not mine to give. Whereto ſhe thus replies: Moſt noble Sir, Death that hath made divorce’twixt you and her, Hath non returned you your heart again, . Diſſolv’d your Pows, diſlink’t that ſacred chain Which ty'd your ſouls: may more, her dying breath Bequeath'd your heart to me; which by her death It grown a debt that you are bound to pay: Then know (my Lord) the longer you delay, The longer time her ſoul is diſpoſeſt (And by your means) of her deſired reſt. Whereto the poor diſtreſſed Argalus, Pauſing a while, return’d his anſwer thus : Incomparable Lady, When firſt of all, by heaven's divine direáions, We lov’d, we lik’t, we link’t our dear affections, And with the ſolemn pomer of an Oath, In preſence of the better Gods, we both Exchang'd our hearts : in witneſs of which thing, I gave, and ſhe received that dear Ring, Which now you wear: by whichſhe did reſigne Her heart to me; for which, Igave her mine. Avon, Madam, by a mutual commerce, -
Page 120

120 3rgălug and Partbenia. Book II. Mine exchang'd heart is not my own, but hers: VWhich if it had the power to ſurvive, She being dead, what heart have Ito give 2 .. | or if that heart expired in her death, What heart had ſhe (poor Lady!) to bequeath 2 Madam, in her began my dear affection; In her it hv'd, in her it had perfeſtion; In her it joy'd, although but ill befriended By Fate; in her begun, in her it ended. #This loºd, if ſhadomblová Parthenia’s beauty, I had ſoon been mov’d To moderate my ſorrows, and to place That Love on you, that have Parthenia’s face : But 'twas Parthenia’s ſelf. I lov’d, and love; Which as no time hath power to remove From my fixtheart, ſo nothing can diminiſh, No fortune can diſſolve, no death can finiſh. - With mingled Frowns and Smiles ſhe thus reply'd Half in a rage, And muſt I be deny'd 2 ~4re theſe the noble favours I expected f To find diſgrace, and go away rejećed ? . Moſt noble Lady, if my words (ſaid he) Sute not your expediation, let them be Imputed to the miſery of my ſtate, Which makes my lips to ſpeak they know not what : Miſtake not him, that only ſtudies how With moſt advantage ſtill to honour you. Alas ! what joys I ever did receive From Fortune,’s buryed in Parthenia's Grave; With whom, ere long (nor are my hopes in vain)". -I hope to meet, and never part again. - The
Page 121

---- -
Page 122

:

Page 123

Book II. T. 3rgains and 42attºrnia. , 123 (16) So ſaid, with more than Eagle-winged haſte She flew into his boſome, and imbrac'd - [In her cros'd arms, his ſorrow waſted was. 1 Surcharg’d with Joy, ſhe wept, not having power - To ſpeak. Have you beheld an April ſhower Send down her haſty bubbles, and then ſtops, a Then ſtorms afreſh, through whoſe tranſparent drops The unobſcured Lamp of Heaven conveys The brighter glory of his refulgent rays : Even ſo, with her bluſhing cheeks reſided A mixt aſpe&, 'twixt ſmiles and tears divided : So even divided, no man could ſay, whether She wept, or ſmi’d, ſhe ſimil'd and wept together ; She held him faſt, and like a fainting Lover, Whoſe paſſion now had licenſe to diſcover Some words: Since them thy heart is not for me: Take, take thy own Parthenia (ſaid ſhe) Chear up ! my Argalus, theſe words of mine Are thy Parthenia’s, as Parthenia’s thine; Želieve it (Love) theſe are not falſe alarms, Thou haſ thy own Parthenia in thy arms. Like as a man, whoſe hourly wants implore Each meals relief, trudging from door to door, That hears no diale&t from churliſh lips, But news of Béadſes, and their torturing whips, Takes up (perchance) ſome unexpe&ted treaſure, New loſt; departs, and joyful beyond meaſure, Is ſo tranſported, that he ſcarce believes So great a truth; and * his eye perceives, - 2
Page 124

F24 itgalus and 42attl)&míà. Bookii. Not daring truſt, but fears it is ſome viſion, | Or flattering dream, deſerving but derifion; So Argalus amazed at the news Fain would believe, but daring not abuſe His eaſie faith too ſoon; for fear his heart Should ſurfeit on conceit, he did impart The truth unto his fancy by degrees: Where ſtop’t by paſſion, falling on his knees, He thus began; O you etermal powers, r That have the guidance of theſe ſouls of ours, Who by your juſt Prerogative can do - - What is a ſinforman to dive into: Whoſe undiſcover'd actions are too high - For thought: too deep for man t’inquire: why? Delude not theſe mine eyes with the falſe ſhow Of ſuch a joy, as Imuſt never know But in a dream ; or if a dream it be, O let me never wake againe, to ſee Myſelfe deceiv'd, that am ordain'd t'enjoy A real greif, and but a dreaming joy. Much more he ſpake to this §. which ended, He blet himſelf, and (with a figh) unbended His aking knees, and riſing from the ground, He caſt his rouling eyes about, and found - ! The room avoided, and himſelf alone - The door half clos'd, and his Parthenia gone, His new diſtemper'd paſſionsgrew extream: . I knew, I knew, (ſaid he J’twas but a dream; A minutes joy, a flaſh, a flattering bubble; Blown by the fancy, full of pleaſing trouble ; Which waking breaks, and empties into aire, 4nd breaths into my ſoula freſh deſpair. >
Page 125

Book II. 3tgalug and 42attijettia. 125 I knew 'twas nothing but a golden Dream, Which (waking) makes my wants the more extream : I knew’twas nothing but a dreaming joy, Abliſ; which (waking) Iſhould ne're enjoy. My dear Parthenia, tell me where, O where Art thou that ſo delud'ſt mine eye, mine ear? O that my weakened fancy had the might To repreſent unto my real ſight What my deceived eyes beheld, that I . Might ſurfit with exceſs of joy, and dye. With that the fair Parthenia (whoſe deſire Was all this while, by fire, to draw out fire; - And by a well adviſed Courſe to ſmother - The fury of one paſſion with another). Stept in, and ſaid, Then Argalus take thou Thy true Parthenia: thou dream'ſ not now ; Behold this Ring, whoſe Motto does impart The conſtancy of our divided heart : - Behold theſe eyes, that for thy ſake have vented Aworld of tears, umpitied, unlamented : Beholdthis face, that had of late the power Töcurſe all beauty, yet itſelf ſecure: - Witneſs that Tapor, whoſe prophetick ſnuff Was outed and revived with one puff: - And that my words may whet thy dull belief, 'Twas Ithat roar'd beneath the Scourge of grief, When thou didſ curſe the darkneſs for concealing Myface; and then the Tapor for revealig Sofoul a face; ’twas I, that, overcome . With violent deſpair, ſtood deaf, and dumb To althy urg’d perſpaſions : it was I, , That in thy abſence, did reſolve to die ~ I 3 *
Page 126

126 3tgalug and 49attijcmia. Book II A vandring Pilgrim, traffing to be ſed By fortune, to my Death ; and thereforeſ!-d. But ſee! the power: above can work their ºnds, I%fight of mortals; and what man intends, The Havens diſpoſº, and order the event : For when mytholights were diſperately bent To mine own ruine, I was led by fate (Through dangers, mºv, too tedious to relate J Tofair ºgeen Hellen's Court, not k, oming whither My unadviſed ſteps were guided. Thither My Genius brought mº, where unknownto any, Imourn’d in ſilence, though o ſerv'd by many: Reliev’d by none ; at length they did aquaint The fair Queen Hellen with my ſtrange complaint : Whoſe noble heart did truely ſympathize With mine, partaking in my miſeries: Who fill'd with pitty, ſtrongly did importune The woful cauſe of my diſaſtrous fortune, And never reſted till ſhe did enforce Theſe lips tºacquaint her with the whole diſcourſe: Which done: her gracious pleaſure did command Her own Chirurgeon, to ... skilful hand - She lift my foil diſeaſe, who in the ſpace Of twice ten days, reſtor'd me to this face: ; The cure perfečfed, ſtraight ſhe ſent about : (Without my knowledge ) to enquire out That Party, for whoſeſake I was contened --~~i? ----> T'endure ſuch grief with patience, unrepeated; ; : Hoping (ſince by her means, and help of art Myface was cur’d) even ſo to cure my heart. But when the welcome Meſſenger return'd The place of thy abode, O how myſpirit burn’d - 76
Page 127

f Book II, 3rgalug and 42atthenia. 127 ſ To kiſs her hands, and ſo to leave the Court : But % (whoſe favors did tranſcend report : As much, as they exceeded my deſert) Detain'd me for a while, as loath to part With herſ. handmaid; till at laſt pretending A lºvers haſt, and freely apprehending So juſt a cauſe of ſpeed; ſhe ſoon befriended My beſt deſires, and ſent methus attended: Where (under afalſe mask) I laud this Plot, To ſee howſoon my Arg’lus had forgot His dead Parthenia; }. my bleſſed ear r Hath heard, what few or none muſt hope to hear: Now farewel ſorrow, and let old deſpair Goſeek new breſts: let miſchief never dare Attempt our hearts: let Argalus enjoy His true Parthenia; let Parthenia's joy Revive in him; let each be bleſt in either, And bleſt be Heaven, that brought us both together. With that the well-nigh broken hearted Lover, Raviſh’d with over joy, did thus diſcover His long pent words: And do theſe eyes once more Behold what their extream diſpair gave ore To hopefor 2 Do theſe wretchedeyes attain The happineſs to ſee this face again f And is there ſo much happineſs yet left For a broke heart, a heart that was bereft Of powert'enjoy, what Heaven hathpower to give f : Breaths my Parthenia? Does Parthenia live? I ... " Q Who,ever ſaw the Pole-affecting ſtone, By hidden power, (a power as yet unknown To our confin’d and darkned reaſon) draw The neighbouring ſteel, which by the mutual law I 4 . - Of
Page 128

-- Book II. 128 3tgalug and Partbeuia. Of natures ſecret working, ſtrives as much To be attra&ted, till they joyn and touch Even ſo theſe greedy lovers meet, and charms Each other ſtrongly in each ochers arms; - Even ſo they meet, and with unbounded meaſure Of true content, and time beguiling pleaſure Enjoy each other with a world of kiſſes, Sealing the Patent of true worldly bliſles; Where for a while I leave them to receive What pleaſures new-met Lovers uſe to have, Readers forbear, and let no wanton eye Abuſe our Scene, let not the ſtander by Corrupt our lines, or make an obſcean gloſs llpon our ſober text, and mix his droſs With our refined Gold, extracting ſowre From ſweet; and poyſon from ſo fair a flower. Correct your wandring thqughts, and do not fear To think the beſt : Here is no Tarquin here, No luſtful, no inſatiate Meſſaline, , , Who thought it gain ſufficient to reſign An age of honour, for a Night of pleaſure; Whoſe ſtrength to endure luſt, was the juſt meaſure Of her aduſt deſire: Ye need not fear Our private Lovers, who eſteem leſs dear Their Lives, than honours, daring not to do But what unſham'd, the Sun may pry into. If any itching ears deſire to know - What ſecret confºrence paſt betwixt theſe two, To them my Muſe thus anſwers: “When your caſe ‘Shall prove the like, ſhe wills you to embrace True honour, as theſe noble Lovers did, “And you ſhall know; till then, you are forbid C. To e' , ,

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 129

Book II argalus and parturnia. Tº -- “To enquire further: Only this ſhe pleaſes To let you underſtand, that love's diſeaſes Being throughly cured by their meeting, they Have once again prefix’t a Marriage day; Which that it might ſucceed with fairer fortune, Readers, ſhe moves your pleaſures to importune The better Gods, That they would pleaſe t'appay . Their griefs with joy, and ſmile upon that day. ************************************ A R G A Lus P A R T H E N I A The Third Book. W. ſturdy March's ſtorms are overblown, 'W And April's gentle ſhowrs are ſliden down, To cloſe the wind-chapt Earth, ſucceeding May, Entershermonth, whoſe early breaking day Calls Ladies from their eaſie beds, to view Sweet Maia's pride, and the diſcotilour'd hiev Ofdewy-breſted Flora, in her bower, Where every hand hath leave topick the flower Her fancy likes; wherewith to be poſſeſt, until it fade, and whither in her breſt. Now ſmooth-fac’d Aleptune, with his gladderſmiles Viſits the banks of his beloved Iles ; Eolus calls in the winds, and bids them hold (Their S
Page 130

is Tºgalug and parturnia. Book ill- Their full-mouth'd blaſts, that breathleſsare control’d. Each one retires, and ſhrinks into his ſeat, And Sea-green Triton ſounds a ſhrill retreat; And thus at length, our Pinace is paſtore The bar, and rides before the Maiden-tower. Ulp, now in earneſt (Voyagers) and ſtand ye. On your faintlegs. Our Long boat ſtraight ſhaliland Forget your travels now,and lead your eyes (ye. From your paſt dangers to your preſent prize: You traffick not for toys, the Gods have ſet No other price to things of price, but ſweat. Chear up; call home your hearts, and be advis'd, Goodseas’ly purchas'd, are as eas’ly priz'd : Youtraffick not for trifles, and your travel Was not to compaſs the almighty gravel Of th’ Indian Mines, to ballaſt your eſtates; *Twas not for blaſts of Honour, whoſe poor dates Depend on regal ſmiles, and have no meaſures, But Monarch's wills,expiring with their pleaſures: ‘Twas not to conquer Kingdoms, or obtain The dangerous title of a Soveraign : - Theſe are poor things: it is but falſe diſcretion Totoyl, where hopes are ſweeter than poſſeſſion; No, we are bound upon more brave adventures, True Honour, Beauty, Vertue, are the Centers - - To which we point, whereto our thoughts do tend ; . . And heaven hath brought our Voyage to an end. - Hail, noble Arg’lus ; now the Cockboat ſtands Secure, ſtepforth; ſpread forth thy widened hands, And take thy faireſt Bride into thy arms: Strike up (brave Spirit) Cupids freſh alarms ! llpon her melting lips: take Toll, before - - Thou ſet herdainty foot upon the ſhore; So |
Page 131

Book III. 3rgalug and 42atthenia. 13t So let her ſlide upon thy gentle breſt, - - And feel the ground; then lead her to her reſt. Go Imps of honour, let the morning Sun Gild your delights, and ſpend his beams upon Your marriage Triumphs; let his Weſternlight Declineapace, and make an early night. Go, Turtles,go,let trebble joys betide - The faithful Bridegroom, and his faireſt bride: Let your own vertueslight you to your reſt; Tomorrow come we to your nuptial feaſt. By this, the curl’d pate Waggomer of heaven º Had finiſh't his diurnal courſe, and driven His panting Steeds a down the weſtern hill, When ſilver Cynthia riſing to fulfil Her nightly courſe, lets falls an evening tear, To ſee her brother leave the Hemiſphere, a Which by the air diſpers'd, is early found (And call’d a pearly denſ) upon the ground: Still as the night, no language did moleſt The wakingear; all mortals were at reſt: No breath of wind had power to provoke. The Aſpine-leaf, or urge the th'aſpiring ſmoke; Sweet was the air, and clear; no ſtar was hid; No envious cloud was ſtirring, to forbid The wild Aſtronomer to gaze and look Into the ſecrets of his ſpangled book; Whilſt round about, in each reſounding grove, (As if the Choriſters of night had ſtrove . T'excel) the warbling Philomel compares . And vies by turns, her Polypholian airs. And now the horn-mouth'd Bellman ofthe night Had ſent his midnight ſummons to invite .Nights
Page 132

#32 3tgalug and 49attijenia. Book III. Nights ravenous rebels from their ſecret holds Torome and viſit the ſecurer Folds ; Whil'ſt drouzy Morpheus with his leaden keys, Locks up the Shepherds eye-lids, and betrays The ſcatter'd flocks; which lie like ſacrifices Expe&ting fire’ when the Sun god riſes. By this the pale fac’d Empreſs of the Night Had re-ſurrendred up her borrowed light, And to the lower world ſhe now retires, Attended with her train of leſſer fires, And early Heſper ſhoots his golden head, To uſher Titan from his purple bed; The gray-ey’d janitor does now begin Toope his Eaſtern portals, and let in The new born day; who having lately hurl’d The ſhades of night into the lower world, The dewy-cheek’t Aurora does unfold Her purple curtains, all befring'd with Gold; And from the pillow of his Crocean bed, Don Phebus rouzes his refulgent head; That with his all-diſcerning eye ſurvays Andgilds the mountains with his morningrays. Now,now, the wakeful Bridegrooom (whoſe laſt night Had made her ſhades too long) ſalutes the light, 'Salutes the welcome light, which now, at length, Shall crown his heart with joys,beyond the ſtrength Of mortal language, whoſe religious fires Shall light thoſe Lovers to their wiſh't deſires. Ulp †. and d'on thy Nuptial weeds, T'enjoy that joy from whence all joy proceeds: 1 Enter thoſe joys, from whence all joy proceeds: Up Argalus, and 'don thy nuptial weeds. And ... • - ſh
Page 133

- --- ~~ * -- ----

Page 134

| ||ſiſ| | | |-· |× || | | ||, |-

Page 135

Book III 3tgalug and 42atthenia. I 35 / And thou fair Bride, more beauteous then the day, Thy day is come, and Hymen calls away; Awake and rouze thee from thy downy ſlumber: Thy Day is come: O may thy joys outnumber Thy minutes that are paſt, and do enſue; Ariſe, and bid thy Maiden bed adieu ; Put on thy Nuptial robes, time calls away; O may thy after days be like this day. . (17) By this, bright Phebus with redoubled glory, Had halfway mounted to the highteſt ſtory - Of his Olimpick Palace: there to ſee This long expected dayes ſolemnity: When all on ſudden, there was heard (around From every Quarter) the Majeſtickſound Ofmany Trumpets: all, in conſort running One point of War, tranſcending far the cunning Of mortalblaſts; and, what did ſeem more ſtrange, The ſhrilmouth'd Muſick did as ſudden change To Dorick ſtrains, to ſweet mollitious airs, To Lyrick .# and voices like to theirs That charm’d Ulyſſes: whilſt th'amazedear Stood raviſht at theſe changes, it might hear Thoſe voices, (by begrees) transform'd to Lutes, To Shalms, deep throated Sackbuts, and to Flutes, Andeccho-forcing Cornets; which ſurpaſt Theart of man: this Harmony did laſt Vntil the Bridegroom came; but allmen wondred . . To hearthe noiſe: Some thought the Heavens had To a new tune;and ſome more wiſer ears (thundred * Concevid'

Page 136

Book III. 3tgalug and 42attöcilia 6 - Conceiv'd it was the Muſick of the Sphears : All wondred, all men gaz'd, and all could hear; But none knew whence the Muſick was, or where, Forthwith, as ifa ſecond Sun had roſe, - And ſtrove with greater brightneſs, to depoſe The glory of the firſt, the Bridegroom came, Ulſher'd along with Eagle-winged fame, Whoſe twice five hundred mouths did at one blaſt Inſpire a thouſand Trumpets, as he paſt: His Nuptial veſture was of Scarlet die, So deep, as it would dazle a weak eye To gaze upon’t ; to which, the curious Art Of the laborious Needle did impart So great a glory, that you might behold A riſing Sun, imboſt with pureſt Gold: From whence ten thouſand trailes of gold came down In waving points, like Sun beams from the Sun: Thus from his chamber’midſt the vulgar Croud (Like Titan breaking through a gloomy cloud) The long expected Bridegroom came, and paſt Th'amazed multitude; till, at the laſt, His Heraldbrought him to the hall of ſtate, Where all th’Arcadian Nobles did await To welcome his approach, and to diſcharge The lower volley of their joyes at large: ... The Hall was ſpatious, lightſome, and beſtrow'd With Flora's wealth, (abounty that ſhe ow’d This glorious feaſt) the walls were richly clad With curious Tap'ſtry, (ſuch as Greece ne'r had Before that day) wherein you might behold, Wrought to the life, incolóur'dſi. and Gold, Th > - -
Page 137

Book III. irgalug and parthenia. 137 This preſent ſtory of theſe peerleſs [lovers, Which like a ſilent Chronicle, diſcovers The ſeveral paſſages that did befal *Twixt their firſt meeting, and their Nuptial; Devis'd and wrought by Virgins born in Greece, Preſented to this Triumph, as a Piece Devoted to the memory and fame Of Argalus, and his Partheniaes name; No ſooner was the Ceremony ended (Wherein each noble ſpirit more contended T'expreſs affection, then affect the expreſſion Ofcourtly Rhetºrick, inabare profeſſion . Ofairy friendſhip) but a ſudden ſhout Of rudely mingled voices flew throughout The ſpatious Caſtle, which confus'dly cry’d, joy to Parthenia, to the faireſt Bride. - Forthwith (as if that heaven had broken looſe, And Dieties had meant to enterpoſe ... Their heavenly bodies, with the mortal tribe *Ofmen; or eſſe, intending to aſcribe Their pers'nal honor to this Nuptial) In more then princely ſtate, enters the haſ A glorious ſhew of Ladies, all array'd In rare and coſtly robes, and richly laid With Gems unvalued; and each Lady wore A ſcarfe upon her arm, embroidred ore With Gold and Pearl; thus hand in hand they paſt Into the Hall, but of their eyes did caſt Abackward look, as if their thoughts did mind, Some greater glory, commingon behind: 4. Next after them came in the Virgin Crew In milke white robes (Virgins that never knew º K . The
Page 138

138 3rgalug and parthenia. Book III. The ſacred myſt’ries of the marriage bed, Nor, finding trouble in a Maidenhead Ere lent a thought to nuptial joyes till now ) Thus paſt theſe buds of nature, two by two, Their long diſhevelled treſſes dangled down With careleſs Art, and on each head a crown , Of Golden Lanrel ſtood: their faces ſhrowded Beneath a vail, ſeem’d as the ſtars were clouded. Have ye beheld in froſty Winters even, When all the leſſer twinkling Lamps of Heaven Are fully kindled, how the ruddy face Of riſing Cynthia locks? with what a grace She views the throne of darkneſs, and aſpires Th’Olympick brow, amidſt the ſmaller fires? So after all theſe ſparks ofbeauty came (They were but ſparks to ſuch a glorious flame) The fair Parthenia: Thus the roſe-cheek’d Bride. Enters the room; a milk-white wail did hide Her bluſhing face, which ne’rtheleſs diſcloſes Some glimpsofred, like Lawn ore-ſpreading Roſes; Thus entred ſhe. The Garments that ſhe wore Were made of purple ſilk, beſpangledore With Stars of pureſt Gold, and round about . Each ſeveral Star went, winding in and out, A trail of Orient Pearl, ſo rarely wrought, That as the garments mov’d, you would have thought The Stars had twinkled; her diſhevelled hair Hºng down behind, as if the only care Had been to reconcile neglect and art, , Hung looſely down; and vail'd the backer part Of theſe her Sky-reſembling Robes; but ſo, That every breath would wave it too and fro, Like
Page 139

Book III. irgalus and parthenia. 139 iike flying clouds, through which you might diſcover Sometimes one glim'ringStar,ſometimes another: Thus on ſhe went ; her ample train ſupported By thrice three Virgins, evenly ſiz'dand ſorted In purple robes; forthwich, the Bridegroom riſes From of his chair; bows down and ſacrifices The peaceful offering of morning kiſs Upon her lips: To ſuch a Saint as this, O, what rebellious heart could chuſe but bon, And offer freely the pºrtiu vow - Of choice obedience 2 - - - - - i ! - With that,each Noblemoves him from his place; And with a poſture, full of princely grace, Salutes the worthy bride, with words, expreſſing zº The joyfull modelofa Kingdom's bleſfing. - But hark | The Hymenean Trumpet ſends Her lateſt ſummons forth: Hºmen attends The noble pair, and is prepai’d to yoke . . . Their promis'd hands; the ſacred Altars ſmoke .. With Myrrh and Frankincenſe, the ways are ſtrow'd * With Flora's pride, and the expecting crowd Have throng'd the ſtreets, and every greedy eye Attends to ſee the Triumph paſſing by. - - - - At length the gates flew open : on this faſhion Began the triumph : firſt a Proclamation Was made, with a loud voice: If any be or Lord, or Knight, or whatſo'er degree, Profeſſing Arms or Honor in the Land, . That at this time can challenge or pretend A title to Parthénia’s heart, or claim A right, or intereſt in her love or name: Let biz comeforth in Perſon, or appear || By noble Proxy, if notpreſenthere: - . . - -- K #2 And / *

Page 140

I4O 3rgalug and partbenia Book III. _- - <nd by the exc'lent honor of a Knight, , - Heſhall recieve ſuch honorable right - 4; the juſt ſword can give; let him now come And ſpeak, or elſe, for ever more be dumb. Thrice was it read; which done, forthwith there True honors Eagle winged Herald,Fame; (came Soundinga ſilver Trump; and as ſhe paſt She ſhook the earths foundation, with herblaſt: Next after whom inundiſſembled ſtate - The Bridegroom came; on his right hand did wait . . The god of war in martial robesofgreen, - All ſtain'd with bleeding hearts, as they had been But newly wounded, and from every wound Freſh blood did ſeem totrickle on the ground: And as the garments mov’d, each dying heart Would ſeem topanta while, and then depart: Upon the Bridegrooms left hand there attended Heavens Purſivant, whoſe brawny arms extended A winged Caduce: he had ſcarce the might .. To curb his feet: his feet were wing'd for flight: Above his head their hands did joyntly hold A Crimſon Canopy emboſt with Gold. Next them twice twenty famous Nobles follow’d, Brave men at arms, whoſe names the world had hal- For rare exploits,and twice as many Knight:(lººd - - Whoſe bloods had ranſom’d, & redeem'd the rights Of wronged Ladyes: Theſe were all array'd In robes of Needle-mork, ſo rarely made, , , That he which ſees them, thinks he doth behold Armours of ſteel, fair filletted with Gold: Andas they marcht, their Squires did advance Before each Knight his warlick Shield and *; d ſ]
Page 141

Bººk III. Targains and particut. Tº 5. - And after theſe, the Princely Virgin Bride On whom alleyes were faſtned, did divide Her gentle paces, being lead between . . . Two Goddeſſes, the one array’d ingreen, On which the curious needle undertook To make a forreſt: here a bublingbrook - Divide two thickets: through the which doth flie / The ſingleDeer, before the deep mouth'd cry That cloſely follows: there th'affrighted Herd Stands trembling at the Muſick, and afear'd Ofevery ſhadow, gazes to and fro, - Not knowing where to ſtay, or where to go : Where, in a Landskip, you may ſee the Faunes Following their crying mothers ore the Lawns: The other was in robes, the purer die - Whereofdid repreſent the mid-day skie Full of black clouds;through which,the glorious beams Of the vićtorious Sun appears, and ſeems . • As’twere to ſcatter, and at length to ſhed His . glory, on a fruitful bed . . - Of noiſome weeds,from whence you might diſcern A thouſand painful bees extraët and earn Their ſweet proviſion: and, with laden thighs To bear the waxy burthens: On this wiſe The princely bride was led betwixt theſe two, The firſt, was ſhe, that on Acteons brow - Reveng'd her naked Chaſtity: the other (ther Was ſhe, to whom joves pregnant brain was mo- Through Vulcans help, and theſe did joyntly hold Upon her head a Coronet of Gold: Whoſe train Diana's Virgin-crew, all crown'd With Golden wreaths, ſupported from the ground. w 3 Next
Page 142

I42 Argalug and partbcuta. Bookli Next after her, upon the triumph waited An order, by Diana new created, - And ſtyl'd, The Ladies of the Madienhead, - In white, wrought here and there with ſpots of red, And every ſpot appeared as a ſtain - Of Lovers blood, whom theircoy hearts had ſlain: Rankt three and three, and on each head a Crown Of Primeroſes,and Roſes not yet blown. - Next whom, the Beauties of th’Arcadian Court March'd two and two, whoſe glory came not ſhort Of what th’unlimited and ſtudied art - Ofglory-vying Ladies.could impart - - | To ſuch ſolemnities, where every one - • Strove to excel, and tob’excell'd of none. Thus came they to the Temple, where attended The ſacred Prieſts, whoſe voices recommended The days ſucceſs to heaven, and did divide A bleſſing 'twixt the Bridegroom and the Bride; Which done, and after low obeiſance made, The firſt (while all thereſt kept ſilence) ſaid: - Welcome to Juno'sſacred Courts: Draw near : . . . . Tomſpotted Lovers, welcome: do not fear . . . . . . . Torough this holy ground; paſs on ſecure; - Ourgates ſtand open to ſuch gueſts as you are: Ourgratious Goddeſs granteth your deſires, - Aud hath accepted of thoſe holyfires - . We offer'd in your name, and takes a pleaſure - - - Toſmell our Incenſe, inſo great a meaſure Of true delight, that me are bold to ſay, She crowns your vons, and ſmiles upon this day. So ſaid they bowed to the ground, and bleſt Themſelves: that done, they ſingled from thereſt The t
Page 143

Book III. 3tgāiug and 42attijetilä. 143 The noble Bridegroom, and his Princely Bride, And ſaid, Our gratious Goddeſs be our guide, As we are yours: And as they ſpake that word, Their well tun'd voices ſweetly did accord With muſick from the Altar: as a long They paſt, they gently warbled out this Song: Th: in Pomp and Prieſtly pride, To glorious Juno's Altar go me; Thus to Juno’s Altarſhow we; The noble Bridegroom and his Bride: Let Juno’s hourly blºſings ſend ye Asmuch joy as can attendye. May theſe Lovers never want True joys, nor ever beg mºvain - Their choice deſires: but obtain What they can wiſh, and ſhe can grant; Let Juno's hourly blºſing ſendye As much joy as can attend ye. ºf Fromſatiety, from ſtrife, From jealouſe, domeſtick jars, From thoſe blows that leave moſcars, Junoprote:{your marriage life: Let Juno's hourly bleſſing ſendye As much joy a can attend ye. Thus to Hymen’s ſacred bands, We commend your chaſt deſerts, That as Juno link’t your hearts, So ſhe would pleaſe to joyn your hands; And let both their bleſſings ſendye As much joy as can attend ye. * K 4
Page 144

I44 3tgalug and 42atthenia. Book III, No ſooner was this Nuptial Carol ended, But bowing to the ground, they recommended This princely pair (both proſtrate on the floor) And with their hands preſented them before The ſacred Altar, whereunto they brought Two milk-white Turtles; and with Prayers beſought That juno's laſting favours would deſcend, And make their pleaſures, pleaſures without end. With that a horrid crack of dreadful thunder, Poſſeſt each trembling heart with fear and wonder; The rafters of the holy Temples ſhook, Asif accurſed Archimago's book (That curſed Legion) had been newly read; The ground did tremble, and a miſt ore-ſpread The darkened Altar. - * - At length deep ſilence did poſſeſs and fill The ſpatious Temple, all was whiſt and ſtill. When from the cloudy Altar brake the ſound Of heavenly Muſick, ſuch as would confound With death, or raviſhment, the earth-bred ear, Had not the Goddeſs given it ſtrength to bear, So ſtrong a rapture. As the Muſickended, The miſt on ſudden vaniſh't and aſcended From whence it came. The Altar did appear, And Aſhes lying where the Turtles were: - Near which, great Hymen ſtood, not ſeen before; His purple mantle was imbroidred ore (behold With Crowns of Thorn, 'mongſt which you might Some, here and there, (but very few) of gold; Upon each little ſpace, that did #. - • The ſeveral Crowns, a Gordian knot was tide; And turning to the Prieff, he thus began: - --- * ºn H'hºg º 2. : ---> --

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 145

|- - -- ---- |- {！ -- - - ！ ！! · · » ---- ~ ！ · |- ~ ~~ ： · •* • |- ...tº Toº {. r is ------- --- '*, *, * ~- - - -, ----

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 146

- - - t - r - - - - * r - - - - - - * -- - - + - - - º - - - -- - * | - | - Hill- + ‘’W. . - Tº º : I \,\! Lº!, * || || | Hº! | \!-- iſ lºsiº j |||||| º | | ºrrº. § ---- | lºss- | r is º | |

Page 147

Book III. 3tgalug and partbenia. , 147 What mean theſe fumes & Say, what hath mortal man To do with us? What great requeſt ? what ſuit Does now attend us, that they thus ſalute Our noſtrils, with ſuch acceptable ſavors 2. Tell us, wherin they do implore the favors Of the pleas'd Gods? for by the eternal throme And Majeſty of Heaven, it ſhall be dome. : . . . Whereto, with bended knees, they thus repli’d; Great God, this noble Bridegroom, and this Bride Whom we, moſt humbly, herepreſent before Great Juno’s ſacred Altar, do implore Tour gratious aid; that with your nuptial bands - Tour grace would pleaſe to tie their promit’d hands. . . . . . l - (18) with that he ſtraight deſcendsheholy ſtairs, And with his widened arms divides and ſhares An equal bleſfing'twixt them both, and ſaid: Oble Touth, and lovely Maid, , , - Heaven accepts your pleaſing fires, • And hathgrantedº : ſ sº - By the myſtery of our power, , , , , Firſt we conſecrate this hour j . . - To Juno’s name, that ſhe would bleſs - - Our proſp’rous actions with ſucceſs. With this oyl (which we appoint For holy uſes ) we anoint , , , º - Tour temples, and with nuptial bands º Thu, we firmly joymyour hands; .- -
Page 148

148 - 3\tgålug and 49attbenia. Book III. Bejoyn’d for ever : and let none Preſumet'undo what we have done Bejoym'd till lawleſ, Deathſhallſever Both hands and hearts be joyn’dforever: Eternal curſes we allot To thoſe,till then,ſhall looſe this knot. So ſaid, he bleſt them both injuno's name, And from their ſight he vaniſht in a flame: That done, they roſe, and with new fumes ſaluted The ſmoaking Altar: thrice they proſtituted Their bended bodies on the holy ground, Where, ſending forth the well accepted ſound Of thanks and Jows, from their divided heart, They kiſs the ſacred Altar, and depart; And with the ſelf-ſame Triumph as they came, Return’d; whil'ſt the louder Trump of Fame With a full blaſt, ſends forth a ſhrilſ retreat, And re-condućts them to the Hall of State, Whoſe richly furniſhttable would invite A bed-rid ſtomack to an appetite, And make the waſtful glutton, that does eat His unearn'd dyet with his dayly ſweat, " Behold his heaven in a more ample meaſure, Than he had hopes to purchaſe with the treaſure Of his beſt faith; ſuch were the dainties, ſuch The viands, that Idare not think too much To term it Paradiſe, where all things did Offer themſelves, and nothing was forbid: Soon as the Marſhal of this princely feaſt Had in his rightful ſeat plac'd every gueſt, A ſoft harmonious rapture did confine Alltongues with wonder, as a thing divine, (19) Forth-

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 149

- - - - - - - • *, - - - - - - - w - - - -- 2. - - - - - - - - º º r * - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - * ) - - - - - - - º -- -- - -- * -- - - - - - - - - - 1 - - º - - - º - - - - - - - - - - - - - •. r- - - * A , , R. K. ** !-- - - - - , - . * * * RY - n - - - - - r * . - - --- ſº ºn * - - - - - - ! . . . . . . . Nº Anº - * - sº tº a T \ſ c. * * **** - ----- - - - - - º - •,• - - t - º - - w r *-
Page 150

------- .|- ， ,！ ：/：/：.： TTL . Till ！№. ---------Zae?：Ss√∞- §|||||№===ºſgæ*§§§§§Š ŅĒĻ||||----|------~~~~§§§§SSSSSSSSSS---- ---- |-- .|-|- -|-|- lae---）） ---------|- -- --

Page 151

Book III ºrgalug and Partbenia. 151 (19) Forthwith, with joyned hands and ſmiling faces - With habits more unequal than their paces A jolly pair drew near the table; th’one Ingreen : his pamper'd body had out-grown His ſeam-ript garments, all imbroider'd ore With ſpreading Vines, whoſe fruitful leaves did cover, With ſwelling Cluſters; his out-ſtrutting eyes Star'd in his head: his dropſie ſwollen thighs Quagg'd as he went ; his purple colour’d ſnout Was deeply furniſh't and inrich’t about With Carbuncles ; around his brows did twine Full laden cluſters, raviſht from the Vine. The other was a Lady, whom the Sun VVith his bright rays, had too much gaz'd upon, The colour of her ſilken mantle was 'Twixt green and yellow, like the fading graſs: - On which were wrought incloſed Fields of corn, Some reap’t,ſome bound in ſheaves,and ſome unſhorn: , , VVell favour’d was her count’nance, plump & round ; Her golden treſſes dangled to the ground: Her temples bound with full ripe ears of Wheat, VVreath’d like a Garland: frequent drops of ſweat Down from her ſwarthy brows did ſlily trickle And in her Sun-burnt hand ſhe bare a ſickle, Thus uſher'd, with a Bag-pipe to the table, ” They both ſtood mute, ; Bacchus as yet unable. To challange language from his breathleſs tongue, Till ſmiling Ceres thus began the ſong. - Welcome

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 152

º . . - 152 3rgalug and 42artbenia. Bookmili Bacch. Chor. Ceres. W; faireſt Virgin Bride, Welcome to our jolly feaſt : Taft what Ceres did provide For ſofair, ſo fair a gueſt: Taft what Bacchus did provide For ſofair, ſofair a gueſt: Welcome faireſt Virgin Bride, Welcome to our jolly%. Our conjoymed bounties do Make Marsſmile, and Venus too. Welcome noble Bridegroom hither. Worlds of bliſs, and joy attendye. Freely welcomeboth together, Bacch. Chor. Ceres. See what Ceres bounty ſends ye. Freely welcome both together, See what Bacchus bounty ſends ye. Welcome noble Bridegroom hither ; Worlds of bliſs, and joy attendye. Our conjoymed bounties do Make Mars ſmile, and Venus too. Here is that, whoſe ſweet variety Gives you pleaſure and delight; Makes you full mithout ſatiety; Bacch. Waſtes the day, and haſtes the might. This willrouz the man of war PWhen the drum ſha/beat in vain, When his ſpirits drooping are, Chor. This will make them riſe again. Tou that joyntly do inherit Venus beauty, Marshi, ſpirit, Freely taſt our bounty: ſo Mars ſhallſmile, and Venus too.
Page 153

Book III. . 3tgalug and 42atthenia. - is, The Song thus ended, joyning hands together, They bow’d and vaniſht, none knew how, nor whi- To make relation of cach quaint deviſe (ther, That art preſented their unwearied eyes: - The nature of their mirth, of their diſcourſe : The dainties of the firſt, the ſecond courſe: The ſecret glances of the Bridegrooms eye On his fair Bride; how oft ſhe bluſht, and why, Were but to rob the Bridegroome of his right, Who counts each hour a Summersday till night. Methinks it grieves me, that my Pen ſhould wrong. Poor Lovers diſappointed hopes ſo long: - And it repents me ſo, that oftentimes - Methinks I could be angry with my Rimes, And for the cruel fins that I commit In being tedious, ſome I wiſh unwrit: Let it #. what glory, what delight, What ſtate, or what to fleafe the appetite, The eye, the ear, the fancy: In a word, What joy ſo ſhort a ſeaſon could afford To well prepared hearts, was here expreſt In this our Nuptial, this our princely feaſt. Thus when the board was voided, and the Semer Had now reſign'd his office with the Ewer, The curions linen gone; and all the rights Perform’d, that'long to feſtival delights: . The light-foot Hermesenters in the Hall, Holds forth the Caduce, and adjures them all To depth offilence; tells them, 'tis his task Tolet them know, the Gods intend a Mask, Tograce theſe Nuptials; and with that he ſpred Hisair-dividingpinions and fled. ! - sº When
Page 154

154. 3tgalug and partººnia. Book III. When ſilence thus had charmed everyear Tººk. With wonder, and attention, they might hear of the Gºd. The winged Quiriſters of night, about Inevery corner, ſweetly warbling out Their Philomelian airs, and milder note, Which nature taught them to divide, by rote; So that the hall did ſeem a ſhady Grove Wherein by turns, th'ambitious Quire ſtrove T'excel themſelves. While thus their ears were feeding with delight Mpon thoſe ſtrains, the Goddeſs of h; night Enters the Scene: Her body was confin'd Within a coal black Mantle, thorow lin’d Withſable Furs: her Treſſes were of hiev Like Ebony, on with a Pearly dew Hung, like a ſpiders Web; her face did ſhrowd Aſvarth Complexion, underneath a cloud Of black curld Cypreſs: On her headſhe more A Crown of burniſht Gold, biſhaded ore With Frogs and Rory miſt: her hand did bear 4Scepter and aſable Hemiſphere: Sheſternly ſhook her dewy locks, and brake ~4 melancholy ſmile, and thus beſpake; Drive on, drive on, (dull Waggoner) letſlip Your looſer reins, and uſe thine idlewhip, Thy pamper'd Steeds are purſie, driveaway, The lower world thinks ſong to ſee the day: Darkneſs befits us beſt; and our delight Will reliſh far more ſweeter in the night: Approach (yebleſled Shadoms) and extend Your early jurisdićtion, and befriend Qur nightly ſports: Approach, make no delay, Irisour Qūcen, your ſoveraign calls away. With
Page 155

Book III. 3rgalug and 43atthenia. 155 N With that, a ſudden aarkneſs fill’a the Hall: The light was baniſht, and the windows all So neerly clos'd their eye-lids round about, That day could not get in, nor darkneſs out ; Thus while the death-reſembling ſhades of night Had drawn their miſty Curtains’twixt the light And every darkned eye, which was deni’d - To ſee, but that, which darkneſs could not hide : The jealous God, fearing he knows not whom, ( Indeed whom fear; he not 2 J enters the room, And with his club-foot groping in theſhade Of night, he mutter'd forth theſe words, and ſaid . ... Where is this wanton Harlot now become? Vºlº Islight ſo odious to her? or is home firit. So homely in her wandring eyes, that ſhe Muſt ſtill be rambling, where unknown to me Can nothing be concluded, nothing done, But intermedling Venus muſt be one Is’t not enough that Phebus does applaud Her luſts, but muſt Wights Goddeſs be her Baud? Darkneſs begone, thou Patroneſ to luſt: , , Iffair means may not rid thee, fouler muſt, Away; my power ſhall out-charm thy charms, I'll find her panting in her Lovers arms. Enter you Lamplets of terreſtrial fire, And let your golden heads (at leaſt) conſpire To counterfeit a day, audon the night Revenge the wrongs of Phebus, with your light, Soſaid, the darkned hall was #. round With lighted Tapers; Every Objeć found An eye to own it, and each eye was fil’d - L 2 - With
Page 156

156 ºrgalug and partbenia. Book III. With pleaſure in the obječf it beheld. * As theſe deviſeful changes did incite Their quickned fancies with a freſh delight, Morpheus came in ; his dreaming pace was ſo, That mone could ſay he mov’d, he mov’d ſo ſlow : PHis folded arms, athwart his breaft, did knit A ſluggards knot, his mºdding chin did hit Againſt his panting boſome, as hepaſt - And oftentimes his eyes were cloſed faſt : - He more a Crown of Poppy on his head; And in his hand he bore a mace of Lead: - He yawned thrice, and after homage done - i To Nights black Soveragn, he thus begun: - Mºtºu, Great Empreſs of the World: To whom Iowe Speech. Myſelf, my ſervice, my perpetual vow : Before the footſtool of whoſe dreadful throne The Princes of this lower world lay down Their Crowns and Scepters ; whoſe vićtorious hand In twice twelve hours did conquer and command This globe of earth, your ſervant (whoſe dependance Quickens his power) comes to give attendance - llpon the earthly ſhadows, and to ſeize upon theſe wearied mortals when you pleaſe T’appoint; till then your ſervant is at hand To put in execution your command, To whom the ſmiling Goddeſs thus repli’d. %. Mºrphº, our pleaſure is to ſet aſide - ##!" This night to mirth, & time beguilingſports; spºt. Our ſleep-reſtraining buſineſs much imports - Your welcome abſence, whil'ſt our ears ſhall Theffing hours;our mirth admits noſlumber. (number, - … . . The ! -
Page 157

Book III. 3rgalug and 42attbcnia. TI 57 The wordſtårce ended, but the 3. of Love . Deſcended from her unſeen ſeat, above: - In her fair hand ſhe led her winged Son, And like a full-mouth'd tempeſt, thus begun : . Diſloyal Sycophant,Death's baſtard brother, Venus, bir Accurſed ſpaun, Caſt from as curs’d a mother: #: That with thy baſe impoſtures rifleſt man º Of half his days, of half that littls ſpan Nature hath lent his life, that with thy wiles Hugg’ſt him to death, betray’ſt him with thy ſmiles: What mak’ſt thou here, and to uſurp my right, Perfidious Caitiffe 2 Penus day is night : - Go to the frozen world, where man’s deſire Is made of Ice, and melts before the fire, Yet ne'r the warmer : Go, and viſit fools, Or Phlegmatick old age, whoſe ſpirit cools As lº as their breath : Go, what have we To do (dull Morpheus) with thy Mace, or thee, As leaden as thy Mace? Th'art made for nought, But to ſtill Children, or toeaſe the thought Of brain ſick Franticks ; or with joys to flatter Poor ſlumbering ſouls, which wak’t, find no ſuch mat- Go ſuccourthoſe that vent by quick retail, (ter. Their wits upon dear penny-worths of Ale: Or marrow'd Eunuchs, whoſe aduſt deſire * Wants means to ſlack the fury of their fire: O that I were a Baſilisk, that I Might dart my venome, or elſevenom'd die. Boy, bend thy bow, and with thy forked dart Drawn to the head, thrill, thrill him to the heart : Let fly Death's arrow, or if thou haſt none, In Death's name ſend an arrow of thy own; - - - - L 3 . . . . We - - - > ... - z
Page 158

158 ºrgalug --- Book III. -------------- and parthenia. We are both wrong’d, and in the ſame degree; Shoot then, at once, revenge thy ſelf and me. With that the little angry God did bend His ſteel bow, and in Death’s Name did ſend His winged Meſſenger, whoſe faithful haſte Diſpatcht his ireful errand, and ſtuckfaſt Within his pierced Liver, and did hide His ſinging Feathers in his wounded ſide. Morpheus fell down as dead, and on the ground Lay for a little ſeaſon in a ſwound, Gaſping for breath. And lovers dreams (they ſay) Have evermore been wanton ſince that day. Venus was pleas'd: The Goddeſs of the night Grew angry; ſhe would needs reſign her right Of Government, and in a ſpleen threw down Her Hemiſphere, her Scepter, and her Crown : And with a duſty fog ſhe did beſmear - The face of Venus, ſoil'd her golden hair With her black ſhades, and with foul terms revil'd Both her, her cuckold mate, and baffard child: Whereat the God of War being much offended, Forſook hoth ſeat and patience, and deſcended; And to the World he proffer'd to make good Fair Venus honour, with hu deareſt blood; To whom poor Vulcan (puffing in a rage, To hear his well known fortune on the ſtage) Scalſ’d many a thank, and with his crouching Knee, Profeſt true Love to ſuch true Friends as he. And ever ſince, experience lets us know, Cuckolds are kind to ſuch as make them ſo. By this god Morpheus making from hisſ,wound, Began to grown, and from his a ſing wound Dren.
Page 159

Book II. Argalug and Patthenia. 159 Drew forth the buryed ſhaft; but Mars (whoſe word Admits no other ſecond but his ſword) Moſheath’d his furious brondiron, and let fly Ablow at Morpheus head, which had well migh Clove him in twain, had not the Queen of night Hurl’d haſty miſts before his darkned ſight: So that the Sword, by a falſe guided aim Stack Vulcan’s foot: which ever ſince was lame : At laſt the Gods came down, and thought it good Tonip this early quarrel in the bad ; Who fearing uproars, with a friendly Cup Ofbleft Nepenthe, took the quarrel up : And for th’ offence committed didproclaim This ſentence in offended Juno’s name. Morpheus from hence is baniſht for this night, ſº And not t'approach before the morning light: . Mars is exil'd forever, as a Gueſt Adjudg’d unfitting for a Marriage-feaſt. Cupid is doom'd torome and rove about To the World's end, and both his eyes putout. Venus is cenſur'd to perpetual Night, And not (unleſs by ſtealth, to ſee the Light: Her chiefeſt joy to be but pleaſing folly, Perform'd with madneſs, dogg’d with melancholly And here the Muſick did invite their paces To meaſure time, and by exchange of places To lead the curious beholders eye A willing captive to variety. Thus, with the ſpeet viciſtude of mirth They ſpent the time, as if that Heaven and Earth Had ſtudied to pleaſe man, in ſuch a meaſure, That
Page 160

ióo Tº 3rgalug and pattbcuta T Book III. That art could not do more t'augment their pleaſure. And ſo they vaniſh't, Now Ceres Evening bounty re-invites Her noble gueſts to her renew’d delights: And frolick Bacchus, to refreſh their ſouls With a full hand, preſents his ſwelling Bowls. Wine came unwiſh't, like water from a ſcource; And Dilicates were mingled with diſcourſe : What art could do to make a welcome gueſt, Wasliberally preſented at that Feaſt. - | - (20) It was no fooner ended, but appears An old grey pilgrim, deeply ſtruck in years, In tatter'd garments: in his wrinkled hand An hour-glaſs labouring with her lateſt ſand; Beneath hisarm, a .#. Knapſack hung Stuft full of writings in an unknown tongue, Chronologies, out-dated Almanacks, And Patents that had long ſurviv'd their wax; upon his Shouldiers Eagle-wings were joyn'd: His head ill thatcht before, but bald behind: And leaning on his crooked Sythe, he made A little pauſe, and after that, he ſaid : Mortals, 'tis out, º Glaſs is run, And with it the day is done: Dark ſhadows have expell'd the Light, And my Glaſs is turn'd for night, Th e * * * .
Page 161

---- ， ！ ~\|- \\ \\

Page 162

-• - w Yºrk … . . . .3RARY * 'o',' twºx ºne Tº De N *CUNCATºº, * |

Page 163

book III atgalug and patthenia. º: The Queen of darkneſs bids me ſay, Mirth a fitter for the day: Mpon the day ſuch joys attend, With the dayſłch joys muſt end. Think not darkneſs gºes about, Like Death, to puffyour pleaſures out : Mo, no, ſhe’llend you new delights, She hath pleſures for the Nights. When as herſhadows ſhall benightye, She hath whatſball ſtill delight ye: Aged time ſhall make it known, She hath dainties of her own : *T is very late, away, amay, Let day ſports expire with day: For this time we adjourn your Feaft: The Bridegroom fatn would beat reſt. And if the night paſtimes diſpleaſeye, Day willquickly come and eaſe ye. with that a ſweet vermiliantinčture ſtain'd The Bridesfaircheeks: the more that ſhe reſtrain'd Her bluſh, the more her diſobedient blood / Didoverflow, as if a ſecond flood Had meant to riſe, and, for a little ſpace, To drown that world of beauty in her face; She bluſht (but knew not why) and like the Moon, Shelook’t moſt red upon her going down. º But ſee: The ſmiling Ladies do begin ... To joyn their whiſperingheads, as there had been A plotoftreaſon:till at length unſpi’d;... They ſtole away th’unwilling-willing Bride: Their buſie hands unrob'd her, and ſoled The timorous Virgin to he Nuptial-bed º
Page 164

164 atgalug and Partbenia. Book iii. Cad By this, the Nobles having recommended Their tongues to ſilence, their diſcourſe being ended They look’t about, and thinking to have done Their Service to the Bride, the Bride was gone: And now the Bridegroom, (unto whom delay Seem'd worſe than Death) could broke no longer ſtay: Attended with his noble Gueſts, he enters That room, where enterchangible Indentures Ofdeareſtlove lay ready to be ſeal’d With mutual Pleaſures not to be reveal’d. Hisgarments grew too tedious, and their weight (Not able to be born) do over-fraight - . His weary ſhoulders : Atlas never ſtoop’t Beneath a greater burthen, and not droop't : No help was wanting, for he did receive . . . What ſudden aid he could expector have From ſpeedy hands, from hands that did not waſte The time; unleſs (perchance) by over-haſte : Meanwhile, a dainty warblingbreſt, not ſtrong Asſweet, preſents this Epithalmion Song. 2 Man of War, march bravely on, The Field’s not eaſte to be won : Ther’s no danger in that War, Where Lips both Swords and Bucklers are. Here’s no cold to chill thee, - A Bed of Down's thy Field: Here's moſword to kill thee, Mnleſs thou pleaſe to yield. Here
Page 165

- ---- ---- Aston, Lt Nox Anº Tº pen FoundaTº



Page 166

- 166 . 3tgalug and 42attbeltia. Bookfit * * Here is nothing will incumber, Here will be noſcars to number. Theſe be Wars of Cupid's making, Theſe be Wars will keep you wakiug, Till the early breaking day Calls your forces hence away. Theſe be Wars that make no ſpoil, Death here ſhoots his ſhafts in vain; Though the Souldiergets a foil, He will rouze and fight again. Theſe be Wars that never ceaſe, But conclude a mutual Peace. Zet benign and proſperous ſtars -Breath %. i. %ars, .4nd when thrice three months be run, lle thou father of a Son : A ſon that may derive from thee The honour of true merit, And may to ages yet to be, Convey thy blood, thy Spirit : Making the glory of his fame Perpetuate, and crown thy Name, And give it life inſpite of death, - ..When fame ſhall want both Trump, and Breath, Have you beheld in a fair Summers Even The Golden headed Charioter of Heaven, With v what a ſpeed his prouder reins dobend . Hispan ting Horſes to their Journies end? How red he looks, with what a ſwift career He hurries to the lower Hemiſphere, And in a moment: ſhoots his golden head Upon the pillow of bluſhing Thetis bed: * Even i
Page 167

* | * Book III. 3rgalug and 49attºrnia. 167 Even ſo the Bridegroom, (whoſe deſire had wings More ſwift than time,ſwitchton with pleaſure)ſprings Into his Nuptial bed; and look how faſt - The ſtooping Faulcon clips, and with what haſte Her talons ſeize upon the timerous prey, Even ſo his Arms, (impatient of Delay) - His circling Arms imbrac'd his bluſhing Bride, While ſhe (poor ſoul) lay trembling by his ſide. The Bridegroom now grows weary of his gueſts, What mirth of late was pleaſing, now moleſts His tired patience: Too much ſweet offends : Sometimes to be forſaken of our Friends, In § Morals, is obſerv'd to be The fruits of Friendſhip in the beſt degree. And thus at laſt the Curtains being clos'd, / They left them each in others Arms repos'd. And here my Muſe bids draw our Curtains too, 'T is unfit to ſeemhat private Lovers do. Reader, let not thy thoughts grow over-rank, But vailthy underſtanding with a blank; Think not on what thou think'ſ : and, if thou canſ, Tet underſtand not what thouanderſtand'ſt. Sow not thy fruitful heart withſopoor ſeeds: Or if perchance (unſown) they ſpring like weeds, Oſe them like weeds, thou knomeſ not how to kill Slight them, and let them thrive againſt thy will. View them like evils, that Art cannot prevent, But ſee thou take no pleaſure in their ſcent : And one thing more; when as the morning light Shall bring the baſhful Bride into thy ſight, Be not too cruel : let no wanton eye Diſturb and wrong her conſcious modeſy: - And if ſhe bluſh, examine not for what: Way

Page 168

168 3tgalug and particula." Book III May, though thou ſee it (Reader) ſee it not. And ſhall our ſtory diſcontinue here 2 Or want a period till another year 2 Shallwebefriend theſe Lovers with the night, And leave them buryed in their own delight, And ſo conclude: No, it ſhall ne'r be ſed - That marriage joys end in the Marriage bed : Fond and adulterate is that love which founds Her happineſs on ſuch unſtable grounds: And, like a ſudden blaze, it never laſts, But as the pleaſure waxes cold, it waſtes. Now Argalus awakes, and now the light Iseven as welcome to him as the night : His eyes are fixtupon his lovely Bride, - While ſhe lies ſweetly ſlumbering by his ſide: She ſleeps, he views her : thrice his mind was bent To call Parthenia, and thrice it did repent : Sometimes his lips, with a ſtoln kiſs would greet Her guiltleſslips : (They ſay, ſtoln goods are ſweet) At length ſhe wakes, and hides her bluſhing cheeks In his warm boſome, where ſhe ſafely ſeeks For Sančuary, whereunto ſhould fly The guilt of her protećted Modeſty : He ſmiles and wiſpers in her deafned ear; (Women can underſtand, and yet not hear ) He ſpeaks, but ſhe (even whil'ſt his lips werebreaking Their words) with hers did ſtophislips from ſpeaking. When thrice three Suns had now almoſt out-worn The rare ſolemnities that did adorn - Theſe Princely Nuptials, and had made report Grow ſomething ſparing in th’Arcadian Court, The
Page 169

Book III. Argalug and parturnia. 169 The Bridegroom, whoſe endeavours were addreſt, Topraćtiſe what may pleaſe his fair Bride beſt, Reſolv’d to leave Kalander's houſe, and crown Parthenia ſole Commandreſs of her own : - Long was it ere Kalander's liberal ear Could be unlockt; it had no power to hear The word farewell : Still Argalus intreated, And fram’d excuſes; which he ſoon defeated. But as the ſtout Alcides did caſhire One riſing head, another would appear: … " Even ſo, whil'ſthis ingenious love did ſmother One cauſe of parting, Rewould find another." . . Kalander thus at laſt (being over-wrought - With words, which importunity had taught Inexorable Argales) was fain To yield what he ſo long gain-ſaid in vain. : *Tis now concluded, Argale muſt go, But yet Kalander muſt not leave them ſo: There is no . till the aged Sire Shall warm his fingers by Parthenia's fire. Parthenia ſues, Kalander muſt not reſt, Till he become Parthenia’s promis'd gueſt. The morrow next, when Titans early ray Had given fair earneſt of a fairer day:. And with his trembling beams had repoſeſt The eyes of mortals, newly rouz'd from reſt, They left Kalander’s Caſtle; and that night Arriv'd they at the Palace of delight : (For ſo’twas call'd) it was a goodly ſeat; Well chozen, not capacious, as neat: Yet was it large enough to entertain A potent Prince, .# all his Princely train: It ~ M -
Page 170

17o argalus and Partbenia. Book III: It ſeem’d a Center to a Park, well ſtor'd With Deer, whoſe well thriven bounty did afford Continual pleaſure and delight; nay, what That Earth calls good, this Seat afforded not 2 Th’impatient Faulkner here may learn to ſay Forgotten Prayers, and bleſs him every day. The patient Angler here may tire his wiſh, And (if he pleaſe) may ſwear, and yet catch fiſh. The ſneaking Fowler may goboldly on, And ne'r want ſport untill his Powder’s done : Atid to conclude, there was noſtint, no meaſure . To th'old man’s profit, or the young man's pleaſure : Thither this night the Nuptial Troop is gone: And now Parthenia's welcome to her own : But would you hear what entertainment paſt 2 Conceive it rather ; for my Quill would waſte Th’unthriving ſtock of my beſpoken time, While ſuch free bounty cannot ſtand with rime: But that which moſt, did ſeaſon and imbelliſh Their choice delights, and gave the trueſt reliſh To their beſt mirth and pleaſures, was, to ſee With what a ſweet conjugal Harmony All things were carryed; every word did prove To add ſome acquiſition to their Love; & So one they were, that none could juſtly ſay, Which of them rul’d, or whether did obey: - He rul’d, becauſe ſhe would obey; and ſhe, In thus obeying, rul’d as well as he . - What pleaſed him, would need no other cauſe . To pleaſe her too, but only his applauſe; - A happy pair, whoſe double life but one : . Madeonelife double, and the ſingle, none. , t - . . . . . . . . Thus
Page 171

Book III. Targalug and particula. Tº Thus when th'unconſtant Lady of the night Had chang'd her horns for an Orb of Light: Kalander (whoſe occaſions grew too ſtrong, And may not be diſpens'd withal too long) Takes leave, and (being equal heavy hearted With ſad Parthenia for his haſte departed : But Argalus (who never yet could own Himſelf with more advantage than alone) & wºrk And fair Parthenia (whoſe well pleas'd deſire LERARY Hopes nothing elſe; if Argalus be by her) - Needs not the help of any to augment …, , , , , , The betterjoys of their retir’d content; its tº xa i Sometimes the curious garden would invite - Their gentle paces to her proud delight, : (pleaſure, Sometimes the well-ſtor'd Park would change their And tender to her view their light-foot treaſure: Where th’unmoleſted Herd would ſeem to ſtand, And crave a death at fair Parthenia's hand: Sometimes her ſteps would climb th'ambitious Tower, From whoſe aſpiring top they might diſcover A little Commonwealth of Land, which none But Argalus durſt challenge as his own: - Sometimes, (for change of pleaſure he would read Sele&ted Stories, whil'ſt her ears would feed Upon theſe lips, and now and then a Kiſs Would interpoſe like a Parentheſis, Petween their ſemicircled arms inclos'd: CO what dull ſpirits could be indiſpos'd To read ſuch Lines!) and whil'ſt upon the book His eyes were fix’d, her pleaſed eyes would look llpon the graceful Reader, and eſpy A ſtory, far more pleaſing in his eye. - - M 2 Upon --
Page 172

- -- --

Page 173

Book III. Targains and particnia. Tº ( 22 ) , Vpon a day as they were cloſely ſeated Her ears attending, whilſt hislips repeated A ſtory, treating the renown'd adventures And famous ačts of great Alcides; enters A Meſſenger, whoſe countenance did bewray A haſt too ſerious to admit delay; -. His hand preſentshim Letters, which did bring Their ſealed errand from th’Arcadian King; Whereat Parthenia roſe, and ſtept aſide: Her thoughts were troubled; ever as ſhe ey’d The Meſſenger, her colour comes and goes: Parthenia fears; and yet Parthenia knows. . . Not what to fear: Her jealous heart knows how To fearanevil, becauſe it fears to know: - And as he read the lines, her eye was fixt Upon his eye, which ſeem'd to ſtrive betwixt Athouſand thwarting paſſions: Once he caſt His eyes on her, and finding hers ſo faſt On his, he bluſht, ſhe bluſht, both bluſht together, Becauſe they bluſht for what, unknown to either. The Letter being read (and having kiſt. Baſilius name) he ſpeedily diſmiſt The Meſſenger, with promiſe to obey Baſilius juſt commands without delay: A - That done he took Parthenia by the hand, His dear Parthenia, by the trembling hand: And to her greedy eye he ſtraight preſents The Paperballac'd withits ſad contents: M ; , Parthenia s | .* -
Page 174

174 3tgalug and 42atthenia. Book III. Parthenia with a fearful ſlowneſs took it, And with a fearful haſte did over-look it : Her face being blanched with the pallid ſignes Of what ſhe fear'd too ſoon, ſhe read theſe lines. Baſilius Rex. W Herea, the famous and vićforious name Of great Amphialus, make the Trump of Fame Bºath nothing but his Conqueſts and Renown: Whoſe lawleſs actions fortune ſtrives to crown (Inſpight of juſtice) with a Vittors merit, Reſpećing more the greatneſs of his Spirit, Then juſtneſs of his cauſe; to the diſhonour Of vertue, and all ſuch as wait upon her. Andfurthermore, wherea, hi, ponſer is known Toppugn the º, of our State and C rown, With ſtrong Rebellion, to the bigh advancement Of his diſloyal glory, and inhancement Of his perfidious Name, the great increaſe Offačions, and diſturbance of our Peace: Likewiſe, whereas his highprevailing hand (Againſt the force whereofnoffſh can ſtand) Could her be equal’dyet, much leſ, orešome: But "ithſoud Triumph ſtill doth carry home The ſpoils of our loft honour, to the fame 9ſhi rebellious glory, andourſhame : Wetherefore in our princely careperpending - Theſerious premiſes, and much depending " 9° yºur known Courage, have ſeleēedyoſ. Tº ſtandour Champion-Royal, and renew Qºr maſted honour mith your Sword and Lawee In equaal Duell: Thusyou ſhall advance Zººglorious pitchofyour renowned Name. - With the bravepurchaſe of eternal Fame: Ia
Page 175

Book II airgalug and partijenia. 175 In this youſhallrevive our dyingglory º .. Anative the ſuijºofinº, (Whichſhall be read till timeſhall have an end) And tie Baſilius your perpetual Friend. . ." To our right truffy and noble * . . . . º . . . . Kinſman, Argalus, But as ſhe read, her tears did trickle down Upon the Lines, as if they meant to drown Th'unwelcome meſſage, and at length ſhe ſaid, Ahme (my Argalus) was’t this you made Such haſte to anſwer £ did that anſwer need To be returned withſo great a ſpeed 2 "º Canyou, O can you be ſo quickly won - - - - To leave your poor Parthenia, and begone? ... To whom reſolved Argalus (whoſe eye Was fixt upon his Honour) made reply, My dear Parthenia, were it to obtain The unſumm'd wealth of Pluto; or to gain The ſoveraignty of th’earth without expence of bloodorſweat, without the leaſt pretence Ofdanger, my ambition would deſpiſe The eaſe Conqueſt of ſo great a prize, If parchas'd ; thy diſcontent, or by The pooreſt tear that trickles from thine eye. But to recall my promiſe, or forſake * That reſolution honour bids me make in this behalf, or to betray that truſt . . . . . . Repos'd in me, the Gods would be unjuſt * (And not themſelves) if they ſhould but command, Or urge memith an over ſwaying hand : . . . . . . M 4 My. w • *
Page 176

176 3rgains and $2artiſemia Book III. * 4; dear Parthenia: lea,falſeſ cºeffion 4%uſe thy paſſion; or pre ::. §ſ. # *areff love, though honorº. part, * honour cannotro thee of my beart": Honour that calls me with her loud alarms - Will bring me back with Triumphrothy arms. So ſaid, the ſad Partheni, (whoſe tears - Areturn'd Lieutenants to her tongue) forbears 3.9%mP:herlanguage. Grieß. ſmall Şanſpeak, when great ones cannot vent at all. Buttenderhearted 4.g4/us, (to whom Such filenceſpeaks too loud) forſook the Room: And with a brefasſulſor penſive care, #honour, gave directions, prepare His Warlike Steed, his Martial attire, - Andall things ſuch Imployment doth require. **ear, Ø thou, thougra,ſpream Protećreſs Of holder Spirits, aft: ſº Direáreſs Of lofty flying &iſi, whichſhall derive 704fter-times, whatglorious Swords atchieve : 4nd mak’ſ theation, of heroick Spirits £ºpetuate, and crown their names, their merits: {&#rious Clio, aidmead Inſpire Myrºged Rimes with thy divinºr Fire : **: to raiſe myſtyle, and toº. ſº that mºtranſcendthe vulgar ſirai, ; Reach me a quiºren;from an Eagles wing: **t my Ink be bloºd. that may ſºng. Pethto the life: Lethinº, reads, expound, Each diſha Sword, and every word a wound. . . . . By this, the Shampion-Royal had put on . His Martial Weeds; but haſting to be gone, The

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 177

|-· ·· · |- |---- - -- - -|-- - - - |-|- -·- |-|--- |-|- |- ----|-· ·~|-· * *|-|---------- - - - ---- - -|-|-· · |-|- |-|-+ ' ， ， , ， ·|-， ，· ·|-|- - - - -----|- |-·* |-|- - º.|--·º. |-· · · ·|-|-- |-|- ·+ *. |-|- ·|-· -- --- _ _ ·|- |-·… }·---- |----- |-|-|- · + ·~~ |- | … "-- - -|-|- |- |-·|-----'--|- |×·}·|- |- |-|-|-|- , ，¿? -|-|-|-|-----|-|-- - -·|-|- |- |-i'|-----|-- -! |--|-|-|--------- *|-|-|-**…*** ·---- |- ··|-|-|-|- ··|-- ;- ./*-|-|- |-- |-|- |-*« …*|-|-, ！|- |-... •|-|-·ae |-！ -----• !****;'， |-|- |-|- |-* ，|-# |-· · · · **|-|-|-|-|-|- -----|--|-|- |-}! |-|-|-----|- |-|-！”· - ---------·, - -：· · · ·|-- -------~~.}）** -|-|-A ：* |-· |- · ---- ------ - -|-------- |-|-|-|- ------------------------------ -------a ---- -- - - •



Page 178

（~~~~ -----• • • • • - ~--~~~~ ~~---- - ~~~~-----！~-------|-*|- ·7|-! H | ---- ---- -· |-}----· |- ·- •·|- |- |× |-- -------- |-*

Page 179

Book III irgalug and 12atthenia. 179 The poor Parthenia, whoſe cold fit is paſt ... . . . . (Like thoſe in agues) now does burn as faſt: . . . . . She leaves the lonely room, and coming out She finds her Argalus inclos'd about - - * * With glittering walls of ſteel: apparrell'd round . . . In his bright arms (whom ſhe had rather found Lockt up in hers) and wanting nothing now , * * But what her lips could not (poor ſoul) allow . . . Without a ſea of tears, her h; farewel, - (23) - She ran untohim, wept, and weeping fell Upon her knees, ſhe claſpt him by the arm, - And ; up, ſhe thusbegan to charm : My Argalus, my Argalus, my Dear . # And wilt thou go and leave Parthenia here? Wilt thoufift. me then? and can theſe tears. Mot intercede betwixt thy deafned ears And myſadſuit 2 Canff thou, O camſ thou go, And leave thypoor diſtreſt Parthenia ſo? Parthenia ſues, Parthenia does implore, Parthenia begs, that never beg’d before: H Remember, Oremember you are, non' * Onder the power of a ſacred vow: . . - Honor muftſtoop to vows, which once being crackt Tou cannot do on honorable ačf. I have a right unto you; you are mine: Ihave that Intreff ºIlene'r reſigne Till death: Ile never hazard to forgo ... * *

Page 180

180 ºrgatus and parthenia. Book iii. My whole eſtate of happineſs, at one throw; No, no, I will not, I will hold thee faſt In ſpight of honour, and her nine days blaſt; 7ſourº afts have given ſufficient proof To the wide World; your valour's known enough Without afarther tryal ; there's enough - To loſe their Lives (leſs worthy) º,you : 'Twas them a time for Arms, when you had none, None other left to venture but your own : - - Excuſe methem, that only do endeavour To hold my own, which now I muſt, or never : ºtine, mineyou are, and you can undertake No danger, but Parthenia muſt partake: Shall your Parthenia be endanger'd then f Parthenia ſhall be preſent, even when - The ſtroakes fall thickeſt; and Parthenia ſhall Suffer what ereto Argalus may befall: Parthenia in your greateſt pain ſhallſmart ; Tour bloodſball trickle from Parthenia’s heart. £anprayers obtainmoplace 2 by this dear hand, Theſacredpledge of our conjugal band. By althepleaſures of our deareſt love; By heaven, and all the heavenlypowers above: Or if thoſe Motives cannot find a room, Jet by the tender fruit that immy Womā £ºgins to bud; or fought elſe appear othy beſt thoughts, more pretious, or more dear, By thatforſakenenot, although the reſt Prevail not, Grant this firſt, this laſt Requeſ.” To whom the broken hearted Argains, Wearied,but not o'rcome, made anſwer thus: * * - ~ * ºf - -
Page 181

Book III. argălug and partººnia. 181 My dear Parthenia; Thy deſires never Gainſaid my will, till non': Do not perſever To crave that boon I cannot grant : forbear To urge me: Reſolution hath no ear; . Weep not, (my joy) let not theſe drops of thine, That trickle from ſo fair an eye, divine A foulſucceſs : Chear up; a ſmile or tro Would makeme half a conquerour ere I go : Shine forth, and let no envious cloud benight The glorious luffre of ſofair a light : Doubt mot my life, the juſtneſs of my Cauſe, That brings meon, millquit menith applauſe : Fear mot that ſuch a blºffing, ſuch a Wife, Was ere intended for foſhort a life : Exped myſafe return; a quick, as glorious ; My genious tells me, I ſhall live vićtorious. Soſaid, as if that paſſion bad forgot Her mother tongue, her tongue replied not: . But, like to one, new ſtricken with the thunder, * as She ſtood betwixt amazement, fear and wonder: - His lips took leave, and as hisarms ſurrounded Her feeble waſte, ſhe ſtrait fell down and ſwounded: But Argalus tranſported with the tide And tyranny of honour, could abide No longer ſtay; he truſts her to the guard Of her own Woman; left her . Unto the Camp; wherein he ſpent ſom In parley with Amphials; and aſſays By all perſwaſive means, to make himyield To juſt demands, and not to ſtain the Field With needleſs blood: but finding him unapt ir’d 1e days, * . * * For
Page 182

182 . 3tgalug and 42atthenia. Book III º For peaceful counſel (being ſtrongly rapt | With his own fame) and ſcorning to afford ſº His ear to any language, but the ſword, || He ceas'd to adviſe him; and (enforc’d to try ſ º Arongher Dialeół) wrote him this defie: | Renown'd Amphialus, - ºf If ſtrong perſwaſions, backt with reaſons, could f Been honor'd with your ear, your miſdom would ſº In yielding tofofair a peace, have won - # ...As ampleglory, as yourſivord hath dome ſh. Touſhould have conquer’d ſouls,where non at moſt, !, Tou can ſubdue but bodies, that have lºſt The power to reſiſt: But ſince my ſuit, $own on ſo barren ſoil, can find no fruit; Receive a mortal challenge, from a hand, Whoſe juſtice takes a glory to withſtand ºf Sofoula cauſe, and labours toſº ſo Tour heedleſs errors, whilſt it honors you: ‘. . º Compoſe you them, to make a preparation, W. According to your noble monted faſhion : #: And fººt.ſlight of ne’rſo weak an arm º That ſtrikes, when juſtice ſtrikes up her alarm. # - || , Argalus º - - ſt No ſooner had heread it, but is Pen, ſº With noble ſpeed, return'd theſe lines agen: / i Much more renowned Argalus, - | Tourfaithful ſervant, whoſevićtorious brow - A. Was neverdaunted yet, is daunted now l By yourbrave curteſe, being ſtricken dumb. A . With -
Page 183

- - - - º º Book III. 3rgalug and parthenia. -18 s With your rare worth, and fairly overcome: Tet doubting not the juſtneſs of my Cauſe - (That’s over ruled by the ſacred laws Of deareſt love) will give my ſword the power Even to maintain it to the lateſt hour; Iſhall erpetſ your coming in the Ile, - - - Where with a heart (not poiſon'd with the bile Orgall of malice) with my deareſt blood, Tour Servant ſhall be ready to make good - His juſt deſigns : aſſured of no leſs - Than treble fame, if crowned with ſucceſs: - If not, there’s no diſhonour can accrew In being conquer'd, and orecome by you. Amphilus. Soon after Argalus (whoſe blood did boil To be in ačtion) comes into the lle, Clad in white Armour, gilt and ſtrangely dreſt With knots of women's hair, which from his creſt. . Hung dangling down,& with their bounteous treaſure Oreſpread his Corſlet in a liberal meaſure : - His curious furniture was faſhion'd out, Like to a flying Eagle round about Beſet with plumes, whoſe crooked beek (being caſt : Into a coſtly Jewel ) was made faſt .." To th’ſaddlebow: her ſpreading Train did cover His crooper, whil'ſt the trappersſeem to hover Like wings, that to the fixt beholderseye, As the horſe pranc'd, the Eagle ſeem'd to fly; upon hisarm (histhreatning arm) he wore A ſleeve, all curiouſly imbroider'd ore - w h - - 1t

Page 184

184* 3rgalug and 49attijenia. Book III. With bleeding hearts, which fair Parthenia made (In thoſe croſs times, when fortune ſobetraid Their ſecret Love, and with a ſmiling frown Daſht their falſe hopes) ascopies of her own. Upon his ſhield (for his deviſe) he ſet - Two neighb'ring Palms, whoſe budding branches met And twin'd together; the obſcure Impreſs / Imported thus: The floriſhing, as theſe: His Horſe was of a º black - His Main, his Feet, his Tail: on his proud back l A coal black Liſt: his noſtrils open wide, Breath’d War, before his ſparklingeye deſcride An Enemy to encounter; up by turns, - He lifts his haſty hoofs, as if he ſcorns The earth, or if his tabring feet had found A way, togge, and yet nºr change the ground By this, Amphialus (who all this while Thought minutes years) was landed in the Ile, In all reſpe&ts provided, to afford - - As bounteous entertainment as the Sword And launce could give: and at the Trumpets ſound, The Steeds (that needed notaprick to wound Their bleeding flanks)both ſtart,and with ſmooth run- Their ſtaves,declining with unſhaken cunning, (ing Perform'd their Maſterswill, with angry ſpeed: But Argalus his well inſtructed Steed (Being hot, and full of courage, fiercely lead By his own pride) preſt in his prouder head : The which when ſtout Amphialus sº Well knowing it unſafe to give his ſide) Preſt likewiſein, ſo that both men and Horſe, shººding each other with a double force Fe} º *
Page 185

Book III. 3rgalug and 42atthenia. 185 Fell to the ground: but by accuſtom'd skill, And help of Fortun's hand, that ſuccours ſtill Bold Spirits, ſhun'd the danger of the Fall, And had (leſs fear'd than hurt) no harm at all : They roſe, drew forth their Swords,which now begun To do what their left ſtaves had left undone. Haveye beheld a Leaguer? In what ſort The deep-mouth’d Cannon plays upon the Fort, And how by piece-meals it doth batter down The yielding Walls of the beſieged Town? Even ſo their Swords, (whoſe oft repeated blows Could find no patience yet to enterpoſe A breathing reſpite) with redoubled ſtrength Sohew'd their proofleſs armours, that at length Their failing truſt began to prove unſound, And piece by piece they dropt upon the ground, Truſting their bodies to the bare defence. Of vertue and unarmed Innocence : Such deadly blows were dealt, and ſuch requited, That Mars himſelf ſtood raviſhtandaffrighted To ſee the cruel Combat; every blow Didaćt two parts: both ſtruck and guarded too At ſelf ſāme Inſtant. So incomparable Their skilful quickneſs was, that none was able Toſay (although their watchful eyes attended The ſtroaks) who made the blow, or who defended : Long was it ere their equal skill and force Ofarms could ſhew a better, or a worſe : Neither prevail'd as yet; yet both excell'd In not prevailing. Never eye beheld - More equal odds: No wound as yet could ſhow A drop of waſted blood, yet every blow - N Was º
Page 186

186 Targains and partuznia TBook iſ Was full of death: When skillful Gameſters play, The Chriſtmas boxgains often more than they. At length the ſword of Argalus (that never Thirſted ſo long in vain till now ; nor ever Made vićtorious doubtful for ſolonga ſpace) Faſtned a wound on the diſarmed face - - Of the renown'd Amphialus, wherein . . Had not his faithful ſhield born part, and been An equal ſharer, his unequal foe - No doubt, had ſumm'd his conqueſt in that blow: With that the ſtout Amphialus, whoſe harm Gave ſprightly quickneſs to his wounded Arm, upheav'd his thirſty Brondyron, and let fly A downright blow; but with a falſifie Reverſt the ſtroak, and left a gaping wound In his right arm : But Argalus, that found A loſs of blood, exchang'd his open play, And for his more advantage, cloſely lay Upon a lower guard; withal expecting - A hop’d revenge, which was not long effe&ting: For whil'ſt Amphialus, (whoſe hopes inflam'd - His tyrannous thoughts with conqueſt, and proclaim'd undoubted Vićtory) heap'd his ſtroaks ſo faſt, As if each blow had ſcorn'd to be the laſt. The watchful Argalus (whoſe nimble eye - Diſpos'd his time in only putting by) - Put home a thruſt (his right foot coming in) And pierc’t his Navel, that the wound had been No leſs than Death, if Fortune (that can turn A miſchief to advantage) had forborn to ſhew a miracle; for with that blow Amphialus laſt made, his arm had ſo - - . . . Oreſtruck t i
Page 187

Book III. Argalug and parthenia. 187 - .. Oreſtruck itſelf; that ſideward to the ground He fell; and falling, he receiv'd that wound, Which ( had he ſtood) had enter'd in pointblank, But falling, only graz'd upon his flank: . Being down; brave Argalus his threatning ſword Bids yield: Amphialus anſwering not a word (As one whoſe mighty ſpirit did diſdain A life of alms) but ſtriving to regain His legs and honour, Argalus let drive, With all the ſtrength a wounded arm could give, . Upon his head; but his hurt arms (not able To do him preſent Service, anſwerable To his deſires) let his weaponfall, , , With that Amphialus (though daz'd withal) . Aroſe, but Argalus run in and graſp’t (Being clos'd together) with him, were both clasp’t Andgrip'd each in th'unfriendly arms of either, "A while they grapled, grapling, fell together, And on the ground with equal fortune ſtrove: Sometimes Amphialus was got above, - And ſometimes Argalus. Both joyntly vow’d Revenge; both wallow'd in their mingled blood, Both bleeding freſh : now Argalus bidsyield; . . And now Amphialus: both would win the Field, . Yet neither could; at laſt, by free conſent They roſe; and to their breathed ſwords they went : The Combat's now renew'd, both laying on, As if the fight had been but new begun : New wounds aſſwage the ſmarting of the old, And warm blood intermingles with the cold: . But Argalas (whoſe wounded arm had loſt More blood than all his body could almoſt N 2 Supply N.
Page 188

188 3tgalug and 42attbenia. Book III. Supply; and like an unthrift, that expends So long as he hath either ſtock or friends) Bled more than his ſpent Fountains could make good; His ſpirit could give Courage, but not blood. º As when to wealthy Clients, that wax old In ſuit (whoſe learned Counſel can uphold, And gloze the Cauſe alike on either ſide) During the time their termly golden tide Shall flow alike from both,’tis hard to ſay Who proſpers beft, or whoſhall ; the Day, But he whoſe water firſt ſhall ceaſe to flow, And ebb ſo long, till it ſhall ebb too low, His Cauſe (though richly laden to the brink With right) ſhall ſtrike upon the bar, and ſink, And then an eaſie Counſelmay unfold The doubt; the queſtion's ended with the Gold: Even ſo our Combatants, the whil'ſt their blood Was equal ſpilt; the Gauſe ſeem'd equal good, * The Vićtory equal, equal was their arms, Their hopes were equal ; equal was their harms, But when poor Argalus his waſtingblood Ebb'd in his Veins (although it made a flood, A precious flood in the ungrateful Field, Hiscauſe, his ſtrength, but not his heart muſt yield : Thus wounded Argalus the more he fail'd, The more the proud Amphialus prevail'd : With that Amphialus (whoſe noble ſtrife Wasput to purchaſe Honour, and not Life) Perceiving what advantage in the fight Hegained, and the valour of the Knight, Became his ſuitor, that himſelf would pleaſe To pity himſelf, and let the Combat ceaſe: - - - ** Which

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 189

- * - - - - * / - t - - - - ,- - - - - - - - - - -4 - - - - - - - - 4. : - - - - --- - - - - - º, N * - w - * . - - - - - - - --- - -- - . - - - - * , a - - n - - - --- - - º - - - - - - - - t - - - - - - * - º - - s - - - - w - - * - - - - - - \ - !. w * , - * - - - - * - -- - º - - * . . .------ ºr **** * - a- - - - - - - ~ * --> - - :-" . - w - - - - - - - - - - - ~ -

Page 190

**, --， - ---- ~~~~ ~~~）***** −****--------------¬

Page 191

Book III. Argalug and parthenia. 19. Which noble Argalus (that never us’d - In honour to part ſtakes) with thanks refus'd : (Like to a luckleſs Gameſter; who, the more º He looſes, is leſs willing to give ore) - And filling up his empty veins with ſpite, Begins to ſum his forces, and unite . The broken ſtrength; (and like a Lamp that makes The greateſt blaze at going out, he takes His ſword in both his hands, and at a blow Cleft armour, Shield, and arm almoſt in two: But now inrag’d Amphialus forgets All pity; and truſting to his Cards ; he ſets That ſtock of Courage, treaſur’d in his breſt, Making his whole eſtate of ſtrength, his Reſt : And vies ſuch blows,as JArg’lus could not ſee Without his loſs of life: ſo thundred he Upon his wounded body, that each wound Seem’d like an open ſluce of blood, that found f (24) No hand to ſtopit, till the doleful cry .. Ofa moſt beauteous Lady (who well nigh Had run her ſelfto death) reſtrain’d his arm - (Perchance too late) from doing further harm: It was the fair Parthenia, who that night ... Had dream'd ſhe ſaw her Husband in the plight She now had found him : fear and love together Gave her no reſt till they had brought her thither: The nature of her fear did now begin T'expel the fear of Nature; ſtepping in - - N 4 . Between f - ~

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 192

------------------------- 192 ºrgalus and parthenia. Book ill. Between their pointing ſwords ſhe proſtrate lay Before their blood-bedabled feet, to ſay - She knew not what ; for as her lips would ſtrive To be deliver'd, a deep ſigh would drive Th'abortive iſſue of her language forth, Which, born untimely, periſht in the birth: And if her fighs would give her leave to vert it, O then a tear would trickle and prevent it; But when the wind of her loud ſighs had laid The ſhower of her tears, ſhe ſob'd, and ſaid ; O wretched eyes of mine! O nailfulſh f 0 day of darkneſs 1 O eternal night ! And there ſhe ſtopt ; her eyes being fixtupon Amphialus, ſhe ſigh'd, and thus went on ; My Lord, *IA ſaid you love; then by that ſacred power Of love, as you’d find mercy in an hour Of greateſt miſtry, leave off, and ſheath Tour bloody ſword: or elſe, if nought but death May ſlack your anger, O' let mine, let mine Be a ſufficient offering at the Shrine Ofyour appeaſed thoughts; or, if thou thirſt For Argalus his life,then take mine firſt : Or, if for noble blood you ſeek, if ſo, Accºpt of mine ; my blood is noble too, And worth the ſpilling: Even for her dearſake, Tour tenderſoul affeifs, awake, anake Tour noble mercy. Grant I care not whether: Let me die firſt ; or killus both together. With that Amphialus was about to ſpeak, But Argalus (whoſe heart did almoſt break To -
Page 193

Book IITirgalug and parthenia.T 193 To hear Parthenia's words) made this reply. Parthenia, ah Parthenia, Then muſt I Be bought and ſold for tears 2 Is my condition So poor, I cannot live, but by petition f So ſaid; he ſtept aſide, (for fear, by chance, The fury of ſome miſguided blow may glance And touch Parthenia) and fill'd with high diſdain, Would have begun the Combat freſh again: But now Amphialus was charm'd ; his hand Had not ſufficient warrant to withſtand Parthenia's ſuit, from whoſe faireyes there came Such precious tears in ſo belov’d a name: His eyes grew tender, and his melting heart Was overcome; his very ſoul did ſmart : He ſtirred not, but kept him at a diſtance : And (puting by ſome blows) made no reſiſtance. But what can long endure? Lamps wanting oyl, Muſt out at laſt, although they blaze a while: Trees wanting ſap, muſt wither: ſtrength and beauty Canclaim no priviledge to quit that duty They owe to Time and Change; but like a Vine (The unſound Supporters falling) muſt decline: Poor Argalus grew faint, and muſt give ore To ſtrike; his feeble arms can ſtrike no more: And natures pale-fac’d Bayly now diſtrains His blood, for that ſmall debt that yet remains Ulnpaid: Hisarm that cannot uſe the point, Now leans upon the pomel ; every joynt Diſclaims their idle ſinews ; and his eye Begins to double every Object by ; Nothing appears the ſame it was; the ground | And all thereondoth ſeem to dance the round: His
Page 194

194 --- atgalug and Partbenia. Book III. His legs grew faint, and thinking to ſitdown, He miſt his chair, and fell into a ſwound. With that Amphialus and Parthenia ran, Ran in with haſte, Amphialus began To looſe his Helmet, whilſt her buſie palm Chaf’d his cold Temples, and (diſtilling Balm Into his wounds) her haſty fingerstore Her linnen ſleeves, and partlet that ſhe wore, To wipe the tear-mixtblood away, and wrap . His wounds withal; upon her panting lap She laid his liveleſs head, and (wanting bands Tobind his bloody cloaths) her nimble hands (As if it were ordained for that end, And therefore made ſo long) did freely rend Her dainty hair by handfuls from her head, But as ſhe wrapt the wounds, her eyes would ſhed And wet the rags ſo much, that ſhe was fain With ſighs and ſobs, to dry it up again : Thus half diſtraćted with her griefs and fears, Theſe words ſhe intermingles with her tears. Diſtreſs'd Parthenia! Into what a ſtate Hathfortune, and the direful hand of Fate Driven thy perplexed ſoul? Othou, O thou, That wert the preſident of all joys but now, Now turns the example of all miſery For torments worſe than death, to praffiſe by How leſs than nothing art thou? and how more Than miſèrable! Thou that wert before All Ladies of the earth for happineſ; 'But very mov (ah me!) non, nothing leſs : O angry Heavens, what hath Parthenia done, . . . . To
Page 195

º wº Book III. Argalug and particula. ºf To be thus plagu'd? or why not plagu'd alone, If guilty, what ſhall poor Parthenia do To whom ſhall ſhe complain Palas ! or who Shall give relief? Nay, who can give relief . - t To her that hopes for ſuccour from her grief ? . . . . . O death muſt we be parted then for ever : And never meet again, what, never, never ? Or ſhall Parthenia now be ſo unkind, To leave her Argalus, and ſtay behind 2 No, no, my deareſt Argalus, make room, . . (There’s room enough in Heaven) 1 come, I come. Whoever ſaw a dying Coal offire Lurkin warmembers (till ſome breath inſpire A forc’t revival) how obſcure it lies, And being blown, glimmers a while, and dies. So Argalia, to whom Parthenia's breath Giving new life, (a life in ſpight of death) Recall'd him from his death-reſembling trance, Who from a j. pillow did advance His feeble head, and looking up, he made Hard ſhift to force a language, and thus ſaid: My dear Parthenia, now my glaſs is run, The Taper tells me, that the Play is done, My days are ſumm’d, Death ſeizes on my heart; Alas! the time is come, and we muſt part : Tet by my better hopes, grim death doth bring Mo grief to Argalus, no other ſing But this, that Imuſt leave thee evez before Mygrateful ačions can croſs the ſcore Of thy dear merits. But ſince it pleaſes him, whoſe Wiſdom ſtill Diſpoſes althings by his better Will, Depend -
Page 196

196 3tgalug and 49attijenia. Book m | 44 She knows not where, unbounded rage deprives her Depend upon his goodneſs, and rely Mpon his pleaſure, not enquiring why, - - And º one day we ſhall meet, and then A Enjoy each other, ne’r to part agen: Meanwhile live happy : Let Parthenia make Mo doubt, but # Arg’lusſball partake In all her joys on earth, which ſhall increaſe Bijoys in Heaven, and ſouls etermal peace : Love well the dear remembrance of iſ, frtée And faithful Arg’lus; let no thought renew My laſt diſgrace : Think not ...}. of fate Made me unworthy, thou unfortunate : And as he ſpake that word, his lips did vent A ſigh, whoſe violence had well-nigh rent His heart in twain; and when a parting kiſs Had given him earneſt of approaching bliſs, He ſnatch'd his ſword into his hand, and cry’d, QPeath ! thq, art a Conqueroar; and dy’d. With that Parthenia, whoſe livelihood was founded Upon his life, bow’d down her head and ſwounded Butgrief, that (like a Lion) loves to play Before it kills, gave death a longer day, Elſe had Parthenia dy’d, ſince death deprived Him of his life, in whoſe dear life ſhe lived. Butah | Parthenia's ſorrow was too deep; Tootoo unruly to be lull'd aſleep Byoughtbut death: ſhe ſtartles from her ſwound, And nimbly riſing from the loathed ground, Kneels down, and lays her trembling hand upon His luke-warm lips, but finding his breath gone, Grief plays the Tyrant, fierce diſtraćtions drive her of

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 197

| - - r - - w - - - . - - w - - * - º º - * * - - - - - a - * A ‘. . . i - l - * Asſoh, Lenox AND - \ Tilt N Fºuxºa rºº. - ſ -- - - - \ - - f - | - | - r 2.



Page 198

| | |- · · ， ，ź（…» ，，，，，|- , - RŅŇŅŇ·！ 5 ÑÑŅŇNR$\ || … `NÈN|- |----- |-|- ··|-|- |-~/- ·|- '*** --~--~ ~ | * ---- |-

Page 199

·- \,\! ||13 \! ||| || - |- ----|-… ）→ *= * -ae-） → ≤º：WWW\\\\\\\\\\ \



Page 200

2OO Argalug and Patthenia. Book III Offence and language, here and there ſhe goes, Not knowing what to do, nor what ſhe does: Sometimes her fair miſguided arm will tear Her beautious face, ſometimes her beauteous hair; Asif their uſe could ſtand her in no ſtead, - Since her beloved Argalus was dead. But now Amphialus (that all this ſpace Stood like an Idol faſtned to his place; | Where with a world of tears he did bemoan - The deed that his unluckly hands had done) Well knowing that his words would aggravate, Noteaſe the miſery of her woful ſtate, Spake not, but caus'd her woman that came with her Tourge her to the Ferry, where together (25) With her dead Argalus ſhe’mbarkt; from whom She would not part : No ſooner was ſhe come To t'otlier ſhore, but all the funeral ſtate Of Military Diſcipline did wait Upon the Corps, whilºſt troops of trickling eyes Fore-ran the well-perform'd Solemnities : The Marſhal Trumpet breath’d her doleful ſound, Whil'ſt others trail'd their Enſigns on the ground : (26) Thuswas the moſt lamented Corps convey'd upon a Chariot lin'd, and over-laid With - - 1t

Page 201

Book III. Altgalug and parthenia. 2O || With ſable, to his houſe, a houſe, than night More black, no more the Palace of Delight: Where now we leave him to receive the Crown Prepar'd for vertue, and deſerv'd renown : Where now we leave him to be full poſſeſt Of endleſs Peace, and everlaſting Reſt. But who ſhall comfort poor Parthenia now? What Oratory can prevail. 2 or how Can Counſel chooſebut bluſh to undergo So vain a task, and be condemned too? May reaſon move a heart, whoſe beſt relief Conſiſts in deſp'rate yielding to a grief ? Or what adviſe can reliſh in her ears That weeps, and takes a pleaſure in her tears 2 Readers, forbear, ſorrows that are lamented, Are but exulcerated, but augmented : Forbear attempt, where there is no prevailing, A deſp'rate grief grows ſtronger by beivailing, ". Leave her to time andfortune: let your eyes No longer pry into her miſeries : True Mourners love to be beheld of none, Who truly grieves, deſires to grieve alone. . . . | But now our Blood-houndMuſe muſt draw,and track Amphialus, and bring the murtherer back To a new Combat : Where, if Fortune pleaſe To crown your Tragick Scene, and to appeaſe The crying blood of Argalus with blood : - Our better reliſh ſtory (making good Your hopeful expećtations) ſhall befriend The tears of our Parthenia, an end. Soon as the ſtout Amphialus had out-worn The danger of his wounds, and made return - s O - -º Into
Page 202

Blank page
Page 203

Book III. 3rgalug and 12atthenia. 203 . Into the Martial Camp, there to maintain His new got honour, and to entertain Aggrieved Challangers, that ſhall demand Or ſeek for ſatisfaction from his hand; An armed Knight camepraunſing ore the Plain, Denouncing War, and breathing for Diſdain: Four Damſels uſher'd him in ſable weeds; And four came after all on mourning Steeds : His curious Armour was ſo painted over With lively ſhadows, that ye might diſcover The Image of a gaping Sepulchre : About the which were ſcattered here and there. Some dead men's Bones : his Horſe was black as Jet His Furniture was round about beſet With branches, ſlipt from the ſad Cypreſs Tree, His baſes (reaching far below the Knee) . . . . Embroider'd ore with worms: upon his Shield, For his Impreſs he had a beauteous Child, Whoſe body had two heads, whereof the t'on Appear'd quite dead; tºother (drawingon) Did ſeem to gaſp for breath, and underneath This Motto was ſubſcrib'd, From Death, by death : Thus arm'd to point, he ſent his bold defie T’Amphialus, who ſent as quick reply. ( 27 ) Forthwith being ſummon'd by the Trumpets ſound, They ſtart; but brave Amphialus, that found, • . The Knight had miſt his Reſt, (as yet not met) Scorning to take advantage, would not let Hi - - O 2 His .

Page 204

2-, 3rgalug and 43atthenia. Book iii. 2O4 ----- His Launce deſcend, nor (bravely paſſing by ) Encounter his befriended Enemy. Whereat the angry Knight (not apt to brook Such unſupportable miſhap) forſook - His white-mouth’d Steed, throwing his Launce aſide, (Which too too partial Fortune hath deny'd A fair ſucceſs) drew forth his glittering Sword; Whereat Amphialus lighted, who abhor’d - A Conqueſt meerly by advantage gain'd, , , Eſteeming it but robb'd, and not obtain'd) Drew forth his Sword, and for a little ſpace Their ſtroaks contended with an equal pace, And fierceneſs: he herein did more diſcover A bravery than anger, whil'ſt the other Bewray'd more ſpleen, than either skillor ſtrength To manage it : Amphialus at length, With more than wonted eaſe, did batter ſo His ill defended armour, that each blow Open’d a door for Death to enter in : And now the noble Conquerour does begin To hate ſo poor a Conqueſt, and diſdain'd To take a life ſo eaſily obtain'd, And mov’d with pity, ſtepping back, he ſtaid His unreſiſted Violence, and ſaid, Sir Knight, conteſt no more; but take the peace Of your own paſſion : Let the Combat ceaſe, Seek not your cauſleſs ruine ; turn your arm (Better imploy'd ) 'gainſt ſuch as wiſh your harm ; Husband your Life before it be too late, Fall not by him that me’r deſerv'd your hate. To whom the Knight return'd theſe words again, Thou ly'ſ falſe Traytor,and Ihere diſdain Both
Page 205

* Book III. Targalus and parthenia. Tao; –* Both words and mercy, and mith a baſe defte, - - And to thy throat my Sword ſhall turn the lye. To whom Amphialus repli’d, Uncivil Knight, Couragious in nothing but in ſpight, And baſe diſcourteſe, thou ſoon ſhalt know Whether thy tongue betrays thy heart or no. And as he ſpake, he gave him ſuch a wound llpon the Neck, as ſtruck him to the ground: And with the fall, his Sword (that now deny'd All mercy) fiercely tilts into his ſide : That done; he loos'd his Helmet with intent To make his over-laviſh tongue repent: Of theſe baſe words he had ſobaſely ſaid, Or elſe to crop him ſhorter by the head. Whoever ſaw th’illuſtrious eye of Noon - (New broken from a gloomy cloud) ſend down His earth-rejoycing glory, and diſplay - His golden Beams upon the Sons of Day:- Even ſo the Helmet being gone, a fair And coſtly Treaſure of unbraided Hair Oreſpread the ſhoulders of the vanquiſht Knight, Whoſe now diſcover'dviſage (in deſpight, Of neighbºring death) did witneſs and proclaim A ſoveraign beauty in Parthenia's Name, | And ſhe it was indeed, ſee how ſhe lies Smiling on death, as if her bleſſed eyes. (Bleſtin their beſt deſires) had eſpied His face already, for whoſe ſake ſhe died : The Lillies and the Roſes (that while ere Strove in her Cheeks,till they compounded there, Have broke their truce,and freſhly faln to blows, Behold the Lilly hath orecome the Roſe : * * , - O 3 Her
Page 206

206 atgalug and parthenia. Book III. Her Alabafter neck (that did out-go) The Dov's in whiteneſs, or the new-fall'n Snow) Was ſtain'd with blood, as if the red did ſeek Protećtion there, being baniſh't from her Cheek : So full of ſweetneſs was her dying face, That Death had not the power to diſplace Her native beauty; only by tranſlation, Moulded and cloathed in a newer faſhion. (28) But now Amphialus (in whom grief and ſhame Of this unlucky Vićtory, did claim An equal Intereſt) proſtrate on the earth, Accurs'd his ſword, his arm, his hour of birth; Caſting his Helmet, and his Gauntlet by, His undiſſembling tears did teſtific What words could not: but finding her Eſtate More apt for help than grief (though both too late) Crept on his Krees, and begging pardon of her, His hands (his often curſed hands) did proffer Their needleſs help, and with his Life to ſhow What honour a devoted heart could do : Whereto Parthenia (whoſe expiring breath Gave ſpeedy ſigns of a deſired death) Turning her fixt (but oft recalled) eyes Upon Amphialus, faintly thus replies. Sir, you have done enough, and I require Mo more: four hand have dome what I deſire, What I expečf ; and if againſt your will, h The * * * º t i.
Page 207

-- ∞ ， w.， （）！ |-

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 208

TTE NEW YOI. º'E. IC LIBRARY - asſon, Lenox and Thuda N Found ATION.3, - - l º - --- * > y * - - - - - +- - | - w - - - - - - - - - - - - - s - - t º - - - - - --- - • - - - - - - - --- -- - -- --, - - : --- - -- " - - -- - - º
Page 209

BoºkIII. Argalug and parthenia. 2C9 The better; ſo I wiſh your favours ſtill ; Tetone thing more, (if Enemi's may ſize) I trave, which is, to be untoucº”, by you; And as for honour, all that I dº mand, Is, not to purchaſe honour from joir hazd : No, no, 'twas no ſuch Bargain made, That he Whoſe hands had kill'd my Arg’ius,ſhould help mes Tour hands have done enough, I crave no ºn re; ‘And for the deed’s ſake, I forgive the Doer. What thin rem tims, but thit I go to reſ? MWith Argalus, and to be repoſºft Of him, with him for ever to aſ ide, Ere (ince whoſe death I have ſo often di’d. And there ſhe fainted (even as if the Clock Of Death had given a warning ere it ſiruck) But ſoon returning to her ſelf again : - Welcomeſweet death, ſaid ſhe, whoſe minutes pain Shall crown this ſoul with everlaſting pleaſure: Delay me mot: Odo me not that wrong, - My Argalus will chide, I ſtay ſo long : O now I feel the Gordian-knotted band's Of life unti’d : O heavens ! Into your hands I recommend my better part, with truſt To find you much more merciful than juſt, ( Tet truly juſt withal) O Life! O Death ! I callyou to a Witneſs, that this breath AWe'r drew a blaſt of Comfort ſince that hour My Arg’lus died : Q thou etermal power, Shroud all my faults behind the milk-white Vail Of thy dear mercy; and when this tongue ſhalſail { * To

Page 210

21o s 3 tº alug and 49attijenia. , Book III. Inforce a helpleſs Audience: It is ſaid, To ſpeak : O them. - And as ſhe ſpake(0 then). Othen ſhe left To ſpeak; and being ſuddenly bereft Of words, the fatal Siſter did divide Her ſlender twine of Life, and ſo ſhe di’d. Sodi’d Parthenia, in whoſe cloſed eyes The VVorld of beauty and perfection lies Lockt up by Angels, (as a thing divine) From mortal eyes, the whil'ſt her vertues ſhine In perfect glory, in the throne of glory, Leaving the world no relique but the ſtory - Of earth's Perfeótion; for the mouth of Fam To conſecrate to her eternal Name, VVhich ſhall ſurvive (if Muſes can divine) (Though not in theſe poor Monuments of mine) To th’end of days, and by the looſer rimes, Shall be deliver’i to ſucceeding times ; Solong as Beauty ſhall but find a friend, Parthenia's laſting fame ſhall never end : Till, to be truly vertuous, to be chaſt, Be held a Sin, Parthenia’s Name ſhall laſt. Thus when Amphialus had put out this Lamp, This Lamp of honour, he forſook the Camp, And like a willing Priſoner, was confin'd . To the ſtrićt limits of a troubled mind : No Jury need b'impanell'd or agreed Upon the Verdićt, none to atteſt the deed ; None to give ſentence in the Judgment Hall ; Himſelf was VVitneſs; Jury, Judge, and all ; VWhere now we leave him, whil'ſt we turn our eyes Upon Parthenia’s VWomen, whoſe fierce cryes Whez,
Page 211

Book IIIT 3tgalug and 49atthenia. 211 When Troy was taken, ſuch a Cry was made. One ſnatcht Parthenia's ſword, reſolv’d to die Parthenia’s death : Another raving by, Strove for the weapon; through which eager ſtrife, They both were hindred, and each ſav’d a Life. Others, whom wiſer paſſions had taught how To grieve at eaſier rates, did rudely throw Their careleſs Bodies on the purple floor: VVhere ſprinkling duſt upon their heads, they tore Their tangled hair, and garments drench’t in tears, And cry’d, as if Parthenia’s bleſſed ears Could hear the Voice of grief, ſuch griefs as would Return her from her glory, if they could: Each heart was turn’d a VVardrobe of true paſſion, VVhere griefs were clothed in a ſeveral faſhion, Sometimes their ſorrow would recall to view Her Vertue, Chaſtneſs, Sweetneſs, and renew Their waſted paſſions, and oft-times they bann'd Themſelves for obeying her unjuſt Command. And now by this the mournful Trump of Fame (Grown hoarſe with very ſorrow) did proclaim And ſpread her doleful tydings, whil'ſtallears . . And eyes were fill'd with death and ſliding tears: Pity and ſorrow, mixt with Admiration, Bećame the threefold ſubjects of all paſſion: Grief went her progreſs through all hearts, or none, From the poor Cottage to the Princely Throne : Could one a thought, whoſe beſt advice could borrow The ſmalleſt reſpite from th’extreams of ſorrow. But all this while, Baſilius Princely brett, As it commanded, ſo out-griev'd the reſt: His ſhare was treble: Hearts of Kings are deep And
Page 212

212 3rgalug and partijenia Book II And cloſe; what once they entertain, they keep With Violence: the violence of his paſſion . . . Admits no means, as yet, no moderation: . . . * * - - & - - (29) - t - -4 -- . . \º But ſoon as grief had done her private Rights And Dues to Honour: Honour (that delights” In publick Service, and can make the breath.” Of ſighs and ſobs to triumph over Death)"." Call'd in Solemnity, with all her train And Military Pomp, to entertain Our welcome Mourners, whoſe ſlow paces tread The paths of death; and with ſad Triumph lead The ſlumbering body to that bed of reſt, Where nothing can diſquiet, or moleſt Her ſacred Aſhes ; there intombed lay The valliant Argalus ; and there they ſay, Ere ſince that time, th’Arcadians oncea year, Viſit the Ruines of their Sepulchre; And in memorial of their faithful Loves, - There built an Altar, where two milk-white Doves They yearly offer to the hallowed Fame Of Argalus, and his Parthenia's Name. - & - . . . . * - Hos
Page 213

--—- |- |-· |- · |- }; ! · ||-- |- ·· -· * »· * *!· |- ·* *-|-·„*- {• · :· 4. }} -~ · }|- ,。 ،|- |-→ ·|- / __-__~~~~）——•—•）

Page 214

2I4 Book III 3tgalug and 49attijenia. Hof ego Perfulos. Ike to the Damask Rºſe you ſee, Or like the Bloſſom on a Tree, Or like the dainty Flower of May, Or like the Morning to the day, Or like the Sun, or like the ſhade, Or like the Gourd that Jonas had : Evenſuch is man, whoſe thread is ſpun, Dramm out, and cut, and ſo is dome. The Roſe withers, the Bloſſom blaffeth, The Florer fades, the morning haſteth, The Sunſets, the ſhadow flies, - "The Gourd conſumes, ama man he dies. Like to the blaze of fond delight ; Or like a morning clear and bright, Or like a Froſt, or like a ſhower, Or like the Pride of Babel's Tower, Or like the hour that guides the time, Or like to Beauty in her Prime : Even ſuch is man, whoſe glory lends His life a blaze or two, and ends. Delights vaniſh,the morn ore-affeth, The Froſt breaks, the ſhower haſteth, The Towerfalls, the hourſpends, The beauty fades, and Man's life ends. Fr. Quarles. - The
Page 215

| 215 3tgalug and 49attbettia. Book III - #~ The Author's Dream. M TSins are like the hairs upon my head, **Andraiſe their Audit to a high a ſcore: In this they differ : Theſe do daylyſhed; But ah! my Sins grow dayly more and more. If by my hairs thou mumber out my ſins; Heaven make me bald before the day begins 2 My Sins are like the Sands upon the ſhore, Which every ebb lays open to the eye: In this they differ: Theſe are cover'd ore / With every Tide; my ſins ſtill open lye. If thou wilt make my head a Sea of Tears, Othey will hide theſins of all my years. * - 3 MySims are like the Stars within the Skies, In view, in number, even as bright, as great: In this they differ : Theſe do ſet and riſe; But ah I myſins do riſe, but neverſet. Shine Sun of glory, and my ſins aregone, Like twinkling Stars before the #. Sun. Fr. Quarles F 1 N I S. 2
Page Scan 230

Blank page
Page Scan 231

Blank page
Page Scan 232

Blank page
Page Scan 233

Blank page

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page Scan 234

-- *—- ------------- - - |3.º |i º -- :--t : - - THE NEW YORK PUBLIC LIBRARY REFERENCE DEPArtMent This book is under no circumstances to be taken from the Building l_- ==HIT º - º —- | |a - + |- * - - – --- - - - - for in 410 . -- : - **º - - - - -- - - - º ** * º * *- - - - - sº - - ---i-º-º-
