Antony and Cleopatra: : a tragedy. As it is acted at the Dukes theatre. / Written by the Honourable Sir Charles Sedley, Baronet., . | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
Antony and Cleopatra: : a tragedy. As it is acted at the Dukes theatre. / Written by the Honourable Sir Charles Sedley, Baronet., .
Author
Sedley, Charles, Sir, 1639?-1701.Sedley, Charles, Sir, 1639?-1701.
Published
London, :Printed for Richard Tonson ...,1677.
Description
[4], 62, [2] p. ;22 cm. (4to)
Rights
Public Domain.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/dul1.ark:/13960/t7mp7ws1d

Table of Contents

    Title Page

Book Text
Title Page
Page Scan 1

ANTONY AND CLEOPATRA TRAGEDY- As it is Adled at the DUKES THEATRE. Written by the Honourable Sir CHARLES SEDLET, Baronet. Licenfed Apr. 24. i 6 7 /• Roger LEfirange. LONDON, Printed for Richard Tonfon at his Shop under / GrayeS'Ime-gate next GrayeS'Ime4me. MDCLXXVIL
Page Scan 2

J [ Digitized by the Internet Arcliiv( in 2014 https://archive.org/details/antonycleopatratOOsedl
Page Scan 3

PROLOGUE. A 5 a brisK Gallant dancing to his Glafs^ Does here and there in nimble fleurets fafs ; Likes every fiep^ and wipes for a Ball^ Where he at once ma) Jhew his Parts to all : So Foets O^iththe like conceit J undone^ Think that dull Verfe which pleas d 'em vphen deney Muft have the like effect on the^ whole Town. Our Poet all fuch hopes ofPrai^ difclaimes^ 1 • ^ Like a true Lover of the Sporty he Games^> And to come off a Saver only aimes. j ; Did he affe^ to be efleem'd a Wit^ Like you ^ hed takg^ an eafier way to it : ^ Write Songs and Prologues^ Jf:ew 'em up and down^ And tear applaufe from every Fool in Town y -^. Mak€ Love to Vizards in a Wit-like Noife^ Dull in his Senfe^ yet aiery in his Voice , Catch at each. Line that grMeiy- and keep ten good^ With his damn'd Noife^ from being under flood. 'Tis well mofl Wits have fomethingof the Mad^ 'Or where Jhoud Poets for the Stage be had^^ Cripples may judge of Vaulting he well knovps^ Cowards of Courage ; and of Verfe and Profe They that know neither ; yet if too fevere Damning thofe Gifts of which they have no Jfmre^ Their Envy more than Judgement will appear. He none excepts^ no^ not his Enemies ; For thofe hei hopes his Friends will counterpoife : - Arid [pight of Faction on both fides he kriows^ , There 16 an honeji Party in this Houfe. -
Page Scan 4

Perlbns reprefented by C^far. Agrippa. Mecosnas. LHcilius a Roman. Thyreus. Antony. Camdins^ his General Photinus, Memnon. Chilax. J Two Egyprian Lords. M. Smith. Mr. Jevon, Mr, HarriSc Mr. Norris. Mr. Crosby. Mr. Betterton. Mr. Medbhrn. Mr. Sandford. Mr. PercivdU. yix.GiUovp. Cleopatra. Odfavia. Iras. Charm on. Mrs. Marj/ Lee. Mrs. Betterton. Mrs. G/M/. Mrs. Hughes. Guards, Meffengers, Villains, Souldiers and Attendants Men and Women. ERRATA. PAg. 3. lin. 53. for n?ee)^read vpeak§^ pag. 4. lin. 25. for ;>^^read power^ pag. 47. lin.26, for balme read ^>toe.pag.46.1in.3.C<e/^ fpeaks. We might, 8cc. ANTONY 1
Page 1

(0 ANTONY AND CLEOPATRA. ACT I. Scene the Firft. C^fars Tents. Enter Ctefar, J^ippa, SMecams. O C<efar. ^^""^ U El Arms an eafie Viftory have found Over a Foe^ in love and pleafure drowned. j4gr7f, I am picas'd we have Antonim fubdu'd Yet ragetothinka was purfu'd: Our fouls did once our conquered Bodies loath. And feldomedid one World contain 'em both. Yet now by'hopes we're flatter 'd to live on^ And with the Common Herd of Mankind run. Crouching to Fate, which we by death might (hun.' C^f* His Army's yet entire, and on the Shore 3 No Troops fo far the Roman Eagle bore ; Armenian Kings they have in Triumph led. And Parthian blood in ten fet Battles (hed : Their General to the laft they will defend. Mec(Bn. None can defend thofcj who themfeves betray r-j He with his Queen again will run away^ C And leave 'em fighting, as he did at Sea. ^ Agrip. Remember, Sir, the joy the World expreft^ When threatning Wars and Mifehiefs youredreft. With a late Ptace, which an Alliance ty'd^ And your fair Sifter made Antonio Brjde. B Th
Page 2

2 Antony and Cleopatra. The like again you to the World may give^ ^If you content with half of it can live. C<ef Againft all ftroke^ of Fate who can prepare ? That Match is half th* occafion of this Wan To him I did my dear O&avia givej That Rome in peace^lhe might in Empire livej That to one Emperor by blood ally'd^ And to the other by her Marriage ty'd^ She might all growing jealoufie removcj And be her felf the Bond of lading love. But fee th* unbleft event 5 Antomus flights That Tycj which even enemies unites 5 And more than drunk with Cleopatra s charms. He fcornsboth Romm-hovQ and Roman- ArmSo Jgrip. Love of our Country and our Intereft Is ihe true paffion of a Roman^x^sS^i^ All other are Ufurpers ' C£f Tis moft true : ' Yet this vile Flame he never will fubdue, Which fpight of time and of enjoyment lives ^. And of it's bane miraculoufly thrives. He thinks his life depends upon her eye^ As that of Plants does on the Sun relye. The ignorant are learn'd^ if fhe think foj And Cowards even Hercules out-do* At her requeft he Provinces beftows , And no mans worth but by her ft amp he knows. Whilft my 0Savia\Q2ids a Stepdames life^ And tends the Children of his former VVife, Ungrac'd without authority or fway. Mecmn. The wrongs of that fair Princefs^Sir, are greats And rage in all^ but in her felf create. What Hersforgives, our virtue fliou'd chaftife: Mortals revenge the blafphem'd i>eities. And ftrait the Impious wretch in pieces tear^ Whom Heaven in clemency wou'd long forbean , From equal po w'r how can you be fecure ? And lefs Antomm wQYQr will endure. Agrip^ Ar7t oni wor{ktd will no league refufe^ Aqd give in peace wh^t battle could not lofe^ ^ He
Page 3

Antony and CL^^j!tra^^^^^^ He may Olfavia receive again^ And in his Bed and Empiric make her reign. Meccen. Men leagues and peace in their diftrefs embrace, But keep 'em only till affairs change face. Ambition s never fafe till pow'r be paft. As men till Impotent are feldom Chafte. Follow the blowj and doubt not the fuccefs 3 But Fortune for her utmofl: favours prels. On petty Kings you trifling Gonquefts make, Antonius brings you here an equal ftake? The World to be divided at one blow. And Fate already has declared for you. Agri^* Men that have once an equal powV enjoy 'd, May fee the Ballance changed, but notdeftroy'd. He that is leffen'd to a Slaves degree, Still confcious of the firft equality, Mufthate the othfer, and himfelf much more. Who ever faw a Captive Emperor? With honour treat and yield perhaps he may. But he can never like a Slave obey. C<zf Peace we will offers that he mayrefufe. And the whole World his bloody mindaccufe. Thyrem knows the Queen : Him I will fend. Charge him that ftrait he in my Tent attend. Ex. Omnes. Scene the Second. The Palace^ Enter Memnon WChilax, two Egyptian Lofd^^ Mentn. Was ever Queen like Cleopatra curft ? Oi Egypt 3 Monfters fure her love's the worft. Where is that falfliood does the Sex purfue. Or are they only to their ruine true ? I faid kntonius might have laid the Scene Of War and Rapine further from the Queen, That our week State (hou'd to the Viftor bow^, And humbly the Decrees of Fate allow. She tells it him^ and I muft be difplac't. Chil. Tis hard men for their love (hou'd be difgrac't. B 2 No
Page 4

4 Mntp^^^,,md Cleopatra. Memn. No man may now his bleeding Country mourn^ Romans owx Lords, and we their Slaves were born. ChiL The Time* our honeft Counccls cannot bear. And men their Thoughts muft in difguifes wear. Memn. Let Women^ and Her Parafites feek to pleafe. Phyfitiansfhould not flatter thedifeafe. Her dang reus ftate'tis Treafon to conceal. Which nothing but Antonius death can heal. ChiL Tis a rough Medicine fhe will never ufe^ And fatal were th' advice fhould (he refufe. We know his intereft does her Councel fway. Memn. We this advice muft privately convey. Make her believe oSavius loves her too : On that (he will an eafie faith beftow^ C And in that hope what ift't (he may not do ?3 chiL 'Twereallinvain, and we our lives (hould lofe. Tamely and vilely laught at by our Foes: Be Thieves and Rogues to execution led) Let us die warm, and at an Army's head. The Romans will not ever be thus ftrong ^ Thoufandsaawell as we for changes long. Memn. Let s filent wait the opportunity. And by main force expel their tyranny. ChiU I love my Queen, and to rebel am loth* Mem. I would but free her from Antonius pow r. And that once done^ lay down my arms next hour. Chil, Let us fome plot againft his life devife : 7 He's not our Prince 5 for publick good he dies, r And for our Country falls a Sacrifice. J But fee He comes, and for his late difgrace^ •His ccnfcious vertue raging in hi3 face. Enter Antomusy Camdius^ Vhotinm^ Ant. How flippery is the Top of humane ftate. And on exalted Heads what tempefts beat ? Whom Jove will ruine he. makes deaf and blind. So that they hugg th' ill fate he has defign d 3 J elfe could never have bold Roman Swords Crowded and throng'd witbiathefe floating Boards^ \ Ships'
Page 5

Antony and Cleopatra. Ships, whom the winds more than their Pilots fway^ Where eager courage for a wave muft ftay. The Valiant cannot board, nor Coward fly. But at theluft of the unconftant sky. At land my Romans Can. Sir they bravely fought y Tho rude in Ships and Sea affairs untaught. Six hours they did a doubtful fight maintain, Deferted by your bafe Egyptian Train 3 S And by your felQ if f may be fo plain. 3 Ant. The juft reproach has rows'd my Lyon heart,. Nor ami angry at the friendly fmart. I fled, Canidius^hdi^QXy run away, 1 And fought for Empire below thofeforpay. > Of my new (hame too much thou canft not fay. > Can. They, who by Ships would fuch a Caufe decide,. Did not for conqueft, but for flight provide* Pardon me, Sir, my bluntnefs muft go on y By barbarous fears and couneels you 're undone. Thoti. We in Neutrality fecure might wait. And calmly expeft an Emp'ror from Fate 5 But in your quarrel half our Fleet we loft. Led by that Roman courage which you boaft. Momn. Our Ships with a promifcuous crowd were fiird. Neither in Battle, nor in Sailing skill'd. Reapers and Ploughmen halfner tugd an Oar, Nor faw the foaming Sea but fromthe Shoar. Muft we be ruin'd and defpis'd at laft? Canid, Did we by land a viftory forego. That a vain Queen might a rich Galley fhow ? My Legions Anto. Canidius no more. I know they flood impatient on the Shoar : Nineteen fuch Legions as might fate controul,- And fortunes wheel at their own pleafure rouU Can. A lofs at Sea let trading Nations raourno. Viftorious Romans to land Conqueft born, Trophies at Sea as much as gain defpife, . vhich an Ifland is the higheft prize» .
Page 6

6 Antony and Cleopatra. The trembling world did to the Viftor yields Crowned with the Laurels of Pharfalus fidd. Chil. Since we have loft 'tis well the gain was fmall, One lucky blow at Land recovers all. Phot. Th' Enemy is already at our Walls, And our diftrefs for fudden Counfel calls. Our Queen amazed at the Siege appears. j4^t. But yet her love is ftronger than her fears, Her Country (he has made the Seat of War, 'Tis jufl: her fafety be our early'ft care : I will her Guard within thefe Walls remain 5 And *gainft the angry Gods her Caufe maintain- Whil'ftyou Canidius to your Legions haft^ Slight our defeat, their loyal hearts make faft To our juft Caufe : our Enemies defpift. And for my abfence fome excufe devife. Can. Sir, I am blun*-, unknowing ro deceive, rie fay you cannot Cleopatra Leave : That you in her defence alone can fight. And bleft in love, the Roman Empire flight. Ant What ftiall I do, (hall I my Qjieen forfake, And not her danger, I create, partake ? C<f/ir, this night, may Alexandria ftorm. And all that luft or rage inftruft, perform. Her beauty may the Conqueror difarm, And his fuccefs and love that beauty charm. Her Subjefts weary of the Wars5 may rife And make her blood their common facrifice. Memn. They fay, their Qneen in policy of State, Should buy her Country's peace at any rate. Ant. They fay ! who fays ? Memnon you fain wou'd ventj In others names, your private difcontent. I fee a fullen fiercenefs in your brow Which you wou'd put in aft, if you knew how. Mem. Sir, I am known to love my Country well* Ant. So they fay all that purpofe to rebel. Chtl. Some with your head would young oUavius gretf, And on thofe bloody terms a Peace compleat : Under fuch Polititians Fompey fell With
Page 7

Antony and Cleopatra. j With tumults backt what may they not compel. Ant. How fhall they foes^ who cannot tumults quell ? The giddy muhitude, we muft not fear. But what we once refolve on^ make 'em bear. Mem. 'Tis ill to difcontent whom we muft ufe^ And men fight beft when they their party choofe# AnU 'Tis chofen for 'em by their Soveraign 5 And 'tis fedition in them to complain : Maxims too popular you ftill maintain. Mem. Sir, my plain fpeech does no defiga contain 5 'Tis the meer ifliie of my heart and brain : If it offend— Ant. It does, be gone. Nor will r learn of you what's to be done. E^c//». When things go ill, each Fool prefumes t'advifej) And if more happyj thinks himfelf more wife. All wretchedly deplore the prefent ftate And that advice feems beft which comes too late. Thot. You loofe your felf in rage and have forgot Amintas^ Deotorus — and the rout Of vulgar Kings have meanly turnd about.. Canid. Veluiium by Seleucm is betray'd. Some fay the Q^ieen did his revolt perfwade. Ant. Monfter^ fuch horrid blafphemy forbear. Both were his own^ the falftiood and the fear. Can. Sir, I but fpeak the language of the World. Ant. Henceforth be ever dumb that World and thou : It cannot, muft not, nor it (ha'nt be fo. ^ Can. Nay if it (ha'nt, I have no more to fay. Ant. Afide all prffion and all heat lie lay. And cooly argue : what can be her end There to betray^ whom (he does here defend* E«^er Cleopatra^ Ch*armion, Iras mth SeleucusV^^»^^ Son^y Egjp tians. But fee the Qiieen : Heart ! but this once (band faft— afide. . And rie forgive thee all thy weaknefs paft. How can your goodnefs to a wretch extend ? Who all he lov'd fo poorly did defends
Page 8

8 Antony and Cleofatra. chop. 'Twas not your life, but me, you cou'd not loofe. Love turn'd your back, not Fear upon your Foes. Ant. The tiraerous Deerjtheir female ftanding by^ Each other will to wounds and death defie. Love gives (hort courage to the meaneft foul. The creeping things he arms^ and winged fowl. Yet overcharg'd with love, I loft the day. And in my Miftrefs prefence ran away, Cover'd with (hame, I fear to meet thofe eyes. Cleop. To them you never were more dear than now: A manly look over your forrows throw. The Captain of my Gallies I have try'd. And for his cowardice the Villain di'd. With him die all remembrance of what's paft, I my C<efarion have toward India fent : This day Antillus to Armenia went. What Merchant in one Ship wou'd venture all ? They may furvive and fo revenge our fall, Ant. *Tis well they're gone, their youth was ufelefs here, And we for them more than our felves fhou'd fear. He fpies cleop. See here the falfe Seleucm only Son, Seleucus / On whom I beg quick juftice may be done. Son. His fathers Treafon might on me refleft Should I the Son from your reveng proteft : My love and honour, let his death fecure. The (horteft doubt they neither can endure. Ant. None dares be impious to that degree. To lay on you the Villains treachery. Now my revenge I cannot execute. Left I (hou'd feem your virtue to difpute. cleop. You doubt me not I know, but others may^ Let his death take their jealoufie away. Can, She fafely may the cruel ofTer make, apart. Which (he well knows Antonius will not take. Ant, He muft not die, nor is it true revenge. When the offenders fuffer by exchange. The youth it feems is not Seleucus care. Or our refentment thus he wou'd not dare. Cleop,Let him at leaft for an example die, Princes invite, who pardon treachery. Ant.
Page 9

Antony and Cleopatra. Ant. Twere cruelty to kill the fnnocent For Crimes they neither kneWjnor cou'd prevent : I beg his life my Queen— chop. You may command Or Life, or Deaths at cleopatrct\ hand. We who but now might halfe the World command. Are overthrown at Sea, befieg'd at Land : Each hour the news of fome frefh Treafon brings. From Faithlefs States or from revolted Kings. AntX^tX. thofe Crown'd Slaves from out our Party go A Treacherous Friend, will be a Tim'rous Foe. deep. The Plains about are cover'd with our Foes, Hiding the Earth, as when our Nile o're-fiows. Yet fate I in Antonius Courage reft. As if that Heart he gave me fili'd my Breaft. Ant* When Brutus this oBavius over-threwj In a pitch'd Field I Cajjius did fubdue. And turn'd the Fortune of that fatal day. Which thus ungrateful Rome and He repay 5 But here remaining I thofe Legions loofe. Which all commands but from my Mouth refufe. Cleop. They ever us'd Canidius to obeys * May he not go, and my Antonius ftay ? For you my Peoples love and more I loft, Muft I not keep what has fo dearly coft ? Ant. Ah Madam, you (hou'd take the v/eakeft part. And kelp a Lover to defend his Heart. Tho fwounding Men with eafe refign their Breath, Their careful Friends ftill pull'm back from Death. You (hould my Lethargy of Honour chide. And drive me tho unwilling, from your fide. Die at your Feet the meanefl: Lover might. But in your quarrel the whole World (hall fight* chop. If I am Captive x.ox}\q Romans made 5 Surprized in this weak place, or elfe betray 'd 5 Think not Pie live to be redeemed again, And like a Slave of my proud Lords complain. At the firft Dawn of my ill Fate Lie die. AnU O name not Death we 1 meet in Triumph here rie raife the Siege e're you have time to fear. C
Page 10

lo Antony and Cleopatra. chop. But then your Love, in abfence, will it laft ? Men think of joys to comej and flight the pad. Ant. My Heart fhall like thofe Trees the Eaft does (hoWj Where Bloflbmes and ripe Fruit hang on one Bough. With new defires^ foft hopeSj at once be preft s And all thofe Riper Joys, Love gives the bleft. Coura2;e and Love (hall fway each in their turn^ rie fight to conquer, conquer to return. Seeming Ambitious to the publick view, rie make my private end and dearer. You. This Storm once paft^ in Peace and Love we'l Raign^ Like the Immortal Gods, the Giants flain. Chop, Moments to abfent Lovers tedious grow 5 Tis not how time, but how the mind does go. And once Antonins wouM have thought fo too. Ant» Dearer than ever think not that I part. Without the utmoft Torment of my Heart. Whil'ft you perfwade, your danger chides my ftay^ Make me not caft me and your Self away. How well 1 lov'd, you did at A&ium fee, When to be near you I left Viftory. And chofe to be companion of your flight. Rather than conquer in a diftant Fight. Prefi not that heart you know fo well, too far. Our Fortune will no feccnd frailty bear. chop. The trueft Mifers choofe to fit about. And tell their wealth : but dare not truft it out. i know as well as you. Vis fit you go. Yet what is beft I cannot let you do* hnt. For my attendance I fome few will take 5 All other Romans of your Guard I make. chop. If you muft go, it quickly (hall appear. My love fought this delay, and not my fear. When you attaque, we1 (ally from the Town, And blood inftead of Nile our Plain (ball drown. We'i in the midfit of C<ffars Army meet^ And like Bellona, I my Mars will greet. Ant, VVou'd Goddefles themfelves to me endear^ 'h^^Ckopatr^'^ (hape they muft appeaio
Page 11

Antorv^ and Cleopatra. ii chop. My heart can danger though not abfence bear. To LovCj 'tis Wax, but Adamant to Fear. Ant. Mine has fuch Courage from your Firmnefs took^ That I can almoftbear a parting look. Cleop. Take it 5 and each unto their charge make hafte. Ant. Our hardeft viftory I hope is paft. Exeunt omnes* ACT II. Scene the Firft. The Town. Enter Antonius, Canidius. Ant. T^Mpire and Glory both farewell : Come (hame, £^ And Ihed thy Venom on Antonius Name ; Wither the Lawrels on his Brows and teach The World to (corn its moft inglorious Wretch. Forfaken in the choiceft hour of time. My hopes and refolutions in their prime. Honor^ my Queen and I Diftator made. And all his rough Commands cou'd have obeyM. Love for a while, we purpofe to dethrone. As Mariners in Storms their Sails take down. Can Romans thus their General forfake ? Can. They urg*d want of Provifion and of Pay. Ant. Both which had been redreft without delay : Th* obliging Qneen-— C^«.' rVVhom you may thank for this — Their general Difcontent at her was lowd : But Souldiers are a rude uncivil Crowd. Play'rs and Minftrelsj Singers and Buffoons^ Are the great Inftruments and Props of Thrones. I my old Legions to your Aid have brought. Firm to your Side, not tainted in a Thought™ They fay rhotinus in the Camp was feen. And that he was imploy'd there by the Queen. C 2 Ant.
Page 12

12 Antony and Cleofatra. Ant. At a revolt fo ftrange I am furpriz'd/1 Can. Pray Heaven it were not in the Town devis'd, ITour upright Nature ftoops not to Defcry Ttie low and fubtil ways of Treachery. Tho you may fail^ She can^r^ Beauty will find^ Viftorious and young Monarchs ever kind. Jnt. Your honeft meaning does your life protedt : Prefume no more her vertue to fufpeft. Can. May I not fay Thotinus is a Knave ? Ant. Tax not the man, unlefs good proof you have* Enter Photinus purjked by fix Villains:, Phot* Thofe two you mull: deftroy, and me difarm. Ah^ Sir, from Murthcrers defend your Life : See with my blood, they have begun the Strife. They draw^ two of the Villains fall ^ the Other run.. The Gods a Guard for Vertue ftill provide: Courage with Treafon feldome doth refide« Th'are fled and you unhurt-— Ant. I am :. But fay, Photinus-) whence thefe Villains cameo Fhot. Juft as I left the Throng — They let upon me Crying this is He, That with O&avius lets us not agree , Antonius Friend, and his own Countreys Foe^ And ftrait that word was followed with this blow* Some of the popular faftion fet 'm on^ Who think to govern all if I were gone. Ant. ^Tis moft unlucky thefe were Kill'd out right, Of their whole Plot we elfe might gain fome light. V\\oX.>flahs one lying on the ground^ he mutters out I . Villain, ihotinm is a Villain . . • . Vhot. See their fpight . . Even at their Death,whichl will thus requite— Can.inierpofes.. Why wou'd you fave from my juft rage fo impudent a Slave }: I. Villain. Thotinus fet us on : vhot. Unheard of villany .... My felf to Kill, they did confpire with Me \ But great j4ntonius is himfelf too juft on a Murd'rcrs malice to diftruft,.
Page 13

Antony and Cleopatra. 13 Camd. Slight not too much the words of dying men^ Thev who hate truth before will fpeak it then. Phot^ My conftant zeal and firmnefs to your fide^ So oft in Council and in Aftion try'd^ This accufation cannot but deride. What- is't a Murth'rer milTing of his blow. In his laft rage would not both fay and do ? Ca^. Who dares die^ And the jufl: Gods provoke with fuch a lie ? Phot. He that dares bafely Kill, what dares he not^ No Crime a Murtherer cou'd deeper blot. Cuft. Yet to that crime ingratitude may add. Pkot, You fpeak as of my guilt you wou'd be glad» j^nt. Mv friendsjlet this untimely difcord fall. Phot. Although much wrong'd, at your Command it (hall.. Cafi. I wifti, Sirj to my Souldiers you wou'd fped^^ And let'm know how well their loves you take. A^t. I go : their Faith fhall fo rewarded be — The reft (hall foon repent their treachery, Ex. Ant. Can.. Phot. Had they fought well their danger had been fmall^ Cou'd they not fear at firft or net at all > Curfe on all middle ways : Courage enough When once engag'dj can only bring us off. But the next blow by fate (hall be my own^ And rie ftrike home for Iras and a Throne, My perfon is ungracefulj I well know It was contriv'd for ufe and not for (how^ Befides I m old^ that too when I am grear^ She may have the Ambition to forget. This gentle Maid all other ways have try'd^ Hopelefs of Love? Tie now attempt her pride-- Ef7ter Iras. But fee (he comes^ and charming as new lights . Appeared to the firft Mans amazed (ight. A noife of Drums^^ You he.ir how Drums and Trumpets fill the Air^ And for a Scene of Blood our Minds prepare. Iras. Tis Lovej vile Love whence this Diforder fprings. P.hot. The tender Parent of the fright fuPft Things* Xet;
Page 14

1 4 Antony and Cleopatra. Yet blame not Love, when to h'sobjeftfixt. It only harms when with Ambition mixt. When raging Winds raife Tempeftson the Main, The gentle Brooks creep mildly through the Plain. Tis only to the Great thefe Storms are known, VhotiPius paffion fears your fcorn alone. Iras* What is this Love, we never can exclude? But whatfoe're we talk of) 'twill intrude. Thot. Of Storms the Seaman tells, of ploughs the Hinds Lovers in fuch difcourfes eafe their mind. 'Tis the glad bufinefs of young Heartj^, the pain^ The old^ for their prefumption muft fuftain. Iras. Is't a difeafe beauties inteftion fpreads? Pray does it feize you in your hearts or heads? Thot. Sweet Innocence ! it enters at the eyeSj And to the heart like fubtle lightning flies. When Lovers meet it is all extafie. And when they part again they more than die. Iras. How chance that I have fcap t this mighty ill? I gaze and ftare at every thing my fill. The Wife, the Handfome, and the Brave, I love. Yet feel no pain at all when they remove. Thot- Paffions lye yet within your tender breaftj Harmlcfs and weak as Eagles in theNeft: But Love hereafter on your heart will prey. Iras. If ever any one efcap't, I may. Thot. Twere mofl: unfit you Qiou'd, Nature <\ocs Provide fome foveraign thing for every ill. For Beauties wounds their kindntfsis the cure : • Scorpions who cou'd without their oyl endure ? Iras. If I have hurt you 'twas againft my will. Thot. Your Charms not like a Foe, but weapon, kill. Iras. Their farther ill efFefts I will prevent. And of what's paft, though innocent, repent; ^'11 go where you (hall never fee me more. Thot. That muft not be, from you whom I adore. Abfence is raging pain, prefence a joy 5 Which will at leaft voluptuoufly deftroy. Iras. Wou'd you not have me go nor ftay ! what then ? This Love I fee makes errant Fools of men. Thot.
Page 15

Antony and Cleopatra. 15 Vhot* Stay gentle Iras 5 learn to love of me^ How eafie were it^ cou'dl charm like thee. Iras. Does no man elfe adore me as you do? Thot. None ever did^I'l place youon aThronej A Scepter may for pers nal wants attone. Beauty and Youth? your Sexes glories are. In men they foon decay, or not appear. Iras* I did not know you were a Prince difguis*d : At your new Majeftyl'm much furpriz'd. Vhot. I am no King. Iras. How then fhall I be Queen? O I could ftrut with Cleopatra % Mein. vhot. The Rowan Empire can a Crown beftow, Iras. Such gifts may be Antonius overthrow* Vhot. So let em be. Iras. But what , he gives you, Rome Will take away, if C£far overcome. vhot. My hopes, fweet Innocence, in C^far lye^ And e're I reign Antonius muft dye. Iras. You have but the Reverfion of a Crown^ And e're he dies how old you will be grown. vhot. Your youth a while may for fuch glories wait^ But you may truft my Love to urge his Fate. Iras. Muft I then marry you , or be no Queen ? vhot. I m not fo withered, nor are you fo green Nay Charmion will accept what you refufe? And when Qie reigns your peevifhnefs accufe— - It works — Iras. No no ! my felf HI have you firft — To fee her Queen I (hould with envy burft. vhot. Will (he then promife to love me alone, When I have plac'd my Iras on a Throne ? Iras. I will do any thing, to be a Queen 5 I could love one whom I had never feen. Enter Mejjenger, Jllejf. Madam, the Queen much wonders at yourftay. Ex.Iras^, vhot. She s gone^ (he's gone, and I me-thinks have more ^ A thoufand times to utter than before, Y So inexhauftible's a Lovers ftore^ J'
Page 16

i6 Antony and Cleopatra. To her Ambition I her Love mufl: own 5 But Fate her youth, my age will have it fo. How falfea Joy in that fair Sex he takesj Whom once the hope of equal love forfakes. Scene the Second, C(efars Tents. Enter C^fir:) MecceMos^ with Atendants^ C^f Meccerjos fee ftrift diTcipline they keep Through the v;holeCamp5 that neither wine nor fleep Betray us to furprize ; tho peace feem near? Wife Pilots at the Port a tempeft fear. Mec(Sfi. Great SirjYOurSouldiers find they have to do Not with a rude unarm'd and barb'rous Crew 5 But Romans like themfelves^ in Conqueft bredj And next your felfj by the beft Captain led. Their jealoufie of Fame and Love for you^ Will make em any thing forbear or do. A poyt of joy. Enter Agrippa. Agrjp. Antonim Legions newly are arriv'd^ And through the Camp are with loud joy received. Tir'd with his impotent and diftant fway . They nowj Great Sirj will you alone obey. Cdef Then vanifh all hishopes, and all my fears. In my whole sky of Fate^ no Cloud appears: That one black corner did a tempeft threat. Agrip. You much are to Fhotinm care in debt : Him in the Campj v/hen I arrived I found. C£f Yee Gods! why am I to a Villain bound? Tell my new friends^ I their arrears will pay 3 h^Roman Emperor they ftill obey. Mcccen. Antomusnow will any Laws receive^ What from weak Foes we do not take, we give. Demand ih^ Roman Legions yet behind. And that his pow'r to Afia, be confined. C(ef The man was once my Friend, my Brother ftill: What are thefe thoughts that wou'd ambition chill? ^ Mecmn. Forget that name he has deferv'd fo ill.. > The fpoil of Egjp will the War defray 5 3 Fcr ameer peace RomQ will repine to pay. Enter
Page 17

Antony and Cleopatra. Efiter Oftavia. tJim brotherj let Egyptian Princes callj, He has no Intereft in your blood at all. Since the beft Ty he flights, and in her place Does a left fair ^Egyptian Queen embrace. oS. Pernicious Counceller that does foment A War, all tvut the Parthians wou'd prevent. My Wrongs (hall never thy Ambition hide. Tie tear the Mafque of pity from thy pride. I thought thee once deferving thy great place. Of tufcan Kings fprung from the glorious race. But thou art falfe, cruelj and bloody now. That open hatred thou durft never Ihow. To my dear Lord, does ftill in malice lurk. And on this dire Occafion feeks to work. C^e/T Sifter^your Husband I would but reclaim, And make him worthy of your virtuous flame. His prefent life does his paft glory ftain. He makes a Qieen the Partner of his raign. The Roman Empire he does much deface. And with the Spoil adorns her foraign race. Arabics where the Nabutheans live. And part o( Syria he did lately give. To their new iflue one he ftiles the Moon : To name the other^ he profanes the Sun. oS. If he has given much, he conquer'd more : j His valour, for his bounty, found the ftore^ > And pardon fomewhat on a Sifters (core. 3 C^f The names of Emperor and Queen they fcorn. And like immortal Gods themfelves adorn. He does for Bacchus^ (he for l(is pafi. And in their (hapes, the wond ring Crowd amaze. oS. To Gods of their own honour leave the Care, Since they both Jealous and Almighty are. I fear fo high you'l my concernments prefs 5 You'l break on that you never can rcdrefs. C£f 1 underfland no Riddles, but he (hall Do my O^^avU fuddea right or faU. D
Page 18

i§ Antony and Cleopatra. The reft I cou'd with fmall. excufe forgive ; j But under this affront I c^nnoi live. > 0(7. You f\y his other faults you cou'd forgive. 3 C£f Empire's our real quarrtl, but J muft {^Aflde. Her virtuous Mind with no fuch fecret truft. " • I could — Off. Then that pretence Fie thus remove and dy ; r Stabs her Still more inhumane muft I then remain, ^ felf. The cover of your Pri de and Luft to reign. )Mec. Tho I were dead you might your ends purfue^ ^ terpofis* But let me vanifh from the painful view. Mec* Not for the World fuch virtue fhou'd not dy. But be intire tranflited to the Sky. C<f/r I Sifter your late rafhnefs can forgive, So you henceforth will promife me to live. Meccenas fee remov'd all means of Deaths Let Nature and not rage conclude her breath. ^Ex, C^far, A- Off. Peace to the W orld and my unhappy Lord, c grippa, (j^c. My Brother but for you wou'd foon afford. Mec. Condemn not adliotis till you know their end, But mine perhaps will then but more offend. off. I know you'l fay 'tis brave to rule alone. That my great Brother wou'd become that Throne. And raifing him you in proportion rife;> 1 But ftill remember there are Deities ^ Above you bothj juft,pow'rful, and wife. 3 Mec. Ambition never overturn'd my mind, ! am already more then I defign'd. Off. Why do you then the general peace oppofe h 'Tis Avarice or Ambition makes Men foes. Mec» I Madam wou'd fome marks of courage (hovi^^ And what I durft for my great Mafter do. off. Romans of courage need no other proof, Since to be born a Roman is enough. Mec. *Tis truth, but yet—- Off. Some unjuft pique you bear. My deareft Lord, you cannot well declare, Sut good Meccena^ 5 for fuch once you were ^ T'obftruft this Treaty for my fake forbear.
Page 19

Antony and Cleopatra. Mec. Tis for your fake alone^ it muft not be. 0(J. If it be good for Kome^ regard not Me. ^ Mec. Y'are Sifter to my Emperor and Friend, My utmoft carej muft your concerns attend : I do not as you think confufiop f^k, v:!: . Nor keep I to your Lord a fecret pique : - But if this Treaty be confirmed to day ^ I muft at Rom^^ and you in Aftci ftay. 0^. It is the part of the wSoIe World Td chufe^ And gaining Him, what is't I care to loo(e. Mtc. Ah Madam5 feem lefs virtuous or Ie(s fair^ Who can behold you and not vengeance fware. Such fufFering goodnefs will mankind ingage^ And on Antonius pull their publick rage. This to the Sifter of your Emperor 5 Mec. This to the only Beauty I adore: Beyond my patience you have rackt my Breaft^ And my deep guilt at laft muft be confeft. I love youj Madam — oS. My next requeft you'l then not difallowj Mec. Speak it, and I a blind Obedience vov/. ^ . ] ,^ OB. Let me then die for I have liv'd too lon^fisi no r And heard of Love in Antonius wrong. ^-trjoa Mec. Not in his wrong f Tie the reverfion waitj' And live like Heirs in hope of an Eftate. ^ ; ^ OU, Your word is paft recall. My Death I claim. ^ ardordW "" Mec. From me who both your;Guard and Lover ani; woM I not the ftroak:, but means of Death require d JaW By my own hand I nobleft ftiall expire. - Will you then promife to promote the peace. Mec. You offer poifon, to my known Difeafe :«-iiqfi}3 ;v But from thofe hands I nothing can refufev j vv ucn^ flob Ili wofcl rie ruine all my hopesj fo you will live ^. v x'^^ rvbooM anw s»v>\h';> 03. Yes, I will live, but not an hour furviv^ My dear Antonius him you muft preferve. If ought you from O&avi^ would deferve — Ex. Jilec. Whom, whiift he lives I never .cao L^jQy, - . > And if he dies (he will her felf deftre^y.^lii.v i-rr.foO vhl .w I am undone 5 obey or difobey^J -^[no I qeeds muft perifti, but may chofe my way. Ex, omms. D 2 ACT.
Page 20

\Antony and Cleopatra. ACT. III. Scene the Firft, (^^efars Tents. Enter C^fir^ Jldecce^aS:, Agrippa. Cafar. ^ I ^He Afians now with double Taxes preft^ X His flothful Days and drunken Nights deteftl Buffoons and Players chiefly have his ear ; He dares not the free tongues of Romans hear» To marry Whores to Fencers is his fportj And with their Iffue throng his loathed Court.' Now lewd Cythtrk has a greater Train, Than his own Mother or his Wife maintain. From fuch a Foe as this what can we fear ! In whom all fymptoms of loft pow'r appear. Mec(sn. The flatt'ring Greekj his eafie aature praile % But on the reft he heavy burthens lays. - ni^rn orn . . i In drunken Bountyj for a riotous treaty He gave hrs Fav nte Cook a (paeious Street : Men fay no hour dares move without its Feaft^ Which is for their fantaftick pallats dreft. Now muft therifingSun their Riot view^ i ^ Which the next cjay prevents the Evening Jew. In every draught they fomerichGemiconfume? \: And fpend a private Fortune in one Room. C<^f. Empire, of pains and virtue^ the flow fruity How ill doft thou with vice and riot fuit ■ Cfmavjzs bloody , Marim unjuftv Tarquin and Apfim- raging in their Luft : LuchUus was luxurious, loud hi*s eafe. Thus on each man his fingle vice did feize I But all ihefe faults ar^ m A^2to^immQt. Mec(en, His Court with Ajian Flatt rers is &iVdr And Lying Gr^f^^ the only Servants held*. Xhefe
Page 21

Antony and Cleopatra. 21 Thefe ferve the turns of riotous delight, Whilft KoniAHs only are thought fit to fight. Agrip, Example is a living Law, whofe fwajv Men more than all the written Laws obey. Princes of all men therefore fhou'd take care^ How in their manners they the Crowd enfnare. But above all his dotage on the Queen Employs my wonder ; was it ever feen A Woman rul'd an Emperor till now ? What Horfe the Mare, what Bull obeys the Cow? Nature that Monfter Love does difavow ; In all her kinds only fantaftick Man Finds ways of folly which no other can. Mecxn, He that will vilify the pow r of Love, In the firft place let him cur Gods reprove. Who oft their heavenly Manfions have forfook. And the mean fliapes of Birds and Beafts have took^ To purfue Mortals in an amorous wayj And form their glorious Image in our clay. Agrip. The God that lov'dj what Nymph yet ever rul'd? He was again a God, his Luft once cool'd : Had womens will our good or ill procured. The World had never half (b long endur'd. The high embrace fill'd all their fpacious thought. And proofs of kindnefs were no farther fought^ cdf Th'unable fure, the ugly, or the old, Firft in affairs of Love, made ufe of gold. Then Princes to out-bid 'em threw in pow'r. Now heart for heart's the Traffick of the Poor. Agrip. Women (hould fit like idle Paflengers, While the tall Ship fome able Seamen fteers. Wifdom, high Courage, Piety are vain^ If o're the Wife and brave a Woman reign. C And this Anionitts condiifl: has made plain. \ C£p Tis time the infur'd World we thould redeem- From a mans fvvay fo loft in her eftfeem. Agrip. What is fuccefs in Arms if ConquVmg Rome^ By Troops cf Ajlan Vices be o recome. C^f To fet all right I muft be abfolute 5 My.leaft conamands None daring todifpute:
Page 22

22 Antony and Cleopatra. Rowes defp rate ftate can never find redrefs? But from apow'r as able to opprefs^ Whilft for the publickgood my pou'r I ufe. Seeing my end Men will the means excufe. Th' Omnipotence of Godsj who thinks too great, ' Since men below they with compaffion treat. Agr/p. But envy does all mortal pow r attend : Men fear the Means^ and ftillfufped: the end. He that can hurt, whoimfwersbut he will: Men pafs in fear by fleeping Lyons ftill. Empire is fafefl: moderately greats And death unfeen does on Ambition wait. C£f. He that can do no ill, can do no good) And if in one, in both may be withftood. The aftions of a Tyrant I abhor^ But ns things ftand I cannot want the pow'r. -^gnp. Our Laws the art of ruling beft contain 5 Mecosn. Fools find it thercj wife Princes in their Brain* \Agrjp. Pow'r long pofleft few Princes care to ufe. But give it up for others to abufe : From PhcebuskW the World no hazard ruUj But cou'd not bear one day his Vent'rous Son : He through new wayes the flaming Chariot drove. And all was fear below, and fire above. C£f I to no Phaeton will the reins commit^ Nor in inglorious eafe a moment fit : He fee the Common- wealth no mifchief take. And do and fuffer all things for her fake. Mec(Bn* Rome on your vertue leans her aged head. As old Anchifes on j^neas did. And thinks ihe may with eafe when propt by you. Faftions at Home, and Foes abroad fubdue. You, whom the general voice of Rome does hold. Bolder than Youth, and wifer than the Old. Agrip* The name of Common-wealth is popular, And every Cddfirm^y his Brutus fear. Mec£n* Romans that barbarous Murder foreveng'd. It fhews the thoughts of a Republick chang'd. Csf Men die of Agues, too much heat or cold, -And others grow ridiculous old. Ex.. <Z^{X^QiM^c.m^net Ag T
Page 23

Antony and Cleopatra. 23 The thoughts of humane chance (houIcJ make us bold. He feizethe Empire, v/hich He die or hold. Agri^* Born under Kmgs our Father freedom fought^ And with their blood the Godlike treafure bought^ We their vile iffuein our chains delight. And born to freedom for our Tyrants fight. Exit. Agrip, Scene the Second. The Palace. Enter Antomus^ Canidius^ Vhotinm* Can. For what Sir, muft we then prepare? Thyreus \ does he bring us Peace or War ? Anto. He offers Peace, but upon terms fo high 5 At the great rate Td not an Empire buy o* My former gifts I meanly muft refume. And 8:ive accounts of all my aft to Rome. My faithful friends from, their Commands remove. And place fuch as the Senate (hall approve. Canid. True friends difplac't will pardon your diftrefsg And tho your pow r— - Anto. A Pageant powr and Empire but in (how— • True Empire only thofe great Souls enjoy^ Who can in what, and whom they pleafe employ, And without leave from Rome a Crown beftow? Exalt a Friend5 and trample on a Foe : This by your Love and Arms l onceattchiev'd. Nor will be of it but by Arms deprived. Can. Ambition is the Dropfey of the Soul, Whofethirft we muft not yield to but controu!. Anto, Some Drudg of State may a lefspow'r efteem^^ And ruling many, let a few rule him 5 Mean Slave to them, high Tyrant to the reft^ With fear and pride at once defile his breaft : By Hercules I won^t, if any here Think that a Courfe too defp'rate I fteer. Let him retire, and his own fears obey. Canid. The Gods well know my fears are all for yoa , - And your moft dating thoughts (hall find me true : It is not C^fur^ nor our blow at Sea, That to thefe terms incline me to agree 5 But:
Page 24

24 Antony and Cleofatra. But 'tis the love of Rof^e which you have loft. And that your Ryots here and Loves have coft. J^t. C<efir and I you know were never friends. And only hung together for our ends : Yet in his Caufe this Tongue an Army rais'd. And made Rome hate that deed (he late had prais'd, 'Brutus and Cabins felt the deadly fting s And all to make oUavtus more than King. So blindly did I aft, fo little fee. Into the dark Decrees of Deftiny. The Common-wealth for him I overthrew^ N6w in efFeft he claims my Empire too. Vhet. The Shell he leaves, the Kernell takes away. You, Sir, muft him, as others, you obey. Ant. He wou'd a fway pretend over roy Love, And teach my free affeftions where to move:. To my embrace his Sifter I muft take. And my beft Queen ingratefully forfake. Can. That Sifter is your Wife. Am* So let her be From paft engagements, prefent Love, fet free. ijjmen is but the Vulgars Deity ... Enter Cleopatra, Charmion, Irasj Egyptians. chop. O my Antonim ! how I fear this Peace ! And fnuft I to O&avia yield my place ? I love you fo, that very found wou'd kill. And leave you free the promife to fulfil. Ant. Were I to gain the Empire of mankind. And for that pow'r. Eternity affign'd : I cou'd not to the hateful change fubmit. Nor my beft Queen fo barbaroufly quit. Clcop. But your OiJavit^loving^ youngs and fair. And fuch a Rival ! how can I but fear ? Ant* Her Hymen never did a Moment pleafe. The hard Condition of a needful Peace : From- every part I faw the growing ftorm^ A fudden (helter in her arms I took, Which when 'twas over I again forfook. C/eop. And can you for My (ake a War fuftain ? Her Brothers friendfhip and Her Love difdain ? Ant.
Page 25

'Antony and Cleopatra. Ant. AH hearts a like, all faces do not move, There is a fecret Sympathy in Love : The powerful Loadftone, cannot move a Straw, No more than Jet, the trembling Needle draw : Your Beauty only on my Heart can aft : All other ways, it is in vain attaqu'd. chop. Sure of this War I am the meer pretence^ How can our Lovcj to Rome^ give fuch offence > She (hou'd revenge the Ghoft of CraJJus flain. And haughty Babel\tvA with the Plain, But let in Egjpt^ Love and pleafiire reign. Ant* Rome like her Eagles, did on Rapine thrive, I am the firft that taught her how to Give. Cleop. What y' have prefented me or plac'd on Mine, I to that griping Senate here refign. I never did the gifts but Giver prize : Some new pretence of War let m devife : All but your felf I for your fake can quit : j For you I did my Crown and Fame forget 5 > And can you now weigh coldly what it is fit ?> Can. Turn my beft Mafter, from her charming Tongue^ 'Tis hard to think fuch Beauty in the wrong : Yet if you don't, we are for ever loft- Ant. I have refolv'd : to Cafar I will fend : p If he his Grace will to the Queen extend, ^ And let the Crown upon her Sons defcend. 3 rie kill my felf, and rid him of his Foe, If not, the laft extreams Tie undergo. C^«. What Roman will the hateful MeflTage bear? Cleop. Let us intreat, we may at Athens live, And taft what joys a private Life can give : Leaving our greatnefs and our pomp behind. We (hall in Love fincerer pleafures find : But whether am I wrapt ? fond thoughts be gone. And melt fome tender Virgin of low race. You are below a heart that wears a Crown, Where Life, Love, all muft to renown give place. Ant. Souldiers, when old we from the Wars difchprc; :. But Fate her Drudges never fets at large; The Higher place they fill, the greater Slaves, Princes have no retirement but their Graves^
Page 26

^4 Antony and Cleoj^atra. My equal pow'r this C^fur cannot bear , His Sauldiers want my Provinces to fhare ;^ • Unaftive Li'j?/^^ he laid afidcj r . And will no longer now the VVorld divide S > VVhofe doubtful Title muft by Arms be try 'do E^ter Thyreus* But fee rhyreu^ here - ' ^f W'^^rl He has fome Meffage for your private Ear, r Which I without a jealous pang can bear. ^ Can. She is a woman^ Sir^ and when y ' are goile^ By C£fars Offers may be wrought iipon. Arit. Jealous ! yet truly honeft. 'Tis ftrange how In thy plain mind fuch wild fufpition's grow, I will return before their Conference end. But on her Love entirely I depend. Ex. Ant. Canid* Thyr. Madam 1 my Mafter's gracious as he's great. See's how y'are forc't t' allow this fhort Retreat, To his proud Foe, and does himfelf excufe? That Ayd perhaps you cou*d not well refufe : The Ruines of a Roman Emperor, In her own Kingdom may a Qiieen o're pow'r. chop. I firft was fummon'd in Romes haughty Name^ E're I into Antonius prefence came. Brutus and his I was accused to Aid, ^ut foon acquitted and her Ally made^ Since \\\ Antonius I have obey'd. Thyr. If an Ally of Rome you Chou'd difclaim, The Man^ whom (he does Foe and Tray tor name* Cleof. Thofe very Titles She Great 'jnlius gave^ And yet anon, obeys him like a Slave. On the Succefs of War, her Voice depends. The diftant Foes (he ftiles the prefent Friends. Let others from Antonufs fortune fly, I will fupport or in their ruine lye. i:hyr. His Sbuldiers have another fence declar'dj And are to ftorm this ftubborn Town prepared. Chop. Bafe Mercenary Souls that fight for Pay^ To morrow Kill, whom they defend to day But Princes Minds on Springs of Honour move, A k1 what caa they not do> wound up by Love ?
Page 27

Antony and Cleopatra. 27 Phot. If not your Self) your harmlefs Subjefts favCj They neither love Co wellj nor are fo brave. Defpair fhall make thofe heartlefs Villains bold^ While by worfe fears^ the fear of Death's controurdo rie Ro/;^e provoke beyond all hope of grace^ Then in their ArmSj they muft their faftty place. phot. They'l fooner take thofe Arms up and Rebel . . . Cleop, Antomus Souldiers will fuch Tumults quel. The People ever difcontented are 5 Their Crouds were made to be the food of War : [jEx* Phot* thjr. Ci^/Srr is pleased - - You (hou'd keep all the Realms •f which y^are feiz'ds Some little to deferve this yovi muft do. Cleop^ Defert proposed me from a mortal Foe ? 7hyr. Give us but entrance in the dead of nightj VVe all will fpare who are not killed in Fight $ Like C£far^ Cleopatra (hall command^ Antomus falls into a Brothers hand. Cleop. Who will revenge the fcornhis Sifter finds 5 Are thefe your deep^ your generous Defigns > 7hj/r. You but precipitate the event of War^ And by that aft a Sea of Blood might (pare. I have a ftep beyond my Orders madcj Which were but to propofe not to perfwade- But who can fee fuch Beauty in diftrefs^- And not the utmoft of his thoughts expreft. chop. In Fates whole fcope I fear but one events ^^/KlJi And that your felf with honour may prevent. Thyr. What is it, Madam ? will you hear me.fwear,; . You truft your fecret to a Lovers ear, i : e One that has long, and privately been (bJ 10 lobr: cleop. Sir to make Peace^ you were Cxom Cafar fentj ^ But make not Love, th6 but in Complement.^ . nr-. If C£fir take this Tov/n by Fates decree? ; ^^m 'V--' ^ ^ - Swear to inform^ what he will do with me-— Thyr, Tis not refolvM^ foon as I know I will • . . cleop. Then found him dayly with your utmoft skilL Thyr. But is this all ? I was in hope to fervej In fome defign that might your Love deferve. ji slltj This
Page 28

28 Antony and Cleopatra. This for yonr meaneft Slave I had performed. deep. Tis all of which I care to be inform'd— Z^y>-./My'Qfferi5 Madam .... Cleop. They are (Ijch as ftiow^ Romatis but ill o{ th' hearts of Monarchs know. But on your promife may a Queen rely> , 'E.nf^r Antorjinsj Canidius nnfeen^ and Souldkru Thjir. Tou may i but doubt not Cafars Clemency j Your Xrown and PerfoDj tha provokr hel fpare, Conqueft and -Ruin will refped :he Fair, VVhat oiay n't fuch Beauty hope, nor is it new. That he who rules, the VVort.^ ftiould bow to you. j^nt. By Heaven, at C )mpl< ments ^ Tie paufe a while, And fee this fubtle Scene f)f VVomans guile. Ckof. My Fates worfe Face you will not then dilguife^ I can behold it with undaunted Eyes. 'ihjr. And may it prove as charming as your own 5 Chop. I fear you will forget me^ when y'are gone. Th^r, I fwear upon fiiy Knees and by that Hand : VV hofe every touchy my Soul leaps up to meet : Let me once more th' inflaming Blifs repeat. Like the firft drop which Men in Feavours taft, ' It to a deeper draught but makes me haft. Thus ftarving Men, think every thing a Feaft, Whil ft fome with taftlcfe plenty^ ly oppreft : O that I were Antonius but one day ! Ant. Slave from that pofture thou ftialt never rife^ But be my Wraths immediate facrifice. Can. Holds Sir^ your Sword you (hall not raftily ftain^ VVhat hopes of Peace Embafladors once flain? Ant. Ambaflador of Love the Villain cames And 'mongft affairs of State he vents his Flame^ He Kift her Handj fome charming MeflTage ftire, Atleaft of half ray Empire, She s (ecure- Which Qie perhaps muft with my. Life repay, Thefe are the Bargains made when I am away i 'Tis more than Madnefs. to believe that you Falfe to my Love^.are to my Empirie tro^^ Ch0p4 I falie to you I
Page 29

'Antony and Cleopatra. 29 Artf. By Hercules you are : and had I ftay'd^ None knows the faithlefi anfwer you had made. chop. What is it that fo ftrange Antomffi finds ? He kift my Hand in taking of his leave^ *Tis a re^eft that Queens from all receive. Ant. The eager Rifs? no Lover can miftake. It exracy and fudden rapture fpake, Thofe of refpeft are of a colder make : Ye Gods ! he (wore by't perhaps endlefs Lovcj Or that he wou*d your Mediator pro</e. Cleop- Aik him ! His offers I have all refus'd^ And yet of fa'.fhood live to be accus'd By yoUj for whom I fuffer^ is this jaft ? One minute? brings long faiih into Diftr Ant. Minutes may ruine what in Ages rofe. Like Thunder, Lov^^in inftants ovenhrows. He has difturb'd me.^ And he (hall be whipt^ Ca^iditis fee he inftantly beftript. Can* If thus you trample on all Roman Laws, What Roman is there that will own your Caufe ? The Law of Nations too does this withftand,^ To any thing that's brave Tie lend my hand5> But ftir to no fuch infamous command: j Ant, Seize the bold Traytor. Sould* Will you have him fliead. Say but the word) this minute he is dead. Ant. There's a true Servant to his Mafters will. Whom I condemn^ he queftions not to kill, Thyr. With this affront if thou dar'ft glut thy hate^ Nopow'r on earth can fave thy falling ftatcr C<efir will take revenge — Ant Away, away .... And my command fee ftfiftly you obey. Ex^ chop. I do not know that I a fmile mifi)lac't. Frown'd v,?here you frown'd, and where you lik't I grac't. Not Wealth to Mifers, Honour to the Brave, Health to the Sick, or Freedom to the Slave Cou'd be more welcome than you Love to Me, Then think how felt, the cruel change mufl be : Ant. What Change >- cUop>
Page 30

^0 Antony and Cleopatra. chop. How can you ask , while this diftruft appears ? Diftruft^ the firft decay of Love in years. What we defire we eafily beheve^ Love on the fmoother fide does ftill deceive. Ar2t. Your Lover (hall be whipt, and as you bear Thnt^ I (hall think you criminal or clear. chop. Not to the Manj but to his Charafter, Such an affront I wifh you wou'd forbean It is a deed that might amaze the Sun, And by the rudeft People yet undone : In all the Travels of his fruitful Hght j He has not met fo barbarous a fight 5 Ambafladors are facred next the Gods^ Above your Axes plac't as well as Rods. Ant» Obferve hoWj leaft I change his punifhment. All ways of my revenge (be wou*d prevent-^ He may not die . . • . ' chop. Nor (han'tj unlefsyour hate^ All human Laws refolve to violate. Then kill me firft. Enter Photinus in hajl. rhot. The Cities up^ the Souldiers Mutiny^ And all-— long live the good thyreus cry. Anto. My Romans take and charge m inftantly. Thot, What they demand, perhaps you'll not refufc. Anto. How 'er their fnfolence I'll not excufe. Canid. Good Sir;> abroad you knov/ we want no foeSg This inward ftrife methinks we might compofe : oSav/uf work our fel vesj let us not do. Cleo. My People Sir^ I hopeyou 11 not deftroy^ Whofd lives I for your fervice, wou'd imploy. Thotinus fay their Queen bids'm begon^ And truft ourLove^ what's fitting (hall be done. Enter Mejjhngers. Meff. Your Romans-^ Sirj joyn with th' unruly crowed. And to defend th'Embaflador, have vow'd ; They fay a Roman never fliall be whipt. While Sword or Spear a Roman arm can lift. I *MeJp They have by this the Caftle Walls broke down^ QMeJf, And fet Thyrem fafe without the Town. Ant»
Page 31

Antony and Cleofatra. 3 B Anf. Draw upmy Guards^ if I have yet a Friend 5 This TumuU fhall in death of Thoufands end. What muft OBavius conclude of me ? If whom 1 once imprifon, they fet free. Cko» They have done right by chance^ excufe 'em fort 5 Tempefts fometimes drives Ships into the Port. Ant. TheRableisathing below myhate^ But my own Romans I will decimate. Eifter Lucilius Captain of the Rout» Luc. For what is done, I fingly am to blame : The reft but on my call and credit came. Ante, What mov'd thee tco'c : Old Ruffian'^ thou (halt dyes In thee Til punifh the whole Mutiny. Lhc, I faw my General about to blaftj By one rafh aft^ his life and Glories paft. Th' unconftant Rabble to my fide I gain'd^ And fpight of him^ his Honor have maintain d>. Af7to» What art thou? Lac. A Roman. Anto. No more? Luc. In Brutus Camp fome fmall Command I bore: Subdued by Arms^ fince by your kindnefs won^ I am refolv*d your utmoft fate to run. If my late fervice grieve you, take my heads- The common path of Love 1 never tread. Brntus-) to fave my felf, like him I fbap't 5 So fell I in your hands, and he efcap't. Anto. Lucilius? Lucilius^ The fame my Int'reft command^ Antonius fhall both rule my heart and hand. Anto. Difchargethe Rabble you haveus'd in this. \^The/JljoHti Luc, They humbly fue youll pardon what's amifs. They are return'd^ and now with (liouts of joy 5 They beg you woud their Swords and Lives imploy. Anto. Moft willingly, juft Heaven, what am I5 Whom the rude People^ teach Humanity? \^Ex-^ ACT
Page 32

92 Scene the firft. C(zfars Tents, Enter C£far^ j4grjppa^ Mec(BnaS' €£far:, A/f Y Offers fcornd! AmbafTadors abus'd! iVl Yet he of Pride unjuftly is accus'd. Mec, rAjre;^ was ill chofc;, he long has been A fecret Servant to th* ^Egyptian Queen. What if I went with terms more moderate 3 1 5 who am lefs Obnoxius to his hate. C^f This Offer now the danger grows fo near. In a man left known, fhoud take for fear. j^grip. His Infolence no longer I defend. C£f Sec here the Challenge he thinks fit to fend. [Jgrip steads. j^grip. In fingle Combat let our Fencers fight; With Armies, Emperors dilpute their right. C^f Like him, I Roman blood would gladly (pare. And to a Combat would contraft the War. My youth, and unfoil'd flrength, may Conqueft claim Over this Shadow of a mighty Name ; Now prefl with Age, and with Debauches worn^ Th* unequal Combat I not fear, but (corn. Agrjp. He like an aged Oak in Autumn (hows. From whofe dry Arms fome Leaves each minute blows 5 One King or Ally, ftill forfake his fide, HisEmpire ebbs like a declining Tide. Have patience. Sir, he of himfelf muk fall. Who in defpair does for the Combat call. C(ef To a brave Death Til open him the way 5 See an AfTault be made without delay. I at my Armies head fhall foon appear, And if he xlares^ he may engage me there. Enter oUavia, Offav^ O Brother ! if that namehave yet a PowV? And be not loft in that of Emperor ; Pity
Page 33

j^ntonj Sind Cleopatra. Pity my fad eftatCj fince I alone On both fides mourning, can rejoyce on none. The World divided in their wifhes ftand 5 My felf alone ftab'd through on every hand. A Brother here! There muft a Husband fall 5 On thejuftGodsI know not how to call! No chance of War can with my mind comply 5 But I muft weep at eithers Vidtory. C£f. It Iorcome-5 your Husband I will fpare. oSuv. He will not ^are himfelG I more than fear. Should he prevail, t\i Egyptim Qaeen will fway 3 Whom you, and I, and he, muft all obey. His am'rous heart muft execute her will. And whom (he frowns on, in Obedience kill. You to Ambition muft a Vi£iim bleed,! And from my hated Title to his bed, > Muft Cleopatra in my Death be freed 5 j And haughty Rome acknowledg a vain Queen, Or be of Civil Arms th' endlefs Scene. C^f! He doth all terms of Reconcilement flight : There nothing now remains but that we fight. He's now a meer foft Purple Af^an Prince 5 And Rome his Empire has difown'd long fince. Ocfav. Ingrateful Rome ! but moft ingrateful you I Can you forget whom C^^^ overthrew ? Who ^xfkto Rome a Tdrthianu'wimi^h. fhovv'd. And the long Pride of that great Empire bow'd ? Who the firft C<epr made, revenged his death. And fixt that Empire, which he did bequeath. On you almoft unknown ; Where they receive, Bafe Natures hate 5 and Love, but where they give. C^f. Goferveth' JEgyptian^ learn to drefsher bead Your flighted Love, and your neglefted Bed Can you forget 5 and fulfomely purfue The Man with kindnefs^ who defpifesyou? -\ I (hou'd my felf fcorn fawning Beauty too: y Tis asabfurdj as if the Gods (hou'd fue. 3 03, Wives (like good Subjefts, who to Tyrants bow) To Husbands though unjuft, long patience owe ;
Page 34

^4 Antony and Cleopatra. They were for Freedom made. Obedience We, Courage their vertue^ ours is Chaftity. Rv^afon itfelf in usmuft notbebold^ Nor decent Cuftom be by Wit controui'd. On our own heads we defperately ftray. And are ftillhappieft, the vulgar way. C£P .Whoever did fuch Moral Nonfence hear? My Sifter fure is turn'd Philofopher. But we Antontm Pride will foon pull down $ This hour (hall give me his whole lifes renown. I the long trade of Fame difdain to drive 5 3u. to the Top will at oneftep arrive. OCtav* Since then my pray rs and tears can nothing gain. In the Foes Camp no longer Til remain. The Armsl hatej my prefence (hall not grace 5 Antonius Caufelll openly embrace. To Rome Til go, and all thy afts difbwns '\ Make thy Ambition^ and thy Fallhood known S. To every Roman of the Sword and Gown^ 3 Till th' art more hated far than C^telim^ Then Scilla^ Marius^ or the tarqnins Line. Some will for Freedomj fome Antonius fights And againft Thee both parties PIl unite ^ Amongft thy Foes I like a Spark will fall. And to a fudden Flame convert em all. C£f You wou'd not fore my Love (b ill repay. oBa, Your Love ! your Pride and endlefi Thirft of fwajc To gain my friends, my Quarrel you pretend^ But universal Empire is your end. ^omes once great <y^»^/e now is but a names While fome with fear, and fome with Bribes you tame. Men learn at Court what they muft there repeat^ And for Concurrence, not for Council meet. At leaft all fuch as think of being great, 1 They blindly labour at their own ill fate, ^ And dig up by the roots the tottering State, j C^ef. AgdiuitA^te^ius Riots they declare. And I at their Command but v/age this War, OSa- Dull Long-gown Statefmen you raay^fcel tha t Sword . Which thus you whet againft my injured Lordc When
Page 35

Antony and Cleopatra. 55 When C£faf wills a Law? for all your rules. It will be better taught in Camps, than Schools^ C£j: Your fears diftfaft you^ or you needs ^muft feo Your hopes of happinefs depend on me. Tis my fuccefs muft make Antonius find The dire effeft of an unbridled mind. Off. Who ever did an Emperor reform ? Scarce Heav n it felf can that great Task performv C£f. Heaven choofes methefitteft inftrument. And on that glorious taskj m w holly bent. oS. 1st thus Mecmas^ you promote the Peace ? But you ne'r meantj and promife but to pleafe. Mec. All that I durft, I have already faid; I urg*d him till he thought I was afraid. But where fuch B eauty, and fuch Goodnefs fail 5 What other Interceffion can prevail 5 OU. Mecodnas^ I no Complements expeft From onej who does my firft Commands negled. Mec. Men that like me have giv'n their Paffions vent^ Are never after held indifferent. Hatred^ orLove, purfues the bold attempt ; It meets with a returnj or with contempt. I fear the latter is Mecanas lor. O^j I charge you^ never entertain me more With that falfeLove which hath fo little pow'r. Your breach of Wordj I eafily forgive, ^ I'm free, and am not now obliged to live :> {^shevpeept* Nor will I long, the firft attacq furvive. 3 Mec. A found like that, what Lover can indure? ril move once more, fhou'd I his hate procure. Ah Sir, your weeping Beautious*Sifter view 5 Then if you can, her Husbands life purfue : Such (bftnefs might an angry God difarm. And from his hand, the brandifht Thunder charm. Cdef. What means Mectsnas foftned in her tears > Another Man he to my eyes appears. Where is that Soul bids me be Abfolute^ And the diflenting World with Swords confute. Move forwards ftill, and fpread my ConquVmg Arms, As far as C//7f lights^ oxvhoehus warms, F 2 Mtc^
Page 36

Antony Cleopatra. Mec. I cnn no more, you your own Caufemuft pleads r I wou'dj but can't againft my felf perfwade 5 Tho unfuccefsful my endeavours were^ It was fome Merit to obey fo far. Enter Mejjinger* Mejf. The Enemy preventing our attacq. Does a fierce Sally on our Forces make. Our formoft Troops the warm ingagement fhun^ And to Canidius his Old Souldiers run. C£f Then be your Tent your Prifon for a while. \to O&avta. Now let us feize the Lyon in our Toil. — Ex - Onmes\ Scene the Second. A Wood. Enter Antomus^ Camdim-^ Vhotiaus^ at one door^ Agrippa^ Thy- reufy at the other^ Fighting. Antony. Turn back Thyreus 5 'tis Antonim cafls 5 The Queen now fees thee flying from our Walls,. Think on that fhamej and it muft warm thy heartj And do not from a fingle Rival ftart. Thyr. A Thought like that^ were all Mankind my Foes, Wou'd fend me headlong amongfl: all their Blows. Ant. He dies of Mine that dares to interpo(e. Thyr. Of Mine he is my bafeft Foe that does. C they fight^ Love^ thou at laft art juft^and having made (Thyr* falls* My Life a BurtheUj help'ft me to unlade : If he o'recome 5 Let Cleopatra know^ She muft to Rome in C^firs triumph go. So now my promife to the Queen is paid> The firft and !aft Command I ever had. Ant. Then all my Fears were falfe. ^ Thyr. Falfe as my hopes^ Or the (hort vigor which my Being props. The Qaeen was Gruel and thy Sword was Kind. Ant. Thou didft attempt her Villain : % thyr. Yes5 I did, And with my dying Breath I boaft the Deed. D/>/. Ant^ What words fit to appeafe her (hall I find ? Jeal6ufie
Page 37

Antony and Cleopatra. 57 Jealoufie for ever from my Soul remove^ Thou magnifying Glafs to erring Love , Thou Viper likej doft thy young Teeth employ. And wou'dft that Love^ which gave the Birch, deftroy. Enter Cxfar and Mecoenas. C£f Charge you Canidius with your Troops^ whirft I Againft Antonius felf my Fortune try. Here is the utmoft bound of thy fuccefs^ The Ocean may as foon his limits pafi. As thou this Ipot of Earth whereon we ftand. ^ Ant. You (peak as you had Thunder in your hand, > The Gods I Heaven ! Hell and Fate at your command-,) Which if thou hadft I'd not one ftep retire : But one by one^ their Prodigies wou'd tire. QCsefar beaten back* Enter Mejjenger- MeJJ^ You muft not ftay your fortune to purfiiej Agrippas got between the Town and you 5 Which Stratagem when Cleopatra found. She Sally'd out, and is incompaft round. Vhotinus ftays behind to awe the Town, And keeps thofe of the pop'lar Faction down. Ant» My Queen ingag'd ! To her relief lets fly^ Death has more Charms near her, than Viftory, Me in her Caufe, the Legions that withftand, Muft fall like Corn^ before the Reapers Hand. Can. Muft we again a Viftory forgo 5 This Qiieen was born to be our Overthrow. Ant. What is't you mutter ? Follow me or dy« Can. My Life you'd fooner want behalf than I: Take it, for 'tis to me an hourly pain, Follies of Friends are nothing to the flain. But whirft I live, methinks you fhou*d purfue^ Retiring Foes and Viftory in view. Ant^ I cannot ftoop to argue, but Obey 3 And till my Queen be fafe, let Conqueft ftay, Scens;
Page 38

Antony and Cleopatra. Scene the Third. A Wood. QHe difcovers AgrippaV Army'^ and the ^een taksn. Ant. By Hercules fhe's tane I So have I feen the Dove, Under the Pounce of eager Falcons move : O ! that I were my felf the Dart I throw. For now, all other Motion feems too flow* QAnt. refines the ^een^ Charges through Agrippa s Army. Agrip. Retreats to the Town. Augures and Entrails, Boys and Quails you ly ! And I henceforth your Omens will defy. Caird by his Name, may fuch ftill profp'rous be. While thus the Gods give Viftory to Me. \jB.xeHnt. Enter Pbotinus as within the Town, phot. They are ingag*d by this : now is the Time> And all things feem propitious to my Crime. Let Fools the Fame of Loyalty divide 5 Wife men and Gods are on the ftrongeft fide. The Town is wholly left to my Command, To make 'em rife I need but flack my hand : They'r prone to Mutiny. Their Queen they hate. And (hew all figns of a diftemper'd State. C^^y But hark already they are up and roar. Like an high Sea that (corns its wonted Shoar. - Enter Iras. But fee fair Iras whofe bright form in Tears, Like Sun-(hine mixt with fudden Rain appears. Iras. Thotinus \ Oh the Queen ! The Queen is gone. And we that (lay behind are all undone. The Pallace flames ^ Memnon and Chilax rage. And all the Egyptians on their fide engage. rhot. Fear nothing Madam, never was a time. When Innocence and Beauty were a Crime : Each (hout you hear, your Greatnefs does advance : Nor is this Mutiny, th' effeft of Chance. But my defign Through
Page 39

Antony and Cleopatra. Through Craggy ways we for a while muft tread : But gentle Iras to a Throne they lead : Ah ! Cou'd I make you Kind as well as Great, Thotinus happinefs were then compleat. Iras. All other Forms Fie ftudy to forget : And think how much I 'm to your Love in Debt : AntiUm is a young gay handfome Man, Yet to pleafe you, I'le hate him if I can. He ftill like you lies Cjueezing of my hand, Han^s o're my Neck^ and from me will not ftand. Vhot. Ye Gods f She loves and knows not yet difguife \ The happy Name, fla(ht at her youthful Eyes. IrJLs. The Manly Gown when he did firfk put on. He was more gaz'd at than C£farion : But for all that I will not love him tho^j Tis fo long fince I have forgot him now » . . . ?hot. Our Serpents though new born are poyfonous ftill? And Women ne'r fo young have Craft and Guile. She has forgot him ! Oh that I cou'd Her ! Too plain, but yet too ftrong I fee the fnarco I got my Rival to Armenia fent. His Name returns and ruins my contents Iras. You feem difturb'd — Thot. Falfe and inhumane .... Iras. What are you mad ? What is it I have done.! What have T faid ? Thot. Thou haft for ever rob'd me of my reft. Iras. By all my hopes to reign I love you beft. vhot. Ay there's your love to me. But that for him how ill you do contain ? Iras. For whom ? I underftand you not, be plain. Thot. Why for Antillus } Your young Gay Delight, Iras. May I not name, but I muft love him ftraight ? Fbot. The Works foon done with Wind and Tide they moves Whom equal Years and Thought.*" difpofe to love.. And to fay truth I ftand condemned v^^ithin. That I did ever an Addrefs bes;in To you, whom Beauty and fuch Youth adorn : I prefl with Age, for Toil, not Pleafure born : > And every way the Objeft of your Scorn. ,V
Page 40

4o Antony and Cleopatra. Go to Afjtilluf ! Fly into his Arms, And meet with equal heat and equal Charms, Whilft my ambition I henceforth purfue. And recompence thofe Joys I lofe in you. Iras. He wou'd not have me if I wou'd^ I fear, He s great and may expeft a Kingdoms Heir. rhot. She fears he wou'd not have her . . . Oh juft Heaven ! I to the lafl: extremity am driven. She1 ask me fure anon to joyn their hands. Ivits. All thoughts of me your felf you have refign'dj And 1 may now to whom I pleafe be kind. Vhot. All thoughts of you 1 I cou'd refign my breath With half the pain .... Irus. Some other Maid you purpofe to make Qiieen, And I but flatter'dj and abus'd, have been. rhot. My Love, a fierce Convulfion did endure^ And in the pain I talkt I know not what 5 But reft for ever of that heart fecure^ Where too much Love did the Ihort ftorm create. Enter a Servant. Serv. The Caftle is befetj and all have vowM, To ftain their Weapons in your treacherous blood. rhot. Step in a while: They that will rifemuft wait? And at each Throw affift their laboring fate. [Ex. Iras, Let 'em all enter, no refiftance make^ I can die gladly for my Country's fake* Enter Memnon and Chilax with the RaUle. What is't my honeft Countrymen demand ? You need not ask with weapons in your hand. Me;^n. Thou haft thy Country to a lafting War betray 'd chil. And therefore for thy death prepare. phot. Who ! I ! alas I but my Queen obey'd^ And both were of Antonius pow'r atraid. Like you I wifht an opportunity When EQypt was from Komm Forces free: That
Page 41

Antony and Cleopatra. That we might then with C^far make our peace. CkiL Now Fate prefentsit, this occafion^leize. In our Queens abfence you the Town command 5 Eg^pt requires her Freedom at your hand. Mc//w. The City Gates againft Antomtfs fliutj So thou wilt put thy meaning out of doubt. Pkot. But then our Qiieen MemtJ. She is Antonius Slave, And merits amongft us nor Throne nor Grave 5 This once performed, be thou our General, If not, like a fa'nt Slave unpitied fall— [Ofers to rnn at km. Phot, ri do unforc't what ever you require. But now you bind me to my own defire 5 I ever thought Antenms Caufe unbleft, I did his Riot loath and Loves deteft; So we did all I think : and 'twere unjuft. We fhou'd defend, whoftill abhorr'd hisluft. Let Pimps and Paiafites his Battels fight. Buffoons, andloofe Companions of the night, Male-Bawds, and let that goatilh drunken Herd Which made him odious, die, to make him fear'd. Memn, Antonius now (at Rorrie) defpaiis of all. And feeks to crufh our Eg)p with his fall 5 But he (hall find that fome of us ftill wake, Who nothing fear, and all dare undertake. ChH. Let's man the Town with all the Force we havcj Keep out Antonius^ and our Country {ave ; C^far will hold us Enemies no more, But call in Friends and Allyes as before. Memn. For us the people do in throngs declare, Tir'd with the danger and the charge of War. Phct. Vm brav'd here by Canidim at each turn. And v/ith revenge and rage like you Lburn : The mighty Charge I greedily accept 5 Your Town (hall be with Faith and Courage kept. In your dilgrace, believe I had no part. But honour'd your free Tongue and honeft Heart. Memn. How we were all raiftarken in this man } Exetm. G Scene
Page 42

42 Antony and Cleopatra. Scene the Fourth. The Gates beina (hut. Ef7fer Antonius, Cleopatra, Canidius, a^d Atteridafiis. Anto. How well my Queen doth this one aft reprove My needlefi Jealoufie, and (hew your Love ? deep. Her ! whom you not efteem, why w^ou d you (ave But tho unjuft, Arjtomus ftill is brave. Ant. I not efteem you ! by the Gods I do As much as Love Chop. No my AMomml No ! You think me all that can a Queen di%race, Lighter than Woman, and than Man more bafe. How cou d I elfe forfake you in diftrefs ? Or could Thynus in a moment pleafe. Anto. It was the raging Feaver of my Love, And ftrongeft Natures, ftrong Diftempers prove v Forgive it Madam, as my Loves excefs. Chop. Had C^Jir (u'd, I had his flame difdaind^ And cou d you think another entertain'd ? When the whole World (hall to his Fortune yield, My Heart againft your Foe ihall keep the Field. Anto. On me fo thick your obligations fall, I muft fubdue that World to pay em all. And make proud Ronn acknowledge you her Queen 5^ Your Glory does demand no lefi a Scene. Canid. Tis very fine, here's all the Senfe he has ! His Legions, Empire, all are in that face! I do not think he knows he is befieg'd, But quite undone, talks how he is obliged ! Pray, Sir, do you confider where we are, If we ftay long we (hall have C^J^r here. Ant. Were he in light Td not one word forbear Till I did guiltleC to my Queen appear. Th)reus dying Cleof. Have you kill'd him then I {hall be hateful to the Race of men. To CU^fatra it is d$ath to fpeak :.
Page 43

Antony and Cleopatra. On him (he loves, (he a (wift War does call. And thofe (he looks on, by Antonius fall. Anto, He cleared your Vertue with his dying Breath. Cko^. You ftain'd it in the manner of his death. Anto. Lovers like Mifeis cannot bear the ftealth Of the leaft trifle from their endlefs wealth. J faw him ki(s your hand, for that he dy'd ; And ftiou d had he Ten Thouftnd lives befide. You feem not pleased with my revenge enough. Cko^. It was too rafh, and for his crime too rough. Anto, T' attempt the Ipotlefs Honor of my Queen, Is fuch a Crime, as it is death to mean. Cko^. He £hou d have liv'd, if that he lov'd indeed. My Scorn all other Torments might exceed : His life had been but one continued pain, And mine but one long hSi of my difdain : But now all means to clear my ftlf are loft ^ You can but think me innocent at moft. Anto. I fiom that Viper (uch an Oyl have wrung,^ As heals that Love which he before had ftung : Since from a dying Rival's mouth I hear, His hope was as ill grounded as my fear : He caird you moft Ingrateful as he dy'd 5 Confe(s*d his Paflion, and accus'd your Pride : What ftronger demonftration can be thought > Cko^. Could nothing I might (ay, the like have wror Then vain is all Fve fuffer'd, and have done : My flighted FamiC, and my endangered Throne, Can nothing weigh 5 and 'tv/as ihyrms grace, That I was cleared ! Antomus held me baft. Anto. O (ay not fo ! My Lov^of its own ftrength Had overcome that jealoufie at length : To him indeed I owe my (pcedy Cure. Cko^. Are you for ever from relapfe (ecure .> Anto. I rather will believe all that is ftrange. The whole Sex true, than that my Queen can chan-
Page 44

^^^^^^mtol^nd Cleopatra. Efttcr Soiildhr from tie Towtf, Siiuld, The Town is loft, yonx Romarfs kiirdcr,fled, And klik Phot'njus does the Traytor h^ad ; Mcmvcn and Chiltx in bright Arms appear, And for OBdvws C^far all declatc Anto. Canid, appear with their Arwy un-^ der the Walls avd find oppofttion^ fome' that go near are lqU\d. Anto, Tr'calbn before, and Enemies behind 5.. In fuch a choice 'twere equal to be blind. I know not which I (hou*d attacque the firft 5 I m only lure of all : Delay's the worft. Storm then the Town with all that we can make EVe C£far fee, and this advantage take. Safe at a diftance here my Queen muft ftay, ^.Charge While we with blood and (laughter force ouc way. iwithont, [Thej are beat off'. Canid. It is in vain, theft BarbVous Villains dare Not hope for the fair Quarter of a War 5 And are turn'd defperate.. Anto. We are alike,, E)efperate with them, When for the whole both Parties ftrike, Courage muft carry't, Char j them once agen. . [Charge. - [Skout.: Scene the Fitch, The Gates drawn open. A Jlmit from the Tovcn^ Photinus is attaoqned from behind. Antonius Enters. Anto. QPare on your Lives th* unarmed and meaner fort^ OAnd all who to Our Clemency refort. This eafie entrance to fome Friend owe • Ws from within came pouring on the Foe*. Canid. They arc no Tfaytors till they kill our rnefij And thea as vanquifli't muft be fpar*d agen. AMt04-.
Page 45

Antony and Cleopatra. A*ito. They're Ckop.itra*$S\.\h]^Sti \ let tliat be A full Proidtion in our Viftory. £;//er Lucilius m/Y/j Photinus, Memnon, and Chilax Pr 'ij'c Lucil. Health to Antonms^ in whofe Cau(e to fight Is lefs LuciUns duty than delight. Take from my hand your treacherous Enemies, And ufe 'em as your Safety (hall adviie. M^mn. Traitor's a nam.e my Vertue cannot brook ^ How cou d I break a Truft I never took ? Anto. Armes 'gainft your Lawful Queen are ftill un^uftj A Subjeft born betrays a Native truft. But thou Photwns beyond Villains bafe, Whom with her Truft and FriendQiip ftie did grace ^ Whom Birth and Fortune both hid laid fo low, . To raile thee up again (he fcarce knew how 5 Only rafli Favour, whofe extravagance Seems yet a blinder Power than that of ChancCj . Remained thy Friend-— Phot. I do confefs, my Queen From nothing made me all that I have been 5 And much I to A>7to^nu<f favour owe, Whom then (hould I depend on but you two? Aftto. We two ! whom thou didft (hut the Tov/n againf And to whom now thou but repentance feign'ft. Phot. From this (editions Rout what cou'd I gain ? I might not hope in Cleopatra s reign : Weigh then my Int'reft, by that Scak youl find My Crime, though great, lay never in my mind :. . I (hou'd have dy'd, I know, I wifli I had. Rather than feem'd to have my Truft betray *d : I fliou'd have cha(e their Dagger, (corn'd their fide 5 It had been paft, and I had nobly dy'd. Chrl. O that thou hadft ! I would have driv n it home. Till forth with the broad p3int thy Soul had come. Phot. Death I have often met in open field, With my Sword fent, repell'd him v/ith my Shield : Surpriz'd, dcfencelefs I I confefs I (hook. And cou d not in cold blood his vifage brook .
Page 46

4^ Antony and Cleopatra. Twas all my Crime ! you Romam only can Serenely and unfliaken, put off man. We might have known that Party needs muft fall, Who to his own fear, owe their General. Pkot. Kill me I alas ! I do not ask to live ! Shou'd you, I never cou d my (elf forgive. Death to my fear is .due, why fhou'd I plead ? I was no Traytor, I was worfe, afraid : Love, Faith, and Zeal, if Refolution fail, No more than the faint Glow-worm's Fire avail. . All that I now repent, is that with fhame I lofe that Life, I might have loft with Fame. Af7to. How cam'ft thou to appear in open Arms, For thy black Soul has Treachery fuch Charms > Pht. Had I not been their General I had dy'd. Death turn'd the Scale, and fb I took their fide. Befides, I for your Service thought it beft, I ftiou d with them maintain my Intereft 3 That at fbme time unlook't for you might j[ee The good intent of (eeming Treachery. What greater Bleffing can your Arms attend, Than t' have your Foes, commanded by your Friend } I early of Ludlh/s projeft knew. And from the neighboring parts my Arms withdrew, That he a Body might of Rowans form. The great exploit fecurely to perform. Anto. Tis poffible thou mayft be honefl: ! yet 'twere ftrange^ Men ftill were doubted, who but feem to change. But (ay ! how came this Tumult to begin ? Phot. The people long have di(contented been, Curft me aloud, and murmur'd at the Queen 5 That to your fide fo firmly we adher'd. And to their Common Peace your Cau(e preferr'd 5 They faid they wou'd not be the Vigor's prey 5^ But whom they muft at laft, betimes obey : S. And ruine all who flop't em in their way. b Anto. Where were the Souldiers ? Phot. When Qie fally'd forth — None ftay'd, who lov'd the Queen or Martial Worth 3 But
Page 47

Antony and Cleoptra. 47 But all the Difcontents remain d behind, And had efFefted what they long defign'd, Had not thofe Powers that Treachery prevent. To your relief the brave Lncilim (ent ; He in the Town a Band of Romans got. And overthrew the Rebels and their Plot. Anto, You then are none of 'em — Phot. I was by force ; But Lucnce ne're cou d hate vile Tarquin worfe, Than I theft Forcers of my Loyalty- — [Points to the Lords* And like her too f fince not believ'd) Tl dye. Memn. You durft not dye by an Egyptian Sword : What is*t this (udden Courage does afford > Phot. I was no Villain thought, but now I hate My Life, and cou*d rufli gladly on my fete 5 And you repent — Chil. That e're we trufted thee Slave f more uncertain than a Winters Sea. Anto. I will believe Death fhook thy Loyalty^ And all thou didft was Fear, not Treachery i Photinus rile ! thy frailty I forgive. [RffeSi And if thou cari'ft or dar'ft thus branded, live $ But never more a weighty Charge receive. Phot. I wou'd live gladly to redeem my Crime 3 Tis all the benefit I ask of Time. Anto. But you Fierce Lords that dare your Severaign baime. And would depoft, or govern in Her name, Shall find what 'tis to play with Royalty 5 And fall like Phaeton from the borrow'd Skte. Chil. We (corn thy Mercy, and our Country lovCj And gladly from her dying Cries remove. The
Page 48

Jntonji and Cleoptm ACT. V. Scene the Firft. The Palace. Enter Antonius, Cleopatra, Charmion, Iras, and Atlcndarjti. Ckop. TT'Ortune s afrefh fond of Afitomus grown, JP And has this Minute her old Love put on 5 She calls her wonted Charms into her Face,] And hugs him — ..y With the fierceardor of a fii ft embrace. J Atito. Of this fuccefs, wh^n they 2itRome Ihall hear,! They'l change; perhaps their Superstitious fearj \> And the ill Om€?2s on my Foe transfer. j His will the Owl bethought, unchas'd away, Which upon Concord's Temple braves the day. The Ape in Ceres Temple will be His, And his defeat the Eight-foot-Dragon hiis. The blood my Statue fhed, will his be thought 5 So are weak minds by Superftition wrought. Chop. What we can't fhun, 'twere better not to know, Nor do the Gods malicioufly forefliow, . To make us feel our Fate before it come 3 But men too nicely pry into their doom. Ante, Let it fall quick whatever they prepare. It is the Thunders voice, we cannot bear 5 Blind to our Fate, let us both hope and fear ; But thou L;/d/;///, who do'ft ftill outrun All that we can expedi: or wifli were done 5 Like fome kind God thou leap'ft into the Scale And tjurn'ft it when all Mortals feem to fail. Take from my hand this Armor of clear Gold. jLct the beft Metal the beft man enfold. hidL Me dead or living you anon (ball praife.
Page 49

Antony and Cleopatra. 49 E^ter Mejjenger. Mejf, With his whole Force Odfavius^ Sir, moves on 5 'Tis thought on every part he'l ftorm the Town. Anto, His late defeat then flings the refllefi Boy 3 And all at once we fhall our Swords imploy. Let us embrace, then each man to his Poft : Wei meet no more but Conquerors or Ghofts. The World's at flake, my Queen, and this ftiort hour Contains the Fate of all (ucceeding Pow r. If this one day we can our Fate defer, To morrow's Sun will (be Ventidius here : Viftorious Legions to my Aid he brings 5 Flefh't all in Parthian Blood and fpoiles of Kings. [Ex, Anto. Canid. Lucil 'EnUr Photinus at amther Door. Chop. My boading Heart fayes we (hall meet no more^ And (ends up thoughts I never knew before. My Ears with di(mal dying cryes are fiird. And my Eyes grow with ghaflly Vifions wild 5 Methinks I fee Antonius bleeding there, And all his Souldiers pale with Death or Fear. Charm, Your wounded Fancy does the(e forms create, Expeft as you de(erve, a better Fate. Ckep. O that betimes he had my Cau(e for(bo k! C<Bpir with pity on a Queen muft look, Defencele(s too. Winds unopposed give ore. And but 'mongft Trees and (olid Buildings roar. The Romans againfl me declared the War, But caught Antonius Vertue in that (hare. • Phot. When two fierce Bulls contend, the doubtful Herd Stand gazing by a while, of both afear'd : But (bon as one the fatal flrife declines. The Captive number with the Viftor joyns. And (b (hould we- — Cleop. Yes ! if meer Brutes wc were — And knew no Nobler Pafl[ion than vile Fear 5 H Minutes
Page 50

50 ^ Antony and Cleopatra. Minutes move (lowly when fuch weight they bear. Each now is more important than a year : I grow impatient, can bear no delay. But quickning Fate would through the (hell (urvey. Char, The ftrongeft place, and neareft is your Tomb 5 Hear good news foon, the bad too foon will come. Be patient Madam—— / - v ' Cleop. Who compos'd can be? A Tempeft heard and their whole Wealth at Sea ? Each Pile that flies may pierce Af7tomHs Heart 5 And they in fhowrs from meeting Romans part. Let us move on, no matter where you lead A breaking Heart, and a diftemper'd Head. [Noife of Arms. Ex. Cleop, Charmw Phot. Clafiiing of Arms I heard, and noife of Drums, Nearer and nearer the fierce Clangor comes. [Photinus Jieals off unfeen^ Enter Antonius, Canidius, Lucilius, as beaten hach^ into the Town. Anto. Gape Hell, and to thy difmal Bottom take The loft Antonius '-^ this was our laft Stake 5 Warn'd by my ruine, let no Roman more Set Foot on this inhofpitable fhoar. Cowards and Traytors fill this impious Land 3 Faithlefs and fearful, without Heart or Hand. Some ran to C^far like an headlong Tyde, . The reft their fear made ufelefs on our fide. Canid. Their Fear ! their Treachery ! we are betrai'd o : By Hands we .truft the fureft Snares are laid. The Queen, no doubt, does correfpondence hold With Rome and C^far^ and we all are fold. AntG. I had but one glad thought within my breft^^ And thou to that one thought, wilt give no reft» Fortune hath (eiz'd my Empire and Renown 3 Honeft Old Souldier, let my Love alone : But you my generous Friends to C£far go, Too much already to your Love I owe : Let me now fink alone 3 enough y'have done t Afalling Tow r 'twere madneft not to fhuno . S>ur?:
Page 51

Antony and Cleopatra. 51 Your guilt is (mall, let early penitence. Your Ties and Love to me plead your defence* LuciL No Sun (hall fte me living after you 5 My Death fhall tell you that my Life was true. Camd. For what fliould I my bending years preferve ? Camdius will no (econd Matter ferve. Jhout without Enter a Mejfenger. Mejf, Your Navy, Sir, is joyn'd with C^efars Fleets And with one^voice their Emperor they greet. Both fides their bloody hatred have laid down. And in one Body row toward the Tov/n. Canid. Sir, with Egyptians it was chiefly mann'd, And is there yet no dealing underhand ? Still does the Queen fb innocent appear 5 Her people guilty, fhe alone is clear. Anto. Her peoples Love, her Love to me has loft 5 And now her Faith, is by their Trealbn cros't. Pity, not blame the Queen, who finks this hour, Crulh't with the ruines of an Emperor. By Land and Sea betray 'd ! what fhall we do ? Canid. Let's fight and die in Arms upon the Foe. > Anto. We of refiftance fcarce can make a fhoe. 3 Death fhuns the naked Throat and profFer'd Breft $ He flies when calFd, to be a welcome Gueft. I may be tane alive, and made a fcorn, x ^ Where I have oft the higheft Honours worn. Rome never fliall my conquered Face behold : Death I have feiz'd, and will not lofe my hold, [^Shout again. Enter, Souldier. Sould. C£far is entred, and we all are^loft 5 Some Roman Souidiers ftill make good t^eir Poft., Their number (peak.; > Sould. Two Legions at the moft. Anto. Command eni to ykl4x^a(^e ^i^oxy r Their number is ^^^jf bLr/orf} I bsbno Too (mall to cojiqti€ri, .and:to(^great to aye. ^ ' H 2 Canid*
Page 52

5^ Antony and Cleoptra. Canid. What means our Emperor ? Anio, To Ipaie your Blood : Too long you have my angry Fate withfto.od. What is Command, for which we fo contend ? ] Danger and Envy the High Charge attend : A fevv^ we plea(e, and Multitudes offend. j ^ , ^, [Canid. Lajnd, Thou art a Coward, fled'ft before thy time. And with pretence of News woud'ft hide thy Crime. 'Tis filfe. Sould. So it were falfe indeed, Fd gladly die 5 But this lhall (hov/ I did not bafely flie. [Kills himfdfl Writer Photinus. Phot, Horror on horror ! Sir, th' unhappy Queen Betrayed by a Report that you were flain ! Anto. I underftand you, (he her felf has kiird5 And better knew to die, than how to vield. Phot. Alas ! llie has, I puird the reaking Steel From her warm Wound, and with it rufli't her life— — Her lateft breath was bufie with your name. And the fweet pledges of your mutual flame : Your Children (he embrac't, and then {he dy'd. Anto, How well had I been with great Julius flain^ Or by fome flying Parthians darted Cane. Thy gentle Nature, Brutus^ how I hate, Through which I live to tafte the dregs of Fate. Such is the gloomy ftate of Mortals here 5 . We knew not what to wifli, or what to fear : My Name in Arms, my Friends and Empire gone. Yet while fhe liv'd, I was not quite undone : Methought I ftill had fbmething to do here — Camd, Y'have more than ever. Sir : your Souldiers chear^ And bid 'em for a bold defence prepare. A^to. Never : let Romarts now each other love, Their tedious quarrel I will foon remove. 'Twice has my Sword with Roman Blood been dy'd 5 It draws no more, but from Antonius fide. Had the juft Gods intended I fhould live, To hcite my life, fuch caufe they vi^ou d not giv^* * They
Page 53

Antony and Cleopatra. They Had prefeiv'd my Empire and my Qiieen. Enough and more, I have both Fortunes feen. Strike good Lnciliiis 3 Tis a friendly part ; Let no Foes weapon pierce thy Mafters Heart. 'LmcxX, goes behind^ makes as if he rvoiild hjll him^ hut gaffes the Weapon through his oxen Body. The Nobleft way : thou fhow'ft me what to do. Thou giv'ft th' Example, and Fie give the blow. [Antonius hills himfelf. Phot, rie call fome help great Jlorjek is giren at his^all. But 'twill but incieafe my ip^iu':) ia// run offtoj the room except Fhou For fhouIdTt thou ftir, Vd ftab my felf again. Canid. Let others figh and weep, but let us go rphot. makes towards And vent our grief, in rage upon the Foe. Jth door. Anto. jtahs From the ftrange horror of that dilmal fight, jhimfdf again and Cowards would rulh into the midft of fight, fjdls. Phot, nmers. Anto. Let Cowards crowd to force refign their breath. Brave Minds look through it, and mske ufe of Death. Thou can'ft not now my fatal Journey ftay. Phot. Nor wou'd I, Sir, you r fairly on your way. Anto. Death (bon will place me out of Fortunes reach 5 Why ftayes my Soul to fally at this breach } Phot. It is not big enough. Anto. Do'ft mock me now ?- Can my few Minutes a new Torture know- — Phot. They may, and to provoke thy parting Soul^ Know that the Queen yet lives, thou loving Fool, And I the Story of her Death contrived, To make thee kill thy (elf, which has arrived Juft as I wifli't 5 by thy own hand thou dy'fl:, And art at once the Viftim and the Prieft. Anto, Furies and Hell — Phot. Curft on 5 but Ccefar fhall With Egypts Scepter thank me for thy fall." Though decently he cou d not take thy Headj He'l inwardly rejoyce to find thee dead 3 And hug the man that eas'd him from the fear Of fuch a Rival, yet his guilt did fpare. - 'Ant0. 53
Page 54

^Mony ana uieofatra. Auto, Thou mak'ft me hate by turns my Life and Death I 0 for a moments ftrength! my Sword to (heath In thy falft Heart — But 'twill not be, my hand forfikes my Will 5 Only himfelf can poor Antonius kill. Phot, 'Coud you have liv'd, I had ftem'd honefl: ftill^ But now take all 5 the Queen her felf muft Bleed 3 Jras and I muft to her Throne Succeed. Thy Councills ftill to C£far I betray 'd. This laft revolt I in thy Nai^y made. AfJto. Triumphant Villain! What provok't thee to't. Phot, Ambition Sir, I had no Armies 1 5 Nor was I born of Royal Progeny. No Crown defended on my Lazy Head, "j 1 cou'd no open path to greatnefs tread : > But none defpis'd that to a Throne did Lead.J AfJto, All Charmon (aid of Thee it fiems was true^ Phot, And all Camdim ere fufpefted too. I have difcharg'd my Confcience at this Laft. — Dy thou. Whilft I to/r^^.and a Throne make haft. [Ex. Phot. Enter Charmion, Iras, and Attendants. Charm, The Qiieen Entreats At?to, Does my Qiieen Live, and may Antonius yet, Above the Earth his Cleopatra Meet. Charm, She lives, but (hut up in her MonumiCnt^ Her rowling Thoughts on fbme dire Mifchief bent. By Ifis Temple, Sir, you know it Stands 5 The'flareft Fabrick made by Mortal hands. All fhe holds dear (he has throng d there, but you, And now intreats that yovi will enter too. Anto, With thofe we love, a Triumph 'tis to fall 3 Moft gladly I obey her &tal Call. Charm, juft Heaven's ! you faint, what is it you have done, That with fuch Streams thefe Living Fountains run ? Anto, It was a fudden qualm : Limbs do but bear Me to My Queen and Tl diffnifs you there:. I cannot dy till I have paid that Debt. - V ^ . , Nor have our Souls appointed where to Meet. J, . . . Stand off my Fate, and dare not touch me yet.J^ - ■ l^rm/
Page 55

Antony and Cleopatra. 5; ^ Cham* Secure from C£far you a while may bej And there what's fitted to be done Decree. lAjImtt. The place. Ar2to. The Viftory comes on, I hear the Nolle, And of prevaihng Foes th'infialting Voyce. C£far to {pare me did ftrickt Order give, ^[ I may be taken and compeird to live 5 •> Move on, all Fates but that I can forgive. J Exeunt, Enter Caviar, Agrippa, Mecoenas, and Souldiers. Mec, Sir, y'are entirely Mafter of the Town 5"] All men their Hatred and their Amies lay down, y And the whole Wo; Id now bends to you alone. J Agvsp, The names of Parties and of Faftions ceafe, And War has brought forth her fair Daughter Peace* C^f Command the Souldiers Fury be reftrain'd. That Rage deftroy not what their Virtue gain'd. Th' Egyptians now my Clemency (hall fhare ^ I would be lov'd in Peace, though Fear d in War. In this Confufion wher's the haughty Queen ? Mec, Since firft we entred, She no more w^as feen. Enter Photinus with a Sword. Phot. Great C£far at my hands that Sword receive. Which his Deaths Wound did to Anton'ws give. C^ f. Thou haft not kilFd him Villain ! quickly fpeak. Thy Limbs upon a Thoufand Racks Fl break. To find the Truth— Phot. He is not Dead, but long he cannot Live y, And his own Arm the Fatal blow did give. By my advice indeed—— C£jC 'By thy advice— - Thus Ro/^/e by Egypt is defeated twice. Thou haft the pow'r of pardoning fmVm.e tane^. And empty Wifhes now alone remain. Each Man will think what he himfelf had done^ And my great mind interpret by his own. Hence from my fight ! fince blaftedis by Thee TJhe faireft Fruit of all my Vifitory. Ph Of.
Page 56

5 6 Antony and Cleopatra. Phot. I wirti Antonim blood were yet unfpilt 5 But Yours is the advantage, Mine the guilt. Empire and Glory can no Partners bear. Since you forgive your Foes excufe my care, C^/t Where is the Queen ? Phot, Fled to -the Monument: Which for her laft Retreat (he ever meant. Where (he has all the Jewels of the Crown, And the Chief Wealth of th' diftrafted Town. There great Antomus Bleeding in her Armes, Takes liis laft Leave of her deflruftive Charmes. Give me Two hundred Men within an houre. They (hall alive or dead be in Your pow'r. Thou Monfter of all Villany forbear 5 Thou woud'ft thy Gods from off their Altars tear. Who woud 'ft not thy Afflifted Sov'raign (pare. Agrif, Men fay (he is Generous, if fb our Force Will only drive her on fome defp'rate Courfe. If Honourable Terms we fhould refu(e. We (hall her Perfon and her Trcafure lofe. She'l both Convert into one fpreading Flame, And (hortning hated Life extend her Fame. Mcc. A Roman Mind can only Death command 5 Fear no fiich Courage from a Barbarous Hand ! '\ Efjter a Servant. Serv. OdazMjS'iY — C£f, Poor Soul ! I pity Her, She ill the news will of Antonius bear. She's paft all human Grief and human Care. C^f. She is not dead. Serv. Yes, in her way to Rome^ Of grief and difcontent, as we prefiime. Cd'.f. Ye joyes of Viftory a while forbear, I muil: on my OStav'ja drop a tear. She was the beft of Women, Gentleft Wife, In every part how vertuous v/as her life ! Mec. From out the Chriftal Palace of her Breft,"] Her clearer Soul is gone to endlefs reft. ^ What time, what reafon can my lois digeft > J Enter
Page 57

Antony and Cleopatnt Efiter yieffevger. Mejf. Canidim ftill does an old fort defend. C£f. On every fpark of War we mud attend. True Wifdom will no Enemy defpife : From fmall beginnings mighty Flames arife. Etiter Canidius with his Souldiers. Canid. Thus the lafl: Sword for Liberty I draw, And whom Defpair thrufts on no numbers awe. Who knows But that thofe nobler Souls of Ancient Rome May ftrike with us 'gainft flavery to come. Vj2ter C^^fir with hk SguJdiers. Cdef I charge you all the brave Canidius (pare, ^ Let not his Blood now (lain the ended War ; j, His number fpeaks not terror, but defpair. J [Canid. is beaten off the Stage. [He re-enters. Canid. Fight but one Minute longer, whirfl: that I And fome few nobler Souls like Romans die. [They kill themfehes. Then may you all by C£fars mercy live, [The reji yields. Whirft we our Freedom from our Swords receive. C<ef What have I done ! that men had rather dye By their own hand, than truft my Clemency ? Meccen. Canidius to his Mafter was moft true, And did for him what I v/ou d do for you. Agrif, The World does no more Enemies contain, And C£far over peaceful Rome may raign. Ex, Omnes. Enter Antonius, Cleopatra, Charmion, and Iras in the Monument. Anto. Twas I that pull'd on you the hate ofRome^ And all your Ills part, prefent, and to come. It is not fit nor pofTible I live, And my dear Queen, it growes unkind to grieve. Cleop, 'Twas I that loft you in each Roman mind ; And to your ruine can you ftill be kind ? How can you bear this Tyranny of Fate, And not the Caule, your Cleopatra hate. m I So 57
Page 58

5 8 Antony and Cleopatra. Ar7to, So Venus look't, when the Idalim Bear The tender fide of her Adonis tore : Nor yields my Queen in Beauty or in grief. When half the World under my rule was plac't] Your Love was all the joy that I cou d tail:, f> It was my chief delight, and is my laft. J I dye, and have but one fliort word to fay 5 But you muft fvvear, my Qiieen you will obey. Clcv^. By all our Love I will, my death command, And fc^e the eager duty of my hand. Anto. Your death ! it is the only thing I fear : And Fate no other way can reach me here. Cko^, Down from a Throne to any private State : It is a difmal Precipice to the Great. I giddy with the horrid profpeft grow 3 And fhall fall in, unlefs Death help me now. Anto. Heav'n that fuccefs does to my Arms deny^ Whifpers a Roman Soul, and bids him dye. Our cafe is different^ to C£far fue, Tho me he hate, he needs muft pity you. Your Beauty and my Love were all your Crime, And you muft live my Queen. Chop. When you are dead — To be defpis'd, reproach't, in triumph lead 5 A Queen and Slave ! who wou'd not life renouncCj Rather than bear thofe diflant names at once. Anto. But you may live a Queen 3 fay you obey'd Through fear : and were compelled to give me Aid: That all your Subjefts private Orders had Not to refifl him, and my Caufe betray 'd. Say, that at laft you did my Death procure 5 Say any thing that may your Life and Crown fecure. Cleof. Twere falfe and bafe, it rather fhall be faid I kiird my felf when I beheld you dead. Anto. Me the unhappy caufe of all your wo ! Your own, aud your dear Country's overthrow. Remember I Vv^as jealous, rafh, fbon mov'd, Sufpefted no lefs fiercely than I lov'd : How I Tkyreus kilUd, your Love accused. And to your kind defence my faith "rfus'd.
Page 59

Antony and Cleopatra. 5^ From fhame and rage I foon (hall be at reft, And Death of thoufand ills hath chofe the beft, [He faints. Chop. O ftay ! and take me with you — Anto. Deareft Qiieen, Let my Life end before your Death begin. O Rome ! thy freedom does with me expire. And thou art loft, obtaining thy defire. [Dks. Cleop, He's gone ! he's gone ! and I for ever loft !> The great Antotiius now is but a Ghoft ; - > A wandring ftiadow on the Stygian Coaft. 3 I'm ftill a Queen, though by the Fate of War, Death and thefe Women all my Subjefts are 5 And this unhappy Monument is all Of the whole World, that I my own can call. Iras, O name not Death ! Cdefar men fay is good, wife, mild and juft 5 So many Vertues how can you diftruft? Cleop. Tho his laft breath advis'd me to ftibmit To C£fay\ and his falling Fortunes quit : When I nam'd Death, (peechlefs my hand he preft 3 And feem'd to (ay that I had choie the beft. Iras. He cou'd not be fo cruel, you miftook^ Too lharply you apply his dying look. Cleo. He does expeft it, and Tie keep my word, If there be Death in Poyfon, Fire, or Sword. Charm, Fortune with lighter ftroaks ftrikes lighter things 3 With her whole weight ftie crufties filling Kings. Cleop, We ftiall in Triumph, Charmioyt^ be led, Till with our (hame Komes Pride be fiirfeited ; Till every finger Cleopatra find Pointing at her, whowas their Queen defign'd. Char, Their Anger they may glut, but not their Pride. They ne'r had Triumph' t if men durft have dy'd. Cleop, Beauty, thou art a fair, but fading flow'r. The tender prey of every coming hour: In Youth thou Comet-like art gaz d upon. But art portentous to thy (elf alone. Unpuniih't thou to few wer't ever giv'n; Nor art ^ Eleffing, but a Mark from Heav n. I 2
Page 60

6o Antony and Cleopatra. Greatnefs inofl: cnvy'dj w^ien leaft undeiftood: Thou art no real, but a feeming good. Sick at the Heart ! Thou in the Face look'ft well^ And none but fuch as feel thy pangs can tell. By thy exalted State we only gain. To be more wretched than the Vulgar can. Iras, Think how he'l ufe your Sons when you are dead, And none their Caufe can like a Mother plead. C/cop, Perhaps, wlien I am dead, his hate may ceafe. And Pity take declining Rages place. Sure in the Grave nil Enmities take end. And Love alone can to the Dead extend. Men fdy that v/e to th' other World (hall bear ThefimeDefiresand Thoughts, imploy'd as here. The Hero (liall in (hining Arms delight, In neighing Steeds, fhril founds and empty fight : Poets ihall fing, and in foft Dances move,. And Lovers in Eternal Ko(cs Love. If fo, Af2torniis^ v/e but change the Scene,. And there purfoe what we did here begin. Charm, I am prepared to follow or to kad : Name but the.fatal Path that you will tread. Chop, In yonder golden Box three Afps there lie,"] Of w^hofe leaft venomous bite men fleep and die ; Take one and to my naked Breaft, apply J Its poyfonous mouth— ^ Ckarm, Alone ihe (hall not die. Iras, When yjiMs C£far in the Senate £11, Where v/ere theie thoughts ? and yet he lov'd as w^elk- Ckop, He lov'd me not ! he Vv\as ambitious he 5 And but at loofer Tim?s took thought of m.e. Glory and Em.pire fiird his reftlcfs mind ; He knew not the foft pleafures of the Kind. Our Joyes were frighted ftill with fiefh alarms. And new Dcfigns fiill forc't him f om my Arms. But m^y Antiwius lov'd rac with lus Soul. No cares of Empire did his Flange controul. I v\Ms his Friend, the Partner of his mind 3. ^ " -'rfal, and our nights were kind ' I will die for" Him. [SU^gs her. ' my eyes grow dim, ■ I am
Page 61

Antony and Cleopatra. 6i I am fi'om triumph and contempt fccure. What all muft bear I eailicr endure. . \^IO:eeIs darn to Anto. To thy cold Arms take thy unhappy Queen, Who both thy mine and her own has been ; Other Embrace than this fhe'l never know, But a pale Ghoft, purfue thy (hade below. Good Afp bite deep and deadly in my Brefl:, And give me fudden and Eternal Reft. \_SLe dies. [Iras r/ws arvaj. Charm, Fool, £iom thy hafty Fate thon can'ft not run^ Iras, Let it bite you, Tie ftay till ypu have done ; I. Alas ! my life but newly is begun J Charm, No : thou woud'ft live to,(liame thy Family But rie take care that thou (halt Nobly dye. Iras. Good Charmion ! Charm, I'le hear no more : faint Hearts that feek delay Will never want fome foolifh thing to fay. Ch'^xm,ftif7gs her^ then pits it to I er own Breajl. At our Queens feet let's decently be f nmd, And Loyal Grief be thought our only Wound. [^D/es Enter C?cfir, Mecoenas, Agrippa, ar^d Photinus. C^f. Yonder's the Monument, that famous Tow'r ^ 'Tis weak, and may be ruin'd in an hour. Summon the Queen 'Tis obftinacy now \Cdlls thriee^ Not reiblution the loft Queen docs (liow 5 (none anfwers. Call for a Battering Ram now dov/n it goes. [Enter alL , .Mect^n. But oh ! what horror does that Breach difcloie ? T!ic Queen, Ar^tonins^ and her Maids lie dead ;■ From their pale Cheeks the Life but newly fled. C£f, Am I fo cruel and relentlcls held, That Women dare not to m.y mercy yield ? Phut, The Queen your Roman Triumphs ever fearVi^ And therefore Poyfbns of all Ibrts prepared To end her life, and to prevent that fhamc, When ever the unhappy profpeft camie. QPhot. runs to Iras.- Some figns of life in that (oft Maid remain 5 She feems to move her dying lips again. Iras, rft thus your word you with poor Ira^ keep The.
Page 62

Si Antony and Cleopatra. The Ci own of B.g^p now you may difpofe On whom you pleafe Death foon my Eyes will clofe^ And C^jar my C^/ The Crown of Egyp^ Slave, difpos'd by thee ? Her dying words contain fbme Myftery: Phot, Which rie take care (he never (hall explain — \_A{ide She raves r the Poifon has difturb'd her brain. \JK.iUs hcv^ C^f. Thou haft not, Slave, the tender Virgin flain ? Phot. I lov'd and cou*d not fee her lie in pain. C£f Villain, thou feard'ft that her laft breath might (ay Something that might thy treacherous heart betray. Me(W}7as^ fcize on him, fte quick Juftice done. Sould, Quicker than this,great C^f^r, there is none. [KHlsVhou C^f. Who art thou that dar'ft kill and C^far by > SohIcL Vm Brother to that Maid, refolv'd to die By the fiime hand, if defar (ay the word. C£f. Put up: it was a kind of Vertue in thy Sword* What cou'd Antor^ius from a Brother fear. Who owes him all the Honours he does wear ? Oh! what a God-like pleafure had it been With thee t' have fhar'd the Empire once agen ? And to have made a (econd Sacrifice To Friendftiip of each others Enemies. By thee I am whatever I was made, But thou art proud, and fcorn ft to be repaid. Agrip. The Queens vaft Treafure, Sir, I blazing found s A greater Wealth than ever Tktis drown'd. She her fair Perfbn to a Carcafi turn'd ; And has her Treafure to vile Afties burn*d. Both ways defeating the proud hopes of Rome, C£f Great minds the Gods alone can overcome—- Let no man with his prefent Fortune fwell *] The Fate of growing Empire who can tell ? y We ftand but on that Greatnefs whence thefe fell, j Ex. Omms- FINIS.
Page Scan 67

EPILOGUE. TWE R E Popifi folly for the Dead to fray : ^ By this time you have damnd or fa v d our Play : > But Gentlemen^ the Poet bad me fay^ y He claimes his Merit on a furer fcore : H has brought you here together ^ and what more Could Waters^ Courts or Conventicles do ? ^Tis mt his faulty if things no further go, K The Gravefi Cit that hopes to he Lord Mayor Mufi come to a New Play with his None Dear 5 And the k^nd Girl engagd another way^ Tells all her Friends fH has been at the New Play. They ashjhe Tale which floe does for 'em get Between the Affs^ from her dear Friend fhe met. The PeacockcBeauty here may fpread her Train^ And by our gazing Fops be made more vain. And all kind Lovers that are here to nighty May thank,the Poet for each others (ight, Thb all be bad^ men blame with an ill grace The Entertainment of a Meeting Place. TH E Art of making Love, or Rules for the conduft of La- dies and Gallants in their Amours. Price bound i s. Prin- ted for i?. Tonfon at Grayes-lnne-gate next Grayes-Inne-lane, 9
Page Scan 68

BooJ^ lately Publijhed. L I ^ H E Courtiers Calling : Shewing the ways of making a _|_ Fortune, and the Art of living at Court, according to Polity and Morality. In mo Parts. The Fiifl: concerning Noble Men, the Second concerning Gentlemen. By a Perfon of Honour. Price bound i s. 6 d. II. Dcfj Carlos^ Prirxe of Sfa'if?^ a Tragedy, asrtisAdedat the Dukes Theatre. Written by Tkomas Oivpaj, Price i s. III. Titus and Bcremce^ a Tragedy, as it is Afted at the Dukes Theatre, with a Farce, called the Chats of Scapw. Written by Tho, Oivpay. Price I s. IV. The Portugal Hiftory, or a Relation of the Troubles that happened in the Court of Portugal^ in the years 1667, and 16685 In which is to be (een that great Tranfaftion of the Renunciation of the Crown, by Alphonfo the Sixths the Diflblution of his Mar- riage with the Princefi Maria Frances Jfabella of Samj 5 the Mar- riage of the fame Princels to his Brother the Pnnce Don Pedro now Regent of the Realm of Portugal^ and the Reafons alledged at Rom for the difpenfation thereof By S. P. Efquire. Price bound 2 s. 6 d. All fold by R. Tonfof?^ at his Shop under Grajes-Inne-gate^ next Graycs-InnC'lane.

End of Title Page. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents

End of text. Return to beginning.
