The Empress of Morocco. A tragedy. With sculptures. As it is acted at the Duke's theatre. Written by Elkanah Settle, servant to his Majesty ..., . | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
The Empress of Morocco. A tragedy. With sculptures. As it is acted at the Duke's theatre. Written by Elkanah Settle, servant to his Majesty ..., .
Author
Settle, Elkanah, 1648-1724.Settle, Elkanah, 1648-1724.
Published
London,Printed for William Cademan at the Popes-head in the Lower Walk of the New Exchange in the Strand,1673.
Description
4 p. l., 72 p.fold. front., 5 pl.22 cm.
Rights
Public Domain, Google-digitized.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/hvd.32044086921434

Table of Contents

    Front Cover
    Title Page
    Section 1 on page number 1
    Section 2 on page number 71

Book Text
Front Cover
Page Scan 1

Blank page

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 2

A HARVARD COLLEGE LIBRARY

BOUGHT FROM A SPECIAL APPROPRIATION FOR DUPLICATE BOOKS
Page Scan 3

Blank page
Page Scan 4

Blank page
Page Scan 5

Blank page
Page Scan 6

Blank page

End of Front Cover. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Title Page
Page Scan 7

mpress of; J-

GO" SEDY. WITH Sculptures, -As it is Acted at the Duke's Theatre r . . •

'-i ^mM^s «ml Peer. Arb. * n by Elkanab Settle, Servant to his Majesty.„c £ Printed for iWtiiam Cademan at the Popeszbead in the Lower ► £. -Walk of the New Exchange in the Strand, 1673. ■ .»
Page Scan 8

HARVARD COLLEGE LIBRARY APPROPRIATION FOR DUPLICATE BOOKS
Page Scan 9

: mmmnmm TO THE RIGHT HONOURABLE HENRY, EARL of Norwich, and EARL - Marshall of ENGLAND,&c. My Lord, THe Impudence of Scriblers in this Age, has so corrupted the Original design ofDedications, that before I dare tell you this tripe begs your Lordships Profession, I ought first to Examine en what grounds I make the attacque for now every thing that ere saw the Stage, how modest soever it has been there, without daring to shew 'its face above three Days, has yet the Arrogance to thrust it self into the World in Print with a Great Nante before it: Where the fawning Scriblcr shall compendiously fay, the fatfuns of Critiques, the ill time of the Tear, and the worse ailing of the Players^ has prejudiced his Play, but he doubts not but his Grace, or his Ho- nours more impartial judgment will find that Pardonable which the World has ft Maliciously Cenfurd\ that is as much as to fay: Sir$ sou are the only Person at Court rhofe blind fide I dare ven- ture on, not doubting but your good Nature will excuse what all the World (except the Authors) has justly condemned. Thus 4 De- dication which was formerly a Present to a person of Quality, is now made a Libel on him, whilst the Poet either supposes his Patron to be so great a [ot to defend that in Print, which he hist off the Stage .- or else makes him self a greater, in asking a Favour from him which he

Page Scan 10

. - THE EPISTLE DEDICATORY. %e nere expects to obtain. However, that which is an abuse to the Patron, is a Complement to the Bookseller, who whispers the Poet, and tells him, Sir, Tour Play had miss or tune, and all that — hut if you'd hut write a Dedication, or Preface — The Poet takes the hint, picks out a person of Honour; tells him he has a great deal of Wit\ gives us an account who writ Se nee in the last Age , supposing we cannot be Ignorant who writes it inThis\Difputcs the nature o/Verse, Answers a Cavil or two,$uiblcs upon theCourt-Huffs the Critiques, and the work's don. Tis not to be imagind how far a sheet os this goes to make a Bookseller Rich, and a Poet Famous. jut my Lord) whilst I trouble you with t his kind of discourse, I beg you would not think I iesign to give rules to the Press, as some of our Tribe have done to the St.ge-,w that I find fault with their Dedications in Complement to my own: No,thaCs a trick I do not pretend to. Be- sides your particular Favours, in the public k honours you have conde- scended to this Play, and the Author, have heightned my fence of Gratitude beyond my Power of expressing it. This Play, which for no o- ther Merit, durst take S anil u ary here) throws it self at your feet, as jour own: the Story of which,I owe toytur Hands,andyour honourable Embassy into Africa : and on that score I present it to your Patro- nage,as the Jewes made their Sacrifices which we read took Fire from Heaven: ihe Incence was lighted by that Divinity to whom it was offer d^ nor is this all I ma) modestly boast of: for besides its noble Birth, you gave it a ntblcEducation,when you bred it up amongst rrinces,presen- ted it in a Coijrt-Theater,&by persons of such Birth & Honour, that they borrow'd no greatness from the charratfers they ailed. Thus has jour Lordship shewed your selfso great a friend to the Muses-jhat as in former a^es thePiet m.ide thePatron-when all that's left ofaMxcems, is,that Horace %avc him aName:your influence on theContrary makes the Poet, and if ihis Play Live, or have Success enough to preserve a name - 'tis by being your creature, and enjoying yiur smiles: which ts the highest ambition of, MY LORD, Your Lordships moil oblidged and mo.t obedient Servant, lilkattab Seltle.
Page Scan 11

P ROLOGUE At the Play House. • FOr this days Treatment sou have said too dcare. Tour best belovd diversion is not here, All you're now like to have is a dull play. The Wells have stoln the Vizar Masks away. Now punk in Penitential Drink begins, T9 purge the surfeit of her London Sins. Their Loves have been o'restockt, and but make stop, For a new tillage towrds another Crop. 'Tis seasonable sometimes to forbeare: Alafs it is not Harvest all the Tear. Though heated they like tatter d Ships keep in, Tbey stay but to refit, then Lanch again. Be honest then one Day, and patient Jit, With neither baudy in the Play, nor Pit. And though thus far you to your loss are come, What's yet still worse you must drive Empty home. Hor when Play's done need the shamefaced Debauch Change the guilt Chariot for the hackney Coach. Then since our sober Andience denyes Ton furious men of prey all hopes of prize: To, fee the Play should be your only Ends, Wee'le then presume you are the Authors Friends. And though you miss your dear delights, you may Be to the Poet kind, and Clap the Play: Tour Hands are now employ'd no other Way,. THE
Page Scan 12

. The Actors Names. -

Mr. Harris. Mnly Htmet) a Prince of the RoyaPi Blood, contracted xoViariamm. \ «. c j ^ i c i o * Mr. Smith. and General ot the Emperours; Forces. . J Crimalba*,, a Courtier and Gallant") D , ,' ... > Mr. Baiterton. to the Queen Mother. J Hantetalba%, his Confident and) Creature, Governour of a Ca r Mr. Medbourne. stle in Morocco. * Abdelcador, Friend to Mnly Hamet. Mr. Crosby. Acbmat, An Eunuch LauLt, Empress of Morocco, and^ Mother to Mnly Labas and M<*-> Mris. Batterton. riamne. * j Mtriamne her Daughter. Mris. Miry Le*. Morena, Daughter to Taffakt. Mris. Jobnson. Villains Lords, Messengers, Priests, Masquers, and other Attendants.
Page Scan 13

The firH Prologue at Court,s]>ofyn by the Lady ELIZABETH HOWARD. IWish you only did expect to day, . . A common Prologue to some usual Play. < For when young Ladies are to speak to King*, You look that they mould say no vulgar things. Tisbelow us what me-ntr Actoisdo . EifLer t'excuse our selves, or railc at You. Nor come you here as to the common Pit, With thelest hope offinding fault with Wit. Loves gentler thoughts possess the men of Sence: At lest it shall be so, e're they go hence. Gallants take warning then: 'tis time to fear 5 When Youth and Beautys on the stage appear. Those charms else where are pretty dangerous sound: But here we shoot upon a Rising Ground. No heart can scape we have a mind to hit, Unless 'tis guarded by some Eyes 'ith Pit. To hearts engag'd our power does not extend: And therefore, sirjto you we humbly bend. [to the Kiag] Yet from your constancy we need not fear: To all fair Nymphs you keep an open Ear?. No watching Eyes, those lost alming wiles, Can hinder you from giving Gracious fm;le«. Now for the Men: Theii pra se mould next be stiewn 5 But that I think were better let alone M^r." >* [Written by the Lord kupptoft'J The second Prologue at Court spleen by the Lady ELIZABETH HOWARD. WIT has of late took up a trick t' appear. Unmannerly, 01 at the best severe. And Poets (hare the Fate by whic^ we fill, When kindly we attempt to nleast- you all. 'Tishard, your scorn shoul J against such prevail, Whose eads are to divert you, tho' they 9
Page Scan 14

Men would think it an ilnatur'd Test,' A fe* *i Should we laugh at you when you did your best. - W'w fAThenrail not here, though you see reason foi't.1 * frlf Wit can find it self no better sport * J Wit is a very sodlish thing at Court. * Wit's buPne'ss is to please, and not to fright, p 'Tis no Wit to be always in the right, > You 'il fin4it none, who dare be so to night* j a Few so ill-bred Will venture to a Play, To spy out faults in what we Women fay: For us no mater what we speak, but how, How kindly can we say--I hate you now. And for the men, isyou'l laugh at 'em, do } They mind themselves so much, they '11 ne're mind you.-— But why do I descend to lose a Piayer On those small Saints in Wit, the God sits there. To you ('Great Sir) my Message hither tends, From Youth and Beauty your Allies and Friends. See my Credentials written in my Face, They challenge your Protection in this place, And hither come with such a Force of charmes, As may give check even to your prosp'rous Armes: Millions of Cupids hovering in the Rear, Like Eagles following fatal Troops, appear. All waiting for the slaughter, which draws nigh, Of those bold Gazers, who this Night must dye. Nor can you 'scape our soft Captivitie, From which old Age alone must set you free. Then tremble at the fatal Consequence- — Since, 'tis well known for you own part (Great Prince) 'Gainst us you still have made a weak defence. « Be generous, and wife, and take our part) / Remember we have eyes, and you a heart. Else you may find, too late, that we are things Born to kill vassals, and to conquer Kings. But oh! to what vain Cohqudt I pretend, Whilst Love is our Commander, and your Friend. Our victory your Empire more assures, For Love will ever make the Triumph yours. IrVrittn Iythe Lori Rochester.3
Page Scan 15

Blank page
Page Scan 16

Blank page
Page Scan 17

CO 'T HE E M P RE SS MOROCCO. The First Ad, Scene the First.' v Scene opens, Muly Labas appears bound in Chains, Attended bj Guards, My Z.^"^OndemnM to Fetters, and to Scepters born! ■ 'Tis in this Garb unhappy Princes mourn. Yet Fortune to great Courages is kind; sTis he wants Lioerty whose Soul's confin'd. My Thoughts out-fly that mighty Conqueror, Who having one World vanquished, wept for more: Fetter'd in Empires, he enlargement crav'd To the short Walk of one poor Globe enslavM. My Soul mounts higher, and Fates Pow'r disdains, And makes me reign a Monarch in my Chains. But'tis my Father has decreed my fate j Yet still he shews his Greatness in his hate. B Thy
Page Scan 18

% '- The Empress os Morocco, Thy rage,brave Prince,mean Subjects does despise j None but thy Son shall be thy Sacrifice. Enter Morena bound. This dazling Object my weak sight invades: Such Beauty would make Dungeons lose their shades. Moren. Remember, Sir, when first vou were a Guest To 7ajfjUn£% Court, and to my Breast, That I, fond Woman, in a borrow'd shape, Was a Conspirator ki my own Rape, When in a fatal night, whose darkness did Both our Escapes, and my faint Blushes hide: With You I fled my Countrey,left a Crown, Heir oaly now t'aa unkiad Vathers Frown; And now for refuge to Morocco come, *We in your Fathers Court receive this doom; [points to her Chains, Our Love from him this Entertainment gains $ We in our Sanctuary .meet our Chains: Oiir Fathers too have now proclaims a War; By Tdffaletta's Arms we are pursu'd. 'Our amorous flights like threatning Comets are, Which thus draw after them a train of Bloud. M»ly L. Why do you thus a fad relation make . Of all that you have suster'd for my sake , Unless you my Unworthiness resent, And os your misplaced kindnesses repent? ( Moren. No, I recount the Scenes of our past storms, To arm your Fancy for more pleasing forms 5 I come to tell you that your 'Father's kind, And has our mutual Happiness design'd. Of our past Woes I have this relation given, As Purgatory doe* make way for Heaven. Muly L. This. does disperse my Fears, checks my Despair: And lias my Father-— Shall we then-— and are Our Lovts and Hopes -— Oh my unruly Joy Which does my Thoughts so in their B;rth destroy, That

End of Title Page. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 1
Page 1

The Empress of Morocco. 3 That my disorders Words no form can bear! Speak then what You would fay, and I would hear.' Moren. He has pronounc'd such great and glorious things," As are fit only for the Breath of Kings: Our happy Passion he so far approves, That ere three days expire he'l crown our Loves. Know then, to grant our Souls a stricter Tye, He has decreed -— we shall together Dye. Muly X. How are my visionary Dreams retir'd, And my fond Hopes in the Embrace expir'd? Mor. That day my Father TaffalettSs Arms To this proud City give their suit Alarms, His Standard fix't before Morocco's Walls, Mu I j Lab as and his Morcna falls. He for my Murder does this reason plead, He will present my Father with my Head. That sudden Blow, which he designs for you, 'Tis your suspected Treason prompts him to: And the fame Jealousie that made his Breath Decree your Chains, makes him pronounce your Death. Muly L. I freely at his feet my Life will throw j Life is a debt we to our Parents ow. But die suspected J Can he think so foul X A Thought as Treason harbours in his *Soul, Which does Moren* s sacred Image bear! No shape of ill can come within her Sphear. But must Moren a fall i when e're (he bleeds, He no severer a Damnation needs, That dares pronounce the-Sentence of her Death, Than the Infection that attends that Breath. Moren. Hold, Sir, and your unmanly fears remove, And (hew your Courage equal to your Love: Let us to Death in solemn Triumph go, As to the nobler Nuptials of the two: For when we're'dead, and our freed Souls enlarg'd, of Natures grosser burdens we're discliarg'd: B a Then
Page 2

4 The Empress of Morocco Then gentle as a happy Lovers Sigh, Like wandring Meteors through the Air we'l fly $ And in our airy Walk, as subtil Guests, We'l steal into our cruel Fathers Breasts, There read their Souls,and track each Passions sphear» See how Revenge moves there, Ambition here: And in their Orbs view the dark Characters Of Sieges, Ruins, Murders,Blood and Wars. We'l blot out all those hideous Droughts, and write Pure and white forms $ we'l with a radiant light Their Breasts incirde, till their Passions be Gentle as Nature in its Infancy $ Till soften'd by our Charms their Furies cease, And their Revenge dissolves into a Peace. Thus by our Death appeas'd, their Quarrel ends: Whom Living we made Foes, Dead we'l make Friends. Muly L. On generous Princess! whose couragious Breath Can set such glorious Characters on Death: The antient World did but too modest prove, In giving a Divinity to Love. Love the great Pow'r oth' higher World controuls, Heaven but creates, but Love refines our Souls. Enter to them Mother voeepng. QsJMoth. Oh Son! your Royal Father —^ M'nly L. Hold! your Tears Confound my hopes. O my presaging sears! Has he -— it cannnot be — has he decreed — Afore na must not, no, she shalLnot bleed: The Skies would blufli when that bold deed were done > And look more red than at a setting Sun. .SJMplb. 'Tisnot Mtrena who is doom'd to dy. Mulf L. Has he decreed I shall her pbce supply if' Is so, thanks my kind Father, thou hast done The only deed that could oblige a Son: If I to save your Life resign my-own [to Morena. Iihallmore gloriousIbine tlun on.his Throne*
Page 3

The Empress of Moroccoi f Q^Moth. That object which your Mothers tears procures Is your great Fathers sudden fate, not yours. Muly L. My Father! ha! ^ JZ^Moth. is dead. Just as he fate Pronouncing yours and your Aforena's fate? A sudden Check his hasty Breath controul'd, He startled, trembled, and his Eye balls rould, His wandring fears, his umhap'd thoughts supplyM With horrourSj then Muly Luhai he cry'd, Forgive what my mistaken Rage has done, In peace possess thy Mistress and my Throne: Then with his dying Breath his»Soul retir'd, And in a sullen sigh his Life expir'd. MulyL. The Emperour dead! and with his dying Breath Did he More ha to his Son bequeath i He in this Gift a Father has out-don, And robs me of the Duty of a Son; For those just Tears, which Nature ought t' imploy, To pay my last Debt to his Memory, The Crowning of my Passion disallows t, Giiefslightly sits on happy Lovers Brows. Enter Crimalhaz and Hametalhaz, with Attendants.. A shut within,. All Long live MulyLabas Emperour of Morocco. Crim. Welcome, brave Prince, to your great Fathers Crown, Advancing from a Prison to a Throne: . The City does in one full shout concur, And in one voice proclaim you Emperour: Yet, Sir, youi Freedom must not reach so far, But this fair Princess Chains you still must wear. . The Sun, Great Sir, must in one circuit view Your Coronation and your Nuptials too. Muly L. Bnjoy a Throne, and my Morcna wedd I A Joy too greai were not my Father dead. D 3 Tjie
Page 4

6 The Empress of Morocco. The Force of one the others Pow'r controuls: Heav'nsits our swelling Passions to our Souls. When some gieat Fortune to mankind's convey'd Such Blessings are by Providence alhy'd. Thus Nature to the World a Sun creates, But with cold Winds his pointed Rays rebates. Exit Muly L. leading Moreru. St^Moth. Besotted in thy Love and Empires Charms, Sleep, and grow dull in your Morcnas Arms. 'Twas not for this I rais'd thee to a Crown, Poison'd the Father to enthrone the Son: Hid It thou been ripe for Death, we had decreed, Thou lliouldst him in hls Fate, not Throne, succeed: Thy early growth we in thy Chains had crufbt, And mix'd thy Ashes with thy Fathers Dust. But live, fond Boy: to manage our Design, We first must thy Great General undermine. They, who by Policy a Crown pursue, Snatch at one Grasp the Sword and Scepter too. Then wee'l with ease depose an Armless King: Men sport with Serpents when they've lost their Sting. When our Designs to the full height succeed I'le place the Crown Imperial on your Head. [to Crimalfuz. Sir, of your Progress a Relation make, How died the King i how did the Poison take i y Crin. With safety I accomplislsd your desire j For Hell and Night did in the deed conspire. As if He by some secret instinct knew The fatal Potion had been sent by you: Up from his Seat he rose, and sighing cried, O unkind Laula! and then groan'd and died. His Death so much of horrour did present, Icurs'dmy Hand for being the Instrument: A strange unusual trembling shook my Heart, As th. t Mag/dan, whose infernal ait, Raising
Page 5

The Empress of Moroccd. \ J Raising a Vision, is with Terrour seiz'd At th'Apparition his own Charms have rais'd. Have you consider'd, Madam, what you've done i SUM. Poison'd my Husband, Sir, and if there need Examples to instruct you in the deed, I'll make my Actions plainer understood, Coppying his Death on all the Royal Blood. / Crim. The Falls of Kings are heavy, and on You-— £>±M. Hold, Sir, sure you have drunk the Poison too, That thus your Blood grows cold, and your faint Breast Is with such dull and stupid Fears possest. A States-mans Breast should scorn to feel remorse 5 Murder and Treason are but dungs of course. / Crim. I am a Convert, Madam, for kind Heaven, Has to mankind immortal Spirits given, And Couiage is their Life: but when that sinks, And to tame Fears and Coward-faintness shrinks, We the great Work of that bright Frame destroy. And shew the World, that even our Souls can dy. By your Example I'll great Deeds pursue: My Thoughts fha'nt stait at what my Hand dares do. Hamet. Madam, as Agents in this great Design, Zibd-j^ Mordt and Abdrahamon joyn; They the Kings Ears will with such Whispers fill} As shall the Poyson Jealousie instill: And by such subtilty his Breast infect, .1» Till he his Generals Loyalty suspect. , Crim. Then to promote Suspition we'l proclaim His Generals high Courage, Pow'r and Fame', His Armies Love, and his great Spirit praise: And to that pitch his heighien'd Virtues raise, That their Perfection shall appear their Crime, As Giants by their Height do Monsteis seem. jj^itf. Brave Crimaihaz! thy Breast nnd mine agree: Mow thou art woithy of a Crown and Mee. And
Page 6

$ The Empress os Morocco. And by such Arts I'll my Jons Breast invade Till his fond Duty has his Life betray'd, Till by my means we have his Army gain'd, And have remov'd the Sword into your Hand: And then we pubhkly and safely may Our bloody Ensigns to the World display: His Pow'r once gone, we'l act his Death in state, And dasli his Blood against his Palace Gate. Great Deeds should in the open day be don, As Sacrifices offei'd to the Sun. Crim. But till these mighty Actions ripen'd are We must theborrow'd Looks of Friendship wear. H^M.'Vo statt'ring light'ning our feign Smiles conform, Which, back'd with Thunder, do but guild a Storm. Finit Attut frimi, \_Excuat, Act the Second, Scene the First. The Scene opened, is represented the ProspeSi os a large .River, with a glorious Fleet of Ships, supposed to be the Navy of Muly Harriet, after the Sound of "Trumpets and the discharging of Guns. Enter King, Young Qgeen, Hametalhaz and Attendants. JIamet. /^Reat Sir, Your Royal Fathers General Prince Muly Hamess Fleet does horae.wards fail, And in a solemn and triumphant Pride Their Course up the great River Tcnfift guide, Whose guided Currents do new Glories take From the Reflection his bright Streamers make: The Waves a Masque os Martial Pageants yield* A flying Army on a floating Field. Order
Page 7

Blank page
Page 8

i.
Page 9

the Empress of Morocco. 9 Order and Harmony in each appear; - - Their lofty Bulks the foaming Billows bear. In state they move, and on the Waves rebound, As if they danc'd to their own Trumpets found: By Winds inspired, with lively Grace they roul As if that Breath and motion lent a Soul. . And with that Soul, they seem taught Duty too, Their Topsails lowi'd, their Heads with Reverence bow As if they would their Generals Worth enhance, "From him, by instinct, taught Allegiance. Whilst the loud Cannons eccho to the shore, Their flaming Breaths salute You Emperour. F/om their deep Mouths he does your Glory sing: W:th Thunder, and with Light'ning, greets his King. Thus to express his Joys, in a loud Quire And Consort os wing'J Messengers of fire He has his Tribute sent, and Homage given, As men in Incense send up Vows to Heaven. Inter Maly Hamet and Abdelcador, Aitended, introduced with 4 Flourif) of Trumpets: Muly Hamet kneels to the King. King. Welcome true owner osthat Fame you bring, AConquerour is a Guardian to a King. Conquest and Monarchy consistent are5 'Tis Victory secures those Crowns we wear. Muly timet. In aU that Sword you lent me has subdu'd, I only, Sir, my Duty have pursu'd: And acts os Duty merit no applause , I owe my Lawrels to my Royal Cause. My Actions all are on your Name enrol I'd, Since'tis from you my Conqu'ring Pow'rl hold. inmei.il. But in Morocco his high Pride may find His Name less glorious, and his Stars less kind. [aside. Muly Hamet. Sir, your victorious Arms are doub'ly crown 'J, On Sea and Land the fame success have found: C When
Page 10

io The Empress of Morocco. When fust our greeting Navies did salute, And in the rage of Flames our Cause dispute: The Trains of Fire our fatal Guns did make Did the fierce stupe of blazing Comets take: Our meeting Heat inch fury cud contract, That Comets can but threaten what we act. But When the Day had a spectatour been, And the whole Progress of this Parley seen, Led by your Genius, fate their Side forsook, Some of their Ships I funk, and some I took. But when the interposing {hades of Night Assisted them in tneir diibrder'd flight, I made their Fleet to Conquest light my way, With burning Ships made Beacons on the Sea. King. Kind Fate, in giving you so great Success, Could scarce grant more, nor did You merit less. Muly H. Their Arms who have at Sea victorious been* Do but the Out works of an Empire win. Then to compleat, what on the Sea before I'd but begun, I landed on their Shore. Abdelc. Sifhee and SaSi} Mugadvre , Or an , The fam'd ArziRt, AUdzer, Titugp^ Which the Usurper Gayhnets Pow'r possest, Those his Sword conquer'd, and his Fame the rest: For the less Cities at his Names surprise, Yielding made Crowds of bloodless V ictories. Your Anns against your Foes so much have done, They feel the Heat though the fierce Fire be gone, /fuly U. And now Heating whose Force Moroeco will invade, I have b: ought home your Army to your aid. r> Valour and Fate such just success allow, As firmly place the Laurel on your Brow, Whose very Looks so much your Foes surprise, Hut You, like Beauty, conquer with your ties,
Page 11

The Empress of Moroca, t i But, Muly Harness now your Sword must be Imploy'd in a more Cruel Victory Against Invaders You your Force must lead,' And meet my Father in an Army's Head: But the rough hand of War more gentle make, And spare His Blood for His Mcrenas fake. Muly H. We only do aspire to this great end, To make your Father not our Prize, but Friend. King. Should Fortune Crown our Forces with Succcis, Our Arms, though Conqu'ring, sliall not make him less Enter Mariamne, tttended. Muly H. Now I'm a Conquerour, Mmmne's Name alone Has Triumph in't; I from this hour am made Greater than if I wore those Crowns I won; My Laurels too without your Beams would fade. Marian*. If Mariamnes Eies, Great Sir, can give Your Laurels Life, she grants them leave to live. Muly H. Oh my full Joys! Miriam. I come, as one of die Admiring Crowd . To welcom Him whose Actions speak so loud. Muly H. Madam, my Deeds can reach no higher Fame, Than that your pretious Breath gives 'em a Name. Mar. No doubt but War and the harsh sound of Arms Has from your Bosome chas'd Loves softer Charms,- Your Thoughts, accustom'd now to Maitial Toils, Court only Honour, drest in savage Spoils. Muly H. No, Madam, War has taught my Hands to aime At Glory, to deserve a Lovers Name 5 Since my Ambition has your Heart pursu'd, I Conquer Crowns to make my Title good: Whose narrow Thoughts to lesser Objects move $ His Soul wants Room to entertain your Love. King. Sir, to requite you with a Crown would be Too mean Reward, Crowns you've bestow'd on me: C z To
Page 12

12 The Empress of Morocco, To speak my Thanks and Gratitude more large,'/. . .; That vaster Debt I owe She shall discharge. .: I To pay what so much Merit does require, I do command you love, where I admire. [to Maiiamne. Muly H. Though Marianne's Love appear'd before The highest Happiness Fate had in store , Yet when I view it, as an Offering Made by the Hand of an obliging King, It takes new Charms, looks brighter, lends new Heat. No Objects are so Glorious or so Great, But what may still a Greater Form put on, As Optick Glasses magnisie the Sun. Enter Crimalhaz, Shouts within. Crtm. Your Subjects wait with eager joys to pay Their Tribute to your Coronation Day. King. You are arrived awelcom Guest, toshare T hose Ceremonies which their Joys prepare 5 f_to Muly Hamer. Your Presence to their solemn Rites will grunt That Ornament which this days Triumphs want: What more could their impatient Wishes meet, Then in one day a King and Conquerour greet i Whilst they behold triumphant on one Throne The Wearer and Defender of a Crown. Lead on Muly IU Lead on, and all that kneel to you, Shall bow tome. This Conquest makes it due. [/tfMariamne. Exeunt all but Clrimalhaz. Crim. Dull Souldier, in thy Victories go on, And live to fee me wear the Crowns you won. Let Cowards to their Fathers Thrones advance , B- Great and Powerful by Inheritance. No Laurels by descent my Brow adorns lint what gains Crowns. lam to Courage born, Ambition is the rife of Souls, like mine. i hose Wreaths my Biidi doss want, my Brain (hall w>n.
Page 12

Blank page
Page 12

Blank page
Page 13

TJje Empress of Morocco." They in advance to Greatness glorious prove, Who out of the dull track of Birth-right move. Birth-right, the Prop of an unpuichas'd Name, A weak Alliance to an elder Tame. - No Glory by Descent is never worn-, Men are to Worth and Honour Rais'd, not Born. Ex/t. The Scene opened. A State is presented, the King, Queen Mariamne seated, Muly .Hamet, Abdelcador and Attendants, a Moorifi Dance is pre- sented by Moors in several Habits, who bring in an artificial Palm-tree,about which they dance to several aniiek Instruments if Mustek; in the intervals of the Dance,this Song it fung by a Moo- rish Priest and two Moons}) Women; the Chorus of it being pe>* formed by all the Moors. z. Stanza. - NO Mustek like that which Loyalty sings , A Consort of Hearts at the Crowning of Kings: There's no such delightful and ravishing Strain, As the Eccboes and Shouts of Long Live and Reign. . Long live and reign, long live and reign, No shouts so delightful, as. Long Live and Reign, Long live and reign, &c. Chorus. 'A 2. Stanza. No Homage like what from Loyalty\ springs, Wee7 kneel to cur Gods, but wee I ditfor our Kings. We'I pay that Devotion our Lives shall maintain . No raising of Altars like Long Live and Reign. Long live and reign, long lize and Reign, No raising of Altars, like Long Live and Reign. Long live, &c. C 3 Afttt
Page 14

* fJ 4 the Empress of Morocco After the Dunce, King. They have paid theirs, now I my Debts will pay i Sir, the next Sun shall see your Nuptial day. We, who would best great Services requite, Do first our Friendships, then our Bloods unite: And that your Hands more solemnly may joine , Our Royal Mothers Gift (hall second mine. T. ^ueen. Her gentle Breath already, from just Fame, Has kindly ent-rtain'J your Glorious Name* Ana' in that Dress, You, as a Conqu'rour, may To Her a more than welcome Visit pay. King. But since the Sorrows of the Mourning Queen, For our late Fattier, mate Her keep unseen, Let this conduct you. [Gives him a Ring* Muly H. I am here more blest —— Than if I an Imperial Seat possest. t Whilst in your Breast an Empire I obtain,' [to Mariamne. Not only Kings, but Gods unenvied reign. Beauty would almost Infidels create, Who, beyond Love, can wisli a higher state? • Exeunt all fo/Abdelcador. Abdelc- Oh Charming Sex! —• How vast a Circle does thy Magick take? The highest Spirits humblest Lovers make. AU that Heroick Greatness, which but now Made haughty Foes and stubborn Nations bow, Turns Vassal to a Smile, a Looks disguise: Who conquer Thousands are one Womans Prize. Fate sets Commanding Beauty in their way, Beauty that has more God-like Pow'r than they: Love o're the Hearts of yielding Heroes sports * Wfco're Conquerours in Camps, are Slaves in Courts. Exit, Finis Aftat fecund/.
Page 15

The Empress os Morocco. if* Act the Third, Scene the First. —■ -— - ■ «» Enter Muly Hamet, Scene ths falace, MhIy H.•'"plsnow oar Royal Mothers Breath must bind That sacred tye of Love my King has sign'd, And Providence has seal'd: make Her bnt kintfr ~ Scene a Bed-Chambcr. The Seene opens, and discovers Crimalhaz and Qjuen Mother slee- ping on a Couch, a Table standing by, with CrimalhazV Pl$mt of Feathersi and his Brawn Sword upon it. Re-enter Muly Hamet. Muly H. Laula in Crimalhaz his Arms asleep! Ha! Does (he thus for her dead Husband weep f Oh fond and amorous Queen.' has Lust such Charms, Can make Her fly to an Adulterers Arms f His Sword drawn for his Guard, [Spies tie Swtrtlm - But he (hall die No, He (hall Wake, and Know The Justice and the Hand that gives the Blow: Should I descend to a Revenge so base, His Death unarm'd my Glory would deface: I will restore the Traytors Sword for still I have been taught to conquer those I kill. Well, as a Witness of his Crime, his Sword Tle take, which when we meet shall be restor'd. Then secretly, but ho iourably too, My Hand shall Act 1...\c to his Guilt is due. For, lest I shoul . - 0-ueens Disgrace proclaimed He right her W. . .'it lie conceal her Shame. Exit.
Page 16

16 Tfje Empress of Morocco, The Scene changesto an Ami-Chamber. MulyHamet re-enters with the fame Swords and in faffing ever the Stage is overtaken 9} the King. Kin*. Muly Hamet s stay. Muly H. The King! King. What have you there i Muly H. Curst Chance! what (hall I fay * [aside. King. You thus appear ToVe left the Field lo gather Laurels here. Wl» is the Man that has this Honour gain'd, To be fubdu'd by such a Geu'rous Hand 1 Tell me. Muly h. Your Royal Pardon. King. No, proceed. If you have kili'J him, I forgive the Deed5 Who e're against You durst his Sword unilieath Has justly from your Handdeferv'd his Death. Muly H. No, Sir, he lives, and lives unranquifli'd too. King. How, lives! Muly H. Oh do not your Demands pursue. Urge me no more, nt)r force me to reveal The only thing my Honour would conceal. King. How, Muly Hamet, durst you act that thing You dare not utter to your Friend, and King. Muly H. My Kings Esteem I by my Silence lose, And Speaking, I his Mothers Shame expose. [aside. King. Speak, if you can by Friendship be conjur'd. Whose is it i Muly H. Sir, V.s Crimalhaz his Sword. King. How Crimalhaz I Are you not newly from Th'apartment of nay Royal Mother come i In what defenceless Garb did you surprise Him there, that you disarm'd him with such ease? We o';e our Womcns Honours set such Eies, That the Seraglio all access denies. Who enters the. e without my Signet dies. Muly H.
Page 17

TJje 'Empress of Morocco. 17 - Muly H. Her Shame too openly will be descry'd j His Jealoasie will find what I would hide.' {ifdei King. A sudden Fancy does my Breast inflame, Something so strange, as I want words to name: But She's my Mother, and I dare not guess Yet She's a Woman, and I can no less Than start at Horrours which my Honour stain. Confusion! and was Crimalhaz the Man i Muly H. Oh! Sir, what has my sorc'd Obedience don f Against a Mother I've incens'd a Son. Your Princely Brow let no disorders change, Let my Hand, Sir, Your disturb'd Peace revenge. King, No, Muly Hamet has a Sword too good To be defil'd with an Adulterers Blood. He t' an ignobler Fate stiall be condemn'd; He make him infamous, low, and contemn'd. Disrob'd of all his Titles he stiall bleed, Like a Crown'd Victim to an Altar led, Whose Wreaths and Garlands to the sire are cast, And then the naked Sacrifice falls last. That sinking States-man undergoes the worst Of Deaths,whose Honours andwhose Pow'r dies first. £ exit King. MnlyH. This was the only Chance could shake my Tame. Oh weak Foundations os a Glorious Name! I from the Field do a Crown'd Conqu'rour come, To turn a base Informer here at horrre: Yet nothing is so bright but has some Scars -, Men can throngh Glasses find out Spots in Stars. [Exit. The Scene changes again to the ^Hfen Mothers Bed chamber, where She and Crimalhaz appear hand in hand - She in a Mor- ning Dress. Crim. Love acts the part of tributary Kings: As they pay homage to their Conquerour j Our kind Embraces are but Offerings Of Tribute to triumphant Beauty's Pow'r. D ojifoth.
Page 18

>$ The Empress os ktorocco. jg^ M, Great Spirits Rivals are to Gods, and can," Were all the World like me, their Heav'n unman: We'd antedate our Bliss, not stay to move, like Pageant-Saints, to airy Seats above: Weed here below enjoy our Chiefest Good , /And reap Delights which they ne're understood. . . Crim. Ha! my Sword gon 1 Madam, we are betray'd. J2^_ M. Whole he that dares our Privacy invade f Crim. Some fatal Eye our interview has seen. S>,_M. Whoe're has seen us, knows I am a Queen. That powerful Word his Silence does demand 5 - Tis Blasphemy to name, nay understand What Princes act. — Crim. Ho! Achmat, Achmat, [_ Eater Achmatt What bold Man has been Admitted to th' Apartment of the Queen? Ach. Pi i nee Muly Ham et. jg. Moih. Ha! by whose Command/* Achm. The Royal Signet from the Kings own hand Gave him Admittance. Q^Moth. But, rude Slave,howduist You violate what f commanded first f Know, Traytor, I am Mother to a King: His Pow'r subordinate siom Me does spring. My Orders therefoie should unquestion'd stand, Who gave him Breath, by which he does Command. What my Commands have mist, this shall make good. Princes are by tlieu Deeds best understood. [Stabs the Eunuch who falls and dies, Crim. Pall, and in Death all hopes of Mercy lose, Who durst the Secrets of your Queen disclose-: Closets of Princes should be held Divine, As a Saints prelence Consecrates his Shrine: And Princes Pleasures llnuld Alliance hold With their great Pow'r, bafree and uucontrou'ldo . JZ^A/oth. Is it not pily npw——- That
Page 19

The Empress of Morocco. '9 That Grave Religion, and dull sober Law Should the high flights of Sportive Lovers aw? Whilst for the loss, of what's not worth a Name, The slight excursions of a wanton flame, You must your Ruine meet, and I my Shame: And yet we must not at our Dooms repine j Because Law and Religion are Divine. Yes, they're Divine-, for they're so over good, I'm sure, they ne're were made by Flesh and Blood. But since tis past, what does your Courage think t You will not shake, at what I scorn to mrink. Crist. No, though I lose that Head which I before Design'd should the Morocco-Crown have wore: Yet what's the fear of Tortures, Death, Hell? Death, Like a faint Lust, can only stop the Breath. Tortures weak Engines that can run us down, Orskrewusup till we are out of tune. And Hell, a feeble, puny cramp of Souls: Such infant Pains may serve to frighten Fools. Fates, if I'm doom'd your Mark, Tie stand you fair j Nor will I for your Favours lose a Pray'r. Q^M.A pray'r, Devotion and a States- mao! No, The Pow's above are titular below: Stars are all Eye, and when great Deeds are done, AH their faint Lights are but bare Lookers on. Now thou art brave, none but a Heart above The shock os Fortune, could deserve my Love: But fear no danger, to our aid Tie call 'My Arts and Fiends in Hell to stop our Fall. To this Tie for our safety take recourse: Through your right Hand this fatal Dagger force: Then leave the Conduct of the Deed to me 5 Fate dares no less than my Protector be. Crimalhaz (labbt himself in hit right Arm, vehich immediately appears blood)'. Crim. Tis don. {Throws rnvay the Dagger. D 2 Enter
Page 20

30 The Empress of Morocco. Enter to them the King and Muly Harriet. King. May Heavn forgive my Eies,that they have seen This Object in a Mother and a Queen. M. Oh Son! be deaf to what will wound your Ear, Let this black Day be cancell'd from the Year. But if your Justice must his Faults pursue, Impose on Me what to his Guilt is due. . Muly H. See how she treats her Shame: Madam, I wiih Your Virtues greater, or your Birth were less. King. Since you have sullied thus our Royal Blood,' The Grounds and Rife of this past Crime relate, \_to Crimalhaz. That, having your Offences understood, We, what we canit't recall, may expiate. Crim. Sir,'Twas my fate - M. Hold, Sir, the Story does to me belong, A Womans Frailty from a Womans Tongue. Whilst pensively I in my Closet sate My Eyes pay'd Tribute to my Husbands Fate, And while those Thoughts my sinking Spirits feis'd .His Entrance my dejected Courage rais'd: [Pointing to MuIyHamct. The sudden Object diJ new Thoughts produce; My Griefs suspended, lent my Tears a Truce: For then I otherwise employ'd my Eies, Whilf: in His Aspect I read Victories. [joints to Muly Hamet. ])uts Muly Hamet, then your cruel Breast Muly II. Speak, jw. M. Let my Tears and Blushes speak the rest: M.i fy H. What does ih? mean i My lab'ring Thoughts dispatch, g^M. Your Soul and Person Nature did ill match. Such lavage Passions and unruly Heat, L-v'g'd in Your Bnast, hold a too glorious Sear. M/ly It. This mystick Language does my Sence confound. & Moth. Oh, Sir! fang. This liddling History expound- Well,
Page 21

The Empress of Morocco. at . JH^ M. Well, Sir, fince you will force my Tongue, I must Be to my Honour and my Virtue just. Having a while upon each other gaz'd, He at my Silence ,1 his Eyes amaz'd: Then, Muly Hamet, then — King. What did he do K Sl^M. Attempt to ravish me. His alterd Brow Wore such fierce Looks, as had more proper been To lead an Army with, than Court a Qjieen. And, as a Ravisher, 1 abhorr'd him more In that black form, than Iadmir'd before; But whilst my Virtue a Resistance made My Shrieks and Cries brought Achmat to my aid: Whilst th' Eunuch stood amaz'd, his Sword he snatc'd> And at one Stroke his wond'ring Soul dispatch'd. Muly //. Olr Honour! Sl^M. Then, led by some happy Chance, Kind Crimalhaz did to my Aid advance. Crim. But being by my sudden Entrance crost, And nll the Hopes of his stoln Pleasures lost, My sight did to his sparkling Eies inspire ^"fc" Such Rage, as if his Lust had lent 'em Fire: Though Justice in Her Cause did guide my Hand., No Sword could his Victorious Arm withstand: And when his Weapon through my Hand run, Tearing th' Event of what his Rage had done, He bore away my Sword, a poor Pretence, To turn his Crime upon my Innocence. Muly H. False and perfidious Traytour! [/o Crimalha;% Sir, to your Royal Favours add one more, [to the King- And Tle quit all that I receiv'd before: To this Adulterer your Leave afford To vindicate his Treason by his Sword $ That Justice, by my Hand, may give him Peats), And stifle with his Blood his peijur'd Breath.
Page 22

a 2 The Em press of Morocco King. Hold, Sir, if you this rosh attempt pursue, You'l make me think, that what he says is true. This subtile mystery confounds me more Than the past horrour of the Deed before. Crim. Alas, Sir, He, who has so savage been , To dare abuse the Honour of a Queen, Esteeming all less Crimes but sportive things. Could not want Words t' abuse the Ears of Kings. Mulf H. Hold Villain King. Hold, your Passions Rage commands You in an injur'd Mona/chs presence stand. Muly If. Can the Eiernal Potvrs such Treachery Permit < You the great Rulers of the Sky, Sitting thuspatient at lo tame a rate, In Heav'ns lose ease are grown effeminate. Is such loud Crimes your armless Pow'r out-face, Your pointless Vengeance will your Heav'n disgrace. Sl^M. Had you my Breast by Honour sought to win, Yet Love t' a pious Mother, and a Mourning Queen, Had sounded harfluBut giant that Time and Love *£_^>uld from my BosonTmy dead Lord remove: I to your Passion might so just have been, To Ve met your Love, but not ith' shape of Sin. Muly H. Madfm, You may say any tliing: Your Sex And Birth the vent of my just Passion checks. Sir,do but hear--—- [Tothe King. Crim. You may vouchsafe to hear What You may read more plainly, here, and there. Q Toints to the dead Eunuch and his mounded Arm, King. I in this Parley too much time bestow: Hearing the Cause, I make the Vengeance slow. Guards Yet Ple hear him Mnly H. My single Word a vain Defence will make, Where so much Witness, and a Mother speak. But yet Heav'n sees my Innocence 5 and know That I am proud this Shame to undergo. Believe
Page 23

The Empress of Morocco. 23 Believe me, her intended Ravisher Appearing so, I take the Guilt from Her. Their false Impeachments do this comfort bring, That I may wear that Cloud would shade a King. King. His kind soft Words do but confirm tli'Offence, Men are nere losers for their Breaths expence: But st.ll speak kindest when their Falls are near, Not out of Generosity, but Fear. It is enough She witness'd his Offence Her Virtue scorns to accuse Innocence. And since her Blood does run within my Veins By ' instinct I know she all that's base disdains. But if I want more Proofs to make it out, His Murder and his Wound removes the doubt. Muly Hamet, for this Guilt our Prophets Breatli Has in his sacred Laws pronoune'd your Death. Sl^M. His Death! f. Surprized, But hold! The King will then my Cheat descry, I wish His Death who tamely fee him dye. [ *fid*> Ocruel Sir, that killing Breath recall: \jothc King, Our holy Prophet dares not fee him fall, I'm sure, had he My Eyes. Heav'n cannot fee Such Courage bear so harsh a Destinie. The Pow'rs above would slirink at what he felt: His Death to Tears their Chrystal Orb would melt. But If You must act what Mercy can't prevent, Inflict inflict some milder Punishment. King, His Deeds and Service in Morocco's Cause May mitigate the rigour os our Laws. His Army then I to your charge commend , Her Honours Guardian, and our Loyal Friend. \.to Ciimalhaz. Here bind the Traytor, and convey him strait [to the Guard:. To Prison, there to linger out his Fate: Till his hard Lodging and his slender Food Allay the Fury of his Lustful BloocL [Guards bind Muly Ham. . vLMoth>
Page 24

5s*. Tht Empress ofltoroca. In whisper between Muly Ha- l met and ^jieen Mbtber. M. Think what Impression on my Breast 'twill make, To lee his Hands wear Fetters for my fake, Muly H. Madam, be serious, tell me bow so foul "j A Treason gain'd admission to your Soul. jPji/.My Soul! Dull Man,what has my Soul to do In such mean Acts as my betraying You f > Murder and Treason Without the help ofSouls,when I think good, Such toys I act-, as I'm but Flesh and Blood. Mu. H. Let net too high your Scorn of Justice swell: Know, Madam on such Crimes there waits a Hell. SUJU. Hell! No, of that I scorn to be afraid: I'le lend such throngs to the infernal made, Betray, and kill, and damn to that degree, I le crowd up Hell, till there's no Room for Me. King. Here, to the Tower that guarded Pris'ner fend: Hisfaither Doom from my Commands attend. Muly H. I for my former state My Homage to your Royal Father paid, And Monarchs may destroy what Monarchs made: For Subjects Glor.es are butborrow'd things, Rais'd by the favourable Smiles of Kings: And at their Authors Pleasures should retire, And when their Breath renounces'em expire. Should I the Sentence of my Sovereign blame, I should be guiltier than They fay I am. But though your Frowns declare my Fetters just, Look to what dang'ious Hand your Pow'r you trust. Monarchs do nothing ill, unless when they By their own Acts of Grace their Lives betray. Wherf Favours they too gen'rousty afford, And in a Treacherous Hand misplace their Sword, Their Bounties in their Ruineare employ'd: Kings only by their Vertues are destroy'd. Km*. Your Counsels weakly do my Ears attract 5 You ill peach Virtue which you cannot act. Live
Page 25

7be Empress of Morocco' 25 Live then, till time this fense of Hon our brings, What 'til to raviih Queens, and injure Kings. Exeunt King and Muly Hamet severally; Muly Hamet led cut by the Guards. S^M. You fee the Fates do their Allegiance know, And to my pow'rful Breath their Conduct ow. 'Tis pity Monarchs are so scarce Such gen'rous, easie, kind, good-natured things ^ That one feign'd Tear can rule the Faith of Kings. Crsm. So bravely, Madam, your Defign succeeds* As if ;he Fates were Vassals to your Deeds. That Politician who to Empire climbs, With Virtues Dress should beautihe his Crimes. Ourguilded Treason thus like Coral seems 5 Which appeais Black within its native Streams: But when Difclos'd it fees the open Air t It changes Colour, and looks Fresli and Fair. [Exeunt. Scene the second, the Scene a Prison. The Scene opens, Muly Hamet appears hound. Muly H. Disrob'd of all at once what turns more strange Can Ages, if an Hour can make such Change i Enter to him Mariamne, with one Attendant, from whom Retakes a Sword, and exit Attendant. Kind Mariamne! Mar. Yes, False Man, the fame, Till your bold Lust had forfeited that Name. The Daughters eafie Breast would ill confer A Kindness on her Mothers Ravisher. Muly H. Can Mariamne think me guilty too? More than my Chains have done your Frowns will do: Mariamne's Eyes out-vie her Brothers Pow'r. I oe're was miserable till this hour. E Mar.
Page 26

q6 The Empress of Morocco Mar. Ungrateful! is yoarSoul so much defaced* Have I so ill a too fond Heart misplaced i My Rival Mother does my Right remove: And in affront to my rejected Love Your Scorn to Me you in her Shame make good, Forcing her Virtue to prophane my Blood. But, perjur'd Man, though you deserve so ill, Yet you shall find me Marianne still. To my past Favours I will add one more. Thus I your Freedom, and your Sword restore. {Unbinds him. and gives him the Sword. Live, and in safety go, and fly that Fate Which does th' unhappy Muly Hamet wait. Muly H. My Sword and Liberty restor'd by You, To one ungrateful, false and perjur'd too! Ah, Madam, is your Mercy can confer Such Bounty on a condemn'd Ravisher 5 What nobler Favours would your Smiles difpence, If Mariamne knew my Innocence i Mar. Sir, you mistake my Favours: I have lent Your Freedom only as your Banishment: That beingreleas'd, you might Morocco fly, Remov'd at once both from my Heart and Eye. For should he stay' "j Something like Pity in his cause would plead, \ Till my faint Anger were in Triumph led. I aside. Some Rebel Thought my ill-senc'd Heart would win, • And treacherously once more let him in. J Go, Ravisher, take yourofser'd Liberty: And to some barb'rous, unknown Desart fly, Whe; e Men have nought but Shape that's humane ., there, Where Virtue looks more ill than Monsters here. Converse with wild and lustful Savages: Live. and inhabit any Seat— but i his. [_Piints to her Bret/t. Muly u. Divine, but cuel Prince's, to whom Heav'n Has all its Tides but its Knowiedg giv'n. Else
Page 27

The Empress of Morbcco. Else, like their Pow'rs, you could not want a Sence Of Muly Harness injur'd Innocence. V Can Murders, Rapes-, or any barb'rons Deed, . Madam, from your Adorers Thoughts proceed f No, Hells Commission does not reach so far, To touch his Heart, which does your Image wear. Mar. Ah, were this true! MulyH. Witness the sacred Pow'rs, If ought of truth be in a Heart that's yours, Then Crmalbaz is false. Your Mother too, (If ought that's ill can be allied to you) Has spoke what Muly Himet durst not think. Achmat his Death, and Crimalbaz. his Wound, Not from My Sword, but from Their Dagger. fonftd. The Eunuchs Blood by their own Hand was spilt j To work my Ruine, and conceal their Guilt. Mar. A gen'e Calm my Anger does astwage, Creeps cooiy o're my Heart, and chils my Rage. Some strange Divine Intelligence is stole Into my B: east, and whispers to my Soul, Unkind, Suspicious, Cruel, and Unjust; That Virtue Love had taught him you may trust. Muly H. Were I that Savage Raviiher I seem, I still might father this imputed Crime: This Prilon, and Our private Interview, Giving me pow'r t'Attempt that force on You. How dare you then ray Out-law'd Virtue trust, And lend that freedom which would arm that Lust i But did you know how clear my Soul does mine, Unclouded, and still pure enough, t'enflirine Such a Divinity as yours, you'd free Your self from Doubts, as you from Chains did Mee. Your Mothers Eyes cannot your Right remove: To prove the power of Mariamnes Love, Madam, my proffer'd freedom I refuse: Hying Morocco, I your fight sliould lose >
Page 28

a# The Emfress of Morocco.' And father than be banifh't from those Eyes, I can all thoughts of Liberty despise: For I in Fetters may your Grace implore, And make your Pity grant one Visit more.. If not your Love, yet your Compassion may Once more, at least, guide your kind steps this way.; Gaining your sight, I can my Chains out-brave,' The Brother's prisoner, but the Sister's slave. Mar. Enough, brave Prince * My Jealousie forgive: Virtue ne're dies, where so much Love does live. Heav'n cannot but, like Me, think it unjust, That so much Virtue mould in setters rust. But since of injur'd Innocence Heav'n dares Be a spectator* lie correct the Star's. I:will redress those Wrongs Which their tame patience lets you suffer. Take Once more your Freedom for your Princess fake* Fly these infected Walls, this barb'rous Town, Where Virtue mourns under a Tyrants frown. Fefore, my Rage your Freedom did Command: But now accept it from a gentler Hand. Kindness and Cruelty one doom decree: None ever Punish, and Reward like Me. Mulj h. And must I from my Princess presence fly i Mar. No, stay. MulyH. Kind Stars! Mar. Yes, in my Memory. Absent you shall in my Remembrance reigne. Tie to your Image dedicate this lbrine. [Points tv herBreast. Enter King, and young Queen, T0 the Door. Muh H. Madam; your Brother, when he hears my Swo:d, And Liberty is by your Hand restor'd, May grow incens'd to such a high degree, To make You share these Frowns which threatoed Me. And
Page 29

The Empress of Morocco. 29 And are my thoughts so low, to make you run Those Dangers which I by my flight m ill shun i Mat. Request does with a Mistress pow'r ill suite. Sir, I Command that freedom you dispute. And, if his stubborn Faith to a just thought Of your wrong'd Innocence cannot be wrought: If his rash passion natures bonds mould quit, And make him both my Sex, and Birth forget 5 Remember that you wear a Sword, and you As you're my Servant, be my Champion too. Enter to them King, Young gueen, ^Mother, Crimalhaz, Hamct- alhaz And Attendants, King. His Sword, and freedom by her hand retrived! Surely my Eyes and Eais are both deceiv'd. How! Rebel, dare you with things Sacred sport, Ravish luc Mother, and the Daughter Court i [to Muly H. Have You your Birth no better understood, [to Mariamne-s . Than to be Traytor to your own high Blood f Since Prisons no restraint o're Lust can have, Why did I not confine him to a Grave *. Muly H. 'Tis not long since your Bounty did designe Not only This, but th'Hand that gave it, mine. King. When I design'd That, I design'd She stwn'd Be in a Palace, not a Prison, woo'd 5 Not circled in a Chain, but in a Crown: Sir, You mistake a Dungeon sor a Throne. £,M. Remember, if your Memory can prove So jult, t'unravel your own Scenes of Love. Unless blest Lovers, whose desires are Crown'd, Mounting so high, forget their using ground. These Prison-walls have Eccho'd to your Sigh?-. Conscious as well of your Amouis, cs His. No setters can Lov's lawless pow'r suppress: You too have betn a Lover in his dress. Some
Page 30

go The Empress of Morocco. Some Pity then should to their Loves be fliown, , Tor their so near iefemblarice of your own. She can forgive h'.s Faults, why cannot You i If Love can Pai don, why not Honour too f M.ir. Knew you his Innocence, you would approve Both his just Liberty, and my just Love. But, Sir, you know, I'm Sisler to a King: p And in that Name I dare do any thing\ > Make where I please my Heart an Offering. S Tortures, nor Chains, lliall not my Love rebate: He share his Breast, though I should share his Fate. Kitg. Sister, your noble Pride has made me kind: Fle give him that Reward which You delign'd. Your Courteous hand his Freedom did restore j -> And lie repeat what you pronounct before: £ Be gpne, and never fee Morocco more. S At the next mornings light, if the Suns Eye Find you within the City-gates*you Dye. And the Tenth day you lose your Head, if found Within the Circuit of my Empires bound. Muly H. Now I am lost, and all my Hopes dispers't. This Monsters villany has done its worst. [to Crimalhaz. Inhumane, to your Conscious Soul- recall - Crim. The Tortures which it feels to lee You fall. Muly H. No, Traytor. Crim. Traytor, Yes Sir, I should be Traytor to Ktaron and Humanity, Should I not grieve for You. Muly H. Oh cunn ng Ignorance! These Traytors walk like mad-men in a Trance: Seem not to understand the Crimes they Act. ButXrom what spring<;,do You your Tears extract! [aside Jo&M. jg.A/. From fpiiligs so deep ilia!] sink Thee down to Hell'. I Ihed my Tears as Rain in Egypt falls, Sent for no common cause, but to foretell [aside to him. Deductions, Ruins, Plagues, and Funerals. I
Page 31

The Ewpress of Morocco. 31 I ne're draw Tears, but when. those Tears draw Blood. King. My Justice in iuspence too long has stood. £l^M. How, Justice i no,I your Cruelty. How can So harsh a Doom against so Brave a man Be Justice i View that Brow, that Ch innlng Eye: See there the Grace and Meen of Majesty. Can you to Exile then that Man enjoyne, Whose Soul must, like his Aspect, be Divine? Oh Son! [Weeps.2 King. His Sentence 9 already past; And now her Kindness does h;s Rune hast. Be gone, and sly to some infected A!re, Where Poysons brood, where men derive their Crime?, Their Lusts, their Rapes, and Murthers, from their Climes: And all the Venome which their Soils do wanr, May the Contagion of your Presence granr. Muly H. I must obey you, and embrace my Doom With the same patience Saints do Martyrdom. Only their Suffering's a Reward receive They Die to meet that Happiness I leave: They Die, that in their deaths they Heaven may fine' But in my Princess, I leave Mine behind. And my hard Exile does this Horrour bring, I lose the power to*serve so good a King: So Good, that 'twould as great a Bliss confer To Die for You, as 'tis to Live for Her. Since in your Kingdoms limits I'm deni'de A feat, may your great Empire spread so wide, Till its vast largeness does Reverse my doom - And for my Banishment the World wants room. King. Fie hear no more. But for this Audience know % How much you to my gracious Favour owe. His Mercy s great, whole Patience is so strong, To give a Traytor leave to Talk thus long. [ E.\eu,;t Miditung Oaten*
Page 32

37 TJje 'Empress of Xforoccv. Mar, Farewel for ever. When you're gone, and all Mariamne ever Lov'd, or ever shall.— She sees.no more* Yet by despair made just, Let not our Hearts take leave, though our Eyes must. Though you through wild and savage Defarts go, -No place so barren, but where Love may grow. Muly H. When to your ears some gentle breath shall bring The last Remains of a lost wretched thing, That lived as long as he could gaze on You j And shined, till that inspiring Lght withdrew. Is Fame vouchsafe words on a wretch so poor5 When you shall hear I was, but am no more-; In my Lost feat let my Remembrance stay: Give my Name life, though Grief take Mine away. [ Exeunt Muly Hamet And Mariamne severity. Crivt. Fate and our Wishes meet. £>±M. His Exile is not all: Our Treasons are not safe but in his Fall. He Lives, though he be BaniuYt h and the Great Are never fully Dark'ned, till they Set: This Cloud may pass, and He mine out once more 5 But from your hand this favour I implore: Pursue him out of Town, and in disguise [to Hametal. 'With some dissembling .Tale his Ears surprise^ Till your Confederate-Party has gain'd time > To place an Ambuscade, and Murder him. Unmet. Conclude it done. Si^M. And your next step t'a Throne [to Crimalhaz. Must be, dear Sir, the Marcher of my Son. Crhn. His Palace And the kind City's love's so strong a Guard, Th'Attempt within these Walls appears too hard. SLM. But what that Bars, this Easier way secures: His Army, and his Treasures Charge, are yours. To Morrow on tliej^lam before the Wall, H:s Forces you t'a general-muster Call. Then
Page 33

The Empress of Morocco, 33 Then their Commander You shall in their Head His Army to the Mountain Atlas lead: And to secure your Flight, to night by Stealth Ransack his Trealury, seize all his Wealth. At first Alarm, this will his Courage damp: But by such Arts, I his Resolves will sway; Tie work him from the Town up to the Camp, And safe into your Hands his Life betray. But when Your Throne I on His Grave have built, Remember Love was Authour of my Guilt. Crim. This work, which we so roughly do begin, Zeal and Religion may perhaps call Sin. No j the more Barb'rous garb our Deeds assume, We nearer to our First perfection come. Since Nature first made Man wild, savage, strong, And his Blood hot, then when the world was Young: If Infant- times such Rising-valours bore, Why should not Riper Ages now do more? But whilst our Souls wax Tame, and Spirits Cold, We Only show th'unactive World grows Old. ^. m. . [Exeunt Crimalhaz, *nd Ywng guten. Hamet. Muly Hamet Bleeds the next. To him, who Climbs by Blood, no track seems Hard: The Sence of Crimes is lost in the Reward: Alpirers neither Guilt nor Danger Dread: No path so rough Ambition dares not Tread. \jEnit. rinU Aft its Tertii. Act the Fourth, Scene the First. Enter King Attended. King- TTOw! Cnmal/jaz up to the Mountains fled, *1 And with him the Morocco forces led. Oh Rebel J F l.Lord.
Page 34

g4 77m Empress of Morocco. 1. Xpri. Sir, he only does pursue That Treason which you lent him Pow'r to do.' He was your Treasurer, and has niade bold To be too strict a Guardian of your Gold. All your Crown-Jewels, and your heaps of Wealth, He in the Night convey'd away by Stealth. And now Encamped on Atlas skirts, he by your Gold Has Rais'd new Forces, and Confirm'd the Old. With that he Bribes your Army to his Cause j And aster him new Trains of Rebeils draws. King. Oh Prophane Gold, which from infectious Earth, From Sulph'rous and Contagious Mines takes Birth. It grew from Poysons, and has left behind Its native Venome to infect Mankind. Rapes, Murders, Treasons, what has Gold not Don? If it has ever any Glory won, Given to Reward a Virtue, or decreed T'a Pious use, or Charitable deed 5 That Sacred Powr's but borrowed, which it bears, Let from their Royal Images it wears. Enter Queen Mother. 2. Lord. I am afraid his Thoughts fly High, his Dreams Have little less than Empires for their Theams. King. On what 111 subjects I my Favours cast f Him high in Pow'r, and Honours I have plac'd. Kings Bounties act like the Suns Courteous smiles, Whose raves produce kind Flowers on fruitful Soyles: But cast on barren Sands, and baser Earth, Oiily breed Poysons, and give Monsters Birth. 2. Lord. Let not too far your Pears your Peace molest: Perhaps you've mis-interpreted his Breast. You know that Crimalhaz his High Command Was formerly in Muly IImett hand.
Page 35

The Empress of Moracco. He who forced Favours both from Fate, and Fame 5 Made War a Sport, and Conquest but a Game. And therefore he, perhaps, to Act some Deed Which Muly Harness glory may exceed. Has for his Mistress from the common Rout Of the worlds beauties singled Honour out. And that which makes him his Defignes disguise, He'll make his flight of Honour a surprize. King. No, he's a Tray tor, and he'll use my Pow'r Not to Promote, but to Usurp ray Crown. Pow'r swoln too High destroys, not guards % as show'rs, Luxurious grown, what they should Cherish, drown. Our Swords in Loyal hands may act great Things: Be both the Glory and Defence of Kings: But when misplaced, those Arms our Ruins be: As Mountains bulwarks are at Land, but Rocks at Sea. j2^J/. Can you Rebellion fear, or any thing Who are my Son, and great Moroccoes King? If he be False, you can't resist your Fate: If True, his aim will be to guard your State. But grant he would some Traytrous act performc: Accept ray Counsel to divert the Storm. Lip to the Mountains strait, and visit Him. Your Awful sight may check an ungrown Crime; Out-face his Treason e're his Rise begin: Men Basliful are i'th' non-age of a Sin. King. Madam, your dauntless spirit would breath sire To breasts as cold as Age. I must admire Your Courage: but your Innocence mistakes. Your Goodness in my Cause weak Jndgment makes, Your Thoughts can't Reach the flights which Treason takes. SUM, You've hit my Thoughts: Alas, I am too good, Treason's a Thing 1 never understood. But yet I understand what's High and Brave. He dares not, Sir, abuse that pow'r You gave* For lie who sav'd my Honour, will guard yours: That very Argument your Life secures. F 2 TI
Page 36

i 3 c? The Empress of Morocco Then trust to Fortune, and my Counsel. Go And visit him5 but wear nojealoas brow: It makes men False to be Suspected so. Tle be your Leader. King. When She leads the Way, Though it were Death to go, 'twere worse to Stay.' Madam, l'le go. For Taffaletta's Armes In few dayes March will reach Moroccoes Walls. If Crimalhaz prove False, at his Alarms Muly Labas by a forreign Conq'rour falls. Staying, I tamely Peristi % if I go, I face my Ruine, and I Charge my Foe. It will more like an act of Courage look, To be by Ruine met, than over-took. But at my sight perhaps he in my brow May something read which his High thoughts may bow. Kings that want Armes, do not want Majesty. - Heav'n is still Heav'n,though't lays its Thunder by. [Exit with At- SUM- Go easy Fool, and Dye,and when you Bleed, (tendants. Remember I was Author of the Deed. T'enlarge Fates black Records, search but My Soul: There ye Infernal Furies read a scrowl Of Deeds which you want Courage to Invent 5 Qf which Hells legends want a President. Scene the Second. The Scene opend, if presented a Prospect of a Clouded Sky, with a Rain bow. After a shower of HaU, enter from within the Scene. Muly Hamet and Abdelcador. Abd. Such Storms as These, this Climate never knew: A Show'r of Hail's an Object strange and new I fear it does Portend some Dire Event, That waits upon your Fatal Banishment. Muly h% My Countiy, Princels, and my King forsook: Stormes to my Miseries like attendants look. These
Page 37

The Empress of Morocco. 37 These Tempests Sir, are to my Sufferings due: When my King Frowns, 5tisJust that Heavn frown too. But why does my dear Confident- intend In my Misfortunes thus to run my Race i As Drowning men sink those whom they Embrace.' Abd. Po not my friendships right forbid. With You I've been a Conq'rour, why net Exile too ■ Shall my Esteem grow faint, or my Zeal less,/ Because I view you in a Meaner dress, Your outward Pomp laid by, and Honours raz*d? The Saint's not less, although the Shrine's defac'd. Enter Mariamne mth a [malt Attendante. Asuly H. Mariamne! Mar. Yes. And she who led by Love, Leaves Palaces, and does to Delarts Rove. Wing'd by that zeal united Souls do beare Those Stars that smile on Lovers, brought me here* I for Your fake my wandring steps engage: Devotion is the rise of Pilgrimage. MulyH. Can Love in Hearts such deep impressions make- That you can for your Wretched Vassals fake Leave Courts, Pomp, Greatness, and all splended things? Mar. Sir, 'tis the fame with Lovers, as with Kings. Thus, if a King should with his Train resort To a poor Cell, he makes that Cell a Court. Oh Sir, the most Illustrious Queen on Earth, Would quit the Pageantry of Clowns and Birth: And in exchange Muriamnes Exile choose. Could she but Love as Mariamne does. Muly H. Oh my kind Princess; King and Court farewel: Where pointed Honours, & feigned Glories dwell: Lovers when hippy ma le, havt? Souls that scorn Those guilded wreatlib which swelling brows Adorn,

Page 38

38 The Empress of Morocco. Mar. Mar'iamne has this glory on her side, That kiadness you- call Love, \ call my Pride. 1 Tor of my Constancy——— > Any less tryal I disdain to make . Then mew I scorn an Empire for your fake: And whosoe'xe does my ram Flight condemn, The meanefs of their Censures I contemn. None of my Actions can fit Judges be, But they who've foul enough to Love like Me. Lovers alone Loves causes can decide,. As Nobles only by their Peers are Try'd. Bitter to them Hametalhaz disguised in the Hsbit of a Priests with Villains in the fame Dress, Ham. Sir, our great Prophet has pronounc't your Fate, Your Love is doom'd to be Unfortunate. Muly H. No Sir, 'tis False, thou doest belye his Name: Our Prophet is a Lover as I am. Ham. Your Mistress too must your Misfortune find. Muly H. To her our Prophet cannot be unkind. She is a Princess. Ham. No Titles his eternal will confute. Muly H. She is a Woman, and he scorns to do's. Did not thy Gaib protect thee Mahomet To wrong her Sex his greatness would forger. Ham. No Sex is from ill destiny debar'd. Muly H. She is a Beauty, and that Name's her guard. Good fates as due should oe to Beauty given: Beauty which decks our Earth, and props his Heav'n. When Heav'n to Beauty is propitious, It payes those Favours it but lends to Us. Ham. Oh, do not Sir, their Oracles decry, W ith patience hear the Language of the Sky. Heav'n when on Earth some Change it does fore-shew, Does write Above what we must read below. This
Page 39

the Empress of Morocco. 39. This Morning, as our Eyes we upward cast, The desart Regions of the Air lay Wast. But strait, as if it had some Penance bore, A mourning Garb of thick black Coulds it wore. But on the Sudden Some aery Demon chang'd its form, and now That which look't black Above look'd white below. The Clouds dislievel'd from their crusted Locks, Something like Gems coin'd out of Chrystal Rocks. The Ground was with this strange bright Issue spread. As if Heav'n in affront to Nature had Defign'd some new-found Tillage of its own . And on the Earth these unknown Seeds had sown. Of these I reacht a Grain, which to my sence Appear'd as cool as Virgin-innocence: And like that too (which chiefly I admir'd) Its ravislit Whiteness with a Touch expir'd. At the approach ofHeat, this candid Rain Dislolv'd to its first Element again. Mulj H. Though sliow'rs of Hail Morocco never see, Dull Priest, what does all this Portend to me i Ham. It does Portend Muly. What i Ham. That the Fates defigne As*//. To tire me with Impertinence like thine. Here a Company of Villains in Ambnst) from behind the Scenes dif- charge their Guns at MulyHamet3 at which Muly Hamet starting and turnings Hamettalhaz from under his Ffiefls habit draws a Sword^andpafjes at MulyH.it'/^/V/; pass is intercepted by Abdelca- der. They engage in a 'very ficrccFightjvhichtbc Villains, who alfa draw and assist Hametalhaz,4/fc/ *o off several ways Fighting ., af- ter the discharge of other Guns heard from within, and the C la fl- ing of Swords, Enter again Muly Hamet, driving in some of the former Villains, which he Kills. Muly H. Dye Staves. and may this desart raise a broo.i Of unknown Monti. s from you: venem'd Blood. My
Page 40

^.o The Empress of Morocco. My Princess gone, Fortune and Justice are • '/. -'- Suie not so Blind, but they of her took Care. Enter Abdelcader. 'Abd. Your Princess Sir, is from your Armes divore'd, In her own Chariot to Morocco sore'd. Mii!y H. Tle fetch- her back, though Abd. Hold! With their fair prize,they've took so quick a flight, That She is now beyond your reach and sight: And the chief Leader of those Villains, was The Old Queens Confident, Hametalbaz. And all the Story which the Slave did frame, Was only to gain time to take his aim. They chose that Garb as what might best prevail, To gain your Patience, and their Swords Conceal: But missing of your Blood, your brave Escape Chang'd his intended Murder to a Rape. Muly H. Hell and Damnation, these curst Traytors seize. But why against such Barb'rous Savages Do I in vain these useless Curses name They are such Brutes, that they ivant Souls to damne i No 'gainst my self I should my Curses bend, Coward so ill my Princess to defend. Abd. Oh Sir, do not profane your Conq'ring SworJ, Their Numbers were too great to be o're-powr'd. Muly H. How, Numbers! Abdelcader, you mistake; No Sir, where Love and Beauty is at stake, True Lovers of their Swords stiould make such Use, As angry Heav'n %f Threatning Earth-quakes does5 To (hake whole Kingdoms, make proud Cities fall, Not to o're-throw one single Criminal. Had they been Thousands more, and each man there, More Feirce than Lust, more Valiant than Despair, I mould have Fought till I my Princess freed, Though I had waaed through the Blood I shed. Abd. Sir, the last words she spake that reacht my Ear, Were, that lhe did your passions Rashness fear: And
Page 41

H The Empress of Morocco. ^ And therefore from me bid yon understand, 'Tis your kind Mariannes last Command 5 You ne're should see Morocco more, lest there You mould endanger what she prized too dear. Muly. II. And am I banisht by my Princess too i Fates ye have done all th' ill your Powers could do 5 Great Minds the pride of Prodigals have Learn'd, At loss of Pow'r or Crowns are unconcem'd $ But when they're Misers, 'tis in Love alone, Then their Hearts rend to fee their Treasure gon. Condemn'd never to see Morocco more! Thus am I doom'd to quit all I Adore .- As piophane Sinners are from Altars drlven, BanisiYd the Temple to be banifht Heaven. Horrourand Toituresnow my Jaylours be, Who paints Damnation needs but Copy me j For if Mankind the pains of Hell e're knew, T'is when they lose a Mistress as I do. f Qfc.vwr. Scene the Third, the Scene a Tent. Enter Queen Mother and pung Queen. Queen. M. No more, dear Madam, Crimalbaz distrust, The Emperour has found him kind, and just. His Entertainments, and his Oaths have prov'd, He has not from the paths df Honour mov'd. And to appear extravagantly great, He makes a splendid Mask his this nights Treat. r. Queen. I've been an Actor in such Comick Sport, When in my Father Taffaletta's Court. He took delight i'th* represented Spoyls Of Cyruj, Cesar and *Æne&$ Toyles. Queen. M. Has Marriage and a Crown so chang'd your Will, You could not act your youthful Pastimes Hill < Could you your Greatness for one Night perfwade To lay by Majesty for Masquerade G T Queen
Page 42

4* The Empress of Morocco, r. Quse/i. I never yet did any thing so ill I ought to leave, or good that is not still: I seem inconstant if you think me Proud $ Inconstancy the guilt of th' untaught Crowd. Madam, I dare do any thing, toshow T a Throne I change of PlaceS not Passions owe. JjKMother. I can't suspect a goodness so Divine. Well Madam, since you fancy the Designe, For yonr Diversion, and your Kings, H'e ask This Boon, that you'd in person grace the Mask. What Character and Part you shall present, We will consult of farther in my Tent. £E*< Enter King and tUmetalbas. s_Scene co{ King. Murder'd this Night and steeping did you fay * > Hamet. Yes, if for your escape Heaven finds no way. King. My Entertainments Imce my beiag here, All mows of Loyalty and Friendship beare. But dees he in that Garb his guilt Disguise To take my Life, by such a base Surprize i . Hamet. Goo.lness may in Mens very Looks be Tracks 5 But Tray tors- rarely look like what they Act: Nor is this Treason Crimalbaz first Crime: Your Fathers Bloud was sacrifie'd by Him. King. By Crimalbaz my Royal Fatner Kill'd? Hamet.. That Poyfon which your Father drank, He fill'd. A'/ws, Poyson'di How was this Murder hid till now, Aud by what arts was it disclosed by You t -5i w. That were too long to tell: th unhappy Son i.s Night too must the Fathers Fortune run. King- h there no Policy, nor Art that may

Enter £hieen Mother. P. trust Sis Treason *
Page 43

The Empress of Morocc9. M. Yes I've found the Way. Accept my Councel, to preserve my Son, l le save your Life, -your Empress, and your Throne. King. But how? M. To you this Night he does a Mask present, A trailing Prologue to his black intent. And the intrigue of this Dramatique sport, Is Orpheus his descent to Plutoes Court. To fetch Furidice from th' infernal shade On this Foundation I've this Structure lay'd. I have in your Name given out To shun the trouble of the formal State, Which does upon your Royal Person waite; That this nights Pleasure may be freer made Your Self and Train will be in Masquerade. Yoar Death being not designd before you sleep, Till then you thus will undiscover'd keep, And that your flight maybe more safe and free, Ycur Self, and your fair Queen shall Masquers bs: You shall act Orpheus^ (lie Furidice. When by the Ma?ks design by Hells Command, Furidice is given to Orpheus Hand, You the last entry shall his Shape assume, And in dumb show enter in Orpheus Roome. Her then you shall lead dut, and in that Shape Pass through the Guards, and to the Town Escape. Ham. The Watches Orders are not strict,' you may Without distuibance at all houres find way. Sl^M. And that he may not miss you till you're gon Beyond his Reach, I, when the Mask is done, Will keep the Revels up, till you're secur'd From hisshaip Malice, and his sharper Sword. King. Bravely contriv'd. M. The Maskers, who already are design'd To act those Parts, are Mine: and them l ie bind To silence : That this safely may be wrought, She shall to Mine, You to his Tent be brought. Ga
Page 44

44 ^* Empress of MoroccipF --' They must be kept asunder for our work. t^fitk] - Hamei. How many Devils in one Woman lurk! t'M3 Madam in vain your Pity bids me Fly, I am in duty bound to stay and Die 5 Knowing how ill your Kindness heel requite, If he mould find you Author of my Flight. £>±M. Leave that to Providence: but grant he fhou'd—- He would not sure attempt aWomans Blood. At least when he considers how t' was don, A Mothers Piety to save a Son. Hamen Tle lead you where you may all eyes escape, And privately put on this borrow'd lhape. ^ M. But in disguise see not one word you say, Least speaking you the Emp'rours Voice betray. Enter twng Queen. Your Empress here i Imust instruct her too. King. I by our Loves conjure you to pursue, What her kind Counsel orders to be don 5 \to the T. Queen. To save your Sels,a Husband5and a Crown. [Exit K.& Hametal. T. ^ What Task is that so strictly he enjoyns? Sl±M. This Nigfit theTraytour Crimalhazdefigns To Ravish You and when that fact is don, To kill your Husband and possess his Throne. r. ^ Oh my Amazement!: jj^As. Being ihform'd what Pa t You act, by his accursed Lust enraged, He with the Masker subt'ly has engaged, His shape in the last entry to aflume, And seize you in the suppos'd Orpheus room. Then will he rudely snatch you from the place, And basely force You to his foul Embrace. And at that instant, Your dear Lord shall Bleed By Murderers appointed for the Deed. Whil'st with the noyse of Drums, and Trumpets found, Your Out-ciyes, and his Dying Groans :re drown'd. r. Q^
Page 43

the Empress of Morocco, 43 r. SL, Inhumane Monster! such a bloody Fact Mo mortal sure can Think, much less dares Act. H^M. Tisbut toorrue: But since No other force this Treason can withstands It is Your Husband, and your Kings command, When the bold Ravistier seizes You, to take This brave resolve for your fair Vertues fake $ Where both your Honour, and his life's at stake. In your Defence t* act your own Champions part, With your drawn Dagger stab him to the Heart. r. ^ Could Fate This Othce on no hand but mine confer f A Queen, aTraytours Executioner. Sl^M. You have no leisure to dispute the deed: You must resolve with Courage, and with speed. r. l'le do't. And thougn it misbecomes my Hand 5 Yet at my Vertues, and my Kings command, Through all my Veins I feel a manly heat .. And this Heroick act looks brave and Great. Methinks I hear loud Fame already sing, She nobly saved her Honour, and her King. g±,M. Fame in this Deed our Sex will higher prize, Proving our Arms Victorious, as our Eyes. T. §h YesRaviiher, meet your intended Prey; Meet ner, but meet your Death too way. To strike my Dagger home Love and Obedience shall that strength supply, Which Nature does t' a female Arm deny. {ExH M, Let those, whom pious Conscience awes, forbear, And stop at crimes because they Vengeance sear. My deeds above their reach, and pow'r aspire: My Bosom holds more Rage, than all Hell Fire. LSxh
Page 44

The Empress of Morocco. The Mask. The Scene opeud^ is presented a HeU, in which Pluto, Proser- pine, and other Women-Sprits appeared seated, attended by Fu- ries; the Stage being fill'don each fide nv/AOimalhaz, Harriet, Mother, and all the Court in Masquerade: After [oft Musics Enter Orpheus. Orpheus Sings. The grones of Ghosts and Sighs of Souls, Infernal Ecchoes and the Howies, Of Tortured Spirits cease: +k A gentle Gust Has all things Huflit; And Hell in spite of Vengeance is at Peace: Whilst Ravifbi by my warbling Strings, The Vultures moult their Wings $ The Furys from their Heads will shake Each useless Snake . The Scorpions loose their Stings, And Hell it self forget their Tyrant Ktngs. Pluto Sings. Whence Mortal does thy Courage growy. To dare to take a Walk so Low*. Orpheus Sings. . To Tell thee God, thou art a Ravijhcr. No Tears nor Prayer Tour unrestfled Will Controules, Who Commit force on Vertue, Rapes on Soflls. Pluto Sings. Dares a weak Animal of Mortal Race, Affront a Gods his Face; And of a Crime Impeach a Deity f 7by Breath has Damrid Thee, thou shalt Die. For your God and Honours fakes, Unloose your twisted crests of snakes: Into his Breast those swift Tormentors fling,' And his tor turd EntHtls Stingl y Proser-
Page 45

Blank page
Page 46

Blank page
Page 47

the Empress of Morocco, 47 Proserpine Sings. Oh Sh, ms fatal Doom recall Biff el your furious Anger; Let not such noble worth your Vittim fall: Se kind both to a Lover and a Stranger. Attendant Sings. oh Pardon, Tardon what his height of Lcve discovers^ Rage is a venial Sin in Lovers. Proserpine Sings. Then gentle Stranger tell; What Fortune has beftll> That brings a Lover down to Hell t Orpheus Sings. 2 have a Miflrcss in your Spbeare, Forced from my Armes By deaths Alarms: My Martyr d Saint brings mt a Pilgrim here? My fair Eurdice my fair Eurdicc. Proserpine Sings. Unhappy Wanderer which tsjhe 1 oh which is she? Orpheus Sings. if a gentle Ghost you bare, Complaining to the Winds, and fi?hing to the Air:; Breathing an unregarded Prayer: if She in faint and murmuring Whispers Cryt Orpheus Orpheus, oh I Die, Snatch'd frct*> Heaven and tbee, Oh that is She. Oh take me down to Her cr (end Her back to mt. Pluto SiogS. Shall Levers idle Prayers disturb my Bare t Mortal we'v'e fcrU'is business here. Tour tiresome Story pleads in vainc j Be con. Prefer-
Page 48

Tloe Empress of Morocco. Proserpine Sings. But with thee thy fair Treasure fStyj Releast by Love from that Eternal chain, Which destind Kings and Conquerours cannot break. \ Pluto Sings. 2io, fond Man,.no, who comes within my Power, From Death and Hell returns no more. Proserpine Sings. // Hell's strict' Laws have never alt'red bin. Let us be kind and now begin. Revoke her angry Doom, That when on Barth they come5 To tti wondring World he in [oft Aires may tell, Mercy as well as justice Rules in Hell. Pluto Sings. Tour love does with Success implore: Conduct Her in, but in such state, As fits the Court of Pate j And to bis Hand the fairest Guest restore, That Ever Landed on the Styginn Shore. Proserpine Exit, and Jleenters with the you#% gucen Dreji for Euiidice Orpheus. For this stgnal Grace to the World fie declare, In Heaven Earth and Hell Loves Pow'r is the S4>ne. No Law there nor here, no God jo Severe, But Love can Repeale, and Beauty can Tame. Chorus. For This Signal Grace to the World Tle declare. In Heaven &c. Here
Page 49

The Empress of Morocco. 4$ Here a Dane* is perform d* by several infernal Spirits* who ascend from under the Stage ., the Dance ended* the King offers f snatch the Young Queen from the Corns any* who instantly draws her Dagger* and stabs him.} T. §L. Take that Ravishcr. [slabs Him '} M. Hold. King. By my Morenas hand! [und/fguifinghimself,} T. Muly Labas I QFaint* away, and salls into the hands of some Women who run in to her Assistance.} [Here aS the Masquers undifguisc* and run in to the Kings assistance,'] ^ M. My Son k I'd by Her hand! Crim. Call my Physitians. Bid my Guards appear. The Emperou: Snb'd, the Queen his Murderer 1 SKing, Have I for this a too fair Saint admii'd 1 And with a more than common Love inspir'd, Rais'd my bold Thoughts so high t'engrois your Charms-, And bounded my Ambition in your Arms 1 And must I die as dtpos'd Angels fell 5 'Cause they afpir'd, and lov'd their Heav'n too well f My death Morena a less pp.in will be, T han 't:s to think 1 owe my death to Thee. Have I less kindness from youi Hands than Eyes, for they have given me gentler wounds than tlitse f Your hand, 'tis true, his your Adorer Ki'ld. 'T has rcacht his Heart, but not the Love it held. Your im..^<: cr.nnot from my Sonl retire j My Lov's Immo.tal though my Life expire. LDJei3 [Here the Young gueen being revived before the hfl words of the King, turnes and kneels to him.'} T. <Hj Oh my desr Lord! Stay gentle foul! Oh stay! Rude Death stand off: his life's too great a Prey 1 But Oh he's gon. His rav.m'c Soul is mounting to the Skyes: But Me send mine t'o'retake it as it fives {.offers to stab be/ [elf but is detain d by Crimalhaz; and the Dagger fnatebt from her. H 7. £.
Page 50

'fc. The Empress of Morocco. r. Why docs your cruelty ray hand debar, From being a Traytors Executioner i .Good, Gentle, Kind, give me the Dagger back . For mine--for His— For Heav'n— and Justice fake. Cannot my Tears and Prayers your heart o'recome i If my Request appear too burdensome, Grant but this one— that pointed Steel restore, And Tie not live to ask you any more. M. Oh cruel Queen, What has your fury done? That made You lose a Husband, me a Son; This Realm a King, the World a Virtue, grown Too sit for Heav'n, but not to go so soon. r. g. Mother it does a much less wonder seem, That rvckU'd him, than that you blame the Crime. Was it not You that arm'd me to this guilt, Told me I should a Raviihers blood have spilt i No 'twas by your design my Husband fell ., You in this Masque have over-acted Hell. M. Alas! she Raves. See how her rage begins, But madness always uilieis in great Sins. This is no News to that which she has don; She was distracted ere the Masque begun. Alone I saw her in a posture set, As if me thought of something High — and Great — Strai t with a more than common rage inflam'd, She aiov'd-star'd-walk'd-storm'd-rag'd-curst-- raVd & dama'd. With a distorted look me tore her hair Unmeath'd her Dagger -— and gave Wounds to th- Air —- Her face difcolour'd grew to a deep red, As if her looks presag'd that blood (lie (lied. Then with an infant Rage, more soft, and mild, She plaid with madness, leap'd, fung, danc'd, and smil'd, Why did not Heav'n this Mystery unfold i Her frantick Rage, his Death too plain foretold, Had I foreknown you did this blow design: To strike his Heart, you Ihould have ptirc'd through mine, 7', «<£_. Think you there isa God, or have a Soulj That on my fco;e da.c such false dimes enroule i Hi
Page 51

Tlje Empress of Morecco. 1'st not enough that my dear Lord I flew* But must be Actor and Designer too? No, barb'rous stepmother,'twas you alone Guided that hand, that kil'd your King, and Son. / g^. Observe bow idly her wild fancies walk, But she who acts so ill, as ill may talk. Who'd think a thing so young, so soft, and Fair, Could be so kind a Husbands Murderer i But fee when Heaven commands its gifts away, The Wits and Sences lost, the Soul may stray. r. Oh perjur'd Woman, how can you invent This feign'd disguise to appear innocent? M. 'Tis pity Fate such Beauty should misplace, So stain'd a Heart, and yet so fair a Face. r. Impostor, speak (if Conscience have a Seat, In Traytors breasts) was it not You whose Cheat, And Cunning did my fatal hand engage, At once t' a Murder, and a Sacriledge? To kill my King, and rob mankind of more Vertue,than ere dwelt in one Brest before. Q. M. Divert thy Frenzy Child, some other way. Oh, my dear Daughter, try if you can Pray. r. gK How the disowns that blood which she has spilt! * Treason with her is but a modest guilt. gl^M. Our presence will but raise her Passion higher.. T'allay her srantick Rage, let us retire. But of your Queen fee that strict care you keep, Wait her to her repose, try if iliee'l Sleep. Sleeping, some Angel may be kind, And in a Dream t'her thoughts her guilt present, That when this fit is o're she may Repent. Here the Attendants carry off the King, over vehom the Young Queen Weeps. Y. g>j Heav'n; fince from Yon the power of Monarchs springs, Sure you were bound t'have had mote care of Kings. Uxeunt all bm g. Mother, Crimalhaz and Hametalhaz. H 2 SL M-
Page 52

$i the Empress of Morocco. z SUM. Now in her Death we must some way invent, hat of his blood we may seem Innocent. First let her Face with some deep poys'nous Paints DiscoTour'd to a horrid black be stain'd. Then say 'twas as a mark of Vengeance given, That she was blasted by the hand of Heaven. And as a publick Spectacle expos'd, Let her be in a burning.pile inclos'd. And whil'it the clouded Air reeks with the smoke, Hire a magician by his art t' invoke A Train of Devils, who in dreadful forms, Waited bv Earthquakes, Thunder, Winds, and Storms, Shall rovei'th' Air, and with loud ecchoes houle ^ As if they watcht to seize her flying Soul. Thus will men think, 'twas only she that fi am'd TJiis Treasonj and that for the deed (he's Damn'd. J Crim. Bring back the Queen E're I sec Justice don,' I.with Morena will converse alone. Enter Guards leading in the Young Queen. Great Empiess stay, and.hear my Story too, S Discourses in.wh/f- Howmuch I for an injur'd ^.ueen dare do. < per with the Queen» Ham. The Emp'rours acting of the Masquers part, His Murder, and th£ management, your Art ;\ And her feigned madness to our wiih succeed. SUM. And more than this to have securd the Deed, Had not Her hand struck home to back her Ciime, The Surgeons I had brib'd to poyson him. 'Tis not the blood of Sons nor Monarchs, shakes Those resolutions which my Courage takes. O re Fear and Vertuetoo, I have this odds: My W U's my King, my Pleasures are my Gods. [Exeunt £*M. & Ham. Manent Crimalhaz & T.jjjinftn, Crim. S nee I'm a Monarchs Heir, may I not own, An equal Title in his Love as Throne i if* you'l accept so m<an an Offering,? you; shall not want a Lover nor a King-
Page 53

The Empress of Morocco $ j My kindness /hall supply T.*^ Hold Do you mean, Thisotter'd service to an injur'd Queen f - How Sir* is my dead King so far remov'd, That I am past remembrance that I lov'J f f Admit new Courtihips, and with the fame Eye, Behold a murder'd Soveraigns Ghost stand by. I thought your profer'd kindness had been this, To've sentenced me to mix my blood with his. ToVe told me I should Die, and ilying have The Happiness of steeping in His Grave. Crim. Death is guilts due. Yours is a gentler Doom 5 You may enjoy my Throne, but not his Tomb. I know >our Innocence and Vertue. You This fatal Deed from some false Copy drew. And Ibeg:n to think your Mothers Hearr, Has Poyson in't, what- ere her looks impart. But to revenge a. Murder'd King, l le sound This Treason, till the utmost Depth be found: And to siich pains the Authors 1'Ie condemne, That to the World Tle your lost Tame redeem. T, Ml A Kings Revenge so brave an act will be, That you'l at once Oblige both Heaven and Me. And his blest Spirit in the Skyes must owe, A Debt, which he has left unpaid below. Crim. That trifling score one smile from you will quit. And sure yon are so kind to pay his Debt. r. ^ My Thanks are granted e're your Suite is heard. Crim. I must have more than Thanks for a reward. T.Si.. The Glory of the deed requites the pains. Crim. But Glory only in your Tavour Reigns. 7\ That Breath I cannot, must not undetstand. Crim. Love needs but little art to be cxplain'd. r. gh Love! stop that bnrbrous Breath, faa new Love J I stab his Image, and profane his Dust. Crimi.But not to love your Champion is unjust. h5 r.^
Page 54

f± Tlje Empress of Morocco. T. J£. Your Service I accept, your Love take back. Crim. None hate the giver who the present take. Why can't your Heart T. g. — Why can't your Arm revenge A King, without my Heart paid in exchange i Know though you balely trade with Loyalty, My Love my Kings revenge does over-buy. Co, Mercenary man, I will resigne His Vengeance to the hand of Heaven, n<k thine. Crim. Let such harsh words be by tame Lovers borne, My Passion is too rough to bear your scorn r. And must my Heart at such a price be sold 1" Thy Seat Ulurpt before thy Blood is cold i This was thy Right, and though thy Death I gave 5 Who lov'd the Martyr will the Reliques save. My Heart by none but thee was ever won. I r Tie guard the Trophy, though the Conqu'rour's gon. ^L^f'*6 But stay — This Grant is to revenge thy Blood, And on that score no Offering's too good. I should scorn Love, Life, Honour, Empires, —- all To strike their Heads whose Treason wrought thy sail. J Can you on no less terms my King revenge i Crim. No second Thoughts my Resolution change. Since all I act is only for your fake, Love must accept those offers Love does make. r. ^Well Sr, my Heart is won. Your Seige remove, I condescend to any thing — but Love. [ Retreating from him. Resign that Heart that's His Heav'ns, shall I live to act so great a Sin! To right a Monarch must I damn a Queen? Be gon! I hate thee now worse fhan before. Descend to thee 1 No, I that Thought abhorre. And though hi? Blood does loud so: Vengeance call; I know fceeM scorn his Queen so low should fall. Though I have lost a King, I'm net so poor*, The Temple ruz'd, t'leRuincs l'!e a-iorc. Crim.
Page 55

The Empress of Morocco. 55 Crim. My Love's too fierce long Seiges to attend: You've lost a Servant, and your King a Friend. {.offers to go, T. SU. Stay-— No, be gon I scorn thee— Yet Sir stay, Hopes of Revenge so much my passions sway5 That what would I not do for Justice sake. (band Where the assault's so strong, hereConqu'rour take \.Cives her Crim. Oh my best hopes -— {.K'Sts ^er t. SU. My — friendship — give my Love! — My Love my Soveraigns Right I rate aoove The Ranfome of a world s and is thy hand Does not perform what his loud wrongs demand 5 Thou art his Murderer. Crim. But when you fee that murderer wear his Crown, You shall too late repent your haughty Frown. s_ Off ers togOj. T. Hold, ere the pleasures of Revenge Tle want, Invader, here what e're you ask Tle grant. Crim. Oh Charming Excellence! r. SU. But Sir. Loving too soon, I shall convince the Faith Of Men, that I design'd my husbands Death. Crim. 'Tistiue, some marks of sorrow should be worn To please the Woild 5 l le give you time to mourn. r. £K_ When you ve appeas'd his Ghost, and th' angry Pov.'ij Above and to his sucred Memory My last debt's paid, all that I am is yours. Crim. My Vow's the seme. First to Revenge lie fly, With Traytours Blood Tle entertain your Eye. E're you're my Queen, and wear a second Crown, Tie build a ScarsolJ first, and then a Throne. [f..<il 7. ^ I ve fouuJ tne way. Oh my dear Lord, thoU£*i now Deathdoes embrace what to my Arms is due 5 I'le keep My Vow to Him, and Love to Thee Entire. No second King lh all to this Throne aspire. s_ Points ti b<r Brcr.J}. To Thee my last Debts payment shall be this3 l ie die --.-- and dead all that I am is His.
Page 56

^6 The Empress vf Morocco. In thy Revenge when I've Triamphant stood, On Tray tors necks amid'st a Scene of Blood 4 Morcnis hand shall wash the stain She. wears $ As Condemn'd men turn Executioners. To expiate thy blood Tle let oat mine, And triumph in my fall, who mourn for thine. Then with a gentle gale of dying sighs, Tle breath my flying Soul into the Skies. VVing'd by my Love I will my passage steer, Nor can I miss my way when You shine there. Exit. The Fifth Act. Enter Crimalhaz attended as King, Crtm. t | * Hough on the Blood of Kings my Throne I've built, I The World my Glory fees, but not my Guilt. A Mysterious Majesty best sits a Throne. They Vertuous seem whose Vices are unknown. Men have ador-'d and have made Offerings To unknown Gods,why not to unknown Kings. [Enter Ham. Ham- Your Guards are set, your forces on the Walls, And in the Streets are rank'd in sighting forms $ Expectingwhen the martial Summon calls, And Tajfalttta this proud City storms. For our last Scouts which newly are come in, Tell us th' assault will in few hours begin. Crint. I thank him for this War he has begun, The number of my Foesenlnnce my Crown. v It does a worth on Kings as Beauties (et, To have our Rivals numerous and Great. But is th'imprifon d Princess, whom your Sword Itavisht fom Muly Hamets hand, fecur'd From the Worlds knowledg Ham. Royal Sir I have The pride to be her Jaylor « and her Slave. Inside.'} Cam.
Page 57

The Empress of Morocco 57 Crim. Muly Htmt arid MarUmne ate the last Of the Imperial Race, that have not past To th' other World, to make me room in this. But though your hand did of his murder miss .. Howe're his exile has restrain'd his Pow'r: :.... And her I have conceai'd within the Tow'r. But should (he be discovers, and I found Her Jay lor, her restraint would horrid sound, . . I am not safe then till I fee her Dead, You therefore mall present me with her Head. Ham. Mdriamnes Head presented by my Hand!"]' I'de first strike his that gives me that Command. For since that Beauteous Prisoner was my charge, Her charming Image did my Soul enlarge. > .r. At the approach of so Divine a Guest, J,ae' I've (hook my late familiars from my Breast $ The thoughts of Mischeifs,Villany and Blood s By her fair Eyes inspir'd I dare be good. Exit. Enter Queen Mother. M. Though your Designs have met so great Success, Doe not forget I was your Patroness \ And she to whom you made this solemn Vow, \jo Cfim. ] That I mould (hare that Throne I rais'd you to. Crim- The highest Seat in all but Monarchs Breasts Should be by th'high'st of Passions, Love, Possest. But Kings in so sublime a Region Move: They have Concerns that must take place of Love. My Subjects call for Veng'ance, and I must To the dead King before my Love be Just. Then give me leave to prosecute his Death, First wear the Cypress, then the Myrtle Wreath. jj^jtf. Bring in the Queen If She dehy our Love, Let out her Blood and those weak Bars Remove. Enter Guards bringing in the Young Queen. Muly Labis his Queen and Murderer, To Expiate his Death you are Summon'd here. I To
Page 58

The Empress of }dorocc9. To prove how much the World by you has loft, And what Atonement's due t' a Monarch's Ghost. r. £. Yes Madam, when great Princes Die, l'de have Their Majesty kept up beyond the Grave. Such streams of Blood should foitheir Murders psy Their Ghosts should have a Train as great as they. ^ M. See Sir (he begs her Death as a Reward: Use Charity.do not her Bliss retard. [to Crimtl. aside Crim. In Common Murders Blood so; Blood may pay: But when a Martyr'd Monarch dies, we may His Murderers Condemn; But that's not all: A Vengeance hangs o're Nations where they Fall. £^M. Wo Tedious Introductions to her Death: Good Sir make haste,more business and less Breath. Crim. Who wears his Crown can best defend his Cause. I'le on his Murderer Execute such Laws, The Rigour of my Justice shall declare, How high-I rate that Majesty I weare M. No Prologues to her Death,let it be done; I could have kil'd ten Queens while you are judge One. Crim. Therefore to profecure his Death SZ^M. Speak Home. Crim. I on hi* Murderer must Pronounce a Doom— Sl^.M. No Mercy, be Severe. Crim. —- As may Express, . I can't do more, nor con his Blood ask less. Guards, I on You th. t Office do Confer, Obey my Orders, seize Th;s Murderer. ^JHere the Guards Thy poylbn'd Husband,and thy murder'd Son* c seize the ^ M. Th;s injur'd Empress, and Moroccoes Throne, Which thy accursed Hand so oft has shook, Deserves A blow more Fierce than Justice ever strook. M. g^M. Inhumane Villain, Monster, Devil \Strnglingin Crim. Silence her Fury,Stop her poyfon'd Breath--^ the Guards. And check her growing outrage by her Death. But since to Me you've been so kind t' impart, Some Favours, and a Tide in your Heart: jfa-
Page 59

The 'Empress of Morocco. «59 In Gratitude and Honour, you shall have This Mercy, to walk gently to your Grave. Bid my Physitians a strong Draught prepare, And leave her Execution to their Care. Ungrateful Slave \. . Crtm. Go-- He not hear her Plead, No Arguments shall save a Traytour* Head. All his Revenge demanded, 1 have done; (tttbiT*£*ee». Perform your Vow, accept my Love and Throne. ^ M. Hold Sir---1 ask not Life such acts of Grace Your Bounty may on little Sinners pass. My Sins are but too Capital, —- My Son, AndPoyfon'd Husband —- What have I not don i . So many Treasons and such bloody Rage, Would fink an Empire and defame an Age. No found but Deaths haish Name, my Soul could Daunt: Now all my Sins my frighted Conscience Haunt. Guilt onely thus to guilty Minds appeares: As Syrens do to drowning Mariners: * Seen onely by their Eyes whose Deaths are Nigh. We rarely see our Crimes before we Die. And now they 're seen, I'm with such Horrour shook They seem so large, I dare not Upwards look. Where's all my Confidence, and Courage driven i Guilt ne're grows baihful till it thinks of Heaven. Though I want Pow'r to ask for Mercy there, I will look down, and beg my Pardon here. QKneels to the T. §. Fair Innocence, I for your Pardon sue, T' a condemn'd Traytour, but a Mother toe: Let her repenting Sighs her Griefs impair? Who thus — Offers her Tears- - and thus— thy Heart. Stubs the Toung glueen. Die Rival — and Die Traytour— \_Runs to stab Crimalhaz, but being stop by the Guards stabs her Jelf. — Then Die Thou. Crim. Morena Kild! 1 2 gL -
Page 60

%q The Empress of Morocco. Sl^ M. Yes Sir, and l'de have don the fame for Yon. But since my Dagger has so feebly don, Missing thy Breast I've sent it to my own. If some kind Devil had but took my part, I'had pierc'd thy Bosom, as I've don thy Heart. . Curse on weak Nature which my Rage unman'd, A Masculine heart linkt with a Female Hand. My Stars had been more just had they design'd Me less of Hell, or less of Woman-kind. T. T'express my Gratitude,thus low I Bow: [_tt tbe§^. M. Murder was ne're an act of Grace till now. Your Curteous Arm retrived mine from a Guilt, Morenas Hand, Afortntu Blood had spilt; Had not that stroke more kindly been decreed. You ne're did act a Mother, till this Deed: Here — T perform my Vow -—1 S To Crimslhtzgiving When IVe resigns, c hm her Hand. My Soul to Him — take — all I leave behind. Thy death, Dear Saint; reveng'd, and mine so near, Sucn charming objects to my Thoughts appear: In hopes IshallmeetThee, my Joy's so high, Methinks I visit Heav'n, before I die. My mourning Soul durst ne're one thought encline. To fense of Joyy till it drew nigh to Thine. Heaven's Blisses are a prize Love only Wins, Where my Life ends my happiness Begins. XjDjcti As. Is this your Thanks for ail her Love has done I Who staked her Soul, to raise Thee to a Throne.. Durst you Perfidious Villain, with one Breath, .Pronounce Her Coronation and my Death f . But I've reraovd that Rival: Thanks to Me^ Her wandring Soul is mounted to a Cloud, But you may Court her still — in Heav'n — if slie Can heat so far, and yon can talk so loud.. Crim. Though against Me your Rage had just pretence j Yet how durst you assault such Innocence i
Page 61

The Empress of Morocco. 61

/QrM. Let single Murthers, Common Hands Suffice: 'I Scorn to kill less than whole Families. In all my Race, I nothing find that's ill S But that I've Barren been j and wanted still Moriarchs to dethrone, more Sons to Kill. * \ctions are scarce worth the Memory, And I am yet too Innocent to Dye. Had but my Hand performed thy Muither too, I mould meet Death with smiles upon my Brow. But Oh my Spirit's Faint — yet I have Breath, Enough to make a Prayer before my Death. If there be such a place as yeilds abodes, To Souls that scorn the company of Gods: May I in Hell hell's greatest Torments bear, Provided 'tis thy Doom to meet me there. C-ty" 1 Crim. Infection stick upon thy blasted name, Thou Foile to Monsters and thy Sexes shame. \J° SU,M^ But here my Heart to Pity does Incline: JjoT. %Hccn, Till now I smil'd at blood, but sigh for Thine. Veitue farewel, I could bewail thy Fate--— But 'tis a Cowards Crime to grieve too later Fury's the Mourning garb great Spirits weare, From this day for thy fake no Lives Tie spare. I will send thousands to attend thy shade, Lust made me King, Love has a Tyrant made. Remove those breathless objects, those dumb mows* Of Majesty j now Tie for deeds prepare: This morning must begin and end a War. Kind Tafalet does for my presence Call, I am invited to his Funeral. The little Champion with impatience waites, To beg a Tomb before Morocco's Gates. And rather than his lingring Fate delay, Tie with my Army take a walk that way. His heat of blood, and lust of Downs mall cease $ Lasht to a Calm and cooi'd into a Peace.
Page 62

6 2 77j* Empress of Morocco. Entet Hamstalhaz in baft? aso*»d of Trumpets beardfrommihia. Ham Your Army's routed ere the War's begun, The City taken, and your Empire won. , »». And tlns surprising Conquest is not gain'd, l By Tajfalcts but MhIy Hamets Hand. Crim. Muly Hamet from his banishment return'd! Ham. Yes, at the News of th' Emperours Death Concern'd 5 That his great Master was by ycu betray'd: He came to TaffaUt, and frankly made A proffer of his Sword : which brave demand] Was by the generous King thus Entertain'd. Welcome brave Friend $ MhIj Hdrnet was ne're taught To back, but head those Armies where he fought. That Fame and Glory then which waits on thee, Shall nei 'e be lessen'd when you Tight for me. With me, brave Youth, thou shalt my Forces lead, And fight my Equal in my Army's head: When to your startled squadrons he appears Taffalets General, who late was theirs. Their former love renew'd, such Changes wrought, That they forgot the Cause in which they Fought. A sudden Clamour Ecchoed through the Throng, Which Mulf Harriets Mulj Hamet, Rung. By their own nands the Gates were straight pul'd down, And he in Triumph marcht into the Town. They paid to him what to their King they owe j And proudly now aloud proclaim him so. .Crim. Draw up my Forces, Rouse my Guard, Tie try, Who's the succesful Rebel, he, or I. Tie write my Vengeance in whole streams of Blood, Fortune take your free Choice, be ill or good $5 I dare your Worst: Yet I deserve to be your Favorite. Tyrants are kind, to those they cannot Fright. [Exeunt.~\ T.nt er
Page 63

The Empress of Morocco. Enter Muly Harriet, and Attendants with dram Swords, dfter a found of Trumpets. Muly H. My Cause subdues more than my Sword, the Town Does at my Feet their prostrate Armes lay down. Conquest sounds best, and Glory brightest mines, Where Loyalty, net Force, the Lawrel wins. Lead to the Palace, through the Guards l ie break, And to th'Usurper I'le in Thunder speak. To the infernal Shades Tie fend a Ghost, Stain'd with more Sins than all their Hell can boast. His Blood, dear Prince, mall pay for shedding thine. No Cause so just, no Rage so fierce as mine Where Loyalty and Love the fuel bring, A Ravish't Mistress and a Murd red King. [Exeunt. The Trumpets continue Sounding, and dashing of Swords is heard from within. Enter Crimalhaz, Hametalhaz, and Attendants, with draw/t Swords, as pursued. Crim. And Muly Hatnet Fighting in their Head. Ham. Fly quickly, Sir, ice where your Guards lye Dead. The furious Muly Hamet leads 'em on, Whose Fortune, and whose Sword has Wonders done. Your Guards hew'd down, He by no Force wichstood . Comes now this .way to sacrifice your Blood: He with such Fer.rs your making Palace fills, That w ith the Honour that he brings he Kills. Crim. In this long Story, all I can descry, Is, my Crown's go ng, and my Death draws nigh. No, 'ris no common Thunder strikes me Dcid: I've a Rot.-eat yet left to save my Head. [Trumpets founding. I by t!i; j.Hand my sinking Throne wilt stay, And :^.g:» to Morrow, though I fly to . [Exiurt.
Page 64

64 the Empress of Morocco. The Scene Changes. - Enter Muly Haniet and Abdelcador Attended. Abdel. Kind Tafalet Concern'd to owe this Conquest to the Charms Of your Victorious Presence, not his Armes r Scorning to wear that which his Armes ne're Won, Frankly Surrenders you Morocco's Crown. Muly H. Well .generous Prince, this offtr'd Crown With Thanks and Envy shall Accepted be5 I'le be a Monarch to act deeds like Thee. He re Mariamne appears from the Balcone dive. My Pi incess, the bright Charms those Eyes convey, Compleat th'imperscct Triumphs of this Day: It do« a larger Happiness sfford, To have a Mistress, than a Crown Restor'd. Here at your Feet, kind Providence has thrown Your banisht Lover, and your Ravisht Crown. Your influence, and my Armes so happy prov'd 5 Th'usurpers Scepter's to your Hand remov'd; His blood, when he his forfeit Head dares sliow, Shall pay what to your Brothers Dust lowe. * Enter to her Crimalhaz into the Balcone. Mar. My Jaylour here. Crim. Though I am fain so low: My fortune lost, I may a Beggar grow. This Mercy does on generous Spirits wait, You always pity the Unfortunate 2 And on that score Tie beg one modest boon . Tie only ask you to restore my Crown. Muly ll. Thanks Heaven, the only man whose Head I wani Ot n. Do not thank Heaven, for what It cannot grant. My
Page 65

the Empress as Morocco, My Head, fond man, is for thy reach too high 5 I from this Castle thy weak arms defie. Immur'd within the walls of this strong Tower, I am so safely Guarded from thy Power $ That I dare tell you, yes and boldly too, This Head you threaten mail be Crown'd by you. Muly. H. What means this Impudence Crim, To end the Strife I ask a Crown a Ranfome for her Life. [.Drdtvs 4»d points his Sword at Mariamnes Breast' Muly. H. Here I my baffled hopes of Vengeance lose: To right my King my Mistress I Expose. Crim. 1 know your Passion has a tye so great, xThat for her fake you'le quit th'Imperial Seat. I knew your Vertue is so strong, that if , You swear you will protect my Throne and Life, You'le keep your Vow: Swear then by all those Powers Which the Religious World fears and Adores, To quit your Claim to Empire Swear You'le make Me Monarch in that Throne which youl'e forsake, And with your Blood you'le guard that Crown you give . If so, your Mistress shall have leave to Live. Though you quit Empires, you shall meet these charms To sleep, and dream of Kingdoms in her Arms. .v If not, prepare to fee her amourous Breast, Give entertainment to this Iron Guest. To this your Answer. Muly. H. Savage Infidel, Monster, there's not a hand on this fide Hell, That dares attempt that Deed $ there's not one Dart In Heav'n, that would not strike the Murd'rers Heart, Before his hand mould touch her sacred Brest. Crim. Since you are with such Heavenly raith posfest, To think Ih'has Champions in the Skies $ lie try, Who'5 the best Executioner, Heaven or I. Muly.H. Hold Barbr'ous, Crue!5 hold your murd'iing hands. Think on the Vengeance which that Crime attends: K Think
Page 66

66 Tfje Empress of Morocco Think wsiat a fierce Revenge I for her sake, Will on my Princess bloody Murd'rer take. Mar.' Hold Muly Harness let his Rage goe on. Can You but think ofsear when I have none i Crim. Tortures and Wracks will prove a vain design: That hand that (beds her Blood shall let out mine. Speak quickly then, e're words will come too late: My Crown restor'd, you'le yet redeem her Fate. Muly H. My Lawrels, Crowns, and Empires are all yours. Crim. Swear then. Muly. H. I swear by tMe Eternal Powers, Tor her Lives ranfofhe I thi&ofPring make: Morocco and your Crown Tle give you back. To my last blood I will your life defend , In Wars your Champion, and in Peace your friend- Crim. A filent Grotto, and a shady Grove, Are far more proper scenes than Thrones for Love. And though your hand and hers no Scepter bears, You Lovers may get Kings to be my Heirs. Mar. Tle bind my Vowl>y the fame pow'rsyou/wore. Tle to a Thousand Deaths my Life expose, Before I will one Inch of Empire lose. 'Tis not,bold Slave, fny threatens death can make [To CrirrW My female fears my Right t'a Throne forsake. Heir to a Crown, though you so fierce have been, Mariamnt scorns to die less than a Queen. Crim. So brisk young Champion! Have at thy Heart. Muly. H. Stay Sir. Oh cruel Marlamnt can you part i:rom Love and Life to rob the world and me f Mar. No Muly Hamtt^ a worse stain 'twill be To have my Crown resien'd, than my Blood spilt, iof the two Will choose the lesser guilt. - - l'ame never mall in Histories express, Born to be great I yeilded to be less. Muly. H. If you aspire to greatness, that Tie grant? .Your Muly jJamtt Empires cannot want- Whilfl
Page 67

The Empress of Morocco € J Whilst he possesses You, and wears a Sword* And if our Africk does no room afford ..> l ie travel then to some remoter Spheare, Till I find out new Worlds, and Crown you there. Mariam. Tis Honour and not Crowns that I esteem. And sliould I basely yield my Throne to him ^ My Name and Story would but poorly sound,'' Who rais'd a Murd'rer, and a Rebel Crowsi'd. No, if at worst I by this Traytour Dye-7 Adore my Name, and love my Memory. Yes Mighty Man, perform this Valiant Parr, £ T§ Crirti- Bravely and boldly pierce a Female Heart: Let stoiy boast, you this great deed fulfil'd 5 Your manly hand an unarm'd Woman kil'd. Crim. Since you at scorne and daring are so good, Tie feel your Pulse, and try your heat of Blood. Guards fire the Castle. And while that burns Tie a new shape assume: Tie Sport and Revel with more pleasing Charms, Than Nero when he fung to burning Rome. I'le fing my Funeral Obsequies in these Armes $ l'le Ravim her Then throw my self and her into the Fire, And arm in arm together wee'U Expire. Burn, Burn the Tower. Enter Hametalhaz, in the Belcone with Guards, wh? seizes Crimalhaz and difarmes Him. Ham. Before this Tower takes Fire, you'le want a Head. Crim. Hametalhaz stand off j am I betray'd! Ham. 1 have no time to answer your demands: Deliver him to Muly Hamets Hands. The highest Triumph my weak Arme're gain'd, Is to present this Princess to his Hand. [Crim. is forced down hj Mnly.//.Her life preserv'd and he the instrument! {the Guards* What Miracle of Honour has fate sent f Sure Heav'n acts Wonders I Wonders, no 'tis none K 2 What
Page 68

$8 TJie Empress of Morocco. What have th'high'r Powers todobut to take care, Of so much Vertue and a Face so Fair? Enter Crimalhaz below, led in by Guards. See him Convey'd to Execution straight': He as he rose in -Blood in Blood shall let. trim. Since I must die, and die Condemn'd by you: Hear Heav'n, for I ne're troubl'd you till now. .« So may my body rot when I am Dead, / Till my rank dust has such Contagions bred: § My Grave may dart forth Plagues, as may strike deat| Through the infected Air where thou draw'st breath. Others may fancy pleasures more divine, I know not where: this sball in Hell be mine- To think. when dead Iyetcan Death Convey, And what my Arm can't act my Ashes may. \_Exit Guarded with Abdelcador. Enter Hametalhaz Leading Mariamne. Mulj.H. My dear and best Life, welcome. By thy Hand, My Crown, my Happiness and Heav'n regain'd. What mystick Blessing docs my fare pursue , To see her Sav'd and fee her Sav'd by you i' Ham. Oh do not at this mystery admire: Nothing is strange which Beauty does inspire; To punilh Treason and preserve a Throne , Are due to Mariamnes Eyes alone. When to his hand I gave that beauteous prize, Design'd for hisambitionsSacrifice: When her hard fate, and her bright Charmes I saw. These did my homage3 that my pity draw. Something so kind I to that face did pay, That to Serve her I could my trust betray. Had I been born a Prince, and, in that name Like You, Erected Trophys to her fame: In all things then I had your Rival prov'd> . And confidently told her lhat ILov'd, But
Page 69

Tfje Empress of Morocco. 69 But wanting worth I wanted words, and chose This way my speechless Passion to disclose. I would defend what I could ne'reinjoy, And break all bars that did her Peace destroy. But I too lateresolv'd a flight so high: I cut my wings before I thought to fly: Too quick to work, too weak to prop her Fall. My Penitence could not my Sins recal, Till this blest moment and your influence gave Her dangers and his insolence a Grave. -. Mnly H. Such Honour and such Love ! I am Conquer'd heie, My Deeds and Passions are below thy Sphear. But as your Worth, your Pow'r shall out-reach mine: Subjects my Homage pay, but Monarchs thine. [Embraces him. Ham. Though Heav'n by me her threatned life secures, And saves her blood tobealiy'd to yours. Despair, not Friendship, yields to that hard task.} I bravely give what I durst never Ask Hold Heart while I this Treasure do resign,. And Crown her Bliss with that which ruins mine. I perish at her feet whom I adore, The greatest Wracks are nearest to the shore. IdarUm. Such Language may by Chastest cars be hcafu, Your Love I must admire, and he reward. A Nobler Passion Story never wr.r, That turn'd a Traytor to a Proselyte. Thou best of Converts, Muly. If. And of Rivals too. Sii, as a Ti ibute to your Venue due, All Honours Merit in a Court cau meet, And a kind Monarchs Love, lye at youi Peer. Ham. Hold, that great act of Mercy must not pal"- Let not your first days R^ign a King disgrace. Os such high Bounty I'm unworthy still: My good Acts have not yet out-weighed my ill No —- 7*
Page 70

jo The Empress of Morocco, To some far Country, I from those Eyes for ever will remove, I cannot stand the siglit of hopeless Love. Pilgrims, whose Z ears more blest though less Divine, Go meet their Saints : but I must sly from mine, [offers togi'. Muly, //. Stay I conjure you ., stay you shalt, you must . You've made me Great; Let me not be unjust. Speak what Command. what Pow'r,what Grown you'l choose. Ham. Crowns, no, such little Favours I refuse. None but the place you hold my wish can bound. But since I. have your free offer to be Crown'd, x It is accepted : I a King will be, Andes my Raign make this my first Decree, This Criminals Banishment, and to pursue My state, a Conqueror and a King like you 5 To what ei'e place my wandring steps incline, 1 le fancy Empires for Tie think her mine. [.F.\it Ham. Here the Scene opens, aridCrimalhaz appears caff down on the Cauncht seeing hung on a Wall set with spikes of Iron. Enter again Abdelcador. • Abd. See the reward of Treason $ Death's the thine Distinguishes th'Usurper from the King. Kings are immortal,and from Life remove, From their Low'r Thrones to wear new Crowns above: But Heav'n for him has scarce that bliss in store: When an Usurper dies herai^ns no more. MhIy. H. My Justice ended ; now Tie meet a Crown: Crownsarc the Common Prizes I have won. Those are Lntayld on Courage. No 'ti* You Can only yield a Bliss that's great and new. The Charm of Crowns to Love but dull appears: Rai^ning's a wliole lifes toyl, the work of Years. In love a day, an hour, a minut's Bliss, !s all Flight, Rapture, Flame, andExtafies. Love's livelye. Joyes so quick and active move 5 An Acic in Fmpire's but an Hour in Love. Exeunt omies. HPILOGUE
Page 70



EPILOGUE. Tills Play like Country Girle come up to Town, Longd t'appear fine-, in jewels, and rich Gown-. And so, Hoping it's Pride you Courtiers would supports To please You, lost its Maiden-head at Court. Pufft with theglitt'ring of your gaudy Charms j It feard to meet no danger in your Arms. And though the harshest Censures he its due j Jet kinder ufa^e it deserves from you. A generous Gallant though tired and Cloy'd, Should still speak well of what he has enjoyd. Should you damn this you would your selves reproach; 'Tis barb'rous to defame what you debauch. Nay, now you've Cast it off, yet do not Frown: Though like the refuge of a Miss oth' Town, It is turnd Common, Tours for half a Crown. - T'was generous at Court and did for Love3 But does for profit to the Stage remove. Women and Wit on equal scores begin $ V Love and afittion first may make 'um Sin, r 7 hey trade for Interest when they're once got in. . But for you Sirs, who Censure but not Write; f' Who do in Wit, as some in War, delight s r Whose Courages do not much care to Fight: '. But though they cant of Scars nor Conquests vapour. 7hey can drawsteges and take Towns;/; Paper. Ton



72 The Empress of Morocco. You 't will be hard to phase j Critiques whose saving and Condemning, Jl/H Ts not your Aft os judgment, but your Will. Who equal choice in Plays as Faces make, 'J Vhat you resolve, not whiqdcscrVcs shall take, 7 hus your applause resemb la your Amours, slave we not seen (On loves almighty Powers!) A Wench with tallow-Looks and winter- Pace, Continue one Mans Favorite seven Tears space: Some Ravisliing knack iih' sport and fomtbril^motion. . Keeps the gilt Coach and the gallants Devotion. Be to this Toy ihus kind, and you will raise Much better Fancies to write better Plays. When meaner Paces are usd kindly by ye, What Power have greater Beauties to deny ye. So your kind Smiles advance thescribling Trade -" To get good Play's you must Excuse the bad. * FINIS. * ERRATA. Firstpigcofcht Kyiille lin? 21 real Kv.bvir.pig 2.l.ii.r.«'*a? ihii eUi. p.9.!.ij. T.f:ilbi'd,\.i6.r giUii. y.12.1 ?i.rfeIe*Mr po io»(.) P l91.2?.r. {fund; p. 21. 1. H.r-banJhaJ'uu p. 94.I.21. r< Lin;- p. j?. I. 4. r. tints 1.29. r wiih,p. 42. r Eu- tidist. p.45.1. r.M ih: ajy- p. $3 i.tf.r. /t./*;;{(, p. S3.I.2D. dele iirj, p.So.I.j. r. h:r Htarii,pAi.l.i%. r. Ruse >r.) Qwd. p.$$ I.15. r. fy;?.
Page 73



THE BORROWER WILL BE CHARGED AN OVERDUE FEE IFTHIS BOOK IS NOT RETURNED TO THE LIBRARY ON OR BEFORE THE LAST DATE STAMPED BELOW. NON-RECEIPT OF OVERDUE NOTICES DOES NOT EXEMPT THE BORROWER FROM OVERDUE FEES.

Page 78

Ths Empress of Morocco. 15485.5.1.5 Widenar Library 001523570
