The scowrers : a comedy acted by Their Majesties servants, . | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
The scowrers : a comedy acted by Their Majesties servants, .
Author
Shadwell, Thomas, 1642?-1692Shadwell, Thomas, 1642?-1692
Published
London :Printed for J. Knapton,1691
Description
53 pages ;22 cm
Rights
Public Domain, Google-digitized.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc1.31822043035971

Table of Contents

    Front Cover
    Title Page
    Section 1 on page number 1
    Section 2 on page number 5
    Section 3 on page number 9
    Section 4 on page number 21
    Section 5 on page number 23
    Section 6 on page number 24
    Section 7 on page number 26
    Section 8 on page number 30
    Section 9
    Section 10

Book Text
Front Cover
Page Scan 1

Blank page

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 2

-）） ） } - . .s: --~~



Page Scan 3

• ， ， ， •••• • • • — ------
Page Scan 4

------ ----

End of Front Cover. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Title Page
Page Scan 5

T H E C O M E D Y, Aćted by Their Majeſties Servants. – - Written by - - - T H 0. S.H. A. D. W. E L L, Poet Laureat, and Hiſtorio- - grapher-Royal i Printed for fames Knapton, at the Crown in - St. Paul's Church-yard. 1691.

Page Scan 6

w - - - - - - - - - - - ~ w - - - - - - - * - - f - - l --- - * * - - - - - - * - - --- -- - --- ". º º *- ------------- - * - - - t - - - - - -- - * - - --- > - - - - - - * - - - - - - \ - - - - - - - . . - - - - - - * - - -- *. - - - - * - ~ - - - - - - - - - ** * .* * * * * 't - - -- - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - - ~ - - - - - - - - * - * - * - * - - - - - - * - - - - - - . - w - - - - - t - \ * º - - - - º --- - - - - *- - - w * - - - ~ : _* - . * - - - -- - º - - - - - - - ~ * - - - - * | - - - . *s- - : ** - w -** * * * -- - - - - - --- -" * • * - -- - º * * - - - - - *- - - - - - - - - f - - * - . - - - - - - - - | - - - - - - _ \ ~ -- - f ~ - - - - - - - - - - y º - t - * . . - - - - - - - - - ſ . - - - - - - - - * --" * -. • --> .*.*. - - - z - - * - * - +. .* - º - - - - - * x - * - * > * º * - - - - # - * > . * - - - - º - - - *- - t * - *** *-4- t - - - - - - - - N w - - - º º - * º: - ,- * º - - - * - w - - - - *. * - 3. - - - * - - - * - * t - - - - - - - . ** – tº -* s - * v - ~ * * a. * * - - - -- ... • - *. * * ~ * * * - - \ * - - : -- -- *. - • * - - -- º - - - - * - t - º * , - * . º - * - * * * º .* *-*- --- * * -- - **** - - - t t - - ** * - - - s -- - - * - * - - - - - º - -- - º * -- ------- - - - - - - - - - - - --- * --- ~~ - º - - - - - - - -- - w "w - - - - - - º - a - • : - * * * - - - s - - \ - v ºr , , ; "Y tº , , ; * - - - r * *. * * , , ºf * * - "... * - - - - - º * * - 5- - - - - -* J. : : l fº-- -- ** * , - - * * : * - - - - - - - - * - - - - * r - º ... x f º * . - º - - - ! -- ------------------- - i - º - * * º * - * - * - x. * - - - - - - * - - - - .* * --- - w - - - - - - - - -- - º º º - - - - º ----- ~ . - - º w - - * * * º - *. * * -- - - - -- - - - * . - - * = - - - - * - - -- - - - - - - - !

Page Scan 7

-- - z -, * - | `s *~ • . . . ; - * * * ----. ** - T A. - “. - - - - - - - **** sº -- - º - * - . . . . . . . - --- - , - . . . . . . - 1 ſº ºf cy - *-* A-. - - tº ſº, - - * . . . O - - ‘. . . . . . . * * *- : *, *, *, *, * *** ***, ~ *- 2 . " ^ - - l - - - -- *- -- - - '** w ** - ... A * - - 'O - *** * ** - * - - - . . . . . . . . . . ; ; ; ; , ; ** - , , Mr. Rant, Father to Sir William. º Mr. Kynaſton. Sir Will. Rant, - . . . Mr. Mºuntfort. Wildfire, Scowrers. . . . . . º . . . Mr. Williams. Tope; . - . . . sº . . . . . . . . . Mr. Leigh. Whachum A City Wit and Scowrer, imitator - * * * - ' ' | Sir William, ". º •) º: º: - - - . . " - sº -- . T. - - #. His two Companions, Scoundrels. F Mr. %. Sir fict. Maggot, A fooliſh jacobite Alderman: , , , Mr. Bright. Ralph, Sir Will's Valet. Mr. Bowen. jaſper, Mr. Rant's Valet. . . Will Peer. - - *- : * * Lady Maggot, Wife to Sir Richard, Mother to Eugenia. Mrs. Leigh. - Eugenia, . . . . . . . . Mrs. Barry. Clara, sº .. Mrs. Bracegirdle. Priſcilla, Governeſs to Eugenia and Clara. - Mrs. Cºry: . Lettice, My Ladies Maid... . . . Mrs. Richeſon. Abigal, Sir William's Houſekeeper. . . . . Mrs. Osborn. #;" |}rwowhole 2 ' , . . . . Glazier, vintner, Drawers, Fidlers, Tradeſmen, Duns, Conſtable, - watchmen, Buttler, and Footmen. - - - - - - - - * * * . . . . . . . . . . . . * - - - … . . . . . . . * * * * * ‘. . . - - * . . . . . . . . . . . . . . * º N. . . . . s- ,- . . . . . - \ , w - - s - | - - r - - , , ------ -- | * * * - ſ . . * - f º - º - - - • , --- - • * - - - - * - - - * - . - - } - . . . . . . . . . . * **, . . . . - * - - - - - * * *- * . . - . . . . . . . . . . - - - -r-, . - -. - - * * ~ * -- - " . - - . . . . . . . . . . * - - - - - - “....-- ... . . .--" " “. . .: * - - * > . . . . º ~ – w - - - - - - - - - - - * . • ,- - º - . . - y - - *. - * º - w - - ---- - - --> s - - - - ºf * * * _- - - * § º - ** - - - - 2- - • - r * - ~ - - \ - s:

Page Scan 8

P Ro Lo G U E. * * . - - *** * - - - - " *** Aº . . ...**.* *s - - *- … --- - --- *-* * T - cºrers * Methinks bººk ſome Ladiet ſay, ; : ; ; ; ; ; , , - S *Hºllºwełe be lºdneſs of this Playhºº ** -i-. § * * * * The Author begs the Title may not fright, Of what he does to vertuous Ladies write. ... Others for guilt may bluſh, ºr rage look pale, 2 ..., … . . . . . . - -- - - - - - - - - - - - - - * * * * And, as they us'd, maligiouſly may rail. --- “... Tho' he ... Vice, the #º: - ‘, - A. º: ** 76e"mice; ſhall not tax it fºr Óbſcene: .2°12'. & CC- } - º * 3%ugh ſome have been ſo tickliſh in the Mind, . . . . . . . . . . They could find &awdy, which he ne're diſga'd : " : T * * * Nor can be think he gave the leaft occaſion; ... . . . . . - T - Wanting their Vigour of Imagination : . . . . . Bat they, their ends had in their falſº *eportſ, ſtºº gº. . . . *A*-*** * And frighthºd whom he moſt ºughld plº, º, Cºrtá, sº !. Any & * > . * * *- --- - - - --- * \ • * * in * * ~ * y * --- *** J -- - -i- 3. * * , ſ ** * * *-*. Tojº be appeal, the Witty, Fair, oná Good; ","...'", - ."ºrry? as an . . *-* . - j’, º/ º - , : A. . #haſ ſºveraign power can never be withſtood,' ' ' . . . -- To all the Audience he bid me ſay, 10 sº . . . º'-'. - . . He of the Gout lay in, and of this Play . . . - Not long continu’d his Poetick Fit, tº ºf , ,-i'ſ Yº, ºf..] . . .7he ºther griefhe cannot part with yet, - ... .s.º. But give him eaſe, and let who will have Wit. º Tour kind indulgence ſure he ought to gain, , , . . . . . . … - - c º - - £ 3. T. - - * - - Zitºr ... ---...--Ty-', *** *--- ºf C) * . . . . \\ . . Who fºr jour pleaſure writes in ſpight of Pain;. º, 'ne ºr " sº .*.*. ºn $49e heeſ, kind to many of his Plays, i. º º, ... ; º - jºu% %t leave him in his latter.º.º. 2 “”, “ . . º ºt. Zhºugh Lºyal Writers of the laſt two Reigns, … ). ºrſ tº sº Who tird their Pens for Popery and Chains ; W. " " . . ...º.º. Grumble at the Reward of a his Pºns; - 1 -- They would, like ſºme, the beneft fifty, Of what they vilely labour’ſ’ #. They cry him down as for his place unfit, Since they have all the humour and the Wit, They muft write better e're be fears them yet ; Till they have ſhown you more Variety, Of natural, unſtoln Comedy than he, - } toll, ºil iſ º. º.º. . . . . . .3 * * - ., ºf -, --, -, --~"F* * - isłºgºſ ºorridorº'ſ . . . . - * - #.you at leaſt he ſhould Protećted be. .#ill the mº at Mark of Bounty have, - -- #ºfamh Royal Mafter gave ; - - Who loves a Subječí and contemns a Slave, - Whom Heav'n in ſpight of Helliſh plots deſign'd, To humble Tyrants, and exalt Mankind.

End of Title Page. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 1

( 1 ) | - - - w - \ . A CT I. S C E N E I \ º Enter Sir William Rant in his Morning-Gown, and Ralph his Mae. Sir Will. I Am plaguy qualmiſh this morning, we drunk, ſwingingly laſt night, what did we do º tell me the Hiſtory. \ Ralph. Muſt every Morning be ſpent in asking Queſtions: 'tis a fine life, you'le ſin over Night;and I muſt come to Confeſſion next Morning. - Sir Will, Sirrah, Know I will have no Wit nor Wiſdom from you. - Ralpb, I don't know what you call Wit, but certainly Wiſdom will never agree with that hot head of yours, Sir!, | - Sir Will. You ſolid Lump of Maſſy Phlegm there is no ſuch bleſfing un- der Heaven, as a hot Head. - - Ralph. 'Twill coſt you and your Companions dear before you part with it; the Devil on't is, you are always the Tranſgreſſor, and I never fail of being the Penitent. - - , - - Sir Will. Sirrah, The Inſide of thy Loggerhead will endanger the Outſide, if thou begin not thy Narrative immediately; ſome Aétion in the forepart of night, I remember, but the latter part is all Darkneſs to me: Yet it runs in my head we had a Fray. - . . . i Ralph. And don't you feel it in your Shoulders? I am ſure you've Reaſon, ſo have I. - - Sir Will. Where was it 2 - : Ralph. Why here, in Covent-Garden - You would needs have a Skirmiſh with ſome drunken Bullies, awkward, roaring, bluſtering Raſcals : And Bri- gadier Stºkes with a detachment of Quarter-Staves, and ruſty Halberts fellia- Pell Mell and routed both Parties. - Sir Will, That damn'd Quarter-ſtaff Rogue would be univerſal Monarch of the Night: We muſt confederate and humble him, but what execution was there 2 Whoſe Skull crackt 2 whoſe Lungs pierced 2 or who luſtily bruiſed. Ralph, One of the Bullies has a good luſty fleſh wound, the other are a ſit- tle hackt, but all of them wer carryed Captive to the Round houſe, where they have ſolaced with Ale and Brandy all night long: Two of your Footmen with bloody Coxcombs, were likewiſe in Limbo: Two or three of the Watch- men have ſlight hurts, which they are ready to ſwear are mortal; But your Friends Mr. Tope and Mr Wildfire are eſcap'd unhurt, ſave a little dry beating which indeed we ſeldom fail of. - Sir Will. An Evening very handſomely ſpent; I am glad the Bullies are maul’d. I would rejoyce as much to run an Engliſh Bully through, as an Iriſh , - - 's B Rapperce ;
Page 2

( 2 ) . . . Rapparee. The City ought to pay a certain number of Bullies heads a tribute to the Government, as the Welſh did Wolves; but ſee my Footmen ranſom'd; Ralph. They are bay!'d by your Taylor, and dreſs'd by your Surgeon, and are ready to be drunk, and ſcower again, Sir, but that was not all, that hap- pened laſt night, 'twould take a Volume to write the Hiſtory of your Aćtions one week. - - - Sir Will. We ſhould be diligent, I love an ačtive life, but what more ? Ralph. Why, in your retreat homewards you pick’d up a Strumpet 1 I muſt needs ſay not very handſome, nor over well dreſt, nor extreamly ſober, nor extraordinary clean, and made me put her to bed in your own Bed, I thank ou, Sir. . . - - --- ºr . y Sir Will. Well, thou art a faithful Bawd. - - Ralph. Bawd, Sir 2 - - . . . . . . ; Sir Will. Yes BawdSir, what a Devil doſt thou think I keep thee for thy meat parts 2 Indeed thou art a little ſtout. . . . . . . . . . . . Ralph. Any man but my Maſter, ſhould find I were a great deal ſo, if he talk'd thus to me. - . . . . . . Sir Will, Well well Sir, but where is the Whore ? . . . . . Ral. I believe where ſhe ſhould be, at the civil Recreation of Hemp-beating. Sir Will. Pox on your Impertinence How got ſhe out * * - Ralph, Why truly Sir, after you had taken your wented Nap in your Chair, recover'd a little, and came to your Bed-ſide, you puk’d at the ſight of her, ask'd her how ſhe had the Impudence to bring ſo ugly a Countenance along with her under your Roof: To all Entreaties were inexorable, you tore her out of the bed, flung her clothes out of the window, and made me turn her naked out of the houſe. - - . . . Sir Will, 'Twas a very impudent thing of an ugly Jade to come hither, Ralph. She pick’d up her Clothes, but was in great want of a Tiring-room; and moſt certainly fell into the enemies hands. - 'Sir Will. Well, and I have never a wench this morning? ... Ralph. Here have been five or fix, they all ſaid they'd come again. Sir Will, Pox on 'em, come again but into whoſe hands may they fall be- fore they come again 2 I hate even a Roſe, after it opens in the morning, and is ruffled by the wind. . . . . . . . . - Ralph. Your provident, prudent, and pious Houſe-keeper has lodged two who came laſt night, for peace ſake, in two ſeveral apartments of your Se- taglio, not knowing which of them you would vouchſafe your Handker- chief to, . . . . . . . - & ... ". . . Sir Will. She has done wiſely, I will have them both : Who are they Ralph. Mrs. Haughty and Mrs. Mavis. . . . . . . . . . . Sir Will. Oh pox they'll never draw together, But go into my Cloſet and fetch me a bottle of Spirit of Clary, and a luſty Glaſs. . . . Exit Ralph. Now is my Father ſ warrant grieving in the Country, bewailing my lewd courſes : To ſay truth, I cannot but love him, he has been very indulgent te me; but methinks he ſhould have the conſcience to remember his own youth- ful gambols: Tope tells me he knew him almoſt as lewd a fellow as my ſelf. *
Page 3

-- - - ** -- ~-- ... . . …” - -- - - - - - * ------------.. - * * * * But the worſt of all is I am in love, moidºſperate moſt abominable love, the worſt of all love, I am afraid honeſt love. Enter Ralph. Ralph. Here's your Spirit of Clary. . | Sir Will. Set it down, and ſee what confounded [A great noiſe of talking noiſe that is without. The Devil take 'em, muſt 1 be . . and knocking without. always interrupted in my reſter my pleaſure ? a man had as good be a great man as a Drunkard at this rate. * . . Exit Ralph, and ſuddenly re-enters. Well what's the matter 2 - - ... Ralph. The noiſe you are pretty well us’d to ; an aſſembly of Düns, Whores and Bawds, as there are every morning at your Levee. Enter Tope & Wildfire. Sir Will, Hail, hail my dear Companions of the night, fack fºpe and Tom - Wildfire. - - - - - - - - - Tape. My dear Knight, my dear Will Rant, thou art the Prince of Drun- kards and of Scowrers; thou art a noble Scavenger, and every night thou cleareſt the ſtreets of ſcoundrel Bullies, and of idle Raſcals, and of all Ale. toſts and ſops in Brandy. - - Wildf.’ And the Taverns of Trades. men and of ſober Rogues of buſineſs, who ſhould be at their cheating callings, or watching of their Wives at home. Sir Will. I am glad to find you ſo hearty, and that ye ſuffer'd ſo little in our laſt nights rout; Tºp. I will not wear like a Bully my arm in a Scarf as a ſign of battel paſt when perhaps the wound is no bigger than that of a Lancet in letting blood ; I have ſeen danger in my life time. . * , . . * Wildf. Yes and felt it too to my knowledge. - . . . . . Tope. Puh this is nothing, why I knew the Hectors, and before them the Muni and the Titire Tu's, they were brave fellows indeed ; in thoſe days a man could not go from the Roſe Tavern to the Piazza once, but he muſt ven- ture his life twice. My dear Sir Willy. Sir Will. Yes, and the Wine was better, and the Women handſomer; you old fellows are always magnifying the days of your youth. - Tape. Old Gad take me, hem, hem; here's a body found wind and limb *** . . Old!’ quoth he, Indeed I have drank off two generations, and intend to drink - off three more yet. Why I wench'd, drunk and ſcowrd with thy Father, Will: He was a pretty fellow in his youth, and I thought he would have come to ſomething, but he married and run into the Country, left our noble - cauſe, and grew a very wiſe, diſcreet, vertuous Country Jobbernoll. • ‘Sir Will. Why you debauch'd with my Grandfather. - Tope. I knew him in his ebb : but thy Father, Tom, was a ſober ſot, a con- ſumptive Scoundrel, and we could make nothing of him, he married like a Puppy,and grew moſt pitifully uxorious,but the comfort is few of that ſort get their own Children: Thou art not like him at all. - * * - - Wild. Thank Heaven, I never remember him, Providence took care of me in good time, . . . . . . . . . . * * - Sir Will. Here Ralph fill. Gentlemen, a health tomy Miſtriſsin a brimmer of Clary. . . . . . . B 2 . -- " - - * . - Top
Page 4

--- - K. 4.) - Tops. I defy mornings Draughts, beſides Spirits will bring you from two. pound of Beef, to two poatch'd Eggs, truſt an experienc'd Drunkard, thou will not live out half thy days, if thou tak'ſt theſe lewd courſes of drinking in a Morning. • , - -- * Wild. But we will live out all our Nights. - - Tope. I have buried two hundred Mornings draught-men of my Acquaintance. Sir Will, You may well kill’em if you drink not fair with them; but thou haſt kill'd as many Evenings Draught-men too. Never Hero in Romance kill'd more in his Adventures. \ Tope. Their Deaths be upon their own Heads, I preſerved my ſelf : why I have been walking two hours in the Park. - , - Wild. The Deaths of theſe men lie upon his Conſcience, and he cannot ſleep. Sir Will. No, no, he wants the dear Balſom of his Youthful blood, that bai- my ſoveraign Juice that ſends kind vapours up to rock the brain; Here, I will, - have my Miſtriſs pledged. \ . . . 2– Tope, Thy Miſtriſs thaha ha, why every one in a Petticoat is thy Miſtriſ, from humble Bulker to exalted Counteſs. , Sir Will. No I am particular, damnably particular, why I am fallen in love. Tope, in Love What a Devil . That is, thou haſt a plaguy mind to ſome Wench ; I have known thee have that to many a Damſel, but when thou haſt gotten her, thou never fail'ſt to leave either her,0r a child by her,to the Pariſh. Sir Will. Why thoſe kind of Ladies come to the Pariſh at laſt, and the ſoon- er they take care of them the better, it is a good ſettled kind of Life. But - this is a Lady of Quality. - - Tope. A pox of a Whore of Quality; they are ten times more troubleſome, and not handſomer than poor Whores. . . . . Sir. Will. A whore this is a Saint. - * Wild. A Saintſ haha ha, a world of Saints there are in theſe days, but ve: ry few honeſt, - - - Sir Will. I can ſcarce forbear.to worſhip her, and call her Nymph; divine, Goddeſs. - - - - - Tope. Nymph 1 divine, Goddeſs! ha haha, language for a young Coxcomb- ly Chaplain to his Ladies waiting woman. - - Wild. Love! Faith I could never believe there was any ſuch thing : I have had a furious Appetite to a new Face, like a greedy ſtomach to a new Diſh', but I never made a very full meal, but I wiſh’d it off again. - Tape. Love Why what a Pox, I have had as many Whores as any of you; but I never had one whom I car'd if ſhe were hang'd or no. Sir Will. Oh baſe, groſs Appetites, of ill-natur'd Fellows. - ** WVild, Oh thou Flower of Civility, and good Nature! I never knew you, - or any Whore-maſter, but minded himſelf, and never car'd what became of the woman, why prithee don't we ruin all we have to do with 2, - Tope. Some few keeping Coxcombs indeed are undone by them; but that grows much out of Faſhion, becauſe keep what you can, Particular Whores will ſoon grow Commons ones. º, - Sir Will. Hence all ſuch profane thoughts, this is a Lady, who has all the Beauty and Vertue of the Sty. Tape. / . . . .

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 5

| - g ºpe, Piſh, Sex ſayſ thou? I warrant ſhe is not over ſtock'd neitherif ſhe has ; but Beauty is frail, and Vertue is more frail, Will. - Sir Will. Away with your babbling, Tom here's to her, take a Glaſs. wild. Come jack her Health. - - Tºpe. God not I I would not drink the Queens health faſting, not I ; charge a bill upon me, and I’le anſwer you in a couple of brimmers of Claret at Lock- ets at dinner, where I have beſpoken an admirable good one for ye; but my Wine ſhall always have ſomething to feed upon. . . . . Enter Ralph. Ralph. Here are a company of Letters, ſome are waiting for anſwers. * Wildf. From Whores, all Whores. - º * . sºil. Hah; they are ſº, ſome in difireſ; Iſuppoſe: Like atrue great man, 1 will put Petitions in my pocket and never read 'em. . Ralph. Sir the Duns are very noiſy, and will not be kept out. . . . Sir Will. Obſtinate Rogues that will fling away their precious time ſo. . Ralph. But there's a pert dapper fellow whom I know not, he will not be denyed. - ; : x . . . Sir Will. Let him in firſt. How now, who are you? [Ralph lets in a Glazier, Glaz. And pleaſe your Worſhip. I am a Glazier, and have an humble petiti- on to your Worſhip; your Glazier dyed within this hour, the bell now goes for him.; and I humbly deſire I may ſucceed in your worſhips work. . . . . Sir Will. Thou art a very pretty fellow. Glaz. I waited for this happy occaſion, and hoped for’t, ſo I made him drink like a Fiſh, and treated him with brandy. The man indeed was an ho- neſt man, but alack, alack he had little to do for a long time, till your bu- fineſs and your friends, Sir, brought him into requeſt: He has had a fine time under you; for your Worſhip. I underſtand has to Shaſh; windows an utter averſion, Sir, when you are in beer. - Tope. A very pretty diſcreet fellow. . . . . . ‘. . . Glaz. Why Sir he bore Offices, maintain'd his wife with all things about her, and now dyes well to paſs, and for all may thank your Worſhip. Now. if your Worſhip will let me have the place, I ſhall ſee that all the Pariſh, when you pleaſe to break their windows, ſhall have as good goods as any man can furniſh 'em with. . . - - - - - Sir Will. Let me ſee, this place muſt be worth Money. . . . Ralph. Let me ſpeak with you, I can do your buſineſs. . . . Glaz. I will Sir ; but Sir do they ſell places now adays 2 - - Sir Will. Oh nono, Heaven forbid! thou ſhalt have it for nothing. Glaz. Thank you, ſweet Sir. . . * . . . . . . . * * * Ralph. Hum, hum, hum. Ralph holds his hand out behind him, the . “Glaz. Ay Sir, there and pleaſe you. Glazier puts Money into it, and Éº. Ralph. A pox on him, a thirteen pence half penny! but I'll after him, and ſqueeze the Sponge, I warrant him. W. - - - Sir Will. Come let in the Canaille, the Rabble of my Anti-chamber, my Duns, &c. Now will I behave my ſelf ſtatelily, impudently, and do no mans, buſineſs but my own. Eater Ralph. - - Ralph, Sir Humphry Maggot has ſent word he'll wait on you cºre you go out. * . --> -- . . . - , Sir a ->
Page 6

" *- ( 6 ) • ‘Sir Will. That's the Coxcombly Alderman that marry'd my termagant Aunt ; her firſt Husband was my Fathers brother by the ſecond venter. She has this dolt under correótion, ſweet Princeſs; and has forced him out of Mark- lane to live in Soho Square. I warrant ſome old lečture from my Daddy. Let the Duns enter. - - * . . . . Enter 8 or Io Dums. Sir Will. Now Rogues, Raſcals, Vermin, Catterpillers, Duns, come on ; I will uſe you ſo like Duns for plaguing me with ſo many dayly viſits, I ſay, I will uſe you ſo like Duns. Enter Sir Humphry Maggot and obſerves them, ‘’ Tope. That is ſend them away without Money. . . . . . . . Sir Will. You filly impudent Puppies, to come to me for ſumms fit for Ha- berdaſhers of ſmall Wares to pay, ridiculous, petty ſumms, come up to bulky ones, either in valuable Goods or Mony, fit for a Gentlemans conſideration, and Security may follow. . . . . . . . . . . . Sir Humph. Here's a Spark, thank Heaven I have kept my Nephew at the Inns of Court, whom ſ bred up, free from his lewd Acquaintance. . . . | Sir Will. Why I never pay a bill till it be as long as an account in Chancery, you Rogues, Dogs. - Duns altogether. Why we ask but for our own Sir. I hope a man may ask for his own Sir. 'My Goods were my own Sir, my own. Very fine a man muſt not ask for his own. Rogues for asking for a mans own : . . . . . . . Sir Will. And Rogues I will make you know this Houſe is my own, which I will ſignifie to you by this Foot which is my own, and by this Cudgel which is my own. . . . . . Sir William Kicks and cudgels them out. Duns. Fly, fly, Murther, murther. May not ask for his own, my own. Mur- ther, Murther. For my own, help, Murther. (In running out they run down the Sir Humph. Gad forgive me, Help help. " " ' " . (Alderman. Sir. Will. Oh Sir Humphrey I cry you mercy, I was at my Morning Exerciſe, diſciplining my Rogues, my Duns. - # Sir Humph. Duns, Sir Will. Rant 2 let me tell you Duns may be very honeſt Intn. - - - - Sir Will. Hum, ſo you Citizens are apt to think, but we Gentlemen beheve no ſuch matter. But come I know you have ſome wife Leóture from nown Daddy, or ſome ſuch buſineſs, come out with it, , I ſtand fair. . . . . . . . Sir Humph. Poor Gentleman my heart bleeds for him, you make him mi- ſerable with your extravagant lewd Liſe, he writes me word you got the Par- ſons daughter with Child, when you were at home laſt, and now ſhe is near her time ſhe names you for the Father, this is the ſtrangeſt thing that ever was. Sir Will. Not at all, it had been ſtrange if ſhe had gotten me with Child; the Parſons are luſty, lazy, well fedfellows,and will be too hard for the Laity, if we don't take Letters of Repriſal upon them. - Sir Humph, Save us Heaven I would not have my Nephew Whachum ac- quainted with you for the World. Sir Will, Nor I with him Sir Nump, I keep ſomewhat better Company, you have ſeen my Friends here. . . . . . - - - - - Sir Humph. Yes and heard of them too, the Nation rings of 'em, my Lady my Wife and your Aunt is perpetually, grieving and fighing for you. - - - - - Sir -- --
Page 7

w - * - … . . . . . (7 ) . Sir Will. Ha, good Lady! Nuncle look to thy City Forehead, there are thoſe who can graft and inoculate. . . . . . . . . Sir Humph. She has kept her two Daughters (ſhe had by your halfuncle J in the Country theſe five years, for fear you ſhould come to her Houſe and bring a ſcandal upon them. . . . . . . ; Sir Will. But they are now in Town, to my coſt I find it (aſide) Oh that dear, ſweet Cºgenial ſhe has kill'd me. - Iſild. Pox on this Blockhead he grows tedious; to your Cue: Has Mon- ſieur Catinat given the Vaudois ſuch a bang? . . . Tºpe. undoubtedly, there's a World of News in Town. . . . - | Sir Humph. Hold hold Gentlemen, I beſeech you hold, News ſay you ? have a little Patience Sir William, here's a Letter from your Father, I have had it ever ſince the laſt Poſt, and you have not been at home till this Morn- ing. But pray Gentlemen what News is of Maſter Catinat 2 I love News ex- treamly, I have read Three News Letters to day, 1 go from Coffee-Houſe to Coffee-Houſe all day on purpoſe. I talk'd with as pretty a man, of a News. Writer, as any in London, and of as neat parts, as bold a Fellow, he cares not what he writes. But he knew nothing of the Vaudois this Morning. Wild. They are ſoundly beaten,almoſt all cut off. . . . . . . . | Sir Humph. Heaven be praiſed, they are damn'd Presbyterian Fellows, and hate the Church, for my part, had Î my will, I would put all the Phanaticks. in Chriſtendom in pitch'd ſhifts, light them, and let them blaze like City Fu- nerals. But hold, is it true that Prince Waldeck is dead of a Feaver? Tope. Oh yes, and he got it with (cowring at the Canal at Bruges. Sir Humph, Goodlackſ Teckel) and the Coſſacks upon theUkrain have totally routed Prince Lewis of Baden, and cut his Army all topieces, Well this Louys is the braveſt King. . - Sir Will. The old Gentleman is very prolix. . . - Reads. Lewd courſes—great afflićtion—bum ; have Ibeen ſº kind. w Very well. Reads. Tour wicked extravagance will kill me. * - " Haha ha, kill not theſe Twenty years, if Heaven takes no better care of me: I ſhall be in a pretty caſe. Reads. But this Aëtion of the Parſons daughter. - - - Pray Heaven the old man got her not himſelf, for her Mother was my Mo- thers VVoman. Piſh pox this is ſtuff, I would the old Gentleman would ſpare his pains. He tears the Letter. . . Sir Humph. Oh impious ! what tear your Fathers Letter? . - Sir Will. Yes when they are nothing to the purpoſe: I ſent to him for a luſty ſumm of Money, and he ſends me a parcel of wiſe Councel that is not worth a Farthing. - * - - - - - * - - - … Sir Humph. But Sir the other News you were ſpeaking of VWild. WWhy ’tis moſt certain Catinat has laid a bridge over the Rhine and ſecured his paſſage into Fraňce, and another over the Moſell to ſecure his paſs. into Italy, - - - . . . . . . . s - * ~ * * * : irº * - - - - - - • * , - • * - - - - * * * * - - * - - * : * ~ * -- . . . . . . .x
Page 8

women. - - - Sir Will. Now my dear Friends let's go quickly now now, I love to leave w * ( 8 ) . - - , -Sir Humph. VVell that Maſter Catinat is a very pretty man, he’ll ſoon de- ſtroy the Presbyterians and burn that Anti-chriſtian Town of Geneva. Oh this Louis is a glorious Prince, what would I give to ſee him, I believe I might have a paſs to go over to be touch'd for the Evil, He muſt needs do it rarely. Sir Will. VVell ſaid old Grumble, have you no wiſe advice from my Aunt, ſhe will have you under Córre&ion if you deliver it not. . . . . Sir Humph, poor Lady, ſhe grieves that you ſhould drink and roar, and beat the whole Town, and ſpend your Money upon ugly Whores. But pray what News of Buda Ž --- - - is Emter Mrs. Mavis and Mrs. Haughty at two ſeveral doors. Ralph. Now they are both gotten "º. will enſue; s | Sir Will. Hold hold Nuncle, ugly Whores ſay you? be you Judge, who keeps the uglier Whores my Aunt or I : . . - Haughty, Ohimpudence another in the Houſe, oh oh. They both fall in A4avis, Oh Devil I cannot endure this, oh oh. 2 Chairs in Fits. Sir Humph. Gad forgive me, look to the Gentlewomen, look to the Gentle- VVhores in Fits mightily. . . . . [Ex. Sir VVill. Tope, VVildfireand Ralph. | Sir Hump, Gad take me 1 hold, the Gentlewomen, bring ſome cold water, and flower, burn ſome blew inkle and Partridge Feathers, 'tis my Ladies Medicine. - Two lufty Fellows hold them. Haughty, Is the Villain gone? . . . . . . . - aſide, Mavis. Is the Rogue fled? . … . . . aſide. Haughty. Oh you Flirts I'le pluck your Eyes out. * They fight and , Mavis. I’le tear you Limb from Limb. . - - - tear one another. Sir Will. Gad forgive me! help help, part them, they are incens'd, why La- dies, Gentlewomen, keep the peace, I charge ye in the Kings Name, I am of the Quorum. - . . . . . . They part them. Enter Houſekeeper with her Spettacles in one hand, and the Ladies calling in the other. * * Haugly, ºh Impudence. . . . . . . . Mavs. Thou common thing. " ' ' ' ' ' ' ' ' " . . . " Haughty, Go jezabel, 3O. . . v . . . - . . . . . º * º - Mavis. Avoid paint and waſh . . . . . Haughty. Go pitiful Creature. , - - - , , Mavis. Creatüre creature in the very face of thee: . . . . . . . . . . . Haughty. The Town knows what thou art. . . . . a navi, whatami,jmº what do they know of me 2 " . . . . Abigal. In truth you are to blame, to diſturb a civil well orderd Family thus, well were it not for good Books that comfort me, I could never bear ſuch exorbitances. . . . . . . . * . . . . - Sir Humph. Ha, The Ladies calling, a very Matronly Gentlewoman truly. , Abigal. But theſe godly books quiet the Coaſtience mightily. . . . . . . . Sir Hunph. Hah good Soul ' ' ' ' " ' " sº º '' tº . . . - tº º . … Haughty. Let me come at her. * - . . º. Mavis, I'le tear her Throat out. Haughty. a - -

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 9

( . ) --J Haught, Bawd, bawd. . . . . - º - -**C. C tº . ... lºt Mavº. Thou art old enough to be my Mother. Haughty, Let me come at her. Mavis. Let me come at her. -- - . . . Abigail. In truth Ladies you are much to blame, cannot you be civil 8 take them away ſeparately. . . . . . Haug. Whore, whore, whore, whore. - They bale them out Mcvá. Whore, whore, whore, whore. .. at ſeveral doors. Sir Humphrey takes the Houſe-keeper under the Arm, andlead; her out. - t - -, * * A CT II. S C E N E . I. -- ſ - - - , - ... " Enter Priſcilla, Clara, Eugenia. . Priſ Wii. account ſhall I give , of my Charge, and Guardianſhip 2 my Lady ſends you out under my prudent condućt, as I may ſay, to look after Commodes and Top-knots, with a flat Injunčtion not to ſee this lewd place, the Park. . . - ! -- Eug. Did ſhe ſo old Mumpſimus 2 - . . . . Priſº. And you in Contempt of her ſoveraign power, and my lawful autho- rity under her, preſume to come hither, what ſhall I do? what ſhall I ſay 2 Clara, Can fleſh and blood forbear this ſweet, this moſt delicious place 2 Priſ. Fleſh and Blood : Yes, it is a place fit for the carrying on the deſigns of fleſh and blood indeed, --- Eug, And what doſt thou take us for Spirits, Woman 2 * Priſ. Come come Gentlewomen, my Lady is a wiſe woman: This is the Exchange for Loters : Here they meet, and if they abſent themſelves are lookt upon as broken; nay worſe, it is the Rendevouz of Fornicators and Adulterers. Clara. Tis the Rendevouz of all who have ſenſe enough to love the deli- cateſt place on Earth. - - Priſ. But I have a ſecret to tell you, it concerns you Madam Clara, I have found from Sir Humphrey your Father in Law, that he has made a match be- * , ; tween his Nephew Mr. Whachum and you. , Eug. The Devil he ſhall! there's a mechanick thing, there is not ſuch an odious creature as a City Spark. . . - f Priſ. Don't you trouble your ſelf, his uncle ſays you are not ſober enough for him, tº . . . . clara. Nor I fool enough forhim, I thank Heaven, a filthy City wit, thoſe Fellows are as lewd as the Gentlemen every whit,only more impudent, fooliſh and ill-manner'd. , - * - - - Eug. Dear Clara thou art in the right, when a man is lewd with a bon : - - --- * . + - ºr º, t ere's --" - - - * * * * *
Page 10

tº , - ( 10 ) . ſomething in it; but a Fellow that is aukwardly wicked, is not to be OTI). - - Priſ. He wicked why he is a Student of the Inns of Court,Madam Eugenia. Eug. Well you had a great ſecret for my Siſter, and I have one for you: In ſhort we are both reſolv’d not to endure any longer the intolerable Yoke of Arbitrary power, under which we have ſo long groan'd, if you will comply, , one or both of us will provide for you: Clara. And preſerve you from making Night-caps or footing Stockings in a Garret, the pitiful remnant of thy decrepid Life. * * * , - Priſ. Oh times and manners I will you break looſe from all Government 2 I ſhall be undone, what will my Lady ſay, if ſhe knows that you ſaw your Co- zen Rant here yeſterday : / - Eug. Mutterno more under thy Gums, old Sybil I did ſee my Cozen yeſter- day, and I hope to ſee him this day, and every day of my life ; keep your di- ſtance, we that are reſolv'd to caſt off my Mothers Tyranny, will no longer . ſuffer thy Inſolence. - - Priſ. What will become of poor me? - Clara. We are true Eugliſh women, Co-heirs oftwo thouſand poundsa year, and are reſolv'd to aſſert our Liberty and Property. + : . . . ... Eug. Does my Mother think ſhe ſhall mew us up any more, at her Jointure houſe, old Doe-little 2 - , Clara. Amongſt poor innocent country things, who never ſtir beyond the Pariſh but to ſome Fair. Priſ. Did ſhe not beſtow good breeding upon you there 2 Eugen. Breeding what to learn to feed Ducklings, and cram Chickens? . Clara. To ſee Cows milkd, learn to churn, and make cheeſe? - Eugen. To make clouted cream, and whipt Sillabubs Clara. To make a Caraway Cake, and raiſe Py-cruſt 2 Eugen. And to learn the top of your skill in Syrrup, Sweat-meats, Aquami- rabilis, and Snayl water. ". - - clara. Or your great cunning in Cheeſe-cakes, ſeveral Creams and Almond- butter. . - - - . . Priſ. Ay ay, and 'twere better for all the Gentlemen in England if their Wives had no other breeding, but you had Muſick and Dancing. - Eug: Yes an ignorant, illiterate hopping Puppy, that rides his dancing Cir- cuit thirty miles about, Lights off his tyred Steed, draws his Kit at a poor country creature, and gives her a Hich in her pace, that ſhe ſhall never recover. Clara. And for Muſick an old hoarſe ſinging man riding ten miles ſtom his Cathedral to Quaver out the Glories of our Birth and State, or it may be a Scotch Song more hideous and barbarous than an Iriſh Cronan. - Eng. And another Muſick-maſter from the next Town to teach one to twin- kle out Lilly burleroupon an old pair of Virginals, that ſound worſe than a Tin- kers kcttle that he crys his work upon—we'll ha' no more on't, we are come up to London and common ſenſe, and we defy thee and thy works. Clara, Keep diſtance. - - Eugen. Avoid thou that think'ſt becauſe thou art old thou muſt be wiſe. - * Clara, |
Page 11

T - - ( 1 r ) Clara, Avaunt we'll have no more to do with thee. . . . . . Euge. Attend. - - - - - - ºv ...” Clara, Obey. . - Euge. Be under good Diſcipline. " - - . . . . . ; Clara. Be a towardly old Governeſs. . . . . . . . . Euge. We are free from this minute. Clara. Never more to hearthy wiſe advice, Eugen. Thy old Saws, and fooliſh Sayings. Clara. We will pare our Nails on any day of the Week. * 'º. Eng. And do what we will upon Childermas day, oh my dear Siſter! How happy are we to come to this moſt bleſſed Town,and theſe moſt heavenly walks. Clara. This Paradice of the world. | (. . . .” bº" Oh this Cozen of ours, he is the prettyeſt man my Eyes ereºyet CICI. t º: º, º . Clara. But ſure Eugenia thou art mad. - Eug. Yes I am mad, ſtark mad, in love with him, and will be mad. . . Clara. Thou art mad indeed, in love with ſo wild a man 2 - . . . . . . . Eug. Wild, never trouble thy ſelf for that,my dear! I warrant thee Ple fame him, the wilder the better. . . . . . . Clara. Thisis ſtark ſtaring madneſs, why this lewd Cozen of ours, they ſay, has had all the women in Town that are to be had for Love or Money. Eug. Sayſt thouſo my Child then will my conqueſt be the greater, and I fhall triumph over all them he has had, and he will be the more likely to be conſtant to me whom he never had. - . ... tº Clara. A ſhort Triumph 'twould be, till he can meet with another weak e- nough to be taken. , - . . . º Eug. I would not give a Farthing for her that cannot ſecure the Conqueſt ſhe has made : I will have him, and I am miſtaken if he be not as fierce upon me, as I am upon him. * -- . , . Clara. Thou art a mad Girl, I would not fall in love with a wild Fellow of the Town, if he would Jointure me with the Eaſt-Indies. , sº Eug. I could not, would not, but have fallen in love with this wild Fellow . of the Town, to have been Miſtreſs of all the Gold and Jewels in both Indies. Clara, Heaven defend me. - - Eug. Thou art only fit to be Spouſe to ſome Ladies darling, who has been cockerd with Cawdles by his Lady mother, bred under a very humble civil Tutor in the houſe, who is always in moſt profound awe of his Pupil, from whence to the univerſity he goes, where Divines (for the great reſpect they have to ſome Livings in his gift ) flatter and indulge him in what he thinks fit. Clara. You are very merrily diſpos'd. , , - - Eug. From thence the Fop comes home, and ſets up his reſt upon Horſes, and Öogs, rides fer a place, grows a moſt furious Nimrod, and hunts perpe- tually.” * N. - - - Clara, Will the Alarum of your Tongue never be down? y C 2. - Eng:
Page 12

Eugen. Come let's walk, and ſee if we can ſpy this ſame dear, dear, wild, very wild couſin, come along. - Extunt Eugen, and Clara. Priſc. Mercy on me, the World's turn'd topſy turvy. My Lady will kill me : She is a very Fury, and when provok'd, nor man, woman nor child can ſtand in her way. . . . . . . . . Exit Priſcilla. - Enter Whachum, Bluſter and Dingboy. . . . . Whach. My dear Rogues! Dear Dogs! Blufter and Dingboy you are the braveſt fellows that ever ſcowred yet. . . . . . . . . . . Bluff. Dear Squire Whachum If ever there was ſuch ſcowring in High- Holbourn ſince ’twas built, may I never taſte Nanti-Brandy more at midnight. ... Ding. The Nation will ring of us; ſuch Exploits ſuch Atchievements : Not a window left in all the Inns of Chancery; thoſe Hives of Attorneys, thoſe Suit-breeders, thoſe Litigious Rogues, the Sons of Court-hand, Copy Paper and Green Wax. - . Bluff. Not a Tavern window in all the ſtreet has a Quarrel in it. VWhaab. Then how we ſcowr'd the Market people, overthrew the Butter- women, defeated the Pippin-Merchants, wip'd out the Milk-ſcores, pull'd off the poºr-knockers, Dawbd the gilt Signs; . . . ." . . . . . . . . , Ding. But a pox ont, we were confoundedly beaten by the Helfiſh Conſta- ble and his Poſſe of Scoundrel Dogs. . . . . . . . . . . . . . - Bluff. That moſt Damnable Inflexible Prig that bound us over this morning muſt be toſs'd in a Blanket. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . " Ding. Slit in the Noſe, and ſuffer other operations not very agreeable to him. Whach. No, let's be brave, but not too brave, I'll pay for the Windows and all; my Head's broken, but no matter I'll not be diſmay'd : Well, never men laugh'd and roar'd more : This ſame Flipp and Punch are rare drinks. - 1)ing. Nay, I'll hang for't if there be a knot of better Laughers in England. * * ºach. We'll laugh with ere a gang in England for a thouſand pound. Why laughing's all the joy of a mans life. " " ' " - . . . - Bluff. Then we have ſcowrd ſo magnanimouſly theſe three nights, that we were taken for Sir William Rant and his complmy. . . . . . . . . . . . | * Whach. Sir William P. no, no; oh Sir William is the fineſt, compleateſt Gentleman that ever wore a head. . . . . . . º - Ding. There are others, Squire, that ſhall be nameleſs. . . . tº Whach. Oh no, never talk on't : there will never be his Fellow, Oh had you ſeen him ſcowre as I did, oh ſo delicately, ſo like a Gentleman how he clear'd the Roſe-Tavern I was there about Law buſineſs, compounding for a Baſtard, aud'he and two fine Gentlemen came roaring in the handſomelieſt, I and the moſt genteely turn'd us all out of the Room, and ſwing'd us, and kick'd us about, I vow to Gad, 'twould have done your heart good to have ſeen it. - - - -, - . . . . . - - . . . a Bluff. I'faith did he ha, ha, ha. . . . . . . . . . . - -: Ding. Brave fellows ha, ha ha. . . . . . . - . . . . . | Whach. Aye, was’t not handſome, hā, "ha, ha. And in a minutes time clear'd the whole houſe, and broke all the windows, beat the woman at the Bar, and ſwagger'd by themſelves. Ha, hā, ha, ' ' ' ' ' ' ". . . . . . . x * -- º Bluff. \ . - –----------
Page 13

- a - ( 13, ) Bluff. Ha, ha, ha. - - | Ding. Ha, ha, ha. . . . - - - - VWhach, Peace, peace ; hold, hold | Here he comes, with his brave Friends. Stand by, and obſerve. Look you there, look you there, there's fine perſon there's a compleat Gentleman! - . . . . . . . à , Enter Sir William Rant, Wildfire and Tope. " Bluff. A good pretty man. - ". * Ding. The man's well enough, but Squire Whachum I ſay for all that. . . . Whach, O fie fie, Pretty-man! well he ſhall be my pattern while I live, an’t pleaſe Heaven. You ſhall ſee him, oh if did you but hear him ſwear and curſe you'd be in love with him . He does 'em ſo like a Gentleman, while a company of ye here about the Town, pop out your Oaths like pellets out of Elder Guns. They come ſo eaſily, ſo ſweetly from him, even like Muſick from an Organ-pipe. . . . . . . Sir Will. What do they lay more upon us than we did 2 who the Devil ſhould theſe be that ſcowre ſo to be taken forus 2 Wildf. Puh, pox theſe muſt be ſome Scoundrels that prophane our noble aćtions with vilé bungling imitation." - - - Tope. A man wou'd think we need no imputative wickedneſs. . - | Sir Will. Theſe Muſhroom Scowrers had beſt ſee they do it handſomely, and bring no diſgrace upon us, or we may chance to whip ſome of 'em thro' the Lungs about that buſineſs. - Whach. Do you hear Blufter and Dingboy 2, Oh if Fate, and my own In- duſtry, could ever make me like this Dear, this gallant Sir William, I were at the end of my Ambition. . . - , , - IVild 'i'is a hard thing to ſcowre naturally, and handſomely. . . . . v. Tope. Every Puppy, now a-days, preſumes to ſet up for a Drunkard ; but there are more good qualities requiſite to a Drunkard than to a Miniſter of State, or a deep Divine. I’ll pick up fellows fit for great men every hour in the Streets, but a Drunkard. ------ - - * * Sir Will. Well ſaid, jack Tope, thou art in the right, he muſt be of Mien and Perſon not ungraceful, of pleaſing Speech, ſharp muſt his Wit be, and . his Judgment ſolid. . . -- - , . . . . . . . . . - . . . wildf. He muſt be chearful, eaſie, and well temper'd, . . . . Tºpe. He muſt be well bred have ſeen the World; learn'd, knowing, and retentive of a ſecret: He muſt have Truth and Courage. . . . Sir Will. In ſhort, he muſt be juſt ſuch a fellow as thou art, if it be poſſible ; while all thy Contemporaries have either Dyed, or left off, and grown ſober, Sots, thou ſtill perſevereſt in generous Lewdneſs. 4. - - - - - - Wild. He is only to blame a little, to bruſh up the Ladies ſo much, when he's an Ancient Gentleman, and knows his own ability. . . . . Tope. Prithee Stripling, trouble not thy ſelf with what I can do, I can make. love enough to make a Husband or Gallant Jealous, and that's as good as any thing thou canſt do. . . . . * * * : *-* * : *i; ; ; ; ; . . . ... Whach. Look youthere now ! Well, all Europe cannot ſhow a knot of finer Wits, and brawer Gentiemen, " " " ' " " ; , , ſ , , , * . . . • º * * --- Ding, -->
Page 14

- - ( 14 ) 4. Ding. Faith, they are pretty ſmart men. Bluff. The Gentlemen, I muſt confeſs, are pretty Gentlemen; but time ſhall try. I’ll ſay no more— - . Sir Will. Gentlemen, I have an adventure will ſeparate as for a while; but this ſhall be our Randezvous. • - : . Wild. 'Tis not fit for a Gentleman to be without an Adventure in this place, jack Tape. - - - º . . . . . . . . Tope. Pox o' your Whorest I come here to venture for a good ſtomach to my Calvert Salmon, and my Turbot ; your lazy fellows loſe the pleaſure of the Park, you ſhou’d be here in a morning, and obſerve crowching Spaniels haſtning to ſome great mans Levee, whom they wiſh hang'd ; and lean, aſſi: duous knaves of buſineſs running from Office to Office, to get , all they can under the Government they hate. - - - - t Wild. How many Villains that wiſh the Government deſtroyed, yet crowd for places in it. ( - Sir Will. Such Rogues can do the Government no harm if they be kept out. But Tºpe, if thou growſt politick, and troubleſt thy ſelf how matters go, thoa art too ſolid for a Drunkard, and muſt knock off. - \ - - Tope. I knock off! Gad I ſcorn your words, I'll bury two or three hundred of you. Hem, hem, I’ll ſcowre in the Mall now, if you will, without the help of Spirit of Clary, faſting, and in cold blood: Come on, fall on, I need no pro- vocations to Lewdneſs. - - Sir Will. Hold hold, a Sayl! a ſayl | Each part, and cruiſe about. Wild. Adieu for a while. - - Tape. A while a pox o' your damn’d Caterwauling : Think on the Turbott and the Calvert Salmon at Lockets. - ! - * Sir Will. Two a clock be the time. Ex. Sir Wil. Rant, Wildfire and Tope, Whach. Let's follow at a diſtance and obſerve 'em. They are the braveſt Blades, and pureſt Witts in Chriſtendom. º - Ding. But hark you Squire, by their diſcourſe, even now, they ſeem to be - ; Damn’d Whiggs methinks. - - - - - - Whac. I am afraid they are a little Whiggiſh; really 'tis a thouſand pities, they have kept ill company. Enter Sir Humphry Maggot, - - - Cods me, here's my uncle 1 Great ſouls contain your ſelves, - Sir Humph. How Nephew What you are never to be found in your , - . • Chamber of late: How will your ſtudies gº on at this rate : Whach. 1 was not well this morning, and came to take a little air. - Sir Humph. Air, ſay you ? Is there not as good air in ºf ball 2 Yes, and a profitable air ſome find it. I went thither expeding to find you upon a Cricket, civilly taking Reports, 1 think they call 'em. - V - Whach. In good time Sir. . . . . . . . . . . . Sir Humph. In good time ! Come mind your buſineſs, I have made a match for you with my wives ſecond daughter; the firſt is a Mad-cap, I’ll have no- thing to do with her; but the ſecond for my money, I have agreed with her Mother that you ſhall give 5 odol., : -- `-->
Page 15

r --~~ - 2. * - { I ºf Whach, I am for the eldeſt, ſhe is for ind fellow ; She will fall in love with me, and I'll marry her for nothing; Aſide Sir Humph. How I What Companions are theſe ? Whac. Students of the Temple Sir, hard Students, very hard Students. Sir Humph. Students of the Temple 2 they look like Students of White-Fryer. Whac. Have a care what you ſay Sir? your words will be actionable, they ſtudy hard all nights, lye rough, and ſeldom go to bed. Sir Humph. Have they read the Year books : Whac. Read all all. Ding. The Devil o' bit, read quoth he - - Blufter, Year books: I never read anything but Gazettes,thoſe are the week books. , | Sir Humph. Well Gentlemen de'e hear any news 2 1 hear the Pope and the King of France are agreed. w Ding. We hard Students never mind News, but that's very good. . . Sir Humph. Hold I ſee one that owes me Money, ſtay I'll come to you here and tell you more, I hope we are all honeſt. - Whach. Oh aye, Sir Humph. Do you and they come dine with me then, Exit Sir Hump. Whac. A pox on him, he has hindered us obſerving theſe fine Gentlemen, let's walk, we ſhall loſe them. Exeunt Whachum, Dingboy and Bluſter. - - - - Enter Lady Maggot, after her Tope. - Lady Magg., Are there no Gallants left? poor gentle love is now neglected, and all mens heads lye towards Knavery and Bnſineſs. I have walk’d the whole length of the Mall alone, on purpoſe for an amorous Adventure, and met none; nor have had any obſerve me except this old Red nos'd, batter'd Drunkard, and yet my ſhape and habit are enough inviting, beſides ſome Jew- els which I ſeem to conceal, and yet take care to expoſe, ſhew my Wealth and Quality ſufficiently. Enter Sir Humphry. . Yope. What ſolitary adventnre is this? ſhe is richlyladen, I'll lay her on board with my two Pounders and my Patereras Sir * That muſt be my ſweet, Duckling—I know her by her pretty \ er waddle in her Gate—beſidzs I have had a ſight of her Rump Jewel ; I know it—my Dear, my Chicken I know thee well enough. Husband firſt 2 How now, what old Fellow art thou? Sir Humph. Come Chicken don't think to bob thy own Dear, don't I know that Jewel 2 --- - - ... " ~ - Tope. Ha! This is the Aklermans Wife, Ple cuckold him, that's certain : I have not cuckolded an Alderman theſe 7 years. If honeſt jack Tope ſhould live to be kept in his old Age 2. Hah! - - - Lady Mag, unlucky Omen for a Lady to be pick’d upby her own muffy - 2 La Mag. Well Sneak-gogſe what then? what do you come poking hither for: - Sir Humph, Come Chicken, I'le take a walk with thee. La Mag. With me'! I faith but you ſhall not, when did you ever ſee a La. dy of my Quality walk with her own Husband? well I ſhall never teach a Citizen manners. I warrant you think you are in Moor-Fields ſeeing Haber- daſhers walking with their whole Fireſide. - - Sir.
Page 16

(. 16 ) Sir Hum. Prithee Chicken be appeas'd, . . . . . . . . . . . . La. Mag. Chicken, you are very familiar, what you would have the world believe you Jealous? - - . . . . . Sir Hum. Who 1 Jealous 2 Heaven forbid. La, Mag. Beſides a Lady of my Quality, that have ſo many great people º bfkin to me, to be ſeen with a pitiful mechanick Alderman. I have diſ. grac'd the Ancient Noble Family of the Rants enough already in marrying you. |- ~ Be gone I ſay out of the Park. . .” - - no more, I am gone. w - Exit Sir Humphry. Tope. So now have at her, pray Heaven ſhe be ſound—ſhe's of Quality —hah I may be ne're the ſounder for that neither—Hail ſolitary Dámſelf by thy penfive walking I find thou art in Diſtreſs; and being a true Knight Errant, come to offer thee the ſuccour of my perſon. . . . . . . L. Mag. Not in ſo much diſtreſs neither. . . Tope. Theſe Vizards have all gotten a road of talking pertly and impudent- ly, they learn it of the Beaux; come, I know what 'tis thou want'ſt; I am ready to pay a Bill at ſight, - ~ * * L. Mag. What do you think I have a mind to drink a Bottle or two 2 Tope. No, thou perveſe creature; thou knowſt my meaning well enough : if thou wilt have me ſpeak broad I can bear it, have at thee. . . . L. Mag. Hold, hold, methinks you ſeem to be an Ancient Gentleman. Tºpe. Ancient Gad take me, I am tough, and well ſeaſon'd? All this laſt Generation were but half gotten, and have the Rickets. . . . . . . . L. Mag. Do not grow troubleſome. . . . . . . tº Tope, Troubleſome, Sweet-heart, be not fooliſh: Ah! thou knowſt not - what’s in me. . . . . . . . . . . . L. Mag, Yes, I ſuppoſe laſt Nights lewd Doſe, and two Bottles this Morn- ing : That an old Gentleman with one foot in the Grave ſhould be thus lewd. Tºpe. Ounds ! I cou’d find in my heart to kick her; ſhe has provok'd my cholier more than ever ſhe can raiſe my love. But I will diſſemble, a whore ſhe is, my whore I'll make her, that, i may revenge the indignity, and uſe "her ſcurvily. Come, my Dear, thqu doſt not take me for a Milk-ſop, to ac- cept of one denial—Have at her. -- — Women born to be controll'd, Stoopto the forward and the bold. La Mag. Old Gentleman be civil. s-- i. • * * - * -- . Tope: Old agen! you women are for the youngſtripling that ſwitch,and ſpur a ſhort race like Citizens on May-day in the Park, but we ſolid Lovers are for the whole courſe, come come I know what you come for, and you ſhall not go without it—l'le carry you to a Friends Lodging—and I gad I'll, I'll—no more to be ſaid. '. La. Mag. You are a ſawcy old Fool, and I'll have you kickt; Tope. Corne, come, you ſhall go, no matter for that. - * La Mag. Help, help, help f : . . . . Enter Wildf. - * Will. A Lady in Diſtreſs! Do you Want my aſſiſtance 2 I am at your ſer- vice—How now jack, what Raviſhing 2. . . . . . . L. * - - - - - * -- r *_*--- Sir. Humph. Well Chicken, thou wilt have thy own way, be not offended
Page 17

------- - - 2 ( 17 ) Lé, Mag. I ſee you are a man of Honour, a thouſand thanks for delivering *me from the Aſſaults of this Libidinous Goat. He is the fineſt Gentleman I ever ſaw. . Aftie. . . . . - - . . Wild. So fine a Lady ſhall never want any Service I can do her. La Mag. Sweet Sir, really your manner is ſo obliging. - Zope. Theſe damn'd young Fellows, like Dutch Capers, will ſnap up all Adventurers, they have the better of us at cruiſing, we have no game to play at but ready. Whore, ready Money. - Wild. You do me too much honour - . La. Mag. O I am charm'd with him— (aſide) You have ſo infi- nitely oblig'd me, that Sir I aſſure you I ſhall be always proud of it, and hope to ſee you at my houſe in Soho Square. . . - . . . Wild, You make me bluſh at my little ſervice: Alas that Gentleman may ſay what he will, he puts on a rough outſide, but he is a very harmleſs man to a Lady as can be. ... • - - . . . . . . . . . Tope. Prithee, now I ſee her Face take her and make your beſt on't. La. Mag. Was there ever ſo rude a Perſon 2 - Wild. You know where you are Sir. Tope. What Sir 2 º . º ºuts jack Tepe diſſemble a little, there's a trick in't, it ſhall turn to thy good. - - Tope. Pox on her? I care not if ſhe were hang'd. Exit Tope. * Lady Mag. Sir I beſeech you engage not your Perſon in my Quarrel, if any hurt ſhould come on't, I ſhould for ever hate and curſe my ſelf. . . . Wild. Not on my honour this is Maggot the Aldermans wife, ſhe has two pretty Daughters come to Town, and great Fortunes; beſides tho ſhe is declining, ſhe is but a little on the other ſide of the Hill, and looks well and luſty, - - a . * Mag. Sir I fear you are meditating on Revenge upon that old Ruffian; I ſhall wiſh I had never been born, if I ſhould engage ſo fine a Gentleman in danger, for that reaſon let me deſire the honour of your walking with me while I am in the Mall, and afterwards if you pleaſe to protećt me to my Houſe; I ſhall there be able to make in ſome meaſure a return for this ſignal favour. Wild. I am your Slave Madam, wholly at your diſpoſal. " ' ". . . . . Lady Mag. Qh lucky adventure I this was the happieſt moment of my Life. aſide. Who's here my Daughters Governeſs 2 " Enter Priſ. Caytiff what doſt thou from thy charge 2 where are my Daughters ? . . Priſ. My charge, they have broken looſe from me and defy'd me, and you too : They forc'd me to the Park, here they are taken up by a wild Fellow; who bid his Footmen ſeize on me and toſs me in a Blanket. . . , Lady Mag. Oh vile wretch! Ple ſtrangle thee, I’le tear thy Windpipe out, where are they 2 ſpeak, ſpeak, ſpeak. Priſ. Hold off your hands. you choke me, I can't ſpeak. -" Lady Mag. Where where, you old fuda. ? Priſ. At the further end of the Mall. - Lady Mag. Forgive my indecent paſſion, and let me beg your aſſiſtance— follow Beldame. ~ - D Wild. z - * v
Page 18

- - { 18 ) - * Will, f wait on you Madam, this was a happy opportunity. [affili, Exeumt. s " Enter Sir William Rant, Eugenia and Clara. - tº f Clara. Dear Siſter, Let's go, I tremble every Joynt, Oh if my Mother ſhould ce us 2 - - - -. . . . . . . -- - - - - Miſſ Hill. Dear pretty Cozen know thy power, and defy the Tyranny of thy other. ** ." . . . . * . . . . . clara. The only man my Mother has perpetually warn'd us off. . . . . . . Sir Will. Ha! I am glad of that, ſhe could not poſſibly have contriv'd better to bring us together. [Aftlej But dear Eugenia, thou ſweeteſt creature that the Earth e're bere ! conſider thy own confinement, and my miſèry: There is not in a Dungeon ſuch a wretch as Iſhould be without thy kindneſs. . . . . . . ... ... Eugen. What you take me for a poor weak country thing, as ready to be º as any Foo you ever ruin'd yet; I'll make you know 1 am above your rts. * * * * * * * * > . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Sir Will, You are to me what ere you pleaſe to be, but I to you muſt be the trueſt, and the heartieſt Lover that ever Beauty was too hard for yet. -- - Eugen. You talk as if you were ſerious, can you imagine this will paſs, how ſmoothly you rehearſe it 2 . . . . . . . . . . . . . *- : . . . . -- r. , Sir Will, Tear out my heart and thou wilt find thy Image there Eugen. "Fuſtian rapture ſaid to a hundred tawdy things in a week. Can you think me ſo mad to fling my ſelf away upon ſo notorious a lewd creature? 'Tis a certain ruin to be ſeen with you. - . . . - | Sir Will. I am ſtruck in a moment, you have already converted me, I will • a be as remarkable in my penitence, as ever I was in my wickedneſs, Parſons * - ſhall write books of it, and preach upon it while I am living. . . . . Eugen. A very pretty piece of Raillery. . . º. º. . . . . . . . . ; *Sir Will. Raiſiery tº by Heaven and Earth't gº. ". . . . . . . . . . . ; , Eug, Nay, nay, no ſwearing, your Bead roll's long enough already,you ſhall fhave no Sin added to it upon my account. . . . . . . . . . . . . . ... Clara. Siſter, dear Siſter lets be gone. “ 2 - 1 1. . . . . Sir Will. All the Sins I ever ſhall commit will fall upon you, I ſhall runmad, ſtark mad, moſt furiouſly mad. * * * * : * ~ * * * * * * . . . . . ** * * * * - - * * * * * * : . . . . . - - - tº a Euge. What madder than you have been 2 : º 'º - . . . . . . . . . . | Sir Will My former life will be thought an Anchorets to what will follow, if you refuſe me. I am reſolv'd to uſe all the ways that cºre were try’d to gain a woman,— and did the world depend on me, I'de ruin all before I'de oſe ou.". . ; : "... º.º.º. -- º . . . . .” * 3, -, 2- - - - - - - - l tº obtaia, fireho hear him any longer. … . . . . . . . . . . ** Eugen, Softly good Sir, he that dares make love to me muſt undergo a Task too hard for you. . . . . . . . *::: ſ , , tº ‘. Sir Will. Name it, there's nothing too hard for ſuch a Lover. . . . . . . . Eug. I muſt have my weekly Tribute of Sonnet and Madrigal, full of ſacred, divine, Nymph and Goddeſs. ". . . * - : … . | Sir Will. It ſhall be done. ** * * ... . . . . , Eug. And my daily offering of humble, and diſconſolate billets dor, about the Lüſtre of my Beauty, the light of my Eyes, &c. - - º, Sir Will. And this. Eug.
Page 19

- - ( 1.9 ) * - Eugen, I muſt have all former women ſacrific'd to me, and he muſt not date to look upon another beſides me. . .*.*, *, * . . . - Sir Will. All all, if I had ten thouſand. . . . . . . . . ...Eugen, All lewd Company muſt be deſerted, and Wine aboliſhed ſave three Glaſſes at a meal, and he muſt be the pattern of Vertue for the whole Town, conſider now, and tremble. . . . ºf . . . . . . - Sir Will. All this ſhall be done, I have conſidered, and will conſider no more, northink, nor live any longer than I ſhall call Eugenia mine. Enter Lady Maggot, Wildfire and Priſcilla. , * * * , La Mag. Oh Heaven they are here with my Nephew, the lewdeſt wretch that ever breath'd this wicked air, but hold! … º 'Clara. What delicate man is this f He is a moſt ſurprizing creature, Heav'n would I had not ſeen him tº Clara lºoking about, ſpies Wildfire firſt. Wild. What Angel's this 2 Ine'r ſaw Beauty till this minute, She has ſtruck me under the left Pap. * . - - Clara. Oh my Mother. - - - --> * La Mag. Do you ſtart you Baggages 2 were it not in the Park, I'd make you ſuch Examples of my Rage—come along-l'Il rout you out of this place, Go, go packing through St. james's houſe: I’ll bring up the Rear. Follow 'em you old Gipſy, Governeſs. Nephew how dare you coinmit this outrage, this inſolence upon me! Avoid my preſence, and never more come near me or my houſe. - Wild. This new Beauty has fir'd me, and blown me up. - --- Sir Will. Look thee, my Termagant, Maſculine, He-Aunt, if thou uſeſt me or my:Couſins thus, I will ſcowre, and roar-thee out of Soho-Square into Mark-lane again: And that will break thy heart.... . . . . . . . . . . . . . . La. Mag. I will conſider of that. Sir, if you pleaſe let me ſtill hold the honour of your company ; haſte, haſte. . . . . . . . To Wildfire. Wild. Why how now Tom 1 * ~ * -º Sir Will. Peace Will peace, I'll keep my time: [Ex. Wild, and Lady Mag. Tope. What a Devil has Tom Wildfire taken up my Aunt 2. Enter Tope. Tope. How now Knight Errant, have you done adventuring for Surgeons work 2 'tis almoſt Dinner time, Ilong for Brimmers, did you ſee who went off with your Aunt is ſhe given to ſtumble 2 will ſhe take a ſtone in her Ear? Sir Will. She comes of a goodſtrain by the Males, but come along with me we'll make 'em a viſit, what Rogues are theſe ? [Enter Whac. Ding, and Bluſt. They have dog’d and ſtar'd at us ever ſince we came into the Park, one looks like a tawdry Spark of the City, and the other two like Bayliffs followers. Whach. Sir, I underſtand Sir, that you are Sir William Rast, Sir. Sir Will. I am, what then 2 - *- - Whac. Nay no offence, my name is Tim Whachum, Alderman Whackums Son deceaſed, and Alderman Maggot your uncle in laws Nephew. . Sir Will. It may be ſo. - * . . . . . Tºpe, what would this Puppy beat - - Whach. I have ſeen your Perſon before, and admir'd you, I have ſeen you ſcower ſo rarely, Sir I have had a mighty Ambition for the honour of your ac- * . - D 2 - quiantance ;
Page 20

* - ( 20 ) , quaintance; For my part Sir, I am a very mad Fellow as any wears a head, and I conceive Sir you love a mad Fellow. - > - Sir Will. A very pleaſant Raſcal. * s - - Whach. I have heard Sir, that you delight much in drinking, whoring,ſcow- ring, beating the Watch, breaking Windows and ſerenading, and the like Sir. Sir Will. Was there ever ſuch an awkard Rogue, to make a man out of love with Lewdneſs. - - - - Whac. Now if there be madder Fellows about the Town than I, and my two Companions—Why we have been bound over to the Seſſions three times this week. I ſuppoſe you may have heard of our roaring about Holbourn, Fet- ter-lane, Salisbury court, &c. : Sir Will. Yes I have Sir, and you are moſt gallant, and magnanimous Fel- lows. Now all's out jack Tepe, we will ſo ſwinge theſe Rogues, Here's a Fellow ofthis Nuncles breeding. - - º Whach. Now good noble Sir if you pleaſe to honour us with your Acquain- tance, I vow to Gad Sir, I ſhall be as proud Sir, as proud Sir as -- - Sir Will. Sir’tis much to my Advantage, and I &mbrace the honour moſt reedily. " - - - - * - 3 i. well here's the fineſt Gentleman that ever beat a Conſtable, let him be whom he will; Sir, Sir I am moſt infinitely overjoy'd, be pleas'd to know my Friends, Godsookes, they are as gallant Fellows as ever walk'd the ſtreets at Midnight. - - - Sir Will. Your Servant Gentlemen. . . . . . . . Ding. Your moſt obſequious Spaniel. rº - Bluff... Your moſt humble Trout... g. … . . . -- * Tope. Trout! Pox on him for a Blockhead, is that Fellow a Trout?' Sir Will. Be pleas'd to know my Friend, - Whach. Sir I am no Stranger to your Worth, and Magnanimity; now no- ble Sir if you, and your Gang will compleat this Hononr, and ſup with us to night at the Bear and Harrow, behind St. Clements, where we intend to begin our Frolick; it may be Sir you may ſee ſcowring that will not be amiſs. Sir Will. We will, be ſure to beſpeak a good Supper. ~ . . . .” *Whach, Dam me I am overjoy’d Sir, if we joyn togetherwe'll carry all the Town before us, your Servant ſweet Sir, I'll be ſure to beſpeak Supper, do you love a huge shoulder of Mutton and Oyſters, and a couple of fat Capons in the firſt place. - - Sir Will. Aye aye, very well: at Eight let it be. Whac. Come Dingboy and Bluffer, I am tranſported, I have much ado to forbear Huzzaing in the Mall. Exit Whachum, Bluſter and Dingboy, Tope, Did yeu ever meet ſuch nauſeous Raſcals, they will convert more than thedrunken Spartan Slaves. A. Sir Will. Whett thy Rage and let us make examples of 'em,now will I teaze my haughty Aunt, and confound my fooliſh uncle. Exeumt. y

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 21

---, ---------------------- ( 21 ) . - - . . . . - - º - - - * - - - º, - - - * - º re * * f - enter Wildſ. La. Mag, Eugenia, Clara, Priſcilla. L. *S* you young Rebellious Sluts, I have you ſafe; I'll teach you to- - O go to the Park. Eugen. So you do, by your own example. - - ... x* - - L. Mag. Yes, Huſwife, I am experienced, and proof againſt temptation, by. my known Vertue and Wiſdom. - , - Clara. And we doubt not but our unknown Vertue and Wiſdom, as you call it, will defend us too. . . . L. Mag, How now, Mrs. Milkſop, are you grown pert and refraćtory 2. Priſc. She, ſhe is as bad as tºother every whit. - - L. Mag. There's none ſo bad as thee, old puſs. Thou filthy, toothleſs, wormeaten old Maid, I'll maul thee, thou Witch of Ender. [She beats and Priſº. Murther, Murther, Murther, will you throttle me? kicks hir. Wild. I cannot live without my pretty Creature: What charms are theſe ? What do I feel 2 º z. - - | - Clara, Oh Siſter, the fight of this man has ruind me; I never ſhall recover. it. - - * * Eugen. Ah! art thou there faith, recover it : Why, who would put a ſtop to love 2. Give Reins to it, and let it run away with thee. T- - - - - L. Mag. Oh prodigious and amazing I Did they ſay all this 2 - Priſ. Yes, that they did, and ten times more : So they did, what would, you have me do 2. They ſaid they would throw off your Tyranny, and have . no more to do with you. - . - * . L, Mag. Oh, Heaven! Is this true 2 Did you ſay.ſo, young Rebels 2. ºf". Yes, and are reſolv'd to do ſo. Siſter, take courage, and ſpeak thy, ITMI1Gä- - - - v . . ~ - - Clara. We were not made to be mew’d up like the Hawks in moulting time. § Eugen. We were born free, and we'll preſerve that freedom ; we have learn'd more Wit than to call Self-defence Rebellion. - r Wildf. Brave mettled Girls ; I grow mad in Love, and 'twill break out . into a flame. [Aſide. - - -- . L. Mag. Moſt amazing impudent Girls; I'll tear your eyes out. . Eugen. Offer to uſeus thus one moment longer, and I will chooſe my unkle Rant my Guardian. - Clara. And I am reſolv'd to do the ſame. w L. Mag. Moſtincredible impudence, let me come at 'em. l - Wilf
Page 22

-------- ------------------ - º . . . . r ~. - ºldf. I beſeech your Ladyſhip. . [He takes Eugenia and Clara by the hands, If you be unkind as you are fair, I am for ever miſerable. [Privately to Clara. • "Chara. Heav'n l-what do I hear! - -- --- - - L. Mag. Sir, I humbly demand your pardon; I muſt confeſs, the diſorders *º- of my Family have tranſported me into an indecent paſſion, which a Lady of cºra: Oh, Eugenia, pity me: I am ruind! loſt to all the world : and diſcourſe theſe matters calmly with you. my Quality ſhould not have expoſed to a perſon ſo gallant and well-bred as your ſelf. . . . - — - Wildf. Pardon me, Madam. - - . L. Mag. But you ſhall find, Noble Sir, that ſhe who can to extravagance be ſenſible of affronts and injuries, can with as much zeal and ardency, reſent * * - - - - - the generous favour you have loaded her with. * Wildf. Madam, you make me bluſh with— -- . . . . . . . . L. Mag. And I'll aſſure you, Sir, there is not a perſon living, who can be more grateful to a perſon, that obliges any perſon, than I ſhall ſhow my ſelf to your Noble Perſon. - . . . . . . . . . Eugen, Hey : What Riddle's this 2 Eugen. But to him, and him, and only him. - * ": - 3 L. Mag; You young Rebellious Sluts, go to yourchamber, Pll come to you Eugen. We'll obey. º . . . . [Exeunt Eugenia and Clara, L. Mag. You Cecropia, when they are in their Chamber lock the Doos upon? them, .# keep the Key, or I will ſtrangle thee, thou old wither'd ſhe Baboon. Priſ. Heyho, hey ho, what ſhall I ſay, what ſhall I do Exit Priſc; Wildf. I am finely drawn in Muſt I come at the Daughter by the Mother 27 my Conſcience ner will ſerve me, that’s certain : She’s furious too, what the Devil ſhall I do to keep her off; I'll try great civility and reſpečt to her. . . La Mag. Now noble Sir, Ibeſeech you pleaſe to retire where we ſhall have a fitter place and opportunity more apt to expreſs my grateful reſentments. . . . . Wildf. For Heavens ſake, Madam, put not a value upon nothing; you have thoſe charms, thoſe graces, and that wit and beauty, that all the ſer- vices of my life would be too little to expreſs the paſſion which I have for you.” La, Mag, Oh Lord, Sir, for me ! a perſon that—I beſeech you Sir let us retire, ſince I have ſomething to impart to you, in which I willingly would not meet an interruption. - Hildf. I am yours, and only yours, Ex. Wildf. and Lady. ** . . . . . Enter Priſcilla. - - * Priſ. So now they are ſure; I have 'em under Lock and Key, I warrant’em, Enter Sir Humphry Maggot, Whachum, Bluſter and Dingboy, Sir Humph. How now old Priſc. Where is my Lady ? . . Priſ. With a Gentleman who came to viſit her, in her Chamber ; he is a ſtranger, I know him not. But I’ll take care ſhe ſhall not be ſurpriz'd. Aſide. Sir Hump. Tell her I am here, bid 'em haſten dinner and bid the Butler bring ſome Hock for a whet; we in the City can't eat without ſeveral whets in a forenoon. Whach, I whet ſo often when I am there, that at laſt ’tis a blunt. - . - Sir

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 23

y- - - - ---------- --- ( 23 )-- º ...' * *. you ſhall ſee your Miſtreſs preſently, . Enter Butler with a Bottle, . . . . . '* * * Sir Humph well fid Nephew, Come, here fill a Glaſs. May I crave your names again, Gentlemen. . . . . Blufter. Mine is Blufter. - * . . . • ". Dingboy. And mine is Dingboy. - * * * - ... • Sir Humph. Brave names for bold pleaders at the Bar. - . * • VWhach. They plead at the Barf ha, ha, ha: They may hold up their hands thore, but never hold up a breviate to point at a Judge with. Aſide. Sir Humph, Come Nephew all of us chockon, chockon, to an abſent friend, - . ha, hum; you know—no more to be ſaid. They claſh their Glaſſess- Whach. Bluff. Ding. With all our hearts. ... • | Sir Humph, Well, things will come about again. Let me tell you, we ſhall be upon a right bottom once more. - . . . . . . . . Blaſt. I am glad to hear you ſay ſo: Your Worſhip's a wiſe man. . . . Whach. As wears a Head in the City. - º . Ding. As wears a pair of Horns there. . Aſide. | Sir Humph. Look you, the King of France will have the greateſt Fleet in the World at the Needles by February. - - - - VWhach. But thoſe French do ſo burn Houſes, Churches, Barns, Men, Wo- men and Children, that I am afraid they'll do a great deal of hurt. . . . * | Sir Hump. Ay that's to their Enemies, but they are our Friends, Did not the Grand Lewis declare ſo? and that he lov'd the Church 2 by that brave and gallant Perſon, our Friend Admiral Bagnio. . . - - - Whach. Oh ay, all he does is out of kindneſs to us, and the ſincere Friend- ſhip he has for his Kindred, I'll tell you, but we ſay here that, the Turks are beaten: - . . . . A - - ~ ; Sir Hump. Piſh not a word, alas we never have any Truth, a worthy Ro- man Catholick whom Irely upon, told me that this ſame Duke of Croy loſt his whole Army, and ran away by himſelf to the Emperour, and the Turks are now in poſſeſſion of that Bridge and Town, and County of what do you call 'em, of Eſſex in Moldavia, and Teckley and the great Baſhaw have coop'dup the German Army. Give us another Whett. - Whac. Come on. . . - * * - * , Sir Hump, Here's to the Turk, the Pope, and King of France, we are of one ſide now. - * - - Bluft, & Ding. Come on. - - Sir Hump. We hear all Lyes • I warrant you think Cork and Kinſale are ta- ken, No no no, not a word; but come we ſhall have my Wife or ſome body” come to interruptus, let’s retire into my ſmoaking Room, and we'd diſcourſe freely of theſe affairs. . . * * ~ * Exeant. . . . . . . . . . Enter Lady Maggot and Wildfire. - Wild. Oh Madam the great Tenderneſs I have for Ladyſhips honour, chills my blood.' ' - - - Lady Mag. 'Tis generouſly ſpoken moſt noble Sir, though I am perfeſt mi- ſtreſs of my own houſe. . - * Wild

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 24

. . " I muſt have all go in the Platonick way henceforth. I ſhall make bold to cal * - (*) * * * , , º, . -' - - - Wild, Oh Madam the danger affrights me from the chief happineſs: I wiſh on earth never man had ſuch a paſſion as I have for her Daughter, aftale. Lady Mag. So generous a paſſion, I cannot but think an honour to me, but you my Strephon, and I beſeech you to accept of this Ring. Wild. Deat Madam you confound me. - - Lady Mag, Dear Sir it muſt not be refuſed, I vow’d never to part with it º but as a pledge of my affeition, and you being the worthieſt Gentleman I ever ſaw. J - - , Wild. You undo me with your Favours; this may be of uſe as I will make. it. . aſide. I long to have the honour of your Ladyſhips converſation at my houſe, where I may fully expreſs the violent paſſion I have. º Lady Mag, Sweet Sir I (A Flouriſh of Fiddles.) Ha what noiſe is that? ſome Rogues, Fidlers are come to welcome my Daughters to Town; I'll leave you for a moment Sir to ſee if they be ſafe. Exit Lady Maggot, Wild. What a prize would this be to a young Fellow, who wanted a keep- er, who can part with ſuch a Ring for a bare promiſe, which I am ſurel ne'r will keep. Enter Sir William Rant. --- Sir Will. VVhat is there no body in the houſe hah Tom what will nothing ſerve you but my Family, but ſhe is by the half blood. . . . . . . . Wild, upon my honour Will, thou art in the wrong, I have no deſign upon thy Aunts perſon, but I hope to make her my inſtrument for ſtealing one of her Daughters perſons. ~ - - * . . . . Sir Will. How, one of her Daughters . . . Wild. You know I have a good clear Eſtate, I ſaw your two Couſins by accident, and am ſo devilliſhly in Love with one of 'em, that I am § I can, even to marry her for one good night, though I were ſure to be hang'd next Morning. - . . . . Sir Will. As for the honour of my Aunt, lye with her when you will, and, I'll be no more concerned than other Sparks about the Town are for their Siſters; but for my Couſins know I am in love to greater madneſs with one of 'em, and if yours happens to be her, I am ſure that both of us ſhall not live. Wild. Thou knoweſt Will, I am not capable of fear, if it be my fate to be in Love with the ſame, I can bewayl it, but can never alter. . . . . . . ." Sir Will. Keep me in doubt no longer, in this caſe a ſhort clearing of the mattel's beſt. L - x - Will You are in the right, and it muſt out, it is— Sir Will. Which. - Wild. The youngeſt. - * * > Sir Will. My dear dear Tommy, let me hug and kiſs thee; go on and proſper, I'll aſſiſt thee. Enter Lady Maggot. - La. Mag. Mercy on me, who's here! are they ſuch dear friends 2 What will become of me! Yet ſure he's a man of Honour; he has too faſt hold on mº, and ’tis too late to retreat. " . . . . . . Sir Will. Oh my ſweet, my honour’d Aunt, your humble ſervant; it is a common blockheaded trick to ſtrenade and diſturb people at midnight, I am - COmē * h - n Leº |
Page 25

x - - - - - - (25) - - come to ſerenade you at Noon, and have ordered my dinner to come hither' I come a houſe-warming. " * La Mag. unheard of Impudence, thou moſt audacious Fellow, thou only blemiſh of our Family, did I not forbid thee my houſe 2 muſt thou bring Infamy: where it never entred. - . . - - - Sir Will. Look thee Aunt, if thou wilt be civil and well bred, I will kiſs thy Hand, make Legs and uſe thee like an Aunt, but if wars muſt enſue, I will roar and ſcowre thy houſe ſo, that thou mighteſt lye as quietly in a beſieged Town, with Bombs and Carcaſſes flying about thy Lodging, - Lady Mag. Avaunt thou Devil incarnate, I’ll order thee. '. Sir Will. Nay then, enter my Friend jack Tope, all my Singers, and Fiddles, and my whole Equipage De boyre, - Wild. Fear not your perſon, I'll protećt it. - La Mag. You ſhall not expoſe your own for it, moſt generous Sir, I’ll order . him, lewd wretch. - * . . - Sir Will. Come, enter, Enter Tope, Sir Williams Servants and Muſicians. Lady Magg. Help, help, here Mr. Alderman, Mr. Maggot. - - Sir Will. Strike up my Lads. They all roar and ſing and play the Tung Tope. Come on my Boys, halloo. . . . of Let the Souldiers rejoyce. Come Lady give me thy hand, dance and frisk about. - - Lady Mag, Hang the old Coxcomb, Hold, hold, hold, Mr. Maggot, Mr. Maggot. TEnter Sir Hump. Whac. Bluſt. Ding, & Butler, with other Servants. Sir Hum. Hah, Gad forgive me, who are here 3 / - : Sir Will. Oh honeſt Alderman, nown Nuncle, i' faith we are come to roar a little with thee, and we have ordered our Dinner, we come a houſe- warming. - - Lady Mag. Ohthou tame Beaſt, wilt thou hear them ſpeak 2 make a w 3ſ- rant and ſend them to the Gatehouſe, or Newgate. Sir Humpb. Oh Nephew have a care of him, let’s retire. Sir Will. Look you Mr. Alderman, I have ſecured the Paſs, If you will be a good towardly unkle and take advice by me, it ſhall be moſt profound peace, and great Civility, but if you will provoke me, I'll make you ſpend your time very uneaſily. VWhac. Oh, rare, Bluffer and Dingbo), here will be gallant ſport, to our Hearts deſire. La. Mag. Oh pitiful Nincompoop, what doſt fear him 2 Sir Hump. Good Chicken, have a little patience. Tºpe. Confider Madam, patience is a great vertue for a Lady of your years. Lady Mag. My years, I ſpit at thee thou old muſty Raſcal, my years Oh thou cowardly Wittal, is thy wiſe Nephew a coward too : I will thunder in their ears. , - Sir Hump. Nay let thee alone thou art a notable Girl. La Mag. Begone you Villains, lewd Raſcals. . - Sir Will. Strike up, out noiſe her | . They roar, and ſing, and play; and leap La Mag. Ruffians, Vagabonds, Ragemuffians, about, and ſo do Whachum, slaves, Dogs, Scoundrels, hold, hold, gº. Bluſter and Diº \\ - ir / * -

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 26

--- ( 26 ) . s Sir Will. Hold, hold, ſhall we come to Articles of Peace? , - Sir Will. Oh Gallant Oh rare ſport | by Gad they are the fineſt Gentle- men in Chriſtendome. - * - - Sir Hump. Mercy on me Nephew, did you fing and rejoyce with them. * forbear. -- Tope, Alderman, I will ſwinge thee with brimmers, and make thy old myul- dy Aldermanſhip, more drunk than ever any of the huzzaing, roaring, loyal Raſcals were, who would have given up the City Charter. - VWild. I beſeech you Madam, diſſemble a little patience, they ſhall give a ſevere account upon my honour. - - . - * . La. Mag. Well you have filenc'd me, and in ſome meaſure appeaſed me . ſince you ſay you intend only a civil Muſick Conſort and a Dance, what would you more, I am tame. . . . . . . . . . . Sir Will. I muſt have both my Couſins, it is my intention to welcome them to Town, - - - - S. . . Lady Mag. Out of my houſe, you ſhall be hang'd firſt, bring Infamy upon them, they are far enough off. . . . . - . . . . . . . Whach. Gad takeme Sir, 'tis ſuch a pretty Tune, fleſh and blood could not sºil."Rººſes, and let nobody out, ſend for my preciſe houſe-keeper, and inſtruct her as I bid thee. • Ralph. Yes, I muſt do it. º Sir Will. Come my Lads march and roar, I will ſearch every Room in the houſe, but I will have her. - Ex. Sir William and Fiddles, &c. La Mag, Qh thouſneaking old Fumbling Fool! get thouout thou Coward, Maggot, Infect, Nittworm. *. Sir Hump. Why Chicken, chicken, chicken, - - La. Mag. Get thee out I ſay, and ſend for a Conſtable, and ſend them to ail. - She beats him out. Wildf. Come along Madam, I’ll protećt you, and appeaſe them, put on a little patience, and I'll warrant you all ſhall be well. [Exeunt Wild, and Lady. ! Whac. Huzza mydear Raſcals | Here's a day ! here's a happy day ! Let's hugg and kiſs one another, oh my brave Midnight-boys, what a night ſhall . we have with this rare, this excellent, this moſt accompliſh'd Gentleman! Oh I could kiſs the ground he goes upon. - * - - - - Bluff. Now we are leagu'd, we'll govern all the Town by night. Ding. We ſhall be ſtil'd the High and Mighty Princes of the night. Whac, Shall our dull Loggerheaded Magiſtrates think to rule the City,with old decrepid Fools in Rug-gowns, and Furr'd Caps, no let them govern by day, but Gad take me, we honeſt Fellows will ſwagger by Night, Boys, Ha Rogues, have at them, hey. - . . Exit Alderman, Sir Hump. What ſhall. I do? Look, my Nephew and his Companions re- joyce as much as any of 'em. . - PWhach. Hold ; my uncle ! * * * to them. * Sir Hump. Students of the Law,4uoth he Rakehells damn'd Rakehells, pray come and retire with me. - …' … Exeunt, | - - . . - - - - - ºr - * - - Enter - * ---—tº --- - - - 1.
Page 27

( 27 ) - - Enter Sir Wiii. Euge, Glara, Lady Mag. Wild, Tope. All the Muſick and - Servants, ſinging and roaring, &c., Sir Will. Madam this is to ſave the trouble of a Habeas Corpus, to free my Couſins from illegal Impriſonment. - - Mady Mag. to Wild, Well I will have patience Sir, but to morrow into the Country they go, and ſhall never come into this wicked Town, till their Huſ- bands ſhall think fit to bring 'em, - - f Wild. You will do well. - - [to her. but I ſhall take care to prevent you. . aſide. Tope. We Knights Errant, Lady, are bound by our noble order to ſuccour diſtreſſed Damſels, and free them from enchanted Caſtles, and to mall Gyants, and more fell creatures, your Viragos Madam, your Viragos, hah. Sir Will. Now my pretty ſweet Couſins, let me have the honour to enter- tain you with Muſick, as your welcome to Town, this is a Forenoon Serenade. Eug. Sir 'tis a favour we muſt think our ſelves obliged for, after Bag-pipers, blind Harpers, and Country old-faſhion'd Virginal Maſters. . . . . Clara. And which is worſe than all, the full cry of a country Cathedral. Lady Mag. Very well, very well Baggages, I'll order you. aſide. Let 'em begin Sir William. - - - Sir Will. Now you are my good Aunt, I love and honour you, now I have brought you to reaſon, come Gentlemen begin. - - - Tope. Where's my Alderman f my dear Alderman 2 I muſt have him here, I will fetch him in. . . - - Exit Tope. - Re-enter with the Alderman Whachum, Bluſter and Dingboy. - Wildf. If you do not contrive ſuddenly, to get your Aunt out of the way for a moment, that I may ſpeak to my Miſtreſs, I am utterly ruin'd. I'll tell you the Reaſon. - - . º ... Sir Will. I warrant you, after the dance expečt I have a way. . . Muſick. Eug. 'I is admirable Muſick. - A Song. Clara. And well performed. - Sir Hump. I charge you Nephew, avoid this Company, as you would Bears or Tygers. . . . . . . - - - . … VWhach, Avoid 'em, no I'll hang firſt, good Nuncle, I intend to throw off your Yoke immediately, our ſcowring cannot be long conceal’d. . . . . . . Tope. Pox I hate theſe melancholy, fooliſh, love Madrigals, with damn'd imitation of the Italians quavering and diviſion, one Jolly drinking Song, is worth a thouſand, you ſhall let me have my Frolick, ſing me a Chauſon de boire. “ -- - A drinking Song. Hah this is right, I Gad there's ſome mettal in this, a Pox of Phillis and Cloris, this is my Frolick. ; Sir Will. Tis very well jack, now ſtrike up for a Dance, and by that time Dinner will enter. . . . . - T- Tops. Come along my Lads, hem, hem, now Madam you ſhall ſee who's old, ‘I will be Maſter of the Revels, and couple ye, here Alderman you ſhall dance with my Lady, no parting Man and Wife, ner diſpute, Gad it ſhall be ſo: Here Will here's a Lady for you. - He gives him Eugenia. Tom Wildfire here's a Lady for yº; : - - - gives him cº, - - 2 : Il
Page 28

- (28) And for my ſelf, I have a pretty young Jade in my Eye, fiété Cóñé out, come Iſay, I'll feague thee away i' faith, ſtrike up, ſtrike up, men of Roſin, Old : Gad take me, I'll ſee who's old now, . . . . - Sir Will. Why thou art a Youth, a Lad jack in thy prime. - Lady Mag. Oh thouold fumbling cowardly Fellow to bear all this, I'll order thee, Old Numps. - Sir Hump. Gad forgive me, what a ſad life ſhall I live with 2 Chicken, Tope. Strike up again. - - - Whac. VWhat a Pox they make nothing of me, but I'll make ſomething of - my ſelf, they ſhall find. They dance, VVhacum jumps and ſtruts, and , Dance. dances awkardly with them. Sir Will. Now Tom watch, my Lady will follow me: Madam I beg the Honour of one word in the next Room. [Sir VVill. draws Eug: to the next Room, Eug. I will if it be only to teaſe my Mother. ... - - *- Tope. Come my little Rogue, let us retire, Alderman I will lye with thy Maid, and make thee drunk, and that will be a good days work. ." | Sir Humph. Go you are a VVag, i' faith you are. Lady Mag. Oh º: My vile Nephew run away with my Daughter, along with me old Fool, with your Nephew and his Friends, come, cºme. Sir Hump. Well Chicken well, come along Nephew and Students. ~, . . . . . . Exeunt Lady, Sir Humphry,Whachum, Blufter and Dingboy. VWild. Madam your opportunities are ſofew, and like to be fewer, that it were an unpardonable fin to let one ſlip, your mother intends to ſend you in- to the Country by violence to morrow morning, you ſee Madam I dare not addreſs to you before her. * .. - - - . . . . . | clara. Sir you oblige me in this notice, but my Siſter and we will prevent - vºll. 1 humbly beg the honour of ſerving you, never man had ſuch a paſſion as you have raiſed in me,a flame will ruine and deſtroy me, your Per- ſon nothing can deſerve, but my Eſtate is plentiful without incumbrance. Clara. Pardon me Sir, that I am ſo free with you, you are a wild man of the Town, and I would as ſoon commit my ſelf to the Mercy of the Sea, in - ** a ſtorm, as into your Hands. - - - Wild. I ſhould not preſume to be thus daring to mention love, at firſt en- counter, but that the difficulty is like to be ſo great of ſeeing you; and I muſt let you know it, if you refuſe me, I muſt periſh, and I dare propheſy you'll be unfortunate. , Enter Priſcilla, and Exit preſently. Priſ. Are you at that ſport, this ſhall to my Lady. Clara.' 'Tis better to be unfortunate than fooliſh. . . . . . . . Wildf. Whatever I have been, the world ſhall never make me wild again unleſs your ſcorn ſhould make me deſperate, and then what fury it may drive me to I know not. - ~ : . . . . . . . . Clara. Nor have I reaſon to be concern'd, 'twill be no fault of mine. Why does the cuſtom of our fooliſh Sex oblige us to lying, I ſee no proſpect of any thing but ruine; I am reſolv’d never to joyn my ſelf to Lewdneſs, and yet his Perſon charms me into madneſs, oh misfortune ºf . She weep. - - 1 °. * , Wildf. ºn |
Page 29

- , - ( 29 ) - Wildſ. ſhall wiſh all the world except your ſelf, on fire if you deſpiſe InC, . Enter Whachum ſneakingly. Curſe on this Raſcal, I could willingly cut his throat. e Whach. Madam your moſt obedient Servant, Sir under the Roſe ſhe is my Miſtreſs. - ſ * . . . - , - Wildf. Damnation on this Loggerhead: ' , Whach. I'll tell you in your ear her Father has made a match for me and her, and I am to give her Mother 50ool for her, ha, hum. - Wildf. Tis very well. Whac. Ay but you area man of honour, to tell you truth I am for the Eldeſt, ſhe loves a mad Fellow like me. - Wildf. Now Madam confider, your Father in Law has made a match, and * - your Mother has ſold you for soool to this Puppy,but he ſays he is for the El- - Tope. Now ſtrike up and march along Boys. deſt, ſhe loves a mad Fellow like him. sº Whae. Sir, let mete'ſ you, 'tis ſomewhat uncivil to tell words that I ſpoke under the Roſe, I truſted to the Faith of a gallant Scowrer. - Wildf. Thou art a mighty thick skull'd Coxcomb, and I have a great Temp- tation to tweak thee by the Noſe. - – %ac. Gad ſave me he is a very gallant Gentleman. - Enter L. Maggot haling in Eugenia by the Hand, Sir Will. and Priſ, follows. Lady Mag. Oh outragious Impudence You ſteal one Daughter out of my preſence, and another makes love to her I left, I'll blow up the houſe before 1'll beat this. * - - - - . Wildf. ſpying my Lady. Prithee come on yourſelf, you ſheaking City wit and make love to your Miſtreſs your ſelf, do you think to put me upon it. - Whac, What a Devil do's he mean. z aftale. - Wild. You are the baſhfulleſt Fop, I ever ſaw, prithee ſtand up, hold up. your head, and ſpeak your mind. Oh Madam I humbly kiſs your Ladyſhips hands, your Kinſman here has been putting me upon ſaying fine things for him. Lady Mag. I am overjoy'd to find you the ſame man of honour I thought you, but my Nephew Sir William - - , - . - Wildf. Madam, I never keep him Company. - . . . . . . . Enter Tope, Alderman, Blufter and Dingboy. - . . . • ‘Tope. Come on my Lads, all you that are not given to mornings draughts, rejoyce, enter-Dinner in ſtate, come in Fiddles, I am Sewer and will march * , - A * * in the head of it. Enter Veniſon, Turbott, Calvert Salmon and the reſt; and . the luſty Bearers of the ſwinging Hamper come, do you Friends wns up the Rear. f & Lady Mag. Well I will diſſemble,till I get theſe Raſcals out of my houſe, aſide; `... Whac, Qh my dear Rogue here will be ſport, here will be a glorious day ! Blufter and Dingboy that old Gentleman is a very pretty Gentleman? - They march out with Disner, ſinging and roaring, and old Tope in the had of them. , ſingtºg g P \ ix. * * --- - * - - - --- º . . . ". . . . . . . . . . . - • '' . . . . . . A I *- - - - ---- C I V. * i. - :- * . -

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page 30

• 2 . . . ‘. . . . . . . . . .” --- * : - - : -.' - . . . . r. T. --- I - - - - º - -- * * -----t - - —a tri-----> * - *** \ . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Enter Eugenia, Clara, in their Chamber. . . Euge, I H ERE will be fine work to day, the Alderman will by typºd as he callsit, my Lady-mother will be outragious; but it ſectiis ſº in- tends us for the Country to morrow. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - - . . Clara. And has ſold me for 5oool, to the Aldermans moſt impertinant Nephew. Euge. And no doubt has made as good a bargain for me, but we willdefeat her Ladiſhip: And for that end I withdrew with thee to conſult aboutour Delive- Taſ) Cé. - - -- - -- Clara. I have no proſpect of Deliverance, ſet me ſtay here, or go into the Country; I muſt be for ever miſerable ; I am in love to madneſs, to utter madneſs., . . . . . ! . . . . . . - - - . . . . . . … Euge, No ſure it cannot be, did not I hear a certain young Lady ſay, ſhe would not fall in love with a wild man of the Town, tho he ſould joyntºre her with the Eaſt Indies. . - - Clara. Oh Eugenial 'tis againſt my will, I ſooner would have choſen to hav been blaſted with Lightning : Love ſtruck as fiercely through my heart, an as little could I reſiſt it: But prithee do not triumph over my Misfortune." Euge, Misfortune why Loves the greateſt bleſſing upon Earth, Life is no- thing but a Shadow, Love is the Subſtance: Methinks I ſhould be nothing but -- a moving clod without it: Beſides he loves thee as furiouſly too, what wouldſt- thou have 2 - - - . . . . •, . . . . . . . . * * Clara. Not him of all the world..., , , - - r--- - tº . . . . . . . . . . . . . * * is Euge. Nor I the other, till I ſee a full Reformation in his Life, and Man- ners; if they think us worth that, they will ſoon ſhew the change, if they do not, ſure we ſhall have the ſenſe to think them not worthy of us. . . . . . . Clara. Theſe wild young men, like Tinder ſoon take Fire, and as ſoon’tis out again; they'll never change, nor has Love left me any ſence, but of my Miſèry— - . * - She weeps. Euge. Poor Clara ! What doſt weep?' poor Girl, thou art a Maudlin Lo- ver; This comes of Romances: I could never wean thee from 'em, for my part I am reſolv'd to keep up my Spirit, come what will. ; . . . . . Clara. Prithee do not laugh at me, to be a Jeſt is the vileſt, and moſt mi- ſerable of Conditions. - . . . * - - Euge. And that thou wilt deſerve, if thou wilt not do anything towards thy own Freedom, thou art like thoſe unreaſonable craven Fellows that would do nothing towards the Deliverance of England, and yet would have all the . *- benefit -- !
Page 31

a - * - . . + - - * -- thºs w a Lady. ; ... ( 31 ) benefit of the change, nay would keep thoſe that did, out of the Government: Clara. Prithee don't draw a Simile upon me, I am reſolv’d to do any thing Reaſon or Honour will allow. - Euge. In the firſt place,you reſolve to chooſe my uncle Rant your. Guardian. Clara. I do. . . ". . . . . . ." Euge. Secondly to be rul’d by him, he is a juſt, vertuous and honourable man, and of great Humanity. - -- Clara. I will wholly reſign my ſelf to him. - - Euge. Thirdly and laſtly, thou wilt take the firſt opportunity of honourably, and prudently running away. - - - - * - . . Glara. I will, . . . . . . . . . Elge. Thy hand upon't. . . . . . . . . . . . ." . - - . * * - º * * * -: * . . Clara. Done. . . *.. º'-- 3: ... ſi *- : “ . . . . . . . . Eng. Now let my brain work, what has out Jaylor been at the Door?' " ... Clara. Twas very filently. Priſ, unlocks the Door, and lets in Whachum. - ºx Euge. Are you there old Mrs Turnkey * - - - . . . . … Priſ. Yes, and you are like to be there, I can tºll you, while I am ſo. . . Whach, Ladies I am your moſt humble iº, we have had finart bout on't with theſe Gallants, to ſay t º on't, they are as fine Gentlemen as ere the Sun ſhin'd on. . . . . . ." . … • * * ...Eng. But how came you to enter here, ſweet Sir? . . . . Whac. Sweet Sir J good. aſide. By your Lady Mothers Com- Eugenia Bat it muſt be in private, your Earſweet Madam. * * * * * . Clara. Yêu need not whiſper, I’ll into the Cloſet. • ? -- 1: … . . . -mand dear ſweet"Madam, I have an affair to communicate to you, Madam . f : ... / º Whach. Now Madam, Cozen, if I may be ſo bold, but I hope to be nearer. of Kin to you. --- `s Eug. What you have bought my Siſter for 50ool. I hear 2 * * * * Wäch. Yes that I have of your Lady Mother, but as Gad ſave me I think my Lady's too dear, ſhe is a very jew, ſhe has no Conſcience, and to tell you the Truth Madam, as I am an honeſt man, betwixt you and , I don't like. the bargain, I had rather buy you Gold to Silver. - #. To tell you Truth, I don't like that bargain. . . . . . Wha c. You are a Wag Madam, but I am for your aery, brisk, gay, wild, young Filly, ſuch as you are, there's your Lady for my Money; and if you will be rul’d by me, we'll ſave the scool, and mump my Lady, Faith what ſay you ? hah hum. - - - - - - - - - - º - - - - - - - * - - - - Eug. My Lady ſhall have no jocol, there I'll be rul’d by you..." . " tºdac. Sweet Madam, I kiſs your hands, Come, come, I know your-heart, as well as if I were in you, as the ſaying is, come you love a brave mad Fel- low, ſuch as I am, Sniggs, I am one of the maddeſt Fellows about the Town, I ſing fear ſerenade, bluſter, break Windows, demoliſh Bawdy-houſes, beat Baºtº, ſº ower the Streets, and the like, as well as any he that ſwaggers in - -T-- * * * * *-* - . . . - - - ... 3-...-4:2+-tº-..…. ºf d.º.º. ºf nº. 3 ºf ºf . . "E: , ; ; pretty ingenfüşFellow. " " " tº tº º affle. * * * - - - - ... " * -: ‘. . .2. Giº be 'º'; ' ' '. º J. to ºx to "... tº lºokſ brº ºf - tº - - * : * * * * * * * : *. - ****** * * * * * * oth o ºsºphae ºr * - - - • * * * -º- is ºf -, -- ". . . . . . t". - “…sº V. … 'Cºil will ºr --
Page 32

. . . . . . . . .( 3.) ... " ." Whach. Ay Madam, I am all Frolick, how many Knockers of Doors do you think I nave at home now, that I twiſted off when I ſcower'd, gueſs now : #.º. gueſs. . . . . . . . . . . . - Whac. Why above two Hundrcd, ha hum, is not that very well?, O my Conſcience this morning I beat 20 Higling women ſpread their Butter about the Kennel, broke all their Eggs, let their fucking Pigs looſe, flung down all the Peds with Pippins about the ſtreets, ſcower'd like Lightning, and kick'd fellows like Thunder, ha, ha, has - - Eug. Very well. - Whach, Ay waſ not, ha,ha, ha; I wip'd out all the Milk ſcores at the Doors, - may l went about ſerenading with ſix Fidlers in a Dung-cart. Ha, ha, there was a Frolick, ha, ha, there's a mad fellow for you, and you talk of a mad Fellow; 'tis true Sir William and his Companions are pretty men, very pretty men : But I wou'd you ſaw me ſcower, - Eug. You a mad Fellow, and talk of ſcowring ! why don't you break open the door, and beat our old ſawcy Governeſs for locking us up? - - - - Whach. º now you put me in mind of it,I vow and ſwear Plldo't preſently, for I love and honour you, and if you don't look upon me, I ſhall hang my ſelf. Eug. No no, but you are in a pretty fair way for another to do it for you. Whac. Well Madam, but I'll ſhow you what a mad Fellow I am, this Night lºve Soho Square, Igad you ſhall ſee ſuch ſcowring, 'twill rejoyce your heart. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ... - Eug. Can you drink hard 2 . . - -: Whac. Oh bloodily, if you could but ſee me at the Popes head, no merry gang can be without me, there I laugh, and roar, and fing and am exceeding witty, the pureſt Company I never ſtir, they ſwear I have more wit than a- ny of the Poets. . " . . . j . . . ) Eug, That may very well be by the late Plays I have read, but all this while we are Priſoners. . . . -- * . . . . . . . Whac. Odſoakers that’s true. Here where are you,old damn'd old ſhe Jay- . lour 2 I'll break open the door, , . . . . . . . He bounces at the Door. Priſ. What means this uproar. . . . . . . . . Enter Priſcilla. tº ~ * ... Whac. Come on Mrs. Tawdry 'Cld Trigrimate 2 I will make thy dry bones rattle within the old tan'd Hide of thee; I’ll ſwinge thee, Mother Damnable what doſt thou lock up theſe pretty Ladies, Drab, Pole-cat. " . . . . Priſ. Help, help, Murther, murther, . He bales and turns her about, and oh you young Impudent Fellow, . . kicks her, ſhe flyes at him and ſcratches him. I'll tear out your Eyes. . * - - - - - - - .*, * Whac. Why how now Hag doſt thou ſcratch? ... Enter Clara. - Old Puſs, thou art grown into a Cat already, and ſhortly wilt take the de- gree of a Witch upon thee, have at thee, do you provoke me you damn'd Puſº Priſc. Murther, murther, murther. He beats her and ſhe ſcratches him. - Enter Lady Maggot. . . - La. Mag, Heav'n and Earth! What outrageia this Some trick of yours, you wicked Sluts. * * * * * - - - - . . . -- . WKhac. Oh ſhe has ſcratch'd and blooded me all over, for ought I know, I may loſe the uſe of my Face, - *rīſī- -
Page 33

( 33) -> Priſ. O Madam he has call’d me filthy names, abus'd and beat and kick'd me, for locking theſe pert unruly Creatures up. ... X Lady Mag. Death you young Raſcal' dare you abuſe my faithful Servant. for obliging me? you ſtupid Coxcomb, for keeping your Miſtreſs from running away from that ugly Phiz of thine ; get thee out of my houſe, I’ll order thee for a City Puppy, be gone, be gone. . . She pummels bim with her Fan, and Whac. Hold hold, hold—was ever ſuch a Vixen 2 hold Fift as he runs Lady Mag. Come Baggages you were of the party, come come, I'll endure theſe things no longer. - -- Euge. Nor we neither. Lady Mag. How 2 - ". … º Clara. Nor will we be for a Country Journy to morrow', Lady Mag. Will not : • * Eug. & Clara. No, will not... - - - - L. Mag. The World, this Houſe, and my Brains, are turn'd topſy turvy. The plagues of this one day alone are able to diſtraćt me: Priſcilla, thou haſt done well, haſte and lock 'em up again, I'll try a pluck with ye. [Ex. La, and Priſ. I warrant 'em, Pll keep them ſafe, . . Priſc. Eugen. Let's into our Cloſet and conſult, we will eſcape before our Country Journey yet. - . . * [Exeun; Eugen, and Clara. * - - Enter Sir William and Wildfire, > * ... Wildf. O Mill, this Couſin of thine has ſo bewitch'd me, that I begin to hate lewdneſs already. - . . . . Sir Will. Faith, I have not ſuch a reliſh for it, methinks, as I have had ; but not a word to old Tope. . . . . . Wildf; when he finds us cut, the Rogue will play the Tyrant moſt inſolently. Sir Will. He'll be worſe to us two than Doll Common to Face and Subtile": But ſomething muſt be done to deliver theſe pretty Rogues; to morrow, at Nine in the Morning, is ſhort warning. . - - - Wildf. Manage matters ſo, that we may appear Enemies when your Aunt comes to us; and that, with what I have already proteſted, will beget ſuch confidence of me, that I'll undertake to ſecure her early in the morning. Sir Will, I have laid a deſign, which I hope will take, to free them; but if Stratagem will not dot, Force ſhall. - - Wildf. That may be dangerous, and hinder us for ever. Here ſhe is, I aſſure you, Sir— Enter La. Mag. - - You ſhall not carry this off, I paſs'd my word to protećt your Aunt, and I ſhall require a ſtrićt account of this affront you have put upon her. Sir Will. What a Devil!"Are you concern'd for the honour of my Aunt 2 What, do you lye with her? ~ - wildf. What ſay you, Sir 2 . . ; . . [He offers to dray. rady. Hold, hold; out thou filthy Fellow; Thou , foul-mouth'd Brute: Thou very Spirit of Lewdneſs and Scandal: Shall I, who am moſt notorious for vertue and Prudence to the whole Town, be blaſted by thy Contagious breath. ! . . . . . . . . . . . . . . º º - | Sir Will. Far be it from Ine to think ſuch a thing; but I might juſtly, for your ſake, ſuſped his Vanity. F. - Lady
Page 34

Nº - - - - ( 34 ) - - La. Mag. He is a Man of Honour, and a Worthy Gentleman; I would I cou’d ſay that of thee. But, ſweet Mr. Wildfire, if you ſhould engage your ſelf in a Quarrel for me, 1 ſhould never enjoy my ſelf while I lived, Sir Will, No, Madam, I’ll not engage with him ; what, mine own Aunt My dear aunt 1 I love and honour thee. - . - . . . L. Meg. Love and Honour thee, quoth he Pray Love and Honour me, and civiliy get out of j - - Sir Will. I will; but by this hand I will Serenade and Scowre thee moſt confoundedly. - - - .* L. Mag. Sir, I muſt have your word not to Quarrel: You ſee what his lewd heast is apt to ſuggeſt, upon your beginning One, I ſhall ſufferin myun- º Reputation, beſides the expoſing your dear perſon, will endanger my ife. - - \ - - - Wildf. You are infinitely gracious. Enter Tope leading the Alderman, drunk. , Tope. Oh Madam are you there, here is your Alderman ſafe and ſound, I deliver him to you, pray give me a note under your hand for the Receipt of him. * * * - - Sir Humph, I ſack Mr. Tope you are a Wag, ay I fack a very Wag; . . sº Tepe I could make as pretty a Magiſtrate of him, if I had but the breeding of him as everſlept upon a Pench yet,old, Madam: jack Tope old, Madam!hah. Sir Hump. Oh Chicken, Chicken! my dear Chicken I’ll ſo mouſe thee. * Lady Mag. Confuſion of Babel what has this day produc’d 2 I ſhall run: mad, mad, ſtaring mad. aſide ºw i Sir Hump. Why Chicken ' I ſay, Chicken. - - º - Lady Mag. Why Buzzard, I ſay Buzzard, get you gone you drunken Owl: . Tope. Nay Alderman, what are you a Flincher 2 does the Hen crow 2 come t'other Brimmer. . . . - .* - . Lady Mag, Out on thee old Satan thou vile Tempter would'ſt thou moſt wickedly ſeduce a man from the Loyalty, and Obedience he owes to his law- ful Soveraign wife. - º . . . . . . . . - - Sir Hump. One brimmer dear Chicken, it ſhall be thy health, never ſtir I'll buſs thee my pretty Chicken, I'll buſs thee. - : * > * > * '. Lady Mag. Buſs me, oh Inſolence I get you out, I ſay, be gone, ha, what dare you ſtay 2 - - 2’ - Sir Humph. Sweet Chicken, now do but hear me. Lady Mag. How is it game to this 2 Nay then I'll make you go, do you Rebel? [She #rikes him with her Fan, and thruſts him out by the Nape of the Neck, - … . . . . . ; ; ; ; ; ºr ; ; ; ; . . . . . . . . . . . and Exit. Tope. Good, good, ha ha, good, hey brave Matrimony oh rare Matrime- ny 'Oh gallant Matrimony Moſt comfortable Matrimony Oh delicate Ma- trimony Ot, tweet Matrimony Oh heavenly Matrimony: Where are you Flinchers : I have been ſain to carry, on thc work of the day, you have been as cull as a couple of old gelt Maſtiffs. … . . . . . . - - -- * * sºil. Why, jº, thºu art the Hero of the Age. - - * * - ... * * * * * ** , . . . . , Wºld. There's not a Youth in Town comes near thee; * - ..." ... Tºe, Hºm, hem; Old ſaid ye; hen; hºw..… . . . . . . Futer ~ - - , * * * * * - . ºf . ºf - . * * - - -------------------- 1: …

Page 35

- - . . ( 35 ) - l *- … . . . . . . . Enter Ralph. , - - * , ." . , Ralph. Sir, here's a Letter from your Father, came juſt now by the Poſt." | Sir Will. Some wiſe advice again, I warraut ; but how does my Houſe. keeper, and the damn'd Governeſs agree ? - Ralph. The Old Dragon ſwallows Sack as greedily as a Eſſex Calf ſucks Milk. She was calledaway once, but we are ſafe now, and hope to bring her to reaſon. - - Wildf. How are the reſt of the Family - l Ralph. All, every one, as drunk as ever you were Sir, except two Maids of my Ladies, Whachum and his two Friends are ſlipt away ; but Whachum had beaten the Governeſs, and ſhe ſcratch'd him moſt wickedly before he went. Sir Will. Go about thy buſineſs. . - , Exit Ralph. Now what ſays Daddy ? . | Sir William goes to the Candle and reads, Reads. I cannot tell how to expreſs the ſorrow I conceive for your obſtinate perſe- wering in ſuch lewd courſes— Piſh, the old ſtuff over and over, I'll ſacrifice thee to the flame: 'Tis better than being put under'ſ ye-cruſt. [He ſets it on fire. Hold, hold What a Devil's here? - -- Reads. I have ordered five hundred pound, which— He puts it out again. Gad I had made fine work on't indeed! Which is to be paid to my Banker in Lumbard-ſtreet, for ſome Uſes of mine not to be diſpenc'd with, and therefore am ºut of Money at this time. - - - - Wildf. This is pleaſantjack, it goes tot now. Tope. As ſure as ever Martyr did in Smithfield. . - Sir Will. Paid away, quoth he 2 paid to a Banker? Oh plague of a Banker, go on, go on, burn in the Devils name, He ſets it on fire again. Ha Death and Hell what's this? I am undone, no 'tis legible. . . . - - --- ºr Puts it out again very haftily. Reads. Tet I have ſent you a bill for 25ol. to receive, which you will find at the bottom of my Letter. Ounds I am undone, hold, hold, O’tis legible, Faith 'twas a narrow ſcape, ’twas juſt a going, He puts it out again hastily. This won't do, but thou art a good Dad, 'tis a Pretty Stop Gap faith Lads, we'll have Dads health in a brimmer. . . . . . . . . . . . . ; Tope. In two Will, at leaſt. . . . . . . . Wildf. Thou art reſolv'd to bea finiſht piece. . . - - - - - - Tope. I hate Oyl-light, I would either be dead ſober or dead drunk... I hate to have one ...; to make me gameſome for another. . . . . . . Sir Will. Thou ſcorn'ſt to be an odious Trimmer in drink. But prithee jack, what if we three ſhould reſolve once, to go tº bed ſober in a Frolick..., , Wild. Faith jack, let us e'en try how it will agree with us. . . . . . . . Tope. What a Pox do you mean 2 are you mad? Rark mad : I go to bed ſober what to hear Chimes, Bell-men, and tell Clocks all night, and be Flea- bitten like a Nurſe-Maid 2 I think the Devil's in you, what is this Fool in Love too 2: ... - - º r - ; : * * * ~ * f tº º Aº ‘º w ~ Sir Will. Ten times more than . tº - - - - Tope: Why you brace of Kaboons ! what melancholy dull Puppies does Lové make of Fellows? A Pox of your Love, Love f 'tis a ſilly boyiſh Diſeaſe, - - F 2 and f
Page 36

* * * and ſhould never come after the Chicken pox, and Kib'd heels. - - Enter Lady Maggot, , " - Lady Mag Now Sir William, I hope you will be ſo civil to leave my Houſe, and take that old Sinner with you. - - - Sir Will, Yes, Madam, and that young Sinner too. Tepe. Oldfinner Gad as good a finner as your ſelf. Lady Mag. I muſt ſecure him for fear of a Quarrel. - - * - Tope. Quarrel 1 Nono, there ſhall be no quarrel; but we will have him a--" long with us. - - - - Wildf. There is no remedy, but your Ladyſhip ſhall hear from me the firſt minute I can get looſe from them, or free from their dogging. . . . . . ." ... Lady Mag. I ſhall either be at home, ſweet Sir, orat my Lady Wagtayles, at Ombre, within two doors. --> - - - Wildf. This noble preſent of yours be the Token. * ... Sir Will. Farewel my moſt dearly beloved and highly honoured Aunt, ſº Tope. For ſerenading and ſcowering have at you ſweet young Lady. * . Wild. Your moſt humble Servant Madam. [Exeunt Sir Will. Tope and Wild. Lady Mag. Your moſt obliged humble Servant,dear Sir! Oh he is the ſweet- eſt perſon, the moſt charming Creature : but for the other two, vengeance light on them; they have put me by the happieſt opportunity. Ex. Lady Mag. Enter Ralph and Sir Williams Houſe-keeper, Abigal, leading in Priſcilla drunk." Priſ. Dear Couſin I am heartily glad doe ſee of your acquaintance, ’tis pure sack, one cup more and then] ſtop, I would not be diſguiſed for the world. Ralph. Here ſweet Madam, drink it off, it makes you look ſo lovely in my Eyes, I am ten times more enamour'd. . . . . . . tº . ; , ".. Priſ. You are very obliging, ſweet Sir. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Abigal. He will be an excellent Match, my Maſter has given him his Life in a brave Farm. . . ... * * -- Priſ. Alas, I marry tº Nay not but I muſt confeſs, he is a pretty young man, - -, -, *- : * Ralph. Humph, ſweet Madam, t'other Cup' beſeech you. . . . . . Priſc. Ha, ha, ha, well, you havea ſtrange way with you.” She drinki. Ralph, Oh let me kiſs thoſe pretty eyes | . . . . .” * . . . . Priſc, Go get you gone you good natur'd Toad. . . . . Abigal. But Cozen my maſter is reſolv'd to increaſe your Fortune, that you ſhal; five like a Gentlewoman, and he intends you roool. . . . - Prſ. Truly he is a fine Gentleman, and if I can with a ſafe, Conſcience, well, no more to be ſaid. ... " ' ' ' ' - 'º - . . . She nod. Abig I'll ſend you a divine. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Priſ. No no, I can drink no more. … . . . . . . . . . . Abig. It ſend you a Divine to ſatisfie your Conſcience. - " Prije. No, not a drop more,goodnight; good Hight. She falls faff aſleep. Abig, Coyou ſee now you ſimple Fellow, you have over-drunk her, and maucher commit a great fin, and ſpoy!’d all. . .” ". . .” * - - - - - - Ralph, Old Nab thou art a Fool, I will pick her Pocket of the Key, and º - . . . 1' ' ' ' ' . . . . . . . . . . . . . . leaſe
Page 37

( 37 ) - - leaſe the Ladies, and leave them to their own Diſcretion: Ha this muſt be it. .. . - [ He picks the Key out of her Pocket Abig. Go go quickly, and I'll haſten home. - * * Ralph. And I to the Bear and Harrow after my maſter, where I doubt not but I ſhall venture a broken head at leaſt, Exeunt Ralph and Abigal. Enter Mr. Rant, Father to Sir William, and his man Jaſper. - Mr. Rant. What's the matter in this houſe 2 The Porter's drunk, and can't ſpeak, no body to be ſeen about the houſe 2 Nothing but Chairs, Stools, Ta- . bles flung about, and every corner ſtrew'd over with empty Bottles, I wiſh the houſe is not rob’d. • . . . . . . . jaſper. Here's an old Gentlewomaain her Cups. Mr. Rant. How, what confuſion has been here 2 Some very extraordinary accident has been in this Houſe, this is the Dragon employ'd to watch my Nieces. Go out and bring what Servants you can muſter, Butler, under But- ler, and Grooms, let us ſee if any one in the Family can ſpeak. - jaſper. I will Sir. - . . . . . - Exit Jaſper, . Mr. Raut. This looks as if my Son, and all his Iewd Companions had reen here. ... My Siſter's not at home, her Doors open, no body to give account of . her, or her Husband, that I could ſee, what all drunk where's my Lady ? Enter Butler and 4 or 5 Servants drunk and ſtaggering; after them Mr. Rants - Servant with my Ladies maid, Lettice. - But. We have been drinking, Helter Skelter, Faith ! r Serv. Sir William Rant's the fineſt. Gentleman. - * Butl. Oh the braveſt Gentleman and his men the braveſt Drinkers. . . Mr. Rant. I thought none, but my profligate Son could have made ſuch diſ. order and confuſion any where. . . - 1 Serv A moſt brave Gallant 1 No more to be ſaid. Mr Rant. Is there not one in the Family can ſpeak 2 - - faſper. Yes here's a young Gentlewoman pretty, ſober, but there are 8 of . 10 men and boys drunk, roaring under Benches and upon the Floor, the houſe looks like a Field after a Battle, ſtrew’d with Bodies, - - - Mr. Ramt. Sweet-heart what’s the cauſe of all this 2 -- Lett. Sir William Rant and his Companions came in here, roaring and ſing- ing with Fiddles at Noon, entertain'd us with Muſick, very fine indeed, and we had a Dance. - • * - Mr. Rant. Heaven! there is no hopes of Amendment. . . . Let. At laſt march'd in a noble Dinner, and great Hampersofall ſorts of wine, and there has been nothing but Roaring, and Drinking ever fince, till juſt now. My Lady laid my maſter drunk upon the Bed, but he has made his eſcape, My Lady has been almoſt diſtraćted. - - • - But. Fly fly, my Lady will be outragious. Enter Lady Maggot. La Mag. On Heaven and Earth what’s here 2 Exeunt Servants. What an image of Hell has this houſe been to day 2 Who's here my Brother 2 Mr. Rani. Madam I knew ſhould ſurpriſe you, my coming to Town was . very unexpeded, and ſudden. - - - Lady Met You find me Sir, in amazement and confuſion, and I am tº: * . - that * * -
Page 38

* * * ( 38 ) that I muſt tell you, your wild Son after I had warm'd him my houſe, broke o- ºpen my Doors, roard and ſwaggerd, and debauch'd all my family. . . . . Mr. Rant. Ah, Madam, I heard ſomething before, and am infinitely ſorry, his ... perſeverance in this wicked life will break my heart, it cannot hold long. Lady Mag. Oh Horrour, Horrour ! Priſcilla drunk too ! Huswife! Huswife ſpeak. . - - \ She Pommel; her, Priſ. I will drink no more, I tell you, I am ſleepy. - - Lady Mag. Mercy on me, where are my Daughters ? They are flown, they are flown. Ha how came they here 2 - - . . ; - * Enter Eug. Clara. Eug. kneels to Mr. Rant. * * * Mr. Rant. O dear pretty Ladies' your humble Servant, bleſs you my ſweet God-daughter. - - - - - Lady Mag. How now Baggages, how came you out? Eugen. A thouſand welcomes to you moſt honour'd uncle. s Clara. You never could have arrived ſo ſeaſonably. . Mr. Ramt. What mean my pretty Nieces 2 * -- L. Mag. I ſhall be diſtraćted, ruin'd. O this fatal day!, I am ſorry, Sir you muſt be witneſs of the further confuſion in our Family ; theſe wicked young Sluts have rebell'd againſt me, that I am forc’t to lock 'em up. Eug. We do rebel againſt the Locking up. Clara. Aud will dye before we will endure it. - Eug. And therefore are both reſolved to chooſe you our Guardian: And ne- ver to diſobey you, who we know to be a man of Honour. - Lady Mag. How they aſtoniſh me! All this miſchief has your Son causd: Oh I ſhall grow mad. - - - - - Mr. Rant, Oh that Son lies heavy on me. My pretty Niéces, I ſhould be glad to ſerve you, for your own ſakes, and for my dear Brothers ſake, thoby the ſecond vener,he was a brave,and worthyman, an ornament of our Family. But I muſt by no means encourage diſobedience to a Parent, or rob a mother of her Daughters. - - - - Eug. I beſeech you give us leave to ſtate our Caſe to you. . . . Clara. And if you think we have not reaſon — … . . . . . Eug. We will do whatever you determine with us.. . - - Clara. But if you will not protećt us from the moſt horrible Cruelty imagi- nable, ſome body elſe muſt. - - Eugen. We'll bear all Torments, rather than the uſage we have met with from a mother. - - Lady Mag. Oh Impudence : I'll beat their teeth out. Mr. Rant. Hold Madam, no ſuch correótion, let's diſcourſe this matter in the drawing-room Nieces, a little Coolneſs and kind uſage ſhall bring 'em into a good Temper, I'll warrant you. . * > * > - º Lady Mig. Heaven preſerve my Sences, l have ſcarce any left. [Ex. Omnes. --> - - - scENE
Page 39

Maft. Gentlemen what do you mean 2 sc ENE the Bear and Harrow tehind St. Claments Church, - The Bar-boy ringing. 1. Enter Sir Humphrey, and another. / - Sir Ham, I am almoſt typſy'd but i muſt have one Half-Flask with my At- torny who is here, as his Clerk ſays. - - Bar-boy rings. Very welcome Gentlemen, here Ralph, George, Humphry, ſpeak here. Enter two Drawers. - Sir Hum. Is Mr. Split-cauſe the Attorny here. - Bar-boy. Yes Sir, ſhew the Half-Moon there. Ringing within. Speak there, they have rung thrice in the Bear. - \ Drawerſ. Anon, anon Sir. Anon, anon Sir. - Enter Whachum, Bluſter and Dingboy, and 3 Footmen of Whachums. Whac. Anon you Dogs, can't you hear 2 I'll try if you have Ears, I'll lug ye. Bluff. Come Rogues, cant you feel, if you can't hear. . They lug’em by the Dingb. Dance ye Dogs, we'll make you frisk. Ears, & beat & kick them. Drawers. Murther' murther. - \ - Whac. Ye Rogues, I'll teach you to wait, you Spaniels you Curs. - Enter Maſter. & - - . . . . Ma. Gentlemen what's the matter? Why do you abuſe and beat my Drawers." Whac. Nay then, Rogue,ay hold on him Footmen. [They lay hold on the Mafter. * s * Bluff. To ſwinge you moſt exceedingly, Raſcal. - Ding. To learn you the reverence due to a Gentleman, Sirrah. - Whác. Hold him faſt, firſt let’s demoliſh ; , They pluck down the Bar. Now as a Correction of greater Dignity to your Perſon, you ſhall be toſs'd in a Blanket, and not kick'd, and we'll toſs fair. - Maff. Hold, hold Gentlemen for Mercies ſake, and I will do any thing in the world. - - - . . . . . . Whac. We’ll let him go on his good behaviour. . Maft. This muſt be Sir W. Rant, and his Company, moſt certainly. ... [aft'e. Whac. Look you Puppy, we intend to ſwagger, roar, and drink bloodily, and domineer in the Houſe by our ſelves. - - Maſł. I beſeech you Gentlemen. Whac, Dam me, what do you mutter? - - Maft. No Sir, not I in the leaſt, do your pleaſure Sir : Plague on ‘em they’ll undo my Houſe. º . . . º aſide. Whac. You harbour a Company of Tradeſmen,who ſhould be at home,mind-. ing of their Callings, and ſolicing their Wives, Bluff: Attornies, and Students, and Clarks ; I warrant you. Ding. Grave men and men of buſineſs drink, and come to Taverns Whac. It muſt not be, I will reform theſe Exorbitances, and you ſhall find us Drunkards do more good than all the Formal, Hypocritical, Nonſenſical, Magiſtrates. Fetch us a Flask, and let it be better than our laſt, as thou ten- dreſt any member about thee, and if thou valueſt thy late Deliverance, Maft. I will Sir. - Whac, A
Page 40

- ( 40 ) Whac. We will drink ſome Bumpers, at thy late Bar,and then, begin our Frolicks. - =- - Maft. A Devil of your Frollicks, my houſe had as good be viſited by the Plague, as ſuch Cuſtomers. Exit AZafter: Whac. Oh that Sir William were here, he’d be in love with us, Come fill round you Raſcal, What Glaſſes are theſe ? fit for Quakers, Browniſts, or Fifth- A4onarchy men, take one your ſelf, now altogether give fire; now to our work. - [They drink and then Huzza. Maff. Well there's no reſiſting, this ſame Sir William and his damn'd Com- pany have beaten half the Town. Exeunt Whach. Bluff. Ding, and Footmen. Enter Whachum, Bluſter and Dingboy, and Footmen, beating a Company of Tradeſmen before 'em, who cry, Fly fly, murther, murther. * Whac. Get you out you Scoundrels, men of Callings, Knaves of buſineſs, muſt you be ſwilling at a Tavern, and neglect your ſeveral and reſpective co- zening Vocations? - * Bluff. You Rogues muſt your poor Wives want your Loggerheads at home, and you be here idling and ſpending their Money. - Ling. Go ye Scot and Lot Knaves that cheat the Pariſh, and the poor when you come to Offices. - * . Wºad. Do you mutter, avaunt ye what d'ee lacks; And impudent Duns, be gone. Don't I do it rarely Come to the next Room. - They beat 'em ſºundly, who cry, Fly, fly, murther, murther. - [Exeunt Whac. Blufter and Dingboy. Enter Whachum, Bluſter and Dingboy, &c. beating the Company, Attorneys, - Clerks, and a Parſon. Whach. You idle drunken Puppies, we'll ſwinge you for your Debauchery, and Extravagance. ` - - Attor. What's this 2 I'll bring my Quare fremuerunt ; the Law's my Buckler. º You Scoundrels ſtay at home, and make cozening bills for your Clients. - - . . Bluff. Praćtice Court-hand, you lazy drunken Raſcals. Ding! And never be out at a Knaviſh Trickum de Lege. Whac Out ye Rogues, I'll ſhew yeu the Law They beat them out. Footman. Here's one Rogue fill hidden in a Cloſet. [Footman bales out Sir Hum. Whac, Mercy upon me, my uncle: [Whac, and he ſtart at fight of one another. Sir Hamph. Oh lack, Oh lack my Nephew Students of the Law quoth he? Whach. What a Pox, all muſt out; 'tis too late to go back : Get you home old Fellow, interrupt not our pleaſures. Get you gone and comfort my Lady if you can ; march, march, I ſay. - Sir Hump. Prodigious ! Amazing! Jºhach. March, march, or I will ſwinge you extreamly. Sir Hump. Murther murther | Students of the Law [They kick him out. Ling. I his was bravely done, Squire. Bluff. Admirably perform'd. - Whac, Aye wait not ; come let's in, Sir William will be here ſoon. - - Exeunt all but the Mafter and Drawers. Małł.
Page 41

A4aft. Theſe are rare Cuſtomers, they have a huge Supper, but what a Pox all I get by 'em. Enter Sir William, Tope, Wild. Ralph, & Footmen. Sir Will. Hey what has been to do here 2. The Puppies have been at work already, who's here 2 what Company have you in your Houſe 2 Maſł. Company, Sir? but one, who have beat all the reſt out of my houſe, . blooded all my Drawers, pull'd down my Bar and ſwing'd me off, Company. for the Devil : Sir JWilliam Rant and his wicked Crew, I ne're ſaw 'em before, and the Devil take 'em before I ſee 'em again. . . . . * - Sir Will. Have they a good Supper ? * – Maff. A huge one. 4 great laugh within. Sir Will. We'll ſup with 'em, theſe are the Rogues that laugh. Maff. Gentlemen, as you love your lives — - Sir Will. Peace Fool, we'll govern your Houſe a little better, come on Friends, let's make 'em a civil viſit by the way of Kick and Cudgel. - A great Laugh again. Maſł. So now I ſhall have Murther in my Houſe. - Exeunt Sir William, Wildfire, Tope, Ralph and Footmen. Enter Whachum, Bluſter, Dingboy and Servants in a Room. Ding. This beating of Nuncle, was the gallanteſt action. They all laugh, Whac. Ay what care I. - Bluff. He could not have been more amazed, if he had ſeen a Ghoſt. * * * - . . . . . . . They laugh again: Whac. Oh Sir William and Gentlemen, your moſt humble Servant, oh if you had come ſooner you had ſeen ſuch Scowring. - Sir Will. You ſcowre, you are meer novices, we'll teach ye how to ſcowre. Whac. Thank you ſweet Sir Will, we ſhall be glad to learn, I vow to Gad Sir. Sir Will. Why look you Gentlemen, you city Puppies, you impertinent conceited Raſcals | Go and ſwagger at Puddle-dock, but do you think we will ſuffer ſuch awkard ſneaking Coxcombs, to wench, drink, and ſcower, to uſurp & the Sins of Gentlemen. " . . . . Tope. We will tweak you by the Noſes moſt exceſſively, LThey tweakWhac. Wild. Kick you moſt plentifully. by the Noſe and kick and cudgel them. . Sir Will. And cudget you moſt extravagantly. . . . . . . . ºf , Whac. I'll take my Oath 'tis mighty well, Haha ha. . . . -o Sir Will. Come Inſeóts, we will correót your Impudence. Such as you turn Gentlemen, when you are intended for Pleaders of the Law. . . ºn tº Whac. Rarely Admirably well done! gº [ Sir Will. and his Company. Bluff. They tweak damnably hard though, tweak, and lead em.about Ding. They do not confider the Tenderneſs ºf ºiby the Nofts; they laugh of my Bolt-Sprit. *- : * * tº all the while.ºrºi, º, . . Tope. Get you home Rogues 2 ſtudy the Law, and put-caſes over a pot of Ale in your Chambers, - , iſ tº . . . . . . . … . . Y . Wildf. Muſt ſuch paltry Fellows as you ſwaggerin Taverns, go and peſter Ale-houſes. : { * : :º . . . . . ºn tº gº. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . What. Incomparable by myº Sword, they are the fineſt Gentlemen in Eurºpe. . . . . . . . ºf it ſº tº º' tº sº º ! .º.º. o. º. 1 G - - Bluff. - >
Page 42

/ - - - , - - , ( 42 ) º . . . . . Bluff. Dam me Squire I don't like this, . . . . . . . . . Ding. Gad they kick with Iron toes. Sir Will. What do you take me to be in Jeſt ? VWhac. Ay ay, why Sir are you not | . . . . Wildf. We'll put you out of doubt of that preſently. * Tope. Out you Raſcals, muſt you be taken for us? to our utter Scandal, Get you out. - They beat 'em out, Bluſt. Sir Will. Ye damn'd dullimitating Dogs, have at ye.& Ding. roar all the time VWhac Why Sir William, Sir William, hold hold and buff : Whac. runs Bluff. What a Devil do you mean? as faft at he can, as they Ding. Do not provoke me any further. - come at the Door, the Con- Sir Will. Provoke 2 Damn thee out, beat 'em out. ſtable with the Watch- Whac. What will become of the Supper ? men & Tradeſmen who Ralph. Come turn out, hang the Supper. were beaten enter, & beat Sir Will. Now Ralph here's Honour to be gotten, them back into the houſe, Ralph. Broken Heads. - Sir Will. & his Company Sir Will. Fall on. • ‘’ beat all out, A C T V. S C E N E L - - --- – Enter Sir Will. Rant, Tope, Wildſ. Ralph, Footmen and Muſicians. - VWild. Hº. the Serenade, the Morning comes on apace,'tis almoſt three, Tope. People will be awake, and then we ſhall loſe the great end Serenading and Scowering, which is diſturbing of Mankind, . ..Sir Will. Now guilty VVretches in their frighted ſleeps, Start with the Terrour of their crying ſins: - Now the mean, buſy, undermining Knave, The treacherous Stateſman who betrays his Prince, And Country, rolls, and turns himſelf about, The Horror of his crimes admits no reſt. - Tope. What a Devil is the Fellow mad. . . Sir Will. The tender Virgins in ſoft Slumbers dream, With Innocence of all the Toys of Love; When Nature free, and undiſguis’d by Art, The Genuine Dićtates of the mind purſues, And they are pleaſed with imitated Joy. . . . . . . . . Wildf. VVhat's the matter man, art thou in a Fit 2 º - Tope. Thou art mad Will, that's moſt certain. but thou haſt laid down a true Doſtrins, that women always diſſemble, but when they are aſleep: But .* * - º - what * . * - º º l
Page 43

→ ( 43 ) - * - what a Devil do you mean * if you don’t begin your Muſick, Gad take me, I will roar moſt bloodily by my ſelf. . . . . . . . Sir Will. Why don't the Poets always make a manif he be damnably intlove, in any great Paſſion, in Haſte, or a Dying, to be full of Similes and long De- ſcriptions 2 tº ..' - Zope. And becauſe they are Coxcombs, wilt thou be one 2 Wildf. I have oxtraordinary buſineſs in haſte, at Three in the Morning, and I muſt ſtop till I make a Poetical Deſcription. Zope. For example. The thirſty Drunkard dreams of Bottle Ale, Or ſucking a whole Barrel from the Tap; - - - The Oyly Cookmaid ſtretches now, and yawns, . . . . And calls on pick the Plowman in her Sleep, - - . \ . Who ſhores with Fumes from Suffolk Cheeſe and Bacon: Green-fickneſs Maids now dream of Clay and Lime. Now what a Devil's this to my buſineſs if they do? either begin your ſerenade, or I will roar and wake your Miſtriſs with my ſhrill melodious Pipe. Wildf. A ganders Pipe has much more Muſickin't. - - Sir Will. Thou fing ſhe will take it for braying : but come on, Ralph is the Conſtables trap ſet to ſecure that paſſage. Ralph. Yes it is, they muſt come this way, 'tis direétly from their Guard. Sir Will. Come then begin. - - -- - A window opens. Symphonies. Eugenia and Clara appears Hold, the young Ladies window opens, give me the cleft ſtick, Ralph. Now Tom for our Billets, good luck go with them, they are they, 1 ſee now. - Opening his dark Lanthorn, Ladies take theſe Notes they concern you, Go on, and fing. Song and Symphony. Sir Will. Who's at the other window I - - `- -- Eugenia takes them. Mr. Rant appears at another window. Wildf. My Lady, I warrant you, I muſt ſtand cloſe. . . . . . Tope. My Lady, then I will roar, play my Rant. s Rant. This muſt be my Son and his lewd Aſſociates, but if this were the worſt I could diſpence with it. 2 he Fiddles play, and Tope roars Lady Mag. Rogues, Villains, Thieves, out his rant, then enter Lady Mag- Robbers, Murtherers, hold, hold. got in the Balcony. - Tape. Hold, does the Lady treat from her Caſtle ž - - - - - zady Mag. Villains, Thieves, be gone. They ſing and roar. Mr. Rant retires, Tape. Nay then. - " . . - - - Enter. Conſtable and Watch. - Comſt. Who's there? Follow, follow. . . . . . . . . Wildf. Come on Bell-weather of that Flock of Raſcals. Ralph Come Cuckolds, come on Cuckolds. [The Conſtable and watch Conff. Follow, follow, follow, knock 'em down. run, & all fall over a Sir Will. Here is a Stratagem for ye. Line ſet croſs the ſtreet, Tºpe, Fall on the Rogues, have at the Dogs. & tumble over one another, Sir Will, and the reſt fall on them, & cudgel them luftily, they roar out Murther.' G 2 - - Fater
Page 44

--- *. - (44), Enter Mr. Rant holding the door of the Houſe in his Hand. - Mr. Rant. Heaven! what will become of this! We ſhalf have murther here, Sir William, Sir William. - - Sir Will. The door opens and I am call'd, this muſt be from the Ladies. Wildſ. I muſt ſneak away, Tope you muſt aſpng with me, you may do me great ſervice and your ſelf too, . . - Tope. You may be ſure I ſhall be civil to my ſelf, what ete I am to you. Exeunt Tope, Wildfire and their Servants: But Ralph & two Footmen of - Sir W. remain. - Rant. Sir William. Sir Will. Who calls me? - Rant. Tisſ, follow me. - - Sir Will. If Lucifer ſhould lead me into this Houſe, I would follow him - Exeunt Mr. Rant and Sir VVilliam. confi, w hat are become of theſe Rogues that have maul’d us 2 - Ralph, Mr. Conſtable, the Hedorly Rogues A ſight of Flambeaux and a that fell upon you, run into the next ſtreet, noiſe of Fiddles. and now they have lighted their Flambeaux, and are coming in Triumph o- ver you, I and my fellow ſervants came juſt now out of my Maſters houſe, the Juſtice, to aſſiſt you: Here's another Stratagem to get off without bloody . Pates. - aſide. Enter Whachum, Blüſter and Dingboy, and, Servants, and Fiddles, roaring . . . ºf ſinging, and playing- Conft. Have we met you again Rogués 'you ſhall not eſcape this bout, knock 'em down. - - - - Whac. We are civilly ſerenading. - - Conft. We'll ſerenade ye, do you lay ſhares for us, and beat us when we are down 2 . n - Whac. What a Devil does he mean now * They fight, the Conſtable & Comſt. Knock 'em down. his Watch beat Whachum and the reë, till the blood runs about their Faces, and take 'em Priſoners, Comſt. Away with them, away with them. . Whach. Why, Mr. Conſtable Conft. Come Raſcals, what do you prate 2 away with them, 'tis Day-light. Whach. Damn’d Luck, but 'tis Fortune de la guerre. - Exeumt Ommes. - Eater Mr. Rant, leading Sir William by the Hand Sir Will. Whether do you lead me 2 - +– Mr. Rant. Into full light, if you dare look upon it. Sir Will. Oh Heaven, my Father - Mr. Rant. wonder not at your ſurpriſe, if there be left But any Seeds of Ingenuity . . Within thy hardened Breaſt, thou could'ſt not bear , The ſight of me. - .*, Sir Will. It is with great confuſion, . That I behold you now, I hardly date . . . Implore your bleſſing. . . . . . . * - sº . . . . . [He kneel. - - - Mr
Page 45

- (4; ) Mr. Rant. Heaven turn your-heart : . . . . . . I am glad at leaſt, you appear ſo much aſham’d, - For Shame for Faults is one good ſtep to Wiſdom';. But what hope can I have, that one ſhort Moment - Can make you turn from your long courſe of Lewdneſs, Such Lewdneſs as I am aſham'd to think of , Such mean, ſuch fooliſh Lewdneſs as has made Your Name too ſcandalous for a civil Mouth, When but even now I ſaw you in your Pranks— Sir Will. Tis the laſt time, - . Mr. Rant. Till wicked drink poſſeſſes you again, That bane to Vertue and to common Senſe, That makes you live in a continued Miſt, Without the benefit of one clear thought; Nature has prudently contrived each Man, In the worſt miſeries of humane Life . Would be himſelf, and I would be I ſtilſ, But ſordid Drunkenneſs makes you differ more - * From your lov’d ſelf, than from another Man. ... Sir Will. Yourouſe me, Sir, out of a Lethargy. Mr. Rant. Ye think your ſelves the fineſt Gentlemen, When you are moſt to be deſpiſed or pitty'd, - Not Monkeys can be more ridiculous, * Beſides the infamy you moſt contraćt, In the opinion of the good and wiſe, As ſoon I’d chooſe a Madman for a Friend, You vomit ſecrets, when o'recharg’d with Wine, You often quarrel with the beſt of Friends : And ſhe muſt be as bold as is a Lioneſs, Who takes you for a Husband : Drink in ſhort Provokes you to all Folly, to all Vice, Till you become a Nuſance to Mankind; You'll ſay they are men of Wit, but have a care Ofa great Wit, who has no underſtanding. Sir Will. You ſpeak, Sir, like an Oracle. Mr. Rant. By Drunkeneſs you are uſeleſs at the beſt, unleſs as Flys or humble Bees, meer Drones. What Office is there in a Common-wealth, A Drunkard can ſuſtain unleſs it be one, / To be a Strainer through which Claret runs. . . Your Nerves youweaken,and you drown your Minds; You're all meer Sops in Wine, your Brains are Bogs; A Toaſt is equal to a common Drunkard : " ' You'll ſay you have Courage, No, it is not Valour; Valour is joyn'd with Vertue, never proſtitute, - But ſacred, and employ'd to juſt Defence
Page 46

----------- —- ------. . -- - ~ - - - - -- ~~ - - ( 46 ) ----> Of Prince and Country, and the beſt of Friends, ... -- 3: With neceſſary vindication of our Honour : & . Yours is a brutal Fierceneſs that annoys - . . . . . Mankind, and makes 'em fear and hate you too. . . . * Sir Will, Theſe are unanſwerable Truths. - o, - M. Rant. The uſe of common Whores is moſt pernicious, . By which, the leaſt you venture is your Noſe, - And private ones you cannot gain, without • Being a moſt perfidious Knave, and ſtriking - . . . At the very Root of all Morality. Have 1 with ſuch Tenderneſs bred you up 2 With ſuch great care and vaſt Expence, infuſed - Whatever you were capable of receiving, ,- Taught you all Arts that could adorn a Gentleman : - None with ſuch care could cultivate a Plant. -s: - | Sir Will. All this with humble Gratitude I confeſs. . . . . . • Mr. Rant. Heaven had endued you with ſufficientWit And Parts, and you, in ſpight of theſe Advantages, - - - - Which might have made you famous in your Country, . . . . . . . “To make your ſelf lewd, even to a Proverb: - Is this your fence of Honour, and is this . . . . Your Gratitude to me, after ſuch great Indulgence, r - Such good Advice, ſtich tender Love, as I. - . º Have ſo long ſhew'd you ? You have ſo often . - . . . Set my Eyes on flowing, that I have wondred . . . . . - ** Whence the Moyſture came that could ſupply them. * -- . . . . Sir Will. Good Sir no more you'll break my Heart, ~ * Gentle and kind Reproof I cannot bear. * . Mr. Rant. I gave you ſuch an ample Income, "Twould have ſufficed the moſt extravagant, Except your ſelf, and when the Court had offered . . . . . . Knighthood to me, I made it be beſtowed . - . . . . . On you, Not that l think it much of Value, . . . . unleſs it be conferr'd for Merit, but a bait For women. All this in order to a VWife I did, and you ungrateful. — - - - - - - Sir Will. No more, Sir, dear and honoured Sir, pray Holmore, You've melted me, and wrought a paſſionin me, i º - Which hitherto I’ve never feſt, pray truſt me, And I will be what you will have me,’ * . . . . And ſuch as you ſhall never bluſh to own, - -- . . Mr. Rant. Oh Will, that this converſion were but perfeſt ; 2 - - Yet, as it is, 1 cannot but embrace - - * - - And weep over thee. * * * -. S. Will. Oh,beſt of Fathers,believe me or you kill me. . . . . . . Mr. Rani. Come then into my Arms. [He embraces and wript over him. Sir * 3.
Page 47

v } Sir Will. I will ſoon convince you I am Sincere, for though you have finiſh'd my - . . . Repentance, another had begun it. . . - I had fix’d upon the moſt charming Creature in the World . To be my VVife, and with your aſſiſtance, have no Reaſonto doubt of ſucceſs; one, Sir, whom you'll Approve. - - - - Mr. Rant. Dear Will, who is it 2 º Sir Will. It is my Couſin Eugenia, who to avoid the Tyranny of her Mother, which has been very barbarous, reſolves to chooſe you her Guardian. . . . Mr. Rant. This, this, compleats my joy, and I ſhall dote upon thee more : than e're I griev'd for thee. Enter La. Maggot. - * , La. Mag. Oh, wicked creature, moſt abandon'd wretch, how dareſt thou be ſo impudent to come within my Houſe, after the great confuſion yeſterday, and the uproar thou haſt made to Night. - - - Mr. Rani. Siſter, if thou wilt pardon this, I'll paſs my honour he ſhall never- do it more, ’twas I now brought him in. L. Mº. You are a fine eaſie Father if you can Hope for his amendment, but I’ll ſee my Daughters ſafe; though he has by craft gotten the Key, I have. w a VVatch upon them. Mr. Rant. VVhat does ſhe mean * - Enter Lettice. “ Lettice. There is a Meſſenger below will not be anſwerd, he has ſent up - this Letter by me, but he ſays he muſt ſpeak with you, it is a buſineſs that con- cerns you nearly, Lady Mag. Thus early in the Morning, I’ll lay my Life, it is to give me notice of ſome lewd deſign of my Rebellious Daughters. Hah, from Mr. Wild- e : Olet me contain my ſelf: . . [Aſide. _^ Reads. I have commanded my Servant to wait this Morning, till your door be. open, to deliver this humble Billet. Where is the Meſſenger ? I muſt leave you for a while ; Brother, pray diſpatch your Lewd Son out of the Houſe : but I have ſet Centinels upon my Daughters. . . Mr. Rant. They ſhall be ſafe for him, I give you my Honour. . Lady Mag. Oh dear, dear Wildfire, thou art a Man of Honour; come, Lettice, bring me to the Meſſenger. . . - [Ex.Laº Let. Mr. Rant. "Tis time for you to reſt Will, and I’ll repoſe a while. Sir Will. Sir, let me beg of you not to ſleep yet, my Lady has a wicked de- fign of ſending her Daughters into the Country this morning, to keep them a Priſoners as ſhe did before ; I have, indeed, provided for a Reſcue, but if you pleaſe, I had rather have it done a fairer way. ~ Ms. Rant. Well, Son, we will conſult about it in my Chamber.[Ex, Mr.Rºn N * and Sir Hilliam. sce N E wildfire's Houſ. - - Enter Wildfire and Tope. . . . . ; ... Tope, A Pox ont, this has been a damn'd ſober Night, I ſhall be ſick after it; this is your Love, with a Murrain : A Drunkard, and in Love! You will . . . - - - - . º b: * º º - * - -
Page 48

- (48) - be as bad company as a Green-fickneſs'd Chamber-maid; nay, worſe, for ſhe, perhaps, may be perſwaded to take her Cure, Love ; ha, hā, ha, - Wild. I am convinc'd, a man will certainly have it cºre he dyes, as the ſmal Pox; look to it, jack, yet. - -- - Tºpe. Heav'n ſend me the great ones rather, without the help of Sarſa, Guya- cum or Mercury ; but prithee, what ſervice can I do thee, Tom 2 - Wild. The truth is, jack, I have ſent a Billet to the Lady you would have Raviſh'd yeſterday and cry’d ; ſhe will come, I believe, very ſuddenly, hither. Will Rant and 1, have ſome deſigns upon her Daughters, which we cannot effect without her abſence. When ſhe comes, I will make way for thee. , Tope. Prithee, Tom, let me have a young Wench, I am fit for her now. Wild. If thou haſt not love for her, . I am ſure thou haſt malice enough for her ; ſatisfie which paſſion thou wilt, ſo thou keepeſt her from interrupting us. Tope. Ha, this is no ill deſign, hah; Pll ſerve you in this, if ſhe thinks me not too old to pleaſe her; i am ſure I am young enough to ſcandalize her. Moſt of the young fellows now make love more for Vanity than Luſt; they have more of the firſt, and leſs of the laſt, than any Generation ſince the Conqueſt. - Wild. The decrepid young fools, were gotten when ſlavery was breaking in : and indeed, by their education, were fitted for it ; they have no vigour in 'em. [Knocking at the door.] Hark!. She's come ; ſhe's a Lady of very juſt dealing, and anſwers a Bill of Love at ſight.jack, do thou retire,’ll come to thee inſtantly. Tops, I will ; but d'ee hear, Tom, fair play. - Wild, upon my Honour. LExit Tope. Enter La Maggot. Dear, ſweet Madam, I am tranſported beyond my ſenſes. a Lady Mag. If I had not believed you to be a Man of ſhining honour, I would not have ventur'd for the World. - - Wildf. Sweet Madam, your Ladyſhip is come ſo much earlier than I could have ſuſpečted, that I muſt go and take order, that no body comes into my Houſe, and confine my Servants to their ſeveral Poſts. : La. Mag, Sweet Sir, you deſerve to be truſted by a Lady. Oh, thou dear creature, my heart and eyes yet never felt ſuch charms. [Ex. Wildfire haftily. - and locks the Lady in ; ſhe walks up and down. Hark! I here him coming, I’ll catch him at the door. , My deat,dear Strephon. Enter Tope, La. Mag, haftily embraces bim, taking for VVildfire, . 7ape. My dear, dear, Phillis. . - Lady Mag. Ah, who's here, Old Satan. Tºpe. I thought you had been paſt the Age of ſqueaking. - Lady Mag. Devil, how camcft thou here 2 : Tape. Sweet Lady, how cameft thou here? ~ - Lady Mag. Abuſed, betrayed, undone, by Heav'n ; they ſhall not live who have done this. - . . - - - - . zºpe. Oh, Madam, Ladies ſhould not kill but with their Eyes. Lady Mag. This Wildfire promiſed me aſſiſtance, to ſend my vile rebellious Daughters into the Country, and ſent for me, telling me all was ready. Tope. He was not you ſee, but you ſhall find meſo. . . . .-- Lady Mag, Oh Belzebub incarnate, I am confident he is a man of Honour, thou baſt betray'd him; ſee in what Confuſion I am in. . [aſide. Tºpe.
Page 49

/ ( 49 ) º 7ope. He is a man of Honour, and knowing the great Paſſion I have for your Ladyſhip contrived this Opportunity. - ) º, . Lady Mag. What pimp for thee? and a man of Honour!' . - Tope. Pimp is a foul word, Pimps are Rogues; but men of Honour aſſiſt one another in theſe neceſſary matters, and take it for a point of Honour. Lady Mag. Where's the Key then, let me out thou old decrepit Toſt. , Tope: Hold there, I have ſome urgent buſineſs with you here. Lady Mag. Had I a Dagger or a Bodkin I would diſpatch my ſelf and him. ... Tope. And for old, if I don't convince you, have at you. Lady Mag. Ah ah, murther, help, help. He runs at her, & kiſſes her. Tope. She ſqueaks like one of Sixteen, if ſhe could but look ſo too, I ſhould be more ſharp ſet ; Come ſweet Madam, let us be more familiar.'. - - -, - 2- He puts down his Sword. Lady Mag. Stand off thou driveling Drunkard, or I'll ſcratch thy eyes out. Tope. I can make love like a man, but not like a Cat, I can't caterwaul. . . - - - Tope catches bold on her Hand. Lady Mag, Oh vile, perfidious Villain Wildfire. - . . . Tope. Look you ſweet Lady, I can ſecure my Eyes againſt your Hands, all could I have as well defended my poor Heart, againſt your Eyes, you had not viſited this place. - Lady Mag. Villain let go my Hands. • - f Tepe. Madam let go my Heart, in ſhort Madam, I am in Love, here's an Opportunity, and I will not be baffled, we muſt come to a cloſe fight. Lady Mag. Avoid thou worſt of Devils.' - - - Tope. If Ladies will be civil, jack Tape can be ſo too, but if not, though he uſes not his Hands, yet he canº uſe his Tongue, and publiſh Frailties or ſo; conſider, be not perverſe, come, come, nay don’t put me to wreſtle, if you put me to two Exerciſes, I may fail you at one.[They ſtruggle, ſhe gets looſe, and runs - Lady Mag. Oh impudent old Devil to the Sword & draws it, & runs at him. - Tope. Hold hold, Sword and Eyes are too much, for my ſingle Weapon. Fare you well. . - - He runs out, and locks her in. Lady Mag. Oh Heaven and Earth he has lockt me in " Oh damn'd Villain, Villain Wildfire, let me ſee if" can make any body hear out of the W. indow, I ſhall run mad, Confuſion ſeize theſe Raſcals. Exit towards the Window. SC E N E Sir Humphry Maggots Houſe. - Enter Eugenia, Clara, Mr. Rant, and Sir VVilliam. . . Eug. Why Sir, do you make this ſo nice a point of Honour? when you may ſave us two from Ruin. - - - , ; 2. Clara. Sir on my Knees I beg your Protećtion. ... Mr. Rant takes them up. Eug. And I on mine, or I by all that's good, will fling my ſelf on any one, that will defend me from my Tyrant Mother. - Clara, I cannot, will not, bear her Cruelty. - Sir Will. Can ſo much Beauty be deny'd Sir f Enter Wildfire hºſtily. \ Wildf. Ladies your humble Servant. ~ - . . . º … . . . *
Page 50

- ( 50 ) Mr. Rant. Who is this, Son? - º -- Sir Will. Mr. Wildfire, you knew his Father, a man of Quality and of great Eſtate, who is a convert to that Lady, as I am made to this. - - Mr. Rant. I knew him well, he was a ſober honeſt Gentleman. [Enter Tope. Tope. Sober and honeſt Gad take me that's impoſſible. * > Mr. Rant. My old Acquaintance! Mr. Tope your Servant. 76pe. Mr. Rant, a Miracle! who thought to have ſeen you here 2 Mr. Rant. You will have your Jeſt ſtill. - - Tape. No faith I am in earneſt, I have known an honeſt man that could not, but I never knew one honeſt that would not drink, Knaves durſt not truſt them. frives with drink, it draws the Scene, and diſcovers them. - Wildf. How the Devil came you here? - Tope. You left me with the Devil, ſhe whipt out my Sword, and if I had not run away, had run me through, but I left her ſafe, here's the Key. . . Eug. Good ſweet uncle, conſider our ſad caſe, and give an Anſwer. Wildf. Ladies now is the time, your Mother's abſent, and is ſafe for ſome time, if you will take this opportunity, there’s a Coach and Six, and half a ſcore men well armed and mounted, Sir Williams and my Servants, that will condućt you where you pleaſe. * - - - • Clara. We are obliged to you Sir, but I fear the Reputation of ſuch an Eſcape would be worſe than our Confinement. Sir Will. Sir I beſeech you, confider and accept of their Guardianſhip. Eug. Now Sir or never, make us happy in your care of us, for let my Si- ſter be as ſcrupulous as ſhe will, I will lay hold on theſe Gentlemens favour, and fly any where, ſo it be from my Mother; but Gentlemen we muſt not have you with us, - - - Mr. Rant. Well my fair Nieces Pll protećt ye, on my honor be it. Clara. We fling our ſelves wholly on you Sir, - Eug. We truſt your Honour, and will in every thing obey you. Mr. Rant. I never will command, but what you pleaſe. - tºld: Now Madam you are happy, will you not pity my caſe, who ſtill am. miſèrable. f - - - - Clara. Would you wiſh me to love any man till I am aſſured he loves him- ſelf, you now are your own greateſt Enemy. - ... . . Wildf. Since I hope you will now be more eaſy of acceſs, I ſhall with the greateſt Duty and Reſpect I can, make approaches regularly,and ſhow you I am become another man, - - . . . . Clara, E're I ſhall have the Impudence to beg one Favour of you, I ſhall be glad to hear of your amendment Sir. - - - 7ape. Why 7am, Tºm, this is a vile repenting ſtrein, as if thou wert ſhow- ing thy paris at the Gallows, why dot thou not lay this Lewdneſs upon Sa- bath breaking. . - - - - - Iſºldſ and ill Company ſack, Old Seducers and Corrupters. - Sir Will. Will you be ſtill hard hearted, this is a day of Jubilee, and you ſhould do ſome generous Aët of Mercy. - . Euge. No, there is a great deal to be ſaid, and a great deal to be done, I - muſt ſee a Sample of your New Life. Sir Will. º * - . … --> - - -

Page 51

- Sir Will. My Life is in your Hand, diſpoſe of it, and direct it as you pleaſe. Tape. You call this Love now, all Cant, Cant, and fillyer than Gypſies Cant: what a Pox you are none of you in Earneſt. [Enter Sir Humphry, & his Clerk. Sir Hump. Oh Prother good morrow, how do you, I was typfied laſt night, but they tell me you were diſturb’d with Royſters, and ſcowreing Rogues, I proteſt and vow I never heard them, but the Conſtable has brought them before me, here in the Houſe, I'll order them. Hah Gentleman he does not mean you, are you brought by the Conſtable Oh here he is. . ." Enter Conſtable, Guard, with Whachum, Bluſter, Dingboy, with black Patches - - - - tº their Wounds. . . - - Conſº. Here are the Scowrers'!hat beat us, and wounded us, there are two of my Watch almoſt kill'd, and ſeveral lam’d, they broke Windows, roar'd and diſturb’d your Worſhip too, all Night. - Sir Hump. Oh Heaved, my Nephew Oh Villain, profligate Villain, my Nephew But you ſhall find Juſtice is blind, do you remember Rogues, what you did, beat me, and lam'd me. .x - - Whac. What a Pox cale I, why did you come in the way of our Scowring? Prithee old Nuncle content vour ſelf, i am out of your Hands, and I will fling off the remainder of your City breeding, and ſwagger, roar and ſcowre, like a Gentleman of the Suburbs. - . . . . . . . Sir Hump. Here Clerk, make their Mittimus, and I'll ſend'em to Newgate. Tape. I think Sir, you are one of thoſe Gentlemen, that we beat and kick'd very much, laſt Night. - - - Włach. Sºrd me to Newgate 2 Let me ſpeak in your Ear, how much Treaſon did you talk before me and my Friends 2 - Bluff. A hat Healths and Confuſions did you drink 2 . . . . . Ding what ſecret Correſpondence, and who invited the French Fleet laſt ſummer ? a > - - Whach. By theſe ten bones, all ſhall out if you preſume. - - Sir Hump. I ſhall be hang'd. What ſays the Rogue 2 Go out Conſtable and * *- : - Watch into the next Room, leave your Priſoner. Enter La Mag. in a Fury. Lady Mag. Oh, Heaven and Earth are they here 1 betray'd, abuſed, moſt villanouſly abuſed. Oh thou old Devilin Grain, and thou worſt of all, thou baſe diſhonourable Raſcal. - She flics at their Faces, Sir Hump. VVhy Chicken, Clicken. - -- - - - - Lady Mag. Make their Mittimus, I'll give you ſufficient Reaſon, ſit in your Seat of Juſtice, and give me my Oath. . . . . . Sir Hump. I will Chicken, I will. Mr. Ramt. VVhat can this mean? - - . . . . . . Wildf. Madam let me adviſe you, you will ſuffer in your Honour. This Ring will be teſtimony. - . - La. Mag. I'll ſwear you ſtole it from me, and you ſhall be hang'd for its Wild. Tope and my man are better evidence, Madam. . ." La, Mag. Thou moſt deteſtable malicious toad. . - Tope. Stir not this matter farther, if you do Pll tell all I know, and more. - : * -º- - H = - Sir *
Page 52

/ - - - - - - .* - . (52 ) - rady Mag.V.What has my raſhneſs brought me to, I will run into a mad-houſe and pºver fee the world again. Going off. - - 2 "Sir Hump. VVby Chicken, I am ready, lay thy pretty hand on the book.” iſºlac. Hold Madam, pray make good your bargain with me, did not I agree to give you soool, for one of your Daughter. - - Lady Mag. Out you impudent Raſcal ; does all the world conſpire againſt Ine 1 . . . . - She takes the Cane out of her plac. VVhat a Pox, what a Devil are you mad? Ounds Husbands hands and I'll turn again. * , beats VWhachum. -- A." R. Siſter, fiſter, I beſeech you contain your ſelf. - Lady Mag...I cannot cºntain, will not contain, Fleſh and Blood cannot con- tain, never Lady was ſo betray’d, abuſed, and diſappointed ; Hell take you all. - - - Enter Priſcilla. . . . - Exit Lady Maggot. Priſ. Oh Ladies have pity on me. I believe ſome Rogue that had a mind to marry me, gave me Deutery laſt Night, and I was diſguis'd and loſt the Key too, and my lady has diſcharged me, to begin my old Age. ~ * – Nº Eugen. Fear not, we'll provide for you. - - jº. VVill you not provide for me, Madam, or at leaſt give me ſome opes. - - * - - Wildf. And can you, Madam, can you have the heart to uſe your Conqueſt to deſtroy me 2 . . - • . Ciara'i now of no conqueſt of mine, nor will! believe it till I ſee you have conquer'd your ſelf. - > ºil, what time will it require to ſatisfie yºu of my converſion ? Eugen. Why you muſt bºat leaſt a years Probationer before you enter into the vow of Chaffity, if I believe you then. • * . . . . . Sir Will. Twill be a thouſand without you, Madam, I hope you will relent. 1 Clara, it muſt be a Year at leaſt, and then, for ought I know, you may ſerve onger. . . " - . - º Wildſ. You are abſolute, and muſt govern me, I'll ſtrive by all the Services. \ I can to mollify your Heart. . . - - * * * * Eugen. The Pomps and all the Vanities of this wicked Town you muſt re- PlötncC. - - - - - . . Cº. wine, women, and baſe Company. Sir Will upon my Knees I vow to it. - Wild. And i for ever to obſerve it. . . . - - - Mr. Rant. I will be umpire in this Buſineſs, and I doubt not but to bring my Nieces to Reaſon. * - - - - C Sir Hump. What are you diſpoſing of my Ladies Daughters without her onſent. - - *. * - - * .. Mr. Rant. No Sir, nothing ſhall be done without her Conſent, I will convince her, of what e're I do ſhall be to her Honour, and her Daughtcra Advantages - }. Where's my wife in the mean time? I forbid the lanes. ..., - * sin iſºll, Sirrah, Coxcomb, if you. ſpeak one word I'll ſlit your VVindpipe. ipiach. very well, very well, no more to be ſaid: Pox on him, I begin to have him now, I don't think him a fine Gentleman, - - * - s • - Tºpe. - - *-
Page 53

\ - * a * . - - 53 ) . . . Tope. VVhy what a Devil are you mad 2 I thought you had beca Drolling, or Fooling all this while, are you in earneſt ? , Sir Will. Moſt certainly. Wildf. And I, jack, we muſt part. -- . . . Tope. Ha, ha, ha, fine Fools, turn, ſober Sots, give over all Vanities, as you call 'em, for the greateſt Vanity on the Earth, Matrimony you may leave any other Vanities when you pleaſe, but that will ſtick to you with a Vengance. Matrimony ha, ha ha, there's nothing in the world worth being in earneſt, I / am ſure not being ſober, 'tis all a Farce. - . . . . ~~~~ . Mr. Rant. I hope for, old Acquaintance, you will embrace this motion,reform, and live a ſober Country Life, then we ſhall be Neighbours. \ Zope. Reform, quoth he, 'tis a pretty age, at Five and Fifty to begin to lead a new Life: No, no, I have gone too far to retreat, I muſt charge through, I’ll drink like a Fiſh, theſe Fifty Years, theſe Fellows will be at Aſſes Milk, within fix Months, and dye oth Pip ſoon after, - . . . . Whach. This old Gentlemans a gallant man, Godsookes, I'll whore, drink, ſwagger and ſcowre while I live. - - - Bluff. Ah brave Squire. … . . . . tº - - Ding. Oh noble Squire. - They embrace VWhachum. Zope. Farewel you Apoſtates, ſneaking ſober Sots, go marry, marry, you are fit for no other purpoſe. - . - - - - Exit Tope, , - % Hump. So Brother, I have loff a Nephew, you have found a Son. - r. Rant. Old º: are with Difficulty broken, “ . . . . And Fools are ever found moſt obſtinate ; - - But the leaſt Seeds of VVit with underſtanding, . . . VVill in ſome time ſpring up, and grow and thrive, • . And bear down the rank VVeeds of Vice and Folly. . . . . Wild. Ladies your Charms a miracle have wrought, \ - And early us home to our ſelves have brought; - \ . No pow'r but Love could thus call back a ſtray, ! . . From all the crooked Paths, to the right way. - Sir Will. But where VVit, Beauty, Vertue keep the Field, As Priſoners at diſcretion, all muſt yield, - . . . . . . . Thoſe Forces joyn'd, ſubdue all Vanities; & ! The moſt compendious way of being wiſe, S. h - - Is to be Convert to a Ladies Eyes. .. w -\ t Extunt. , ~ : - -- |
Page Scan 62

EP I LO GUE. Nº. Lady Mothers, you who frown to Day, - Will be thought like the Lady of this Play; You'll not condemn your ſelves, but like bad Faces, Loath the Refºšions, and abhor true Glaſſes: But know all, by theſe Preſents; there's no way: But Gentleneſ, to make ripe Girls obey : U;'dill, if they have Beauty, Wit, or Sence; They will rebel in their own juſt Defence. You in your ſelves, from Grandam Eve ſhou'd find, \ The true Perverſeneſ of a Womans Mind, $ Towhat is moſt forbidden, moſt inclin'd ; ' ' J What ſharply to your Daughters you deny, rou fire their Curioſities to try: - - They think when ſtriëlly kept from all Mankind, There's much more in't than afterwards they find. Tour ſelves, go Flanting to all publick Places, 7 . . Expoſing all you can, your Feeble Graces, - : * - - Darting weak Rays from your Autumnal Faceſ. Heav'n knows true Languiſhing of Eyes you ſhow, "When e're yºu mince, and ſimper at a Beaux; - High Dreſſes, and rich Petticoats will tell us, That all your Ornaments you wear at Fellows ; - . Like Woodcocks, or like Teagues purſu’d, you hide N Tour Heads, and think yºur Body's uneſty d: "... . Tour Daughters find you out, and will obey, What e're they ſee you do ; not hear you ſay.. . . . . . . . . ; The Gawdy Mother hates the Daughters ſight, Whoſe dazling Beams Eclipſe herglimmering Light; She muſt the Viſitants but ſeldom ſee, - - And when 4dmitted to the Company, " With down caſt Look, ſhe enteri, and affraid, She ſneaks like an offending Chamber-maid: . With tºff'd up Head, ſhe muſt be ſubd and chidden, And Mothers dear Delights to her forbidden ; Zhà begets Scorn, how canone #and in awe, Of a vain Taoudry, Amorous Mamma. Of theſe the Poet mºſt deſpair to Day, They will be mortal Fºes to him and’s Play. While theſe frail panes the Authºr does expºſe, The Luftre of the Good, that clearly ſhews, From them a Plaudit muſº not be demy'd, The Witty, Fair ones, muß be on war ſide, So much ſtir Power by him is magniff'd. We ſhow you how your vigorous Beams tº exert, 2?ting vicious men to Conquer and Convert : Firm, to our ſeves we always have a way, To make the fierceſ; Beaſt, Wild man, obey. * * *

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page Scan 63

Books newly Printed for james Knapton, at the Crown in St. Paul's Church-yard. 1691. S$; of Alſatia. Bury-Fair: True Widow. . . * - - --- – Amorous Bigott, or, Teague O Devilly, the Iriſh Prieſt. - The Scowrers. All 5 Comedies, and Written by Tho. Shadwell, Fortune-Hunters, a Comedy; written by Captain Carlile. - Widow Ranter, or, the Hiſtory of Bacon in Piginia; a Tragi-Comedy. Forc’d Marriage, or the Jealous Bridegroom ; a Tragi-Comedy. Sir Patient Fancy; a Comedy. - The feign'd Curtizan, or a Nights Intreague ; a Comedy: all four written by Mrs. A. Behn the Author of the Rover, and Empe- rour of the Moon. - Fngliſh Frier, or the Town-Sparksa Comedy; written by Mr.Crown, author of Sir Courtly Nice. . . . . - Female Prelate being a Hiſtory of the Life and Death of Pope jean ; : a Tragedy written by Elk. Settle. - - Mr. Anthony a Comedy ; , written by the Right Honourable the Earl of Orery, author of Henry V. and Muſtapha. The Devil of a Wiſe, or a Comical Transformation ; written by Mr. jevon. - 2. ' Deluge, or the Deſtruction of the World; an Opera. Don Carlos, a Tragedy. . . - Friendſhip in Faſhion, a Comedy. Titus and Berenice, a Tragedy, with a Farce called The cheats of Scapin ; all three written by Mr. Tho. Otway. - - The Spaniſh Frier, or, the Double Diſcovery, written by Mr. Dryden. Circe, a Tragedy, written by Charles D'Avanant, LLD. Anthony and Cleopatra, a Tragedy, written by Sir Charles Sedley, Bar. Lucius 3anius Brutus, a Tragedy, written by Mr. Lee. The Siege of Babylon, written by Samuel Pordage, Eſq; The Sicilian Uſurper, a Tragedy, written by Mr. Nath. Tate, with a Preſatory Epiſtle in Vindication of the author, occaſioned by the prohibition of this Play on the Stage. Citherea, or the Enamouring Girdle; by Mr. John Smith. The Engliſh Monarch, an Heroick Tragedy; by Tho, Rymer, Eſq; A * - -
Page Scan 64

--------------- . . . . . . . . . . . P_0 E. M. S. &c. g . . . . . . . . ‘A Congratulatory Poem to His Highneſs the P. of O. on his coming into England . . . . . . . . . * . . . . . - A Congratulatory Poem to Q. M. on her coming into England. Ode on the Anniverſary of the King's Birth. . . . . . . ~ Ode on the Kings Return from Ieland; all written by The Shad. well, Poet Laureat and Hiſtoriographer-Royal. * Governour of Cyprus, or the Loves of Piotta and Dorothea, a No- vel, in Twelves . . . . . . • . . ." The Wanton Frier,0r the Iriſh Amour, 1ſt & 2d part,a Novel, inſivel. .The Hiſtory of the Inquiſition, as it is Exerciſed at Goa; written in French by the Ingenious Monſieur Dellon, who laboured 5 years under thoſe Severities ; with an account of his Deliverance. Tranſlated into Engliſh. Quarto, price is. . . . . Some Obſervations concerning Regulating of Elections for Parlia- ment, humbly Recommended to the Conſideration of this pre- ſent Parliament. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . 24adriennium jacobi, or the Hiſtory of the Reign of King jameſ II. from his coming to the Crown to his Deſertion.Price bound 1s 6d. Their Highneſſes the Prince and Princeſs of Orange's Opinion about. a a General Liberty of Conſcience, being a Colle&tion of four Se- lect Papers, viz. I. Mijn Heer Fagel's firſt Letter to Mr. Stewart. 2. Reflections on Monſieur Fagell's ſecond Letter. 3. Fageſ's ſecond Letter to Mr. Stewart. 4. Some Extracts out of Mr. Štein- arts Letter, which were communicated to Mijn-Heer. Fagell; … together with ſome References to Mr. Stewarts Letters. Quarte. ſtitch'd 6 d. - . . .” --- . . . . . . . * * * *::: - Miracles of the Bleſſed . or an Hiſtorical Account of the Original and Stupendious performances of the Image, called our Bleſſed Lady of Halle, viz. Reſtoring the Dead to Life, Healing -- - the Sick, Delivering of Captives, &c. Price 6 d. . . . . . . . A Juſtification of K. W. and Q. M. of their Royal Highneſſes Prince George and Princeſs Anne, of the Convention, Army, Miniſters of State, and others, in this great Revolution. ...” * > ... i - º-- - . a. ----- i. * - - * - - - - - - - - - . . . . . . - º -- " - .” . . • * -- " . . . . ~ . . . . . . . . . . . . . F I N I S. . . - - - - - - - - - - . . - • --> º . . .” . . . . . . . . . ; *... -- . . ) - . . . . . . . : - - ** - - - - - --- r - - - -- º - - -- - - - - - - - - - - - - --- - - - - * * . . --- - - - - - - - º * - - - - - - - - -: - - - º + - - • *. - º § - - -- - - - * • ... " \
Page Scan 65

Blank page
Page Scan 66

-

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section
Page Scan 67

ſae ，**** * |- ！· `------- - |- |-• |-（«|- |-… ' •· |- |-¿.* ， |-} , ! |- ！}, ·+ · * · { ·| * * · → ！ ?|- { · · · |--|-|------ |-|-|-|- |- -------|-----|-

Page Scan 68

Blank page

This page contains an image.

End of Section. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents

End of text. Return to beginning.
