Othello, the Moor of Venice. A tragedy, as it hath been divers times acted at the Globe, and at the Black-Friers: and now at the Theatre Royal, by His Majesties servants. Written by William Shakespear., . | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
Othello, the Moor of Venice. A tragedy, as it hath been divers times acted at the Globe, and at the Black-Friers: and now at the Theatre Royal, by His Majesties servants. Written by William Shakespear., .
Author
Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616.Shakespeare, William, 1564-1616.
Published
London,Printed for W. Weak,1681.
Description
2 p.L., 76 p.22 cm.
Rights
Public Domain.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/mdp.39015082232466

Table of Contents

    Front Cover
    Title Page
    Section 1 on page number 1
    Section 2 on page number 5
    Section 3 on page number 14
    Section 4 on page number 17
    Section 5 on page number 32
    Section 6 on page number 35
    Section 7 on page number 37
    Section 8 on page number 50
    Section 9 on page number 67
    Section 10 on page number 72

Book Text
Front Cover
Page Scan 1

|- |- | |- - - -

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 2

É |||||||||||||||} º ſºul.



This page contains an image.
Page Scan 3

Shakespearſ, Çüllection PR 2.37 ºf - A7 D Tº |(-$



This page contains an image.
Page Scan 4

Blank page

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 5

Blank page

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 6

º | - º

This page contains an image.

End of Front Cover. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Title Page
Page Scan 7

OTHELLO. T H E Moor of Venice. T R A C E Dy, As it hath been divers times aged at the Globe, and at the Black-Friers: - And now at the THEATER Roy AL His MAJEST Esse R v ANTs. Written by ºilliam S º L. O. N. D. O. N. Printed for W. Weak, and are to be ſold by Richard Ben- ley and M. Magnes in Ruſſel Street near Coven Garden, 1681.









This page contains an image.
Page Scan 8

|- |- · - . . . . . ·| |- |- |-





This page contains an image.
Page Scan 9

LL the Tragedies and Comedies of Francis Beumont and john | Fleſher, in one Volume,containing fifty one Plays. Tartuff, or the French Puritan. - Forc’d Marriage, or the Jealous Bride. Engliſh Monſieur. - All Miſtaken, or the mad Couple. Generous Enemies. Andromacha : A Tragedy. Califto: or the Maſque at Court. Country-Wit. A Comedie. Deſtruction of jeruſalem, 2 parts. Miſeries of Civil War. Henry the 6th, with the Murder of the Duke of Glocºffer, in 2 parts. Nero, a Tragedie. Gloriana, a Tragedie. Sophoniſba, or Hanihalf overthrow, Alexander the Great, or the Rival Queens. Mithridateſ King of Pontus. Ceſar Borgia, Son of Pope Alexander 6. Oedipus King of Theber. Theodºſius, or the Force of Love. The Plain Deal, r. The Town-Fop or Sir Timothy Tawdry. ºdellazar or the Moor, Revenge. Madam Fickle: or the Witty Faiſe one. Books Printed tº Year. Siſters. A Catalogue of ſºme Play Printed for R. Bently, and M. Magnes, in Ruſſel-Street, near Covent Garden. Notes and obſervations on the Empreſs The Fond Husband, or the Plotting | The Vertuous, wife of good luck at laſt. - - The Fool turn’d Critick, a Comedie. Squire Oldſap, or the Night Adven- turers. - The Miſtaken Husband, a Comedy. Mr. Limberham, or the Kind Keeper. of Morocco. - The Orphan, or unhappy Marriage. The Souldiers Fortune. Sertoriuſ. A Tragedie. Tamberlain the Great. King Lear. The Unhappy Favourite, or the Earl of Thyeſter, a Tragedy. - Othello, the Moor of Venice. Novel, Printed this Year, 1680. The Amours of the King of Tamaran. The Amours of the French King and Madam Lanilaz. The Amours of Madam and the Count de-Guich. The Pilgrim : A Satyrical Novel on the horrible Villanies of thoſe Perſons. The Secret Hiſtory of the Earl of Eſſex and Queen Elizabeth. - | The Policy of the Clergie of France, to ſuppreſs the Proteſtants of that Kingdom. - Dram.

















This page contains an image.
Page Scan 10

Dramatis Perſonae. Gentlemen. The Tuke of Venice. Mr. Lydal. - Brabantio, a Magnífico, Father to - Deſdemona. & Mr. Cartwright. Gratiano, his ſºrother. Mr. Griffin. Lodovico, their Kinſman. Mr. Harris. Senators. - Othello, the JMoor, General of the . | Army in Cyprus. - * Hart. Caſſio, his Lievtenant General. Mr. Kynaſton. Jago, ſtandard-bearer to the Moor; . . . . ". Villain. - - Mr. Mohun. | Roderigo, a fooliſh Gentleman, that fol. lows the Moor in hopes to Cuckold him. Mr Beeſton. Miaoanio, the Moors Predeceſſor in *: Mr. Watſon. Covernment of Cyprus. Clown, Servant to the Moor. Mr. Hayns. Officers. Muſicians. - Herald. - . Deſdemona, Daughter to Brabantio, and - Wife to j. . - . Mrs. Cox. - Emillia, Wife to Jago. Mrs. Rutter. Bianca, Caſſio’s Wench. - Mrs. Iames. Attendants. - - - Scaene Cyprus.





This page contains an image.

End of Title Page. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 1
Page 1

T H E. MooR or v ENICE º Eater Jago and Roderigo. *Uſh; Never tell me, I take it much unkindly That thou who haſt had my Purſe, As if the ſtrings were thine, ſhouldſ know of this. º jag. But you’l not hear me, - If ever I did dream of ſuch a matter, abhor me. Rod Thou toldſt me, thou didſt hold him in thy hate. jag. Deſpiſe me if I do not: three great ones of the City In perſonal ſuit to make me his Lievtenant, - Oft capt to him, and by the faith of man, I know my price, I am worth no worſe a place. But he, as loving his own pride and purpoſes, Evades them, with a bumbaſt circumſtance, Horribly ſtuft with Epithites of war: Non-ſuits my Mediators: for Certer, (ſays he) I have already choſe my Officer, and what was he Forſooth, a great Arithmetician, One Michael Caſio, a Florentine, A fellow almoſt damn’d in a fair wife, That never ſet a ſquadron in the field, Nor the diviſion of a battle knows, More than a Spinſter, unleſs the bookiſh Theorique, Wherein the tongued Conſuls can propoſe - As maſterly as he: mecre pratle without practice. ls all his Souldier-ſhip; but he Sir had the election. And I, of whom his eyes had ſeen the proofe, At Rhodeſ, at Cipreſſ, and on other grounds, Chriſtn'd and Heathen, muſt be be-leed and calm’d, By Debitor and Creditor, this Counter-Caſter: He (in good time) muſt his Leivtenant be, And I Sir (bleſs the mark) his Mooreſhips Ancient. Rod.

















This page contains an image.
Page 2

º 0 T H E L L 0. #24. By heaven I rather would have been his hangman, . jag. But there's no remedy, Tis the curſe of ſervice, Preferment goes by letter and affection, Not by the old gradation, where each ſécond Stood heir to the firſt : Now Sir bejudge your ſelf, Whether I, in any juſt tearmam affin'd To love the Moore; - Kod. I would not follow him them. jag. O'Sir, content you, I follow him to ſerve my turnupon him, We cannot alſbe Maſters, nor all Maſters Cannot be truly followed, you ſhall mark Many a dutious knee-crooking knave, That (doting on his own obſequious bondage) Wears out his time much like his Maſters Aſſe, For nought but provender, and when he’s old caſhier’d, Whip me ſuch honeſt knaves: Others there are, Who trim’d in forms and viſages of duty, Keep yet their hearts, attending on themſelves, And throwing but ſhews of ſervice on their Lords, Doe well thrive by 'em, - - And when they have lin’d their coats, Do themſelves homage. Thoſe fellows have ſome ſoul, And ſuch a one do I profeſs my ſelf. It is as ſure as you are Roderigo, Were the Moore, I would not be fage: In following him, I follow but my ſelf. Heaven is my judge, not I, - For love and duty, but ſeeming ſo, for my peculiar end: For when my outward action doth demontate - The native act, and figure of my heart, ºn complement externe, 'tis not long after, But I will wear my heart upon my ſleeve, For Daws to peck at, am not what I am. Rod. What a full fortunedoes the thicklipsowe, if he can carry’t thus? - jag. Callup her father, Rowſe him, make after him, poyſon his delight, Proclaim him in the ſtreet, inſence her Kinſmen, And tho he in a fertile climate dwell, Plague him with flyes: the that his joy be joy, Yet throw ſuch changes of vexation out. for sis,

This page contains an image.
Page 3

the Moor of Venice. As it may loſe ſome colour. Rod. Here is her fathers houſe, Ile call aloud. jag. Do with like timerous accent, and dire yell, As when by night and negligence, the fire - Is ſpied in populous Cities. Rod, What ho, Brabantio, Signior Brabantic, ho, ag Awake, what ho, Brabantic, Thieves, thieves, thieves : Look to your houſe, your Daughter, and your Bags, Thieves, thieves. Brabantio at a window. - Bra. What is the reaſon of this terrible ſummons? What is the matter there? - Rod Signior is all your family within - jag. Are your doors locktº Bra. Why, wherefore ask you this? - jag. Sir you are rob'd, for ſhame put on your gown, Your heart is burſt, you have loſt half your ſouls Even now, very now, an old black Ram Is tupping your white Ewe ; ariſe, ariſe, Awake the ſhorting Citizens with the bell, Or elſe the Devil will make a Grandſire of you, ariſe I ſay. Bra. What, have you loſt your wits 2 - Rod. Moſt reverendSignior, do you know my voice Bra. Not I, what are you ? Kod. My name is Roderigo. Bra. The worſe welcome, I have charg’d thee not to haunt about my doors, In honeſt plainneſs, thou haſ heard me ſay My daughter is not for thee, and now in madneſs, Being full of ſupper, and diſtempering draughts, upon malicious bravery, doſt thou come - To ſtart my quiet 2 - Rod. Sir, fir, ſir. Bra. But thou muſt needs be ſure My ſpirit and my place have in them power, To make this bitter to thee. Rod Patience good Sir. Bra. What, tell'ſ thou me of robbing? this is Venice. My houſe is not a graunge. - - Rod. Moſt grave Brabantic, In ſimple and pure ſoul I come to you. - jag. Sir you are one of thoſe, that will not ſerve God, if the Devilbid you. Becauſe we come to do you ſervice, you think we are Ruffians. you’lhave your daughter covered with a Barbary horſe; you’l have your Ne- phews migh to you; you’l have Courſers for Couſens and Gennets for Germanſ. Bra. What prophane wretch art thou? B 2. fag.







This page contains an image.
Page 4

a 0 T H E L L 0. jag. I am one Sir, that come to tell you, your Daughter, and the Moore, are now making the Beaſt with two backs. Bra. Thou art a villain. - jag. You area Senator. Bra. This thou ſhalt anſwer. I know thee Roderigo. Rod Sir, I will anſwer any thing. But I beſeech you, 1ſt be your pleaſure, and moſt wiſe conſent, (As partly I find it is) that your fair daughter At this odd even, and dull watch oth night, Tranſported with no worſe nor better guard But with a knave of common hire, a Gºndelier, To the groſs claſps of a laſcivious Moor: If this be known to you and your allowance, We then have done you bold and ſawcy wrongs? But if you know not this, my manners tell me, We have your wrong rebuke: Do not believe That from the ſenſe of all civility, I thus would play and trifle with your Reverence, Your daughter (if you have not given her leave, I ſay again) hath made a groſs revolt, Tying her duty, beauty, witan fortunes, In anextravagant and wheeling ſtranger, - Of here, and every where: Straight ſatisfieyour ſelf. If ſhe be in her Chamber, or your houſe, Let looſe on me the juſtice of the State, For thus deluding you. Bra. Strike on the tinder, Ho: Give me a taper, call up all my people: This accident is not unlike my dream, beleef of it oppreſſes me already : - light I ſay, light. - jag. Farewell for I muſt leave you, - It ſeems not meet, nor wholſom to my place, To de produc’d (as if I ſtay I ſhall,) -- Againſt the Moore, for I do know the ſtate, (How ever this may gaul him with ſome check) Cannot with ſafety caſt him, for he's imbark d, With ſuch loud reaſon, to the Cipre wars, which even now ſtands in agº) that for their ſouls, Another of his fathome, they have none To lead their buſineſs, in which regard, Tho I do hate him, as I do hells pains. Yet for neceſſity of preſent life, - muſt ſhew out a flag, and ſign of love, which is indeed but ſign, that you ſhall ſurely find him Lead to the Sagitary the raiſed ſearch, And there will I be with him. So farewell Exº







This page contains an image.

End of Section 1. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 2
Page 5

the Moor of Venice, - with Torcheſ, Era. It is too true an evil, gone ſhe is, And what’s to come of my deſpiſed time, is nought but bitterneſs now Roderigo, - where didſ thou ſee her O unhappy girle! With the Mooreſaiſt thou? who would be a father How didſt thou know 'twas ſhe? (O ſhe deceives me Paſt thought,) what ſaid the to you *get more tapers, Raiſe all my kindred, are they married think you? Rod, Truly I think they are. Bra. Oheaven, how got ſhe out? O treaſon of the blood; Fathers from hence, truſt not your daughters minds, By what you ſee them act: is there not charms, By which the property of youth and manhood May be abus’d have you not read Roderigo, Of ſome ſuch thing. - - Rod. Yes Sir, I have indeed. - - º Bra. Callup my Brother. O would you had had her, Some one way, ſome another; do you know Where we may apprehend her and the Moor? Rod. I think I can diſcover him if you pleaſe To get good guard, and go along with me. Bra. Pray you lead on, at every houſe Ile call, I may command at moſt: get weapons ho, And raiſe ſome ſpecial Officers of might: On good Roderigo, Ile deſerve your pains Extant, - Enter Othello, Jago, and Attendants with Torcher. jag. Tho in the trade of war, I have ſlain men. Yet do I hold it very ſtuff oth conſcience, - To do no contriv'd murther; I lack iniquity Sometimes to do me ſervice: nine or ten times I had thought to have jerk’d him here ºlnder the ribs. Oth. Tisbetter as it is, - fag. Nay, but he prated And ſpoke ſuch ſcurvy and provoking terms Againſ your honour, that with the little godlineſs I have, I did full hard forbear him; but I prayºſº, Are you faſt married ? For beſure of this, That the Magnifico is much beloved, And hath in his effect, a voice potential. As double as the Dukes, he will divorce you, Or put upon you what reſtraint, and grievance. The law (with all his might, to inforce it on.) Enter Brabantic in his Night gºne, and Seº







B 3

This page contains an image.
Page 6

6 0 T H E L L 0. We’ſ give him cable. - Oth. Let him do his ſpite, My ſervices which I have done the Signiory, Shall out tongue his complaints, 'tis yet to know, Which when I know that boaſting is an honour, I ſhall promulgate, I fetch my life and being From men of royal height, and my demerrits, May ſpeak unbonneted as proud a fortune - As this that I have reach'd; for know jago. - But that I love the gentle Dºſemona, - I would not my unhouſed free condition, Put intocicuumſcription and confine º For the ſeas worth, Enter Caſſio with light Officers, and Torcher. But look what lights come yonder 2 - jag. Theſe are the raiſed Father and his friends, You were beſt go in. Oth. Not I, I muſt be found, My parts, my Title, and my perfeół ſoul, Shall manifeſt my right by: is it they fag. janus H think no. Oth. The Servants of the Duke, and my Lieutenant? The goodneſs of the night upon you &friends.) What is the news? Caſ. The Duke does greet you (General,) And he requires your haſte, poſt-haſte appearance, Even on the inſtant. Oth. What’s the matter think you ? Caſ. Something from Cipres, as I may divine, It is a buſineſs of ſome heat, the Galleys Have ſent a dozen ſequent meſſengers This very night one at anothers heels: And many of the Conſuls rais'd and met, Areat the Dukes already; you have been hotly call’d for, - When being not at your lodging to be found, The Senate ſent above three ſeveral queſts To ſearch you out. Oth. 'Tis well I am found by you, I will but ſpend a word here in the houſe, and go with you. Caſ: Ancient, what makes he here? . 7. Faith he to night hath boarded a land Carria& If it prove lawful prize, he’s made for ever. Caſ. I do not underſtand. ja. He's married. Caſ. To whom? -























This page contains an image.
Page 7

the Moor of Venice. Enter Brabantio, Roderigo, and others with Light; and Weaponſ. a. Marry to—Come Captain, will you go? Oth. Ha’with you. Caſ. Here comes another troop to ſeek for you. ja. It is Brabantio, General be adviſã. He comes to bad intent. Oth. Holla, ſtand there. - - Rod. Seignior it is the Moor. Era. Down with him thief. - - fag. You Roderigº, come Sir, I am for you. - Oth. Keep up your bright ſwords, for the dew will ruſtem, Good Seignior you ſhall more command with years Then with your weapons. - Bra. Othou foul theef, where haſt thou flowed my daughter? Damn’d as thou art, thou haſt inchanted her, For Ile refer me to all things of ſenſe, (If ſhe in chains of magick were not bound) Whether a maid ſo tender, fair and happy, So oppoſite to marriage that ſhe hund The wealthy curled darlings of our Nation, Would ever have (to incur a general mock) Run from her gatdage to the ſooty boſome Of ſuch a thing as thou? to fear not to delight : Judge me the world, if tis not groſs in ſenſe, That thou haſ pračtis'd on her with foul charms, Abus’d her delicate youth with the drugs or minerals, That weakens motion: Ile have’t diſputed on ; 'Tis portable and palpable to thinkings I therefore apprehend and do attach thee, For an abuſer of the world, a practiſer Of Arts inhibited, and out of warrant. Lay hold upon him, if he do refitt, Subdue him at his peril. Oth. Hold your hands, Both you of my inclining and the reſt : Were it my cue to fight, I ſhould have known it, Without a prompter, where will youthat I go, To anſwer this your charge Bra. To priſon, till fit time. Of Law, and courſe of direct Seſſion Call thee to anſwer. Oth. What if I do obey How may the Duke be there with ſatisfied, Whoſe Meſſengers are here about my fide,

This page contains an image.
Page 8

3 O J H E L L 0. The importancy of Ciprus to the Turk: For that it ſtands not in ſuch warlike brace, Upon ſome preſent buſineſs of the State, To bear me to him. Officer. Tis true moſt worthy Seignior, The Duke's in Council, and your noble ſelf, I am ſure is ſent for. - Bra. How * the Duke in Council 2 In this time of night? bring him away; Mine’s not an idle cauſe: the Duke himſelf, Or any of my Brothers of the State, Cannot but feel this wrong, as 'twere their own. For if ſuch A&tions, may have paſſage free, Bondſlaves, and Pagans ſhall our Stateſmen be. Exetent. - Enter Duke and Senatorſ, ſet at a Table, with lights and Attendantſ. Duke. There is no compoſition in theſe news, That gives them credit. - - I Sena, Indeed they are diſproportioned, My letters ſay, a hundred and ſeven Gallies, Dº, And mine a hundred and fºrty. - - 2 Sen. And mine two hundred : - But though they jump not on a juſt account, - (As in theſe caſes; where they aim reports, - 'Tis oft with difference,) yet do they all confirm - A Turkiſh fleet, and bearing up to Ciprer. - Da Nay, it is poſſible enough to judgment: * I do not ſo ſecureme to the error. - But the main Article I do approve In fearful ſenſe One within. What ho, what ho, what ho? Officer. A meſſenger from the Galleys, Du. Now, the buſineſs? - Sailor. The Turkiſh preparation makes for Rhodeſ. Enter a Meſſenger. So was bid report here to the State, by Seignior Angelo. - Du. How ſay you by this change? Sena. This cannot be by no aſſay of reaſon 'Tis a Pageant, To keep us in falſe gaze: when weconſider And let our ſelves again but underſtand, That as it more concerns the Turk then Rhodeſ, So may he with more facile queſtion bear it, Who altogether lacks thabilities - That Rhºdeſ is dreſ in: if we make thought of this, We muſt not think the Turkis ſo unskilful,





This page contains an image.
Page 9

- To wake and wage a danger profitleſs. the Moore of Venice. 9 To leave that lateſt which concerns him firſt : Neglecting an attempt of eaſe and gain, Dº. Nay, in all confidence he's not for Rhodeſ. Officer. Here is more news. - Mºſſ. The Ottomiter, reverend and gracious, Steering with due courſe, toward the Iſle of Rhodeſ, Have there enjoymed them with an after fleet. - Sena. I, ſo I thought, how many, as you gueſs Meſ. Of 30 ſail, and now they do reſtern Their backward courſe, bearing with frank appearance Their purpoſes towards Cypriºr: Seignior Montano, Your truſty and moſt valiant Servitor, With his free duty recommends you thus. And prays you to believe him. Du, Tis certain then for Cyprus, Marcus Luccicoſ is not he in town 2 I Sena. He’s now in Florence. Du, Write from us to him poſt, poſt haſt diſpatch. Enter a 2d. Mºſſenger. Enter Brabantio, othello, Roderigo, Jago, Caſſio, Deſdemona, and Officerſ. Sena. Here comes Brabantia and the valiant Moore. Du Valiant Othello, we muſt ſtrait imploy you, Againſt the general enemy Ottoman; I did not ſee you, welcome gentle Seignior, We lackt your counſel, and your help to night. Bra. So did Iyours, good your Grace pardon me Neither my place, norought I heard of buſineſs Hath rais'd me from my bed, not doth the general care Takehold of me, for my particular grief, Is of ſo floodgate and ore-bearing nature, That it engluts and ſwallows other ſorrows, And it is ſtill it ſelf. º - - Du. Why whats the matter - - Bra. My daughter, O my Daughter. - All, Dead 2 - Bra. I to me: - She is abus'd, ſtoln from me and corrupted, By ſpels and medicines, bought of Mountebancks. For nature ſo prepoſterouſly to erre, (Being not deficient, blind or lame of ſenſe.) Sans witchcraft could not. Du. Who ere he be, that in this foul proceeding Hath thus beguild your daughter of her ſelf.) And you of her, the bloody book of Law, C You

This page contains an image.
Page 10

| D. 0 T H E L L 0. You ſhallyour ſelf read in the bitter letter, After its ownſence, yetho our properſon . Stood in your action. Bra. Humbly I thank your Grace; Here is the man, this Moor, whom now it ſeems Your ſpecial Mandate, for the State affairs Hath hither brought. 4. We are very ſorry for’t. Dº. What in your own part can you ſay to this 2. Era. Nothing, but this is ſo. - Oth. Moſt potent grave and reverend Seigniors, My very noble and approv’d good Maſters: That I have tane away this old mans daughter, it is moſt true: true, I have married her, - The very head and front of my offending. Fath this extent no more. Rude I am in my ſpeech, And little bleſ with the ſet phraſe of peace, For ſince theſe arms of mine had ſeven years pith, Till now ſome nine moneths waſted, they have us d Their deareſt action in the tented field; And little of this great world can I ſpeak, More then pertains to feats of broyls, and battail, And therefore little ſhall I grace my cauſe, In ſpeaking for my ſelf; yet by your gracious patience, I would around unraviſh'd tale deliver, Of my whole courſe of love, what drugs, what charms, what conjuration, what mighty magick. For ſuch proceedings am I charga withal:) I won his Daughter. - Brº. A Maiden never bold, Of ſpirit ſo ſtill and quiet, that her motion - Bluſht at her ſelf; and ſhe in ſpight of nature, Of years of Country, credit, everything, To fall in love with what ſhe fear'd to look on 2 It is a judgment maim’d, and moſt imperfect, That will confeſs perfeótion ſo would erre - Againſt all rules of Nature, and muſt be driven - To find out practiſes of cunning hell, - Why this ſhould be, I therefore vouch again, That with ſome mixtures powerful ore the blood, Or with ſome dram conjur'd to this effect, He wrought upon her. - Dº. To vouch this is no proof, Without more certain and more overt teſt. Theſe are thin habits, and poor likelihoods, Of modern ſcernings, you prefer againſt him. Sen. But Obºlº ſpeak.























This page contains an image.
Page 11

And ſhe in mine. the Moor of Venice, bid you by indirect and forced courſes, | Subdue and poyſon this young Maids affections? Or came it by requeſt, and ſuch fair queſtion, As ſoul to ſoul affordeth 2 Oth, I do beſeech you, Send for the Lady to the Sagittary, And let her ſpeak of me before her Father: If you do find me foul in her report, - The Truſt, the Office, I do hold of you, Not only take away, but let your ſentence Even fall upon my life. Du. Fetch Deſdemona hither. And till ſhe come, as truly as to heaven I do confeſs the vices of my blood, So juſtly to your grave ears Ile preſent, How I did thrive in this fair Ladies love, Du, Say it Othello. Oth. Her Father loved me; oft invited me, Still queſtioned me the ſtory of my life, From year to year, the battels, ſeges, fortunes That I have paſt: - ran it through, even from my boyiſh days, Toth very moment that he bid me tell it : Wherein I ſpeak of moſt diſaſtrous chances, Of moving accidents, by flood and field; Of hair-breadth ſcapes ith imminent deadly breach ; Of being taken by the inſolent fo, - And ſold to ſlavery of my redemption thence, And portance in my travels hiſtory; Wherein of Antars vaſt, and Deſarts idle. º Rough quaries, rocks and his, whoſe heads touch heaven, It was my hint to ſpeak, ſuch was my proceſs: And of the Cannibal, that each other eat; The Anthropophage and men whoſe heads Do grow beneath their ſhoulders: theſe to hear, Would Dºſemona ſeriouſly incline; - But ſtill the houſe affairs would draw her thence. Which ever as the could with haſte diſpatch, Sheed come again, and with a greedy car Devour up my diſcourſe; which I obſerving, Took once a plyant hour, and found good means To draw from her a prayer of earneſt heart, That I would all my pilgrimage dilate, Whereof by parſels ſhe had ſomething heard, But not intentively, I did conſent, - - Exºni fºg of fºrce. Oth. Ancient condućt them, you beſt know the place; - - And - -



This page contains an image.
Page 12

- O T H E L L 0, | | And often did beguile her of her tears, - When I did ſpeak of ſome diſtreſsfull ſtroak That my youth ſuffered: my ſtory being done; She gave ºne for my pains a world of fighs: She ſwore I faith 'twas ſtrange, 'twas paſſing ſtrange; Twas pitiful, 'twas wondrous pitiful; She wiſht ſhe had not heard it, yet ſhe wiſht That heaven had made her ſuch a man: ſhe thanked me. And bad me if I had a friend that loved her. I ſhould but teach him how to tell my ſtory, And that would woe her, upon this heat I ſpake: She lov'd me for the dangers I had paſt: And I lov’d her that ſhe did pitty them, This only is the witchcraft I have us’d: Here comes the Lady, Let her witneſs it. Enter Deſdemona, Jago, and the reſt. Du. I think this tale would win my Daughtor to 5– Good Brabantic, take up this mangled matter at the beſt, Men do their broken weapons rather uſe, Then their bare hands. Bra. I pray you hear her ſpeak. If ſhe confeſs that ſhe was half the wooer, Deſtruction light on me, if my bad blame Light on the man. Come hither gentle Miſtreſs: Do you perceive in all this noble company, Where moſt you owe obedience? Deſ My noble father, I do perceive here a divided duty : To you I am bound for life and education; My life and education both do learn me How to reſpect you, you are the Lord of duty, I am hitherto your daughter, But here's my husband. And ſo much duty as my mother ſhewed ſo you, preferring you before her father, So much I challenge, that I may profeſs, Due to the Moore my Lord. Bra. God buºy, I ha done: Pleaſe it your Grace, on to the State affairs. I had rather to adopt a child than get it; Come hither Moore: I here dogive thee that, with all my heart, Which but thou haſ already, with all my heart I would keep from thee; for your ſake (Jewel). I am glad at ſoul, I have no other child, For thy eſcape would teach me tyranny, To





This page contains an image.
Page 13

the Moor of /en/ce. 3 To hang clogs on 'em, I have done my Lord. - Du. Let me ſpeak like your ſelf, and lay a ſentence Which as a greeſe or ſtep may help theſe lovers Into your favour. When remedies are paſt, the griefs are ended, By ſeeing the worſt, which late on hopes depended, To mourn a miſchief that is paſt and gon, Is the next way to draw more miſchief on: What cannot be preſerv’d when fortune takes, Patience her injury a mockery makes. - The rob’d that ſmiles, ſteals ſomething from the thief, He robs himſelf that ſpends a bootleſs grief. Bra. So let the Tºrk of Cyprus us beguile. We loſe it not ſo long as we can ſmile; He bears the ſentence well that nothing bears, But the free comfort, which from thence he hears: But he bears both the ſentence and the ſorrow, That to pay grief, muſt of poor patience borrow. Theſe ſentences to ſugar, or to gall, Being ſtrongon both ſides, are equivocal : But words are words, I never yet did hear, That the bruis'd heart was pierced through the ear. - Beſeech you now, to the affairs of the ſtate. Du. The Turk with moſt mighty preparation makes for Cyprus : Oiºſ, the fortitude of the place is beſt known to you, and though we have there a Subſtitute of moſt allowed ſufficiency, yet opinion, a ſovereign Miſtreſs of effects, throws a more ſafer voice on you 5 you muſt therefore be content to ſlubber the gloſs of your new fortunes, with this more ſtubborn and boiſte- rous expedition. Oth. The tyrant cuſtom, moſt grave Senators, Hath made the flinty and ſteel Cooch of war, My thrice-driven bed of down: I do agnize A natural and prompt alacrity, - I find in hardneſs and do undertake This preſent war againſt the Ottomites: Moſt humbly therefore, bending to your State, I crave fit diſpoſition for my wife, Due reference of place and exhibition, With ſuch accommodation and beſort, As levels with her breeding. Du. If you pleaſe bee’t at her fathers. Bra. Ilenot have it ſo. Oth. Nor I. - Deſ. Nor I, I would not there reſide, To put my father in impatient thoughts. By being in his eye: moſt gracious Duke, To my unfolding lend a gracious ear, C = And -|

This page contains an image.

End of Section 2. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 3
Page 14

I aſſiſt my ſimpleneſs.- Dº, What would you Deſdemona º Deſ. That I did love the Moore to live with him, My down right violence, and ſtorm of Fortunes, May trumpet to the world; my hearts ſubdued, Even to the very quality of my Lord : I ſaw Othello’ſ viſage in his minde, - And to his Honors, and his valiant parts - Did I my ſoul and fortunes conſecrate. So that dear Lords, If I be left behinde, A Moth of peace, and he goe to the warre, The rites for which I love him, are bereft me, And I a heavy interimſhall ſupport, - By his dear abſence; let me goe with him. Oth. Your voyces Lords: beſeech you let her will Have a free way. º Vouch with me Heaven, I therefore begit not To pleaſe the palate of my appetite, Nor to comply with heat, the young affects In my defunét, and proper ſatisfaction, But to be free and bounteous to her mind, And heaven defend your good ſouls that you think And let me find a charter in your voyce, . I will your ſerious and good buſineſs ſcant, For ſhe is with me , no, when light wing'd toyºs, And feather d Cupid foyls with wanton dulneſs, My ſpeculative and active inſtruments, - That my diſports, corrupt and taint my buſineſs, Let Huſwives make a Skellet of my Helm, And all indigue and baſe adverſities, Make head againſt my reputation. Dº Be it, as you ſhall privately determine, Either for her ſtay or going, the affair cryeshaſte, &nd ſpeed muſt anſwer, you muſt hence to night. Deſ. To night my Lord * - Dº. This night. Oth. With all my heart. Dº. At nine ºth morning here we’l meet again. Othello, leave ſome officer behind, And he ſhall our Commiſſion bring to you, With ſuch things elſe of quality and reſpect, As doth import you. - 0%. Pleaſe your Grace, my Ancient, A man he is of honeſty and truſt, To his conveyance I aſſigne my wife, With what elſe needful your good Grace ſhall think. ſo be ſent after me. - Dº, Let it be ſo. Good -



This page contains an image.
Page 15

the Moor of Venice. Good night to every one, and noble Seignior, If virtue no delighted beauty lack, Your Son in law is far more fair than black. Seng, Adieu brave Moore, uſe Deſdemona well. Bra. Look to her Moore, if thou haſ eyes to ſee. She has deceiv'd her ſather, and may thce. - Oth, My life upon her faith. Honeſt jago, My Dºlomona muſt 1 leave to thee, I prethee let thy wife attend on her, - - And bring her after in the beſt advantage; Come Deſdemona. I have but an hour - Of love, of wºrldly matters and direétion, To ſpend with thee, we muſt obey the time. Rod, fago. fag. What ſaiſ thou nobleheart? Koº, What will I do thinkſt thou ? fag. Why goe to bed and ſleep. Rod. I will incontinently drown my ſelf. jag. Well, if thou doeſt, I ſhall never love thee after it, wºod iſ sºleman. - . . . . Rod. It is ſillineſs to live, when to live is a torment, and then we have a preſcription, to dye when death is our Phyſitian. - jag, O villanous, I ha look’d upon the world for four times ſeven years, and ſince I could diſtinghiſh between a benefit, and an injury, I never tound a man that knew how to love himſelf. ere I would ſay I would drown ſºy felf, for the love of a Ginny Hen, I would change my humanity with a Baboone. - - - - - Rod. What ſhould I doe? I confeſsitis my ſhame to be ſo fond, but it is not in my virtue to amend it. - jag. Virtue, a fig, 'tis in our ſelves, that we are thus, or thus, our bodies are gardens, to the which our wills are Gardiners, ſo that if we will plant Nettles, or ſow Lettice, ſet Iſop, and weed up Time; ſupply it with one geº- der of hearbs, or diſtract it with many; either to have it ferrill with idleneſs. or manur'd with induſtry, why the power, and corrigible Authorit ºf this, lies in our wills. If the ballance of our lives had not one ſcale of reaſon, to poyſe another of ſenſuality; the blood and baſeneſs of our natures. would conduct us to moſt prepoſterous concluſions. But we have reaſon to coole ºur raging motions, our carnal ſtings, our unbitted luſts; where - of . ake this that you call love to be a Seół, or Syen. | Rºd. It cannot be. - jag. It is meerly a luſtof the blood, and a permiſſion of the will; Come, be a man; drown thy ſelf ; drowne Cats, and blinde Puppies: profeſs methy friend, and I confeſs me knit to thy deſerving, with Cables of perdurable toughneſs; I could never better ſteed thee then now. Put money in thy purſe follow theſe wars, defeat thy favour with an uſurpºd bºard ſay, put money in thy purſe. It cannot be that Dºſamºng ſhould - - long -

















This page contains an image.
Page 16

16 0 H E L L 0, long continue her love unto the Moor, put money in thy purſe, nor he his to her ; it was a violent commencement, and thou ſhalt ſee an an- ſwerable ſequeſtration: put but money in thy purſe.-Theſe Moores are changeable in their wills.-Fill thy purſe with money. The food that to him now is as luſhious as Locuſts, ſhall be to him ſhortly as bitter as Coloquintida: She muſt change for youth; when ſhe is ſated with his body, ſhe will find the error of her choice; ſhe muſt have change, ſhe muſt. Therefore put money in thy purſe: If thou wilt needs damn thy ſelf, do it a more dilicate way then drowning; make all the money thou canſ. If ſančtimony, and a frail vow, betwixt an erring Barbarian, and a ſuper-ſubtle Venetian, be not too hard for my wits, and all the tribe of hell, thou ſhalt enjoy her; therefore make money, a pox a drowning, tis clean out of the way 5 ſeek thou rather to be hang'd in compaſſing thy joy, then to be drowned, and go without her. - Rod. Wilt thou be faſt to my hopes, if I depend on the iſſue 2 jag. Thou art ſure of me—go, make money—I have told thee of: ten, and I tell thee again, and again, I hate the Moor, my cauſe is hearted, thine has no leſs reaſon, let us be conjunétive in our revenge againſt him : If thou canſ cuckold him, thou doſt thy ſelf a pleaſure, me a ſport. There are many events in the womb of Time, which will be dº- livered. Traverſe, go, provide thy money, we will have more of this to morrow, adieu. - Kod. Where ſhall we meeti'th morning jag. At my lodging. Rod. I’ll be with thee betimes. - jag, Go to farewell:—do you hear Rodergº Rod. What ſay yoa 2. - - - fag. No more of drowning, do you hear? Rod, I am chang'd, I’ll go ſell all my land. - Exit Rodergo. jag. Thus do I ever make my fool my purſe: For I mine own gain'd knowledge ſhould prophane if I would time expend with ſuch a ſhip, But for my ſport and profit; I hate the Moor. And it is thought abroad, that twixt my ſheets Ha’s done my Office; I know not if t be true- Yet I, formeer ſuſpition in that kind. . Willdo, as if for ſurety; he holds me well, - The better ſhall my purpoſe work on him. Caffo's a proper man, let me ſcenow. To get this place, and to plum up my will. A double knavery—how, how-let me ſee, After ſome time, to abuſe. Othello's ear, That he is too familiar with his wife : He has a perſon and a ſmooth diſpoſe, To be ſuſpected, framid to make woman falſe: The Moor is of a free and open nature,





















This page contains an image.

End of Section 3. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 4
Page 17

the Moor of Venice. That thinks men honeſ, that but ſeems to be ſo: And will as tenderly be led bith noſe—as Aſſes are: That, it isingender'd : Hell and night Muſt bring this monitous birth to the worlds light. Actus Secundus, Scoena prima. Enter Montanio, Govermour of Cyprus, with two other Gentlemen. - Montamia. 7 Hat from the Cape can you diſcern at Sea? 1 Gent. Nothing at all, it is a high wrought flood, I cannot 'twixt the heaven and the main - - - Deſcry a ſail. - Møn. Methinks the wind does ſpeak aloud at land, A fuller blaſt neºr ſhook our battlements: If it harufliand ſo upon the Sea, - What ribs of Oak, when mountain melt on them, Can hold the morties, What ſhall we hear of this? 2 Gent. A ſegregation of the Turkiſh fleet: For do but ſland upon the foaming ſhore, The chiding billows ſeems to pelt the clouds. The wind ſhak’d ſurge, with high and monſtrous main Seems to caſt water on the burning Bear, - And quench the guards of th’ever fired pole, I never did like moleſtation view, On the enchaſed flood. Mon. If that the Turkiſh Fleet Be not inſhelterºd, and embayed, they are drown'd. - It is impoſſible to bear it out. - º Enter a third Gentleman. 3 Gent. News Lads, your wars are done: The deſperate Tempeſt hath ſo bang'd the Turk. That their deſigment haults: A noble ſhip of Venice, Hath ſeen a grievous wrack and ſufferance. On moſt part of their Fleet. - Mon. How, is this true 3. Gent.The ſhip is here put in : A Veroneſia, Michael Caſio, - - - D - Lieutenant



This page contains an image.
Page 18

18 0 T H E L L 0. Lievtenent to the warlike Moor Othello, is come a ſhore: the Moor himſelf at Sea, And is in full commiſſion here for Cyprus. Mon. I am glad on’t, 'tis a worthy Governour. 3. Gent. But this ſame Caſio, tho he ſpeak of comfort, Touching the Turkiſh loſs, yet he looks ſadly, And prays the Moor be ſafe, for they were parted, With foul and violent Tempeſt. Mon. Pray heaven he be: For I have ſerv'd him, and the man commands Like a full Soldier: Lets to the ſea ſide, ho, - As well to ſee the Veſſel that’s come in: As to throw out our eyes for brave Othello, Even till we make the Main and th’Air all blew, An indiſtinči regard. - - 3. Gent. Come, let's do ſo; For every minute is expectancy Of more arrivance. Enter Caſſio. Caſ. Thanks to the valiant of this Iſle, That ſo approve the Moor, and let the heavens, Give him defence againſt their Elements For I have loſt him on a dangerous ſea. Man. Ishe well ſhipt * Caſ His Bark is ſtoutly timberd, and is Pilot Of very expert and approv’d allowance, Therefore my hope’s (not ſurfeited to death) - Stand in bold cure Enter a Meſſenger, Mºſ. A ſail, a ſail, a ſail. Gaſ. What noiſe 2. - - Mºſ The Town is empty, on the brow oth ſea, Stands rancks of people, and they cry a ſail. - Gaſ My hopes do ſhape him for the Government. - - 2. Gent. They do diſcharge the ſhot of courteſie, Our friend at leaſt. Aſºo’s Gaſ I pray you fir go forth - - And give us truth, whº 'tis that is arriv'd. - 2. Gent, I ſhall. Exit. - Mºn. But good Lievtenant, is your General wiv'd? Gaſ. Moſt fortunately, he hath archiv'd amaid, That parragons deſcription and wild fame; One that excels the quicks of blaſoning pens; - - And in the eſſential veſture of creation, Does bear an excellency: –now, who has put in Fºey



This page contains an image.
Page 19

* He has had moſt favourable and happy ſpeed, Good Ancient you are welcome, welcome Miſtreſs. the Moor of Venice. Enter 2 Gentleman. 2 Gent. 'Tis one jago, Ancient to the General; Tempeſts themſelves, high ſeas, and houling winds, The guttered rocks, and congregated ſands, Traitors ºnſteep'd, to clog the guiltleſs Keel, As having ſenſe of beauty, do omit Their common natures, lettinggo ſafely by - - The divine Deſdemona. - - Møn. What is ſhe? - Caſ. She that I ſpeak of our great Captains Captain, Left in the condućt of the bold fago, Whoſe footing here anticipates our thoughts A ſennights ſpeed–great jove Othello guard, - And ſwell his ſail with thine own powerful breath, That he may bleſs this Bay with his tall ſhip, And ſwiftly come tº Deſdemona's arms Enter Deſdemona, Jago, Emilia, and Roderigo. Give renew’d fire, To our extinéted ſpirits: - And bring all Cyprus comfort, O behold The riches of the ſhip is come on ſhore. - Yemen of Cyprus, let her have your knees: Hail to the Lady: and the grace of heaven, - - Before, behind thee, and on every hand, Enwheel thee round. Deſ. I thank you valiant Caſſio: What tidings can you tell me of my Lord? &aſ. He is not yet arrived, nor know I ought, But that he's well, and will be ſhortly here. - Deſ O but I fear –how loſt you company? [within] a ſail a ſºil. Caſº The great contention of the ſea and skies - Parted our fellowſhip; but hark a ſail. 2 Gent. They give their greeting to the Citadel, This likewiſe is a friend. - Caſ. See for the news: Let it not gallyour patience, good fago, That I extend my manners, 'tis my breeding. That gives me this bold ſhew of courteſe. jag. Sir, would ſhe give you ſo much of her lips, As of her tongue ſhe has beflowed on me, You'd have enough. - D 2 Deſ.









This page contains an image.
Page 20

20 0 T H E L L 0, - - Deſ: Alas! ſhe has no ſpeech. - - jag. In faith too much: I find it ſtill, for when I ha leave to ſleep, Mary, before your Ladiſhip I grant, - She puts her tongue a little in her heart, And chides with thinking. - Em, Youha little cauſe to ſay ſo. jag. Come on, come on, you are Pićtures out of dores: Bells in your Parlors: Wild-cats in your Kitchins: Saints in your injuries: Divels being offended: Players in your houſe-wifery; and houſe-wives in your beds. Deſ; O fic upon thee ſlanderer. - jag. Nay, it is true, or elſe I am a Turk. You riſe to play, and goe to bed to work. Em, You ſhall not write my praiſe. jag. No, let me not. Deſ What wouldſt thou write of me, If thou ſhouldſt praiſe me? fag. O gentle Lady, do not put me toºt, For I am nothing, if not critical. Dºſ Come on, aſſay—there's one gone to the Harbour. jag. I Madam. - - Deſ. I am not merry, but I do beguile The thing I am, by ſeeming otherwiſe: Come, how wouldſ thou praiſe me? fag. I am about it, but indeed my invention Comes from my pate, as birdline does from freeze, It plucks out braine and all: but my Muſe labours, And thus ſhe is delivered : If ſhe be fair and wift, fairneſ and wit: The one’ſ for uſe, the other uſeth it. - - Deſ Well prais'd : how if ſhe be black and witty fag. If ſhe be black, and thereto have a wit, She’ll find a white, that ſhall her blackneſºfit. Deſ Worſe and worſe. Em. How if fair and fooliſh ºr Jag. She never yet tº fooliſh, that waſ fair, For even her folly help her to an Heir. - Deſ. Theſe are old Paradoxes, to make fools laugh ºth Alehouſe What miſerable praiſe haſ thou for her, - That’s ſoul and fooliſh 2 Jag. There’ſ none ſº fºul, and fºoliſh thereunio, But doeſ foul prankſ, which fair and viſº one duº Deſ. O heavy ignorance that praiſes the worſt beſt; but what praiſe could ſt thou beſtow on a deſerving woman indeed? one, that in the authority of her merits, did juſtly put on the vouch of very malice itſelf? - Jag |-







This page contains an image.
Page 21

the Moor of Venice. of Jag. She that was ever fair, and never proud, Had tongue at will, and yet was never loud, Never lack gold, and yet went never gay, Fled from her wiſh, and yet ſaid, now I may - She that being angred, her revenge being migh, Bad her wrong ſtay, and her diſpleaſure fly: - She that in wiſdome never was ſº fail, To change the Codſhead for the Salmon, tail : . She that could think, and ne're diſcloſe her mind, See Sutorſ following, and not look behind : - She wº, a wight, (if ever ſuch wight were,) Deſ. To do what? -- Jag. To ſucklefoolſ, and chronicle ſmall Beene. Deſ: O moſt lame and impotent concluſion : - Do not learn of him Emillia, tho he be thy husband How ſay you Caſio, is he not a moſt prophane and liberal Counſellour. º Caſ. He ſpeaks home Madam, you may reliſh him. - More in the Souldier than in the Scholler. jag. He takes her by the palme; I well ſed, whiſper; with as little a webb as this, will I enſnare as great a ſlie as Caſſ I ſmile upon her, doe: I will catch you in your own Courtſhip: you ºtrue, 'tis ſo indeed. If ſuch tricks - as theſe ſtrip you out of your Lieutenantry, it had been better you had not rift your three fingers ſo off, which now again, you are moſt apt to play the ºr in a very good well kiſt, and excellent courteſie: ’tis ſo indeed : yet again, your fingers at your lips ? would they were Cliſterpipes for your ſake.-The Moore, I know his Trumpet, |Trumpet within. Enter. Othello, and Attendantſ. - - Gaſ 'Tis truly ſo. Deſ. Lets meet him, and receive him. - - Gaſ Loe, where he comes. - Qib, O my fair Warriour, - Deſ My dear Othello. - 9th. It gives me wonder, great as my content To ſee you here before me: O my ſouls joy, If after every tempeſt, come ſuch calmneſs, May the winds blow, till they have wakened death sº And let the labouring Bark clime hills of Seas, Olympus high, and duck again as low, As Hell's from Heaven ; If it were now to dye, Twere now to be moſt happy, for I fear My Soul hath her content ſo abſolute, That not another comfort, like to this Succeeds in unknown Fate. - Deſ. The Heavens forbid. - But that our loves and comforts ſhould increaſe, Even as our dayes do grow. - - - 0%. | |



This page contains an image.
Page 22

22 O T H E L L 0. Oºh, Amen to that, ſweet Powers : I cannot ſpeak enough of this content, It ſtops me here, it is too much of joy: And this, and this, the greateſt diſcord be, [kſ. That ere our hearts ſhould make. ag. Q, you are well-tun'd now, But I’le ſet down the pegs, that makes this muſick, As honeſt as I am. Oth. Come, let us to the Caſtle: News friends, our wars are done, the Turkſ are drown'd. How does my old acquaintance of this Iſle? Honny, you ſhall be well deſir'd in Cyprus ; I have found great love amongſt them : O my ſweet: prattle out of faſhion, and I dote, In mine own comforts: I prethee good jago, Go to the Bay, and diſimbark my Coffers; Bring thou the Maſter to the Citadel: - - He is a good one, and his worthineſs, - Does challenge much reſpect, come Deſdemona. Once more well met at Cyprus. - Exetent. - jag. Do thou meet me preſently at the Harbour : come hither, if thou beeſ: valiant, (as they ſay, baſe men being in love, have then a Nobility in their na-. tures, more than is native to them,)—liſt me, the Lieutenant to night watches on the Court of Guard : firſt I will tell thee this, Deſdemona is dircółly in love with him. fºod. With him? why ’tis not poſſible, jºg. Lay thy finger thus, and let thy Soul be inſtructed: marke me, with what violence ſhe firſt lov’d the Moore, but for bragging, and telling her fan- taſticallies; and will ſhe love him ſtill for prating? let not the diſcreet heart think it. Her eye muſt be fed, and what delight ſhall ſhe have to look on the Devil? When the blood is made dull with the act of ſport, there ſhould be a game to inflame it, and give faciety a freſh appetite, Lovelineſs in favour, ſym- pathy in years, manners, and beautics; all which the Moore is defective in : now for want of theſe requir’d conveniences, her delicate tenderneſs will find its ſelf abus'd, begin to heave the gorge, diſreliſh and abhor the Moor, very na- ture will inſtruct her to it, and compel her to ſome ſecond choice: Now Sir. this granted, as it is moſt pregnant and unforced poſition, who ſtands ſo emi- ºnently in the degree of this fortune, as Caſio does a knave very voluble, no farther conſcionable, than in putting on the meer form of civil and humane ſeeming, for the better compaſſing of his ſalt and moſt hidden looſe affections : A ſubtle ſlippery Knave, a finder out of occaſions; that has an eye, can ſtamp and counterfeit advantages, tho true advantage never preſent it ſelf. Beſides. the Knave is handſome, young, and hath all thoſe requiſites in him that folly and green minds look after : a peſtilent compleat knave, and the woman has found him already. - Rod, I cannot believe that in her, ſhe’s full of moſt bleſt condition. jag. Beſt figs end; the wine ſhe drinks is made of grapes: if ſhe had been - - Bleſt,



This page contains an image.
Page 23

the Moore of Venice. Rod. Yes, But that was but courteſie. - - - - fºg. Lechery, by this hand , an Index and obſcure prologue to the Hiſtory, of juſt and foul thoughts: they met ſo near with their lips, that their breaths embrac'd together, villanous thoughts, when theſe mutualities ſo marſhal the way; hand at hand comes Roderigo, the maſter, and the main exerciſe, the in- corporate concluſion. But Sir, be you rul’d by me, I have brought you from Venice; watch you to night, for command, I’le lay't upon you. Caſio knows you not, I’lenot be far from you, do you find ſome occaſion to anger Caſio, either by ſpeaking too loud, or faintinghis diſcipline, or from what other courſe you pleaſe; which the time ſhall more favourable miniſter. Rod. Well. fag. Sir he is raſh, and very ſudden in cholar, and haply with his Trunchen may ſtrike at you provoke him that he may, for even out of that, will I cauſe theſe of Cyprus to mutiny, whoſe qualification ſhall come into no true taſte again’t, but by the diſplanting of Caſio : So ſhall you have a ſhorter journey to your deſires, by the means I ſhall then have to prefer them, and the impedi- ment moſt profitably remov’d, without which there were no expectation of our proſperity. - - - fºod. I will do this, if I can bring it to any opportunity. jag. I warrant thee, meet me by and by at the Cittadel; I muſt fetch his neceſſaries a ſhore.—Farewel. - Rod. Adieu. - - Exit. jag. That Caſio loves her, I do well believe it; That ſhe loves him, 'tis apt and of great credits. The Moore howbe’t, that I endure him not, is of a conſtant, noble, loving nature ; And I dare think, he'ſ prove to Deſdemona A moſt dear Husband now I do love her too, Not out of abſolute luſt, (tho peradventure, Iſland accomptant for as great a fin,) But partly lead to diet my revenge, For that I do ſuſpect the luſtful Moore, Hath leap'd into my ſeat, the thought whereof Doth like a poyſonous Mineral gnaw my inwards; And nothing can, nor ſhall content my Soul, Till I am even’d with him, wife for wife; Or failing ſo, yet that I put the Moore, At leaſt, into a jealouſe ſo ſtrong, That judgement cannot cure ; which thing to do, If this poor traſh of Venice, whom I trace, For his quick hunting, ſtand the putting on, Ple have our Michael Caſio on the hip, Abuſe him to the Moore, in the ranke garbe, (For I fear Caſiº, with my night-capto) - Make the Moore thank me, love me, and reward me, bleſ, ſhe would never have lov’d the Moore, Didſt thou not ſee her paddle with the palme of his hand?didſ not marke that? - For

This page contains an image.
Page 24

24. 0 T H E L L 0. For making him egregiouſly an Aſs, And practiſing upon his peace and quiet, Even to madneſs – 'tis here, but yet confus'd : Anarctics plain face is never ſeen, till usd. Ex?. - Enter Othello's Herauld, reading a Proclamation. It is Othello's pleaſure, our noble and valiant General, that upon certainti- dings now arrived, importing the meer perdition of the Turkiſh Fleet; that e- very man put himſelf into triumph ; ſome to dance, ſome make Bonefires; each man to what ſport and Revels his addićtion leads him; for beſides theſe bene- ficial News, it is the celebration of his Nuptials: So much was his pleaſure ſhould be proclaimed. All Offices are open, and there is full liberty. from this preſent hour of five, till the belihath told eleven. Heaven bleſs the Iſle of Cy- pruſ, and our noble General Othello, - - Enter Othello, Caſio, and Deſdemona. - º º Oth. Good Michael look you to the guard to night. Lets teach our ſelves that honourable ſtop, Not to out-ſport diſcretion. - Caſ: jago hath direction what to do : But notwithſtanding, with my perſonal eye Will I look to it. 0th jago is moſt honeſt. Michael goodnight, to morrow with your earlieſt, Let me have ſpeech with you, come my dear love, The purchaſe made, the fruits are to enſue. That profits yet to come 'twixt me and you, Good night. - Enter jago. Caſ Welcome jago, we muſt to the watch. jag Not this hour Lieutenant. 'tis not yet ten a Clock: our General caſt us thus early for the love of his Deſdemona, wholet us not therefore blame, he hath not yet made wanton the night with her; and ſhe is ſport for jove. Caſ. She is a moſt exquiſite Lady. jag. And I’le warrant her full of game. - Caſ. Indeed ſhe is a moſt freſh and delicate creature. fag. What an eye ſhe has - Methinks it ſounds a parly of provocation. caſ. An inviting eye, and yet methinks right modeſt. - jag. And when the ſpeaks, 'tis an Alarm to love. - Caſ. She is indeed perfection. - - jag. Wellhappineſs to their ſheets come Lieutenant, I have a ſtope of Wine, and here without area brace of Cyprus Gallants that would ſain have a meaſure to the health of the black Obello. -









This page contains an image.
Page 25

the Moor of Venice. 25 Caſ Not to night, good jº have very poor and unhappy brains for drinking: I could well wiſh courteſie would invent ſome other cuſtome of en- tertainment, - - jag. Othey are our friends—but one cup: I’le drink for you. Caſ: I ha drunk but one cup to night, and that was craftily qualified to, and behold what innovation it makes here : I am unfortunate in the infirmity, and dare not task my weakneſs with any more. - jag. What man, 'tis a night of Revels, the Gallants deſire it. Caſ. Where are they jag. Here at the dore, I pray you call them in. Caſ. I’le doºt, but it diſlikes me. Exit. jag. If I can faſten but one cup upon him. - With that which he hath drunk to night already, He'll be as full of quarrel and offence, - As my young Miſtreſs dog.-Nay my ſick fool Roderigo, (Whom love has turn’d almoſt the wrong ſide outward.) To Deſdemona, hath to night carouſt. - Potations pottle deep, and he's to watch: Three Lads of Cypruſ, noble ſwelling ſpirits, That hold their honour in a wary diſtance, The very Elements of this war-like Iſle,) Havel to night fluſired with flowing cups, - And the watch too: now mongſt this flock of drunkards, I am to put our Caſio in ſome action, That may offend the Iſle; Enter Montanio, Caſſio, But here they come: and other r. If conſequence do but approve my dream, My boat ſails freely, both with wind and ſtream. Caſ. Fore God they have given me a rouſe already. Mon. Good faith a little one, not paſt a pint, As I am a Soldier. - fag. Some winehoe: And let me the Cannikin clink, clink. and let me the Cannikin clink, clink. 4 Souldier's a man, a life’, but a ſpan, - Why then let a Soulcher drink–Some wine boys. Caſ. Fore heaven an excellent ſong - - jag. I learn’d it in England, where indeed they are moſt potent in potting: | your Dane: your Germane, and your ſwag-bellied Hollander, (drinkho.) are - nothing to your Engliſh. - - - Caſ: Is your Engliſh man ſo exquiſite in his drinking jag. Why, he drinks you with facility, your Dane dead drunk; he ſweats not to overthrow your Almain ; he gives your Hollander a vomit, ere the next pottle can be fill'd Caſ. To the health of our General. Mon. I am for it Lieutenant, and I will do fag, O ſweet England,- you juſtice. E.













This page contains an image.
Page 26

0 T H E L L 0. King Stephen was and a worthy Peer, His breecher coſt him but a Crown, He held 'em ſix pence all to dear, With that he callºd the Taylor lown ; He was a Wight of high Renown, And thou art but of low degree, Tir pride that pull; the Country down, Then take thine auld cloke about thee.—Some wineho. Cºſ. Why, this is a more exquiſite ſong than the other. jag. Willyou heart again. Cºſ. No, for I hold him unworthy of his place, that does thoſe things welf, Heaven’s above all, and there be Souls that muſt be ſaved. - jag. It is true good Lieutenant. º Caſ. For mine own part, no offence to the General, nor any man of quali- ty, I hope to be ſaved. jag. And ſo do I Lieutenant, Caſ 1, but by your leave, not before me; the Lieutenant is to be ſaved Be- fore the Ancient, Let’s ha no more of this, let's to our affairs : forgive us our ſins: Gentlemen, let’s look to our buſineſs: do not think Gentlemen I am drunk, this is my Ancient, this is my right hand, and this is my left hand: I am not drunk now, I can ſtand well enough, and ſpeak well enough. All. Excellent well. Caſ: Why very well then: you muſt not think then that I am drunk. [Exit. Mon. To the platform Maſters. Come let’s ſet the watch. jag. You ſee this fellow that is gone before, He is a Souldier fit to ſtand by Ceſar. - And give direction: and do but ſee his vice 'Tis to his virtue, a juſt equinox, - The one as long as th’other 'tis pity of him. I fear the truſt, Othello put him in, On ſome odd time of his infirmity, Will ſhake this iſland. - Mºn. But is he often thus: - jag. Tis evermore the Prologue to his ſleep. - He'll watch the horolodge a double ſet, If drink rock not his cradle. Møn. Twere well the General were put in mind of it. Perhaps he ſees it not, or his good nature Praiſes the virtue that appears in Caſio, And looks not on his evils: is not this true? - jag. How now Roderigo, Enter Roderigo. I pray you after the Lieutenant go Exit Rod. Mºn. And 'tis great pity that the noble Moore - Should hazard ſuch a place as his own ſecond With one of an ingraft infirmity: it were an honeſ action roſy ſo to the Moore. - jug



This page contains an image.
Page 27

In quarter, and in terms, like bride and groom. Diveſting them to bed, and then but now, - | (As if ſome Planet had unwitted men,) - - | the Moor of Venice. 2 y - jag. Not I, for this fair Iſland. do love Caſio well, and would do much, - Help, Help, ºil, To cure him of this evil: but hark, what noiſe. Enter Caſſio, driving in Roderigo. - - caſ. You rogue, you raſcall. - Møn. What’s the matter Lieutenant 2 Caſ: A knave, teach me my duty: but I’le beat the knave into a wicker bottle. - - Rod, Beat me? - - Caſ Doſt thou prate rogue 2 - Mon. Good Lieutenant; pray Sir hold your hand. Caſ Let me go Sir, or I’ll knock you o're the mazzard. Mon. Come, come, you are drunk. - Caſ. Drunk? [they fight. - jag. Away I ſay, go out, and cry a mutiny. Exit Rod. Nay good Lieutenant: God’s-will Gentlemen, Help ho, Lieutenant: Sir, Montamio, Sir, - Help Maſters, here's a goodly watch indeed: A bel ring: Who's that that rings the Bellº Diablo–ho, The Town will riſe, fie, fie, Lieutenant hold, You will be ſham'd for ever, Enter Othello, and Gentlemen with weapons Oth. What's the matter here 2 - Mon. I bleed ſtill, I am hurt to the death. [he faints. Oth. Hold for your lives. jag. Hold, hold Lieutenant, Sir Montania, Gentlemen, Have you forgot all place of fence and duty : - Hold the General ſpeaks to you hold, hold, for ſhame. Oth. Why how now ho, from whence ariſes this Are we turn’d Turkſ, and to ourſelves do that, Which Heaven has forbid the Ottamirer - - - | For Chriſtian ſhame, put by this barbarous brawles He that ſtirs next, to carve for his ownrage. - - Holds his ſoul light, he dyes upon his motion : - Silence that dreadful Bell, it frights the Iſle From her propriety: what’s the matter maſters 2 | Honeſt jago, that looks dead with grieving, Speak, who began this, on thy love I charge thee. jag. I do not know, friends all but now, even now, E 2 - Swords

This page contains an image.
Page 28

28 0 T H E L L 0. Aſſayes to lead the way: If onceſ ſtir. - And cºff, following him with determinºwoºd, - Swords out and tilting one at others breaſt, In oppoſition bloody. I cannot ſpeak Any beginning to this peeviſh odds; And would in action glorious, I had loſt Thoſe legs, that brought me to a part of it. 9th. How came it Michael, you were thus forgot a Cºſ I pray you pardon me, I cannot ſpeak. - 9th, Worthy Montanio, you were wont to be civil, The gravity and ſtilneſs of your youth The world hath noted, and your name is great, In mouths of wiſeſt cenſure. What’s the matter. That you unlace your reputation thus, And ſpend your rich opinion, for the name Of a night brawler? give meanſwerto’t Mon. Worthy Orbello, I am hurt to danger, Your Officer jago can inform you, While I ſpare ſpeech, which ſomething now offends me. Of all that I do know, nor know I ought By me, that’s ſaid or done amiſs this night 3 Llpleſs ſelf-charity be ſometime a vice. And to defend our ſelves it be a ſin, When violence aſſays us. - Oth. Now by Heaven My blood begins my ſaferguides to rule, And paſſion having my beſt judgement cool’d, Ordo but lift this Arm the beſt of you Shaº ſink in my rebuke give me to know How this foul rout began, who ſet it on, And he that is approv’d in this offences Tho he had twinn’d with me, both at a birth, Shall loſe me; what, in a Town of war. Yet wild, the peoplesheartsbrimfull of fear, To mannage private and domeſtick quarrels, In night, and on the Court and guard of ſafety º 'Tis monſtrous, jago, who began * Mon. If partiality aſſign'd, or league in office. Thou doeſ deliver more or leſs than truth, Thou art no Souldier, - - fag Touch me not ſo near, I had rather haſ this tongue out of my mouth, Then it ſhould do offence to Michael Caſiº Yet I perſwade my ſelf to ſpeak the truth. - - | Shall nothing wrong him. Thus it is General: - Mºntamia and my ſelf being in ſpeech, There comes a fellow, crying out for help, - To |



This page contains an image.
Page 29

the Moore of Venice To execute upon him: Sir this Gentleman. Steps into Caffo, and intreats his pauſe: My ſelf the crying fellow did purſue, Leſt by his clamor, as it ſo fellout, The Town might fall infright: he ſwift of foot, Out-ran my purpoſe ; and I return the rather, , For that I heard the clink and fall of ſwords; And Caſio high in oath, which tilltonight, I ne’re might ſay before: when I came back, For this was brief, I found them cloſe together, - - At blow and thruſt, even as agen they were, - When youyour ſelf did part them. More of this matter can I not report, But men are men, the beſt ſometimes forget :: Tho Caſio did ſome little wrong to him, As men in rage ſtrike thoſe that wiſh them beſt Yet ſurely Caſio, I believe receiv'd From him that fled, ſome ſtrange indignity, Which patience could not paſs. - Oth. I know jago, - Thy honeſty and love doth mince this matter, Making it light to Caſio; Caſio, I love thee, But never more be Officer of mine. - Look if my gentle love be not rais’d up: Entee Deſdemona, ºth otherſ. I’le make thee an example. Deſ. What’s the matter? Oth. All's well now ſweeting: Come away to bed: Sir, for your hurts, My ſelf will be your Surgeon lead him off; jago, look with care about the Town, º And ſilence thoſe whom this vile braul diſtraćted. Come Deſdemona, ’tis the Souldiers life, - To have their balmy ſlumbers wak'd with ſtrife, fºg. What, are you hurt Lieutenant? Exit Moor, Deſdemona, and Attendantſ, Gaſ I, paſt all Surgery. fag Marry Heaven forbid. Caſ: Reputation, reputation, hot loſt my reputations I ha loſt the immortal part Sir of my ſelf, And what remains is beſtial, my reputation. jago, my reputation, - E 3 jºgº.

This page contains an image.
Page 30

30 0 T H E L L 0. jag. As I am an honeſt man, I thought you had receiv'd ſome bodily wound, there is more offence in that, then in Reputation: reputation is an idle and moſt falſe impoſition, oft got without merit, and loſt without de- ſerving : You have loſt no reputation at all, unleſs you repute yourſelf ſuch a loſer; what man, there are ways to recover the General agen : you are but n w caſt in his mood, a puniſhment more in policy, then in malice, even ſo, as one would beat his offenceleſs dog, to affright an imperious Lion ſue to him again, and he's yours. - - - - Caſ: I will rather ſue to be deſpisºd, then to deceive ſo good a Commander, with ſo light, ſo drunken, and diſcreet an Officer. Drunk? and ſpeak parrat; and ſquabble, ſwagger, ſwear? and diſcourſe fuſtian with ones one ſhaddow, O thou inviſible ſpirit of wine, if thou haſte no name to be known by, let us call thee Devil. - - - - fag. What was he that you followed with your ſword? What had he done to you? Caſ. I know not. jag. Is’t poſſible? - Caſ, I remember a maſs of things, but nothing diſtinctly ; a quarrel, but nothing wherefore. O that men ſhould put an enemy in their mouths, to ſteal away their brains ; that we ſhould with joy revel, pleaſure, and applauſe. transform our ſelves into beaſts. - jag. Why, but you are now well enough: how came you thus recovered 2 Caſ. It hath pleas'd the devil drunkenneſs, to give place to the devil wrath; one unperfectneſs ſhews me another, to make me frankly deſpiſe my ſelf. jag. Come, you are too ſevere a morraler; as the time, the place, the con- dition of this Country ſtands, I could heartily wiſh, this had not ſo befaln 3 but ſince it is as it is, mend it for your own good. Caſ, I will ask him for my place again, he ſhall tell me I am a drunkard : had as many mouths as Hydra, ſuch an anſwer would ſtop 'em all; to be now a ſenſible man, by and by a fool, and preſently a beaſt: every inordinate cu is unbleſt, and the ingredicnce is a devil. - jag. Come, come, good wine is a good familiar creature, if it be well us dº exclaim no more againſt it and good Liev tenant, I think you think I love yOll. - - - Caſ I have well approv’d it Sir:- drunk? - - fºg. You, or any man living may be drunk at ſome time man : Ple tell you what you ſhall do, our Generals wife is now the Generał? I may ſay ſo in this reſpºt, for that he has devoted and given up himſelf to the contem- plation, mark and devotement of her parts and graces. Confeſſe your ſelf frcely to her, importune her, ſhe’ll help to put you into your place again: He is ſo free, ſo kind, ſo apt ſo bleſſed a diſpoſition, that ſhe holds it a vice in her goodneſs, not to do more than ſhe is requeſted. This broken joynt between you and her husband, intreat her to ſplinter, and my fortunes againſt any lay, worth naming, this crack of your love ſhall grow ſtronger then’twas before. - Caſ. You adviſe me well.





This page contains an image.
Page 31

the Moore of Venice. 3 ag. I proteſt in the ſincerity of love and honeſt kindneſs. Gaſ I think it freely, and betimes in the morning, will I beſeech the ver- tuous Deſdemona, to undertake for me: I am deſperate of my fortunes, if they check me here. ag. You are in the right: Good night Lieutenant, I muſt to the watch. Caſ, Good night honeſt fago. Exºr. jag. And what's he then, that ſays I play the villain, When this advice is free I give, and honeſt, - Probal to thinking, and indeed the courſe, To win the Moor agen 2 For’tis moſt caſe The inclining Deſdemona to ſubdue, in any honeſt ſuit ſhe's fram’d as fruitful, As the free Elements: and then for her To win the Moor, wer’t to renounce his baptiſm, All ſeals and ſymbols of redeemed fin, His ſoul is ſo infetter'd to her love, That ſhe may make, unmake, do what ſhe liſt, Even as her appetite ſhall play the god - With his weak function; how am I then a villain, To counſel Caſio to this parrallel courſe. - Directly to his good? divinity of hell, - When devils will their blackeſt ſins put on, They do ſuggeſt at firſt with heavenly ſhews, v. As I do now ; for whilſt this honeſt fool Plys Deſºlemona to repair his fortunes, And ſhe for him, pleads ſtrongly to the Moor; I’le pour this peſtilence into his ear, That ſhe repeals him for her bodies luſt; And by how much ſhe ſtrives to do him good, She ſhall undo her credit with the Moor; So will I turn her vertue into pitch, And out of her own goodneſs, make the net That ſhall enmeſh them all: Enter Roderigo. How now Rodrigo 2. - Kod. I do follow here in the chaſe, not like a hound that hunts, but one that fills up the cry: my money is almoſt ſpent, I ha been to night exceedingly well cudgell'd : I think the iſſue will be , I ſhall have ſo much experi- ºnce for my pains, and ſo no money at all, and with a little more wit re- turn to ſenice. fag. How poor are they, that have not patience? What wound did ever heal but by degrees 2 Thou knoweſt we work by wit, and not by witchcraft, And wit depends on dilatory time. Does not go well? Caſo has beaten thee, And thou, by that ſmall hurt, hath caſheird Caſio, The other things grow fair againſt the ſun, Yet

This page contains an image.

End of Section 4. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 5
Page 32

22 0 T H E L L 0. Cºntent thy ſelf a while; by ºth maſs 'tis morning; Myſelf a while, to draw the Moor apart, $olliciting his wife: I, that’s the way, for loves ſake, to make no more noiſe with it. Yet fruits that bloſſom firſt, will firſt be ºpe, Pleaſure, and action, make the hours ſeem ſhort: Retire thee, go where thou art billitted ; Away I ſay, thou ſhalt know more hereafter : Nay get thee gon: Some things are to be done. My wife muſt move for Caſio to her Miſtreſs, I’le ſet her on. And bring him jump, when he may Cafto find, Dull not deviſe by coldneſs and delay. Excans Actus Tertius. Scoena prima. - Enter Caſſio, with Muſicians. - - - caſ. A / Aſters play here, I will content your pains, - Y. Something that's brief and bid goodmorrow General. They play, and enter the Clown. - Cº. Why Maſters, ha your Inſtruments been at Naples, that they ſpeak ºth noſe thus 2 - Boy. How Sir how” - Clo. Are theſe I pray.call'd wind Inſtruments? Boy. I marry are they Sir. Clo. O, thereby hangs a tail. - Boy. Whereby hangs a tail Sir? Clo. Marry Sir, by many a wind Inſtrument that I know. But Maſters, her's money for you, and the General ſo likes your muſick, that he deſires you - Boy, Well Sir, we will not. - - Clo. If you have any muſick that may not be heard, toºt again; but as they ſay, to hear muſick, the General does not greatly care. - Bay. We ha none ſuch Sir - - - - lo. Then put your pipes in your bag, for ſºle away 5 go vaniſh into air, a Way. - Caſ Doſt thou hear my honeſ friend ? Clo. No, I hear not your honeſt friend, I hear you. * - Caſ. Prethcę keep up thy quallets, there's a poor piece of gold for thee: If the Gentlewoman that attends the Generals wife be ſtirring tell her there's one Cºſº, entreats her a little favour of ſpeech—wilt thou do this? Co.

This page contains an image.
Page 33

- the Moor of Venice. 33 Clo. She is ſtirring Sir, if ſhe will ſtir hither, I ſhall ſeem to notific unto her. - Enter | 330- Caſ Do good my friend. In happy time jago. Exit Clown. jag. You hanot been abed then. - - Caſ. Why no, the day had broke before we parted: Iha made bold jagº to ſend in to your wife, my ſuit to her, Is that ſhe will to vertuous Deſdemona Procureme ſome acceſs. jag. I'le ſend her to you preſently, And ſºle deviſe a meanto draw the Moor Out of the way, that your converſe and buſineſs May be more free. - - - Caſ. I humbly thank you for’t : I never knew A Florenţine more kind and honeſt. Exº. Enter Emillia. Em. Goodmorrow good Lievtenant, I am ſorry For your diſpleaſure, but all will ſoon be well, The General and his wife are talking of it, And ſhe ſpeaks for you ſtoutly: the Moore replies, That he you hurt is of great fame in Cyprus, And great affinity, and that in wholſome wiſdom, He might not but refuſe: but he proteſts he loves you, And needs no other ſutor but his likings, To take the ſafeſt occaſion by the front, To bring you in again. Caſ. Yet I beſeech you, If you think fit, or that it may be done, Give me advantage of ſome brief diſcourſe With Deſdemona alone. - - Em. Pray you come in, - - I will beſtow you where you ſhall have time, To ſpeak your boſome freely. Caſº I am much bound to you. Exempº, Enter. Othello, Jago, and other Gentlemen. Orb. Theſe letters give jago to the Pilate, And by him do my duties to the State; That done, I will be walking to the works, Repair there to me. fag. Well my good Lord, I’le dot, - Oth. This fortification Gentlemen, ſhall we ſee tº Gent. We wait upon your Lordſhip. Exegº. ſº





This page contains an image.
Page 34

34 0 T H E L L 0, - He’s never anything but your true ſervant. Vnfit fºr mine own purpoſe, Enter Deſdemona, Caſſio and Emilia. Deſ Be thou aſſur’d good Caſio, I will de All my abilities in thy behalf. Em, Good Madam do, I know it grieves my Husband, As if the caſe were his. - - - Deſ O that’s an honeſt fellow:—do not doubt Caffo, But I will have my Lord and you again, - As friendly as you were. - Caſ: Bounteous Madam, What ever ſhall become of Michael Caſio, Deſ O'Sir, I thank you, you do love my Lord : You have known him long, and be you well aſſur’d, He ſhall in ſtrangeſt, ſtand no farther off, Thenin a politick diſtance. - Caſ. I but Lady, - That policy may either laſt ſo long, Or feed upon ſuch nice and wateriſh diet, Or breed it ſelf, ſo out of circumſtance, That I being abſent, and my place ſupplied; My General will forget my love and ſervice. - Deſ: Do not doubt that, before Emilia here, I give thee warrant of thy place: aſſure thee, If I do vow a friendſhip, I’le perform it, To the laſt Article: my Lord ſhall never reſt, Iºle watch him tame, and talk him out of patiences His bed ſhall ſeem a School, his boord a ſhrift, I’le intermingle every thing he does, With Caſiº’s ſuit; therefore be merry Caſiº, For thy Soliciter ſhall rather die, Then give thy cauſe away. Enter Othello, jago, and Gentlemen. Em, Madam, here comes my Lord. Gaſ Madam I’le take my leave: Deſ Nay ſtay, and hear me ſpeak. caſ. Madan, not now, I am very iſlateaſe, Deſ. Well, do your diſcretion, Exit Caſſic jag. Ha, I like not that. 05. What doſt thou ſay fºg. Nothing my Lord, or if- know not what- | º, was not that Caff, parted from my wife 2 fºg. Caſin my Lord?-no ſure, cannot think it. Th - - at

This page contains an image.

End of Section 5. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 6
Page 35

s Orſue to you, to do a peculiar profit the Moor of Venice. That he would ſteal away ſo guilty-like, Seeing you coming - Oth. I do believe 'twashe. Deſ. How now my Lord, I have been talking with a Suitor here, A man that languiſhes in your diſpleaſure. Oth. Who iſ ſt-you mean? - - Deſ Why your Lieutenant Caſio, good my Lord, If I have any grace or power to move you, His preſent reconciliation take : For if he be not one that truly loves you, That errs in ignorance, and not in cunning, I have no judgment in an honeſt face, I prithee call him back. th, Went he hence now * * Yes faith, ſo humbled, That he has left part of his griefs with me, To ſuffer with him; good Love call him back. Oth. Not now ſweet Deſºlemon, ſome other time. Deſ. But ſhall’t be ſhortly - Oth. The ſooner ſweet for you. Deſ Shall’t be to night at Supper ? Oth. No, not to night. - Deſ. Tomorrow dinner then Oth. I ſhall not dine at home, I meet the Captains at the Cittadel, Deſ Why then tomorrow night, or Tueſday morn. On Tueſday morn, or night, or Wedneſday morn, prithee name the time, but let it not Exceed three dayes: faith he's penitent. And yet his treſpaſs in our common reaſon, (Save that they ſay, the wars muſt make examples, Out of her beft) is not almoſt a fault, To incurra private check: when ſhall he come? Tell meCubello I wonder in my ſoul What you could ask me, that I ſhould deny Or ſtand ſo mamm ring on 2 What Michael Caſio 2 That came a wooing with you, and ſo many a time When I have ſpoke of you diſpraiſingly, Hath tane your part, to have ſo much to do To bring him in Truſt me, I could do much,-- - Oth. Prithee no more, let him come when he will, will deny thee nothing. - peſ. Why this is notaboon "Tis as I ſhould intreat you wear your gloves: Or ſeed on nouriſhing diſhes, or keep you warm-

F 2

This page contains an image.
Page 36

36 0 T H E L L 0. To your own perſon; nay, when I have a ſuit, Wherein Irnean to touch your love indeed, It ſhall be full of poiſe and difficult weight, And fearful to be granted. Oth. I will deny thee nothing, Whereon I dobeſeech thee grant me this, To leave me but a little to myſelf. Deſ, ſhall I deny you? no, farewel my Lord. Oth. Farewel my Deſdemona, I’le come to thee ſtraight. Dºſ Emilia, come, be it as your fancies teach you, What ere you be I am obedient. Exeunt Deſ, and Em. Oth. Excellent wretch, perdition catch my ſoul, But I do love thee, and when I love thee not. Chaos is come again. jag. My noble Lord. - - 0th. What doſt thou ſay jago? fag. Did Michael Caſio when you wooed my Lady, Know of your love 2 - Oth. He did from firſt to laſt :-Why doſt thou ask? jag but for a ſatisfaction of my thought, No further harm. . Oth. Why of thy thought jago 2. jag. I did not think he had been acquainted with her. Oth, O yes, and went between us very oft. fag. Indeed? - - Oth. Indeed? I indeed, deſermºſt thou ought in that?' is he not honeſt 2 - jag. Honeſt my Lord * Oth, Honeſt I honeſt. jag. My Lord, for ought I know, º Oth. What doſt thou think? - fag. Think my Lord? - Oth. Think my Lord why doſłthou eccho me, As if there were ſome monſter in thy thought, Too hidious to be ſhown: Thou doſt mean ſomething: I heard thee ſay but now, thou lik'ſ not that? When Caſio left my wife: what didſt not like And when I told thee, he was of my counſel, In my whole courſe of woing thou criºdſ indeed? And didſt contract, and purſe thy brow together, As if thou then hadſt ſhut up in thy brain, Some horrible conceit: If thou doſt love me, Shew me thy thought. jag. My Lord you know I love you. - Oth. I think thou doſt. And for I know, thou art full of love and honeſty, And weigheſt thy words, before thou giv'ſ 'em breath, Therefore theſe ſtops of thine fright me the more:



















This page contains an image.

End of Section 6. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 7
Page 37

the Moor of V.enice. - 37 For ſuch things in a falſe diſloyal Knave, Aretricks of cuſtome; but in a man that’s juſt, They are cloſe dilations, working from the heart, That paſſion cannot rule. jag. For Michael Caſſia, I dare be ſworn, I think that he is honeſt. Oth. I think ſo too . - jag. Menſhould be what they ſeem, Orthoſe that be not, would they might ſeem none. Oth. Certain, men ſhould be what they ſeem, - fag. Why then I think Caſio's an honeſt man. Oth. Nay, yet there’s more in this, I prethee ſpeak to me, as to thy thinkings. As thou doſt ruminate, and give thy worſt of thoughts, The worſt of words. - - jag. Good my Lord pardon me; Though I am bound to every act of duty, I am not bound to that all ſlaves are free top, 11tter my thoughts: Why, ſay they are vile and falſe: As where's that Pallace, whereinto foul things Sometimes intrude not Who has a breaſt ſo pure, But ſome uncleanly apprehenſions Keep Leets and Law-dayes, and in Seſſion fit With meditations lawful? Oth. Thou doſt conſpire againſt thy friend fago, If thou but thinkeſt him wrong’d, and makeſt his ear. A ſtranger to thy thoughts. jag. I do beſeech you, - Though I perchance am vicious in my gheſs. (As I confeſs it is my natures plague, To ſpy into abuſes, and oft my jealouſie Shapes faults that are not :) that your wiſdome yet; From one that ſo imperfeótly conceits, Would take no notice, nor build your ſelf a trouble. Out of my ſcattering and unſure obſervance; it were not for your quiet, nor your good. Nor for my manhºod, honeſty, or wiſdome, Tolet you know my thoughts. Oth. What doſt thou mean * jag. Good name in man and woman (dearmy Lord) is the immediate Jewel of our Souls: - Who ſteals my purſe, ſteals traſh,’tis ſomething, nothing, 'Twas mine, 'tis his, and has been ſlave to thouſands: But he that filches from me my good name, Robs me of that which not inriches him, And makes me poor indeed, Qib, I'll know thy thoughts.









F 3

This page contains an image.
Page 38

28 0 T H E L L 0. jag. You cannot, if my heart were in your hand, Nor ſhall not, whilſt 'tis in my cuſtody. Oth, Ha 2 - jag. O beware (my Lord) of jealouſie; It is a greeney’d monſter, which doth mock * The meat it feeds on, That Cuckold lives in bliſs, who certain of his fate, loves not his wronger: º º - But oh, what damned minutes tells he ore. Who dotes, yet doubts, ſuſpects, yet ſtrongly loves. 0th, O miſery jag. ſ ºntºn. is rich, and rich enough, But riches fineleſs, is as poor as winter, - To him that ever fears he ſhall be poor : - Good Heaven, the Souls of all my Tribe defend From jealouſe. Oth. Why, why is this? Thinkſ thou I'de make a life of jealouſe 2 To follow ſtill the changes of the Moon With freſh ſuſpitions 2 No, to be once in doubt, Is once to be reſolvd exchange me for a Goat, When I ſhall turn the buſineſs of my Soul To ſuch exufflicate, and blown ſurmiſes, Matching thy inference: ’tis not to make mejealous, To ſay my wife is fair, feeds well, loves company, is free of ſpeech, ſings, plays, and dances well: Where virtue is, theſe are more virtuous: Nor from mine own weak merits wiłł 1 draw The ſmalleſt fear, or doubt of her revolt, For ſhe had eyes, and choſen me: no fago, * lºſe ſee before I doubt, when I doubt, prove : And on the proof, there is no more but this: Away at once with love and jealouſe jag. I am glad of it, for now I ſhall have reaſon To ſhºw the love and duty that I bear you, With franker ſpirit: therefore as I am bound, Receive it from me: I ſpeak not yet of proof, Look to your wife, obſerve her well with Caſio Wear your eye thus, not jealous, nor ſecure, would not have your free and noble nature, Out of ſelf-bounty be abus'd, look too tº know our Country diſpoſition well, in Venice they do let Heaven ſee the pranks, They dare not ſhew their husbands: their beſt conſcience is not to leave’t undone, but keep’t unknown. Oth, Doſt thou ſay ſo jag. She did deceive her father marrying you : And when ſhe ſeem'd to ſhake and fear your looks, She lov’d thern moſt. - - -



































This page contains an image.
Page 39

the Moore of Venice. 9th. And ſo ſhe did. jag. Why go too then, She that ſo young, could give out ſuch a ſeeming. To ſeal her fathers eyes up, cloſe as Oak, He thought 'twas witchcraft ; but I am much too blame: I humbly do beſeech you of your pardon, For too much loving you. Oth. I am bound to the for ever. jag. I ſee this hath a little daſht your Spirits. Oth. Not a jot, not a jot. - fag. Truſt me, I fear it has. - I hope you will conſider what is ſpoke, - - Comes from my love; but I do ſee you are mov’d, I am to pray you, not to ſtrain my ſpeech To groſſer iſſues, nor to larger reach, Then to ſuſpition. - Oth. I will not. - jag. Should you do ſo my Lord. My ſpeech ſhould fallinto ſuch vile ſucceſs, As my thoughts aim not at : Caſſio’s my worthy friend: My Lord, I ſee you are mov’d. - Oth. No, not much mov’d. I do not think but Deſdemona's honeſ. - jag. Long live ſhe ſo, and long live you to think ſo. Oth. And yet how nature erring from it ſelf. jag. I, there's the point; as to be bold with you, Not to affect many propoſed matches, Of her own clime, complexion, and degree, Whereto we ſee in all things nature tends ; Fie we may ſmellin ſuch a will moſt rank, Foul diſproportion, thoughts unnatural. But pardon me: I do not in poſition, Diſtinétly ſpeak of her, thoſ may fear Her will recoyling to her better Judgment, May fall to match you with her country forms, And happily repent. Oth. Farewel, if more Thou doſt perceive, let me know more, ſet on Thy wife to obſerve leave me jago. fag. My Lord I take my leave. Oth, Why did I marry.” This honeſt creature doubtleſs Sees, and knows more, much more than he unfolds, jag. My Lord, I would I might intreat your honour, To ſcan this thing no farther, leave it to time, And though 'tis fit that Caſo have his place, (For ſure he fills it up with great ability.) Yet if you pleaſe to hold him off a while, 3 9



This page contains an image.
Page 40

as o f H E L L 0. You ſhall by that, perceive him and his means : Note if your Lady ſtrain her entertainment, With any ſtrong or vehement importunity, Much will be ſeen in that, in the mean time, Let me be thought too buſie in my fears, As worthy cauſe I have, to fear I am :) And hold her free, I dobeſeech your honour. Oth. Fear not my government. jag. I once more take my leave. [Exit. Oth. This fellow's of exceeding honeſty, - And knows all quantities with a learned ſpirit O humane dealings: If I do prove her haggard, Tho that her Jeſſes were my dear heart ſtrings, I’de whiſtle her off, and let her down the wind, To prey at fortune. Happily, for I am black, And have not thoſe ſoft parts of converſation, That Chamberers have, or for I am declin’d Into the vale of years, yet that’s not much, She’s gone, I am abus'd, and my relief Muſt be to loath her: O curſe of marriage, That we can call theſe delicate creatures ours, And not their appetites: I had rather be a Toad, And live upon the vapor in adungeon, Then keep a corner in a thing I love, For others uſes: yet 'tis the plague of great ones, Prerogativ'd are they leſs then the baſe, 'Tis deſtiny unſhunnable, like death: Eventhen this forked plague is fated to us, When wedo quicken: Deſdemona comes. It ſhe be falſe. Othen Heaven mocks it ſelf. I’le not believe it. Enter Deſdemona and Emillia Deſ. How now my dear Othello? Your dinner, and the generous Ilander By you invited, do attend your preſence. Oth. I am to blame. Deſ Why is your ſpeech ſo ſaint 2 are you not well ? Oth. I have a pain upon my forehead ear. Deſ. Why that’s with watching, "twill away again : Let me but bind it hard, within this hour - It will be well. - - Oth. Your napkin is too little: Let it alone, come I’ll go in with you. Deſ. I am very ſorry that you are not well. - Em, I am glad I have found this napkin. Exº Oth, and Deſ th. - - 15



This page contains an image.
Page 41

- the Moor of Venice. 4. This was her firſt remembrance from the Moor, My wayward husband, hath a hundred times Wooed me to ſteal it, but ſhe ſo loves the token, For he conjur’d her ſhe ſhould ever keep it, That ſhe reſervs it ever more about her, To kiſs and talk too; I’le ha the work tane out, And givºt jago: what he'll do with it. Heaven knows, not I, - . | Enter Jago. I nothing, but to pleaſe his fantaſie. jag. How now, what do youhere alone * Em, Do not you chide, I have a thing for you. jag. A thing for me, it is a common thing- Em. Ha 2 - - jag. To have a fooliſh wife. Em, O, is that all what will you give me now, For that ſame handkerchief ? jag. What handkerchief ? Em, What handkerchief? Why, that the Moor firſt gave to Deſdemona, That which ſo often you did bid me ſteal. fag. Ha’ſ ſtole it from her Em. No faith, ſhe let it drop by negligence, And to the advantage, I being here took it up ; Look, here it is, _-- fag. A good wench, give it me. Em. What Will you do with it, That you have been ſo earneſt to have me filch it? jag. Why, what’s that to you? - - Em. Ift be not for ſome purpoſe of import, Give met again, poor Lady, ſhe’ll run mad When ſhe ſhall lack it. jag. Be not you acknown on't, I have uſe for it -go leave me - I will in Caſio's lodging loſe this napkin, Exit Em. And let him find it : Trifles light as Air Are to the jealous confirmations ſtrong As proofs of holy Writ, this may do ſomething: The Moor already changes with my poiſon, Dangerous conceits are in their natures poiſons, Which at the firſt are ſcarce found to diſtaſt : But with a little act upon the blood, [Enter Othello Burn like the mines of Sulphure: I did ſay ſo: Look where he comes, not Poppy, nor Mandragora, Nor all the drouſie ſirops of the world, Shall ever medicine thee to that ſweet ſleep, Which thou owedſ: yeſterday. oil. Ha, ha, falſe to me, to me? - jag. Why how now General? nomore of that G on

This page contains an image.
Page 42

Oth. Avant, be gone, thou haſ ſet me on the rack, I ſwear, 'tis better to be much abus’d, Then but to know’t a little. jag. How now my Lord * Oth. What ſence had 1 of her ſtone hours of luſt: I ſaw’t not, thought it not, it harm'd not me, I ſlept the next night well, was free and merry : I found not Caſſº's kiſſes on her lips; He that is robºd, not wanting what is ſtolne, Let him pot know’t and he’s not robºd at all. jag. I am ſorry to hear this. Oth. I had been happy if the general Camp, Pyoners and all, had taſted her ſweet body, So I had nothing known: O now for ever Farewel the tranquile mind, farewel content; Farewel the plumed Troop, and the big wars, That makes ambition virtue: O farewel, Farewel the neighing Steed, and the ſhrill Trump, The ſpirit-ſtirring Drum, the ear-piercing Fife, The royal Banner, and all quality, Pride, pomp, and circumſtance of glorious war. And O ye mortal Engines, whoſe wide throats; The immortal fover great clamors counterfeit Farewel, Othello's Occupation’s gone, fºg. It poſſible my Lord? Öſ. Villain, be ſure thou prove my Love a whore; Be ſure of it, give me the ocular proof, Qº by the worth of my eternal Soul, Thou hadſ better have been born a dog, Then anſwer my wak'd wrath. jag, 1ſt come to this? - - O). Make me to ſee tº or at the leaſt ſo prove it. That the probation bear no hinge, no loop, To hang a doubt on: or woe upon thy life fag. My noble Lord. - Oth. If thou doſt ſlander her, and torture me, Never pray more, abandon all remorces. On horrors head, horrors accumulate: Do deeds to make Heaven weep, all Earth amaz'd. For nothing canſ thou to damnation add greater than that: jag, O grace, O Heaven defend ºne. Are you a man have you a ſoul or ſenſe God buy you, take my Office,—O wretched fool, That liveſt to make thine honeſty a vice: O monſtrous world take note, take note O world. ſo be direct and honeſt is not ſafe, thank you for this profit, and from hence,



















































This page contains an image.
Page 43

the Moor of Venice. 43 I’le love no friend, ſincelove breeds ſuch offence. Oth. Nay ſtay, thou ſhouldſt be honett, fag. I ſhould be wiſe, for honeſty's a fool, And loſes that it works for. - Oth. By the world, - I think my wife be honeſt, and think ſhe is not, I think that thou art juſt, and think thou art not; I’le have ſome proof: her name that was as freſh As Dianº viſage, is now begrim’d, and black As mine own face : if there be cords or knives, Poyſon, or fire, or ſuffocating ſtreams, I’le not endure it: would I were ſatisfied. jag. I ſee Sir, you are eaten up with paſſion, I do repent me that I put it to you; You would be ſatisfied. Oth. Would, nay, I will. - jag. And may, but how, how ſatisfied my Lord? Would you the ſuperviſion groſsly gape on, Behold her topt - Oth. Death and damnation—oh. fag. It were a tedious difficulty I think, To bring 'em to that proſpect, damnºem then, If ever mortal eyes did ſee them boulſter More than their own; what then, how then What ſhall I ſay? where’s ſatisfaction? It is impoſſible you ſhould ſee this, Were they as prime as Goats, as hot as Monkies, As ſalt as Wolves in pride, and fools as groſs As ignorance made drunk; but yet I ſay, If imputation and ſtrong circumſtances, Which lead directly to the dore of truth Will give you ſatisfaction, you may hat. Oth. Give me a living reaſon, that ſhe's diſloyal. fag. I do not like the Office, - But fith I am enter'd into this cauſe ſo far, Prickt toºt by fooliſh honeſty and love, will go on. I lay with Caffo lately, And being troubled with araging tooth, I could not ſleep. There area kind of men ſo looſe of ſoul. That in their ſleep will mutter their affairs, One of this kind is Caſio In ſleep I heard him ſay, Sweet Deſdemona, Let us be wary, let us hide our loves; And then Sir would he gripe and wring my hand. Cry out ſweet creature, and then kiſs me hard, As if he pluckt up kiſſes by the roots, That grew upon my lips, then *: his leg - ºf 2.















This page contains an image.
Page 44

44 0 T H E L L 0. Over my thigh, and figh'd, and kiſſed, and then Cryed, curſed fate, that gave thee to the Moor. Oth. O monſtrous, monſtrous. jag. Nay, this was but his dream. Oth. But this denoted a fore-gon concluſion, *Tis a ſhrewd doubt, thoit be but a dream. jag. And this may help to thicken other proofs. That do demonſtrate thinly. Oth. I’lé tear her all to pieces. fag. Nay, but be wiſe, yet we ſee nothing done, She may be honeſt yet: tell me but this, Have you not ſometimes ſeen a handkerchief, Spotted with ſtrawberries in your wives hand 2 Oth. I gave her ſuch a one, 'twas my firſt gift: jag. I know not that, but ſuch a handkerchief, I am ſure it was your wives, did [to day. See Caſio wipe his beard with, - Oth, Ift be that, fag. If it be that, or any, it was hers; It ſpeaks againſt her, with the other proofs. Oth. C that the ſlave had forty thouſand lives, One is too poor, too weak for my revenge: Now I do ſee’tis true, look here jago, - All my fond love, thus do I blow to Heaven, 'tis gone. Ariſe black vengeance from thy hollow Cell, Yield up Olove thy crown, and hearted Throne, To tyrannous hate, ſwell boſome with thy fraught. For tis of Aſpicks tongues, be kneel; jag. Pray be content. - Oth, O blood, jago, blood. - - jag. Patience Iſay, your mind perhaps may change. Ot/. Never jago. - - Like to the Ponick Sea. Whoſe icy current and compulſive courſe, Neºr feels retiring ebbe, but keeps due on. To the Propontick and the Helleſpont : Even ſo my bloody thoughts, with violent paces. Shall ne're look back, ne’reebbe to humble love, Till that a capable and wide revenge - Swallow them up. Now by yond marble Heaven. In the due reverence of a ſacred vow, There engage my words, - - fag. Do not riſe yet : Jagokºlº Witneſs the ever-burning lights above, You Elements that clip us round about 5. Witneſs that here, jago doth give up The execution of his wit, hand, heart º

This page contains an image.
Page 45

-- - - the Moore of Venice. To wrong’d Othello's ſervice: let him command, And to obey, ſhall be in meremorce, What bloody work ſo ever. - Oth. I greet thy love; - - Not with vain thanks, but with acceptance bounteous, And will upon the inſtant put thee toº, Within theſe three dayes, let me hear thee ſay That Caſio's not alive. jag. My friend is dead : - 'Tis done as you requeſt, but let her live. Oth, Damn her leud minks: Odamn her, Come, go with me apart, I will withdraw, To furniſh me with ſome ſwift means of death, For the fair devil: now art thou my Lieutenant. - jag. I am your own for ever, [Exeuni. - Enter Deſdemona, Emília, and the Clown. Deſ. Do you know Sirra, where the Lieutenant Caſio lies 2 Clo. I dare not ſay he lies any where, Deſ. Why man - - Clo. He is a Souldier, and for one to ſay a Souldier lies, is ſtabbing, - Deſ Go too, where lodges he? - - Clo. To tell you where he lodges, is to tell you where I lie. Dºſ Can any thing be made of this 2 Clo. I know not where he lodges, and for me to deviſe a lodging, and ſay he lies there, were to lye in mine own throat. - - Deſ, Can you enquire him out, and be edified by report? Clo. I will catechize the world for him, that is, make queſtions, and by them anſwer. - - Deſ. Seek him, bid him come hither, tell him I have moved my Lord in his behalf, and hope all will be well. - - - Clo. To do this, is within the compaſs of mans wit, and therefore ſºle at- tempt the doing of it. - | Exit, Deſ. Where ſhould I loſe that handkerchief Emiliia P. - Ein. I know not Madam. - * Peſ. Believe me, I had rather loſe my purſe Full of Cruſadoes ; and but my noble Moor, Is true of mind, and made of no ſuch baſeneſs, Asjealous creatures are, it were enough - To put him to ill thinking, - Em. Is he not jealous 2. - Deſ Who he? I think the Sun where he was born; Drew all ſuch humors from him. [Enter Othello, Em. Look where he comes. - Deſ. I will not leave him now. - Till Caſio be call'd to him ; how is it with you my Lord 9th, Well my good Lady Ohardneſs to diſſemble











This page contains an image.
Page 46

46 How do you Deſdemona º Deſ Well, my good Lord. Oth. Give me your hand, this hand is moiſt my Lady, Deſ. It yet has felt no age, nor known no ſorrow. Oth. This argues fruitfulneſs and liberal heart, Hot, hot, and moiſt, this hand of yours requires A ſequeſter from liberty: faſting and praying, Much caſtigation, exerciſe devout ; For here’s a young aud ſweating devil here, That commonly rebels: 'tis a good hand, A frank one. Dºſ You may indeed ſay ſo. For 'twas that hand that gave away my heart. Oth. Aliberal hand, the hearts of old gave hands, But our new heraldry is hands, not hearts, Deſ. I cannot ſpeak of this; come now your promiſe. Oth. What promiſe chuck? Deſ. I have ſent to bid Caſio come ſpeak with you. Oth. I have a ſalt and ſullen rhume offends me, Lend me thy handkerchief. Deſ. Here my Lord. Oth. That which I gave you. Peſ. I have it not about me. Oth. Not. Deſ. No indeed my Lord. Oth. That’s a fault: that handkerchief Did an Egyptian to my mother give, She was a Charmer, and could almoſt read The thoughts of people; ſhe told her while ſhe kept it. *Twould make her amiable and ſubdue my father Intirely to her love: But if ſhe loſt it. Or made a gift of it, my fatherseye Should hold her loathed, and his ſpirit ſhould hunt After new fancies: She dying gave it me, And bid me, when my fate would have me wive. To give it her; I did ſo, and take heed on t. Make it a darling like your precious eye. To loſe, or giv't away, were ſuch perdition, As nothing elſe could match. - Deſ. Isºt poſſible 2 Oth. 'Tis true, there’s magick in the web of it, A Sybel that had numbred in the world, The Sun to courſe two hundred compaſſes, In her prophetick fury, ſowed the work: The worms were hallowed that did breed the ſilk, And it was died in Mummy, which the skilful C oncerve of Maidens hearts.







This page contains an image.
Page 47

the Moor of Venice. Def Indeed, isºt true Oth. Moſt veritable, therefore look toºt well. Deſ. Then would to God that I had never ſeen it. Qib, Ha, wherefore? - - Deſ: Why do you ſpeak ſo ſtartingly and raſh? Oh, I’ſ loſt 2 iſ gone? ſpeak, is it out oth way 2. Deſ Bleſs us. 9th. Say you? Deſ. It is not loſt, but what and if it were? Oth. Ha. Deſ I ſay it is not loſt. Oth. Fetcht, let me ſee it, Deſ: Why ſo I can Sir, but I will not now, This is a trick, to put me from my ſuit, I pray let Caſio be receiv'd again. Oth. Fetch me that handkerchief, my mind miſgives. Deſ Come, come, you’lnever meet a more ſufficient man. Oth. The handkerchief. - Deſ. A man, that all his time Hath founded his good fortunes on your love, Sharºd dangers with you. Oth. The handkerchief. Deſ. In ſooth you are to blame. Oth. Away. E., Em, is not this man jealous? Deſ I mere ſaw this before: Sure ther's ſome wonder in this handkerchief, I am moſt unhappy in the loſs of it. Enter Jago and Caſſio. Em, 'Tis not a year or two ſhews us a man, They are alkbut ſtomachs, and we all but foods. They eat us hungerly, and when they are full, They belch us; look you, Caſio and my husband. fag. There is no other way, 'tis ſhe muſt do its And to the happineſs, go, and importune her. - Deſ. How now good Caſio, what’s the news with you? Caſº Madam, my former ſuit: I do beſeech you, That by your vertuous means, I may again, Exiſt, and be a member of his love, Whom I, with all the office of my heart, Intirely honour, I would not be delayed : If my offence be of ſuch mortal kind. That not my ſervice paſt nor preſentſorrows. Nor purpos'd merit in futurity, Can ranſom me into his love again º

This page contains an image.
Page 48

as o T H E L L 0. | - Then for my ſelf I dare, let that ſuffice you. Made demonſtrable here in Cypreſſ to him, was (unhandſome warrier as I am) And he's indited falſly. - And no conception, nor no jealous toy Concerning you, Deſ Alas the day, I never gave him cauſe. ºn. But jealous ſouls will not be anſwered ſo, lºy are not ever jealous for the cauſe, ºut jealous for they are jealous: 'tis a monſter - E got upon itſelf, born on itſelf - But to know ſo, muſt be my benefit, - So ſhall I cloath me in a forc’d content, And ſhut my ſelf up in ſome other courſe, To fortunes alºnes. - - Déſ Alas thrice gentle Caſio, - - - My advocation is not now in tune; - - - My Lord is not my Lord, nor ſhould I know him, Were he in favour as in humor alter’d : So help me, every ſpirit ſančified, As I have ſpoken for you all my beſt, - - - - - - And ſtood within the blank of his diſpleaſure, For my free ſpeech you muſt a while be patient, - - What I can do I will, and more I will - fag. Is my Lord angry 2 Em. He went hence but now, And certainly in ſtrange unquietneſs. - fºg. Can he be angry I have ſeen the Cannon, When it hath blown his ranks into the air; - And like the devil from his very arm, Puft his own brother, and can he be angry 2 Something of moment then : I will go meet him, There's matter in't indeed, if he be angry. - Dºſ I prethee do ſo; ſomething ſure of State, Either from Venice, or ſome unhatcht practice, Hith padled his clear ſpirit, and in ſuch caſes, Mens natures wrangle with inferiour things, Tho great ones are the object. 'Tis even ſo for let our finger ake. And it endues our other healthful members. Even to that ſenſe of pain; nay, we muſt think. Men are not gods, - Nor of them look for ſuch obſervances As its the Briſal : Beſhrew me much Emilia, Arraigning his unkindneſs with my ſoul; - ºut now I find, I had ſubborn'd the witneſs, - - - - ºn. Pray heaven it be State matters as youthink,



This page contains an image.
Page 49

the Moor of Venice. 49 Dºſ Heaven keep that monſter from Othelºr mind. Em. Lady, Amen. - peſ. I will go ſeek him, Caſio walk here about. If I do find him fit, I’le move your ſuit, Exetent Deſd. And ſeek to affect it to my uttermoſt. and Emillia. Caſ. I humbly thank your Ladiſhip. Enter Bianca. Bian. Save you friend Caſio. Caſ. What make you from home? How is it with you my moſt fair Bianca” Indeed ſweet love I was coming to your houſe. Bia. And I was going to your lodging Caſio; What keepa week away? ſeven days and nights, Eightſcore eight hours, and lovers abſent hours. More tedious then the dial, eightſcore times, - O weary reckoning! - Caſ. Pardon me Bianca, - I have this while with leaden thoughts been preſt, - But I ſhall in a more continuate time, º Strike off this ſcore of abſence: ſweet Bianca, - Take me this work out, - Bia, Oh Caſio, whence came this? This is ſome token from a newer friend To the felt abſence, now I feel a cauſe, Is’t come to this? well, well. Caſ, Goto woman, Throw your vilegheſſes in the devils teeth, From whence you have them, you are jealous now, That this is from ſome Miſtreſs, ſome remembrance, No in good troth Bianca. - Bia. Why, whoſe is it 2 Caſ. I know not ſweet, I found it in my chamber. I like the workwell, ereit be demanded, As like enough, it will I’de have it coppied, Take it and doºt and leave me for this time - - Bia. Leave you, wherefore? Caſº I do attend here on the General, And think it no addition, nor my wiſh. To have him ſee me woman'd. Bia. Why I pray you ? Caſ Not that I love you not. Bia. But that you do not loveme: ſpray you bring me on the way a little, And ſay, if I ſhall ſee you ſoon at night. Caſ: "Tis but a little way that I can bring you, For lattend here, but Pleſee you ſoon. bia, 'Tis very good, I muſt be circumſtanc'd. Extºnſ. H

























This page contains an image.

End of Section 7. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 8
Page 50

50 0 1 H E L L 0. Actus Quartus. Scoºna prima. - Enter Jago and Othello. - j. W ſillyº thinkº jag - Oth. Think ſo fagº. jag. What, to kiſsin private 2. Oth. An unauthorizºd kiſs. jag. Or to be naked with her friend abed, An hour, or more, not meaning any harm 2 Oth. Naked abed jago, and not mean harm * It is hypocriſie againſt the devil: They that mean:vertuouſly, and yet do ſo, The devil their vertue tempts, and they tempt heaven. jag. So they do nothing 'tis a venial ſlip; But if I give my wife a handkerchief. Oth. What then? - jag. Why then 'tis hers my Lord, and being hers, She may, I think, beſtow't on any man. Oth. She is protećtreſs of her honour too, May ſhe give that? - jag. Her honour is an eſſence that’s not ſeen, They have it very oft, that have it not: But for the handkerchief. Oth. By heaven I would moſt gladly have forgot it Thou ſaidſ (Oit comes o're my memory, - As doth the Raven o're the infected houſe, Boding to all) he had my handkerchief. fag. What of that - 9th. That’s not ſo good now. jag. What if I had ſaid I had ſeen him do you wrong? Of heard him ſay, (as knaves be ſuch abroad. who having by their own importunate ſuite, Or voluntary dotage of ſome Miſtris, - - Conjured, or ſupplied them, cannot chuſe, But they ºnuſt blab.) - Oth, Hath he ſaid anything? - fag. He hath my Lord, but beyouwell affºrd, | No more then he’l unſwear, - Oth. What hath he ſaid jag. Why that he did— know not what he did. Qºh, What? - - jag. Lye, - | - Oth. |

This page contains an image.
Page 51

the Moor of Venice. - 5. Oth. With 2 jag. With her, on her, what you will. - . . Oh, Lie with her, lie on her? We ſay lie on her when they bely her; lye with her, that’s fulfome, handkerchiefs, confeſſion, handkerchiefs: to confeſs, and be hang'd for his labour, firſt to be hang'd, and then to confeſs; I tremble at it Nature would not inveſt her ſelfin ſuch ſhadowing paſſion, without ſome in- ſtruction: It is not words that ſhakes methus, (piſh) noſes, ears, lips: 1st poſ- ſible 2 confeſs 2 handkerchief? O devil. Fallſ in a trance. - jag. Work on my medicine, work; thus credulous fools are caught, and ma- ny worthy and chaſt Dames, even thus (all guiltleſs) meet reproach: What ho my Lord, my Lord I ſay, Othello, -how now Caſio & Enter Caſſio. Caſ: What's the matter . jag. My Lord is fallen into an Epilepſy, This is his ſecond fit, he had one yeſterday. Caſ, Rub him about the temples. fag. No, forbear The Lethargy muſt have his quiet courſe, If not, he foams at mouth, and by and by Breaks out to ſavage madneſs: look, he ſtirs : Do you withdraw your ſelf a little while, He will recover ſtraight 5 when he is gone, I would on great occaſion ſpeak with you. How is it General, have you not hurt your head 0%. Doſt thou mock me? Exit Caſ fag. I mock you, no by heaven, Would you would bear your fortunes like a man. Oth. A horned man’s amonſter, and a beaſt. jag. There's many a beaſt then in a populous City, And many a civil monſter. - - Oth. Did he confeſs? fag. Good Sir beaman, - Think every bearded fellow, that’s but yoak'd. May draw with you, there’s millions now alive, That nightly lye in thoſe improper beds. Which they dare ſwear peculiar: your caſe is better: Q is the ſpite of hell, the fiends arch mock. To lipa wanton in a ſecure Couch, And to ſuppoſe her chaſt: No, let me know, And knowing what I am, I know what ſhe ſhall be Oth. Othou artwiſe, 'tis certain. - jag. Stand you a while apart. Confine your ſelf but in a patient liſt: Whilſt you were here orewhelmed with your grief (A paſſion moſt unfitting ſuch a man.) H 2. - Caſ

This page contains an image.
Page 52

52 - O T H E. L L 0. - Cºffo cam hither, I ſhifted him away. And layed good ſcuſeupon your extaſy ; Bad him anon retire, and here ſpeak with me, The which he promisºd: But incave your ſelf, And mark the jears, the gibes, and notable ſcorns. That dwell in every region of his face; For I will make him tell the tale anew, Where, how, how oft; how long ago, and when, He has, and is again to cope your wife: - I ſay, but mark his geſture, marry patience, Or I ſhall ſay, you are all in all, in ſpleen, And nothing of a man. 0th. Doſt thou hear jago. - I will be found moſt cunning in my patience; But doſ; thou hear, moſt bloody. jag. That's not amiſs: But yet keep time in all: will you withdraw Now will I queſtion Caſio of Bianca; A huſwife, that by ſelling her deſires, Buys her ſelf bread and coaths; it is a creature, That dotes on Caſa ; as 'tis the ſtrumpets plague To beguile many, and be beguil’d by one: Enter Caſ He, when he hears of her, cannot refrain - From the exceſs of laughter: here he comes: As he ſhall ſmile Othello ſhall go mad, And his unbookiſh jealoufie muſt conſter Poor Caſio’s ſmiles, geſtures, and light behaviour, Quite in the wrong: How do you now Lievtenant º Caſ The worſer that you give me the addition, Whoſe want even kills me. . jag. Ply. Deſdemona well, and you are ſure on tº Now, if this ſuit lay in Bianca'ſ power. How quickly ſhould you ſpeed. Caſ Alas poor cative. - Oth. Look how he laughs already. fºg. I never knew a woman love man ſo. Caſ Alas poor rogue, I think indeed ſhe loves mes. Oth. Now he denies it faintly, and laughs it out, jag. Do you hear Caſio 2 Oth. Now he importunes him to tellitons Go to, well ſaid. jag. She gives it out that you ſhall marry her, Do you intend it * Caſ Ha, ha, ha. - Oth, Do you triumph Roman, do you triumph” Gaſ I marry her what? a Cuſtomer I prethee bear ſome charity to my wit, Do |



This page contains an image.
Page 53

* - the Moore of ſenice. Do not think it ſo unwholſome :, ha, ha, ha. Oth. So, to ſo, ſo, they laugh that wins. jag. Why, the cry goes, that you ſhall marry her, Cºſ. Prethce ſay true. - - jag. I am a very villain elſe. Oth. Ha you ſcoard me well. ... Caſ. This is the monkies own giving out; ſhe is perſwaded I will marry her, out of her own love and flattery, not out of my promiſe. Oth, jago beckons me, now he begins the ſtory. Caſ. She was here even now, ſhe haunts me in every place, I was tother day talking on the ſea bank with certain Venetianſ, and thither comes this bau- ble, falls me thus about my neck. Oth. Crying, O dear Caſiº, as it were : his geſture imports it. - Cºf Sohangs and jolls, and weeps upon me, ſo hales and pulls me.hahaha. Oth. Now he tells how ſhe pluck him to my Chamber ; - I ſee that noſe of yours, but not that dog. I ſhall throw’t to. 5 s Caſ. Well, I muſt leave her company: Enter Bianca. Before me, look where ſhe comes. * - Tis ſuch another Fitchew; marry a perfum'done: What do you mean by this haunting of ºne - . - Biaº, Let the devil and his dam haunt you; what did you mean by that ſame handkerchief you gave me even now I was a fine fool to take it; I muſt take out the work a likely piece of work, that you ſhould find it in your cham- ber, and not know who left it there: this is ſome minxes token, and I muſt take out the work; there, give it the hobby-horſe; wherefoever you had it, I’le take out no work on tº - - - Gaſ. How now my ſweet Bianca, how now, how now? 9th. By heaven that ſhould be my handkerchief. - - Bia. An you'll come to ſupper to night, you may, anyou will not, come when you are next prepard for - Exit. jag. After her, after her. ºf muſt ſhºt ºf ºne area alſº jag. You ſup there. Caſ: Yes, I intend ſo, . - - - fºg. Well. I may chance to ſee you, for would very ſain ſpeak with Olle - - gaſ. Prethee come, will you? 9th. How ſhall I murder him jagº fag. Did you perceive, how he laughed at his vice Oth, Ojago. - - - jag. And did you ſee the handkerchief Oth. Was that mine - - would have him nine years a killing; a fine woman, a fair woman, a ſweet WOſſian. - - - fag. Nay, you muſt forget that - - 9th And let her rot and periſh, and be damnºd to night, for ſhe ſhall not - H 3 - live jag. Go to ſay no more - - Exi, Caſſic. -



This page contains an image.
Page 54

- 5. - live; no, my heart is turn'd to a ſtone; I ſtrike it, and it hurts my hand: O the world has not a ſweater creature, ſhe might lie by an Emperors ſide, and com- mand him tasks. - jag Nay, that's not your way. Oth. Hang her, I do not ſay what ſhe is: So delicate with her neadle, an admirable Muſitian ; O ſhe will ſing the ſavageneſs out of a Bears of ſo high and plentious wit and invention. jag. She's the worſe for all this. - - Orb. A thouſand thouſand times: and then of ſo gentle a condition. jag. I, too gentle. - - Oth. Nay that’s certain, but yet the pity of it fago, oh the pity. - jag. If you be ſo fond over her iniquity, give her patent to offend, for if it touches not you, it comes near no body. - Oth. I will chop her in meſſes—cuckold me! fag. O, 'tis foulin her. Oth. With mine Officer. jag. That’s fouler. - - - Oth. Get me ſome poiſon jago, this night IIe not expoſtulate with her, leſ: her body and beauty unprovide my mind agen, this night jago. jag. Do it not with poyſon, ſtrangle her in her bed, even the bed ſhe hath contaminated. Oth. Good, good, the juſtice of it pleaſes, very good. - fag. And for Caſio, let me be his undertaker: you ſhall hear more by midnight. - - A Trumpet. Enter Lodovico, Deſdemona, and Attendants. Oth. Excellent good: What Trumpet is that ſame * jag. Something from Venice ſure ; ºtis Lodovico Come from the Duke, and ſee, your wife is with him. Lod. Save you worthy General. Oth. With all my heart Sir. Lod. The Duke and Senators of Penice greet you. Oth. I kiſs the inſtrument of their pleaſures. Deſ. And what’s the news good couſen Lodovico? fag. I am very glad to ſee you Seignior – Welcome to Cyprus. - - Lod. I thank you, how does Lieutenant Caſº fºg. Lives Sir. - - Deſ Couſen, there's fallen between him and my Lord, ºn unkind breach, but you ſhallmake all well. Oth. Are you ſure of that? - Deſ My Lord. Oth. This fail you not to do, as you will— Lod. He did not call, he’s buſie in the paper : ºthere Diviſion 'twixt my Lord and Caſº pſ.







This page contains an image.
Page 55

the Moor of Venice. pºſ. A moſt unhappy one, I would do much to attone them, for the love I bear to Caſio. Oth. Fire and Brimſtone. Deſ My Lord. Oth. Are you wiſe? Deſ: What, is he angry Lod. May be the letter mov’d him; For as I think they do command him home, Deputing Caſio in his government. Deſ: Truſt me, I am glad on t. Oth. Indeed, - Deſ My Lord. - Oh, I am glad to ſee you mad. Deſ. How ſweet Othello? Oth. Devil. Deſ: I have not deſerv'd this. - Loº. My Lord, this would not be believ’d in Venice. Tho I ſhould ſwear I ſaw’t : 'tis very much, - Make her amends, ſhe weeps. - Oth, O Devil, Devil. - If that the earth could teem with womens tears. Each drop ſhe falls would prove a Crocadile: Out of my fight. Deſ. I will not ſtay to offend you. Lod. Truly an obedient Lady : I do beſeech your Lordſhip, call her back. Oth, Miſtreſs. - Deſ My Lord. - Oth. What would you with her Sir Lod. Who I my Lord 2 - Oth. I, you did wiſh that I would make her turn: Sir ſhe can turn, and turn, and yet goon, And turn again, and ſhe can weep Sir, weeps And ſhee's obedient, as you ſay obedient, Very obedient, proceed youin your tears, Concerning this Sir O well painted paſſion: I am commanded home get you away. I’le ſend for you anon: –Sir I obey the Mandat, And will returne to Venice —hence avant, Caſio ſhall have my place; and Sir to night I do intreat that we may ſup together. You are welcome Sir to Cyprus, goats and monkies, Lod. Is this the noble Moor, whom our full Senate. Call all in all ſufficient This the noble nature, Whom paſſion could not ſhake? Whoſe ſolid vertue, The ſhot of accident, nor dart of chance. Could neither graze nor pierce 55. jug,

This page contains an image.
Page 56

* 56 O T H E L L 0. - fºg. He is much changed. - Lºd. Are his wits ſafe 2 is he not light of brain? jag. He's that he is, I may not breath my cenſure, What he might be, if what he might be, he is not, I would to heaven he were. Lod. What, ſtrike his Wife fºg. Faith that was not ſo well; yet would I knew That ſtroak would prove the worſt. Lod. Is it his uſe 2 Or did the letters work upon his blood, And new create this fault - jag. Alas, alas: It is not honeſty in me to ſpeak What I have ſeen and known; you ſhall obſerve And his own courſes will denote him ſo, That I may ſave my ſpeech: do but go after him, And marke how he continues. - Lod. I am ſorry that I am deceiv'd in him Excº. Enter. Othello and Emillia. Cº. You have ſeen nothing then. ºm. No ever heard, nor ever did ſuſpect. ºth. Yes, and you have ſeen Caſio and ſhe together. £m. But then I ſaw no harm, and then I heard ºach ſyllable that breath made up between em. Oth. What, did they never whiſper? Em, Never, my Lord. 0th. Nor ſend you out o'the way Em, Never. - - Oth. To fetch her Fan, her Mask her Gloves not nothing. Em, Never, my Lord. Oth. That’s ſtrange. - Em. I durſt my Lord, to wager ſhe is honeſt. Lay down my ſoul at ſtake: if you think other, Remove your thought, it doth abuſe your boſome ºf any wretch ha put this in your head, - Let heaven require it with the Serpents curſe, For if ſhe be not honeſt, chaſt, and true. There's no manhappy, the pureſt of their wives, is foul as ſlander. Exit Emillia. Oth. Bid her come hither, go, - She ſays enough, yet ſhe’s a ſimple Bawd. That cannot ſay as much: this is a ſubtle Whore, A cloſet, lock and key, of villanous ſecrets, And yet ſhee'lkneeland pray, I ha ſeen her dot. Enter

This page contains an image.
Page 57

the Moor of Venice. Enter Deſdemona and Emilia. Deſ My Lord, what is your will 2 Oth. Pray chuck come hither. Deſ. What is your pleaſure ? Oth. Let me ſee your eyes—look in my face. Deſ: What horrible fancy’s this? Oth. Some of your function Miſtreſs, Leave procreantsalone, and ſhut the door, Coff, or cry hem, if any body come, Your Miſtreſs, your Miſtreſs; nay diſpatch. Dºſ upon my knees, What does your ſpeech import? I underſtand a fury in your words, But not the words. Oth. Why, what art thou? Deſ. Your wife my Lord, your true and loyal wife. Oth. Come, ſwear it, dam thy ſelf, Left being like one of heaven, the devils themſelves Should fear to ſeize thee, therefore be double damn'd : Swear thou art honeſt. Deſ. Heavendoth truly know it. Oth. Heaven truly knows, that thou art falſe as hell. Deſ. To whom, my Lord, with whom how am I falſe? Oth. O Deſdemona, away, away, away. Deſ. Alas the heavy day, why do you weep? Am I the occaſion of thoſe tears my Lord * If haply you my father do ſuſpect, An inſtrument of this your calling back, Lay not your blameon me; if you have loſt him, Why I have loſt him too. Oth. Had it pleas'd heaven To try me with afflićtion, had he rain’d All kinds of ſores, and ſhames on my bare head, Steep'd me in poverty to the very lips, Given to captivity, me and my hopes, ſhould have found in ſome part of my ſoul A drop of patience; but alas to make me A fixed figure, for the time of ſcorn, To point his ſlow unmoving finger at-oh, oh, Yet could I bear that too, well, very well. But there, where I have garner'd up my heart, Where either I muſt live, or bear no life, The fountain from the which my currant runs. Or elſe drives up, to be diſcarded thence, Or keep it as a Ceſtern, from foul Toads Toknot and genderin: turn thy complexion there. I - 57 Patience

This page contains an image.
Page 58

58 0 T H E L L 0. Patience thy young and roſe-lip’d Cherubin, I here look grim as hell. . Deſ. I hope my noble Lord eſteems me honeſt. Oth. O I, as ſummers flies are in the ſhambles, That quicken cwen with blowing: O thou black weed, why art ſo lovely fair º Thou ſmell’ſ ſo ſweet, that the ſence akes at thee, Would thou hadſtºne're been born. - - Deſ. Alas, what ignorant fin have I committed? Oth. Was this fair paper, this moſt goodly book, Made to write whoreupon?—What committed? Committed: Oh thou publick Commoner; I ſhould make very forges of my cheeks, That would to cinders burn up modeſty, Did I but ſpeak thy deeds: what committed 2 Heaven ſtops the noſe at it, and the Moon winks; The bawdy wind that kiſſes all it meets, is huſht within the hallow Mine of earth, - And will not heart:-what committed,—impudent ſtrumpet; Deſ. By heaven you do me wrong. Oth. Are not you a ſtrumpet? Deſ: No, as I am a Chriſtian: ºf to preſerve this veſſel for my Lord, From any other foul unlawful touch, Be not to be a ſtrumpet, I am none. Oth. What, not a where? Deſ. No, as I ſhall be ſaved. Oth. Isºt poſſible 2. Deſ Oheaven forgive us. Oth, I cry you mercy then, That married with 9thºllo: You miſtreſs, That have the office oppoſite to St. Peter, And keeps the gates in hell; you, you, I you 5. We hadone our courſe; there’s money for your pains; I pray you turn the key, and keep our counſel Eºf, Em, Alas, what does this Gentleman conceive: How do you Madam? how do you my good Lady: Deſ. Faith half a ſleep, - Em, Good Madam, what’s the matter with my Lord ** Deſ. With who º Em, Why, with my Lord Madam. Deſ Who is thy Lord P. Em. He that is yours, ſweet Lady. - Dºſ 1 ha none, do not talk to me Emiliº. ſcannot weep, nor anſwer have bone, ºut what ſhould go by water prºthee to night: I took you for that cunning whore of Venice ºr Emilia.











This page contains an image.
Page 59

the Moor of ºemice. Lay on my bed my weddingſheets, remember, And callthy husband hither. - Em. Here is a change indeed. Exit. Deſ: 'Tis meet I ſhould be uſ"d ſo, very meet, How have I been behav'd, that he might ſtick The ſmall'ſ opinion onmy leaſt miſuſe. Enter Jago jag. What is your pleaſure Madam? and Emillia. How isºt with you? Deſ; I cannot tell, thoſe that doteach young babes, Do it with gentle means, and eaſie taskes; He might ha chid me ſo, for in good faith, I am a child to chiding. jag. What is the matter Lady? Ém. Alas jago, my Lord hath ſo bewhor'd her. Thrown ſuch deſpite, and heavy tearms upon her As true hearts cannot bear. - Deſ: Am I that name fago? jag. What name fair Lady ? Deſ. Such as ſhe ſays my Lord did ſay I was. Em. He call’d her whore; a beggar in his drink Could not have laid ſuch tearms upon his Callet. jag. Why did he ſo? - Deſ. I do not know, I am ſure I am none ſuch. jag. Do not weep, do not weep: alas the day. Em. Has ſhe forſook ſo many noble matches, Her Father, and her Country, and her Friends, To be call’d whore ? would it not make one weep? Deſ. It is my wretched fortune. jag. Beſhrew him for it; how comesthis trick upon him? Deſ. Nay, heavendoth know. Em, I will be hang'd, if ſome eternal villain, Some buſie and infinuating rogue, Some cogging, couſening ſlave, to get ſome office, Have not devis’d this ſlander ſºle be hang'd elſe. fag. Fiethere is no ſuch man, it is impoſſible. Deſ: If any ſuch there are heaven pardon him. Em. A halter pardon him, and hell gnaw his bones: Why ſhould he call her whore? who keeps her company What place, what time, what form, what likelihood? The Moor's abus’d by ſome moſt villanous knave. Some baſe notorious knave, ſome ſcurvy fellow ; O heaven, that ſuch companions thoudſ; unfold, And put in every honeſt hand a whip, To laſh the raſcal naked through the world. Even from the eaſt toºth weſt. jag. Speak within doors. Em, O fieupon him; ſome ſuch Squire he was, - a







This page contains an image.
Page 60

66 0 T H E L L 0. That turnd your wit, the ſeamy ſide without, And his unkindneſs may defeat my life, Not the worlds maſs of vanity could make me. - And he doeschide with you. Hark how theſe Inſtruments ſummon you to ſupper. And made you to ſuſpect me with the Moor. fag. You are a fool, go to. Dºſ! O good jago, What ſhall I do to win my Lord again? Good friend go to him, for by this light of heaven, I know not how I loſt him. - Here I kneel: * Ifere my will did treſpaſs gainſt his love, Either in diſcourſe, or thought, or actual deed, Or that mine eyes, mine ears, or any ſence, Delighted them in any otherform; Or that I do not yet, and ever did, And ever will (though he do ſhakeme off To beggerly divorcement,) love him deerly : Comfort forſwear me; undindneſs may do much- But nevertaint my love, I cannot ſay whore, It doth abhor me, now I ſpeak the word, To do the aët, that might th'addition earn, fag. I pray you be content, 'tis but his humour, The buſineſs of the State does him offence, Deſ. If 'twere no other. - jag. Tis but ſo, I warrant you: The meat, great Meſſengers of Venice ſtay 3 Goin, and weep not, all things ſhall be well. Exit woman. How now Roderigo 2. - - Enter Roderigo. Rod. I do not find that thou deal’ſ juſtly with me. jag. What in the contrary? Rºl. Every day thou doſeſt me with ſome device jagº; and rather as it ſeems to me now, keepſ from me all conveniency, then ſupplieſ: me with the eaſt advantage of hope; I will indeed no longer indure it, not am I yet per- ſwaded to put up in peace, what already I have fooliſhly ſuffered. fag. Will you hear me Roderigº º Rod Sir I have heard too much, For your words and performance, Are no kin together. - jag. You charge memoſt unjuſtly, Rºl. With nought but truth: I have waſted my ſelf out of means; the jewels you have had from me, to deliver to Deſdemº would half. have Coº rupted a Votariſt: you have told me the has receiv'd em, and return'd me expectation, and comforts of ſudden reſpect and acquaintance, but I find monº- fºg. Well, gº o, very well. -





This page contains an image.
Page 61

- - - ºr - - - - the Moore of Venice. 6 Rod. Very well, goto, I cannot go to (man) not 'tis not very well; I ſay: *tis very ſcurvy, and begin to find my ſelf foptin it. - fag. Very well. - - - " - Rod. I ſay it is not very well: I will make myſelf known to Deſdemona if ſhe will return me my Jewels, I will give over my ſuit, and repelt my un- lawful ſolicitation, if not, aſſure your ſelf, I'le ſeek ſatisfaction of you. jag. You have ſaid now. - Rod. I, and ſaid nothing, but what I proteſt entendment of doing, - ag. Why now I ſee there's mettle in thee, and even from this inſtant, do build on thee a better opinion then ever before ; give me thy hand Roderigo: Thou haſt taken againſt me a moſt juſt conception, but yet I proteſt, I have dealt moſt directly in thy affair. - - Rod. It hath not appeared. . . . . - fag. I grant indeed it hath not appeard and your ſuſpition is not without wit and judgment. But Rodrigº, if thouhaſ that within thee indeed, which have greater reaſon to believe now, then ever, I mean, purpoſe, courage, and valour; this night ſhew it; if thou the next night following enjoyeſ: not Pºſ- demona, take me from this world with treachery, and deviſe engines for my life. Rod. Well, is it within reaſon and compaſs? jag, Sir, there is ſpecial commiſſion come from Venice, To depute Caſio in Othellº Place. Rod. Is that true? why then Othello and Deſdemona Return again to Venice. - fºg, Qing, he goes into Mauritania, and takes away with him - The fair Deſdemona, unleſs his abode be linger'd - - Here by ſome accident, wherein none can be ſo determinate, As the removing of Caſio. Kod. How do you mean removing of him? jag. Why, by making him uncapable of Obello's place, Knocking out his brains, - Rod, And that you would have me to do. jag I, and if you dare do your ſelf a profit and right; he ſups to night with a halotry, and thither will I go to him; he knows not yet of his honourable fortune: if you will watch his going thence, which I will faſhion to fall out between twelve and one, you may take him at your pleaſure: I will be neer to ſecond your attempt, and he ſhall fall between us; come, ſtand not amaz'd at it, but go along with me.I will ſhew you ſuch a neceſſity in his death, that you ſhall think your ſelf bound to put it on him. It is now high ſupper time, and the night grows to waſt; about it. Kºd, I will hearfurther reaſon for this, - jag. And you ſhall be ſatisfied. Exeºni, Enter Othello, Deſdemona, Lodovico, Emilia, - - and Attendantſ. - Lod. I do beſeech you Sir, trouble your ſelf no further. - 9th, O pardon me, it ſhall do me good to walk. Lºſ

This page contains an image.
Page 62

H E L L 0. Lod. Madam, good night, I humbly thank your Ladiſhip. Deſ Your Honour is moſt welcome. - Oth Will you walk Sir:-O Deſdemona. Deſ: My Lord. - - Oth, Get you to bedo the inſtant, I will be return'd, forthwith diſpatch your Attendant there.-look it be done. - Exeant. Deſ. I will my Lord. Em. How does it now 2 he looks gentler then he did. Deſ. He ſays he will returnincontinent: - He hath commanded me to go to bed, And bad me to diſmiſs you. Em. Diſmiſs me? - - - Dºſ. It was his bidding, therefore good Emillia, Give me my nightly wearing, and adieu, - We muſt not now diſpleaſe him. - Em, Would you had neverſeen him. Deſ. So would not I, my lovedoth ſo approve him, That even his ſtubbornneſs, his checks and frowns, (Prethee unpin me) have grace and favour in them. Em. I have laid thoſe ſheets you bad me on the bed. Deſ. All's one, good father; how fooliſh are our minds; If I do die before thee, prethee ſhrowd me In one of thoſe ſame ſheets. Em. Come,come, you talk. Deſ My mother had a Maid call'd Barbary, She was in love, and he ſhe lov’d prov’d mad, And did forſake her ; ſhe had a ſong of willow, - An old thing 'twas, but it expreſt her fortune, And ſhe died ſinging it; that ſong to night Will not go from my mind: I have much to do; - - - But to go hang my head all at one ſide, and ſing it like poor Barbary prethee. diſpatch. - . Shall I go fetch your night-gown - Deſ: No, unpin me here. - - This Lodovico is a proper man. - Eºn. A very handſome man. Deſ. He ſpeaks well. - ºn. I know a Lady in Venice, would have walkºdbarefooted to Paleſtine for a touch of his neither lip. - Deſdemona ſing: The pºor ſºul ſº ſighing by a ficamour tree ſing all a green willow. - - Her hand on her boſºme, her head on her knee, ſing willow, willº, willow:













This page contains an image.
Page 63

| I might as well do it in the dark. For the whole world. - If wives do fall: (ſay that they ſlack their duties. the Moor of Venice. 63 The freſh ſtreams ran by her, and murmur'd hermoanſ, ſing willºw, willºw, willow, Her ſalt tears fell from her, which ſoftned the ſtoneſ, ſing willom, ºc, (Lay by theſe.) willow, willow. (Prethee hie thee, he'ſ come anon.) Sing all agreen willow muſt be my garland. Let nobody blame him, his ſcorn. I approve: (Nay, that’s not next; hark, who's that knocks?) Em, 'Tis the wind. Deſ; Icall'd my Love falſe, but what ſaid he then * ſing willow, willow, willow, If Icourt mowomen, you'l couch with momen. So, get thee gone, good night, mine eyes do itch, Does that boad weeping 2 - Em, 'Tis neither here northere. - Deſ. I have heard it ſaid ſo. Otheſe men, theſe men: Doſt thou in conſcience think (tell me Emillia,) That there be women do abuſe their husbands In ſuch groſs kinds 2. - Em. There be ſome ſuch no queſtion. Deſ. Wouldſ thou do ſuch a thing, for all the world? . Em. Why, would not you? - Deſ. No, by this heavenly light, Em, Nor I neither, by this heavenly light, Dºſ Wouldſ thou do ſuch a deed, for all the world? Em, The world is a huge thing, it is a great price For a ſmall vice. - Deſ. In troth.I think thou wouldſt not. Em. In troth I think I ſhould, and undo't when I had done it, marry I. would not do ſuch a thing for a joynt-ring, or for meaſures of Lawn, nor for Gowns, Petticots, or Caps, nor any petty exibition; but for the whole world : why who would not make her husband a Cuckold to make him a Monarch? I ſhould venter purgatory for it. - Deſ. Beſhrew me, if I would do ſuch wrong Em, Why, the wrong is but a wrong ºth world; and having the would for . abour, 'tis a wrong in your own world, and you might quickly make it right. - - Deſ I do not think there is any ſuch woman. Em, Yes, a dozen, and as many to the vantage, as would ſtore the world. they played for. - - But I do think it is their husbands faults, And pour our treaſures into foreign laps, Cº.



This page contains an image.
Page 64

& O T H E L L. 'Tis but a mangon: forth my ſword, he dies. or elſe break out in peeviſh jealouſes, Throwing reſtraint upon us; or ſay they ſtrike us, Or ſcant our former having in diſpight,) Why we have galls, and though we have ſome grace, Yet have weſome revenge: Let husbands know Their wives have ſence like them; they ſee, and ſmell, And have their pallats both for ſweet and ſowre, As husbands have: what is it that they do, When they change us for others? is it ſport? I think it is ; and doth affection breed it? I think it doth; isºt frailty that thus errs 2 It is ſo too; and have not we affections Defires for ſport? and frailty as men have 2 Then let emuſeus well, elſe let emknow, The ills we do, their ills inſtruct us ſo. - Deſ: Good night, goodnight, heaven me ſuch uſes ſend, - Not to pick bad from bad, but by bad mend. Exetent. Aétus Quintus, Scoena prima. - Enter Jago and Roderigo. fag. Hº ſtand behind this bulk, ſtrait will he come. Weare thy good Rapier bare, and put it home. Quick, quick, fear nothing, I’le be at thy elbow ; It makes us, or it marrs us, think of that, And fix more firm thy reſolution. Kod. Beneer at hand, I may miſcarry int. jag. Here at thy hand, be bold and take thy ſtand. Kod. I have no great devotion to the deed; And yet he has given me ſatisfying reaſons; jag. I have rub'd this young Quat almoſt to the ſenſe, And he grows angry, now, whether he kill Caſio, - Or Caſio him, or each do kill the other, - Every way makes my game; live Koderigo, He calls me to a reſtitution large, For Gold and jewels that I bob'd from him, As gifts to Deſdemona: It muſt not be, if Caſio do remain, He has a dayly beauty in his life, That makes me ugly: and beſides, the Moor May unfold me to him ; there ſtandſ in much peril.





This page contains an image.
Page 65

the Moor of Venice. No, he muſt die, betſo, I hear him coming. Enter Caſſio. Rod. I know his gate, 'tishes villain thou dieſt. caſ. That thruſt had been my enemy indeed, But that my coat is better than thou know’ſ I will make proof of thine. Rod, O, I am ſlain. Caſ: I am maim'd for ever, lightho, murder. Enter Othelio. Oth. The voice of Caſio, jago keeps his word. Rod, O villain that I am. Oth. Hark, 'tis even ſo. Caſ O helpho, light, a Surgeon. Oth. 'Tis he, O brave jago, honeſt and juſt, That haſ ſuch noble ſenſe of thy friends wrong, Thou teacheſt me;—minion, your Dearlies dead, And your unbleſ fate hies; ſtrumpet I comes Forth of my heart, thoſe charms thine eyes are blotted. Thy bed luſ ſtain'd, ſhall with luſts blood be ſpotted. Enter Lodovico and Gratiano. Caſ: What ho, no watch, no paſſage, murder, murder. Gra. 'Tis ſome miſchance, the cry is very direful. Caſ. O help. Lod. Hark. Rod, O wretched villain. - Lod. Two or three grones, it is a heavy nights Theſe may be counterfeits, let’s think’t unſafe To come into the cry without more help. Rod, Nobody come, then ſhall I bleed to death. Enter Jago with a light, Lod. Hark. - Gra. Here's one comes in his ſhirt, with lights and weapons. jag. Who's there? whoſe noiſe is this that cries out murder? Lod. I do not know. - jag. Did not you hear a cry? - Caſ Here, here, for heavens ſake help me. jag. What's the matter? - Gra. This is 0thello’ſ Antient as I take it. Lod. The ſameindeed, a very valiant fellow. ºfag. What are you here that cry ſo grievouſly K. Caſ



This page contains an image.
Page 66

& - s 0 T H E L L 0 Caſ: jago, oiam ſpoil'd, undone by villains, Give me ſome help. - fag, O me, Lieytenant, what villains have done this? . Caſ, I think the one of them is hereabout, º And cannot make away. - jag, O treacherous villains: - What are youthere? come in and give ſome help. - Rod. O help me here. - Caſ. That's one of em. - - * jag, O murderous ſlave, O villain. Thruſts him if - Rod, O damn'd jago, O inhuman dog-o, o, o. jag, Killmen ºth dark? where be thoſe bloody thieves? - How ſilent is this Town Ho, murder, murder : - What may you be are you of good or evil? - Lod. As you ſhall prove us, praiſe vs. - jag. Seignior Lodovico. - Tod. He Sir. - - jag. I cry you mercy: here's Caſſic hurt by villains. º Gra. Caſio. - - jag. How is it brother? Caſ. My leg is cut in two. jag, Marry heaven forbid? - light Gentlemen, I’le bindit with my ſhirt. Enter Bianca, - Bia. What is the matter ho, who isºt that cried ? jag. Who isºt that cried? Bia. Omydear Cºſio, O my ſweet Caſio, Caſio, Caſtº. fag O notable ſtrumpet: Caſio, may you ſuſpect Who they ſhould be that thus have mangled you ? Caſ' No. - Gra. I am ſorry to find you thus, I have bin to ſeek you. jag. Lend me a º ſo; ho for a chair to bear him eaſily hences Bia. Alas he faiºts; O Caſio, Cºſio, Caſio. jag. Gentlemen all. I do ſuſpect this Traſh - To bear a part in this injury patience awhile good Caſio; Come, come lend me a light: Know we this face, or no 2- Alas my friend, and my dear country-man: Rodergo ºn yes ſure: yes, ’tis Roderigo. Gra. What of Venice P. jag. Even he Sir, did you know him? Gra. Know him 2 ſ, jag. Signior Gratiano, I cry you gentle pardon- - | Theſe bloody accidents muſt excuſe my manners: that ſo neglected you. - - - Gra,



This page contains an image.

End of Section 8. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 9
Page 67

- the Moor of Venice. Gra. I am glad to ſee you. - jag. How do you Caſio 2 O, a chair, a chair. Gra. Koderigo - - jag. He, 'tis he: O that’s well ſaid, a chair; Some good man bare him carefully from hence, I’lefetch the Generals Surgeon: for you Miſtreſs, Save you your labour, he that lies ſlain here, (Caſſia,) Was my dear friend; what malice was betwixt you ? Caſ. None in the world, nor do I know the man. - jag. What, look you pale º O bear him out oth air. - Stay you good Gentlewoman, look you pale Miſtreſs 2 Do you perceive the geſtures of her eye * - Nay, an you ſtir, we ſhall have more anon: Behold her well I pray you, look upon her, | Do you ſee Gentlemen? nay guiltineſs - - - Will ſpeak, though tongues were out of uſe. Enter Emi. - Em. Las what’s the matter? what’s the matter husband? jag. Caſio has been ſet on in the dark, - By Roderigo, and fellows that are ſcapºt, - He's almoſt ſlain, and Roderigo dead. m. Alasgood Gentleman, alas good Caſio. jag. This is the fruit of whorings prithee Emilia. Go know of Caſio where he ſupt to night, What, do you ſhake at that? - Bia. He ſupt at my houſe, but I therefore ſhake not. fag O did he ſo, I charge you go with me. Em. Fieupon thee ſtrumpet. - Bia. I am no ſtrumpet, but of life as honeſt, As you, that abuſe me, Em. As I; now fieupon thee. fag. Kind Gentlemen, let’s go ſee poor Caſio dreſts Come Miſtreſs, you muſt tell's another tale. Emillia, run you to the Cittadel, - And tell my Lord and Lady what has hapt: Will you go on I pray this is the night, That either makes me, or ſoredoes me quite. Exeºnſ. - Enter. Othello wº, a º, and Deſdemons in her bed. 0th. It is the cauſe, it is the cauſe, my ſoul. Let menot name it to you, you chaſt ſtars: It is the cauſe, yet I’le not ſhed her blood, Nor ſcar that whiter skin of hers then ſnow, And ſmooth as monumentalalablaſters Yet ſhe muſt die, elſe ſhe'ſ betray more men. ºut out the light, and then putout the light: ºf Iquench thee, thou flaming Miniſter,











































K 2.

This page contains an image.
Page 68

68 0 T H E L L 0. I can again thy former light reſtore, Should I repºrt me; but once pueout thine, Thea cunningſt pattern of excelling nature, I know not where is that Prometian heat, That canthy light relumine: when I have pluckt the roſe, I cannot give it vital growth again, It muſt needs wither I’le ſmel it on the tree: kiſſes her. A balmy breath, that does almoſt perſwade Juſtice her ſelf to break her ſword: one more; Be thus when thou art dead, and I will kill thee, And love thee after: one more, and this the laſt : So ſweet was nexe ſo fatal: I muſt weep, But they are cruel tears : this ſorrows heavenly, It ſtrikes where it does love: ſhe wakes. - Deſ Who's there Othello 2 Oth. I, Deſdemona. Deſ Willyou come to bed my Lord 9th. Have you prayed to night Deſdemona º Deſ I my Lord. - - - - Oth. If you bethink your ſelf of any crime, Vnreconcil'd as yet to heaven and grace, Solicite for it ſtrait. Deſ Alas my Lord, what do you mean by that * Oth. Well, do it, and be brief, I will walk by, I will not kill thy unprepared ſpirit, - No, heaven fore-fend. I would not kill thy ſoul. Deſ Talk you of killing? 9th, I, I do. - Deſ. Then heaven have mercy on me. Oth. Amen, with all my heart. Deſ. If you ſay ſo, I hope you will not kill me. 0th, Hum. - Deſ. And yet I fear you, for y’are fatal then, When your eyes roul ſo: why I ſhould fear, I know not, Since guiltineſs I know not, but yet I feel I fear. Oth. Think on thy ſins. Deſ. They are loves -bear to you. Oth. And for that thou dieſt. - Deſ. That deaths unnatural, that kills for loving: Alas, why gnaw you ſo your neather lip: - Some bloody paſſion ſhakes your very frame, Theſe are portents: but yet I hope - They do not point on me. 0%. Peace and be ſtill. Deſ I will ſo, what's the matter Oth. That handkerchief which I ſolov'd and gave thee, Thou gaveft to Caſio -

This page contains an image.
Page 69

the Moore of Venice. Deſ: No, by my life and ſoul, Send for the man and ask him. Oth, Sweet ſoul take heed, take heed of perjury, Thouart on thy death bed. - Deſ I, but not yet to die. Oth. Yes, preſently: Therefore confeſs thee freely of thy ſin, For to deny each article with oath Connot remove, nor choak the ſtrong conception That I do groan withal: thou art to die. Deſ. Then Lord have mercy on me. Oth. I ſay amen. - Deſ. And have you mercy too : I never did offend you in my life, never lov’d Caſio, But with ſuch general warranty of heaven, - As I might love; I never gave him token. Oth. By heaven I ſaw my handkerchief in his hand: Operjur’d woman, thou doſt ſtone my heart, And makft me call, what I intend to do, A murder, which I thought a ſacrifice; i ſãº, the handkerchief. Deſ. He found it then, - I never gave it him, ſend for him hither, Let him confeſs a truth. Oth. He has confeſt. Déſ. What, my Lord ** Oth. That he hath–vſed thee, Deſ. How, unlawfully *- Orb, I. - Deſ. He will not ſay ſo. 9th. No, his mouth is ſtopºd, Honeſt jago hathtain order fort. Deſ My fear interprets then-what is he dead º 0th. Had all his hairs been lives, My great revenge had ſtomack for em all, Deſ Alas he is betrayºd, and I undone. - Oth, O ſtrumpet, weepeſt thou for him to my face? Deſ Obaniſh me my Lord, but kill me not. Oth. Down ſtrumpet. - Deſ Kill meto morrow, let me live to night. Oth. Nay, an you ſtrive. - - Deſ. But half an hour, - 0th. Being done, there is no pauſe. - - Deſ. But while I ſay one prayer. he fifter her. Oth. 'Tis too late. Emillia call within. Em, My Lord, my Lºrd, what ho my Lord, my Lord. 9th, What voice is this? not dead not yet quite dead

This page contains an image.
Page 70

70 T H E L L 0. - I that am cruel, am yet merciful, would not have theelinger in thy pain 3–ſo, ſo. Em, What ho, my Lord, my Lord. Oth. Who’s there 2 - Em. O good my Lord, I’de ſpeak a word with you. Oth. Yes, ’tis Emilia, by and by: ſhe's dead: - 'Tis like ſhe comes to ſpeak of Caſſio’s death; The noiſe was here ; ho, no more moving, Still as the graveſhall ſhe come in? wer’t good? I think ſhe ſtirs again; no, what’s the beſt? if ſhe comein, ſhe’ſ ſure ſpeak to my wife. My wife, my wife, what wife? I ha no wife: O inſupportable; O heavy hour. Methinks it ſhould be now a huge Eclipſe Of Sun and Moon, and that the affrighted Globe, Should yawn at alteration. - Em. I do beſeech you I may ſpeak with you.-O good my Lord. Oth. I had forgotten thee : come in Emillia: - Soft, by and by 5 let me the curtains draw. Enter Emillia. Where art thou? what’s the matter with thee now * - Em, O my good Lord, yonder’s foul murders done. Oth. What? now 2 Em. But now my Lord. Oth. It is the very error of the Moon, She comes more near the earth then ſhe was wont. And makes men mad. Em, Caſio my Lord has kil’d a young Venetian. Call'd Roderigo. - Oth. Roderigo kil’d, and Caſio kil’d Em, No Caffo is not kil’d, - 0th. Not Caſio kil’d then murthers out of tune And ſweet revenge grows harſh. - Deſ O falſy, fally murdered - Em. Alas, what cry is that 2 - Oth. That, what? Em. Out and alas, it was my Ladies voice, Help, help ho help, O Lady ſpeak again, Sweet Pºſdemona, Oſweet Miſtreſs ſpeak. Deſ. A guiltleſs death I die. - , Fºº, O who has done this deed 2 Deſ. No body, I myſelf, farewel: Commend me to my kind Lord, O farewel. ſhe dies. Oth. Why how ſhould ſhe be murdered? Em. Alas, who knows 2 0th. You heard her ſay, her ſelf, it was not I. En. She ſaid ſo. I muſt needs report a truth. Oth. She’s like a yargon to burning hell,



























This page contains an image.
Page 71

the Moor of Venice. 71 º Twas I that kil’d her. - Em, O, the more Angelſhe, And you the blacker devil. - Oth. She turn'd to folly, and ſhe was a whore. Em, Thou doſt bely her and thou art a devil. - Oth. She was falſe as water. - Em, Thou art raſh as fire, - To ſay that ſhe was falſe: O ſhe was heavenly true. Oth. Caſtodid top her, ask thy husband elſe, O I were damn’d beneath all depth in hell, But that I did proceed upon juſt grounds To this extremity, thy husband knew it all. Em. My husband : - Oth. Thy husband. Em, That ſhe was falſe to wedlock 3 Oth. I, with Caſis : nay, had ſhe bin true, If heaven would make me ſuch another world, Of one intire and perfeół Criſolite, I’de not have ſold her for it. Em. My husband 2 Oth, I, twashe that told me firſts. An honeſt man he is, and hates the ſlime That ſtickson filthy deeds. Em. My husband 2. - Oth. What needs this iteration? woman, I ſay thy husband, Em. Oh Miſtreſs, villany hath made mocks with love: My husband ſay that ſhe was falſe? - - Oth. He woman, I ſay thy husband; doſt underſtand the word * My friend, thy husband, honett, honeſt jago. Em. If he ſay ſo, may hispernicious ſoul Rot half a grain a days he lies toºth heart, She was too fond of her moſt filthy bargains Oºh, Ha 2 . Em Do thy worſt; - This deed of thine is no moreworthy heaven, Then thou waſ worthy her. Oth. Peace, you were beſt. Em, Thou haſt not half the power to do me harm, As I have to be hurt: O gull, O dolt, As ignorant as durt; thou hat done a deed— I care not for thy ſword, I’lemake thee know. Tho I loſt twenty lives: help, help, O help : The Moor has ki’d my Mittreſs, murder, murder. Enter Montano, Gragantio, Jago, and otherſ. Mºn. What is the matter 2 how now General 2



This page contains an image.

End of Section 9. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 10
Page 72

I thought ſo thens ſºle kill my ſelf for grief, O villany, villany. - - * * * * * * * Em, O, are you come jagoº you have done well, That men muſt lay their murder on your neck. Gra. What is the matter? ... Em. Diſprove this villain, if thou beſt a man; He ſays thou toldſ him that his wife was falſe : I know thou didſt not, thou art not ſuch a villains Speak, for my heart is full. - jag. I told him what I thought, and told no more, Then what he found himſelf was apt and true. Em. But did you ever tell him ſhe was falſe? jag. I did. - Em. Youtold a lie, an odious damn’d lie Lipon my ſoula lie, a wicked lies. - She falſe with Caſio; did you ſay with Caſio 2 ag. With Caſio Miſtreſs; goto, charm your tongue. m. I will not charm my tongue, I am bound to ſpeak: My Miſtreſs here lies murdered in her bed. All. Oh heavens foreſend. . Em. And your reports have ſet the murder on. Oth. Nay, ſtare not maſters, it is true indeed, Gra. Tis a ſtrange truth. Mon. O monſtrous agº Em. Villany, villany, villany; I think upon't, I think, I ſmell a villany; jag. What are you mad? I charge you get you home. Em, Good Gentlemen let me have leave to ſpeak; 'Tis proper I obey him, but not now: Perhaps jago, I willne’re go home. Oh. Oh, ho, ho. Oth fall on the bºd. º Em, Nay, lay thee down, and roar, For thou haſ kill'd the ſweeteſt innocent That ere did lift up eye. I ſcarce did know you Uncle, there lies your Niece, Whoſe breath indeed, theſe hands have newly ſtopt: know this ačt ſhews terrible and grim. - - Gr, Poor Deſdemona, I am glad thy father's dead. - Oth, O ſhe was foul. Thy match was mortal to him, and pure grief - Shore his old thread in twain: did helive now, This ſight would make him do a deſperate turn, Yea, curſe his better Angel from his ſide. And fall to reprobation. Oth. 'Tis pitiful, but yet jago knows. That ſhe with Caſin, had the act of ſhame A thouſand times committed; Caſio confeſt it: And

This page contains an image.
Page 73

the Moor of Venice. And ſhe did gratifiehis amorous works, - With that recogniſance and pledg of love, Which I firſt gave her; I ſaw it in his hand; A. It was a handkerchief, an antique token My Father gavemy Mother. Em. O heaven, Oheavenly powers. - ag. Come, hold your peace. Ém. Twill out, 'twillout: I hold my peace Sir, no, Plebe in ſpeaking, liberalas the north; Let heaven, and men, and devils, let 'em all, All, all cry ſhame againſt me, yet I’le ſpeak. jag. Be wiſe, and get you home. Eme. I will not. Gra. Fie, your ſword upon a woman? Em, othou dull Moor, that handkerchiefthouſecak ſton, I foundby fortune, and did give my husband: - For often with a ſolemn earneſtneſs, (More then indeed belong’d to ſuch a trifle,) - He beg'd of me to ſtealit. jag. Villanous whore. - Em. She gave it Caſio 2 no, alas I found it. And I did givºt my husband. jag. Filth, thou lieſt. Em. By heaven I do not, I do not Gentlemen, O murderous Coxcomb' what ſhould ſuch a fool Do with ſo good a woman? - -- The Moºr runs at Jago, Jago kill his wift. 9th. Are there no ſtones in heaven, - - But what ſerves for the thunder 2 pernicious villain. Gra. The woman falls, ſure he has kil’d his wife. Em. I, I, O lay me by my Miſtreſs ſide. Exit Jago. Gra. He's gone, but his wife's kil’d. - Mºn. Tisa notorious villain, take your weapon, Which I have here recovered from the Moor: Come, guard the door without, let him not paſs, But kill him rather; I'le after that ſame villain, For ºtis a damned ſlave. Exit Mont, and Gratiano, * Oth. I am not valiant neither, But every puny whipſter gets my ſword: But why ſhould honour out-live honeſty 2 Let it go all. - - Em, What did thy ſong bode Lady ? Hark, canſ thou hear me? I will play the Swan, - And die in muſick; willow, willow, willow. Moor, ſhe was chaſt, ſhe lov’d the cruel Moor, - - L - So



This page contains an image.
Page 74

74 0 T H E L L 0, That with this little arm, and this good ſword, Pale as thy ſmock; when we ſhall meet at compt, And fiends will ſnatch at it: cold, cold, my girl, From the poſſeſſion ºf this heavenly fight, Waſhime in ſteep down gulphs of liquid fire, So come my ſoul to bliſs, as I ſpeak true; - So ſpeaking as I think, I die, I die. - ſhe dieſ. Oth. I have another weapon in this chamber, It is a ſword of Spain, the Iſebrooks temper: O here it is; tıncle, I muſt come forth. Gra, within. - - Gra. If thou attempt it, it will coſt thee deer, Thou haſ no weapon, and perforce muſt ſuffer. - Oth. Look in upon me then, and ſpeak to me, - - - - Or naked as I am, I will aſſault thee. Gra. What is the matter? - Oth. Behold, I have a weapon, A better never did itſelf ſuſtain Llpona Souldiers thigh: I have ſeen the day, I have made my way through more impediments Then twenty times your ſtop; but Owain boaſt, Who can controuſ his fate? 'tis not ſo now. Be not afraid, though you do ſee me weapon'd : Here is my journies end, here is my Butt, The very ſea-mark of my utmoſt ſail. Do you go back diſmaid ' 'tis a loſt fear, Man but a ruſh againſt Ohello's breaſt, And he retires. Where ſhould Othell, go? How doſt thoulook now O ill-ſtar'd wench, This look of thine will hurl my ſoil from heaven, Even like thy chaſtity: O curſed lºve: Whip me you devils. Blow me about in winds, roaſt me in ſulphur, O Deſdemona, Deſdemonas dead, O, o, o, . Enter Lodovico, Montanos and Officerº, Caſſio in a Chair. Lºd. Where is this raſh and moſt infortunate man? Oth. That’s he that was 6thelio, here I am. - Lod. Where is that Viper’ bring the villain forth, Oth. I look downtowards his feet, but that’s a fable, If that thou be’ſ a devil I cannot kill thee. Lod. Wrench his ſword from him, jag. I bleed fir, but not kil’d. Oth. I am not ſorry neither, I’de have thee live, For in my ſenſe 'tis happineſs to die. Lºd. Othou Cºhello, that weſt once ſo good, ºan -

This page contains an image.
Page 75

- How came you Caſin by a handkerchief Faln in the practice of a damned ſlave. What ſhould be ſaid to thee? Oth, Why, anything. - An honourable murderer if you will; For nought did I in hate, but all in honour. Lod. This wretch hath part confeſt his villany: Did you and he conſent in Caſio’s death Oth. I. - Caſ Dear General, I did never give you cauſe. Oth. I do believe it, and I ask you pardon; Will you I pray, demand that demy devil, Why he hath thus inſnar'd my ſoul and body ? jag. Demand me nothing what you know From this time forth I never will ſpeak word. Lod. What, not to pry 2 Gra. Torments willope your lips. Oth. Well, thou doſt beſt. Lod. Sir, you ſhall underſtand what hath befalº, Which, as I think you know not: here is a letter, Found in the pocket of the ſlain Roderigo; And here anothers the one of them imports The death of Caſio, to be undertook by Roderigo. Oth. O villain, Caſ. Moſt heatheniſh, and moſt groſs. Lod. Now here's another diſcontented paper, Found in his pocket too, and this it ſeems. Roderigo meant to have ſent this damned villain, But that belike, jagº in the interim Came in, and ſatisfied him. Oth. O the pernitious catifſ: º That was my wifes? Caſ. I found it in my chambers. And he himſelf confeſt it but even now, That there he droptit, for a ſpecial purpoſe, Which wrought to his deſire, - Oth, O fool, fool, fool. Caſ. There is beſides in Rodergoes letter, How he obraids jago, that he made him Brave me upon the watch whereon it came, That I was caſt; and even but now he ſpake, After long ſeeming dead, jago hurt him, jagoſet him on. Lod. You muſt forſake this room, and go with us, Your power and your command is taken off. And Caſio rules in Cyprus : For this ſlave. If there be any cunning cruelty, the Moor of Venice.





This page contains an image.
Page 76

76 That can torment him much, and hold him long, It ſhall be his: You ſhall cloſe priſoner reſt, Till that the nature of your fault be known To the Venetian State; come bring him away. - Oth. Soft you, a word or two before you go; I have done the State ſome ſervice and they know’t No more of that: I pray you in your letters, When you ſhall theſe unlucky deeds relate, - Speak of me as I am; nothing extenuate, Nor ſet down ought in malice: then you muſt ſpeak. Of one that lov’d not wiſely, but too well: - Of one not eaſily jealous, but being wrought, Perplext in the extream: of one whoſe hand, Like the baſe Indian, threw a pear away, Richer then all his Tribe: of one whoſe ſubdued eyes, Albeit unuſed to the melting mood, Drop tears, as faſt as the Arabian trees Their medicinal gum: Set you down this; And ſay beſides, that in Aleppo once, Where a Malignant and a Turband Turk, Beat a Venetian, and traduc'd the State; I took bºth throat the circumciſed dog, And ſmote him thus. Heſtabs himſelf. Lod, O bloody period. Gra. All that’s ſpoke is marºd. - | Oth. I kiſt thee ere ſkild thee, no way but this, - - Killing my ſelf, to die upon a kiſs. He dier. . Cºſ. This did I fear, but thought he had no weapon, For he was great of heart. - - - Lod. O'Spartant dog. More fell then anguiſh, hunger, or the Sea. Look on the tragick lodging of this bed, This is thy work; the objeº poiſons fight, Let it be hid: Gratiano, keep the houſe, And ſeize upon the fortunes of the Moor, For they ſucceed to you: To you Lord Governour, Remains the ſenſure of this helliſh villain, The time, the place, the torture; O enforce it, My ſelf will ſtrait aboard, and to the State, This heavy act with heavy heart relate. Exetent omner. - F N I S. - - - - - º - - - - -

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 87

Blank page

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 88

Blank page

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 89

Blank page

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 90

Blank page

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 91

-ſaeſaeĶſ. （ ） ſae|-： ：）





This page contains an image.
Page Scan 92

- | |- |- | ） - |- |-

This page contains an image.

End of Section 10. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents

End of text. Return to beginning.
