<l><?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?></l>
<TEIHeader>
    <l>Digitized by the Internet Archive </l>
    <l>in 2017 with funding from </l>
    <l>Boston Public Library </l>
    <l>https://archive.org/details/titusberenicetraOOotwa </l>
</TEIHeader>

<front>
    <l>Titus and Berenice, TRAGEDY, A&ed at the DUKE ’s THEATRE With a F A R C E called the Cheats of Sea pin. By Tho: Otway. </l>
    <l>Grandis Oratio non est Turgida Sed Naturali fulcbritudine exfurgit. Pet. Arb. „ y / / * _ Licenfedthe 19 th . 1677. Roger Z!£(lrange. </l>
    <l>LONDON: Printed for Richard Tonfon at his Shop under Graj/s-Lm-Gate, </l>
    <l>next Grays-Inn-Lane. 1677. </l>
    <l>TO THE </l>
    <l>RIGHT HONOURABLE. JOHN Earl of ROCHESTER. One of the Gentlemen of his Ma] eflies </l>
    <l>Bed-Chamber, & c. My Lord, J -| ^ / v - V - ± * ir' 1 1 J D Educations are grown things of fo nice </l>
    <l>a Nature , That it is altnoH impojfl- </l>
    <l>hle for me to pay your Lordjhip thoje </l>
    <l>Acknowledgments I owe you, And not </l>
    <l>(from thofe who cannot Judge of the Sentiments </l>
    <l>I have of your Lordjhipr Favours ) incurre the </l>
    <l>Cenfure either of a fawner or a flatterer. Both </l>
    <l>which ought to be as hateful to an Ingenuous Spi¬ </l>
    <l>rit as Ingratitude. None ofthefe would I be guilty </l>
    <l>of, and yet in letting the World l\noiv how Good </l>
    <l>and how Generous a Patron I have , (in flight of </l>
    <l>Malice ) I am jure I am hone(l. A 2 My </l>
    <l>The Epiftle Dedicatory. s . '/ V.; v' \ , ’ '* ■ ' l -./ . f > • •, My Lord, Never was Poetry under fo great an opprejfion </l>
    <l>as now, as full of Phanaticifms as Religion, </l>
    <l>where every one pretends to the Spirit of Wit, </l>
    <l>Jets up a DoBrine of his own, and hates a Poet </l>
    <l>worfe then a Quaker does a Priejl. To examine how much goes to the making up </l>
    <l>one of thofe dreadful things that refolve our dijfo - </l>
    <l>lution. It if for the moil part,a very little French </l>
    <l>breeding much ajfurance, with a great deal of tall ^ </l>
    <l>and no fence. Thus he comes to a New Play, Enquires the </l>
    <l>Author of it, and (if he can find any ) matys his </l>
<l>perfonal misfortunes the JubjeB of his malice io </l>
<l>fome of his Companions, who have as little Wit </l>
<l>and as much ill Nature as himfelf ; and Jo to be </l>
<l>fure (as far as he can ) the Play is damn’d. At night he never fails to Appear in the' </l>
<l>With-dr awing room, where he picky out fame that </l>
<l>have as little to do there as himfelf who mujlring </l>
<l>up all their puny Forces damn as pojftively, as if </l>
<l>Ul^e Muggleton it were their gift, when indeed </l>
<l>they have as little right to Wit, as a Journey man. </l>
<l>Taylor can have to Prophecy . Wit , </l>
<l>The Epiftle Dedicatory; Wit y which was the miflrefs of former Ages 3 is </l>
<l>become the Scandal ofours ; Either the Old Satyr </l>
<l>to let us underftand what he has tyiown Damns </l>
<l>and decry es all Poetry 3 but the old; or elfe the </l>
<l>young affeUed Fool that is impudent beyond Cor- </l>
<l>reUiotij and ignorant above inflru&ion , will be </l>
<l>Cenfuring the prefent; tho he misplace his wit as </l>
<l>he generally does his Courage , and ever maizes ufe </l>
<l>of it on the wrong occafon. How great a Hazard then does your Lord- </l>
<l>pip run in fo Jledfaflly prote&ing a poor Exil'd </l>
<l>thing that has fo many Enemies! But that your </l>
<l>Wit is more Eminent than all their Folly or Ig¬ </l>
<l>norance y andyour Goodnefs greater than any Ma¬ </l>
<l>lice or 111 Nature can be. 1 amJure (and I mujl </l>
<l>own it with gratitude) I have t a fled of it much </l>
<l>above my M erit, or what even Vanity might </l>
<l>prompt me to expect • Though in doing this 3 1 pall </l>
<l>at heft but appear an humble debtor , who acknow¬ </l>
<l>ledges honestly ivhat he owes } though to fyep up </l>
<l>bis Credit he mu ft be forc’d to borrow more ; For </l>
<l>my Genius alwayes led me to feel^ an inter eft in, </l>
<l>your Lordpip ,\ and I never fee you y but I am, </l>
<l>fird with an. Ambition of being in your Favour : for </l>
<l>The Epiftle Dedicatory. for all I have receivd 3 the highefl return 1 am </l>
<l>able to mahg 3 is my acknowledgment 3 in which </l>
<l>I can hardly diflinguijh whether my Thankful- </l>
<l>nefs or my Pride be the greater 3 when I fubferibe </l>
<l>my felf </l>
<l>Your Lordihips y » ■* ... v:^ ' ' -! 1 . .• .. . $ • r'. x- ' • V • * | •> * * f V 4 . \ . ; * *, . * . t ^ i -- v». . . s - y 1 «• ^ \ ’ \ ’ >•./ Moft Obliged and moil Devoted Servant, Tho. Otway. </l>
<l>PROLOGUE. ' • ■ ' ' . • . - yy, .. . r;-. i O * Spoken by Mr. ‘Underhill. </l>
<l>j 11 JL </l>
<l>/ r r </l>
<l>Vi Ij’i </l>
<l>G allants our Author met me here to day 9 Nnd beg d that fd fay fomething for his Play. Tou Waggs that Judge by Roat , and damn by Rule 3 </l>
<l>Faking your meafures from fome Neighbour fool y </l>
<l>Who has Impudence a Coxcombs uffulTool • That always are fevere you know not why , r * i ' ‘ ~ Nndwould bethought great Criticks by the By: With very much ill Nature , and no Wit, Juft asyou are , we humbly begyoitd Sit , Nnd with your Silly felves divert the Pitt. Tou Men of Sence-, who heretofore allow'd) Our Author s Follies; make him once more proud\ ? r </l>
<l>Butfor the Touths, that new l" are come from France ? ‘ v a Whos Heads want Sence, though heels abound with dance f </l>
<l>Our Nuthour to their Judgment wont fubmit , 2 Butfwears that they who fo inf eft the Pit ? > With their own Follies , ne'fe can Judge of Wit. j </l>
<l>3 Tis thence he Chiefly favour would Implor e, . i {/to the Bokes, </l>
<l>sfnd Fair Ones fray oblige him on my Score. / f •/ ? A Confine his Foes , the Fops within their Rules 5 </l>
<l>For Ladies you know how to manage Fools. . — —. /*•: U x ^M»Vk) </l>
<l>ij </l>
<l>t* w </l>
<l>’cvuQ </l>
<l>} y </l>
<l>»nn 3;i I </l>
<l>Petfons </l>
<l>Perfons Reprefented in the Tragedy By </l>
<l>Titus Eefpatian, Etnperour of Rome -Mr. Betterton, sfntiochm, King of Comagene -Mr. Smith. Paulinus, The Emperors Confident - ; —Mr. Medbourn. sir faces, slntiocbus his Confident-Mr. Crofhy, Rutilius , A Tribune--——-----Mr. GiUow. </l>
<l>Berenice, Queen of Pdef ine --Mrs. Lee. Phenice, Her Confident-- — — --Mrs. Burry. </l>
<l>The SCENE ROME. </l>
<l>Perlons Reprelented in the Farce. By Thrifty CMr. Sandford. S Two old Merchants.- Gripe, j CMr. Nodes. Oft avian,"1 CMr. Norris. S Their Sons-- ——-< Leunder, j c/Vlr. Percivdl. Scapin, A Cheat - - • • ■ Mr. si nth. Leigh. Shift, 5 CMr. Richards > Scapins Inftruments*-— —• *- 2 Sly, j cMr. - </l>
<l>Lucia, Thrifty s Daughter,- </l>
<l>Qara, Gripe’s Daughter.— </l>
<l>•Mrs. Barry. </l>
<l>-Mrs. Gibbs. </l>
<l>The SCENE DOVER. </l>
</front>

<body>
<l>TITUS: and BERENICE. </l>
<l>ACT I. SCENE I. </l>
<l>A Palace. </l>
<l>Enter Artiochus and Arfaces. </l>
<l>Antiochus. </l>
<l>T Hou my Arfaces art a Stranger here, This is th’ Apartment of the Charming Fair, That Berenice, whom Titus fo adores. The llniverfe is his, and he is hers : Here from the Court himfelf he of’t conceals. And in her Ears his charming ftory tells, Whilft I a ValTal for admittance wait, And am at beft but thought importunate. Arfac. You want admittance! who with generous care </l>
<l>Have follow’d all her Fortunes cvcry-whcrc, Whofe Fame throughout the World fo loudly rings. One of the greafeft of our Eaftern-Kings. As once you feem’d the Monarch of her Breaft, Too firmly feated to be difpofleft. Nor can the pride flic doth in Titus take. Already fo fevere a diltance make. Antio. Yes! hill that wretch Antiochus I am. But Love 1 oh how I tremble at the name; And my diftradted Soul at that doth ft art. Which once was all the pleafure of my heart, B Since TIT VS and BERENICE . Since Berenice has all my hopes deftroid. And an Eternal filence on me laid. Arfac . That you refent her pride 5 I fee withJoy 5 </l>
<l>Tis that which does her gratitude deftroy 5 </l>
<l>But Friendfhip wrong'd fhould into hatred turn, And you methinks might learn h©r Art to fcorn. Anti . Arfaces , how falfe Meafures doft thou take, Remove the Boles , and bid the Sun go back: Invert all Natures Orders, Fates Decrees^ Then bid me hate the Charming Berenice. Arfac. Well, love her (till, but let her know your pain, </l>
<l>Refotve it you (ball fee, and fpeak again 5 </l>
<l>Urge to her face your rightful Claim aloud. And court her haughtily, as fhe is proud. Antio. Ar/aces? No, fhe’s gentle as a Dove, Her Eyes are Tyrants, but her Soul’s all Love,. And owes fo little for the Vowes I’ve made, That if (lie phy nre, I’m more than paid. * £ Enter Kufrlius. But fee the man I fent, at laft returns, Oh how my heart with Expectation burns. Until jus, have you Berenice feen?- </l>
<l>Rut. I have. Antio. Oh fpeak! what fays the Charming Queen ? Rut. [ preft with difficulty, through the Croud, A throng of Court-Attendants round her flood. The time now paft of htsdervere retreat, Titvs laments no more his Fathers fate. Love takes up all his thought s> and all his cares, Whilft he *to meet thefe mighty Joys prepares: Which may in Berenices arms be found. For file this day will be Romes Emprefs crown’d. Anti. What do I hear? Confufion on thy tongue! To tell me this, why was thy fpeech fo long ? Why didft not Ruine with more (peed afford ? Thou mightft have fpoke and kill’d me in a word. But may I not one Moment with her (peak. And my poor heart difclofe before it break ? Rut. You (hall 5 for when l told her what you defign’d, </l>
<l>Shefweetly fmil’d, and her fair head inclin’d : Titus ne’r from her had a look more kind. \jLnter </l>
<l>TITVS and BERENICE , [JE'/tfer Berenice and Phoenicia. She’s here. Berenice , At laft from the rude Joy I’m freed, . Of thofe new Friends whom my new fortunes breed* The tedious form of their refpefl: I fhun 5 </l>
<l>To find out him whofe words and heart are one. </l>
<l>Antiochus? for I’ll no flattery ufe </l>
<l>Since your neglett I juftly may accufe. How great your Cares for Berenice have been, Ev’n all the Eafi ? and Rome it felf have feen. In my word fate I did your friendfhip find, But now I grow more Great, you grow lefs kind, Antio. Now durft I hope, I would forget my fmart^ So well (he underftands to footh my heart. But, Madam, its a truth by Rumour (pread. That Titus (hall this night poffefs your bed. Ber. Sir, All my Conflicts Til to you reveal. Though half the Fears l 5 ve had? I cannot tell i </l>
<l>So much did Titus for his Father mourn, I almoft doubted Love would ne'r return 5 </l>
<l>He had not for me that Affiduous heat </l>
<l>As when whole days fixt on my Eyes, he (ate. Grief in his Eyes, Cares on his Brows did dwell ? Oft came and lookt? faid nothing but farewell. Ant . But now his kindneft he renews again? Ber . Oh! he will doubly recompence nis pain </l>
<l>For that, if any Faith may be allow'd? Two thoufand Oaths, two thoufand times renew'd y </l>
<l>Or any Jufticein the Powers Divine, Antiochus , He'll be for ever mine. Antio How fhe infults and triumphs in my ill, Sh’as with long pra&ice learnt to fraile and kill. Oh Berenice^ Eternally farewel. Ber . Farewel! good Heav’n! what Language do I hears </l>
<l>Stav ! I conjure you Sir— by alls that dear. Antiochus , What is it I have done? Whv don’t you (peak? Antio . Madam I muft be gone. Ber . How Cruelly you ufe me 1 1 implore </l>
<l>The Reafon-. Ant. I muft never fee you more* B .2 </l>
<l>Ber* T I TV S and BERENICE. Ber. For Heav’ns faKe tell, you wound me with delay. </l>
<l>Ant. At leaft remember I your Laws obey. Why fhould L Here wretched and; hopelefs ftay } If the remembrance be’ht Extinguifht quite, Of that bleft place where firft you faw. the light > 5 Twas there, oh there began my Endlefs fmart. When thofe dear Eyes prevail’d upon my heart. Then Berenice too, my Vowes approv’d. Till happy Titus came and was belovd. He did with Triumph and with Terror come. And in his hands bore the Revenge of Rome . Judea trembled., but ’twas I alone </l>
<l>Firft felt his weight, and found my felf undone, Ber . Hah! Antio. You too, then t’encreafe the pains -1 bore* </l>
<l>Commanded me to fpeak of Love no more. So on your hand I fwore at laft, t’obey y </l>
<l>And for that tafte.of Blifs gave all away. Ber . Why do yo.u ftudy ways t’affiift my mind 3,. You believe Sir, I am not unkind. Alas I’m fenfible how well.y’have ferv’d, And have been kinder mqch than I deferv’d. Antio. Why in thi^ Empire fhould I longer flay,. My Paflion and its weakgefs to betray. Others, though I retire, will bring their Joys,* To Crown that Happinefs which mine deftroys. Ber. You triumph thus, becaufe your pow’r you know. Or if you did not, you’d not ufe me (b. Though Crown’d Romes Emprefs, I the Throne afcend. What pleafure in my Greatnefs can I find. When I fhall want my 'beft and trueft Friend. Ant. I reach your purpofe, you would have me there* </l>
<l>That you might fee the world‘ot my defpair. I know it, the Ambition of your Soul 3 </l>
<l>Tis true. I’ve been a fond obedient Fool. Yet came this time but to new freight my ..heart* . And with more Love poffeft than ever part. Ber . Though it could never enter in my mind,' Since c&fer's Fortunes muft with mine be join’d That TIT VS and BERENICE That any Mortal durft fo hardy prove., T’invade his Right, and talk to me of Love, I bear th' unpleafing Narrative of yours. And Friendfhip, what my Honour iffiuns,' endures* Nay more5 Your parting, I with trouble hear, For you next him 5 are to my Soul moft dear. Antio . In J.uft ice to my Memory and Fame, I fly form Titus > that unlucky Name. A name which ev’ry Moment you repeat, Whilft my poor heart lies bleeding at your feet, - </l>
<l>Earewel: Oh be not at my Ravings griev’d, 1 </l>
<l>When of my death the news ("hall be receiver Remember why I di’d, and. what I liv'd*.J [ Ex . Antioch* ■* Tb<en . I grieve for him, a Love fo true as this*... Deferv’d, methinks, more fortunate fuccefs* Are you not troubled Madam™ Ber, Yes, I feel Something within me difficult to queh </l>
<l>Than. You (hould have Raid him. Ber , Who, I ftay him ? no. From my Remembrance rather let him go, - </l>
<l>His Fancy does with wild Diftra&ion rove. Which thy raw ignorance, interprets Love. Than. Titus his thoughts, yet to unfold, denies* - </l>
<l>And Rome beholds you but with jealous eyes. Its rigorous Laws, create my fears for you b </l>
<l>Romans no Forrain Marriages allow </l>
<l>To Kingly Power (till enemies ^h'ave been. Nor will, I fear, admit of you a Queen, Ber, Vhdenicia , no, my time of fear is pa ft. Me Titus loves, and that includes the reft. The fplendor of this night thou haft beheld. Are not thy Eyes with bis bright Grandeur fill’d? Thefe Eagles fhfces, marching all in ftate: And crowds of Kings that with their Tributes wait* Triumphs below, and Bleflings from Above, Seen} all at ftrife to grace this Man of Love* Away Vh£niciA , let's go meet him ftrait, I can no longer for his comtng wait. x My, ^ '4 . a ' V. * mvs arid BERENICE. My Eager wilhes drive me wildly on 5 </l>
<l>Nor will be temper’d till my Joy’s begun. [Exeunt. SCENE If. Entet' Titus Paulinus, Attendants . "Titus. / “T~'Oth J Syrian King, did you my Meflage bear? JL And does he know that I expeft: him here ? Paul. Sir, in the Queens appartment, He alone </l>
<l>Was feen, but e 7 r I there arriv’d 5 was gone. Tit. Tis well Paulinus for thefe ten days paft. I have to Berenice -a ftranger been: But you can tell me all— what does the Queen? Paul. She does, what fpeaks, how much (he values you 3 </l>
<l>When you mourn’d for your Father, (he mourn’d too. So Juft a Sorrow in her face was (hown , It Teem'd as if the Lofs had been her own. Tit . Oh lovely fair one, little doft thou know £ ajtde . How hard a Trial thou muft undergo. Heav’n! oh my heart ! Paul. What is’t your Grief fhould raife </l>
<l>For her whom almoft all the Eajl obeys. Tit. Command Paulinus that thefe retreat, rPaul. moves hk </l>
<l>Rome of my purpofes uncertain yet, J ^ hand and all the Expefts to know the fortune of the Queen $ Ireft exti . Their Murmurings I have heard, and Troubles feen. The bufinefs of our Love, is the Difcourfe, And expectation of the Univerfe. And by the face of my affairs, I find, Tis time that I refolve and fix my mind. Tell me Paulinus , juftly, and be free, What fays the World of Berenice and me? Patti. In every heart you Admiration raife: All, Your high Vertues, and her Beauty praife* Tit. Alas! Thou anfwerft wide of my defire, Paulinus , be my Friend, and come yet nigher </l>
<l>How do they of my fighsand vow| approve? Or what expeCt they from fo true a love ? . Paul </l>
<l>TIT VS and BERENICE Paul Love or not love, Sir, all is in your power. </l>
<l>The Court will fecond ftill thcEmperour. Tit. Courtiers Paulinus feldomare fincere </l>
<l>To pleafe their Matter they have too much care* </l>
<l>The Court did Nero's horrid Adts applaud. To all his lufts fubfcrib’d, and call’d him God. Th* Idolatrous Court (hall never judg for me 3 </l>
<l>No 5 my Paulinus, I rely on thee : What then mutt Berenice expeCt ? declare, Will Rome be gentle to her, or fevere? My happinefs is plac’d in her alone. Now they have rais’d me to the Imperial Throne, </l>
<l>Where on my head continual cares mutt fall, Will they deny me what may fweeten all? Paul. Her vertues they acknowledg and defers </l>
<l>Proclaim indeed (lie has a Roman heart : * Rut (he’s a Queen, and that alone withftands * All which her beauty and her worth demands. In Rome the Law has long unalter’d flood, Never to mix it’s race with ftrangers blood. Tit . It is a fign they are capricious grown. When they defpife all vertues but their own. Paul Julius, who firftfubdued her to his Arms, </l>
<l>And quite had filenc’d Laws with Wars ahrms, </l>
<l>Burning for Cleopatra's love 5 to Fame </l>
<l>More juft fled from her eyes, and hid his flame. Tit. But which way from my heart (hall I remove, </l>
<l>So long eftablifht and deep rooted love? Paul. The Conflift will be difficult I guefi 3 </l>
<l>But you your rifing forrows muftfupprefs5 </l>
<l>Tit.Who c:n a heart that’s not his own controul ? </l>
<l>Her prefenee was the comfort of my Soul. After a thoufand Oaths confirm’d in tears. By which I vow’d my felffor ever hers, I hop’d with all my Love and allhe’r charms, Atlaft to have her in my longing Arms. But now I can fuch rare perfections crown. And that my love’s more great than overgrown, </l>
<l>When in one hour a happy Marriage may • Of all my five years vows the tribute pay- T7 TVS and BERENICE. I go Tdulinus- .how my heart does rife. Paul. Whether ? Tit. To part for ever from her eyes, Tho I requir’d th’affiftance of thy zeal. To cru(h a paffion that’s fo hard to quell. My heart had of it’s doom refolv’d before* Yet Berenice does ftill difpute the war. Theconqueft of fo great a flame muft coft </l>
<l>Confli&s, in which my foul will oft be toft. Paul. You in your birth for Empire were defign’d. </l>
<l>And to that purpofe Heav’n did frame your mind) </l>
<l>Fate in that day wife providence did fhew,* Fixing the deftiny of Rome in you. Tit. My youth rejoyc’d in love and glorious wars. </l>
<l>But my Remains of life muft waftein cares. Rome , my new ConduQ:, now obferves ’twould be </l>
<l>Both ominous to her,and mean in me. If in my Dawn of power to clear my way </l>
<l>To happinefs,I fhould her Laws deftroy : No, I*ve-refolv’d on’t. Love and all (hall go-5 </l>
<l>Alas! it muft, fince Rome will have it fo. But how (hall I poor Berenice prepare ? Paul. You muft refolve to go andvifit her. Sooth her fad hearty and«on her patience win. Then by degrees. Tit .--But how (hall I begin? Oh my Paulin#*) J have oft defign’d To fpeak my thoughts, but ftill they ftay’d behind. I hop'd as (he difeern’d my troubl’d Breft, 'She might a little at the caufe have gueft) But nought fufpefting, as I weeping lay. With her fair hand (he’d wipe the tears away? And in that mift never the loft perceiv’d </l>
<l>Of the fad Heart (he had too much believ’d $ But now a firmer conftancy I take. Either my heart (hall vent its grief 3 or breaL </l>
<l>I thought to have met Antiochus 3 and here </l>
<l>All I e’re lov’d furrender’d to his care. To morrow he ccndufts her to theEaft, And now I go to figh, and look my laft. </l>
<l>Paul • </l>
<l>TIT VS and BERENICE 17 Paul. I ne’re expe&ed le(s from that Renown, Which all your Aftions muft with glory crown. Tit* How lovely’s glory 3 yet how cruel too !* How much more fair and charming were fhe row. If through eternal dangers to be won ! So I might ftill call Berenice my own. In Nero's Court where I was bred, my mind </l>
<l>By that example to all ills inclin’d., . The loofe wild paths ofpleafures I purfu’d. Till Berenice fir ft taught me to be good. She taught me Vertue, but oh fcurfed Rome ! The good I owe her, muft her wrong become. For fomuch Vertue and Renown fo great 3 </l>
<l>Fotyall the Honour I did everget : Her for whole fake alone, I fame purfu’d, I muft forgo to pleafe the Multitude. Paul. Ypli cannot with Ingratitude be charg’d. You have the bounds of Pulejiine enlarg’d. Event ' £upkrates s her wide power extends , So many Kingdomes Berenice commands. Tit . Weak Comforts, for the Griefs muft on her dwell! I know fair Berenice , and know too well 3 </l>
<l>To greatnefs fhe fo little did incline. Her heart ask’d never any thing but mine. Let’s talk no more of her, Paulinus* Paul * Why ! lit* The thought of her, butfhakes my conftancy. Yet in my heart if doubts already rife. What will it do when I behold her eyes ? Enter Rutilius. Rutil. Sir, Berenice defires admittance here—- Tit . Palinus -- Oh ! Paul . Can you already fear } So foon are all your resolutions (hook ? Now,Sir,’s the time-— [Ex . Rut* Enter Berenice, Ph^nicia and attendants. Tit. I have no power to look. Ber . Sir, ben’t difpleafed, that I thus far prefume. It is to pay my gratitude I come. Whilft all the Court affembled in my view. Admire the Favour you on me beftows </l>
<l>C </l>
<l>It </l>
<l>18 riTVS and BERENICE. It were unjuft, (hould I remain alone, Silent, as though I had a fenfe of none. Your mourning-’s done, and you from griefs are free. </l>
<l>Are now your own, and yet not vifit me? Your prefentof new Diadems I wait. Oh! give me more content , and lefs of ftate. Give me a word, a figh, a look at lead, In thofe th‘ Ambition of my Soul is plac’t. Was your dilcourfc of me when I arriv’d? Was I fo happy may it be believ’d ? Speak, tell me quick, is Berenice fo bleft. Or rvas I prefent to your thoughts at leaft ? Tit. Doubt it not, Madam, by the Gods I fwear’t. </l>
<l>That Berenice is always in my heart. Nor time, nor abfence, can you thence remove. My heart’s all yours, and you alone I love. Ber. You vow your Love perpetual and fincere, • But ’tis with a ftrange coldnefs that you fwear. Why the juft Gods to witnefs did you call ? I don’t pretend to doubt your faith at all. In you I truft, would only from you live 5 </l>
<l>And what you fay I ever muft believe. Tit. Madam ! Ber. Proceed: Alas, whence this furprize 1 </l>
<l>You feem confus’d to turn away your eyes. Nothing but trouble in your face I find, Does ftill a Fathers death affiift your mind? Tit. Oh, did my Father good Tefpajian live! How happy thould I be! Ber. Ah, ceafe to grieve! . Your tears, have reverenc’t his mem’ry now. Cares are to Rome, and your own glory due. A Father you lament, a feeble grief, _ Whilft for your abfence I find no relief. But in your prefence only take delight, I, who'Ihall dye, if but debarr’d your fight. Tit. Madam, what is it that your griefs declare? </l>
<l>What time d’ you choofe? For pi tty’s fake forbear. </l>
<l>Your Bounties my Ingratitude proclaim. Ber. You can do nothing that deferves that name 5 </l>
<l>N«V TITVS and BERENICE. No Sir, you never can ungrateful prove. May be I’m fond, and tire you with my Love. Tit. No Madam ! No, my heart ( fince I mud fpeak) Was ne’re more full of Love or half fo like to break. But. Ber. What? Tit. Alas! Ber. Proceed. Tit. The Empire Rome - Ber. Well. Tit. Oh, the difinal fecret will not come— Away Paulinus, e’re i’m quite undone. My Speech forfakes me and my heart’s all done. |^£x. Tit. Paul. Ber. So loon to leave me, and in trouble too? Titus how have I this deferv’d from you ? What have I done, Phoenicia ? tell me^fpeak. Pkten. Does nothing to your memory appear : That might provoke him-—’? Ber. By all tha’ts to me dear. Since the fird hour F faw his face, till now, Too much of Love, is all the guilt I know. Thus filence is too rude, and racks my bread, In the uncertainty I cannot red. He knows, Phoenicia, all my moments pad. Perhaps he ’s jealous of the Syrian King 3 </l>
<l>’Ti« that’s the root whence all this change mud fpring, Titus , this Victory I (hall not boad. I with the Gods would try me to the mod. With a more potent Rival, tempt my heart, One that would make me greater than thou^irt. Then my dear Titus? (houldd thou foon difcern, How much for thee I all mankind would fcorn. Let’s go, Phoenicia, with one gentle word </l>
<l>He will be fatisfied, and I redor’d: <c My Injur’d truth by my complyance find, “ And if he has a heart he, mud be kind, </l>
<l>c Exeunt Omnes. Ends the firfl Aff. 30 . TrtVS and BERENICE. </l>
<l>ACT II. SCENE I. </l>
<l>Enter Titus, Antiochus and Arfaces. Tit» /L Ntzochus ! y’have done your Friendfhip wrongs </l>
<l>In that y’have kept this Secret hid fo long, X ^Y\yhat t j iat y OUr d e p arture d oes incite, Which not unjuftly, I may call a Fright? Tho on the Imperial Throne I’m plac’d, So highly feem with Fortunes favour grac’d 5 </l>
<l>As if (he nothing further had to grant : I more than ever, do your friendfhip want. Ant . Sir, your great kindnefs I fo well did know* I durft.not ftay where I fo much did owe. When firft Jud£a heard your loud alarms. You made me your Companion* in your arms; Nay, nearer to you did with friendfhip joyn 5 </l>
<l>And lodg’d the fecrets of' your Brefirin mine. Yet all this goodnefs but augments my fin 5 </l>
<l>For I have falfe and mod ungrateful been. Tit . I can’t forget that to your arms alone, I owe the half of all I ever won: Witnefs thofe precious Spoils you hither brought. Won from the j krvs when on my fide you fought. To all thofe Purchafes I lay no claims </l>
<l>Your heart and friendfhip are my only aim. Ant . My Heart! my Friendfhip ! Heav’n, how you miftake I </l>
<l>On my deceipt how weak a gloG you make! t ; When firft you thought your felf of me pofl’eft. You took a very Serpent to your breft. Tit . Antiochus 5 I find where thou art ftungr - </l>
<l>Tell me th 3 officious Slave that does me wrong. Some bafe Detra&or has my Honour ftain’d. And in your eafie heart a Credit gain'd. Abts’d and told yoa Titus is unjuft* But I will krow th? treacherous Fiends I muft. Tho </l>
<l>mrr ■ TITVS and BERENICE. Tho you unkindly from your friend would run. </l>
<l>And own th’ unjuftice which you think I’ve done. Ant. Oh Titus , if I durft but fpeak my heart y </l>
<l>But ’tis a Secret hard from thence to part. Tis not from you, it is from Rowe I fty. There’s a Difeafe in’t, I muft fhun or dye. Seek then no more what’s dangerous to know. </l>
<l>When moft your friend, I (ball appear your foe. Tit. I either to your heart a ftranger am, Or fure Antiochus is not the fame r What elfe fhould make you not your mind declare? What is’t that you dare fay, I dare not hear ? Ant. If then, what e’r I utter, you dare hear, </l>
<l>Receive the fatal Secret in your Ear. But arm your heart with Tempers well ’tis this </l>
<l>Tit. Go on. Anti. I love the charming Berenice. Tit. Hah! Ant. Yes, nor was I hateful to her Eyes, Till you came on and robb’d me of the prize. • When at your Armies head.you did appear. You fackt Jerufdem and conquered her. Tit. A braver Rival I’d not with to find. Than him that dares be juft and tell his mind.- </l>
<l>So far’s Refentment from my heart remov’d y </l>
<l>. That Berenice is by my friend belov’d. That I, Antiochus , the thing extol. For (he was made to be ador’d by all i~ And happy he that (hall poflefs her 5 </l>
<l>Ant. True, But ’tis fit none fhould be fo bleft but you*- </l>
<l>And Berenice for none could be defign’d. But him that’s the Delight of all Mankind, ’Tis for this caufe to Syria. I repair. For when you ’re bleft no envy fhould be near. Tit . O my Antiochus , when thou fhalt fee. How fmall’s the happinefs in ftore for me: * Thou needft not fear thy Envy, let me have </l>
<l>Thy pitty and thy aid, ’tis that I craven- </l>
<l>21 ' </l>
<l>My </l>
<l>*22 TlTVS and BERENICE . My beft and trueft friend, you muft be fo. For there’s none fit fort in the World but you. None but a King, my Rival and my friend, Is fit to fpeak the torments of my mind. In my behalf you Berenice muft fee. Antio . Is that an office, Titus^ fit for me > Is’t nor enough her Cruelties I bear, But you muft too folicite my defpair ? I fwore for ever from her to depart 5 </l>
<l>Alas ! and dare not truft again my heart. Your paffion by another may be fhown, I have enough to do to rule mv own. Tit . He that fo well his own misfortunes bears. Can beft inftrud her how to temper hers. Nay, my Antiochus , you muft not ftart. I know by mine, your news will (hake her heart. For I muft too, for ever from her part. Antio. You part? Tit . Yes! curft necefiity ! ’tis true. She that both conquer’d me and fetter’d you 5 </l>
<l>In whom alone I fum’d up all Delight, Muft be for ever baniflvd from my fight. Antio . It cannot be. No Slave that wears her Chains, </l>
<l>Upon fo eafie terms his Freedom gains. Tit . Lord of the World my Empire wide does flow, I can mike Kings, and can depofe ’em too* The ftubborn’ft hearts muft to my power bow down. </l>
<l>And yet I am not Mafter of my own. Konte that to Kings fo long a foe has been, Will not admit my marriage with the Queen. If Berenice to morrow fee not gone. The Multitude will to her Palace run 5 And from their rude omragious tougues, ftie’ll hear The news I dread to tell, and you to hear. Antio . Now if my heart was to Revenge alli’d. How might T triumph in her falling Pride! To fee her Cruelties to me repaid. And with ’em all her tortur’d foul upbraid. But, Titus-) I’m more juft, and rather mov’d, That ev’n, Sir, you dare wrong the thing Pve lov’d. 2 3 </l>
<l>TITVS and BERENICE. Tit. When I the Imperiaf Power did firft aftume, I firmly fwore t’uphold the Rights of Rome'-) Should I to follow Love, from Glory fly 5 </l>
<l>Forfake my Throne, in every VaflTal’s eye. How mean and defpicable mud: I prove! An Emperor led about the World by love ! No, Prince, the fatal (lory you mu ft tell. And bid from me, poor Berenice fareweh </l>
<l>But if the hopes of reigning in my heart . May any eafe to her fad mind impart 5 </l>
<l>Swear, friend, by all that to my Soul is dear. Entire I will preferve her ever there. Mourning at Court, and more exil’d than (he. My Reign but a long Banifhment (hall be. From all thofe Joys that wait on Pomp and Power* </l>
<l>Tomorrow (he her journey hence muft take, And fo I all that e 5 r I lov’d, forfake. Her to your Care and Conduft I commend^ For tho my Rival as a King and Friend, The deareft Treafure I dare with you trufts </l>
<l>Ant-io. Sit, do not tempt me, left I prove unjuft: Her charms that made me my own Fame forgo, Will' be too apt to make me falfe to you. Tit . No more 5 I know thee, have thy Honour try’d. Firm (till in Dangers found thee by my fide. « Thou knew’ft my Love, whilft thine was yet conceal'd. </l>
<l>When all thy hopes by my fuccefs were quelkd: Even at that time thou didft no falfhood (how, [Exit* Titus. </l>
<l>And wilt not wrong me on advantage now. Antio. No, Fie not fee her, neither dare I go: Toofoon from others her hard lot (he 5 l know. Doft thou not think her Fate’s enough fevere 5 </l>
<l>Uqlefs that I th’ unwelcome Mefiage bear ? I who’m her hate, enough have felt before. And need not feck new ways to purchafe more. Arfa. See, (he approaches^ now the Coward play^ And when you might have Conquer’d run away. </l>
<l>Enter. </l>
<l>34 </l>
<l>'tl'tVS and BERENICE. Enter Berenice and -Phoenicia. Antio. Oh Heaven ! Ber , My Lord* I fee you are not gone, Perhaps ’tis me alone that you would fhun. Antio* You came not here Antioch us to find. The vifit to another was defign’d. C<efar-> and’tis on him the blame mufl: light* </l>
<l>ilfnow my prefence here offend your fight. Th’ are his Commands, are guilty of the fin : •It may be elfe I had at Ojiia been. Ber. His friends are always with his ppefence Grac’d* </l>
<l>’Tis I alone that cannot be fo bleft. Antio. Too much his prejudice upon you gain’d: "Twas for your fake alone I was detain’d. Ber. For mine ? away. Antio. Tyrannic fair, ’tis true* He kept me here only to talk of you. Ber . Of me, my-Lord! forbear this courtly art, Y’ are brave and fhould not mock an eafie heart. In my diftrefs, what pleafure could you fee£ Alas ! or what could tit us fay of me? Antio. Better a thoufand times than I can tell. So firm a pafiion in his heart does dwell. When you are nam’d, he’s from himfclf transform’d. And every way betrays how much he’s charm’d. Love in his face does like a Tyrant rife, And Majefty’s no longer in his eyes. But there are things behind I dare not (peak .* For at the news your tender heart would break. Ber. How Sir? Antio. Ere night the truth of what I’ve faidyou’l know, </l>
<l>And then,I doubt not,Juftifie me too. Farewell- Ber. Oh, Heaven what can this Language mean! You fee before your eyes a wretched Queen. Sir, of my quiet, if you have fuch care. Or if my felf your eyes held ever dear, Difpel this mift of trouble from my Souk </l>
<l>* Antio . Madam, your felf excufe. 717VS and BERENICE. For your own fake it is that I refufe. ’Twill not be long before the doubts remov’d. Ber. You told me once A>:tiochus> you lov’d 5 </l>
<l>But fure’twas only that you might betrays </l>
<l>Or elfe you more would fear to difobey. Antio. I difobey you, ask my life and try 5 </l>
<l>How glorioufly I for your fake can dye. ]t would by far, ibe the more welcome fate. Then now to fpeak, and ever gain your hate. Ber. No Sir, you never (hall my hatred find', ’Tis my defire, and you mull be fo kind. Will you? Antio. Heaven this conftraint is worfe than deaths </l>
<l>You drive, and will not give me time to breath. Ob, Madam! put me too no further pain. Ber. Muft I then ever beg, and beg in vain ? Hence forward Prince, either the truth relate. Forbear or be allur’d for ever of my hate. Antio . My heart was always yours, and is fo (till s </l>
<l>For ever muft depend upon your Will. I wifh another way, your power you’d tty’d: But you ’re refolv’d, and muft be fatisfi’d 5 </l>
<l>Yet flatter not your felf, I fhall declare, Thofe horrors which perhaps you dare not hear. </l>
<l>You cannot but believe I know^your heart. Look then to feel me ftrike its tender’d part. Titus has told me. Ber. What?fear no Suiprize. Antio. That he muft part for ever from your eyes. </l>
<l>Ber . We part lean things another nature take? Or Titus ever Berenice for fake? Antio . Perhaps ’tis ftrange that I fhou’d tell you fo, </l>
<l>But you (hall find I’ll do him Juftice too. What ever in a heart both kind and great </l>
<l>Love with defpair moft dreadful could create. I faw in his he weep’s, laments, and more. Then ever dos fair Berenice adore. But what avails it 5 that fuch love he fhow 9 ? A Queen fufpe<fted to Romes Empire grows. And Titus cannot with her Laws difpence. For therfeore ’tis you muft be baniftit hence. </l>
<l>a 6 </l>
<l>TlTVS and BERENICE. </l>
<l>Ber. What do I hear, alas Phoenicia! Antio, Nay 3 to-morrow is your laft and utmoft day, </l>
<l>In bearing this the Courage well’you'l prove </l>
<l>Of that great haughty Soul which fcorn'd my love® </l>
<l>Ber. Will Titus leave his Berenice forlorn ? He who fo many Qaths, fo oft hath fworn ? I’le not believe't , his love and faith's mor t e ftrong, </l>
<l>I'm fure he’s guiltlefs and you do him wrong. This is a fnare to difunite us laid. Tit us i thou lov'ft nif 3 doft not with me dead. No, (trait Tie fee him., and fecure all fear. Let's go. Antio. Too well you may behold him here $ Ber, Too well you wifh it to perfwade^it, Noy </l>
<l>In this your bafe degenerate Soul you (how. When you no other ftratagem could find, T' abufe my heart you would betray your friend. </l>
<l>How e’re he prove, Know I your fight abhor* And from this minute never fee me more. Antio o Oh Berenice ! remorfelefs cruel fair 1 </l>
<l>Born only for my torment and defpair. Was It for this ifo faithfully I ferv'd ? Is this the recompence I have deferv'd ? I who for you did all Ambition wave. And lefc a* Kingdom to become your Slave, Curfe on my Fate! Ber, If 're my heart you priz'd, You never had this cruelty devis'd. Never to work my Torment, been thus boldy </l>
<l>And fo Triumphantly the ftory told. Away Phoenicia, no more lie hear him (peak. Ex, Ber. Phx Antio, Now, my Arfuces , would my heart but break </l>
<l>But yet I hope in part lVe freedom won. And what love would not, by her hate ftl'aS done. </l>
<l>The pain I lately endur’d thou haft beheld, 1 left her all Enamour’d, Jealous, Wild. But now performing this Ignoble part, Perhaps, Ue ever banifh her my heart. n't VS and BERENICE. She left me cruelly, and let her go. My Honour and Repofe command it too, For ever to my eyes a ftranger be, Till I have learn’t to fcorn as well as Hie. \_Exetwt, </l>
<l>ACT III. SCENE I. </l>
<l>Enter Berenice in diforder, f ' ' ' * 1 I $ ^ • : " t ‘ ,, .--js Ber. TT Of my wrong too well am fatisfied 3 To fee the perjur’d Titus, twiceitry’d. Twice for admittance to him begg’d in vain </l>
<l>Nor is Phoenicia yet return’d again. Phoenicia. has no anfwer to bring back. Inrgateful Titus will not hear her (peak : But hides himfelf and from my fury flyes : Nor will have fenfe, though Berenice dies. [Enter Phamice. </l>
<l>Phanice^ Well, my Titus haft thou feen ? .What will he come and make me live again? Ph&. Madam, the Emperor I alone did find 3 </l>
<l>And faw in bis the trouble of* your mind 3 </l>
<l>I faw the tears he would have hid run down. Ber. But was he not afham’d they (hould be fhown £ Look’t he not as he thought his Love difgrayCe? And was not all the Emperor in his face? ^ Ph<e. Doubt it not. Madam, he willfoonbe here, </l>
<l>but wherefore will you this diforder wear ? Tour rifl’d drefs let me in-order plac^ , And thefe diftieveld locks that hide your face. Ber. Forbear? Ph<emce, let it 3II </l>
<l>No, he ftiall fee the triumph l)e has won? • How vain thofe foolifh ornaments muft prove >• D 2 If </l>
<l>a 8 T I TV S and BERENICE. If neither faith nor tears nor means can move ? \ Enter Antiochus, Affaces, ©h, my unruly for raws / Oh, my fears ! Who’s here ? Antio. Arfaces^ Berenice in tears, TBcr. Antiochus! Thanice^ let’s away, To let him fee my torments lTe not ftay. fEtf. Antio . Now whither’s all'my refolutions gone ? At faces , who could let** and be his own? Ifaid I’d never fee her face again: But come and find my boaftings all were vain $ Seeing her fofferings, all her fcorn forget, And lofe at once my vengeance and my hate*. </l>
<l>Wretched Antiochus ! with how much care </l>
<l>And labours, my own mifchiefs I prepare ! How poorly all my injuries have born ! Hopelefs, undone and to my felf a fcorn. Leave me alone unhappy as I am: I would not have a witnefi of my fhame^ Enter Titus Attended. I . ' V rs - i r — tit. T was cruel not to fee her, Oh my heart!’ </l>
<l>And now I go to fee her , but to part. Rptilius, fly and footh the Queens defpair, And for our meeting Berenice prepare. Antio. What have you dene,Sir ? Berenice will dye </l>
<l>I fuw her hence with hair difh'pvei’d fly. Tis only you her fury can furceafe. When eie you ’re nam’d (he’s inftantly at peace. Her eyes ftill bent- to your apartment were. And every moment feem’d to wifh you near.- </l>
<l>tit* Antiochus^ affift me what to do. I’m not prepar’d, for the fad Interview. I have not yet eonfulted well my heart, And doubt it is not (Vrong enough to part. Since firft I took pofleflion of the Throne, What is it for my honourl have done? My love and folly only I’ve difclos’d. riTVS and BERENICE. And nothing but my weaknefles expos’d. The golden days where are they to be found. So much expefted, when this head was Crown’d ? </l>
<l>Whofe tears have I dry’d up ? or in what face </l>
<l>Can I the fruits of any good aft trace? Know I what years Heaven has for me decreed ? </l>
<l>And of thefe few, how few are to fucceed ? And yet how many have I fpent in waft ! But now to honor Fie make greater haft. Alas! ’tis but one blow and all is paft. Enter Berenice, prejjzng from Fait, and Paulo Ber. Let me alone, your conrifels all are weak. See him I muft, he’s here, and I will fpeak. Has Tit ns then forfook me ? is it true > Muft we too part, does he command it too? Tit. Oh! ftop the deluge, which fo fiercely flows § </l>
<l>This is no time t’ allay each others woes. Enough I feel my own affiiftions fmart,* And need not thofe dear tears to damp my heart > </l>
<l>But if we neither can our griefs command. Yet with fuch honour let’em be fuftain’d. As the whole World to hear it told (hall fmart </l>
<l>For deareft Berenice we muft part. And now 1 would not a difpute maintain. Whether I lov’d, but whether I muft Reign. Ber. Reign fCruelJ then and fatisfie your pride, * </l>
<l>And for your Cruelties be deift’d. I’lene’r difpute it farther, I but ftay’d </l>
<l>Till Titus who fo many vows had made. Of fuch a Love as nothing could impair. Should come himfelfand tell how falfe they were, </l>
<l>Now I believ’t, enough Fve heard you tel!* And I am gone— eternally farewell, Eternally—— Ah, Sir, confider now. How harflh that word is and how dreadful too* </l>
<l>Confider, Oh the Miferies they bear, That are for ever rob’d of all that’s dear. From this fad Moment never more to meet, riXVS and BERENICE . Is it for day to dawn,, and day to fet. In which I muft not find my hopes ftiil young, Nor yet once fee my Titus all day long ? H eavVis bow I wildly rave-—' to lofe my pains </l>
<l>On him ungrateful that myj:earrs dfdains! Of all tnofe days of abfence I (hall count. With him 0 the number will to nothing mount. Tit. Doubt it not, Madam, there will be no need </l>
<l>To count the days that fhall your lofs fuceed. I hope e re long that you will hear from fame., .How very wretched and how juft I am. My heart bleeds now, I feel the drops run down i </l>
<l>Nor can it be long dying when you ®re gone. Bcr . Ah why. Sir, muft we part if this be true ? </l>
<l>My claims to Marriage I’le no more renew. Will Rome accept of nothing but my death? Or why d’ ye envy me the air you breath ? Tit. Madam, you are too powerful every way* </l>
<l>Shall I withftand it? no,for ever flay. Then I from blifs muft always be debarr’d 5 </l>
<l>And on my heart for ever keep a guard. With fears through all my courfe of Glory move. </l>
<l>Left e’re aware I lofe my felf and Love. Ev’n now my heart is from my bofom ftray’d. And all its fwellings on a fudden laid. Bent thus to you by all Loves fofteft pow’rs. And only this remembers that 5 tis yOurs Bcr, 0,7 'itHS) whilft this charming tale you tell. </l>
<l>D’ye Tee the Romms ready to rebel ? Tit . How they will look on the affront who knows, </l>
<l>*If once they murmur and then fall to blows: Muft I in Battel juftifie my Caufes Or df they fhould fubmit and fet their Laws 5 How muft. I be expos’d another day 5 And for their Patience toot> how largely pay ! With Grievances and wild Demands ftiil curft, Shall I dare plead the Laws that break ’em firft ? Bcr. How much you are an Emperor now I find, </l>
<l>3 Tis plain in your unfteady anxious mind. You we*gh your Peoples Rights to your own fears. Tirvs and BERENICE . Eut never value Berenices tears ? Tit* Not value ’em ! Why are you fo unjuft? Now by the honour of my Father's duft. By Heav’n and all the gods that govern there, If to me any thing be half fo dear 5 </l>
<l>May I be as a Slave, depos’d and ferve. Or elfe forlorn in fome wild Defart ftarve, Till I’m as wretched as my ills deferve. Ber. Laws you may change 5 why will you for their fake? </l>
<l>Into your breft eternal forrows take? Rome has her Priviledges^ have not you </l>
<l>Your Int’refts, your Rights asfacred too? Say, fpeak. Tit . Alas! how do you rend my breft ! I know indeed I never can have reft } And yet the Laws of Rome I cannot change. Do, break my heart and take your full Revenge, </l>
<l>2 ?er. How weak a Guard does now your Honor keep! </l>
<l>You are an Emperor, and yet you weep l </l>
<l>Tit. I grant it, I am fenfible I do, I weep, alas f I figh and tremble too. For when to Empire firft I did attain? Rome made me fwear I would her Rights maintain, I did, and muft perform what I then vow'd. Others before me to the Yoke have bowM: And ? tis their Honor : yet in leaving you 3 </l>
<l>All their Auftereft Laws I fhall out-do. And an Example leave fo brave and great. As none (hall ever after imitate. Ber. To your Barbarity there's nothing hard. Go on? and Infamy be your reward. Long fince my fears your falftiood had difplayM^ </l>
<l>Nor would I at your Sute have longer ftaykk </l>
<l>Would I the bafe Indignities had born? Of a rude People, publick Hate and Scorn ? No, to this breach I would have fpurr’dyou on, </l>
<l>And Lam pleas’d it is already done* </l>
<l>3 a TITVS and BERENICE, No longer fhall the fear of me prevail, Alas! you mud not think to hear me rail. Or Beav’n invoke, its vengeance to prepare s </l>
<l>No, for if Heav’n vouchfafe to hear my Pray‘r, I beg no memory may there remain, Of either your Injuftice, or my Pain. [' Kneels . But the fad Bcrcnktk before fhe dies. Is fare to have Revenge if you have eyes. Nor, Titus , need I go to find it far. No further than that heart, I have it there :[Points to hk brejL </l>
<l>Within your felf fhall rife your dreacffull’d foes </l>
<l>My paft Integrities, my Torments nows ‘ Which you, ungrateful -perjutM Man, have bred, My blood which in your Palace I (hall (bed. Sufficient terrors to your Soul (hall give, And *tis to them that my Revenge HI leave. ijExit furioujly 'Toni. Thus, Sir, at lead the Conqutd you have won. The Queen you fee’s contented to be gone. Tit . Curfe on thv Roman Rudenefs, that canft fee </l>
<l>Such tears, unmov’d, and mock fuch Mifery ! Oh! r am loft, and \is in vain to drive, Ilf Berenice dies, I cannot live. Fly and prevent that Fate to which (he’s gone. Bid her butlive, tell her theWorld’s her own. [Exit Rut* Paul . Sir 3 if I might advife, you fhould not fend, Rather command her women to attend s </l>
<l>They better can her Melancholy chear , The word is pad, andnow ’tis mean to fear. K favv your melting Pity when (he wept. And my rough heart but very hardly fcap’d. Yet look a little farther and you’! find </l>
<l>That fpite of all your fortune yet is kind. What triumphs the whole World prepares, you’ll fee. And then hereafter think how great you’ll be. Tit. Who for Barbarity would be ador’d! I hate my fel£> Nero fo much abhor’d. That bloody Tyrant, whom I blufh to name S </l>
<l>Was never half fo cruel as I am. No TITVS and BERENICE . No, III purfuethe Queen, (he loves me (till,! Will pardon me when at her feet I kneel: > Let’s go, and let proud Rome (ay what it will. S </l>
<l>Paul. How Sir ? Tit. By Heav’n I know not what I fay : Excefs of Sorrow drives my mind adray. Paul. O follow where your full Renown does lead. Your laft adieus Report abroad has fpread. Rome that did mourn, does now new triumphs frame, The Temples fume with Offerings to your name: The people wild in the applaufe y’have won </l>
<l>With Laurel Wreaths to crown, your Statues run. Tit. By that their Salvage natures they betray. For fo wild beads roar o’r their murder’d prey. Who would havefenfe the fweets of power to prize! Since mod in danger when we highed rife: For who by Greatnefs e’r did happy grow? None but the heavy Slave is truly fo. Who travels all his life in one dull road. And drudging on in quiet, loves his load. Seeking no farther than the needs of Life, Knows what’s his own, and fo exempt from drife </l>
<l>And cherifhes his homely careful wife. Lives by the Clod, and thinks of nothing higher j </l>
<l>Has all, becaufe he cannot much defire. Had I been born fo low, I had been bled </l>
<l>Of what I love, without controul poffed. Never had Honour or Ambition known. Nor ever to be Great, had been undone. [shout within* VauI. The Tribunes, Sir, and Senate with their date, I’th’ name of all the Empire for you wait, Thej’r follow’d too by an impatient throng, Who feem to murmur, you delay fo long. </l>
<l>Titus ^ E </l>
<l>44 TITVS and BERENICE. • t - - . Tit. Toyle me no more* difperfe that clamorous Rout: Tell ’em they fhal! no more have caufe to doubt 5 </l>
<l>The Queens departure they’ll to morrow fee* And me as wretched as they’d have me be* Take this Paulina: bear it to the Queen* [ Writes on a Tablet* </l>
<l>For (hould we meet* I muft relapfe again 3 </l>
<l>I hve bid her here eternally adieu* Stay while (he reads it* and her troubles view* And bring me faithful word* as thou art true. Hold! oh my Heart! yet go* it it muft be done* For what’s neceffity* we cannot (hun. Would I had never known what ’tis to live* Or a new Being to my felf could give. Some monftrous and unheard of Shape now find* As Salvage* and as Barbarous as my mind. . Antiochus t Enter Antiochus* Attendant /* Arfaceso Anti My laft Adieu to pay, I come* and dare in Rowe no longer ftay. My griefs* and my affidtions* grow fo high 5 </l>
<l>If not by abfence flacken’d* I muft dye. Tit . What reafon have the happy to repine? Now Berenice for ever will be thine. With all her charms receive her to thy breft* And be of all I ever lov’d* polled. Ant . It is beneath you 5 Sir* to mock my pain." I ever kneel to Berenice again ! No* (hould I ftay to fee you when you part* Tho I am fure the fight would break my heart* 7 Yet (he, as ftill my prayers have been deny’d 3 </l>
<l>Tho I but beg’d one bl effing ere I dy’d* Even then with fcorn would throw me from her fide. Tit. Oh Heaven! (he s ent ring* from her Charms lets fly 5 </l>
<l>I know my weaknefs 3 if I ftay* I dye. Meet^ </l>
<l>■r TITVS and BERENICE. </l>
<l>Meet 3 and prevent her———- * \ Enter Berenice., &c. </l>
<l>[Ex. Titus. </l>
<l>Ber. How he hafts away ! Ingrateful! Deareft Perjur'd Titw> ftay. [kneels^ </l>
<l>Aftli&ions catch him, great as thofe I bear. My Lord, at latt I have receiv’d my Doom: </l>
<l>a Tis feal’d, but ere I part from you and Ramey </l>
<l>I ask, and I your pardon would receive: Can you the wrongs which I have done, forgive? Ant . I never any Injuries did find , No, Berenice has always been too kind. With one foft word, how fuddenly I’m loft. And have no fenfe of my dilgraces paft ! But muft I then for ever lofe you fo? Iam no Romany nor was ere your foe. No, rather here continue, and be Great, Whilft I live ever hopelefs at your feet. Ber. Should I ftay here and my wrongs tamely bear </l>
<l>From him that fhuns, and flies me every where £ I have a nobler mind, and you (hall fee </l>
<l>1 can difdain and fcorn as much as he i </l>
<l>For tho ’tis true, I never can be yours’. Both Rome and him my heart this hour abjures. Ant. To banilhhim your heart, whilft you prepare. </l>
<l>What will you do with all the Love that’s there ? </l>
<l>There’s no one Mortal can deferve it all, And fure a little to my (hare might fall. Ber. Oh of that killing Subjeft, talk no more, I would have lov’d you, if I could, before. Love for another ftruck me with his Dart, And ’tis not in my power to force my heart. Ant. When firft my Paffion was difdain d for him, ; </l>
<l>You kept me yet alive with your efteem. But now at laft his breach of Faith you fee, And bear it nobly too: how can it be </l>
<l>T‘ your felf fo Juft, and yet fo hard tome? E 2 </l>
<l>46 TITVS and BERENICE. Ber. What cruel ftorms 5 and fierce affaults you make, </l>
<l>To batter down a heart you cannot take ! Till you have broke it. Will you not give o’r ? No, rather let me go 5 and hear no more. Antio o O ftay, fince of the Viftory you are fecure, </l>
<l>Pitty the pains and anguifh I endure 5 </l>
<l>In wounds which you and none but you can cure. </l>
<l>Look back, whilft at‘your feet my (elf I caft. And think the figh that’s coming is my laft. My heart it’s fad eternal farewell takes : Be but fo kind to fee me when it breaks. Ber. Rife, rife my Lord. The Emperor’s return’d. </l>
<l>Conduft me hence, let me not more be fcorn’d. Enter Titus. Tit. How am I loft ! refolve on what I'will*. Spite of my (elf I wander this way ftill. Why would you Berenice my prefence fhun £ Ber. No ! lie hear nothing. I’ve refolv’d on flight. </l>
<l>And will be gone. Why come you in my fight i. </l>
<l>Why come you thus t’exafperate my defpair ? Are you yet not content > I know you are. Tiu If ever yet my heart was dear to yours y </l>
<l>By all our plighted vows, thofe foPteft hours </l>
<l>In which for ever to be true I fwore, I beg that you’d afford me yet one more. Ber . I till to morrow had your leave to ftay 5 </l>
<l>But my refolves are to be gone to day. And I depart. Tit. No journey mu ft you take. Would you poor Titus in his griefs forfake ? No! Stay— Ber . I ftay ! Ungrateful as you are. For what? a Peoples rude affronts to bear. That with the found of my misfortune rend </l>
<l>The Clouds, and fhouts to Heaven in Vollys fend ? </l>
<l>Does not their cruel joy yet reach your ears, </l>
<l>Whilft I alone Torment my felfin tears ? By what offence or crime are they thus mov’d? Alas! what have I done, but too much Lov’d 7 </l>
<l>i </l>
<l>['Emets </l>
<l>Tit. </l>
<l>47 </l>
<l>TltVS and BERENICE. Tit. D you mind the voice of an outragious throng ? </l>
<l>I ever thought your conftancy more ftrong. Never believ'd your heart fo weak could be, Whofe powerful charms had captivated me. Ber . All that I fee diftra&ion does create^ Thefe rich Apartments and this Pompous State* Thefe Places where I fpent my happieft hours. And plighted all my Vows, falfe Man, to yours. All, as moft vile Impoftors I deteft. How ftrangely, Titus> might we have been bled ! Tit . This art to torture fouls where did you learn > </l>
<l>Or was it in your nature with you born ? Oh Berenice ! how you deftroy me \ Atendants, bring your Chair nearer, Ber . No, Return and to your famous Senate go 3 </l>
<l>That for your cruelties applaud you fb. Have you not honour to your full delight ? Have you not promis'd to forget me quite ? What more in expiation can you do? Have you not ever fworn to hate me too ? Tit . Can you do any thing to make me hate } Or can I ever Berenice forget ? This hard fulpition was unjufHy urg'd, 'Gainfl: a poor heart too much before fiircharg d. Oh Madam ! know me better, and recall </l>
<l>The wrong, fince firft I at your feet did fall. Count all the fingle days and minutes paft. Where in my vows and my defires I prefh </l>
<l>And at this time your greateft Conqueft know. For you were never fo belov'd as now. Nor ever- • # Ber. Still your Love you’d have me own. Yet you your felf command me to be gone. Fs my delpair fo charming to your view ? D’ you think the tears I filed are all too few ? Gf fuch a heart, a vain return you make. No never call thofe dear Idea’s back. But fuSer me inthis belief to reft 5 </l>
<l>That fecretly, long fince exil’d your breaft, </l>
<l>l 4 8 XlTVS and BERENICE. I only from a faithlefs wretch depart} And one that never lays the lofs to heart. If you had Lov’d me , this had nere been lent, I-lere you have commanded me to banifhment. [Opens' the Tablett </l>
<l>What wondrous Love you bear me this doth (how. </l>
<l>Ixeadjfread, ungrateful, read and let me go .[Gives himthe Tabelto </l>
<l>Tit. You (hall not go, I have not given confent, Nor will I ever to your baniftiment. Your cruel refolution I defer y, To be reveng’d of me you feek to dye. And then of all I love, except the pain. Nought but the fad remembrance will remain. Antiochus ! be thou a witnefs here f Ber .fmkj damn in Of all my mifery and my defpair. \ a Chair. Antio. Defpait’s a Theam I only underhand. You, if you will, your wifhes may command. Such Beauty ready for pofleflion fee, And leave that ugly hag Defpair, to me. Antio. Behold thole eyes how dull and dark they grow! </l>
<l>Madam, when at your feet I fall thus low, [Kneels. Vouchfafe my fad afflictions to believe, Alas! ’tis all the eafe I’m like to have. When firft the dreadful minute I beheld , That by my duty and the Laws compel’d, I found it forc’d that you muft hence depart. Though nothing ere can baniffl you my heart. ’Twas then my foul had firft a fenfe of fears, Forefeeing your reproaches and your tears. I then expefted, Madam, all the weight </l>
<l>Of woes that can on worft misfortunes light. But whatfoever fears oppreft my heart, I find I but forefaw the leffer part. I thought my vertuenot fo apt to bow j </l>
<l>And am afham’d ’tis thus intangled now. Ber. Let me alone and vex my foul no more. You of your vertue talk’t enough before. Urge it not ftill to aggravate my (hame. When Crown’d with conqueft from the wars you came, I know you brought me but to fill your ftates </l>
<l>For elfe the-triumph had not beerwsamplete. Tit. </l>
<l>TIT VS and BERENICE. 49 Tit. Since you have then refolv’d: It fhall be lo. And judg by this if y’are belov’d or no. No longer Torments on my foul fhall prey. Since I to freedom fee fo brave a way 3 </l>
<l>A way by more than one great Rorr^n fhown 5 </l>
<l>Who, whentheir Mifery’s had preft ’em down? Propt from within, (hook off with life? the weight, y Offers to </l>
<l>And thus fell nobly grapling with their fate. iftabkimfdf </l>
<l>Ber. Oh ftay! to wrong me more what way dy’e take? Would Titus die For Berenices fake? » I fee the blow you cruelly prepare To wound that breaft where I, you fay, have (hare* * To hurt what’s mine would be unjuftly done. No, rather (hike this heart, that’s all your own* • * Tit. Belt of thy fex ! and dearth:, now I fee. How poor is Empire when compar’d to- thee. Hence ye, perplexing Gares, that clog a brain, Whilft ftruck withextafie, I here fall down. [Kneels Thus at your feet a happy proftrate laid. I’m much more bleft than if the world I fvvaid. Ber. Now the. bleft Berenice enough has feen: [Kneels* I thought your Love, had quite extinguifht been: But ’twas my error, for you (till are true. Your heart is troubled^ and your tears I view. Ev’n my worft fufFerings much o’repaid I fee. Nor (hall th’ unhappy world be curft for me. Nothing fince firft ’twas yours, my love would (hake, So abfolute a Conqueft did you make. But now lie bring it to the utmoft teft. And with one fucal A 8 c crown all the reft. Tit. Hah! tell me Berenice what will you do? Ber. Far from your fight and Rome for ever go • I have refolv’don’t, and it fhall be fo. Tit. Antiochus ! I’m born to be undone 3 </l>
<l>When I the greateft conqueft thought t’have won; Ev’n in my nobleft race I am out-run. But thou wer’t always gen’rous, always kind 3 </l>
<l>Your inlarg’d Kingdom fhall to hers be joyn’d. And now how much you are my faithful friend 3 Id $ o T I T V S and BERENICE. In being fo to her, you’l beft exprefs. $ Filling on </l>
<l>Never forfake her in fad diftrefs. ihis neck^ Where e’re (he goes, for everwkh her be. And fometimes in my abfence figh for me. Antio. Arfaces ! on thy bofome let me lye, </l>
<l>VVhilft I but take one laft dear look, and die. Ber. No live : and by a generous ftrife out-do </l>
<l>Us both, and of your felf be conquVour too. Farewel. Let us all three a rare example prove : Ofa moft tender though unhappy love. Thus, Sir, your Peace and Empire I reftore. Farewell and reign. Tie never feeyou more. j_E*. Ber. </l>
<l>Antio. Oh Heaven! Tit . She’s gone and all I valu’d loft : Now Friend, let Rome , of her great Emp’ror boaft. </l>
<l>Since they themfelves firft taught me cruelty, </l>
<l>i le try how much a Tyrant I can be. Henceforth all thoughts of pitty He difown, And with my arms the Univerfe ore-run. Rob’d of my Love, through ruins purchafe fame. And make the world’s as wretched as I am. [Exeunt Omnes. 33 </l>
<l>THE Cheats of Scapin. </l>
<l>Ad Firft. Scene Firft. Eater OBavian^ Shift. OB. P’ | ^HIS is unhappy Hews; I did not exped my Fa¬ </l>
<l>ther in two Months, and yet you fay he is re- </l>
<l>1 turn’d already Sh. ’Tis but too true. OB. That he arriv’d this Morning ? Sh. This very Morning. OB. And that he is come with a refolution to Marry me ? Sh. Yes, Sir, To Marry you. OB. I am ruin’d and undone 5 prithee advife me. Sh. Advife you ? OB. Yes, advife me. Thou art as furly,as if thou really couldft </l>
<l>do me no good. Speak : Has Necellity taught thee no Wit ? </l>
<l>Haft thou no Shift ? Sh. Lord, Sir, I am at prefent very bufie in Contriving fome </l>
<l>Trick to fave my felf 5 I am firft prudent, and then good natur’d. OB. How will my Father rage and ftorm,when he underftands </l>
<l>what things have happen’d in his abfence ? I dread his anger and </l>
<l>reproaches. Sh. Reproaches! Wouldl could be quit of him fo eafily ; me- </l>
<l>thinks I feel him already on my Shoulders. OB. Dif-inheriting is the leaf! I can exped. Sh. Y ou fhould have thought of this before, and not have fallen </l>
<l>in Love with I know not whom, one. that you met by chance in </l>
<l>the Dover- Coach. (be is indeed a good fmug.Lafs, but God knows </l>
<l>what (he isbefides . perhaps fome- OB. Villain. Sh. I have done, Sir, I have done. OB. </l>
<l>F 34 Cheats of Scapin. Oct. I have no Friend that can appeafe my Father’s anger, and </l>
<l>now I (hall be betrayed to want and mifery. Sh. For my part, I know but one Remedy in our misfortunes. Oct. Prithee what is it ? Sh. You know that Rogue and arch-Cheat Scapin. Ott. Well. What of him ? Sh. There is not a more fubtle Fellow breathing • fo cunning, </l>
<l>he can cheat one newly Cheated • ’tis fuch a Wheadling Rogue, </l>
<l>I’ll undertake in two hours he (hall make your Father forgive you </l>
<l>all, nay, allow you Money for your neceffary Debauches: I (aw </l>
<l>him in three days, make an old cautious Lawyer turn Chymift </l>
<l>and Proje&or. Oct. He is the fitted perfon in the World for my Bufinefs. the </l>
<l>Impudent Varlet can do any thing with the peevifli old Man. </l>
<l>Prithee go look him out, we'll fet him a work immediately. Sh. See where he comes—Monfieur Scapin / Enter Scapin. Scap. Worthy Sir! Sh. I have been giving my Madera brief Account of thy mod </l>
<l>Noble Qualities : I told him, thou wert as Valiant as a ridden </l>
<l>Cuckold, Sincere as Whores, Honed as Pimps in want. Scap. Alas Sir ! I but Copy you: ’Tis you are brave * you fcorn </l>
<l>the Gibbets, Halters and Prifons which threaten you, and valiant¬ </l>
<l>ly proceed in Cheats and Robberies. ’ Oct. Oh Scapin ! Iam utterly ruin’d without thy affidance. Scap. Why? What’s the matter good Mr. Oct avian ? Oct. My Father is this day arriv’d at Dover with old Mr. Gripe, </l>
<l>with a refolution to Marry me. Scap. Very well. Oct. Thou knowed I am already Married; How will my Fa¬ </l>
<l>ther relent my Difobedience ? I am for ever lod, unlefs thou canft </l>
<l>find fome means to reconcile me to him. Scap. Does your Father know 7 of your Marriage ? Oct. I am afraid he is by this time acquainted w r ith it. Scap. No matter, no matter, all (hall be w 7 ell: I ampublick-fpi- </l>
<l>tited ; I love to help diftreded young Gentlemen, and thank </l>
<l>Heav’n I have had good fuccefs enough. Oct. Befides, My prefent want mud be confidered, I am in re¬ </l>
<l>bellion without, any Money. Scap. * Cheats' of Scapin. 35 Scab. IhaveTricksandShiftstooto getthat: lean cheat upon </l>
<l>occafion • but Cheating is now grown an ill Trade • yet Heav’n </l>
<l>be thank’d, there were never more Cullies and Tools ; but the </l>
<l>great Rooks and Cheats allow’d by publick Authority, ruin'fuch </l>
<l>little Undertraders as I am. OB. Well, Get thee ftraight about thyBus’nefs: Canft thou </l>
<l>make no ufe of my Rogue here ? Scap. Yes, Khali want his afliftance • the Knave has Cunning, </l>
<l>and may be ufeful. Sh. Ay Sir. But like other wife Men, Iamnotover-Valiant : </l>
<l>Pray leave me out of this Bus’nels; my Tears will betray you ; </l>
<l>you (hall execute, I’ll fit at home and advife. Scap. I (land not in need of thy Courage, but thy Impudence, </l>
<l>and thou haft enough of that: Come, come, thou (halt along - </l>
<l>What, Man, ftand out for a Beating ? That’s the worlt can </l>
<l>happen. Sh. Well, well. Enter Clara OB. Here comes my deareft Clara. Cla. Ah me OB avian /1 hear fad News; They fay, your Father </l>
<l>is return’d. OB. Alas! ’Tis true, and I am the moft unfortunate perfon in </l>
<l>the World ; but’tis not my own mifery that I confider,but yours: </l>
<l>How can you bear thofe wants to which we muft be both reduc’d ? Oar. Love (hall teach me, that can make all things eafie to us, </l>
<l>which is a fign it is the chiefeft good: But I have other Cares; </l>
<l>Will you be ever conftant ? Shall not your Father’s Severity con- </l>
<l>ftrain you to be falfe ? OB. Never, my deareft, never. Oar. They that love much, may be allow’d fome fears. Scap. Come, come • we have now no time to hear you fpeak </l>
<l>fine tender things to one another : Pray do you prepare to encoun¬ </l>
<l>ter with your Father. Oar. I tremble at the thoughts of it. Scap. You muft appear refolute at firft: Tell him you can live </l>
<l>without troubling him • threaten him to turn Souldier ; or what </l>
<l>will frighten him worfe, fay, you’ll turn Poet. Come, I’ll war¬ </l>
<l>rant you, we bring him to Compofition. OB. What would I give ’twere over ? F 2 ’ Scap. </l>
<l>3 6 Cheat / of Scapin. Scap. Let us p.rac'tile a little what you are to da. Suppofe ms </l>
<l>your Father, very grave and very angry. Ott. Well. Scap. Do you look very carelefly, like a fmall Courtier upon his </l>
<l>Country Acquaintance^ a little more furlily: —Very well:—Now I come full of my Fatherly Authority.-- Otftavian, Thou makeft me weep to fee thee • but alas they are </l>
<l>not tears of joy,but tears of forrow. Did ever fo good a Father </l>
<l>beget fo lewd a Son? Nay, but for that I think thy Mother Ver- </l>
<l>tuous , I ihould pronounce thou art not mine ; Afewgate-Bird, </l>
<l>Rogue, Villain, what a Trick haft thou play’d me in my abfence ? </l>
<l>Marry’d? Yes: but to whom? Nay that thou knoweft not. FI </l>
<l>warrant you fome Waiting-Woman corrupted in a Civil Family, </l>
<l>and reduc’d to one of the Play-Houfes, remov’d from thence by </l>
<l>fome Keeping Coxcomb, or- C/a. Hold Scapin, Hold—— Saap. No offence Lady, I fpeak but anothers words. Thou abominable Rafcal, thou fnall not have a groat, not a </l>
<l>groat. Befides, I will break all thy bones ten times over- get thee </l>
<l>out of my houfe—Why Sir, you reply not a word, but ftand as </l>
<l>balhfully, as a Girl that’s examin’d by a Bawdy Judge, about a </l>
<l>Rape. on. Look yonder comes my Father. Scap. Stay Shift, and get you two gone, let me alone to manage </l>
<l>the old fellow’. \_ExitOn. and Clara, Enter Thrifty. Th. Was there ever fuch a rafli aftion ? Scap. He has been inform’d of the Bufinefs,and is now fo full of </l>
<l>it, that he vents it to himfelf. Th. I would fain hear what they can fay for themfelves. Scap. We are not unprovided. \_TJt a dijlance. Th. Will they be fo Impudent to deny the thing ? Scap. We never intend it. Th. Or will they endeavour to excufe it ? • Scap. That perhaps we may doe. Th. But all (hall be in vain. Scap. Wei try that. Th. I know how to lay that Rogue my Son faff. Scap. That w r e muft prevent. </l>
<l>Cheats of Scapin. Th. And for that Tatterdemaliion^//>,rie thrafli him to death, </l>
<l>I will be three Years a Cudgelling him. Th. I wondred he had forgot me fo long. Th. Oh Oh / Yonder the Rafcal is, that brave Governour, he </l>
<l>tutor’d my Son finely. Scap. Sir, lam overjoyed at your fafe return. Th. Good morrow Scipin , indeed you hive followed my In- </l>
<l>ftru&ions very exa&ly, my Son has behaved himfelf very pru¬ </l>
<l>dently inmyabfence, has he not Rafcal, has he not? Scap. I hope you are very well. Th. Very well — Thou fayft not a word Varlet, thou fayft not </l>
<l>a word. Scap. Had you a good Voyage Mr. Thrifty ? Th. Lord Sir! A very good Voyage, pray give a Man a little </l>
<l>leave to vent his Choler. Scap. Would you be in Choler Sir? Th. Ay, Sir, I would be in Choler. Scap. Pray with whom? Th. With that confounded Rogue there. Scap. Upon what reafon ? Th. Upon what reafon ? haft thou not heard what hath hap¬ </l>
<l>pened in my abfcence. Scap. I have heard a little Idle ftory. Th. A little Idle ftory. Quoth a! why Man,my Son’s undorifcj </l>
<l>my Son’s undone. Scap. Come, come, things have not been well carried, but I </l>
<l>would advife you to make no more of it. Th. I am not of your opinion, I’le make the whole Town ring </l>
<l>of it. Scap. Lord Sir, I have ftormed about this bufinefs as much </l>
<l>as you can do for your Heart, but what are we both the bet¬ </l>
<l>ter ? I told him indeed, Mr.Offavian, you do not do well,to wrong </l>
<l>fo good a Father: I preached him three or four times afleep, but </l>
<l>all would not do,'till at laft,when I had well examined the Bufinels </l>
<l>I found you ha'd not fo much wrong done you as you Imagine. Th. How not wrong done me to have my Son married without </l>
<l>my o~nfent to a Beggar ! Scap. Alas he was ordained to it. Th. That’s fine indeed, we (hall fteal, cheat, murder, and fo be </l>
<l>hang’d, then fay we were ordained to it, Scap. Cheats of Scapin. </l>
<l>Soup. Truly I did not think you fo fubtile a Phylo'opherJ mean </l>
<l>he was fatally engaged in this affair. Th. Why did he Engage himfelf? Scap. Very true indeed, very true ; but fie upon you now, </l>
<l>would you have him as wife as your felf, } oung men will have </l>
<l>their follies,witnefs my charge Leander; who has gon and thrown </l>
<l>away him felf at a fixanger rate then your Son, I would fain know </l>
<l>if you were not once young your felf • yes I warrant you, and had </l>
<l>your frailties. Th. Yes,but they never coft me any thing; a man may be as </l>
<l>frail and as wicked as he pleafe, if it coft him nothing. Scap. Alas he was fo in Love with the young wench, that if he </l>
<l>had not had her, he muft have certainly hang’d himfelf ; Sh. Muft! why he had already done it. But that I came very </l>
<l>feafonabiy and cut the rope. Th. Didft thou cut the rope, Dog ? Tie Murtherthee for that </l>
<l>thou fliouldeft have let him hang. Scap. Befides, her Kindred furprized him with her, and forc’t </l>
<l>him to marry her. Th. Then fiiould he have prefently gone, and protefted againft </l>
<l>the Violence at a Notaries. Scap. O Lord Sir, he fcorn’d that. Th. Then might I eafily have difanulled theMartiage. Scap. Difanul the marriage. Th. Yes. Scap. You (ball not break the marriage. Th. Shall not I break it ? </l>
<l>.Scap. No. Th. What (ball not I elaim the priviledge of a Father, and have </l>
<l>the Satisfaction for the violence done to my Son ? Scap. ’Tis a thing he will never confent to. Th. He v ill not confent to] Scap. No. Would you have him confefs he was he&or’d into a- </l>
<l>ny thing, that is to declare himfelf a Coward : Oh fie Sir, one </l>
<l>that has Honour ofbeing your Son, can never do fuch a thing. Th. Pifh, ta.k not to me of Honour, he (hah do it or be dif-in- </l>
<l>herited. Scap. Who {hall dif-inherit him ? Th. That will I Sir. Scap. Youdif-inheritbim ] very good. </l>
<l>39 </l>
<l>Cheats of Scapin. Th. How very good? Scap. You (hall not dif-inherit him. Th. Shall not I dif-inherit him? Sc.tp. No. Th. No! Sc.ip. No. Th. Sir, you are very merry • I (lull not difinherit my Son ? Sc up. No I tell you. Th. Pray who fliallhinder me? Scap. Alas Sir, your own felf Sir; your own felf. Th. I my (elf? Scap. Yes Sir, for you can never have the Heart to do it. Th. You (hall find I can Sir. Scap. Come you deceive your felf. Fatherly affection muff: (liow </l>
<l>it felf, it mud, it mufl; do not I know you were ever tender hear¬ </l>
<l>ted. Th. Y’are miftaken Sir,Y’are miftaken:— Pi(h,why do I fpend </l>
<l>my time in tittle tattle with this Idle fellow?— Hang-dog go find out my rake-hell -- [to Shift. whii'ft I go to my Brother Gripe and Inform him of my misfor¬ </l>
<l>tune. Scap. In the mean time if I can do you any fervice.— Th. Oh ! I thank you Sir, I thank you.- [Exit Thrift. Shift. I mufl: confefs thou art a brave Fellow,and our affairs be¬ </l>
<l>gin to be in a better pofture —but the money, the money— we </l>
<l>are abominable poor, and my Mafter has lean Vigilant dunns that </l>
<l>torment him more than an old Mother does a poor Gallant, when </l>
<l>(he folicits a maintenance for her difcarded Daughter. Scap. Your money (hall be my next care-let me fee, I want a fellow to— Canft thou not Counterfeit a roaring Bully of Alfatia-l </l>
<l>— Stalk— look big— very well. Follow me,I have ways to dif- </l>
<l>guifethy voice and countenance. Sh. Pray take a little care and lay your plot fo that I may not </l>
<l>adt the Bully all wayes, I would not be beaten like a Bully. Scap. We’l (hare the danger, we’l (hare the danger. Exeunt. </l>
<l>Adi 40 </l>
<l>Cheats of Scapin. ✓ ACT II. SCENE I- Enter Thrifty and Gripe. Gr. Olr, what you tell me concerning your Son, hath ftrangely </l>
<l>l3 fruftrated our Defigns. Thr. Sir, trouble not your lelf about my Son, I have underta¬ </l>
<l>ken to remove all Obftacles, which is the bufmefs I amfovigo- </l>
<l>roufly in purfuit of. Gr. In troth, Sir, I’l tell you what I fay to you, The Education </l>
<l>of Children after the getting of e’m, ought to be the neareft Con¬ </l>
<l>cern of a FatherAnd had you tutored your Son w'ith that Care </l>
<l>and Duty incumbent on you, he never could fo flightly have for¬ </l>
<l>feited his. Thr. Sir, to return you a Sentence for your Sentence.Thofe that </l>
<l>are fo quick to Cenfure and condemn the Conduct of others, </l>
<l>ought firft to take Care that all be well at home. Gr. Why Mr. Thrifty Jaws you heard any thing concerning my </l>
<l>Son ? Thr. It may be I have, and it may be worfe than of my own. Gr. What is’t I pray ? My Son? Thr. Ev’n your own Scapin told it me, and you may hear it, </l>
<l>from him or fomebodyelfe; For my part, I am your Friend, and </l>
<l>would not willingly be the Meffengerof ill news to one that I </l>
<l>think fo to me: Your Servant: I mull haften to my Councel to </l>
<l>advife what’s to be done in this Cafe.God-bu’y till I fee you again. \_Ex. Thrifty. Gr. Worfe than his Son! For my part I cannot imagine how- </l>
<l>For a Son to marry impudently without the Confent of his Fa¬ </l>
<l>ther, is as great an Offence as can be imagin’d I take it: But </l>
<l>yonder he comes. _ Enter Leander. Lewd. Oh my Dear Father, how Joyful am I to fee you fafely </l>
<l>return’d. Welcome as the Bleffing which I am now craving will be. Gr. Not fo faff Friend’a mine,foft and fair goes far Sir. You are </l>
<l>my Son, as I take it. Leand. What d ee mean Sir? Gr. Stand ftill, and let me look yee in the Face. Teand. Cheats of Scapiru 4 1 Leand. How muft I ftand Sir ? Gr. Look upon me with both Eyes; Leand. Well Sir Ido. Gr. What’s the meaning of this Report? Leand. Report, Sir ? Gr. Yes Report Sir, I fpeak Englifh as I take it, What i's't that </l>
<l>you have done in my abfence ? Leand. What is’t Sir which you would have had me done ? Gr. I do not ask you what I would have had you done; but </l>
<l>what you have done. Lewd. Who I Sir? Why I have done nothing at all, not I Sir. Gr. Nothing at all! (Leand.) No Sir, Gr. You have no Impudence to fpeak on. Leand. Sir, I have the Confidence that becomes a Man,and my </l>
<l>Innocence. Gr. Very well, But Scapin , d’ye mark me young man ^Scapin has </l>
<l>told me l'ome tales of your Behaviour ? Leand. Scapin ! Gr. Oh have I caught you? That name makes ye blulhdo’s it? </l>
<l>’ Tis well you have fome Grace left. Leand. Has he faid any thing concerning me ? Gr. That (hall be examined anon. In the mean while get you </l>
<l>home d’ye hear. And ftay till my return. But look to’t, if thou </l>
<l>haft done any thing to diflionour me, never think to come within </l>
<l>my Doors, or fee my Face more; but expert to be as mi ('enable as </l>
<l>thy folly and poverty can make thee. [Exit. Gr. Leand. Very fine: I am in a hopeful Condition. This Ralcal </l>
<l>has betrayed my marriage and undone me: Now there is no way </l>
<l>left but to turn Outlaw, and live by rapine: and to fet my hand </l>
<l>in. the firft thing fliall be to Cut the throat of that perfidious </l>
<l>Pick-thank Dog that has ruined me. Enter Od. and Scapin. OB. Dear Scapin , how infinitely am I obliged to thee for thy </l>
<l>Care! Leand , Yonder he comes: I’m overjoyed to fee you good Mr.' </l>
<l>Dog/ Scap. Sir your moft humble Servant, You honour me too far. L.eand. You ad an ill fools part, But I (hall teach you. Scap. Sir. Oct. </l>
<l>G Cheatf of Scapin. </l>
<l>OB, Hold Leander . Leand. No, OBavian, lie make him confefs theTreachery he </l>
<l>has committed; yes Varlet Dog, I know the trick you have playd </l>
<l>me: you thought perhaps no body would have told me. But i’ie </l>
<l>make you confefs it, or He run my Sword in your Guts. Scap. Oh Sir 5 Sir, would you have the heart to do fuch a thing? </l>
<l>have I done you any Injury Sir ? . Leand. Yes Rafcal that you have, and lie make you own it too, </l>
<l>or Tie fwing it out of your already tan’d thick hide. [Beats hwf\ Scap. The Devil's in’t, Lord Sir, what d'yeemean? Nay good </l>
<l>Mr. Lewder , pray Mr. Lewder ; Squire Lewder — As I hope to </l>
<l>be faved— OB, Prithee be quiet: for (hame enough:— [Interpofetb ] Scap. Well Sir, I confefs indeed that- Lewd. What ! fpeak Rogue. Scap. About two Months agoeyou may remember, a Maid Ser¬ </l>
<l>vant dyed in the hou fe.— Lewd. What of all that ? Scap. Nay Sir, if I confefs you mull not be angry. Leand. Well go on. Scap. 'Twasfaidfliedyed for loveofmeSir ; But let that pafs. Leand. Death, you trifling Buffoon ; Scap. About a week after her death, I dreft my felf up li^ke her </l>
<l>Ghoft, and went into Madam Lucia your Miftreffes Chamber* </l>
<l>where (lie lay half in half out of bed, with her woman by her,read- </l>
<l>ing an ungodly Play-book, Leand. And was it your Impudence did that ? Scap. They both beleive it was a Ghoft to this hour. But it </l>
<l>was my felf playd the Goblin to fright her from the Scurvy Cu- </l>
<l>ftome oflying awake at thofe unfeafonable hours, hearing filthy </l>
<l>Plays when (he had never laid her Prayers. Leand. I (hall remember you for all in time, and place; But </l>
<l>come to the point, and tell me what thou haft faid to my Father. Scap. To you Father? I have not fo much as feen him fince his re¬ </l>
<l>turn, and if you’d ask him he’ll tell you fo himfelf. Leand. Yesfie has told me himfelf,and told me all thou haft faid </l>
<l>tb him! Scap. With your good leave Sir, thenhely’d, I beg your par¬ </l>
<l>don I mean he was miftaken. [Enter Sly~] Sly , Oh Sir, I bring you the moft unhappy news. Leand * </l>
<l>43 </l>
<l>Cheats of Scapin. Lewd. Whats the matter ? Sly. Your Miftrefs Sir, is yonder arrefted in an A&ion of 200 1. </l>
<l>They fay tis a debt (he left unpaid at London . in the haft of her </l>
<l>el'cape hither to Dover , and if you do not raife money within this </l>
<l>two hours to difcharge her, Shee’i be hurried to prifon. Leand. Within this two hours? Sly. Yes Sir, within this two hours. Leand. Ah my poor Scapin^ I want thy affiftance. fScapin walks about Surlily ] Scab. Ah my poor Scapin ] Now I’m your poor Scapin now </l>
<l>you’ve need of me. Leand. No more.- I pardon thee all that thou haft done, and </l>
<l>worfe if thou art guilty of it. Scab. No no, never pardon me, run your Sword in my Guts , </l>
<l>you’l do better to Murder me. Leand. For Heaven’s fake; think no more upon that, but ftudy </l>
<l>now to affift me. Oct. You muft do fomething for him. Scap. Yes to have my bones broken for my pains. Leand. Would you leave me Scapin in this fevere extremity! Scap. To put fuch an affront upon me as you did • Leand. 1 wrong’d thee I confefs. Scap. To ufe me like a Scoundrel, a Villain, a Rafcal, to threa¬ </l>
<l>ten to run your Sword in my Guts. Leand. I cry thy Mercy withall my Heart, and ifthou wilt have </l>
<l>me throw my felf at thy Feet, 1’le doo’t. Oct. Faith Scapin you muft, you cannot but yield. Scap. Well then; But d’yee mark me Sir, another time better </l>
<l>words and gentler blows. • Leand. Will you promife to mind my bufinefs ? Scap. As I fee convenient, Care (hall be taken, Leand. But the time you know is Ihort. Scap. Pray Sir, don’t be fo troublefome: How much money is’t </l>
<l>you want ? Leand. Two hundred pounds.— (Scap.) And you?— (Off.) As </l>
<l>much. , Scap. No more tobefaid. It (hall be done-For ^ </l>
<l>you the Contrivance is laid already • and for yourf </l>
<l>Father though he be covetous to the laft degree, C Leander. Yet thanks be to Heaven hee’s but a (hallow per- j G 2 fon. 44 Cheats of Scapin. Ion, his parts are not extraordinary, do not take it ill Sir, for you </l>
<l>havenorefemblanceofhim. But that y’are very like him . Begon </l>
<l>I fee Oct av tins Father coming, I’le begin with him. \_Exemt Oct. and Eeand. \_Enter Thrifty] Here he comes mumbling and chewing the Cud to prove him- </l>
<l>felfa clean Beall. Thr. Oh audacious Boy, to commit fo infolent a Crime, and </l>
<l>plunge himfelf into fuch a mifchiefi Scap, Sir, your humble Servant. Thr. How do you Scapin ? Scap. What, you are ruminating on your Sons ralh Action. 7 hr. Have I not reafon to be troubled ? Scap. Thelifeofman isfull of troubles, that’s the truth on’t; </l>
<l>But your Philofopher is alwaies prepared I remember an Excellent </l>
<l>Proverb of the Ancients, very fit for your Cafe. Thr. What’s that? Scap. Pray mind it, ’twill do ye a World of good. Thr. What is’t I ask you ? Scap. Why 5 When the Matter of a Family (hall be abfent any </l>
<l>confiderable time from his home or Manfion, he ought rationally, </l>
<l>gravely, wifely, and Philofophically, to revolve within his mind </l>
<l>all the concurrent Circumftances, that may during the Interval </l>
<l>confpire to the Conjunction of thofe misfortunes, and trouble- </l>
<l>fome accidents, that may intervene upon the faidabfence, and the </l>
<l>interruption of his Oeconomical inl'pci'tion, into the remifsnefs, </l>
<l>negligences, frailties, and huge andperillous Errours, which his </l>
<l>Subftitutes, Servants, or Truftees, may be capable of,'or liable </l>
<l>and obnoxious unto , which may ariie from the imperfection </l>
<l>and corruptnefsof ingenerated Natures, or the taint and conta¬ </l>
<l>gion of corrupted Education , whereby the Fountain-head of </l>
<l>Man’s Difpofition becomes muddy, and all the Streams ofhis Man¬ </l>
<l>ners and Conversation run consequently defiled, anJimpure: </l>
<l>Thefe things premised, and fore-confidered, arm the faid pru¬ </l>
<l>dent Philofophical Pater Eamlias , to find his H rufe laid watte, </l>
<l>his Wife murdered, his, Daughters deflowred,*his Sons hang’d: Cum mult is ati'k p* W une perfcrtbere longum ejl. </l>
<l>and to thank Heaven tis no worfe too: D’ye mark. Sir? Thr. S’death ! Is all this a Proverb ? Scap. Cheats of Scapin. 45 Scap. Ay, and the beft Proverb, andthewifeft in the World: </l>
<l>Good Sir, get it by heart: Twill do ye the greateft good imagi¬ </l>
<l>nable • and don’t trouble your felf: lie repeat it to you, till you </l>
<l>have gotten it by hear*. Thr. No, I thank you, Sir, I’ll have none on’t. Scap. Pray do • you’l like it better next time ; hear it once </l>
<l>more, I fay-When the Mafter of a-- Thr. Hold, hold, I have better thoughts of my own , I’m </l>
<l>going to my Lawyer, I’ll null the Marriage. Scap. Going to Law ! Are ye mad to venture your felf among </l>
<l>Lawyers ? Do you not fee every day how the Spunges fuck poor </l>
<l>Clyents, and with a company of foolifh, non-fenlical terms, and </l>
<l>knavith tricks,undo the Nation: No, you lhall take another way. Thr. You have reafon, if there were any other way.’ Scap. Gome, I have found one. The-truth is, I have a great </l>
<l>compaflion for your grief, I cannot when I fee tender Fathers af¬ </l>
<l>flicted for their Sons mil'carriages, but have bowels for ’em, I </l>
<l>have much ado to refrain weeping for you. Thr. Truly my Cafe is fad, very fad. Scap. So it is; tears will burft out , I have a great refpeCt for </l>
<l>your perlbn. Q Counterfeits weeping. Thr. Thank you with all my heart , in troth we ihouldhavea </l>
<l>fellow-feeling. Scap. Ay, fo w 7 e (hould ; I aflure you there is not a perfon in </l>
<l>the World whom I refpeCt more than the Noble Mr. Thrifty. Thr. Thou art honeft Scapin. Ha’ done, ha’ done. Scap. Sir, Your moft humble Servant. Thr. But w 7 hat is your way ? Scap. Why, In brief I have been with the Brother of her whom </l>
<l>your wicked Son has Married. Thr. What is he? . v: . Scap. A moft outragious roaring Fellow, with a down-hang¬ </l>
<l>ing Look, contracted Brow , with a fwell’d red Face enflam’d </l>
<l>with Brandy, one that frowns, puffs, and looks big at all Man¬ </l>
<l>kind, roars out Oaths and bellows out Curfes enough in a Day, </l>
<l>to ftrve a Garrifon a Week •, bred up in blood and rapine, ufed to </l>
<l>daughter from his youth upwards -, one that makes no more con- </l>
<l>fcience of killing a Man, than cr.icking of a Lowfe; hehaskilled </l>
<l>fixteen, four for taking the Wall of him, five for looking too big </l>
<l>upon him, two he Ihot pilling againft the Wall: Inlhort, he is </l>
<l>the moft dreadful of all the Race of Bu Hies, Thr. Cheats of Scapin. </l>
<l>Thr. Heav n ! How do I tremble at the Defcription? But what’s </l>
<l>this to my Bufmefs ? Scap. Why, He (as moft Bullies are) is in want, and I have </l>
<l>brought him, by threatning him with ail theCourfesof Law, all </l>
<l>theafiiftance ot your Friends, and your great Purfe, (in which I </l>
<l>ventur’d my life ten times, for fo % often he drew and run at me) yet, </l>
<l>I fay, at laft I have made him hearken to aCompofition, and to </l>
<l>null the Marriage for a fum of Money. Thr. Thanks, Scapin ^ but what fum? Scap. Faith, He was damnably unreafonable at firft, and gad </l>
<l>I told him fo very roundly. Thr. A Pox on him, what did heask ? Scap. Ask? Hang him, why he ask’d 500/. Thr . Ouns and Heart, 500 /. Five hundred Devils take him,— </l>
<l>and fry and frigaffee the Dog; does he take me for a mad-Man ? Scap. Why, folfaid; and after much argument/brought him </l>
<l>to this; Dammee, fays he, /am going to the Army, and/muft </l>
<l>have Tw'o good Horfes for my felf, for fear one (hould die ; and </l>
<l>thofe will coft at leaft Threefcore Guinea’s. Thr. Hang him Rogue / Why (hould he have tw r o Horfes ? But </l>
<l>/care npt if I give Threefcore Guinea’s to be rid of this Affair. Scap. Then, fays he, my Piftols, Saddle, Hofe, Cloth, and all, </l>
<l>will coft Twenty more. Thr. Why, That’s Fourfcore. Scap. Well reckoned; faith, this Arithmatick is a fine Art </l>
<l>Then /muft have One for my Boy, will coft Twenty more. Thr. Oh the Devil! Confounded Dog ! Let him go and be </l>
<l>damn’d, I’ll give him nothing. Scap. Sir. Thr. Not a Sous, damn’d Rafcal, let him turn Foot-Souldier </l>
<l>•andbehang’d. Scap:- HehasaManbefides; Would you have him go a Foot ? Tmi Ay, - and his Matter too, I’ll have nothing to do with him. Scap. Well, Youarerefolv d tolpend twice as much at Doctors </l>
<l>Commons, you are, you will ftand out for fuch a Sum as this; do. Thr. Hah ! Oh damn’d unconicionable Rafcal ! well if i anuft </l>
<l>be -fo. ' Let him have the. other twenty. Scap. Twenty' ! why it;comes to forty. Thr. No Fie have nothing to : do in it.Oh a Coveteous Rogue ! </l>
<l>I wonder he is not afhamed to be lb Covetous. Scap. </l>
<l>Cheatf of Scapin. 47 Scap. Why this is nothing to the Charge at Doctors Commons, </l>
<l>and though her Brother has no Money, Are has an Uncle able to </l>
<l>defend her. Thr. Oh Eternal Rogue! well I muft do’t,the Divels in him I </l>
<l>think ! Scap. Then faies he, I muft carry into Trance money to buy a </l>
<l>Mule to carry- Thr. Let him to the Devil with his Mule, l ie appeal to the </l>
<l>Judges. Scap. Nay good Sir, think a little. Thr. No, l’le do nothing. Scap. Sir, Sir, but one little Mule? Thr. No not fo much as an Afs! j Scap. Confider. Thr. I will not confider, Tie go to Law. Scap. I am fure if you go to Law you do not confider the Ap- </l>
<l>peales, Degrees of Jurifdidion, the intricate proceedings, the Kna¬ </l>
<l>veries, the Craving of fo many Ravenous Animals that will prey </l>
<l>upon you, Villanous Harpies / Promoters, Tipftaves,and the like* </l>
<l>None of which but will puffaway the cleared right in the World </l>
<l>for a Bribe ; on the other fide the Prodor (hall fide with your Ad- </l>
<l>verfary, And fell your caufe for ready Money; Your Advocate (hall </l>
<l>be'gained the fame way, Andfliallnot be found when your caufe </l>
<l>is to be heard: Law 7 is a torment of all torments. Thr. That’s true: Why what does the damn’d Rogue --rec¬ kon for his Mule ? Scap. Why for Horfes,Furniture,Mule, andtopayfome Scores </l>
<l>that are due to his Landlady, he demands and will have two hun¬ </l>
<l>dred pounds. Th. Come, come, let’s go to Law. c Thr. walks up and down Scap. Do but refled upon— d in a great heat. Th. l’le go to Law? Scap. Do not plunge your felf. Thr. To Law l’le tell you ? Scap. Why there’s for Procuration, Prefentation, Council, Pro¬ </l>
<l>ductions, Prodors, Attendance,, and fcribling vaft Volumes of </l>
<l>Interrogatories, Depofitions,and Articles,Confultations and Plead¬ </l>
<l>ings ofDodors,for the Regifter,Subftitute, Judgments,Signings— </l>
<l>Expedition Fees,befides the vaftPrefents to them and their Wives, </l>
<l>Hang t, the Fellow is out of Employment, give him the money, </l>
<l>give him it 1 fay. • Thr.. </l>
<l>48 Cheats of Scapin. Thr. What, two hundred pounds! Scap. Ay, ay, why you’l g.un 150/. by it, I have fumm’d it up* </l>
<l>I fay give it him, I, faith do. Thr. What 200/. Scap. Ay,befides you ne’re think how they ’1 rail at you in plead¬ </l>
<l>ing,tell all your Fornications,Baftardings,and Commutingsin their </l>
<l>Courts, Thr. I defie ’em, let ’em tell of my whoring,’tis the fafhion. Scap. Peace,Here’s the Brother. Thr. Oh Heaven! what lhall l do. (Enter Shift difguifed ( like a Bully. S h. Damme,where is this confounded Dog, this Father of OCi.x - </l>
<l>viaftt Null the Marriage: By all the Honour of my Anceftors l’le </l>
<l>chine the Villain. Thr. Oh, Oh/ \Hides himfelf behind Scapin] S cap. He cares not Sir, He’l not give the 200 /. Sh. By Heaven, he (lull be Worms-meat within thefe two </l>
<l>hours. Scap. Sir,hehas Courage, he fears you not. Tb. You lye, I have not Courage, I do fear him mortally. Sh. He! he lOundshe 1 would all his Family were in him, I’d </l>
<l>cut off Root and Branch: Dilhonour my Sifter / This in his Guts: </l>
<l>What Fellow’s that ? Hah! Sup. Not he. Sir. Sh. Nor none of his Friends ? Th. No, Sir: Hang him, I am his mortal Enemy. Sh. Art thou the Enemy of that Rafcal. Th. Oh! ay, hanghim-Oh damn’d Bully! ( ptfide. Sh. Give me thy hand, old Boy, the next Sun (hall not fee the </l>
<l>impudent Rafcal alive. Sup. He’ll mufter up all his Relations againft you. Th. Do not provoke him, Scapin. Sh Would they were all here : Ha! hah! c He foyns every way </l>
<l>luh' Here I had one through the Lungs ; l rvith hte Sword. </l>
<l>there another into the Heart; Ha! there another into the Guts: </l>
<l>Ah Rogues! there I was with you. Hah --- hah / • Sup. Hold. Sir, we are none of your Enemies. Sh] No butlwill find the Villains out while my Blood is up-I will deftroV the whole Family. Ha,- ha, --- hah / (Zx.Shirt. Th Here Scapi*. 1 have two hundred Guineas about me,ta.:e 1 am.. Cheats of Scapin. 49 e’m, No more to be laid, Let me never fee his face again, take e m </l>
<l>I fay, This is the Devil. Sc dp. Will you notgive e’m him your felf? Th. No, no] I will never fee him more. I fhall not recover this </l>
<l>thefe three Months. See the bufinefs done, I truft in thee, Honeft </l>
<l>Sctpin: I mull: repofe fomewhere; I am mightily out of Order—■ </l>
<l>A plague on all Bullies I fay. [Exit Thrifty. Scap. So ther’s one difpatcht, I rauft now find out Gripe ; He’s </l>
<l>here-, how Heaven brings e’m into my Nets one after another / Enter Gripe. Scxp. Oh Heaven 1 Unlookt for misfortune, poor Mr. Gripe , </l>
<l>what wilt thou do [walks about dijlractedly Grip. What’s that he lays of me ? Scap. Is there nobody can tell me News of Mr. Gripe ? Grip. Who’s there Scapin'. Scap. How I run up and down, to find him to go purpofe ' Oh! </l>
<l>Sir, is there no way to hear of Mr. Gripe ? Grip. Art thou blind,I have been juft under thy Nofe this hour. Scap. Sir,- Grip. What’s the matter ? Scap. Oh! Sir your Son-— Grip. Hah,my Son—■— Scap. Is fallen into theftrangeft misfortune in the World. Grip. Whatis’t — Scap. I met him a while ago, diforderedforfomethingyou had </l>
<l>faid to him, wherein you very idly made ufe of my Name. And </l>
<l>feeking to divert his Melancholy,we went to walk upon the Pier > </l>
<l>amongft other things he took particular Notice of a New Caper </l>
<l>in her full Trim, the Captain invited us aboard, and gave us the </l>
<l>handfomeft Collation I ever met with. Grip. Well, and where’s the difafter of all this ? Scap. While we were eating he put to Sea • and when we were </l>
<l>at a good diftance from the Shoar, He dilcover’d himfelf to be an </l>
<l>English Renegade that was entertain’d in the Dutch Service • And </l>
<l>fent me offin his Long-Boat to tell you,That if you do not forth¬ </l>
<l>with fend him two hundred pounds, he’l carry away your Son </l>
<l>Prifoner. Nay, for ought I know he may carry him a Slave to sTigier. Gr. How in the Devils name ? 200 /.' H Scap. </l>
<l>50 Cheats of Scapin. Sea. Yes Sir, and more then that, he has allowed me but an </l>
<l>hours time; you muft advife quickly what courfe to take to fave </l>
<l>an only Son. Gr. What a Devil had he to do a Shipboard ? —Run quick¬ </l>
<l>ly Scapin, and tell the Villain lie fend my Lord Chief Juftices </l>
<l>Warrant after him. Sea. Ola law! his Warrant in the open Sea,d’ye think Pyrates </l>
<l>are Fooles? Gr. I’th Devils name what bufinefs had he a Shipboard ? Sea. There is an unlucky Fate that often hurries Men to mif- </l>
<l>chief, Sir. Gr. Scapin thou muft now aft the part of a faithful Servant. Sea. As how, Sir? Gr. Thou muft go bid the Pyrate fend me my Son and ftay </l>
<l>as a pledge in his room, till I can raife the Money. So*. Alas Sir, think you the Captain has fo little wit as to </l>
<l>accept of fuch a poor Rafcally fellow as I am, inftead of your Son ? Gr. What a Devil did he do a Shipboard ? Sea. D’ye remember, Sir, that you have but two hours time, Gr. Thou fay’ft he demands.'- Sea. 200 1 . Gr. 200 l. Has the fellow no Confcience ? Sea. O law ! the Confcience of a Pyrate, why very few lawful </l>
<l>Captains have any. Gr. Has he no reafon neither ? Do’s he know what the Sum </l>
<l>of 200 /. is. Sea. Yes Sir, Tarpawlins are a fort of People that underftand </l>
<l>Money , though they have no great acquaintance with Sence. </l>
<l>But for Heav’ns fake difpatch. Gr. Here take the key of my Compting Houfe, Sea. So. Gr. And open it. Scap. Very good. Gr. In the left hand Window lyes the Key of my Garret , go </l>
<l>take all the Cloaths that are in the great Cheft, and fell ’em to the </l>
<l>Brokers, to redeem my Son. t Scap. Sir, Y’ are mad ; I (han’t get Fifty Shillings for all that s </l>
<l>there, 1 and you know how I am ftreightned for time. Gr. But what * Devil did he do a Ship-board ? Scap. Let Ship-board alone, and conftder, Sir, your Son. But </l>
<l>1 ' Heav’n Cheats of Scapin, 51 Heav'n is my witnefs, I ha’ done for him as much as was poffible, </l>
<l>and if he be not redeemed, he may thank his Father’s kindnefs. Gr. Well) Sir, 1 11 go fee if I can raifethe Money. Was it not </l>
<l>ninefcore Pounds you 1poke of? Scap. No, 200 /. Gr. What, 200 1 . Dutch, ha? Scap. No, Sir, I mean Englijh Money, 200/. fterling. Gr. I‘th Devil’s Name, what bufinefs had he a Ship-board ? </l>
<l>Confounded Ship-board. Scap. This Ship-board fticks in his Stomach. Gr. Hold Scapin , I remember I received the very Sum juft how </l>
<l>in Gold, but did not think I (liould have parted withitfofoon. He prefents Scapin his Purfe , but will not let it go, and in his tran- </l>
<l>fportments,pulls his Hrm to andfrojvhiljl Scapin reaches at it. Scap. Ay, Sir. Gr. But tell the Captain, he is a Son of a Whore. Scap. Yes, Sir. Gr. ADogbolt. Scap. I (hall, Sir. Gr. A Thief, a Robber, and that he forces me to pay him </l>
<l>200 1 , contrary to all Law or equity. Scap. Nay, let me alone with him. Gr. That I will never forgive him, dead or alive. Scap. Very good. Gr. And that if ever I light on him, I’ll murder him privately, </l>
<l>and feed Dogs with him. Scap. Right,Sir. \_He puts up his Purfe,and is going away. Gr. Now make haft, and go redeem my Son. Scap. Ay, but d’ye hear, Sir? Where’s the Money ? Gr. Did I not give it thee ? Scap. Indeed, Sir, you made me believe you would, but you </l>
<l>forgot, and put it up in your Pocket again. Gr. Ha—my griefs and fears for my Son make me do I know </l>
<l>not what. Scap . Ay, Sir, I fee it does indeed. Gr. What a Devil did he do a Ship-board ?—*—Damn’d Pyrate, </l>
<l>damn’d Renegade, all the Devils in Hell purfue thee. Scap. How eafily a Mifer fwallows a Load, and how difficultly </l>
<l>he difgorges a Grain ? But I ll not leave him lb, he’s like to pay in </l>
<l>other Coyn, for tellingTalesof me to his Son. H 2 </l>
<l>Ente 52 Cheats' of Scapin. Enter Oft. and. Leander. Sc.tp. Well,Sir,I have fucceeded in your Bufinefs,C fg ^ „ . there’saoo/. which Ihave fqueez’d out of yourFather. £ '-'ctavian. Oct. Triumphant Scapin. Scap. But for you I can do nothing-• [To Leander. Lea. Then may I go hang my felt’. Friends both adieu. Scap. D’ye hear, d’ye hear • the Devil has no fuch neceflity </l>
<l>for you yet, that you need ride Poft. With much ado I've got </l>
<l>your Bufinefs done too. Lea. Is’t pollible ? Scap. But on condition that you permit me to revenge my felf </l>
<l>on your Father, for the Trick lie has lerved me. Lea. With all my heart, at thy own -difcretion, good honeft </l>
<l>Scapin. Scap. Hold your hand, there’s 2 co l. Lea. My thanks are too many to pay now ; Farewel dear Son of </l>
<l>Mercury , and be profperous. Scap. Gramercy Pupil; Hence we gather. Give Son the Money, hang up Father. The End, of the Second Ltd. </l>
<l>Ad Third. Scene Firft. Enter Lucia and Clara. Lucia. \\J A S ever fuch a Trick play’d, for us to run away </l>
<l>' ' from our Governelfes, where our careful Fathers </l>
<l>had placed us, to follow a couple of young Gentlemen, onlybe- </l>
<l>caufe they laid they lov’d us,I think ’twas a very nobleEnterprize? </l>
<l>I am afraid the good fortune we (ball get by it, will very hardly </l>
<l>recompence the reputation we have loll by it. Clar. Ourgreateftfatisfa&ion is, that they are Men of faihion </l>
<l>and credit, and for my part I long ago refolv’d not to Marry any </l>
<l>other, nor fuch a one neither, till I had a perfect confirmation </l>
<l>of his Love; and twas an aflurance of Octavian s that brought me </l>
<l>hither. Lucia. I mull confefs, I had no lefs afence of the Faith and Ho¬ </l>
<l>nour cf Leander, Clar, </l>
<l>Cheatf of Scapin. 5 3 CUr. But Teems it not wonderful,that the Circumftances of our </l>
<l>Fortune (hould be To near ally’d, and our felves To much Stran¬ </l>
<l>gers. B.Tides, if I miftake not, I Tee fomething in Leander , To </l>
<l>muchrefembling a Brother of mine, of the Tame Name, that did </l>
<l>not the time fmce I Taw him make me fearful, I (hould be often apt </l>
<l>to call him To. Lmcia. I have a Brother too, whofe Name’s Oct avian, bred in </l>
<l>Italy, and juft as my Father took his Voyage, return’d home; not </l>
<l>knowing where to find me, I believe is the reafon I have not Teen </l>
<l>him yet: But if I deceive not my Telf, there is fomething in your </l>
<l>OCtavian, that extreamly refrefiies my memory of him. CUr. I wilh we might be To happy, as we. are inclin’d to hope ; </l>
<l>but there’s a ftrange blind Tide in our Natures, which always </l>
<l>makes us apt to believe what we moft earneftly d'efire. Lucia. The worft at laft, is but to be forfaken by our Fathers - </l>
<l>and for my part, I had rather lofe an old Father than a young </l>
<l>Lover, when I may with reputation keep him, and Tecure my Telf </l>
<l>againft thelmpofitionof fatherly Authority. CUr. How infufferable it is to be facrificed to the Arms of a nau- </l>
<l>feous Blockhead, that has no other fenfe than to eat and drink </l>
<l>when ’tis provided for him, rife in the morning, and go to Bed at </l>
<l>night, and with much ado be perfwaded to keep himfelf clean. Lucia. A thing of meer Flefti and Blood, and that of the worft </l>
<l>fort too, with a fquinting meager hang-Dog Countenance, that </l>
<l>looks as if he always wanted Phyfickfor the Worms. CUr. Yet Tuch their filly Parents are generally moft indulgent </l>
<l>to, like Apes, never To well pleas’d, as when th’are fondling with </l>
<l>their ugly Iflue. Lucia. Twenty to one, but to Tome fuch charming Creatures,’ </l>
<l>our careful Fathers had defign’d us. CUr. Parents think they do their Daughters the greateft kind- </l>
<l>nefs in the World, when they get them Fools for their Husbands, </l>
<l>and yet are very apt to take it ill, if they, make the right ufe of </l>
<l>them. Lutia. I’de no more be bound to fpend my days in Marriage to a </l>
<l>Fool, becaufe I might rule him, thanl would always rideanAfs, </l>
<l>becaufe the Creature was gentle. CUr. See, here’s Scapin, as full ofDefigns and Affairs, as a Cal¬ </l>
<l>low Statefman at a Treaty of Peace.. Leap, Ladies 1 ChU 54 Cheats of Scapin. CUr. Oh Monfieur Scapin / What’s the reafon you have been </l>
<l>fuch a Stranger of late ? Sc up. Why, faith Ladies, Bufinefs, Bufinefs, has taken up my </l>
<l>time, and truly I love an adtive life, love my Bufinels extreamly. Lucia. Methinkstho, this fliould be a difficult place for a Mm of </l>
<l>your Excellencies to find imployment in ? Scap. Why, faith Madam, I'm never fhy to my Friends: My </l>
<l>Bufinefs is, infhort, like that of all other Men of Bufinefs, dili¬ </l>
<l>gently contriving how to play the Knave and Cheat, to get an ho- </l>
<l>neft Livelyhood. CUr. Certainly, Men of Wit and Parts need never be driven </l>
<l>to indirect Courles ? Scap. Oh Madam / Wit and Honefly, like Oyl and Vinegar, </l>
<l>with much ado mingled together, give a Relifli to a good Fortune, </l>
<l>and pafs well enough for Sauce, but are very thin Fare of them- </l>
<l>felves. No, give me your Knave, your thorow-pac’t Knave - </l>
<l>hang his Wit, fo he be but Rogue enough. Lucia. You’r grown very much out of humour with Wit, Sca¬ </l>
<l>pin , I hope, yours has done you no prejudice of late ? Scap. No, Madam, Your Men of Wit are good for nothing,dull, </l>
<l>lazy, reffive Snails . *tis your undertaking, impudent, pufhing </l>
<l>Fool, that commands his Fortune. CUr. You are very plain and open in this Proceeding, what¬ </l>
<l>ever you are in others. Scap. Dame Fortune', like moft others of the Female Sex, </l>
<l>(I fpeak all this with refpedt to your Ladifhip ) is generally </l>
<l>moft Indulgent to the nimble melted Block-Heads , Men of </l>
<l>Wit are not for her turn,even too thoughtful when they fhould be </l>
<l>A<ftive ; why who beleives any man of wit to have fomuch as </l>
<l>Courage. No Ladies, if y’ave any Friends that hope to raife them- </l>
<l>felves, advife them to be as much fools as they can, and they’l near </l>
<l>want Patrons: And for honefty, if your Ladifhips think fit to </l>
<l>retire a little further. you (hall fee me perform upon a Gentleman </l>
<l>that’s coming this way. Clara. Prithee Lucia ^let us Retreat a little and take this oppor¬ </l>
<l>tunity of fome divertifement: which hath been very fcarce here </l>
<l>hitherto. </l>
<l>Enter </l>
<l>55 </l>
<l>Cheats of Scapini jE nter Shift with a Sack. Scap. Oh Shift! Shift. Speak pot too loud, my Matters coming. Scap. I am glad on’t, I (hall teach him to betray the fecrets of </l>
<l>his Friend, if any man puts a trick upon me without return, may </l>
<l>I loofe this Nofe with the Pox, without the pleafure of getting </l>
<l>it: , Sh. I wonder at thy Valour, thou art continually venturing </l>
<l>that body of thine: to the Indignity of bruifes and indecent Ba- </l>
<l>ftinadoes. Scap. Difficulties in Adventures makes them pleafant when ac- </l>
<l>complitht Sh. But your Adventures how Comical foever in the beginning, </l>
<l>are fure to be Tragical in the end. ' Scap. ’Tis no matter, I hate your pufillanimous Spirit ; Revenge </l>
<l>and Leachery are never fb pleafant as when you venture hard for </l>
<l>them, begone: here comes my Man. Enter Gripe. Oh Sir, Sir, fhLft for your felf, quickly Sir, quickly Sir, for Hea¬ </l>
<l>vens fake. Gr. What’s the matter Man? Scap. Heaven! is this a time to ask queftions ? will you be </l>
<l>Murdered inftantly ? I am afraid you’l be killed within thefe two </l>
<l>Minutes. Gr. Mercy on me! killed for what? Scap. They are every where looking out for you. Gr. Who? Who? Scap. The Brother of her whom your Son has marry’d, hee’s </l>
<l>A Captain of a Privatere, who has all forts of Rogues, Englijb , </l>
<l>Scotch, Weljb) Eri/h , French , under his command ; and all lying • </l>
<l>in wait now, or fearching for you to kill you, becaufe you would </l>
<l>Null the Marriage; they runup and down, crying where is the </l>
<l>Rogue Gripe, where is the Dog,where is the Slave Gripe;they watch </l>
<l>for you fo narrowly that there’s no getting home to your Houfe. Gr. Oh Scapinl what (hall I do? what will become of me? Scap. Nay Heaven knows, but if you come w ithin their reach </l>
<l>they’l De—wit you, they’l tear you in pieces: heark, Gr. Oh Lord/ Scap. Hum ’tis none of them? Gc. Cheats of Scapin. </l>
<l>Gr. Canft thou find no way for my Efeape, dear Scapin j Sc.ip. I think I have found one. Gr. Good Scapin, (how thy felf a man now. Scap. I (hall venture being moft immoderately beaten. Gr. Dear Scapin, do; I will Reward thee bounteoufly: lie give </l>
<l>thee this Suit when I have worn it 8 or 9 Months longer.. Scap. Liften ! whoarethefe? Gr. God forgive me, Lord have Mercy upon us. Scap. No, there’s no body; look, if you’l lave your life go into </l>
<l>this Sack prelently. Gr. Oh/ whole there? Scap. No body: get'into the Sack and ftir not, what ever hap¬ </l>
<l>pens, I’le carry you as a Bundle of Goods through all your Ene¬ </l>
<l>mies to the Majors houfe, or the Caftle ? Gr. An Admirable Invention, Oh! Lord quick. (Gets into the c Sack. Scap. Yes, *tis an Excellent Invention. if you knew all, keep in </l>
<l>your Head, Oh here’s a Rogue coming to look for you. Scapin counterfeits a Welihman. Do yon hear , I prayyou, where is Leander’s Fathers, look you. In his own Hotce. .How Ihould I know•, what would you have with him —\Jie clofe. Have with him , lookyou ! her has no creatpus’nefs, but her woud </l>
<l>havefatisftttions and reparations,look you, for Credits and Honours fay </l>
<l>St. Tavy he Jhall>wt put the Injuries and Hfronts upon my Captains , </l>
<l>lookyou now. Sir, In his own Voyte. He Affront the Captain, he meddles with no Man. Ton lye Sir , lookyon,and hurwill give you beatings and chaflifements, </l>
<l>for your Contradictions when hnr IVells ploods up, lookyou, andhur will </l>
<l>Cudgel your Packs and your Nottlesfor it, take you that pray you now. His own Voyce, * Beat the Sack. Hold, hold, will you Murder me. I know not where he is , </l>
<l>Hurwill teachfawey Jacks how they profookHur IVelfe ploods and </l>
<l>hur Ch oilers : and for the old Rogue hur will have his Guts and his plood </l>
<l>look yon Sir, or hur will never wear Leek upon St. Taffyes day more,look 57 </l>
<l>Cheats of Scapin, His own Ho'ce, Oh! He hsts maw id me , a damn'd Welch Rogue . Gr. You? The Blows fell upon my Shoulders: Oh! Oh! Scap. Twas only the end of the Stick fell on you, the main fub- </l>
<l>ftantial part of the Cudgel lighted on me. Gr . Why did you not ftand further off ? Scap. Peace — Here's another Rogue* In a Lancashire Dialect. Scap. 2 aw Fellee) with Sacktheere y done yawknaw whear ih'awd </l>
<l>RafcattGvhpis ? Not I; but here is no Rafcal. Taw Leen^ yaw Dogue^, yaw knxwn we el eernh whear he is , an yaw - </l>
<l>den teel , ond that he is a foo Rafcatt as any is in aw the Pawn; Ts tell a </l>
<l>that byr Lady . Not I, Sir, I know neither, Sir, not I. By thMef an ay tack thee in hont , ay s raddle th'bones on thee] </l>
<l>ay's keeble thee, to fame tune . Me, Sir ? I don’t underftand ye. * JVhy^ Ttiawrt his Mon y thaw Hobble , Tllfnite th'Afafe o'thee. Hold, hold, Sir* What would you have with him ? IVhy^ Imun knock him dawne with my Kibbo^ the fir ft bawt to the </l>
<l>grawnt , and then Imun beat him aw to pap by tti Mefi\ and after / 4 y </l>
<l>muncut of the Lugs andAfaes on en y and dywot) hell be a f ratty </l>
<l>fwatley Pellee , bawt Lugs and Ndes. Why, truly Sir, I know not where he is, but he went down </l>
<l>that Lane. This Lone , fayn ye ? Hys find him byr Lady , an he be above </l>
<l>grawnt. So, he’s gone, a damn’d Lancashire Rafcal. Gr. Oh good Scapin / go on quickly. Hold, here’s another. [Gr . pops in his Head, In an Irifli Tone. • ■ ' ,. a , T . \ p p Doji thou he at Sack-man ? Ifrideefare u de dam Dog Gripe ? </l>
<l>I </l>
<l>m </l>
<l>53 </l>
<l>Cheats of Scapin. Hk own Voice. Why, What's that to you? What know I. Ffit's dat to me Joy ? By my foul Joy, Iwill lay x great Blow upon </l>
<l>thy Pxte 5 and de Devil take me , but I will make thee know fare he is in¬ </l>
<l>deed, or Tl beat upon till thou dof know 5 ^ my fxlvaticn indeed. Sexy. I’ll not be beaten. Now the Devil take me , / fvexr by him that made me , if f/w# doji </l>
<l>not tell fare is Gripe, but I will beat thy Father's Child very much </l>
<l>indeed. What would you have me do? I cann’t tell where he is. But </l>
<l>what would you have with him ? Fat would I have wid him ? By my foul , if I do fee him , I will </l>
<l>make Mur the r upon him , for my Captain s fake. Murtherhim? He 11 not be murther’d. If I do lay my Eyes upon him 5 gad / will put my Sword into his Bow¬ </l>
<l>els , Devil take me indeed. Fat hafi dow in dat Sack ? Joy y by my </l>
<l>falvation I will look into it. But you (hall not. What have you to do with it ? By my foul Joy 3 I will put my Rapier into it. Gr. Oh! Oh! Scap. Fait it does grunt 3 by my falvation ; de Devil take me, Twill fee it indeed. You (hall not fee my Sack • I will defend it with my life. Den I rbill make beat upon thy Body • take that , Joy y and that, and </l>
<l>tlrxt.upon my foulywd fo Ido take my leave Joy. f Beats him in theSack. A Plague on him, he’s gone. he has almoft kill’d me. Gr. Oh / 1 can hold no longer •, the Blows all fell on my Shoul¬ </l>
<l>ders. Scap. You can nt tell me; they fell on mine: Oh my Shoul¬ </l>
<l>ders / Gr. Yours ? Oh my Shoulders ! Scap. Peace, th’are a coming. In a hoarfe Sea-mans Voice. Where is the Dog ? I ll lay him on fore and aft^ fw'mge him with & </l>
<l>Cat o nine tails 5 Keel-hale, and then hang him. at the Main Tard, </l>
<l>In </l>
<l>Cheats of Scapin. </l>
<l>59 </l>
<l>In broken French-Englifh. If dere be no more Men in England, Ivill kille him^ I vill put my </l>
<l>Rap ire in his Body , And Ivill give him two tree pufhe inde gutte. Here Scapin a Humber of e'm together. IVe mm go this way —— oth' right hand^ no to tti left hand —— lye clofe- fearcb evry where - by my falvation^Iwill kill the dam Dog - and we do catch en y we'll tear 'en in pieces , an I do heer he went thick way - no^ freight forward. Hold , here is his Man , where's your Mafler <- Dam me^ where ? in Hell ? Jpeak --- hold,not fo furioufly- and you don't tell us where he is yvell mur¬ </l>
<l>der thee - Do what you will, Gentlemen, I know not. Lay him on thick , thwack him foundly . Hold, hold, do what you will, Ill nere betray my Mafler. Knock' en down-, beat enzoundly^ toen , at’en^ at en^ at. \_As he is going to fir ike, Gripe peeps out,and Scapin takes to his heels'. Gr. Oh Dog, Traitor, Villain / Is this your Plot ? Would you </l>
<l>have murder’d me,Rogue?Unheard of Impudence. [ 'Enter Thrifty. </l>
<l>Oh Brother Thrifty ! You come to fee me loaden with difgrace - </l>
<l>the Villain Scapin has, asl am fenfible now, cheated me of 200/. </l>
<l>this beating brings all into my memory. [ \Hfide . Th . The impudentVarlet hasgulfdmeof the fameSum? Gr. Nor was he content to take my Money, but hath abus’d me </l>
<l>at that barbarous rate, that I am afhamed to tell it; but he (hall pay </l>
<l>for it feverely. Th. But this is not all. Brother, one Misfortune is the fore¬ </l>
<l>runner of another : Juft now I received Letters from London, that </l>
<l>both our Daughters have run away from their GovernelTes, with </l>
<l>two wild debaucht young Fellows, that they fell in Love with. Enter Lucia, and Clara,’ Lmc. Was ever fo malicious Impudence feen—-Hah-T—Sure- </l>
<l>iy, if I miftake not, that ihould be my Father. da. And the other mine, who Scapin has usd thus. Luc. Blefs us! Return’d, and we not know of it ? 1 2 c u: </l>
<l>60 Cheats o/'Scapin. Cla. What will they fay to find us here ? Luc. My deareft Father, Welcome to England.. Th. My Daughter Luce ? Luc. The fame, Sir. Gr. My Glam here too? Cl a. Yes, Sir, and happy to fee your fafe Arrival. Th. What ftrange deftiny has directed this happinefs to us ? Enter Odtavian. Gr. Hey day! Th. Oh Son ! 1 have a Wife for you. Oct. Good Father, All your Propofitions are vain ; I muft </l>
<l>needs be free, and tell you, I am engaged. Th. Look you now; is not this very fine ? Now I have a mind </l>
<l>to be merry, and be friends with you, you! not let me now, will </l>
<l>you? /tell you, Mr. Gripe's Daughter here- Off. l ie never marry Mr. Gripe's daughter, Sir, as long as I </l>
<l>Live ; No,yonder’s (lie that I muft Love, and can never Entertain </l>
<l>the thoughts of any other. C/a. Y esOffavian, I have at laft met with my Father, and all </l>
<l>our fears and troubles are at an end. Thr. Law ye now, you would be wifer than the Father that </l>
<l>begot you, would you ? did not I always fay you (hould marry </l>
<l>Mr. Gripes daughter ? But you do not know your Sifter Luce ? Oft. Unlook’d for bleffing, why (he’s my friend Leander's Wife ! </l>
<l>j Thr. How Leander’s Wife ! Gr. What my Son Leander ? Oct. Yes, Sir, your Son Leander. Gr. Indeed 1 well Brother Thrifty, ’tis true, the Boy was al¬ </l>
<l>ways a good nitur’d Boy. Well now am I fo overjoyed, that / </l>
<l>.could laugh till I (hook my (houlders, but that / dare not they </l>
<l>are fo fore. But look here he comes. Enter Leander. Lean. Sir, I beg your pardon, I find my marriage is difeove- </l>
<l>red • nor would /indeed, have longer concealed it, this is my </l>
<l>Wife, and / muft own her. , Gr. Brother Thrifty did you ever fee the like, dia you ever fee the like ? Ha ? ,. Thr. Own her quoth a! why kifs her,kifs her,Man,oddsboddi- </l>
<l>kins, when 1 was a young fellow and was firft mairied, /did </l>
<l>nothing elfe for three months. O my eonfcience I got my Boy Cheats of Scapin. 61 Octi. there ^ the firft night before the Curtaines were quite </l>
<l>drawn / Gr. Well,tis his Fathers nowne Child ; Juft fo Brother was it </l>
<l>with me upon my Wedding day, I could not look upon my dear </l>
<l>without blufhing, but when we were a Bed,Lord ha mercy upon </l>
<l>us-butlle lay no more; Lean. Is then my Father Reconcil’d to me. Gr. Reconcil’d to thee, why I love thee at my heart man, at </l>
<l>my heart, why ’tis my Brother Thrifty’s daughter, Mrs. Luce, </l>
<l>whom I always defign’d for thy Wife, and that’s thy Sifter Cla¬ </l>
<l>ra married to Mr. Octa. there. Lean. Oct avian are we then Brothers ? there is nothing that L </l>
<l>could have rather wiilit after the Compleating of my happinefs </l>
<l>with my charming Lucia. Thr. Come Sir, hang up your complements in the Hall at </l>
<l>home, they are old and out of fafliion ; Shift go to the Inn and </l>
<l>befpeak a Supper may coft more Money than /have ready to pay </l>
<l>fort, for L am refolved to run in.debt to night. Sh. L {hall obey your commands Sir. Thr. Then d’you hear, fend out and mufter up all the Fidlers, </l>
<l>Blirid or not Blind, Drunk or Sober) in the Town ^ let not fo </l>
<l>(much as . the Roafter of Tunes, with his crack’d Cymbal in a </l>
<l>Cafe, efcape ye. Gr. Well what would I give now for the fellow that lings the </l>
<l>Song at my Lord Mayors Feaft, I my felf would make an Epitha- </l>
<l>lamiumby way of Sonnet, and he (hould feta Tune to it, twas </l>
<l>the pretty’fthe had laft time. Enter Sly. «’ Sly. Oh Gentlemen here is the ftrangeft accident fallen out. Thr. What’s the matter. Sly. Poor Scapin. Gr. Ha ! Rogue let him be bang’d, Tie hang him my felf. Sly. Oh Sir, that trouble you may fpare, for palling by a </l>
<l>place where they were building, a great it one fell upon his </l>
<l>head and broke nis Scull fo, you may fee his Braines. 7 hr. Where is he? Sly. Yonder he c-omes. </l>
<l>Enter </l>
<l>6 2 Cheats of Scapin; . Enter Scapin between two , his Head wrap'd up in Tmic n as </l>
<l>if he had been wounded Scap. Oh me ! Oh me i Gentleman you fee me, you fee me </l>
<l>in a lad Condition, cut off like a Flower in the prime of my </l>
<l>years: But yet I could not dye without the pardon of thofe that* </l>
<l>I have wrong’d, yes Gentlemen /befeech you to forgive me all </l>
<l>the injuries that I have done; but more efpecially^ /beg of you </l>
<l>Mr. Thrifty , and my good Matter Mr. Gripe . Thr. For my part, I pardon thee freely, go, and dye in peace. Scap. But his you Sir, I have moft offended, by the inhumane </l>
<l>Baftinadoes which--— Gr. Prithee fpeak no more of it, I forgive thee too. Scap. ’Twasamoft wicked Infolence in me, that I fhould with </l>
<l>Vile Crab-tree Cudgel- Gr. Pith,no more,! (ay I am Satisfied. Scap. And now fo near my death his an unfpeakable grief that </l>
<l>I £hould dare to lift my handagainft—— Gr. Hold thy Peace, or dye quickly, I tell thee I have forgot All—* Scap. Alas! how good a man you are ! But Sir, d’you pardon </l>
<l>me freely and from the bottom of your Heart, thofe mercylefs </l>
<l>drubs that 1 - Gr. Prithee fpeak no more of it. I forgive thee freely,here’s my </l>
<l>hapd upon t. \_Pulls off his Cap. Scap. Oh ! Sir, how much your Goodnefs Revives me! Gr. Hows that / Friend take Notice I pardon thee, but his up¬ </l>
<l>on Condition that you are fure to dye! Scap. Oh me! I begin to faint again. Thr. Come, fie Brother, never let Revenge imploy your </l>
<l>thoughts now, forgive him, forgive him without any Condi¬ </l>
<l>tion. Gr. A dewce onk Brother, as I hope to be fav’d he beat me </l>
<l>bafely and feurvily, never ftir he did ; But fince you will have it </l>
<l>fo,I do forgive him. Thr. Now then let’s to fupper, and in our mirth drown and for¬ </l>
<l>int all troubles. * Scap A y,and let them carry me to the Lower End of the Table. Where in my Chair of State, Tie ft at eafe, And eat and drink, that I may dye in Peace. The. End. ~ ✓ 'S </l>
<l>A Dance . Epilogue. Spoken by Mrs. Mary Lee x when (he was out of Humour. </l>
<l>H O v little do youguefs what I'm to fay ? I'm not to ask you how like Farce or Play ; </l>
<l>Foryou mujl know , Tve other bus'nejs now : </l>
<l>Jt is to tell k, Sparks 3 how we like you. How happy were we when in humble guife^ Tou came with honejl Hearts and harmlefEyes i </l>
<l>Sate without Noife and Tumult in the Pit: Oh what apretious Jewel then was IVit / Tho now V is grown fo common 5 let me dye ? </l>
<l>Gentlemenfcorn to keep it company. Indulgent Nature has too bounteous been 5 </l>
<l>Tour too much Plenty is become your Sin. Time was ye were as meek as nowy are proud^ Did notin curjl Cabals of Cr kicks croud > Nor thought it witty to be very loud . But came to fee the Follies you would[hun: Tho now fo fondly Hntick herey 9 are grown. Tinvert the Stagespurpofe^ and its Rules: Make us Spelt ators^ whilfiyou play the Fools. </l>
<l>Equally witty as fome valiant are; The fad defells of both are expos d here. For here you R Cenfurewho dlfdain to write 5 </l>
<l>Hsfome make Quarrels here^ that fcorn to fight. The rugged Sonldier that from War returns 5 </l>
<l>j4ndfill with * heat of former Hltion burns, </l>
<l>let him but hither come to fee a Play , Proceeds an Errant Courtier in a day e . </l>
</body>

<end>
<l>:,0 3tiT </l>
<l>? ' UIJ </l>
<l>Shall </l>
<l>u. f Epilogue. Shall fleal from th ? Pit, And, fly up to the Box </l>
<l>There hold impertinent chat with Tawdry Manx • </l>
<l>Title 're aware the Blufl'rer falls in love . Hnd Hero grows as harmlefs as a Dove . With u* the kind remembrance yet remains, </l>
<l>fVhen we were entertain d behind our Scenes. </l>
<l>Though now alas 'we muflyour abfence mourn, </l>
<l>IVhilfl nought but Quality willferveyour turn , </l>
<l>Damrid Quality / that ufles poaching Hrts, Hnd (as 'tis faid) comes mask'd to prey on hearts . </l>
<l>The proper ufe of Vizors once was made , </l>
<l>fVhen only worn by fuch Os own'd the Trade: </l>
<l>Though now all mingle with 'em fo together y </l>
<l>That you can hardly know the one from t'other . </l>
<l>But tis no matter , on, pur fie your Game, Till wearied you return at lajl and tame; Know then'twill be our turn to be fevere, </l>
<l>JForwheny ave left your Stings behind you there : </l>
<l>Ton lazy Dr ones,ye Jhant have harbour here . </l>
<l>> </l>
<l>v </l>
<l>FINIS. •I . . • . • </l>
<l>The Courtiers Calling : Shewing the Art of Living at Couit, according to </l>
<l>the Maximes of Policy and Morality. By a Perfon of Honour. 12 . </l>
<l>Price 1 (h. 6 d. * * The Art of making Love , Or, Rules for the Condu& of Ladies and Gal¬ </l>
<l>lants in their Amours. 12* Price 1 s . Don Carlos Prince of Spain. A Tragedy, A&cd at the Dukes Theatre. Writ¬ </l>
<l>ten by T ho. Otway. Price 1 /. Publifhed this Term. The Portugal Hiflory ;Or, A Relation of the Troubles that hapned in the </l>
<l>Court of Portugal 5 in the Years 1667, and 1668, By S t P. Efq. All Sold by Bichard Tonfon at his Shop under Grays-Inn\ </l>
<l>Gate , next Grays-Inn-Lane, , </l>
</end>