The adventures of five hours. : A tragi-comedy, . | HathiTrust Digital Library

View this item in the fully-styled HathiTrust interface.

Use of this online version is subject to all U.S. copyright laws. Please do not save or redistribute this file.
For questions or comments, contact HathiTrust.org at feedback@issues.hathitrust.org

Go to full bibliographic information
Go to table of contents
Skip table of contents and go to current page
Full Bibliographic Information
Title
The adventures of five hours. : A tragi-comedy, .
Author
Tuke, Samuel, Sir, -1674Tuke, Samuel, Sir, -1674
Edition
2nd ed
Published
London :Printed for Henry Herringman,1664
Description
[123] pages ;19 cm
Rights
Public Domain, Google-digitized.
Permanent URL
https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc1.31822043035914

Table of Contents

    Front Cover
    Section 1
    Title Page
    Section 2
    Section 3
    Section 4
    Section 5
    Section 6
    Section 7
    Section 8
    Section 9
    Section 10
    Section 11
    Section 12
    Section 13
    Section 14
    Section 15
    Section 16
    Section 17
    Section 18
    Section 19
    Section 20
    Section 21
    Section 22
    Section 23
    Section 24
    Section 25
    Section 26

Book Text
Front Cover
Page Scan 1

ITVG. I.C.U. I'S |- I U. K.G. 1664

This page contains an image.
Page Scan 2

ae|- ſae. ~ ~ ~ ~ ~ ~~~~ |- *.*.*-- zºº. R. #575± ***. Şº Gººg º ----|- 7：|-|- ·|×|-~ ！（）, º！|-- ---- *********w*w*************** • • • ••••••••••----- ----+---------------- – |-- -

Page Scan 3

º *S. （tal， a § 2.º.º. ('^'^^'！2！！ ！！ %± - |- %！

Page Scan 4

*…

End of Front Cover. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 1
Page Scan 5

IKE (SAMUEL). The Adventures of Five Hours. A Tragi-Comedy. Small 4to, newly bound in full tobacco-brown crushed levant morocco, Jansenist, inside gold borders, gilt edges, BY RIvIERE. London, 1664 SUPERB Copy of the Rare Second Edition, containing verses in commendation 5f the book by Abraham Cowley, John Evelyn, and other prominent men of the time. This copy has very wide margins. From the ARBURY LIBRARY, with book- abel inside front cover.

Page Scan 6

Blank page
Page Scan 7

&{<<<Vºš>'''& →
Page Scan 8

Blank page

End of Section 1. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 2
Page Scan 9

! ADVENTuREs FIVE HOURS § X N ; § Tras Comedy. The Second &dition. \ Non ego Ventoſe Plebis ſuffragia venor. - " - Horat. Febr. 12. I 6 & 2. I MPR IM A TUI R - John BERKENHEAD. 5. - -- § - Lo N Do N, º Printed for Henry Herringman, and are to be ſold at his Shop & at the Sign of the Anchor in the Lower Walk of § the New Exchange. 1664. 5. * §

End of Section 2. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 3
Page Scan 10

|-|-- - · - ---- · · |- ~ · · → - -· + |- |-· v · |- ----- |-* · |×- · |-|- · · -- -- ---- · - -- ---- , - ---- * · |---- - --- - - · |- · |- ---- , ，|- |- -------- - - |-~ |- ---- ||- |- |-* * - - |----- |- ----|- ----- - - |- |-+---+|- •• • * - ---- -|-|- |-|- · ----- -.^ |- -------- ·|----- |-|----- ----|- |-·|----- ----|-|- |-|- · . ae---- ---- |- • “|- … * * · · · ----|----- |----- ·|-|- -|-|- · ·- ·• • •~^ · |------ * *---••• ·（~~ … *---- ---- |-|- ^ • • ·！ |-* · |- · ---- * …'~. -- : * .* -·|- - ----- -*ae • • • • • *----- *· - • • • • •---- · · |-- … * ！ |-·

End of Section 3. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 4
Page Scan 11

To the Right Ho N or A B L E, HENRY HOVV AR D, o F No R F O L K. #Ince it is Your Pleaſure (Noble Sir ) that % I ſhould hold my Fortune from You; like * thoſe Tenants, who pay ſome Inconſide- . rable Trifle in lieu of a Valuable Rent, "I humbly offer You this Poem in Acknowledgment of my Tenure: and I am well pleas'd with this Occa- ſion to Publiſh my Senſe of Your Favours, ſince it ſeems to me a kind of Ingratitude to be Thankful in Private. It was bred upon the Terrace-Walks in Your ... Garden at Aldbury; and, if I miſtake not, it re- - - - A 2. , -’ ſembles : º 2- §§ X : § ;



End of Section 4. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 5
Page Scan 12

ſembles the Place where it was Brought up : The Plot is Delightful, the Elevations Natural, the Aſ. cents Eaſie, without any great Embelliſhments of Art. - I deſign'd the Charaćter of Antonio as a Copy of Your Stedy Virtue; if it appear to thoſe, who have the Honor to know You, ſhort of the Original; I take leave to Inform them, that You have not ſat to me long; 'Tis poſſible, hereafter I may Gratific my Country for their Civility to this I ſay with ſomething more worthy of Your Patronage, and their Indulgence. - - In the Interim I make it my Glory to avow, That had Fortune been Juſt to me, She could not have Recompens’d the Loyal Induſtry of my Life with a more illuſtrious Title, than that which You have been pleas'd to Confer; upon me 3 of TO 11 R FRIEND. To which ( as in Gratitude I am found ) I Subjoyn that of * - - Tour most humble Servant, - -- S. Tuk P. - - -, - - r | - - ––––-T-- -

End of Section 5. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 6
Page Scan 13

|! : | : - To my moſt Honour’d Friend Colonel Tuke, upon his Exem- plary Dramatique Poem the Adven- - * tures of Five Hours. In this we find how Vaft's the ſcope of Wit, Although reſtrain'd within the bounds of fit sº The work’s Heroick ; it redeems the Stage From flat andfoul,whilst that riforms the Age; what Figures of things rare how well deſign'd, Of which the noblest Sir expreſs your mind; The brave Antonio's words amaz'd us all; From what Pen elſe could ſuch high Rapturesfall 2. The Geºrous gratefull Maida Fire expreſs'd, which ſprang to Flames in ev'ry Manly breast 3 No more Spetiators now, w are Ašiors all, With ev'ry Change our Paſſions riſe, or falls, Of all who Live the best diſcerning King . The Sutješ choſe for him who beſt cauld ſing 3: . For him whoſe Muſe does Charm the nicºſt Ear, , For him who beft could hºrite, and teſt forbears • 2 ſ - • * ;1th Fletcher's Nature, Learned Johnſon's Art, Of others too the more Tranſcendent part : Dramatique Laws not only kept but taught, And new Perfestions into Precept brought. ** : * *





End of Section 6. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 7
Page Scan 14

That Caſar's Spirit was ſo long reſtrain'd, Amazes more than that at length it Reign'd; In this our King is moſt Auguſt, and Great, That Arms, and Arts do make hit Reign compleat; º And you in both may claim an ampleſhare, - rour Pen in Peace equals your Sword i'th marr. James Long. Upon my Worthy Kinſman Co- lonel Tuke, His Incomparable Play. Would you had not Writ ! but 'tis too late, - Againſt what is decreed, to Deprecate, The Fates do Limits to each thing diſpenſe, To Poets rage, to Arms, to Eloquence; - Thus the Learn'd Greece, and the more Poliſh'd Rome, Had bounds like Seas; Hitherto ſhall ye come; And hitherto our Stage 3. Olympus top who has once gain’d (which dos the Heavens prop ) can ſore no Higher; rour Head has bruſh'd the Spheart, Then 'tis no wonder if you Charm our Ears. rou in Five Hours have here performed more, Than in Five Ages all our Bards before: . . . Nor tell me of another Spaniſh Plot, unleſs it ſhould to Write it beyour Lot: 'I is not the Story makes the Smilingfaces , , - . . . But who recites that Story with your Graces : hºrite then in pity to th’ abandon'd Stage, a ºv But in Another tempt your own free Rage: º “ . . . ----- irhat

End of Section 7. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 8
Page Scan 15

hhatt hough the Serpent bite, and Fools revile, He breaks his Teeth who thinks to hurt your File, - But why would you beſo Injurious to The other Houſe 3 all our Old Plays und, 2 4ll our New ones at leaſt For who will write z mºho can indeed, unleſ; it he in ſpight? Tou by this One have ſo improvº, the Trade, 44en will ſee none unleſs by you they're made; And yet jeſay that you will write no more, - ** ſwear it too! Sir William ſhut your Door. J. Evelyn. ~ To the Author. * : . . . . . . . . * > . . . . . . . . . . ; . . . - . . . . . - * * * * * *...* * - - S S when our Kings (Lords of the ſpacious Main) - A Take injuſt Warrs a Rich plate-Fleet of Spain, The rude unſhapes Ingots they reduce ' ' Into a form of Beauty, and of uſe; ' ' ' ', sº º On which the Conqu'rours Image now does ſhine; Not his whom it belong'd to in the Aſiae : So in the mild contentions of the Muſe, º (The marr which Peace itſelf loves and peſºs). So have you Home to as in Triumph trought This Cargazon of Spain, with 77 eaſuresfraught : Y rou have not baſelygotten it ºffealth, . Norby Tranſlation borrow'd all its mealth; * . But by a powerfull Spirit made it your own; * * *.*. Metall before, Money by you 'tis grown; 'Tis currant now by your adorning it. a With the fair Stamp of your Piñorious hit : But

End of Section 8. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 9
Page Scan 16

- And Spain on you ſhall make Repriſals then. The numerous Theatre has decreedyour Praiſe, - ſ But though me praiſe this Voyage of your Mind, And thongh ourſelves Enrich't by it we find, we're not contented yet, becauſe we know . . . . . . . inhat greater Stores at bome within it grow ; , , w" haveſeen how well you forein Oar refine; Produce the Gold of your own Noëler Mine. - The World ſhall then our Native Plenty view, And fetch Materials for their hit from you : They all ſhall watch the Travels of your Pen, - ) A. Cowley. To my Excellent Friend Col. Sam. - Tuke, on his Adventures of Five Hours. - - - . º - ** Yº: 4re too happy, Sir, and doubly bleft5 * , - At once to pleaſe the wiſer, and the beft, - And raiſe the envy of thoſe men who grieve - To ſee your Play do's, and is like to live; mhile their crude births, for lack of genial fire, No ſooner are produced, than expire. , - - But here, good Plot, clean Language, well-weigh’d Senſe, Challenge applauſe, and make their own defence. Old Ben. for his Good Play, Illanderſtood, Thought it enough to ſirear, He knew 'twas good: ~ - - * - . . . . * > º - * - " - * - * * * * * ** * * - * ... . The proper judges to decide the Bayes. . . . . * * * * * * - - - - *. • * * < *, *, * r * --> , , , , , , , , --~ **- Hºt Nººp -- . . . * *** * * * *- * * . . . . . . . . . To

End of Section 9. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 10
Page Scan 17

To the Author of the Adventures, Tour # Guſtoes all our Cooks anda, - - … &c. Perſwading him to write again. Hough Darkneſs were the Midwife to your Plot, I ret that was clear to all who envy'd not Sofair a birth 3 begot by Wit, and Art, - Great Nature's Ornaments in everypart : . mhythen ſhou'dyon profeſs to write no more z unhappy Iſſues make a Parent poor. . • * , , , , , , , Tou are ſo rich in Praiſe, that there will be ‘’’. More than enoughfor a great Progeny; No diſh will taff wellifnot dreſt by you: º mhoſe Eagle cMuſe to ſuch a height was got That clear eyes only ſaw, the dull could not Till the Cloud varied; to compleather Fame At lałł ſhee bravely ſtoºpt, and kill'd her Game. Envy incites; make good your place once more, Elſe the windsfavour'd, and you did but ſore; Thoughſlander move you not, Religion may, 7..#us the Art to pleaſe your vertuous way: - For though our ºices have debauch'd the stage More Poets made like you mayflop that rage. mitethen ; forfew elſewill, what's a ſlight Praiſe, mhilſt Admiration gild, your crown of Bayes 2 " . * * * Lod. Catile. tº | - * -- \ . * * - - * * - ** - . . . . . * . . . . . . . * * - * * • ‘. * To

Page Scan 18

To my much Honoured Kinſman Coll. Samuel Tuke, on his Adventures, &c. Hat Poet who can his clear thoughts diſpenſe,... When Language is to ſtrive with variouſ Sºft, whom well plac'd labours have remov’dfrom blame, Freed of Ambition, though he #and for Fame, . . . May brave Detrašion; and ntºeſtruples ight, º - ret equal fu.ges with reſpett invite: *** * * * Conſcious of worth he tread; the bending #age, Daring the Cenſures of this curious Age; - Th’impartial Mullitude (ta do them * ) . . . . .* -- º ...º.º. Not yet concern’d in Fałion,far from Guile * . . . . mhen mov’d to joy, or Pity, heep, or Smile; . . . . Ten times the Play recalºrith generau, heat, , , , , Ten times attend, and freſh Applauſe repeat ; * * * * * 4s Lambs new ſuckled leap, as Fields lºok gay. , , , , , , After ſweet ſhowers, as Bird; ſalutethe Day; ' ' . . . All but the Owls, and Bats, thoſe Sons of Ni ht, - That revell,hout, and brooknor Arts, nor Light. . . . . . Thu, on the banks of Hébrus Orpheusrau'd , , , , , Stop the quick Stream and move the rootedmond; Hºibhi, Lºsinº,” And favelins flyi 'g in the Air diſarm ; -- Birds ſilent tº: - v -- *- : *** His Notes, which Notes (alas!) amon are drown'd, when frantick Paſſions, Wine, and Shouts conſpire Ta rend the Peet, and to break his Lyre : Art lyes oppreſs'd ; but why do I relate Fables 3 rou need not fear ſº hard a Fate CT $ - - - - * - : - - - -- -- A - --- - - - - marian Caves reſuand a ... . . . From

End of Section 10. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 11
Page Scan 19

From Engliſh Breaſis ; theſe Iſles (milderrate º . . . . of men produce, than grows on rocky Thrace; º * Nor let the Dutch beforward to cºmplain, º º º --. what eye it ſaid they know the Scene is Spain ; º º º Sonorade handſball tear your wreathed Bayes, * * * * * All Mirth with Mirth, and hit repaywithfraiſe. º ºvº wº. - º -- " -- . . ." t . . . . \\\, , , Chr Waſ :\, : ...G. . ." - - * > * º, Nº. - - - - * . * , , , •º - * * **t *... ." - - sº - - - * - - … . . . . . . * * * • * * * : * * * * - - -, * ~ * * tº rive - --- - - - -- - ~ - - - -- * , , , , , . . . . - - - - - \ -—— º - - - º º º º, *C. * * * * * To the Author upon the Adven- tures, &c. w Heywhefrientiuſhalftrathe laws – : Irºf writing well, and each peculiar cauſe whº, Lºnghage-lth herprººftºff influenº. 9 º'; a - -- - Inſtills herſelf into the raviſh'd ſenſe ; , , ... ." Say 'tis an Art, not by Inſtruñions taught," " - But freely iſſuing from a breſt that's fraught - mith Prudence, Honour, Nobleneſs. Why then Amazeth us this off-ſpring of your pen-f , º, * . . . .'; V. ~. 'Tis true it may do wonders, and redreſs º' . . . . . . Th"errors, with which the Pulpit, and the Preſs, ºvºs (Toth' beſt of Princes ruine ) here of lates º ºr .º.º. Corrupted had both Eloqaence, and States, sº wº, º All this avouching, with the general Qaires a va, . . . . I joyn my’ applauſe, yet can't with them admire: ' , , , , , , , Thefaculties, Sir, of your noblemind. A vs tº º ºsº. - I know ſo well, and hº fits enſhrinºd ºxº vs. º Wirtue with her attendants ſº confined ºf ººº sº * * * 3 2. - - That

End of Section 11. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 12
Page Scan 20

º That in an unaccuſtom'd way I ſmile . . . - - - - To ſee by you impoveriſh'd ºur Iſle. . . . . . . . . . Though then thirpiece be of refinedore, ºf , º, . 'Tis a ſmall grain out of your richer ſtore. º: That which ſo dazzles in this exc'lent Play The Theatre, it but a ſingle ray . . From the rich treaſure of your fancies light Darted; though efficacious, and ſo bright, That we ſhall ſee from thence diſpell'd the might Where ignorance envelop'd had the age (Her Luminary being eclips'd the Stage) So the Sun chaſes darkneſs from our Sphear, * - E’re in his luſtrebekouthſafet'; appear. . . ; ; ; ; ; º William Joyner. - - - - - * +1 1– - sº º .* º . º . > To the Author, upon his finiſh'd Poem, The Adventures of Five t - -- - * - * * * Houſes, &c. - º sº. “ . .º.º. º.º. . . . . Fº: this Agedies want that noble pride, Forwhich bravemenofold were dei §d: And that thoſe perſºns who are nobly born, , . . . . . . . . Virtue, which made'em ſº, dº turn to ſcorn: , , , , , , As if that Honor were the child of Fate, . . . . . . . . And vertuous men did ſupererogate;. S In were compaſſion to this wretched age . . . . . . . Toubring heroique Vertue dm the ſtage 3, , , , , , , , , , Hºping her genuine Graces might entice, y \, , , , , Theſe whom her Precepts could not turn from Vice sº

End of Section 12. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 13
Page Scan 21

4nd though no ſtranger to thoſe antient rol; which keep the Records of departed Souls; ret you not knowing amongſt them toſº •'. A nobler Image, copy your own mind; *here you ſuch charming features do diſcover Jºyour brave Souldier, and yourfrithful Lover, The ſilent Circle were in aſuſpenſe, Not knowing where to wiſh the preference; But as from th' Elements contrariety Almighty Natureforms a harmany; So by the Magick of your Artful Muſe, Toufrom your Kivals diſcords do produce Such a delightful concord, that all thoſe whofear'd their Fate, are pleas'd that they werefoes. In whºſeſ rene, andſted Looks wefnd Delight, and monder did poſſeſs their mind, º ſirii attentionſpeaks your praiſes higher Than the loud Plaudits of #. upper Tire. whilſt others writing raiſe the Vulgar cry, rours, Sir, are only prais'dby Extaffe. ‘P O S T S CRIPT. On to all other writers give their due ; - Andforgive thoſe, #. have denyldit you;. 4nd left by your reply their ſhameſhould live, Touſtillforget that which you didforgive; * Though (whilſt you live) they envy your juſt praiſe, They will (when dead) jour Cypreſs'wreath with Bayes; Good Writers (like good Christians) never have Their #ate ºf Glory till th’ are intheir Grave. ... -- - ? MElpomene. The

Page Scan 22

The Firſt scENE is The City of S E V I L. The Prologue E mir, with a Play-B ill in his hand, - and Read (, - This Day being the 15" of December, ſhall be Aéted a New Play, never Play’d before, call’d The Adventure, of Five Hours. A N E W P L A Y. TH are i'the right, for I dare boldly ſay, The Engliſh Stage ne'r had ſo New a Play; ‘. . . º º The Dreſs, the Author, and the Scenes are New. . . . . . . . . This ye have ſeen before ye’lſay: 'tis true ; , . * * .. º But tell me, Gentlemen, who everſaw . . . . sº ... . . . . . . 4 deep Intrigue confin'd to Five Hours Law. º, Such as for cloſe Contrivance yields to none : \ . . ‘. 4 Modeſt Wan may praiſe what's not his own. . . . . . º 'Tis true, the Dreſs is his, which he ſubmits To thoſe who are, awd thoſe who would be Wits ; Ne'r ſpare him Gentlemen, for to ſpeak truth, * . He has a per’lous Čews’rer been in routh; And now grown Bald with age, Doating on Praiſe, He think to get a Periwig of Bays. Teach him what 'tis, ji. Diſcerning Age To bring his heavy Genius on the Stage; ~ : Where jou have ſeen ſuch Wimble hits appear, That paſs'd ſo ſoon, oneſcarce could ſay th’ were here. Tet after our Diſcoveries of late . . . . . . . . . . . . Of their Deſigns, who would Subvert the State; sº Tou'l wonder much, if it ſhould prove his Lot, . . . . . . . . To take all England with a Spaniſh Plot; . . . . . . . . . . But if through his ill Conduit, or hard Fate, , , , o … . This Forei. Plot (like that of Eighty Eight ) sº vº º sº. º. Should ſuffer Shipwrack in your Narrow Seaſ, - - Tou’l give your Modern Poet his Writ of Eaſe ; For by th' Example of the King of Spain, He reſolves ne'r to trouble you again. * . . . . - * * \ The

End of Section 13. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 14
Page Scan 23

P R O * U E - T H E . Lo G / A T - He Addreſs himſelf to the Pit. A’. to a dying Lamp, one drop of Oyl - This refers to P. Gives a new Blaze, and makes it live a while; the Authors So th’Aathor ſeeing his decaying Light, *::::..., | And therefore thinking to retire from ſight, - hiº K. Washindred by a Ray from th’ upper Sphere, - when his Ma- s Jaff at that time he thought Žižº 3. - jeſty recom- He chanc'd to hear his Maieffy once ſay. mended this He lik'd this Plot: he ſtai’d ; and writ the Play; Plot to him. So ſhould Obſequious Subjećts catch the A4inds Of Princes, as your Sea-men do the Winds. If this 4ttempt then ſhews more Zeal, than Light, "I may teachyon to Obey, though not to Write. - - . . . - -- He loºk H ! he is there himſelf. Pardon my ſight, e looking up - . . and ſeeing the AMy Eyes were dazled with Exceſs of Light; - K”, ſtarts. Evenſo the Sau, who all thing elſe diſplays, . . . . • He Kneels. Ishid from us ºth glory of his Rays ; He riſes, Hill rou vouchſafe four Preſence f rou, that were given To be our Atlas, and ſupport our Heaven 2 - will you (Dread Sir) rour Pretions Moments loſe- To Grace the firſt Endeavours of our Muſe 2 This with your Character most aptly fairs - Even Heaven it ſelf is pleas'd with the firſt Fruits. f - - - - * t -- .. - - *\_* < \; DRAM- :

Page Scan 24

Dramatis Perſonae. Porcia. - . Ladies. Camilla. Toung Ladie t - - Don Carlos. A Kind Brother to Camilla. Don Henrique, A severe Brother to Porcia. Don Antonio Pimentel. Contrahed by the Mediation º of Friends to Porcia be- - * - - • fore he ſaw her. Don Oétavio. secret Gallant to Porcia, but - wº - feigning to be in Love with Camilla. Flora. waiting-woman to Porcia. Erneſto. • Sancho. servants to Don Antonio. - z - Diego. servant to O&avio. º Sylvio. Geraldo. servants to Don Henrique. . . . Pedro. v The Corigidor, and Attendants. The Scene S E V I L f

End of Section 14. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 15
Page Scan 25

ºSRG /Sººr ººz mºr, . . . . * The Firſt Act. THE scene DON HENRIQves ~ * T —- Enter Don Henrique, who is immediately follow'd - - º, by Sylvio. tº ºf . . . . . - - … . . . . . . . . . i2. 1 , , , , , sº - . . . . . . Sylvio. Ignior, Don Carlos is without. * * * Henr. Wait on him in. Enter. Carlos.io, - ºr v. ... ºf Cº y º f ; # ºv; , , , , , Car. Cozin,to me this day hath longer ſeem'd than uſual, Since’tis ſofar advanc'd without our ſeeing one another. Hemr. Methinks ſo too; but you repair your Stay, , By º hither opportunely now 3: ... Yº You have ſo often born with my Diſtempers, '' • . 'Tis fit that once at leaſt you º partake - . . . . . . . ** *** - ) wº - Of



End of Section 15. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 16
Page Scan 26

The Adventures of Five Hours. In the ££a, an # A Heart aſ t Your Friend has been with the li º Tealous of the Honour of his Fami 5- - . . ly's - **g, *, - - (Yet never blemiſh'q}\to H ºiced. | º É.i...ºf wººd * Of my good humºur.gº. - (arº hâtereºtfig @##: For a Gentleman Rich, Beautiful, and Young. Car. You know, Don Henrique foºdivers years, rovince charg'd , . A tende: Siſter, by our Parents will , . . . . . . ; ( Włºś their Cares below)” . To mine committed; Of lovely Porcia, I conclude, that you Cº And to the Malice of theirenvious Sex, , , , , You muſt confeſs the Confines of their Fame As to her Virtué, I have ſcenhºt OW Still to the world than . ; and (Sir) Nearneſs of blood deceive me , ſhort offew In the advantages that draw Pretenders; Yet thanks to my Temper, Cozin, as well: ; ; G --- d though more º - F.) unkſs up from her Childhood, to her Dangerous Age, Without the leaſt Diſturbance tothy reſt: . . . .” & 3. And when with equal juſtice I refle&A. £ 2," On the great Modeſty and Circumſpection . . . w Might well have ſlept as undiſturb’d as I. sº Henr, Sir, I complain not of my Siſters condućt; . . . But you know well; young Maids are ſo expos'd . To the Invaſion of audacious men, J. C. º. 2: . . . . . . . ." . . . . fºr " Are never ſafe till guarded by a Husband 3.





Page Scan 27

The Adventures of Fiye Hºurs. º We ſing and figh One The wiſdom of Relations ought to uſe , - . Preventions of all ſorts; but dear Çarks , . . . . . . The Blemiſh once received, no Waſhis goodſ For ſlains of Honor, but th’Offenders blood. - - - Car. Y’are tooſevere a Judge of point of Honor. Henr. And therefore having not longſince receiv'd. , The news, that Don Antonio Pimentel, ſº nitrila 3 ºr , Is likely to be here this night from Flanders; tº c. To whom my Siſter by Welladas means, , , , --, (Our common Friend and Patron) is contračted; y I will not cloſe theſe eyes: tillº, I have ſeen tº ºf Her, and my Cares, ſafe lodgåwithin his arms; ºr, £ar. I find your travels, Cozin, have not cur'd you. Of that iunate Severity to Women, x, y, zºº, , , , , \;. to be a National reproach Untous all abr 13, thº º ents, fººt. A lif That miſerablé Sex . #a i. º.º.d Born onely to be honºrable Priſoners'; . . . ." . . . The more of Quality, the #: 3 ºf . . . Which Gr elty is rºy ºš. º jääurſelves. ºnly ºf Whilſt by Immuring thºſe y ; Lºwes.,.]: y - #. ºivº iſ ºf: U --- - As cruel is thatóver-cautious - - - -, -, * * * : , . . . . - - - - - - * - " - - - - - * - -- . . . . By Proxy to contra: Párties unknown ... . . . To one and ther; this is ºngly fit #23rººt For Soveragi Princes, whóſé igh qualitis - "Will not allow of previous interviews; “They ſacrifiſe their Loveto Publick good, * Coſing ºyingreſſ and Boº & A cuſtom, which as yet, never knºw... , 1,… ſºn-i 3. . . lls'd between perſons of a Lower rank, - . . . . . . . Without a ſequel of ſad Conſequence: . . . . . . Sir, underſtand me right; I ſpeak not this 'ſ . . . . º | - B 2 - By r

Page Scan 28

The Adventures of Five Hours. By way of Prophecy; I am no ſtranger ~ To Don Antonios great reputation, - - , a Which I believeſo juſt, I no way doubt Your Siſters being happy in him. - Hen. Don Carlos, let us quit this Argument; I now am going to our noble friend - - And kinſman the Corigidor, to ſee -- . If he will honor with his Company My Siſters Wedding; will you come along? . Car. Moſt willingly; asſoon as I have brought My Siſter hither, and lefther with yours. . . . . . Henr. I have ſome buſineſs, Cozin, by the way, I'lgo before, and wait you i'th Piazza. { . Your Servant, Cozin, . . . . . . ~ +...º." - ... . . . . . . . . . . . [Exit Carlos. This Kinſman º friend, and yet". . . . . Ofall men living, I muſt hide from him My deep reſentments of his Siſters ſcorn 5 ' ' ' ' " That cruel Maid, to wound me to the Heart, Then cloſe her Ears againſt myjuſt complaints; But thoughas yet I cannot heal my wound, I may, by my Revenge upon my Rival Divert the Pain; and I will drive it home; - There's in Revenge a Balm, which will appeaſe. The preſent .# and Time cure the diſeaſe. v Enter Porcia. . ." A- Porcia. My heart is ſo oppreſt, withfear and grief, That it muſt break, unleſs it find relief; ' ' '. The Man I love is forc'd to fliemy ſight, And like a Parthian, kills me in his flight: One whom I neverſaw, I muſt embrace, [Exit Henrique. or
Page Scan 29

The Adventures of Five Hours. Or elſe deſtroy the Honour of my Race. . . . A Brothers Care, more crucl than his Hate; Obowperplex is my unhappy fate 1 - Enter Carlos and Camilla. . . . . . gar,Sozin, Ithought my Siſterscompany º, Would not diſpleaſe you, whilſt I wait upon Your Brother in a viſit. . . . . . Porc. Sir, you oblige me with a welcom favours ... I ratherſhold havefiſditcharity, . Tobring a friend to her, whoſe cruel fate } aſide. . . . Has robb'd her of her ſelf. . . . . - Cam. Methinks,'tis pitty that a wall ſhould make The houſes two, offriends ſo entirely one , -- As you, and I, and our two Brothers are, . . . . Porc. If it be true, that Lovers live much more, There where they Love, than where they Breath, i'm ſure No walls can ſever us, w are ſtill together. - - . . . Car. Were I not muchengag’d, I would not quit So ſweeta Converſation; but, Siſter, , At my return, I'l wait uponyou home. . . . . . . . Porc. For this night, Cozin, pray lether be mine, I begit of you both. - - Car. You may command, we are both yours. w . . . . . . . . [Exit Carlos Port. Mydear Camilla,how I long'd to havee }: the, - - § ned. Wherefreely breathingout my Grief, I might. Some mitigation from thy Pitty find; . . . . . ; “But ſince there's notrue Pitty without Pain;. Why ſhould I Eaſe, by thy Afflićtion gain Cam. Ah Porcia!...if Compaſſion Suffering be, And to Condole be Pain; my Deſtiny . . . . Willfull revenge in the ſame kindafford; Should an 3. s.
Page Scan 30

The Adventures of Five Hours: w 'to . : . . . . . . . . Should I, but my unequal’d griefs relate, ºf...' . . . . ; And you, but equally participate. " : º32: … . " Porc. If yours, as hine, from Love-diſaſlets riſe yo: O Our Fates are more alli'd than Families. - - Cam. What, to our Sex, and blooming age can prove Ananguiſhworthy of our Sighs, but Love?", " 'º Porc.”Tis true; Camilla, were your fate like mine, 2 / ! Hopeleſs to hold, unable to reſign. º 'º' ): I º *" Čam! Let's tell our Stories, then we ſoon ſhallſee; Which of us two excells in Miſery. º, ºf Porc. Cozin, agreed: " " . . . . . . tº ºf Cam. Do you begin then. . . . . . . . . ºº: Portº'ou know;Camilla,beſt,bow generouſly, ; Aftºiu, How long, and how diſcreetly, my Ofiavio lººk...ii Hath ſerv'd me; and what trials of his faith. . . . . . . ** And fervout'ſ did ſnake, cre I allow'dºrº iſ 1... sº- The leaſt hope to ſuſtain his noble Love.' . . . . ." … I Cozin, all this you know; ’twas in your Houſe We had our interviews; where you were pleas'd . To ſuffer feign'd addreſſes to your Self, ºr ºf To cover from mywatchful Brother's eyes," " : *. The real paſſion which he had for me. ". . . . . . . Cam. My memory in this needs no refreſhing. . . . . Porc. And how one Evening (O that fatal hour). My Bºbther paſſing by Don Carlos houſe, With his great Friend and Confident Don Pedro sº.sº Did chance to ſee th' unfortunate Oñavia, f At your Balcony, chtertaining me; -- - - , , Whom not believing there, he took for you; ºn - ºn, Where mad with jealouſie, his cruclimature... º.º. i* (Towhich all Moderation is unknown). . . . . . . . . " - - - - - • * Reſolves to ſtamp aliyour Neglects of him, . . . . . In’s ſuppos'd Rival poor Octavio's heart; . . . . . . . . - - - tº i iſ ºn ºl. He
Page Scan 31

. The Adventures of Five Hous, !, He, and his Friend both draw, Qāavio . . . . . . .” ". Retires, thcy aſſault him, who in's own defence Does kill Don Pedro, and is forc'dig flie. * ~ * : * ~ * My Brother cruclly purſues him ſtill,... . . . . . . . . . . . With ſuchinſatiate thirſt after rivenge, . . . . s That nothing but Qāavio's blood can Quench; , , - Yet covering ſtill his Rage and Jealouſie, . . . . . With the reſentment of Dan Pedra's death. . . . . . . . . Cam. Is this the ſum of your ſad ſtory, Porcia . . . " Is this all? . . . . . --- * . . . . Por. No, no, Camilla, 'tis the Prologue onely, The Tragedy does follow;ithis Tyrant, This cruel Brother, toth'Impetuous Laws . . . . " Of whoſe Tuition, our deceaſed.Parents . . . . . * My Perſon and my Fortune have condemn'd, - * in his unjuſt Suſpicion reflieſ grown," -- . (Which he to palliate Vice with Virtues name, - Does Senſe of Honor call) takes an Allarm , , . . . . And ſtarts at every ſhadow ; as if reproach . . . . Attended all the ačtions of a Siſter, -- - - - | Thoughne’rſo Circumſpe&; and uſes me, As if the Honor of our Family; . - " - Were over-thrown for ever, ſhould my Eyes,” Or Judgment, bebut the leaſt part allow'd * : . . . - In making choice of him ſhould bemy Husband. . . . º). Thereforetofruſtrate all my hopes at once, He has already marriºd me by Proxies - - Toone in Flanders, whom I never ſaw , , Who is this very night expeſted here. , Cam, Isſuch a rigour poſſible, dear Porcia & Por. Was ever Miſerie like mine, Camilla 3 : - - - - - - - Heightned to ſuch extremes, paſt all relicf: If I acquaint my Brother with my Love -- . . . . fºll T' Oštavio
Page Scan 32

The Adventures of Five Hours. . T'OHavio, the man he moſt does Hate, I muſt expect the worſt cffects offury; If I endeavour to Forget Oğavio, … Even that attempt renews hismemory, And freſh Diſquiet gives; If I refuſe To marry, I am loſt; If I obey, I caſt Oğavio and myſelf away. Two ſuch Extremes of ill, noChoice admit, Each ſeems the Worſt; on which Rock ſhall I ſplit 2 Since if I marry, I cannot ſurvive 3 *. And not to marry; were to die alive. Cam. Your Story (I confeſs) is ſtrangely noving; Yet if you could my Fortuneweighwith yours, In Scales of equal Senſibility, You would not change your Sufferings, for mine. Por. What can there be in Nature more afflićting, Thana Divorce from th’Object of our Love , * - - - For ever, to cmbrace the thingwe Hate ; - Cam. Have you not known that Obječtofyour Love? And entertain'd the Perſon you eſtcem? Have you not heard, and anſwered to his Sighs? . . . . Has he not born his Partinallyour Cares tº - Do not you live, and reign within his heart tº . Por. I doubt no more his Faith, than my hard Fate.” “. Cam. But tell me, deareſt Porcia, if I love . . . . " ": One, I ne'r ſhall ſce, and ſuffer as much" " " ... º.º. Without the Means of e'r cyprefing it, … . . . . . . . . As what I ſuffer is above expreſſion; : . . . . If all my Sighs wander in fleeting Air , , , Andne’rcan reach his cars for whom they'rd form'd; If all my Paſſion, all my killing Cares, º, - - Muſt be for ever to their Cauſe unknown; If that their weight muſt ſink me to my Grave; \ Without

End of Section 16. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 17
Page Scan 33

Off s - "st -- ºr " - . - - " whexaventureof Five Hoº * Without one Groan that he can ever hear, /.º. Or the leaſt hope, that Iſſhoulder obtain fl. W." tº ºf By Pitty Eaſe ; or Curé by his Diſdain: , ... in gºt If this the ſtate of my Misfortunebe, , ; ; ; *... . . A Say, deareſt Porca, do you envie me?” . . . . . . . . () Por. What over-cruel Laws ofJDécency ºf Leiſtoriºt. Have ſtruck you dumb? have you misplacid your Love, #! Oh ſucha Subječ, a you dare not own tº º Cam, No, the Cauſe is worthy of the Effect ; , . . . And though I had no Paſſion for his Perſon, ºn of tº ing; I were ungrateful if ſhould not give () tº tº y The firſt place in my Heart to ſuch high Merit. ** . . . . .'' Por. If he has been ſo Generous, to deſerve . . . . . . . . Your Love, why are notyouſo Juſt, tolet º: s - ; : - - - - a . . . .. 5 * , . . . ; W . . . - in Himknow it? . . . . . . . . * - 3, Cam. Tis impoſſible; "Ah! that diſmalwordº ºi Does full ſtate the Difference of our Fortunes: , , . . . . Loſt You, in your firſt Adventure have beencroft, is tº " . But I, before I can ſet outam loſt, ºl... . . Por. Pray make me comprehend this Myſtery. ºn 5 Cam.”fist open my wounds afreſh, dear Portia, , , , But You muſt be obey'd--------- . . . [Afteratitlerºſ, The Conde de Omniate being ſent ºf ºººº... ;- iſ, Embaſſadour unto the 'Emperour; … tº ºvº º Vehaving th’honor to benear ally dº º'º To him, by his Lady, (who likewiſe went tº . . That Journey with her Husband) my Brother . . . Was deſir’d by her to make that Voiage; ' ' ' '.' . . . Whoſe tenderneſsforme, not ſufferinghim ( " . d; To let me ſtaybehind, I wasingag'd ; ºf G iſ And treated by th' Ambaſſadreſſ, my Cozin, With more reſpećt than 1 could ever merit.” Por. She's a Lady, fam'd for great Civility. ... Wilſº ' ' ' ". . . G - Cam, WVe . - *-*. --~~~~ --~~~~ ~~ *-i- 2
Page Scan 34

The Adventures of Five Hours. Cam.We had not paſs'd much time i'th Emp'ror's Corut, When my dear Brother unexpectedly, .. By urgent buſineſs, was call'd back to Sevil; And in our return (too near a Gariſon Ofth Enemies) our Convoy was ſurpriz'd, And routed by a Party of their Horſe. Por. Camilla, you begin to raiſe my fears. - Cam. We Priſoners made, were hurri'd ſtreight away . To their Quarters, where my malicious Fate - - Made me appear too pleaſing to the Eyes Of their Commander ; who at firſt approach Pretends to Parly in a Lovers ſtyle, . . . Proteſting that my Face had chang'd our Fortunes, And him my Captive made: But findingſoon How little he advanc'd in his Deſign By Flattery, and his feign'd Submiſſion 3 He ſhifts his Perſon, callsme his Priſoner, And ſwears my Virgin-Treaſure was his Prize; And yet proteſts he had much rather owe it , k Tomy Indulgence, than his own Good Fortune; . . And ſo through Storms and Calms, the Villain ſtill A Purſues his Courſe to his accurſed End; - But finding me inflexible to Threats As well as Fawnings, he reſolves to uſe . . The laſt, and uncontroled Argument . . . . , , , Of Impious Mcn in Power, Force. . . . . . : … Por. Ahpoor Camilla 1 tell me , where was then . . . Your Brother, at a time of ſuch diſtreſs? . , Cam. My Brother he, alas, was long before . . . . . Born away from me, in the firſt lncounter; . . . . ." Where having certainly behav'd himſelf As did become his Nation and his Name, Remain'd fore wounded in another Houſe, - - - * * * * - -- . . . . . - - • * * º, Por. Pry- - — , - --- . . A - --~/ - --- ---- - - º - ---- º--- . . - - -
Page Scan 35

|f|, The Adventures of Five Hours. 's (m tawi. .P. Piſtols go Por. Pr’ythee make haſe to free me from this fright. i Cam. The Brute approaches, and by Violence” º, . Endeavours to accompliſh his intent; 7. " I Heaveh invoke, and ſtrong Reſiſtance make, But with uncºual force, though Rageſuppli’d Thoſe Spirits, which my Fear had put to flight; . . . . Breathleſs at length with crying out, and ſtriving, ... . .” I ſpi’d a Dagger by the Villain's ſide, . . . . . . . . . . . Whichſnatching boldly out, as my laſt refuge, . . With his own Arms] wound the Savage Beaſt; He, at the ſtroke, u-ſeas'd me, and gave back 3. . . . . . (“So Guilt produces Cowardice) then I . . . The Dagger pointing to my breaſt, crid out , -Villain, keep off, for if thou doſtperfiſt, "... º I'l be myſelf both Sacrifiſe and Prieſts." - I boldly now defie thy Luſt, and Hate; ". . . . . . . “She that dares Chooſe to die, hºck, Fate. º: Drums and Trumpets ſound, . . . , andºff: To Arms , , , , "… . . . To Arms: The Luſtful Satyr flies; I ſtandſ, . . . ." Fix'd with amazement to the Marble floor, "... ". Holding my Guardian Dagger up aloft, ºf . As if the Raviſher had threatned ſtill. - Por. Ifancy thee, Camilla, in that brave poſture • Like a noble Statue, which I remember ºr tº To have ſeen, of the inraged funa, I . . . . . wVºihnderbolt. . . . . Cam, Freed from this Fright, my Spirits flow ſo faſt To the forſaken Chanels of my Heart,. . . . . . . . . . . That thoſe who by their orderly acceſs . . . . . . . . Would have Supported life, by Throngs oppreſs. . . . . O're-charg’d with Joy, I fell into a Swoon; And what was done in this Parentheſis w C2 is / : * *

End of Section 17. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 18
Page Scan 36

--- * -- ---Yº ºn • * * ... .Yºu', The Adventures of Five Hours. Is not within the Circle of my Knowledge, . . . . . . Por, Yº have rais'd me to a flighty Expc&ation; ' ' . VVill the Adventure anſwer it, Camilº º 'º' Cam. At my return to life, op'ning my eyes, Think, deareſt Porcia, how I was aſtoniſh'd, º' - To find there kneeling by myſide, a Man, º, . . . Of a moſt noble Form, whábowing to me; * ºf Aſadam, (ſays he) y'are welcome to the world 3. ‘’’ ‘’’ Pardon, I pray, the Boldneſs of a Stranger, That humbly ſues tyoutoContinue in it; , ; , , , Or if You needs will Leave us, ſtay at leaſt. tº Till I ſhall have Reveng'd your wrongs, and theſiº I'l wait upon you to the otherworld, . . . " ``' For You with-drawn; this willa Déſertſeem, : " And Life a Torment. iſ: º: * . . . . . . & º ; : Por. High gallantry; Corin, for a firſt Addreſs. ºlod i Cam, "ſwasſo Surpriving, that my Confuſion º!, tº Check'd my Reply; but I ſuppoſe my Looks. * 'tºº Didſpeak the grateful Language of my Heart; º: For I .#. of; enlighten º' * : zºº, c. - His manly Face; but, Ofit ſoon was elowāgā, "tº Byfreſh Åi.º.º. Soldiers cry;” tº - . Where's Antonio, th’Enemy is rallid, º' And coming on to give a Second Charge; . . . . . . . He ſtarted up, and with a Mcen, that mark dºº-ºº! sº The Conflić'twixt his Honor and his Love; tºº Madam, (ſays he) the Soul was never yet ſº ... º With ſuch Convulſion from the Body torn; * : * > . . As I from you; buriefitſ. Herbeſºid, ſº ... That Don Antonio Pimentel was ſeemiºſ.' "... º º To Follow in Dangers thoſe he ought to Lead; ' " ' " And thus the Vanquiſh'd, Conqueror Diſappear'd , . Leaving that Image ſtamp'd upon my Heart, " . Tc - - - - - O N
Page Scan 37

The Adventºes of Five Hours.AY To which I all the joys mºſt Sacrifice - - Ofthe poor remnastófmy wretched Life; I - - - If properly to live I mayºbé ſaidyº ºr 3. She puts her | Whchaſmy hopes of Sceighináre dead.ift:%;"f*. Por. What ſaid you was his name,éamilla tº }º . º - | Cam. Don Antonio Pimentel, It lºo, .#4 ºf 514 ! Tor. O Heavéſis.} º; Izºd ºf , sº - liftºn II.x iſºtºlib Lié.1% whº .º. . . . ." Enter Henrique. . . .” - ſº tº . , tº - Hen. I’m pleas'd to find º: of your Husband. - Cam. What's that I heatºharſhusband [Aſide, - Hen. Have you the Letter ready, Ideſir'd you - To write to him riſenda Servant with it,” “º - To meet him on the way;'twill ſhew Reſpect. Porc. You know my Qbediende, Brother; ºiſ; 2.3%. sº . Hen.'Tis well, Siſter. : Wºrridoſ Cuoibo º ºxi's liſts on 2. ... * * * ... i2.ſillºtſ 2'rofts!," Iyo Y . Enter Sylvio. . . ." Logº ſº, sº Sylv, Sir, herº's a Servant of Dow Antonio, sº sº. ~ Newly-alighted at the Gate; be's come oviſ wo: ºl 'wº Poſt from his Maſtery chargºdiwablettºs fºr You...? ſton'ſ Hen. Youndrcould bringinea more welcom News4 xi, Call him in, Sylvia ; Siſter, you may ºf .3.1: … .o. noviº With-draw, and take this time to ask your Cozing:0; Lºº How ſhe likesmy Choice of youtſºlºddilig-Cleathes... Por. My Wedding Gloaghestākhººmiſèrable Maid tº The Heathen ſo to their Reigºd Deities. Eid II . . . Adorn'd the Vićtims they did Sacrifice, º iſ . 1, gºiti i o żº ſig Exeunt Percia'éº Camilla, C .e.:3:2 ... iſoftw.61 ºil, gº of , gºinter|Erneſto and Sylvić.if yº; I sº Ern, signior, Dom Antonio'kiſſes your hands, And ſends me to preſent this Letter to you. . . . . . **** - He *-

Page Scan 38

The Adventures of Five Hours. N. This night, as I expeºted..., 1. And Beautie. [ He gives a Letter to Don Henrique. Don Henrique opens it, and/reming to have , - - - - };. i i , ; , , , , , Hen. I'm glad you left him well; but yet methinks, He writes doubtfully of his being here . - Ern. His Letter, Iſuppoſe, declares his purpoſe. . ." Henr. I’lanſwer’t, and diſpatch you preſently. - In the mean while go make him welcom, Sylvio. ...! iſ tº 5 Exeunt Sylvio and Erneſto at one door, * hand Henrique at the other. A / .…. I , ºf 51..…. . . . * … ." nºw bºil, : ; **'. . . - Enter Sylvio, Erneſto, Geraldo, Pedro, with ſome Cups of Chocolate. . . . . . . . Sylv. Meethinks, Camerade, a ſoop of Chocolate Is not amiſs after a tedious Journcy 3.1 : . . . . . . . . . . Your Maſter's Health.Sir. . . [He drinks. Ern. I'ldoyou reaſon, Sir.’ ” “ - Sylv. Prayhow longist, Brother, ſince you left Spain Ern. "Tis now five years, and upward, ſince I went. . . From Seuil, with my Maſter, into Flanders , lyi ººt º' The King's Fencing-School; whereall his Subjects, ... . Given to Fighting, are taught the uſe of Arms, in And notably kept in breath. - i º sylv. Your Maſter, Iamſure, has got the Fame. º To be aperiousman in that rough Trade...º.º. Ern. He's a brave Soldier, Envy muſt confeſs it. Pedr. It ſeems ſo iſfaith, ſince meerly by the force Of his great Reputation, he can take our Bright YoungMiſtris ſo, without a Siege. Ern. I hope ſhe'lbe Reveng'd on him ere long, And take him too, by the force of her Wit, - Pedr. - -
Page Scan 39

The Adventures of Five Hours. Pedr. Shas more thana Child's Portion, Sir, of both, I dare aſſure you. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ." º, Sylv. But, pr’ythce, Brother, inſtrućt me a little, … Tell me, what kind of Country is this Holland, That's ſo much talk'dof, and ſomuch foughtfor. . . . Ern. Why, Friend, 'tis a huge Ship at Anchor, fraught Withaſort of Creatures, made up of Turf, ºn tº And Butter. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Pedr. I pray, Sir, what do they drinkin that Country? 'Tis ſaid, there's neither Fountains there, Nor Vincs. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . , , , , , , Ern. This is the Butler ſure by his apt queſtion, [Aftd. Fricnd, they drink there a certain muddy Liquor, , , Made of that Grain with which you feed your Mules. . Pedr. What?Barley?can that] .. quench their thirſt: Ern. You'd ſcarce believe it i. dyou but ſeen a How oft they drink. ..., zºº a zºº (Camerade, Pedr. But, me-thinks, that ſhould make them drunk, Ern. Indeed moſt Strangers do thinkſo, butthey 3.” believe it not becauſe they're ſo, Oſteil. * -- ...º.º. tº Ger. A Nationſure of Walking Tuns; the World Has not the like. . . . . . . . . . . . . Ern, Pardon me, Friend, there is but a great Ditch Betwixt them and ſuch another Nation; - If theſe Good-fellows would but Joyn, and drink That drie, ifaith they might ſhake hands. F . Prythce, Fricnd, canthºſe Dutch Harraccios 1ght? ºr * ~ "... º.º. . . " º * * , #. They can doeven as well, for they can Pay Thoſe that can fight... . . . . . . . . . . . . . Sylv. But where, I pr’ythec, do they get their Money : Ern, Oh, Friend, they have a Thriving Myſtery; . - ºu They *
Page Scan 40

The Mºntereof Fººhoº. They'GHeat their Neighbouring Princes of their Trade, And then they Buy their Subjećts for their Sqldiet; ºf Sylv.Méthinksáàr Athies ſhotſdbeat theſe,Dull-Fālows Out of the World.” tº º 'º'; … ºr sºrt ºf | Ern. Theſe pulſfellows will ſooner beatpur Armies Out of their-Coutitry; Why, Friend, ready Mouyº, Will do much jº. fºcºmº ºf Than a Ready Wit, I dare aſſure you. . . ." Mºſ º Ger:Whata Göäsname could come into the Heads . Of this People, to make thern Rebell ?” -: * ~ * ~, º sº -: * , ººlºº gº Burwhita Devil made the Noblemen -- * * -- . . - - - - - - - - - - - Rebel? * * * *. 3. J . . ... . . . . . . . . . ... . . . . . , Ern, why that whichhlade the Devil himſelfRebel, Ambition. 7". ;:3. !. He zºº is ºf … º. º i J º .*, * * - . Sylv. This is a pleaſant Fellow ; , ſº tº "[Affle. I find that you Soldiersdonot want Wit. `sº t * G º º, , , entlemen, your Company's very º -- hº that requires Diſpat à. - - - - " …" º * → Pedr. Willyounot mendyour Draught before you go? Ern. I thank you, Sir, I have done very well.” “” . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ;--> - - - - - - - . . . . . . [#nt. ºz ºr as ºf tº ºn. Hº"? - . . . . : : . º * -- - - - - - - - ... " T.; - . . . . - * , .* 1: ...," ſº ºwn ºr . . . . Cº-ºº! i. i* ºr ºf 3.7 ...! Enter Camilla, Porcia, Flora, , \ -, *, * ~ * : * - - - - - - * c.. " * - .* º º --- ... - Por. Waser Misfortunelketomic, camil, ". Cam, Wase'r Diſaſter, Porcia, like to minº, rº for. That I muſt neverſee oilvio more...º.º. Cam. That I again muſt Dom Antonioſce, '... *** - - - . . Never to ſee him Mine. . . . . . . " º * Por, I, to bemarri'd to the Man I Hate, . . . . . * : * ~ * * ºlfax f. i. I
Page Scan 41

The Adventures of Five Hours. Cam. And I, to have the Man I Love, torn from me. Por. I am, by Robbing of my Friend, undone. Cam, And I (alas) by Yielding, ruine both. - Por, Ye Powers, who theſe intangledfortunes give, Inſtructus how to Die, or how to Live. . . [She weeps. Cam. Cozin, when we ſhould Aét, then to Complain, Is Childiſhly to beat the Air in vain. - Theſedeſcants on Our Griefs do but Perplex, Let's ſeek the Remedy; You know, our Sex This Honor bears from Men, in Exigents Of Love, never to want Expedients. Por. You have awaken'd me, give me your Veil, - Quickly, my Deareſt, quickly; and You, Flora, * * Run and ſee if my Brother be ſetled ; off Camil- To the Diſpatching of Antonio's Man. } ºriº, ºf . . . . . . . . . . . . . . [Exit Flora. Cam. What mean you, Porcia 2 . . . . . . . Por. If once my Brother beſet downto write, ºf I may ſecurely reckon one hour mine; ; , i.e. A 2 º His Wits are onely in his Choler quick, º f : . . . . ." And his Hand ready in Revenge 3, he's ſo . . . Extravagantly |. he diſtruſts . . . . . . - The Meaning of his own ill-choſen Words, And ſo at length can hardly fixon any. , º, . . . . . . This Time I will make uſe of to go ſee . . . . . … is t - Offavia, and let him know that the laſt Term Of allour Hopes is ready to Expire , , - unleſs his VVit, his Courage, and his Love, , , . . . Some quick Expedient find for our Relief. . . . . (him?..." cam. Why, How, and VVhere d'you hope to ſpeak with . Por. In his own Houſe, where he does lic conceal’d, "Tis not far off, and I will venture thither. •. Cam, Know you the way 3. - -> . . . . D Par. Not
Page Scan 42

The Adventures of Five Hours. Por. Not very well, but Flora's a good Guide. 2 . . . . . . Enter Flora haſlily. . . . . . . Flo. O Madam : he's coming already. Por. Ah ſpiteful Deſtiny let us retire, - Cozin, into my Chamber. - * 2: - ſ Exeunt Porcia and Camilla, Enter Henrique and Erneſto. Henr.lf you deſire to ſpeak withher, you may. Ern. I ſhould be very glad to tell my Maſter . . . . . That I have had th’Honour to ſee his Bride. ' ' ' ... Henr. Where's your Lady, Flora . . . . . . Flor. She's in her Chamber, Signior. Henr. Tell her, Antonio's Servant does deſire . . . . . . . To do his Duty to her, ere he goes. [Exit Flora. Friend, you will find her there, without a Veil, . . . . In her Home Dreſs, but you are privileg'd ..., For this free Acceſs, by your Relation. ºr º' ºr Whilſt you wait on her, I'lgo end my Letter, ºf ºf - - [Exit Henrique." ' - Enter Camilla, Porcia, and Flora. Por.If thou lov'ſt me get him quickly away, ºsbegº, Flora Beforemy Brother come, and give him º: a Ecitºr. . . - Erneſto addreſſes himſelf to Camilla, - ſeeing her without a Veil. . . . Ern, Madam, I have been bold to beg the Honor. Of Seeing you, to make myſelf more welcome … sº To my Lord, at my return. ". . . - - - -- Por. A rare Miſtake, further it, dear Camilla. [Aftde. . Who knows what Goodthis Error may produce Cam, Friend, in what ſtate left you your Lord and mine? & - - - - Erm. As * - < - - - -- ~ -- - -
Page Scan 43

- © - - * - The Adventures of Five Hours. Ern. As happy as the Hopes of being Yours - oftº: ; Cam. I would the Malict were ascaſily deceiv'd. [Affae. l pray preſent my Humble Service to him: . . . . . Flora, give him the Letter ; Farcwel, . . . . [Exeunt Camilla, Porcia, and Flora. Ern, Now by my Life, ſhe is a lovely Lady; . . . . . - My Maſter will be raviſh'd with her Form; . . . . . I hope the Bargain, which her Brother made, By th’ º: Wellada's Power , . . . . . (Though founded onely in Intereſt) may prove As happy a Marriage, as any other . . . . Madeafter th’Old faſhion, chiefly for Love; And that ſorare a Beauty may have power Tobring him back to his right Wits again - From his wildl{avings on an unknown Dame, . . . Whomas he fancies (once upon a time) . He recover'd from a Trance, that is, . . . . . From a ſound Sleep, to make him Dreamc'rſince. . . . . l'I haſtento him with this pleaſing news. [Exit Erneſto. *- ~ s : i , iſ . . . . . . . * * Enter Camilla, Porcia, Flora. . . . ." . . . Cam. My sº could hardly hinder me . . . . From laughing at the Formal Fools miſtake; But tellne, did not preſent your Pers'nage : *- With aſſurance? the way for both to thrive, . . . . . . Is to makemeyour Repreſentative. . . . . . [Smiling. . Por. Moſt willingly, and I am confident, v_ ) When you, your Charms ſhall to his heart apply, Youallyour Rivals ſafely may defie. . . . . . . . . . . Cam. I wiſh I could be vainenough to hope it. '''''' But, Cozin, my Deſpairs are ſo Extreme, . . . I can't be flatter'd, though but in a Dream. . > , ' * - D 2 Flo. Aſ dam - - w
Page Scan 44

The Adventures of Five Hours. | - Flo, Madam, do we go, or what a your ſolve on Por. I muſt reſolve, I ſee, yet know not what. " Cam. Cozin, take heed, I am afraid you venture" . . . Too much, your Brother cannot tarry long; And, if returning, he ſhould find you miſſing------- Por, Yºhave reaſon, the opportunity is loſt, What is't a Clock, Flora 2. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Flo. I think near Eight, for the Clock ſtruck ſeven, Juſt as Camilla enter'd the Chamber. -, . . . . Por. Quick then, Flora,fetchyour Veil, you ſhall carry My Tablets to OHavia, there he'l find " " . . . . . The Hour and Place where I would have him meet. ºº - . . . . . . . . . . . . -[Exit Flora. Cam."Tis well reſolv’d; but where doyou deſign Your Meeting . - . . . . . . . . Por. In the Remoteſt part of all the Garden, " . . . . . Which anſwers (as you know) to my apartment; And Flora has the Key of the Back-door. . . . . Cam. As the Caſe ſtands, you chooſe the fitteſt placc. . . . - . . . [Flora returns Weird. ‘Por. Cozin, Ibeg your patience whilſt I write. Cam. You,Flora,by this Accident may chance; Flora write, To ſce your faithful Lover Diego. in her. Tables Flo. He is a faithful Lover of himſelf, . . . iſ Without a Rival, Madam. . . . . sºliº º Cam. Damſel, your Words and Thoughts do not agree; For could we ſee his Image in your Heart, - --- , , … [..." . 'Twould be a faircr far, than cre his Glaſs RC fle&ted. - . . . . . . . . . Flo. Madam, I am not yet ſo very Old, tº ºf . That I ſhould Dote. - ** * * * Cam, Noryct ſo very Young, but you may Love. . . . Dotage and Love are Cozin-germans, Flora. - ~ Flor. Yes
Page Scan 45

The Adventures of Five Howry: Flo.Yes, when we Love, andare not lov’d againy if f For elſe, I think, they're not ſoncarakin. ºf . ; º Cam. I've touch'd a Nettle,and have ſtung myſelf.[Aſide. -- aſ, 42.... c. 12.4 tº C Porcia?ives Flora the ". ..º.º. Should I not play my part, f were to blame,” ſº Since iº...'...}º 2Madam, has Oğavio the other Key” “. . . ºf º Belonging to the Tablets. º 'º º 'º fººt Por: Yes, yes, I praymake haſte. . . . [Exit Flora. Let usretire, Camilia, a little Reſt, 19 ſilº 'º- And Mcditation, may new aids ſuggeſt. - - - , -º- ºf . . . . . . . . . ; **, * * * . . . - - - - * *~ - - - - - * , N. A.C.T. . ; : ºil ºr ... ºo ::= [ . .'; 'prº tº Y. & *- * : ... : THE SCENE, ºn . . . . . . . . . - - - J.'il tº - * 2°. " – ; *... . . . . . . " : - The City of S E VI. L. A f. .2” Mº 23rºfit ºf T. Enter Don-Antonio and Sanchoin Riding-gloathes.) - * * * . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . *Q}r, we are arriv'd in very goodtime...º.º. . . . ii A \- I did not thinkit would have been ſo ſoon, ºn 4 O By an hour at leaſt, but Lovers ride apace. ºf , 9 ‘Why ſmile you, Sáncho º' . . . . sº -- 2 : Sam. Faith at the Novelty of your Amours, . Tofall in love with one,you Scarcely ſaw, ºr tº y And marry one, you Neverſaw; 'tis pretty: ºo'ſ But we póor Mórtals have another Method. ºf 4n. Y'are very pleaſant; this, Sancho, is the place,” VVhere I chargd Ernesio to expect me, . . . . . . . WHOm * º
Page Scan 46

The Adventures of Fiye Hours. VVhom Iſent before to my Brother-in-Law; | But with this Order, not to let him know, tº | -that intended to arrive this Evening; ‘tº Surprizes in Love-meetings render Men . . . More welcome, and have more of Gallantry. . . . . Sam. Since youáre here, Sir, Carlier than you thought; - vviº: go ſhift º:* º And be back here, before Ernesto come; . . . . . . . . . . . Howe're,'tis better, that he wait for you, º, . . . ] Than you for him i'th open Street. . . . . . . . . : Am.' Tis wellthoughton; come, let's to the Poſt-houſe 1 - jº º sº tº ºr ſº [Exeau, r . .312. Enter Don Oćtavio, and Diego. . . . . . oă, Come, Die 'tisſipeto quitour Lurking: les - And to iº ºrrºr.” gło, 5 Die. Of what, Sir 2 Bats, or Owls, now the Sun's ſet? Call you this making of Love 2 me-thinks,’tis More like making of VVar; marching all night ... -- *:::::::::::::::::::"", . The Enemies Quarters. * - - \ . Oğ.VWhy would'ſ not thouventure as much for Flora : ... Die. No in good faith; i ſhall venture enough - Ife'r I Marry her; Il run no hazard, iſ . . . . . . . . . (By my good-will) before-hand. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . OH. That's from your Fear, not Prudence, Diego. * * vº Die. Sir, you may call it what you pleaſe, but I | | Dareboldly ſay, there lives not in the world, | A more Valiant Man, than I, whilſt Danger . . . . . 1)oes keep its Diſtance; but when ſawcily ºf ... ſº. It preſſes on, then (I confeſs)'tis true,' ' ' ". . . . . . . . I have accrtain Tenderneſs for Life, . . . . . . That checks my Ardor, and cnclines my Prudence º, W. . . . . . . Timely
Page Scan 47

The Adventure of Five Hours, º, Timely to withdraw. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . OH. Your Style is wondrous civil to your ſelf; ; ; ; ; ; How you Soften that harſh word, call'd Cowardice; sº I But the Danger is not always evident, º, . . . . . . . WWhen you are peas'd, my Friend, to Run away. … Die, t may be ſo, Sir, HQt to Vulgar eyes; f.º.o But I have ſuch a peircing ſight, that canº, ºn 2 Diſcover Perils cut of others. Ken; , , , , , , … . . . . . WWhich, they not ſeeing ſoon enoughto Shun, Are forc'dt'Encounter; and then their ſtrugling ºf y. Is, by th'unwarie world, taken for Courage, . . . . . . Oš. You have more Light, Diego, I ſee, than Heat; º; But I’lallow your VVit and Honeſty . . . . . . . . . To come to Compoſition for your want . . Of Courage; though it be a Quality, Gº tº , , , , , I may have uſe of; but we loſe our time."; ºr nº WVas ever Lover's Fate ſo rude as mine?: , ; ; 3 - 1 ---> --> Condemn'd to Darkneſs, forc'd to hºmy Head, º - - / Aswell as Love? and to domea Spight, L. g . - Fortune has Contradićtions reconcil'd, cºdex I am at once a Priſoner, and Exil'd, ºr ; c. ſº...o - Enter Antonio and Sancho. ". Ant, Mc-thinks, Erneffo ſhould not tarry long, tºº. - lfnot already come 3 Sancho, how call you …. I ºf , The Street there juſt before us? where you ſee (, , º, - Yon Gentleman with his Cloak o're his face 3', S' 1 have quite loſt the memory of this place. . . . . . . . . . Sam. I am as much toſeck, as you; Sir. … tº . … 4nt. Let us go to him, Sancho, and enquire; i. A He has a notable good Meen; me-thinks, ". . . . . . Ine’rſaw an Air more like Ośavio's. - Oğ, unleſs my eyes do very much deceive me, . 2 : 'Tis
Page Scan 48

The Adventures of Five Hours. 'Tis Don Antonio ; if it be he, Diego, – - - There is no danger in his knowing us; º # ſill i. He ever was my faithful friend; 'Tis he. 3: fºom b.fore his Ant. You injure me, Ottavio, to be ſolong Aknowing one, who is ſo intirely yours. - Oä. Your preſence here, noble Antonio, was . Sounexpºacă, that ſhariyārā "fineyami.ac. Believe my eyes; VVhen game you to this Town Ant. I am juſt now arriv'd. Oğ, I joy to ſee you here, but ſhould have thought #. to have heard of you at Court, - - Purſuing there the Recompences due ºr . . . . . . . To your tranſcendent Merit. . . . . . . . . . . . Ant. That is no place for men of my Moralitie. ~ I have been taught, Qātavio, to Deſerve , . . . . . . . J. But not to Seek Reward; that does prophane ºf ºf The Dignity of Virtue; if Princes . . . . . . . tº ºvº For their own Intereſts will not advance. . . . . . . . Deſerving Subjećts, they muſt raiſe Themſelves : . . . . . By a brave Contempt offortune, ſº ſº, . . . tº Oä. I'm glad to find in you ſome Seeds yet left to gº ºne Of th’Antient Virtue; may they Fruit produce - Fit to Illuſtrate;and Inſtrućt the Age. - - Let me once more embrace you, Sir, Welcome, .....'. Brave Leader. ſº ſº. º. º.º. ...r.o. º. 2:04. Ant. Oh, you muſt ſpare your Servants; Sir. . . . . o. Qā. He has not liv'di'th reach of publick Fame, Who has not heard your noble Character; º; “ This is my houſe, be pleas'd; Sir, to goin, i r ºf . And make it yours; though truly at the preſent :: * ~ * I am in a very ill condition ºf . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ." To receive the Honor offucha Gueſt; ºr Having by an unlucky accident, * . Been -- 2. - - -

End of Section 18. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 19
Page Scan 49

... -- *** -\ ... . . . . The Adventures of Five Hours. Been forc'd of late to keep myſelf conceal’d. . . . . Ant. I humbly thank you, Sir, but cannot yet : Receive that favour, for I here muſt ſtay . . . . Expecting the Return of one, ... " . . . . . . . Before to town to my Brother-in-Law. Oś. Have you a Brother-in-law in Sevil? . You ſurprize me much. " . . . . . . . . . . . . An. It is moſt true, Ottavio, I come hither - A Marri'd man, as far as friends can make me. - OH. Since it imports you not to miſs your Servant, Let us ſlay here without, untill he come; ". - And then go in, and reſt yourſelf a while. , - > But how go our publick Affairs in Flanders : * . . Amt. I left our Armies in a better ſtate, Than formerly. . . . . . . - OH. And our brave Vellada (I ſuppoſe) in great Reputation. - - - - Ant. The Honor of our Country, and the Terror Ofothers; Fortune conſulted Reaſon, When ſhe beſtow'd ſuch Favours upon him. - OH. They ſay he did Wonders at the Relief Of juliers. . . . Ant. It was indeed a famous Aëtion. Ośī. You'l much oblige me, if whilſt you expect Your Servant here, I might learn from your ſelf Some few particulars of your own Aćtions; - Fame ſpeaks Loudly of them, but not Diſtinétly. Ant." Fame, like Water, bears up the Lighter things, “And lets the Weighty ſink; I am notus'd To ſpeak in the Firſt perſon ; but if needs You'l have a ſtory to É up the time, Tl tell you an Adventure of mine own, > * , Where you'l find Love ſo ignia with Arms, - That \

Page Scan 50

The Adventures of Five Hours. That (I am confident) twill raiſe your wonder, . How being prepoſſeſs'd with ſuch a Paſſion, I ſhould (upon Prudential motives onely) . . . " Beingag'd (as now you find me) to Marry A Lady whom I never ſaw. . . . . . Ośī. The Perſon, and the Subjećt, Sir, do challenge My beſt attention. . . . . . . . . Ant. The following Evening to that glorious Day; . . . . . . . . . . . [After a littlepauſe. Wherein our great Wellada gain'd ſuch Fame, . - - - Againſt the cautelous Naſſam ; ſome Horſe : Were ſent from th’Armie, under my command To cover the Limbourg Frontiers, expos'd To th’Enemies Inroads 5 ſcarce ſetled there , , I receiv'd intelligence, that a Party . . . ! . Of theirs (about two hundred Horſe) were come That very Evening to a neighbouring Village, Intending there to lodge; I inſtantly Cauſe Sound to Horſe, and march to their Surprize So luckilie, that by the break of day . . . . . Their Quarters were on fire. . . . . . . Oğ. You had been taught, Sir, by our wiſe General, That Diligence in Execution is * Even above Fortune, Miſtris of Succeſs. Ant. They made but faint reſiſtance; ſome were ſlain, Some periſh’d in the flames, others eſcap'd, Giving th' Alarm in Quarters more remote To their Companions drown'd in Sleep and Wine; Who, at the Out-cry, and the Trumpets ſound, Me-thinks I fancie ſtarting from their Beds, . . . . As pale and wan, as from their Dormitories Thoſe the laſt Trump ſhall rouze; differing in this, That they awake to Live, but theſe to Die. Qš. How unſafe it is to be Secure! Aut.Finding —------------- _ ~
Page Scan 51

The Adventures of Five Hours. - That Body, which, though Dead , ſcarce Mor Ant. Finding no more reſiſtance, I made haſtel. - To a lofty Structure, which I conceiv'd, , , , º, . . . Tobeth likelieſt Quarterfor their Chiefs . . . . . Led thither by deſire to reſcue both; ºf Him, from the Soldier's rage; That, from the Fire. - Oä. A care moſt worthy of a gallant Leader. . . . . Amt. But think, Qāavio, bºwſ wasſurpriz'd, / ; * . - - When, on the floor of a Pavillion, a gº. ...O. ºf Belonging to the Garden of that Houſe, sº to I found a Woman of a Matchleſs Form, - - - Extended all along. . . . . . . . . a º . “ ºr ; ; ; , off. I eaſily can divine how ſuch a Heart, , , º, . As harbours in the brave Antonio's breaſt, tº a May ſuffer at ſo Sad a Spectacle, Ant. At the firſt ſight I didbelieveher Dead s Yet, in that ſtateſo Awful ſheappear'd, º º, That I approach'd her with as much Reſpect 3: . . . . . . . As if the Soul had animated ſtill ºf ºººººº, tº alſeem’d, But as the Sun from our Horizon gone, , . . . . . . . . . His Beams do leave a Tinóture on the Skies; . . .I crº Which ſhews it was not long ſince he withdrew; ...) So in her lovely face there ſtill appear'd in . . . … ::: º, Some ſcatter'd ſtreaks of thoſe Vermillion Beams 3. i. Whichus’d tirradiate that bright Firmament.... sº, Thus did I find that diſtreſſ'd Miracle, fºliº, sº Able to Wounda Heart, as ifialive:, . . . . . . . . . . Uncapable to Cure it, as if dead. . . . . . . . . . . . Oğ. I no more doubt your Pitty, than your Wouder. Ant My Admiration did ſuſpend my Aid, `. Till Paſfion join'd to Pitty, made me bold; tº . I kneel'd, and took her in my arms, tº bowd º Her body gently forward; with which motion, .. - - - E 2 A Sigh \ \ .

Page Scan 52

The Adventures.of Five Hours. - Sobreaks the Day; and ſo do all the Creatures - ~ A Sighſtole from her; Oth'raviſhing ſound ! Which being a Symptom of remaining life, Made me forget it was a ſign of Grief. At length ſhe faintly opens her bright eyes; Rejoice, as I did, at the newborn Light: . . . But as the Indians, who adore the Sun, - Areſcorch'd by’s Beams, ere Half his Race be Runs So I, who did adore her Riſing Eyes, º Found my ſclf Wounded by thoſe Deities. Oä. How you have rais'd my Expectation : . . . Pray releaſe me quickly. - - - 2nt. From her fair handa bloody Poniard fell, - Which ſhe held faſt during her Trance, as if - - Shadonely needed Arms whilſt ſhe did Sleep, And truſted to her Eyes whilſt ſhe did Wake. Where is our Leader? where's Antonio 2 My Love a while diſputed with my Honor, . But that the longerſetled Power o'r-came, . . . And fear of Future danger to her Perſon. a \ . What Iſaid to her, being a produćtion Of meer Extaſic, I remember not; She made meno Reply, yet I diſcerR'd Ina Serener Air of her pale face, Some Lincs of Satisfaction mix'd with Fear. Oğ. Such looks in Silence have an Eloquence. But pray goon. - - . . . . - Amt. Rais'd from the ground, and to her ſelf return'd, I ſtept a fitting diſtance back; as well Togazeupon that lovely Apparition, , , As to expreſs Reſpe&t; when at that inſtant The Trumpets ſound a Charge; my soir, crie 5- Made me then ſeckthe Preſent for myſelf; - _ - & 2. / - -
Page Scan 53

The Adventures of Five Howrs. Icame uptomy Troops, left in Reſerve, As they were ready to receive a Charge From divers Squadrons offreſh Horſe, who being Quarter'd in Neighbouring Villages, had taken Hotly th’Alarm, and came (though then too late) In ſuccour of their friends; Honor and Love Had ſo inflam'd my heart, that I advanc'd Beyond the Rules of Condućt, and receiv'd So many wounds, that I with faintneſs fell. Oä. How can this Story end 1 . Ant. My Soldiers beat th' Enemy, and brought me off, Where Surgeons quickly cur'd my Outward Wounds, But the remembrance of that Heroine, - My Inward Hurtskept bleeding ſtillafreſh; Till by the buſineſs of the War conſtrain'd -- To attend my Charge I'th’Army, my deſpair Of ever finding her, concurring with r The powerfuſperſwaſions of Pellada, I was at length even forc'd to an Engagement Of Marriage with a Lady of this City, Rich, Noble, and, as they ſay, Beautiful. And ſo you have me here, come to Conſummate Thoſe Nuptial Rites, to which my Intereſt, And th’Importunity of Friends advice, - O're-rule my judgment, though againſt my heart. • Oš. A wonderful Adventure! but pray, Sir, May I not take the liberty to ask you, - Who may this noble Lady be, to whom The Fates have deſtin’d ſo much Happineſs? . . - º: I have no Reſerves for you, 'tis the Siſter Of--------- - ... ; ; , Enter -
Page Scan 54

The Adventures of Five Hours. Enter Erneſto , and Oötavio re- tires haſtly, and covers his face - with his Cloak. . . . . . . Antonio modding to Ośtavio. It is my Servant, Sir. . . - O#. Step to Antonio, Diego, and deſire him To ſend him off. - Ant. I will immediately; Well, Erneſto, º Pº." ntonio, and What good news 2 ſpeak freely. whiſpers. Ern, Sir, as you charg'd me, told your Brother-in-Law, I thought you hardly could be there this night; . . - - - ---- ~ * * * He kiſſes your hands, and bad metell you, That he expects your coming with impatience; . He charg'd me to preſent you with this Letter; Th’other is from your beauteous Bride, a perſon . . ." The moſt accompliſh'd that I ever ſaw. - - § being yours gave me the privilege - - - - Ofa Domeſtick, in the free admiſſion Toſee her in her Chamber-dreſs, without A Veil, either to cover Faults,or hide Perfeótions. Ant. Tell me truly, is ſhe ſo very handſom? ' ' ' '. Ern. Handſomer far in my opinion, Sir, Than all the Bruxels Beauties, which you call - The Finiſh'd Pieces; but I'l ſay no more; Let your own Eyes inform you; here's a Key ' Of the Apartment, that's made ready for you; A Lower Quarter, very nobly furniſh'd, That opens on St. Vincent's Strect. - Ant. Give it me; and go you to the Poſt-houſe, And take care that my things be brought from thence. - - - [Exit Erneſto. Oāavio, will you go along with me, t / . - And - *
Page Scan 55

The Adventures of Five H.ours. - And be a Witneſs of my firſt Addreſs? - - OH. Sir, you chooſe in mean lll Companion - For Nuptial Joys, or any Happineſs; - - One, whoſe Misfortunes to ſuch ſad Extremes Are heightned, that the very Mentioning Of Happy hours ſerves onely to Imbitter The memory of my Loſt Joys. Ant. So deep aſenſe of your Misfortunes, Sir, Is prejudicial to your Self and Friends. - - - Enter Flora in haſte. Flo. Where's your Maſter, Diego 2 . - Pie. There's ſome Illtowards, when this Bird appears. Agº.. Do you not ſee him? y’have liv'd too long a Maid. Aſide. Flo. I have ſomething to ſay toyou in private, Sir, That requires haſte. _* [Goes to O&avio. - [She draws Oétavio affae, and puts up her vail. Oä. What new Accident brings you hither, Flora 2 Flo. Theſe Tablets will inform you, Sir, Farewell. . . Die. Will you not ſtay for an Anſwer Damſelf …, Flo.’Tisa Command, not a Queſtion Diego. . . . - Die. Short, and Sweet, Flora. . . . . . . . . O8. Good Flora ſtay a Minute; I much fear - It is ſome new Misfortune. . . . . . . . . . Die. Nay, Sir, you may be ſure’tis ſome Diſaſter, Elſe it would ne'r have come ſo Eaſily, - 2. And ſo unfought for. - • Off. Will you allow me for a Moment, Sir, ſhºwing to To ſtep into my Houſe, and read a Letter. lantonio. Ant." attefid you in, and wait your leiſure, ,- - - - [Exeunt all but Diego. . . Die. Theſe little black Books do more Devils raiſe, Than all the Figures of the Conjurers. . . . . - 2 * - - What .
Page Scan 56

The Adventures of Five Hours. t What can this be I have not ſeen this Damſel With ſo buſie a face; but here ſhe comes Already, 'twas a quick diſpatch. v . \ Enter Flora, and ſeems to go away in baſe. Die. A Word, Flora, or a kind Glance at leaſt, What grown cruel P. Diego nobody w you? Flo. This is no time for fooling: Die. Nay, if you be ſo ſerious, fare you well; Yet I’l perform the Honor of our Street, And bring you to the endon't. . . . . . - Flo. I ſhall be well holpup with ſuch a Squire ; , - If now ſomewandring Knight ſhould chance t'aſſaultyou, To bear away your Damſci, what would you do? Die. I'd uſe no other Weapon but a Torch; I'd put aſide your Veil, ſhow him your face, That, I ſuppoſe, would guard us both. * Flo. Why, d'you think it would fright him, Diego 2 Die. Ohno, 'twould charm him, Flora. “ Flo. Well, ſuch as 'tis, I'l venture it without Engaging your known Valour. - Die. Faith you may ſo ; - The face, dear Flora, defends all below. Flo. Away, you Fool ; Good-night to you. - - - [ Exit Flora. Enter Oétavio and Antonio. LOH.What may this be? O my Malignant Fate! The Warning's ſhort, yet ſhe muſt be Obey'd; / The hour draws near; I muſt go ſeek a Friend; QAftd. Her words ſeem to imply need of a Second ; Twere barbarous to engage Antonio - Newly arriv'd, and come on ſuch an Errand. . . . - - -- i. - Noble – -
Page Scan 57

The Adventures of Five Houkº Noble Antonio, my confuſion's éat, ..º. ºn 9 º' Y º, - To tell you thus abruptly, I muſt leaveydu: , '73 ... . . Th’occaſion's indiſpenſable...in tº ºs liff: i.º.º. 4nt. I muſt not quit you, Sir, I knowtootwell j .º. The Laws of Honor, to deſertyounow ::i5 uſ ... . . . When I my friend in ſuch diſorder ſee, , , , , , , , , Andall the Marks that he is call'd to Danger, - To leave him then-------- Qā. It is a Summons from a Lady, Sir, Whom I have lov'd with Paſſion and Succeſs; To meet her in her Garden preſently: H All is propitious on her part and mine 3, But ſhe's ſo Guarded by a Tyrant Brother, - So Jealous naturally, and ſo incens'd By that new Accidentifold you of, , , ; ; ; – tº Which makes mea cloſe Priſoner all the day; 'º' \\ *-*- That to perſwade youthere no Danger is - In this Adventure, were to abuſe you; , , . . . . . . J . But even for that reaſon I am bound . Not to conſent to the Imbarking you . In an oëcaſion that's º 2 º' “... ." To what you come for; Antonio;We muſt tº ºt. . . As wellté Friends as to our Selves be juſt. . . . . . . . Ant. He ought not to pretend to Friendſhips name , . . . Whoreckons not Himſelf and Friend the ſame. * * * * O3. Friendſhip with Juſtice muſt not diſagree; ; , ; That were to break the Virtue's Harmony. Tº , , º, Ant. Who in his Friends Diſtreſſes takes no part, tº His Friendſhip's onely in his Tongue, not Heart... ... . OH. Youfrom a life of Perils hither come tº To find a Nuptial Bed, not ſeek a Tomb. ºf , ºr, E. i. * . . . . . -- * An My Friending gºd, increr muſtbeſaid, sº Antonio left him ſo to goto #1 ! * º oà.Y’are
Page Scan 58

The Adventures of Five Hours. Oä, Y'are marri'd, and expoſe what's not your own. . Ant. Wedded to Honor, that muſtyieldtonone. . . . . Oä. I find, Antonio, you muſt ſtill ſubdues ºn ..…., , Ant. Ibwmy Triumph tomy Cauſe, not You. . .”. Come, we loſe time, your Miſtris muſt not ſtay, ºr ºf Oä. Who'sſo accompanid, needs not fear his w *: . . " , ºr Lºſ & ºf ºi nº in ºf iv. 2.É Exéunt. --------' aſ; ſiſ...} ), ºf - ** = ºil-----|-- . . . . . . . . . . . - : fººt ºf 3:3: " 'iſ tº ºr ºf 'A - +. *The sch Nºis, ; : J of º *** - b's tº , , ; * . . . . . . . . jº- * : * '-- - º: c. *. * . ran a wrº. tº as , , T05C HENCRIQA/E’s Houſe. . . . 3 ºf ºil. tº 24, wi: G of it. I Camilla, Porcia, Flora appenina Bakone, in tº º Por. Ome, Cozin, the hour aſſign'da Çam. Nay, more thanſo, for 'tis already nightni Flo. And thanksto your Stars ſufficiently dapkº, , , Por. To the Clowds you would ſay, Flºra, for Stars, J. In this occaſion, would not much befriend us. . . . . Pray, Cozin, when OHavio ſhall arrive.,i . . . . . . . . - _* *-** . Do you and Flºra watchabove with care; ſº For if m cruel Brother ſhould ſurprizeus------, ‘. . . . . º - Cam, Let usalone to play the Sentinels." * . . . . Flo. I'm confident he's abroad, and will not * * > . Suddenly return; for Iheard himſay, , , , , , , , ..., He'd paſs th’Evening at the Corigidors ; ; ºf . E.; ºf .*. Enter Andthence, youknow, he ſeldomtomes bomecatly. . v -- ºr " ' ". . . . . . . . . IRD ACT, i. tº . . . . . . . . . . . pproaches, 1.2, .
Page Scan 59

ºf ºil c.º. º. i. º. º. º. . . . . Enter Antonip, Qāavio, and Diego, with their fibaks ºr their faces, and their swords.andrawn in their hands. " 4nt. Isitiot ſomething early for Adventures’ º Of this Nature ? ſ ... : : T. º 'º º 'º. 2 ! i. l º . OR. Tisthe Hourſhe appointed. - 4.4% ºf (... *... Ame. How dark’tis grown ºth ſudden, there's not one' Star appears inabèFirmament.” ". ! #ſº i.e. Dié8ómuch the better; forwhen Imuſtfight ..., I covet no Spectators of my Proweſs, ºr ºf *IAftd. OH. Stay you here, Antonio, PHtepbefores”. ºr , Andgive the Sign; when you here the door ºpen,**** Then come on and follow mein. . ſ: it. "y.º.º. .*.* tº \;. sº **, ºr ; s: " : ; ; ; ; ; *... . . . . Emera theatherfideofthe stage Henrique and Carlos, . . Henr.The Cºrigidors is a pretty place, º' º ... ca. The Walks doſointiceme, falways "...º Weariety ſelf, before ſtan retire. 'º, Henr. Indeed we have ſtaid longer than we thought sº Andtherefore let's go home the ſhorterway;”* * The backdoor of my Garden's here at hand..., , , , , car. It willbºbetter thanºgo about ºil Por.Would he were come;I fear the Riſing Moon tºove. Will give us little time. . . . . . . .” . . . [O&avig knocks upon the Hill ºf his sword. riºticeletºnkº,X; # , * , , ; ; .W.I. ºf -1 tº º J. in -- Por, I hope are not alone; J. : * º ... . . .” .*** - Oğ. No; . Diego with me, and a Friend.” iſ . - ºrºſis well;ITopen the door prºfently. tºo. Henr. Come; we are now hard by the Garden gic. E. Oä. Let's to the door; ſure ſhe's there by this time Be not afraid Diego. F 2 - - - > Die.

Page Scan 60

The Adventures of Five Hours.” Die. Agree that with him that made me, who has Given me a Heart . than my Thumb; ºr º In - Y'had as good command menot to Breath. ..º.º. O3. Comc on 3, what art thou thinking ou? is . . . . . Die. That I ſee Company, or that my Fear does. 93. Y'are in the right; let's to avoidſuſption; the rift ºf Walkºnarlarge still they are ºut of diſtance, iº Carl think Theard your Garden door opcil.º.º. 5:2 Hemr, I thinkſotoos Ha! at this time Gºth'night ºn What £an be the meaning on tº 'lisſo, , , . . . . . . . 4nt. They have open'd the doors,'tis time for me...) To follow, ſurely 9iavia isgonein, , º, .º. - [Antonio moveštawards the door, Por.What ſtay you for?" [Holding the door half open. - Henr. What's that I hear?. ſure 'tis Porcia's voice. . . Por. What mean you to ſland there? come in, I ſay. ---- Henr. Hell and Furies tº ... [He goiste draw his frond. Carl. Be patient, Sir, and you will make a clearer ºxº Diſcovery of your Affront. . . . . . ºf . , º, Por. You may come inſecurely, Ottavio: , , ; ºr: - - ... , ; , , , ... [Setting ºpen the doore. I have ſet thoſe will watch my Brothers, soming, i. 4nt. Madam, I am not Otiavia., ºpiº, . . . Por. Not Ottavio 2 who are you then? and who's ...Henr.I can hold no longer; I'mthy Chaſtiſer, ſpraw: Vile Woman, jë. Chaſtiſer, his ſword "Ant. Ha! my Mortal Enemy 2 ... º. ºº Henr. Yes, Villains who cre thouart, thou ſhalt pay This Treacherſe with thy Life. . . . . . . . . . . . 4nt. Vain Man; who ere thouart, know, the Life thou Threaten'ſt, is Gua . by toogood a Sword..., , ***".. † - - * * * * - * * * * * . * - - - - - . . . - Carlos - - - > - - - - • - -- - - ſ - ~ ---
Page Scan 61

The 4. “Five Hoºrs; v.º.º. ºf y Garlos draws, and they all enter the ºf , i. 2 Garden fighting. . . . . . . . . . . . . : Hebr. Make faſt the doot: 2: º, ... [To Carlos, Heur, Thouat ſome deſperate Villain hird tº murder. . . . cºy" ºr iºnºſºn the Garden. – º – s; , º, of £ Oétavio and Dicgo came to the door. Ant. Hir’d by Fricndſhip, and Honor's my Sallary.,. Lºrº ºf or ºff, ºff [ Andiſ. ºf fighting within. , Q3, Fhat's Autonio's *:::::ideniş; - w hat, the door ſhutºmy Friend engagid sandlºň Excluded , curſed Fate! this ſree may help me::" ºr To climb o're; if not, I'Hlje t' him. - Die. You may do ſo; your noble Edve thas. Wings,' And's ever Fledge; 'tis Molting time withmine:59:1 cºiſ Yet I’lup too; the hazards not in climbing, [Heclimbº, Here I will ſit, and out of dangers reach ºi! ... º.º.º. Exped thełſſue, º AºS off. O -- The Scene thanges to a Gardeh;6Ht of." - which they iſſtić fighting rºl ºf - nich they iſſue tighting. ... 1 Oğ. Courage, brave Friend; you have Q&avia by you..., Ant:80 Seconded;a Coward would grow firm...º. Henr. What is there more of your crue? thenºti; time; To call for help; Höl Sylvia, Geralda, • Pedro, come forth, and bring out Torches with you, , , , º ºs º º, ø, º] - Entes Sylvionith his starddrain... ºrja Sylv. Here am IySir; my Camerades will follow ºf Asſoon as they have lighted their Torches. … [They fight. Ant. How I deſpiſe theſe Slaves Oğavio, sº gº. Having you by nic: , ſº tºpi, tº ſº. [In the Tree. *Dir. ſheir Swords do clatter travely in the dark. . . . Sylv. I’m ſlain.” ". . . ºst. [Sylviofalls. . . . . . . . ." y: Die. Good - z - N lºſt O -

Page Scan 62

The Adventures of Firehours , Die. Good; that's Sylvio's voice; I have ow'd that Fellow A Good-turn this twelve-moutlifºr a Miſtake; Breakingmy Head, when he ſhould have Broke a jeaſt; Nowhé's paid. Gºlfi'ſ 2,812, 12, ſilo, 1sh ºx{1 \º. ****śHenrique ſtepping backfalls over Sylvio, and ºf loſes his Smard, and Carlos runs in to him. Car. What! are you hurt?.g., ſº I gº ºst. ºw: No, onely if { } Help me to find my Sword. ..ºhatºyºgive taºkºyou do well toºkabreath, Whilſt you'haweliny left; twiſlnot belong, Sºñº. Now that the Riſing Moonlands is ſomelight,ºf - -- - - inid' [Potgiarºus putto Q&avid. Par:O6tiatio 3 latinotºhismoment flip La Lºſ .sº To Freemefrom my mixi Brother's Fury;... I 19, 2 ºf, Or never hopete ſegme any more L.A.: 2.1 : º, . . . . . . . . Amongſt the living. … º.º. º. Lºs : . . . . . ; [Oétavio leads her away by the 4rn. oã,3}}Noblºg ifighty poſſeſºdi, Of º; º; … 2. i Lethim live Wretched, and Deteſted dić;" Where's my brave Friend? … : “. . .25°º 2...& Ant. You havemeby youtſide, lead off your Miſtris, I'lſecureyour Retreatº 39 yºxa tºil ºf it, ºvº.º. [Exeumi Oétavio, Porcia, and Antonio. Die. That doubtleſs is my Maſter, who vićtorious & ... [In the Tree pointing to thoſe who are going off. Isbravely maréhingoff with his fair Prizes” Ildown, and follow, inventing all the Away is on ºf . º. Some handſome Lie t'excuſemy Cowardice; , , º, Why liv'd not Ifive thouſand years ago, tº ºt; … Being ne'r made for this damn'd Iron Age?"g Lo, ºgº - Hºuſ ºf ſix, ºpiego'comes down frºm the Trree, **oº. ' - sºfollows Antonio, º f : \º. - ~ * : *ſ: . . . Car.But
Page Scan 63

The Adventures of Five Hours. Tcar.But whilſtmydarekdmetoſuccolrygus #zº Our Enemies, Iftargare got away; ºr, ſt *::::: lic.” I heard the door open, and ſee none Hergºt tº Lº? Although the Night's much brightergrown than'twas 3. I’l follow, and tract the Villainsifican is g.º.º.o. i. To their Dens; meanwhile take careofyeut $iſters, waſ And (pray) till my pºtaſtníbaſſicklerate,...sº ºn, ºr Henr. How I Moderationinthis caſe lawhat boºk, 1.Y Geraldo, Pedro, ahye curſed Rogues, ºr is ſº of - - ...ijº º Gº. ... Enter. Servamºrith Tarther...r.º.º. Durſtye not ſhºw.your headstill they wºrégone? Geraldo, light me in, whilſt Pedrº looks . . . . . . . . . To his hurt Companion; ah Portia! Porcial, ºr { Exeunt Henrique and Geraldo; Pedro carries ºut Sylviofainting with his hurts, Lºla, , , ...I “... *****.*** {, , . . . - The Scene Changestbthe City of SEKHL. h; Cº cººl...º.º. ii º ºxº. 2. ºn 3 Enter O&avio, Porcia, Antonio, and a little after Diego, . . . . xiii, and after him Carlos... tº . . . ... ºozººi ºilº ºf fºr Die.Sure,that's Antonio bringing up the Rere; ſpointing to 'Sir, th’are but . bears her... .Y.Satlº's Moſt gallantly away; loſt nºt fight of me. . . . . . yºſhiºglººms fºrgºthiºrºw; A He will by his miſtake help me to harbour’em, ... . . - [Exeunt. - … ſº 2°. ." . .” ---, º'-' . . . . . . . …ii ººſii Cº. ºffſ * * * * * * * * * {{..." -** "tcºminariºsºriºkºlº." …] o' ºf .” ". … ºil toº. 1.1--" ".. The Scene changesto Dan Hanrique's Houſe. - - r *: *. Try S. it, . . . . . . . ) * * * *, *..…"? Q. o. ºº Cam, Was there ever ſuch a Diſaſter, Flºra 3, ... " - . tº - Sure
Page Scan 64

The Adventures of Five Hours. Sure, th'are all dead, ſo great's thc Siknce, ſº jº.º.) - Flo. Madam, if I miſtakótiot Wºry much; sº tºº tº I heard your Brother's voice amongſtem, pºſſ iºd . Cam, Å. my dear Brother, how thyill-plac'd Friendſhip upon that Brutal Kinſman has abus’d ... " " ºf Thy Goodneſs; though my Natural affection I ſº or Moves me, Flora, to Pittyhimih.Danger, ſº (º) ºn A Yet my Concernment formy Colin Portià ºf sº, Does prevail at preſent; forcia, Porcia; , , , , , º, Nobody anſwers. * . . . . . . . - Flo. Madam, let us go down into the Garden. . . . . . Cam. Take heed of that; 'twere to involve myſelf ºti In this unlucky Scandal; 'tis poſſible, iſ ºn: . .º.º. Affrighted with the Scuffle, ſhe's return'd, 2 × . . . . . . Into her Quartet by the other-door; . . Let us haſt thither, sº º 'º'; ' ' | - - -- . . ... [hey gº down and enter upon the Stage. } Flo, Oh! Madam, iſoea Light, and Don Henrique | Coming this way with his Sword drawn, what ſhall -": ..." . . . . . . . * -- ~~~. . . … .VWe do?,’’. ‘’.A. i. ºst, . ciliº, ſº ... yº)". - . . . . ºxº ! Cam. Peace; letushide ourſelvesbehind the door, Till we diſcover his Intentions. - - /* : ! . . . . .'; ...º.º. . º, . . . ." . Enter Henrique, and Geralda with a Torch, and Pedro with a Light; Henrique and Geraldo their Suvrdº draws; º' Pedr. Sir, I have ſearth'd all the Rooms of the Houſe, Andamoi ſãºr. T. "Tº Tº Henr. Baſe Infamous Woman ; maybe ſhe's fled Toth'Quarter order'd for Antonio. ºf Pedr, That door is lock'd, his Scrvant has the Key. . Henr. Ah this unworthy Wörnand tâustofobº ſº I A Brother of the Fruits of all his Care; - And caſt this Stain on th' Honor of our Houſe; - * But
Page Scan 65

The Adventures ºf Five Hour. But ifever get the Fugitive • * Within my reach, "I Sacrifice her Blood. . . . . . . . . To the Offended Spirits of my Anceſtors. . . . . . . . . . Flo. Aſadam, dº you hear * … . . . . Cam. I, and tremble, Flora. . . . . . . . . Henr. Call out for her Woman. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Pedr. Flora, Flora. wºn tº . . . Enter Flora. Flo.My good Angelguardme;what would you have Sir? Henr. Where's your Miſtris, Huſſy; ; , . . . . . ; Flo. She told me, Sir, bout half an hour ſince t . . ) She would go down into the Garden. . . . . [Exit Flora. Henr. My Shame is certain; ah! the ſad condition Of us Men of Honor how unequally, “ . º Our Croſſes and our Comfortsmingled are : º, . Our Orphan Siſters are no ſooner grown. . . . . . . . . Above the Follies of their Childiſh Age; , , , , , , , During which Seaſon Cuſtom does exact . . . . . . Our Watchful Caution overall their A&ions; . . . But they are Grafted on ſome Stranger Stock, . . . ; Where they do change both their Aboads, and Names, Without Reflexion in the leaſt Degree - Of Gratitude, on thoſe, who Pain'd themſelves To Cultivate their Youths 3 or elſe become An Hourly Torture tous, whilſt the beſt Continu'd in our Care do never.ceaſe gº Togive the Fears at leaſt of what I feel. Ounjuſt Heavens! why ſufferyouthat they, Who toour Joys of Life ſuch Bubbles are, i. - Should add ſuch Weight unto our Griefs, and Care 2 - r Ah 'Porcia; Portia! . . . . . . ºf . , ... . . . G Enter

Page Scan 66

The Adventures of Five Hours. - - Enter Carlos. . . . Car. Cozin, I'm much miſtaken, or I have ºn In very Little time made a Great Progreſs Towards your Revenge; I comefrom harbouring The Villains, who have done you this Affront. Cam. It imports to be attentive now. - Henr. Oh, you revive me, may l but once enjoy . . . The Pleaſure of my Revenge, though the next Moment were the laſt Period of my Life, I ſhould depart contented; are the Villains Within our reach * , - - - - - - - Car. Be patient, Sir, and I'l inform youfully; You were no ſooner up, but I purſu'd Your flying Enemies, hoping the night Grown ſomewhat Lighter, would enable me (At a convenient diſtance) to diſcover The place of their Retreat; one of their Partie, Who was behind the reſt, miſtaking me . . . For one of his Camerades, bad me come on 3 - Saying his Maſter was but juſt before; That he had born his Miſtris bravely off. We had not paſt above a Street or two, Before he ſtopt, and at the ſecond Houſe . Beyond the Church in St. Iago's Street, He enter'd, and deſir'd me to follow him; I making a ſtand, he grew ſuſpicious, And from my Silence gueſfing his Miſtake, He ſlipt into the Houſe, and lock'd the door; I having well obſerv'd the Street and Houſe, Return'd with ſpecdtogive you this account. Flo. Oh, Madam, this is Don OHavio's Houſe; Without all doubt they've carri'd Porcia thither. Cam. Peace, Flora, and liſten to the ſequel. Hºn. Come,
Page Scan 67

The Adventures of Five Hoºrs. Hen.Come,Cozin, we looſe time;call all my Servants; I will beſiege the Houſe; if they refuſe ºf . , , , To render; I will reduce that Theater 'º';* * * * Of my Shame to Aſhes, and make their Fort º º Both Theirs and its own Sepulchre; There are Such Charms in Vengeance, that I do not wonder, " . It is reſerv'd for him, who form'd the Thunder. . . Car. Have patience, Cozin, and conſult your Reaſon i. 'Twill ſoon convinceyou, how unpračicable " And Vain your Propoſition is, t'attempt ''' At this time of the night, within a City,. . . . . A Houſe ſo Guarded. That, indeed, would prove . . . Very like Thunder, which the Clowd deſtroys ** Wherein’twas form’d, producing onely Noiſe. - What can the Iſſuebe, but to Allarm " " The Town ; expoſe your Perſon, and your Fortune To th’ Rigour of the Law 5 publiſh your Shame 3 And fruſtrate your Revenge for ever? ... . . . - Henr. What would you have metarry till theſe Villains, Who have invaded my Houſe; Affronted My Perſon; Murder'd my Servant; and Robb'd Me of a Siſter 3 may evade my Vengeance 2 . . . . . . Car. No; fear not that; let me alone to find A certain way to hinder their eſcape; : * * * * l’l inſtantly to the Corrigidors, . . . And beg th'aſſiſtance of his Authority, To ſecure theſe Criminals for the preſent, & That afterwards the Law may puniſh them. # , Henr. A fine Propoſalſ why, Cozin, can you think That l'Iſubmit a Perſonal Injury unto a tame Deciſion of the Law 8 . . . w And having been Affronted by the Sword , . . . . To pray the Aid of the Long Robe, and take ~ An

Page Scan 68

The Adventures of Five Hours. An Advocate for Second car. Your Provocationsgreat, Reſentment's juſt; But, Cozin, the Greater they, the More you ſtandi, scº In need of Moderation, and th’Advice . . . . . . it Of ſuch a Friend, as you have always found me 3. . . Nor can le’r expreſs it more than now, - Infreely tellingyou, you muſt not ſuffer ºr " Your Paſſion to Commandin this occaſion; “Paſſion, § hereſoever it contends . . . . . . “To Govern moſt, there moſt Deſtroys its Ends, , , , Henr. Oh how I hate your drie Moralitic | To treat a Friend with Sentences; that's raging. In a Feaver 3 you may as well pretend, To teach a Manto Sing his Part, th: 'ſtretchd . . upon a Rack *:::: I’I ſºn: die, - Thanerºconſent to publiſh my Diſgrace, Before I have Reveng'd it, . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Car: 'Tis far from my intent; all my deſign . is onely, how . Conceal your Shamg, Till we have got theſe Villains in our Power. Which can be brought about by no ſuch means, As by demanding Juſtice againſt thoſe, . . . . . . . Who did aſſault your Perſon, and have ſlain Your Servant; a moſt plauſible pretence. . . . … Will this content you? truſt my Condu& Cozin 3 Is not my lintereſt the ſame with yours ? . . . . Henr. Well,ſince it muſt befo, I pray make haſte. . . . Car. Doubt not my diligence; by this I'l prove ºr " Friendſhip has Fire, and Wings as well as Love, . . . Hen.If you §. move with too much Leiſure; Ah tedious Minutes which Revenge does meaſure I \, [Exit Carlos. Fb. Madam,yiavelcardúciº miſdicººdſ. - Cam.Yes,
Page Scan 69

The Adventures of Five Hoters. ~ Cam. Yes, Flora, out of queſtion Porcia's there; ; And if they find her,ſhe is loſt forever. " … :: * * Flo. I'le try to Hinder it, though I were ſure..., To Periſh in th’ attempt ; I am confident tº ... . The Houſe at preſent is in ſuch confuſion, I may run thither without being miſs'd. Cam.'Tis well thought on 3 in th’interim I'l retire , To Porcia's Chamber, [Exeunt from behind the door. ...' ... . . . . . . . . . . r, tº ‘Enter Geraldo. . . º . Ger. Sir, Don Antonio is juſt now arriv'd. Hemr. Ha! what's that you ſay Sirrha 2.4. tº ºn. Ger. That Don Antonio, Sir, your Brother-in-law ºn. Is without, walking i'th Hall, and bad me . . . . . . . . z Give you notice of it, ſhall he come in?... . . . . . . . . . . . Henr. Antonio arriv'd O Heavens ! this Circumſtance Alone was wanting to complete my Shame, , , , … : :º) When he deſires to See his Wife, ſhall I • My ſelf inform ſo generousa Perſon, * ~ That ſhe is Run away 3 where ſhall I find … . . . . A Heart, a Tongué, a Voice, or Breath, or Face . . . . Toutter this unparallel'd Diſgrace . . . . . A Ger. What isyour pleaſure, Sir Don Antonio, i.e. May think it long. . . º' -- . . . ºf . Henr. Wait on him in, but at the ſame time tell him You cannot find mc; I will leave my Houſe, . . . . . . . . And the diſcovery of my Shame to Fate; , , , , , ºr ſº And any Cenſur; rather undergo', ; , , , , , , , … Thanbé Relater of my own Diſgrace ; , , , , Till firſt I have my Honor's Ranſom paid . . . . . . . . In the Vile Blood of that perfidious Maid....., x, sº . . . . . .” Éxit Henrique. Enter Antonio and Erneſto... . . . . .a. Am. Myfriendandhiſai Măiţăfºlyiodgå, - 4: . And

Page Scan 70

The Adventures of Five Hours. And free from their Adventure 5 'tis now fit To mind my own Engagement; But Erneſto, VVhat can the meaning be of this indecent Suffering me to remain without thus long upon my firſt Arrival? come, let's goo Into the other Rooms. - Ern. Iſwear, Sir, I'm amaz'd at this great change; 'Tis not above two hours, ſince I found here - A numerous and well-order'd Family, In all appearance, nowd ſee the Pages Boult out of the doors, then ſtart back again . . . . Into their holes, like Rabbets in a Warren; . . . . . The Maids lie peeping at the Garret windows,' ' ' ' . Like th' upper Tire of Ordinance in a Ship; "-" - All looks diſorder'd now; nor can I gueſs . What may have caus'dſoſtrangean alteration; But there iſee the Servant you ſeat in. ' ' ' ' '. - Enter Geraldo. Ant. Friend, where's your Maſter? Ger. I cannot tell, Sir. - + -- Ant. VVhere is his Siſter 2 - - - Ger: Intruth I know not, Sir; we Men-ſervants Have little to do in the Ladies Quarters. . 4. . . - - [Exit. Geraldo, Ant. This looks but odly; are you ſure Ernesto, Y'have not miſguided me to a wrong Houſe? Erm. If you are certain that we are awake , , , Then I am certain this is the ſame Houſe - Wherein this afternoon I ſaw, and ſpoke with Don Henrique and your Bride; by the ſame Token There was a Lady with her in a Veil; . . . - And this very Room is the Ante-chamber º' . . . . . . - - To
Page Scan 71

The Adventures of Five Hours. To her Apartment. . . . . . . . 24at. I ſhould befinely ſerv'd, if after all This Negotiation, and a tedious Journey, My Pains and Patience ſhould be caſt away On ſome ſuch wither'd Sybil for a Wife, As her own Brother is aſham'd to ſhow me. * * * - - . . . . . . . . . . . . . [Erneſto Goes towards the doore. Ern. You'lſoon be freed from that fear, Sir. . . . . - Amt. How ſo 2 Erm. Becauſe I ſee her in the Inner Room, Lying along upon her Couch, and Reading; . . . - : Herface is turn'd the other way, but yet . . . . . Her Shape, and Cloathes aſſureme it is ſhe. . . . Amt. Artſure’tis ſhe - - . . . . . Erm. There are not many like her. . . . . . Amt. If thou beſt ſure’tis ſhe, l'lventure in, Without her Brother's help to introduce me. . . . . . . Ern. She's coming this way, Sir. . . . . . Camilla Enters Reading. Cam. Yºhave reaſon, Dido, and 'tis well remarqu'd, * The Woman, whoſuffers her ſelf to Love, “Ought likewiſe to prepare her ſelf to Suffer; There was great Power in your Charms, ~£meas, Tenthrall a Ladies heart at firſt approach s , . . And make ſuch early and ſuch deep Impreſſions, . . That nothing, but her death, couldere deface. . . . . ." Alas! poor Didol . . . . . . . . . . . . Ant. What do I ſee; or do Iwaking dream . . . . . 2. Antonioſeeing her,ſtands as if amaz'd. Sure I am aſleep; and 'tis a Viſion - - Of her, who's always preſent tomy Thoughts; , , , WWho fearing my Revolt does now Appear T . - * * O t --

Page Scan 72

The Adventures of Five Hours. To Prove and to Confirm my Conſtancy. . . . . . . . . . . When firſt i ſaw that Miracle, ſhe ſcend . . . . . . . . An Apparition, here it muſt be one, , , , , , , Era. What fit of Frenzy's this, Sir why'tis Porcia, A Lovely Living Woman, and your Bride. . . . - Ant. The Bleſing is too mighty for my Faith. ... 'Erm. Faith; iner trouble yourFaith in this occaſion, Approach herbókily, Sir, and truſt your Senſe. . . . . . Ant. As when we dream of ſome Tranſporting Pleaſure, And finding that we Dream we fear to Wake, º, … . Leſt Senſe ſhould robus of our Fancie's Treaſure,' … Andour Delightful Viſion from us take 5: ... iſ ºn . . Bleſs'd Apparition; ſo it fares with me.' . . . . . . . . . That very Angel does once more appear, . . . . . . . . To whoſe Divinity long fince I raisid . . . . . . . An Altar in my Heart, where I have Offer'd . . . . . The conſtant Sacrifice of Sighs and Vows. . . . . . My eyes are open, yet I dare not truſt’em; * , Bliſs above Faith muſt paſs for an Illuſion; If ſuch it be, O let me ſleep for ever Happily deceiv'd; but Celeſtial Maid, . . . . º. . If this thy glorious Preſence Real be, . . . . . . O let one word of Pitty raiſe my Soul . . . . . . . From Viſional Delights, and make me die With Solid Joy inſtead of Extaſie. . Ern.’Slife he's in one of his old Fits again 3. .. VVhy what d'you mean, Sir? 'tis Percia her ſelf. - Cam. I am that Maid, who to your Virtue owes Her Honor then, and her Diſquiet ſince; Yet in my Pain I cannot but be Pleas'd To find a Stronger Paſſion juſtifi'd , . . . . . By Obligatign; I may avow the Fire, º, . . To which both Love and Gratitude conſpire. . . - Ant. Incom- * -
Page Scan 73

The Adventures of Five Howr. v. - Ant.Incomparable Creature! can it be? | * * That having Süffer'd all, which mighty Love. . . . . . . . . Did er inflict, I now ſhould be repaid ºf Loſ With fuller Joys, than Love could ever give; ºzº. Fortune to make my Happineſs complete, ; - - - - Has joyn'd her Power, and made me find a Bride In a Lóſt Miſtris, but with this Allay, ºo, º º Of leaving me no Means my Faithto prove, º Y - w f , But how can that conſiſt with ſo much Paſſion X if: 'Tis poſſible the Senſe of my Diſtreſs'd tº Condition might diſpoſe à Gentle heart tº To take Impreſſions then, which afterwards ºf: 1...ſº Time, and your Second Thoughts may havel»eſtroy'd; ; ; But can a Conſtant Paſſion be produc’d - From thoſe Ideas Pitty introduc’d 2 tº . . …, Let your Tongue ſpeak your Heart, for ſhould y'abuſe me, I ſhall in time diſcover the Dcceit ; You may Paint Fire, Antonio, but not Heat. Amt. Madam----------- ... . . . . . . Cam. Hold; be not too Scrupulous, Antonio; ; , , Let me Believe it, though it be not True; tº j : . For the chief Happineſs, poor Maids receive, sº tº Is when our Sºlves we happily Deceive. . . . . . . . . Ant. If, ſince I firſt thoſe onquering Eyes beheld, You have not reign'd unrival’d in my Heart; º; ) . May du Deſpiſe me, now you are my Own, Which is, I think, all Curſes ſumm'd in one. . . . . . But may your Servant, Madam, take the boldneſs To ask, if you have ever thought of him ; _1 * w * - * * , , t → - - - - Can. A \ Since Chance anticipates the Hopes of Love. . . . . ] Cam. The Scrvant's Error has miſled the Maſter, ) . . . . . He takes me too for Porcia, bleſs'd Miſtake; . . . ( ..., Affiftmenow Artful Diſſimulation; ſº ºf Aſide.
Page Scan 74

The Adventures of Five Hours. Cam. A Love, ſo founded in a Noble Heart, Has need of no Remembrancer, Antonio; … ." You know your ſelftoo well; thoſe of your Trade Have skill to Hold, as well as to Invadé. Ant. Fortune has lifted me to ſuch a Height Of Happineſs, that it may Turn my Brain, When I look down upon the reſt o' th' world... . . . . . VWhat have I now to wiſh but Moderation. 4 º' To Temper, and to Fix my joys 2 - Cam. I yield as little t'you, noble Antonio, In Happineſs, as Affection, but ſtill . . . Porcia muſt do as may become your Bride, , , And Siſter to Dan Henrique, in whoſe abſence. - > Alonger Conference muſt be excus’d. And ſo I take the freedom to withdraw. -- Should I haveſaid untill Don Henrique came ... º. His preſence would have mart'd my sº ſide. [Exit Camilla. Ant. Where Beauty and Diſcretion ſo combine , , 'Tis Heaven, me-thinks, to find that Treaſure mine. - Enter Henrique. . . . . Henr. Sure Don Antonio, having long ere this Found out th’infamous Flight of my vile Siſter, VWill be retir'd to meditate Revenge .. - upon us both : ah Curſe I he is there ſtill; I'l ſlip away ; but, O Heavens ! 'tis too late, He has perceiv'd me. . . . - - - Ant. How, Don Henrique ! avoid your Friend that's cºme So long a Journey tembrace you, and caſt : *-ºs Himſelfat the feet of your fair Siſter 2: . Henr. Noble Antonio, you may well imagine The trouble I am in, that you ſhould find A - * *-x.i. My - - - ~/
Page Scan 75

The Adventures ofFive Hours. My Houſe in ſuch Diſorder, ſounfit Yºº 1.3 L º The Honor to receive of ſucha Gueſt.º. tº . , , , , , Ant, "Tis true, Don Henrique, I am much ſurpriz'd. With what 1 find ; I little did expc& ... . . ºf ſº Your Siſter Porcia ſhould have been----, * : . . . . . ; Henr.Oh Heavens! I'm loſt,he has diſcover'd all, [Aſide, 'Tis not, Antonio, in a Brothers power, 8 9-5 tº sº, i. To make a Siſter of a better Paſte, Slovº º * * * ~ * - ~ * . . Than Heaven has made her. H. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Ant. In your caſe ſpecially; for out of doubt, Heaven never made a more Accompliſh'd Creature, ps. Henr. What means the Mān º ºxiºidºs Ant. I come juſt now from Entertaining her: , , Whoſe Wit, and Beauty ſo excell all . tº -- Of her fair Sex, whom Ihave ever known, o.º.º. 1 . . . That my Deſcription of her would appear Eroii i Aws Rather Detradion, thana Juſt Report bººp, do Of her Perfeótions. "g. ...— … ºº Henr. Certainly he mocks me; he never could) . . . Have choſen a worſe Sufferer of Scorn 3 ºntºy But I will yet contain myſelf awhile tº 6 p. * *. To ſee how far he'l drive it ; Sayyou; Sir sº, tº That you have Seen, and Entertain'd my Siſter 2. . Ant.Yes, Don Henrique; and with ſuchfull Contentment, So rais'd above Expreſſion, that I think ºnto sº, ºr /. The Pains, and Cares of all my former Life ºf . , tº Rewarded with Exceſs, in the Delightº: , , , , Of thoſe few Minutes of her Converſation; . . . . . . . 'Tis true, that Satisfaction was abridg'd * - By her well-weigh’d Scºerity to give me ºf , º, º A greater Pleaſure in the Contemplation Of her diſcreet Obſervance of the Rules . Of Decency; not ſuffering º though now : - 2 - - vº - A * , , - - - -- ~ * - - - Her - *~

Page Scan 76

The Adventures of Five Hours. Her Husband, any longer to enjoy. . . . So great a Happineſs, you being abſent. . . . . . . Hehr. I am confounded; but I muſt diſſemble . MyAſtoniſhment, till I can unfold . . . - The Myſterſe; She might have ſpar'd that Caution,? Aſide. But I ſuppoſe you’leaſily Forgive . . . . . . . . . . ). . An Error on the Better ſide. . . . ." . . . . . . . . . . . . . Ant. Sir, I have ſeen ſo much of her Perfeótions,' ' ' . In that ſhort Viſit, I ſhall ſooner doubt . . . . . . . . All Definitions in Morality, . . . . . . . . . . Than oncé ſuppoſe her capable of Error.º.º. Henr.This Expoſition makes it more Obſcure: [Aſide. - r Innuſt get him away. Sir, is't not time º, I I bring you to your Chamber 2 it is late ; . . . . And I believe that you have need of Reſt. . . . ." - Ant. I ſhould accept your offer, were I not . . . . . . Oblig'd, as late as 'tis, to ſee a Friend.º.º. 1. . . . . . . . Before I go to Bed. to . . . to ºx! Henr.ſi wait on you, Sir, ifyou'lgive me leave. * * Ant. Phumbly thankyou, Sir, but can't conſent sº To give you ſo much trouble; I'l returnº). . . . . . Within an hour at fartheft. : : º, … . . . Henr. When cºr you pleaſe: y’are wholly Maſter here. 4nt. I never ſaw a man ſo Diſcompos'd, . . [Affa. Whater thematter is. [...], º, . . dº º 'º', Ernesto, I muſt make a ſtep to ſee ºr ºf . , , , , A Friend near hand; bid Sancho follow mé; , . . . . And ſtay you in my Chamber till f come. " " -- . . . . . [Exeunt Antonio, Erneſlo. Hemr. Your Servant, Sir; this ſudden Salley hence ºf - º! [Henrique waits on him to the door. At this time of the night, and newly’arriv'd From a long Journey, does imbroil me;more. - - But
Page Scan 77

The Adventures of Five Hours. - But now I will not longbeinSuſpenſe . . . . . . . I'l to my Siſter's Chamber. - * * * * *- : * * Enter Carlos as Henrique is going into Porcia's Chamber. Car. Ho Don Henrique, there is haſte requir'd : all's, , , Prepard, and if the Quarrie lodg’d ſhall prove . . . . . . Worthy of our own Swords, we may employ them; If not, the Sword of Juſtice ſhall revenge . . . . . . . . Our Injuries; for the Corrigidor Isready with a band of Serjeants. . . . . . . .” Henr. Speak ſoftly 3 Don Antonio is arriv'd , And ſome of his may over-hearus. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Carl. That's very unlucky, but does he know . . . That Porcia's miſſing 3 . . . Henr. Ithink not yet. . . . .” - . Carl. Come, let's away; we haveno time to loſe. Henr, Pray ſtay awhile 3:l labour with a Doubt º Will burſt me if not clear'd before I go. . . . . . . . Carl. What Cozin' will you looſe an Opportunity Never to be recover'd are you mad 2 . . . . . . . . . Will you permit the Villains to eſcape, sº . . . . And laugh at us for ever? come away. " [Hepulls him. - * - - - - . . . . . . . . [Exit Carlos. Henr. Well, I muſt go; and let time make it out; “The worſt Eſtate of Human Life is Doubt, º, . . . • * - -- ---. * , , tº '. º … " - ... " 1. - ' ' -- ...? : ; ; ; - 2 . . . . " '94 l - - * , ! … a “… ºf - - | - / • * , " ; * * ºf . . . . ." . . -- * ... -- - - - - --- * * * > * ; : } * * * * : * * \ -- -- - - - - - -- +4 ° - - ºr

End of Section 19. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 20
Page Scan 78

The Adventures of Five Hours. THE FOURTH ACT. . The S C E N E is To Nº. oc TAvio's Houſe. Enter O&avio angrily puſhing Diego, and Porcia following. - *Vº thou haſ undone us , curſed Villain;. Where was thy Soul,had Fear quite Baniſh’d it? And left thee not one grain of commonSenſe 2, ... . . . . Porc. Was there ever ſo fatalan Accident 2 . Oś. Why, Traitor, did'ſt thou not let me know it, As ſoon as we were come into the Houſe? -- Die, What wouldy' have done if ye had known it then? Oä. I would have ſally’d Out, and Kill'd the Rogue, In whoſe Power thou haſt put it to Deſtroy us; - Can it be doubted, but that longere this He has acquainted Henrique where weare? - . . . . From whoſe black Rage we muſt immediately ºf , Expect to encounter all the pernicious Effects of Malice, back'd by Sceming Juſtice; Curſe on all Cowards ! better far be ſerv'd By Fools, and Knaves: they makéleſs dang'rous Faults. Die. Am I in fault, becauſe I'm not a Cat? How could I telli'th'dark whether that Raſcal Was a Knight Errant, or a Recreant Knight? I thought him one of us, and true to Love; Were it not for ſuch Accidents as theſe That mock Man's Fore-caſt, ſure the Deſtinies Hadner been plac'd amongſt the Deities. Oä. Peace,cowardly Slave; having thus plaid tle Rogue, Art
Page Scan 79

The Adventures of Five Hours. Art thou Sententious grown did I notRear . . . To Stain my Sword with ſuch Baſe Blood, I'd let Thy Soul out with it at a thouſand wounds, … . . . Die. VWhy then a thouſand Thanks to my Baſe Blood - For ſaving my Good Fleſh. . . . [Aſide. Oä. Pardon, my deareſt Miſtris, this Exceſs . . Of Paſſion in your preſence. . . . . . . Por. What ſhall we do Oğavio 2 we are loſt For ever ; if we ſhould ſtay here, my Brother Will be upon usinſtantly. Alas! . . - - * } My Own Life I value not Ottavio, . . . . . . . Where yours, my Better life, ſuch hazard runs; . . . But O my Honor O my Innocence - Expos'd to Scandal; there's my deepeſt Senſe. Oä. Though the Complexion of your Brother's Malice Reſemble Hell, it is not Black enough . . . . . . . . . . To caſta Stain upon your Virgin Whiteneſs. -- As Contraries compard ſet Öffeach other, . . . . . The Siſter's Brightneſs will expoſe the Brother. º - Por: O my oãavio ! he is ſtill my Brother; . . . . . But what do you reſolve to do 2. - . . . . . . Oğ. Imuſt reſolve and ſuddenly, but what Iſwear (know not, there have been ſuch Turns In my Misfortunes, they have made me giddy. - Por. You muſt determine, time waſtes Ośīavio. . . . . Oä. If I ſhould lead you through the Streets, and meet Th’inquiſitive juſtice, I daring not º Tavow myſelf upon the other ſcore. - You know of, you might that way be in danger; We muſt not venture’t ; * Run Raſcal, and fetch A Chair immediately. * To Diego. . . Due. A pretty Errand at this time oth night; Theſe Chair-men are exceedingly well natur'd , ~ # . Th’are \
Page Scan 80

- -, - --- The Adventures of Five Hours. Th’arc likely to obcy, a Servant's Orders . . . . . . . . After ten a clock: , ; , . . . . . . . . . [Exit Diego. Oğ. Ye Powers above, why doyelay ſo great A VVeight on Human Nature, and beſtow . . . . - | Such an unequal Force to bear Our Loads 2) After a long purſute through all thoſe Storms , , . . . Which Hell-bred Malice, or the Power of Fate . . . . . Could ever raiſe, t'oppoſe a Noble Love; , , To be at length poſſeſs'd of the Rich Mine, 2. - Where Nature ſeem'd to have lodg’d all her Treaſure; And in an inſtant have it raviſh'd from me, . . . . . . Is toorude a Trial for my tir’d Patience, - To ſuſtain; I cannot bear it. , , | - Por. My Senſe of this Misfortune Equals yours, a But yet I muſt conjure you to ſubmit º, - To Heavens Decrees; ſuch Reſignation , , , , . . . . . 'Tis poſſible, their Juſtice may induce The miſchief to divert, though ne’rſonear. Oğ. Ah Porcia to part with you! - Por. Looſe not your ſelf with me, though we are forc’d To Separate, yet we are not Divorc’d. . . . . . . . . . . nº Oä. Whilſt our Souls ačt by Organs of the Senſe; *Twixt Death and Parting there's no difference. - Por. Conſult your Reaſon, then you will comply; Making a Virtue of Neceſſity. º, Oä. Ahlovely Maid, 'twas not allow'd to jove . . . . t ºl -- * . . . . . -- * ~ To hold at once his Reaſon, and his Love. w * . . . . Enter Diego. . . . . . Die. The Chair is come, Sir, juſt as I expcétéd. . . . . Oći. Where is it - . Die. Even where it was; they arc deeply engag’d At New Cut, and will not leave their Game, - - * , They ~ - / -
Page Scan 81

The Adventures of Five Howry. They ſwear, for all the Dons in Sevil. Oä. Acurſe upon theſe Rºgues l’Imake 'em come, Or put ſome of 'em in a condition... . (; , . To be carrºd themſelves. - * * w - . . . . . . . [Oétavio runs out. Die. Madam, though I was never yet unkind - **- : *w---. - Tomy own pººr, I am ſo much troubled º, º 'º' At the Diſquiet my Miſtake has brought you; , , . . . . . That could I do it conveniently, ifaith, I could even cudgel my ſelf. * - * : : - . 1.- : - - - - - - - . . . Tor. Away Buffon, is this a time for fooling . . . . . . - - * ----- tº - - . . . x - - - - - - - - - - . . . . . . . . . . .'; º' -- * Enter Antonio and Sancho. . . . . Ant. Where is my noble Friend Ośavio 2 " . Die. Did you not meet him at the door, Sir . 44t. No. . . . . . . . . . . . . ." Die. He went out juſt as you canne in. . . . .” Ant. Madam, I might have gone to Bed, but not . . - ; Addreſſes himſelf to Porcia. To Reſt, without returning to enquire . . . . .º. º. º.º. Anew of Yours, and of my Friends Condition; tº And once more offer you my Service. . . . . . . ºccº, Por, I take the boldneſs in Qāavid's abſence º To return his with my moſt humble Thanks . . . . . For your late generous Aſſiſtance of us, nº lºº And for this nºw. Addition to our Debtº gº ºf , º, Ant. Madam, though I have not the Happineſs, , º, To be Known to you, yet my conſtant Friendſhip f : . ; * , ,- *: - With Oğavio is of an antient Date; , . . .'' And all Occaſions where I may expreſs . . . . The Fervour of it, are moſt welcome to me. . . . . . - I Enter
Page Scan 82

The Adventures of Five Hours. - . . . . . . . . . . ºf , º Enter Flora ingreat haſe, wº 1. .*.*} r" * - * -- . 1 , ----... -- . 1 ( : « Flo. O Madam----- I'm out of breath with running. Por. What Accident, Flora, brings you hither 2 . " Flo. Aſad one, Madam, and requiring haſte , , , , , To give you timely notice on't 3 Pongarloss... . . . . Aſſiſted by the light ºth Riſing Moon; ' ' ', " ": And by a Miſtake º ; : " . . . . . . . Has Trac'd you to this Ho - - Inform'd your Brother of the Place, and Manner . . . Of your Retreat, who is now coming hither ‘’’’ ‘’’ Accompani’d with the Corigidor , , , , a - Toſeize on whomſoeverſhall be found. . . . . . . . Within theſe Walls, upon pretence of Murder. . Por. O cruel Accident 11 º’’’ ‘’’’ ‘’’ º º k- Flo. Madam, make haſte, get . at the backdºor}. Or you will certainly beſthet witHall. " " ' "." * for. Howvika Čreature aminow become?” “º For thoughin my own Innocence ſecure ... . . . . . As to my ſelf, tºothers IſhāHap gar 1 (jj Nº. sº sº º º Some wicked Womad, that has föğher Honor. so º To purchaſe Infamy. ...” Yºº "ºº" Flo. They'linſtantly behere." ſi. . . o. 2.; 22. 1 º' Por. O that Oğavio ſhould juſt flow be abſefit tº But to expe&t till he return wºrtin digſs, º, ..., Ant. Y. have reaſon; Aſadām; and ifyou'dáté truſt" º Your Perſon totheºonduct of a Stranger, . . . . Upon my Honor, Lady, Il Secure ſoi, º' " Or Periſh in th’Attempt.” * : * > . . . . ºf to dº º º Por. Generous Sir, how ſhall âwrečićd Māū’,” Abandon'd by her Fate to the purſute " '''''''''' Of an Inhumane Brother, er be able -. Either to Merit, or Requite your Favours? Aut. Madam, and immy hearing . .”. uſe, and in my hea hg: ". . .
Page Scan 83

The Adventures of Five Hours. * \ 4nt. Madam, they're more than Paid in the Admiſſion, And your Acceprance of them will transfer ºn ºf The Obligation, making me the Debtor. ºf Por. To your Protećtion I reſign myſelf, . . . With equal Gratitude and Confidence. . . . . . Ant. Come Madam, there is notime to be loſt; , , , Diego, find out your Maſter preſently, ºr ºf . . . º. And tell him, that the Danger not allowing º' ' ' ' ' Qur Stay till his Return, I ſhall convey ºf . . " His Miſtrisſafely to a Nunnerie. . . . . . for and Flºtayyoubercrobringmeword, : , . " ‘. . . ) What he reſolves to d6 in this our deſpitate - Condition... . . . . .” - [Exit Diego. Flo. Madam, I ſhall, . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Amt. But ſtay; I ſwear I'd like to have committed . . . . A foul Miſtake ; the Monaſtery Gates tº ºr . . . . . . . Will not be open'd at this time of Night, f [Going out Without a firićt Inquiry into the Cauſe;" {º. - Beſides, ’tis poſſible, that once Lodgºd there, . . . . . She maybéðut of my Friends Power, or mine, Q Ever together thence if it be known... ºf 'i' o? Lady, I have thought better on't 3 tº ſhall . . . . º Condućt you to my Brother-in-law's houſe; : . . . . . . . . A Perſon of ſuch Quality, and Honor, . . . . . . . . As is fit to engage in your Protećtion; º º tº And theremy Wi may have the Happineſs . . . . . - Tº accompany you, and pay the Qffices . . . . . Due toygur Virtue, and digreſs'd Condition: And going to a Houſe º mine, Make account; Madam,’tis to your own Home. Sancho,ſtay you here to attend Oğavio, [Turning to Sancho. And guide him the next way to my Apartment; - Here is the Key; I ſhall have little uſeon't , , , , * - - I 2 - Having --- - -- `---— —

Page Scan 84

The Adventures of Five Hours. Having left Erneffo waiting for methcre. . . .: One word more, Sancho; let Offavio know . . . . 'Tis my advice that he come in a Chair; . He by that means may ſcape Examination, Should hc be met with. w Por. Flºra, I pray do you continue here, And if by any accident Očiatio . . . . . "Should hindred befrom coming after us . . . Obſerve his Motions, and where he Fixes; Then return home 5 and I ſhall find ſome way . . . . Of ſending to you to inform my ſelf. . . . . . . . . . ) º . . . . " - f : . . . . - 7 Flo. I ſhall not fail t'obſerve your Orders, Madam. * Ant. Madam, I’m ready to wait on you. - Por. Ah cruel Brother l ah my dear OHavio ! • O how perverſe, and rigorous is my Fate J. . Thus to torment me betwixt Love and Hatc.... . . . . . . . . . [Exeunt Antonio, Porcia. , Sam,' ſis no ſmall Compliment my Maſter, makes - Your Ladie, and her Gallant, at this time . . . . . . . . 9'th night to quit his Brother-in-laws, and kavej, So fair a B ideas Porcia allalone. . . . . . . a - ; : . . tº * * - - Flo. What? is his Miſtris's name Porcia too San. Yes; and if ſhe has but as fair a Hand-maid “. As yourſelf, I ſhall ſoon forget my Damſel j . In the Low-countries. . . . . . . . . . . . . Flo. If your Low-country Damſels reſemble us, You would not be put tot to forget firſt 3. . . . . . . But I believe that you are ſafe enough; I have not heard ſuch Praiſes of their Wit, But that wemay ſuppoſe they have good Memories. . . . . . - Enter Diego. Die. Is not my Maſter yet return'd? . . . . .” Flo, No. - Die. -
Page Scan 85

The Adventures of Five Hours. Die. Well; now have we an Honorable Cauſe Towcar the Bcadles Livery; faith, Flora , ; ; ; , , , , If your tender Sex had not tº privik'g'd : . . . . . From this harſh Diſcipline, how prettily Would the Beadles Crimſon Lace ſhow upon Thy white back. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Flo.’ſ won't doſo well as on a darker ground; . . 'Twill ſuit much better with your Tawney hide. Sam. I pray, Camerade, is it the Mode in Sevil To be Whip'd for Company?, , a. Die. Oh! a well-bred Soldier willne'r refuſe a Such a Civility to an old Friend; … . . . . . . . . . . . . This is a new way of being a Scoond, - Toſhew your Paſſive Courage. , > * san. We Soldiers do not uſe to ſhow our Baks. * * Die. Not to your Enemics; but, Sir, the Beadle Will prove your Fricnd, for your Blood being Heated With your long Journey, Breathing of a Vein Is very requiſite. . . , º, of - Sam. W. to Heaven that I were in the Camp again; There we are never ſtript till we are dead. º - Enter Oétavio, and the Chair-men appear at the door.- Oä. Be ſure you ſtir not thence till I *} To the Sirrha, where's Porcia tº . . . . . . . . . Chair-mem. Die. She's fled away i'th'dark, with a Young man Of your acquaintance. - - -- - Öğ, Raſcal, leave your fooling, - - Die. There's none i'th caſe, Sir, 'tis the wiſeſt thing She ever did, had ſhe ſtaid your return, She would have fall’n into thoſe very Clutches, In which you will immediately be grip'd, unleſs you make more haſte: Flora is come - - 3 - With
Page Scan 86

The Adventures of Five Hours. With allpoſſible ſpeed, to let you know: ; ; , .º Th'are coming with the juſtice to lay hold tº 58.2°º , Ofall within this Houſe; upon prºtérice%2% 1 ºn 1* Of a moſt horrid Murder; be quick, Sir ; º' : And ſave yourſelf. She's ſafe in a Nunnerie; 2 ſº Condućted thither by Antonto; ºf i ºriº ºf Where, poor Lady, ſhe's dropping for you nowl ' ' More Beads, perhaps, than Tears; , , tº Oä.PeaceScreetch-Qwl;Fire conſume that Tongue ofthine. What ſaiſt thou Villain? in a Nunnerieſ? : . . . . . . 9- Porcia in a Nuhfieries' O Heavens ! nothing ! ſo º But this was * to make me Deſperate; ºf What hope's there left ever together thence, a After ſuch Accidents as theſe made Publique? . . Ah Flora, is it true that my dear Porcia º . . . . . Is gone into a Monaſteryż, , , , ; ; ; º' . . . Flo. Once, Sir,’twas ſo reſolv’d, and Diego'ſent ºil Togiveyounotice on't: but afterwards "" " ' '. He being gone, they chang'd their Reſolutions: º, . . . . There's ºne can telīyou more------ºffilining#Sahiho. - - Sam. My Maſtef bad theſay tolét}jäkiibwº He has convey'd her to his own Apartment, , , In his Brother-in-laws Houſe, a perſon" Soeminent in Qūality, and Credit, tº Bººt º' That the ingaging him in her, and your 2". Hºw sºlº 2 - Protećtion, Sir, ſhay mºdiyºoth ;: º º - Beſides, ſhe'lhave thepleaſure there of being", º Very well treated by my Maſter's Bride. 2. *323i º There \el expectybii; Sir, and does #39;ſº * T .'s (A ** * Your coming in a CHāif,' to avoid Qºſţīondº o In caſe of any Encounter. . . . . . " " º 2 : ºr wº º Flo. And my walking by, Sir, as an Attendant, º, Will paſs you without ſcruple for a Lady; º' ' ' '." - - - - Oğ.I’ _--—--------------- ----
Page Scan 87

- The Adventures ofFive Hours - Oğ. I’l take his counſel, he's a generous Friend. " . Come Chair-mgn, away. *Pray, friend, do you guideus. - " - . . . . [* To Sancho. Die. up with your Burden Beaſts, and fall forth-with To your Half-Trot. - [Exeunt. . . . . . . SThe Chair is carri'd aver the Stage, * I vº. - - " - . . . . Diego, Sanchº, and Flora fºllow. tº [4 Noiſe within, Follow, follow, follow, ſ Enter Carlos, the Corigidor, and Šerkants, purſuing - Sancho, Flora, and Diego, ºr . . . . Die. This is one of Don rupid's pretty Jeaſis, ... . . . .", W’ are ſtruck upotra Shelf before we could, Put out to Sea. - - ‘. . . . . . . . . . ." . . . . . Flo. Oh, we are undone Diega: . . . . . - Car. You find, Sir; my Conjećtures notill grounded. . [To the Corrigidor. Cor. What are you, Sirrha . . . . . . . Die. A Living Creature, very like a Man, -, -, *, * Onely I want a Heart. … º. ** . . . . . . . . . . . . Cor.Y’are pleaſant; Sirspray Heaven your mirthcontinue. Who is that Woman with the Veil 2 . . . . . . . . . . Die. Lether anſwerfor her ſelf, ſh'has a Tongue, Set it but onceagoing, and ſhe'ſ tell All that ſhe knows, and more, º f : ), º wº Cor. Make her diſcover her face. . . ſo ºf - [One of the Serjeants goes to lift up her Weil. Car. Hold Friend; Cozin, if it ſhould be Porcia, 'Twere not fit to expoſe her here. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Cor.”Tis very wellconſider'd, go you to her, ſº …, , 'ſ Andſpeak to herin private. º' ſº "º . . . . [Carlos goes towards Flora. Flo. 'Tis I Sir , Flora, who being commanded B - - 3 * - y -
Page Scan 88

The Adventures of Five Hours. By my Lady--------- : . . . . . Carl, Speakſoftly prithec Flora, ’tis cnough; , , , , , I undcrſtand the reſt, and pitty her ; , ". * * Bid her fit ſtill i'th Chair, l'I do my b, ſtº To ſave her from the Fury of her Brother. * Flo. He thinks 'tis Portia thºre, a good Miſtake, 2 Aſ de It may ſecure Oñavio for the preſent ; a 4. From the hands of this rude Rabble; * Sit ſtill, - - * To Oétavio in the Chaire, They take you for my Miſtris Sir, I’lfollow The Chair, and have a watchful Eye on all. Occaſions, that may further your Eſcape. . . . . . . . … Car. We have found our wandring Nymph. . . Cor. Is it Porcia her ſelf? \ ſ ) . . . Car. No,'tis her Woman Flora following . . . . . The Chair, wherein they were conveyirg fºr . . . . . To ſome other place. - Cor. We arriv'd luckily, had we but ſtaid, ". . A moment longer, they had all becn fled. . . . . . Ser. Will you have us ſce, Sir, who's in the Chair ? Cor. Forbear Fellow! 4 Her own Folly' puniſhment Enough t'a Woman of her Quality, [* To Carlos, Without our adding that of Publique ſhame. . . . . . . . Carl.’ſ was luckily thoughton, when you oblig'd Don Henrique to expectus at your Houſe ; ; , . . . . . . For had he come, and found his Siſtcr thus, . . . . . *Thad not been poſſible to have reſtrain'd º * His Paſfion from ſome great Extravagance. *- ~ ; : Cor. I could not think it fit to let him come; , . . . . For one offuch a Spirit could ne'r brock . . . . . . The ſightof thoſe had done him theſe Affronts, Without invading thoſe ſtrićt Rules, which might Rendór his Life obnoxious to the Laws. " .
Page Scan 89

– - The Adventures of Five Hours. Tisbetter that a buſineſs of this nature, $. 'twixt Perſons of ſuch Quality) . . . . . hould rather be reduc’d by Mediation " ' " ..." (If it be poſſible) to ſome fair Agreement, Than to a publiqueTrial by the Law, - Or, which is worſe, ſome Barbarous Revenge. . Carl. This Fellow (if l am not much miſtaken) ls Donošavid's Man. . . . . [Looking upon Diego. Cor. Who ºrs too, Fričnd 2 Die. To nobody, Sir. . . . . . . . . . . Cor. Do not you ſerve 2 . . . . . . . . . . Die: Yes Sir, but my Maſter is not himſelf. . . . . - Cor. Take his Swordfrom him Serjeant. §:# - Die. Diego diſarm'd by any other and $... " Than by his own know Friend, it is a Weapon . . . . Of ſuch dire Execution, that Idare not ". . . . . Deliver it, but tothe hands of Juſtice. . . . . .” y The Corrigdor receives the Sword, and 3::::::::::::::: * * Signior, pray call for it, when you come home, a And hang't up in your Hall, then under-write, " . This isbold Diego's Sword; Q may it be . . . . . . . Ever from Ruſt, as 'tis from Slaughter free. . . . . . . . . . Cor. Thou art a Fellow of a pleaſant humour. . . . Die. Signior, I never pain myſelf for Love, ... Or Fame, or Riches, not do i pretend. . . . . . . To that greatſubtilty ºf Senſe to Eccl.", . . . . . . Before I am Hurt, and for the moſt part I keep my ſelf out of Harms way. . . . . . . . . . Carl. The Definition of a Philoſo her. . . . . . . . Cor.Come, cave your fooling. #ºr, yourMaſter? Die. I am afraid we are not to be parted. ". . . . Cor. Whom do you * *Die.
Page Scan 90

The Adventures of Five Hours. Die. My Maſer, myself, and befººl your Worſhip Mentions, for ſure Öſe that had any Wit; Would never ſerve a Lover Militant ; He had better wait upon a Mountcbank, And be run through the Body twice a week . . To recommend his Balſom. . . ." . -- Cor. This Féllow's an Original.' ' ' ... '" Die. But of ſo ill a hand, I am not worth . . . ." The hanging up, Sir, in my Maſters room, , Amongſt the worſt of your Collection. * > . Enter Serjeants with two Foot-men, and two Maid-ſervants. Serj.An't pleaſe your Worſhip,we have ſearch'd the Houſe, . From th’Cellars to the Garrits, and theſe are all. . . . . *. 2 ... " The living Cattel we can find." cor. Friends take a ſpecial care ofthat ſame Varlet, And the Waiting-woman; we'l find a way” tº To make them tell the Truth, I warrant you. - Flo. O Diego! muſt we be Priſoners together? Flora. -- - - - tº rºº cor.Come, let's away; but whither to convey her------ To her own Houſe certainly were not fit, ''''' - Becauſe of her incenſed Brother. ". . . . . . Car. If you approve it, Cozin, I' carry her ºf . . . To mine; for ſince wefeek (if poſſible). "... * * * * The buſineſs to compoſe, ſhe will be there * * * * * With much more Decency, and Satisfačtion, ſº ***: # , ºt Being in a Kinſmans Houſe, and having there tº My Siſter to accompany her. . . . . . . . . . . . Cor. This buſineſs cannot be in better hands, Than yours; and there I'l leave it, and bid you '''' º ". Good- powly, that forſobadastleBanjºof widº, And leſs expos'd to Cenſureofthe world, *: ºn tº
Page Scan 91

The Adventures of Five Hours. Good-night. Gºrkyout Šervant Cozin, I wiſh}: home. . . - º, iſ . . . . [4; the Corrigidorgoes out. çozin,you may be pleaſedto takeyour Serjeants Along with you; there are without two Servants Belonging to Don Henrique, they'lſuffice º To guard our Priſoners, and with far leſs notice. … Cor. Come Serjeants, follow me. . . . . . . . . . . Carl. Well, you may go about your buſineſs, Friends, , gº, c. ºf . [To the Foºt-men and Maids. I'l not be troubled with ye; I am glad ' . . . . . . . We did notfind Qāavio here; though I . . . . . . . Might unaffetted Ignorance pretend, , , . . . . . . I would not bring him (thoughby chance) this End. 12, ſº . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . [Extant Servants. Sam. Well, inwasimº ſ: i:. . . . . .” - And ſincethere is no notice taken of me, to . . . . TI fairly ſteal away, and give my Maſter . . . . . . Account of this Misfortune... . . . . [Exit Sancho, Carl. Take up the Chair, and follow me... º. º. º. . . - . . . . . . . . . . [They take u the Chair.’ Die. A Lovely Dame they bear, 'tis true,ſhe's ſomething Hairie, but that's a ſign of Strength. . . . Carl. Make haſte, I long to let Don Henrique know, That his loſt Siſterisby my dexterity . . . . . : Recovered, and hope to findſome means. . . . . . To calm his Furie, and to repoſſeſs - My Cozin Porcia, and (if't be poſſible) ; Oğavio of his good Graces. Come away.... . . - - [The Chair is carri'd off. … Die. How like an Aſshe'ſ look, whenop'ning the Shell, His Worſhip finds within ſorough a Kernel; . . . - - [Exeunt omnes. ::1 K 2 The ---
Page Scan 92

The Adventures ofFive Hours. N The Scene Changes to Don Antonio's Apart - ment in Don Henrique's Houſe, Enter Antonio and Porcia. . Ant. Madam, baniſh all your Fears, you are nowº, Safe in this Houſe; be pleas'd to remain here, Jºe Till I ſhall bring ſome Lights, and acquaint-Porcia . . With th' Honor ſhe receives in entertaining . So fair a Gueſt. ." § tº 2 ºzº.º.º. 9 i. Por. Who is't you ſay you will advertiſe Sir Fºr tº: Ant. My Wife Porcia; have but a little patience ; , , And ſhe ſhall wait upon you. . . . . [Exit Antonio. Por. Is her name Porciº too I pray Heaven ſend her A better Fate than her diſtreſled Names-ſake... : W.W.s..?. O Oğavio ! O Love! how deat do you; ºf tº Coſt me ! where am I brought what Houſe is this? ºf What withiny Fears, and farineſ, , I have loſt 1: ...* All my meaſures; I can't ſo much as gueſs ºk, ... What Quarter of the Town it is waré in, - For to avoid th’Encounter of my Brother, º f * ~ * And his Revengeful Train, we have been forc'd : \sº To make ſo many Turnings, I am Giddy. . . . . . . . But thanks to Providence I have this comfort, That I am in a place out of his reach. * . . . Enter Antonio with two Lights, and ſets them on the Table. Amt. Madam, my Wife will preſently attend you, Pardon I pray my abſence for a moment. . . . . . . - [Exit Antonio, Por. Now I begin to hope my Sighes, and Tears, Have in ſome ſort with the juſt Heavens prevail'd, z At
Page Scan 93

The Adventures of Five Hours. At length to free me-------- *But what do I ſee : - * ... . . . . . . [* Looking about her. Am I awake, or is it an Illuſion?", tº j, Is not this my Brother's Houſe? Is not this ºne . . . The Quarter joining to my own Apartment? . . . . Thcre is no room for Doubt, and my Misfortunes . . . . Arealways Certain; Miſerable Créature, ſº That I ſhould betlius Bandi'dupand downs...} : . . . . From one Hazardt another, greater ſtill..., tº o Ah cruel Heavens! what have lever done - To deſerve this laſting Perfecution? . . But how came I here? brought by oãavio's friend, - Upon whoſe Virtue 1 did ſorelie º 'º, º sº I - That I my Brothers Malice durſt defie. * * Canhe betray me? ſure I am in a Dream, ºg º But if oğavio--------- O vile Suſpition! .o. º. . OHavio falſe 2:rio, Truth and He are pne. Hó. 'Tis poſſible his Friend may guilty be sº a rººf, ºn tº , , But to what end ſo baſe a Treacherie : . . . . . And if Perfidious, how could he be his Friend. . . . . I am confounded with the various forms,º . . . . A Of my Misfortunes, Heightned ſtill the more, ºr ºr ºn The leſs I can their Hidden Cauſe explore, ºz. ..., Thisonely's evident, that I muſt flie º ºſ cº, ºr Immediately this fatal place; But why: y : " . . . . . Struggle 1 thus with Fate? ſince Go, or Stay", iſ . . . . Deathſeems alike to wait meeveryway. . . [She weeps. *. . . . . . . . . . ; ": – ' '...' ...º. º. º. " . Enter Antonio and Camilla... . . . . . Cam, I wonder much what Lady this can be rºſ., . Antonio mentions. * * * * * . . . . . . [Aſide. Aut. Pardon, my deardſt Miſtris, the Liberty Which Iſo carly take; but I preſume º - - - - - - * * Such
Page Scan 94

The Adventures of Five Hours, such is yout Generous Tenderneſs to thoſes. . . . . Whoſe ſad Misfortunes, not their Fault, have driven Into Diſtreſs, that you will think yourſelf. . . . . . . . . Oblig'd to him, who gives youthéoccaſion, a . . To exerciſe thoſe Virtues which do Viſit. . . . . . . others, but Reſide with you : This fair Lady------ - * - - - - But ſhe will beſt relaxchcrown ſad Story; , . . . . . . . Whilſt Iſeek out Dan Henrique, and engage himſ; , E., Both to Protećt and Serve her with his Credit. . . . . . . . …! 3. i-º, . . . . . . ...[Exit Antonio, « » the Handkerchiffrom her Eyes. ... I Cam. Ha! what's that I ſee? ſtay, ſtay Antonia.v. ºf w ;ºfiº j, q, ...[She runs after 4ntonio. It is not fit Don Henrique,”---- but he's gone, . . . .2 And we are loſt for ever. 2', () --------... . . . iii.33. Porc. O Heavens! isthis Antonio, the ſame Manºo To whom I am Betroth'd; themmy Deſtruction ſº, º Is inevitable. . . . . . . . . . . . . ºf tº jºi:18 Cam. Are you äh Apparition ? or are you...] . . . . . 1 may not yet believe you. ... ſº " . . . . . to , ºn 3 Por. You well may Doubt even what you See Camilla; Since my Diſaſters are ſomew, and ſtrange, . . . . . They ſever Truth from Credibility. …, , , , , - Cam. Howisit poſſible you ſhould be here?: ºº: º * Pºr. I know not how, onely of this 'mſure , . I have not long tº xpečt the diſmal end r Of my ſad Tragedy; ſince’tis evident The Perſon that hath led me to this Place, tºº, . . . . This fatal Place, is the abus’d Antonio; . . . . . . . . Who with my Cruel Brother has conſpir’d To take away my wretched life, and choſe Porcia her ſelf? ſpeak, that wheny have ſaid it thrice ºf This º: Camilla's approach Porcia takes . . . . . . . Nº
Page Scan 95

The Adventures of Five Hoºrs. This Scene as fitteſt for their Cruelty,” º' ºf : " :" And thus, ſtränge Fate!! (through ignorance betraid) I have Protećtion ſought from the ſame Partie, º, . Whom I have injur'd, and have made my Husband Th’onely Confident of his own Affront; e : º, . . . . Who tô accompliſh his too juſt Revenge, "4: . - As well upon my Family, as Perſon; : " . . . - Gives me up to be Murder'd by my Brother. So whilſt I'm branded as a Faithléſ, Bride, ſº º He’l be deteſted as a Particide... . . . . . . ºf . , Cam. Prodigious Accident; but wert thou blind Not to know thiné own Houſe unhappy Porcia 2 Por, Alas, how could I in ſo darka Night; . In ſuch Confuſion, and ſo full of Fear? Tº "... Beſides, he brought me in by the Backway, 7 º' Through his own Quarter, where was neither Light, " Nor any Greature of the Family. . . . ." . . . . . . Çam. Although I cannot comprehend the ſteps ' ' ' ... Of this your ſtrange Adventure,2. Cozin, Your caſe (as I conceive) is not ſo deſperate. Por. “We eaſilyperſwadeourſelves to hope - “The things we wiſh ; but Cozin, my condition Will not : Sºfiarº #: ‘. . . . º 1: . Canyou propoſe to tempermy. Deſpair 3 º' . . . . º: $...y Evening Antonio's Man finding meih your Quarter" . . . .” Without a Well (you havingput on mine). . . . . . That he appli’d himſelf to me; and Hºº'." Byyoi command, ºur perſon did affème; ºf sº ‘Por. Yes very well. ºr " 'º', Cam. The Maſter ſince has by the Man's Miſtake Been happily led into the ſame Error 3'2" dº. . . . . And Inordiſabus’d him yet, in hopes º' I * jº ºr t
Page Scan 96

The Adventures of Five Hours. Reverſeth orderoffic wholečreation, , , , It might produce Advantage to us both. . . . Por. On! he has ſpoken with my Brother ſince, Who ſure has undeceiv'd him long cre this. . . No, without doubt they having found themſelves Affronted both, have both conſpir'd my death. . Cam. How Cozin, can that be * if Don Antonio In your Protećtion has engagd himſelf, . . . . . . . And is OHavio's Fricnd. - Por. Cozin, if you impartially refle&t - On the Affront which I have done, Antonio, , , ; ; You will not wonder much if he recede . From the ſcarce-troden Path of rigid Honor . . . To meet with his Revenge; and to that end Proceeds thus cautelouſly, and does feign . . . Not to know me, thathémay diſavow Both to Ottavio, and to all the world; , , . . . . . Th’Infamy of Betraying a poor Maid, nº, , , . . . . Toloſs of Life and Honor.….. *... . . . . . . . . Cam. Misfortungs make you rave; this vile Suſpiriono, Is inconſiſtent with Antoño's Fame : ; , , , ; tº is ºf - - ... ºt - - You may as well believe that Nature will . . . . . . As that Antonio, a Man, whoſe Soul: , , , , , , Is of ſo ſtrong, and perfºëta Complexion, toº ºf C Should gre deſcend to ſuch a ſlaviſh Sin, , , . . . . . . . And if we had the leiſure, I couldgive you . . . Such reaſons to convince you of your Error , , . Thatyou wouldeaſily acknowledge it. . . . . Por. I had forgother near Concernments for [Aſide. 4ntonio. Pardon and Pitty me Camilla; . . . . My mind is by Afflićtions made ſo Weak, . . . . I'm ready to believe Impoſſibilities. Can. I Pitty thee with all my heart; but Cozin, . f - - - - I e--- -
Page Scan 97

The Adventures of Five Hours, If Antonio not knowing you, nor your .… Relations, ſhould chance to find yout Brother, ſº Life z And him inform of what has paſs'd, and that - He has convey'd the diſtreſſ'd Partie hither, . . He preſently imagine it is you; i, º, . . . . . . . . And then (I fear)'twillbeimpoſſible. , , , , , º, ..., (Though he ſhould interpoſe with all his power) º gº To ſtop the Torrént; or divert his Rage. ºt. 10, iſºs i From breaking in, and executing on us of ſº That horrid Particide, which (though too latc.) tº , , , It maybe he himſelf wºuld exºratºjoti ºgºn, i. Por. There's rºomuchground for what you fear Gamila: But if we ould ſégure our ſelves this night,’ wºr: º, ſº There were ſome hopes that we to morrow may ºf Engage both Don Antonio, and your Brother ºf . . . To find out ſome Expsdient to fedeeminac ºr ºrj E. . From this deplorable gºndition.jd ºilº tºo jºi..', Cam. Were you onely in pain for your Security: , ºo, This night, I know an eaſie:Remedy ºf , , º, . For that. …,]ºjo ovº 3 ºr sº gº cool iv. H. J.H. Tor. Which way my Dcareſ}}|... I a... iſ #if: citik) Cam. Why what does hinder us from making uſe s (On this occaſion) of the ſecret Door, By which (you know) yon have ſo often paſt ºr Into our Piouſe #. ingrepkaſing Etrands?) iſ , , , , By this we ſhalſ theſe Bºxfits obtain; , , , , , , , , , Øf Safety from your Brothers preſent Fury," " ' ". And time to try ifdarlos, and Antonio 2 gº Maybe ingag’d tomediate in this Buſineſs, a ... . And I have cauſe rºſhink you will not find. : ſº...! I r - - ~ !-- 2. Antagioſo implacable, as you - Imagine. ". . . . . . . . . . . . . . ºr ºlº. --!º 2. Por. I conceive you Cozin 3 Fool that I was, " . T .* - L. -- 9 ~ *
Page Scan 98

The Mdventurer of Five Hoºs, To thinka Heart once Conquer’d by your Eyes. . . . . . Shoulder become 4hotherºVirgin's Prizelºſt ºi::::/ſ ºf bºt Jºd iſ ſº, o intoni inid Lºſ, - tº Enter. Antonio, .5 bºowººd. Ant, Solate; a Gueſtin's Houſe; that's coine ſofary; On ſuch a Buſineſs; and not yet come hôtieri º ºſ-Aflac, . There's ſońetliſt gºin't I camoºqomprehend. 2d ſºo’ſ I cannot, Madam, yſt find but your bruthtº), 2d, oil of But ſure’twill not be longere he return.ſi: gºi; ºt Then I’lācquaint him with the Accidentºr.' … º. Has made his Houſe this ladie's Sauðtiaty, 24.3% ºf *Por. Here is a glympfebfcºmfort; for Íſee 19’ſ.’" He takes my Cozi for Dan Henrique's Siſter# 9 aftº O bleſs'd Miſtakeſo luckily continu'd ºf yº’ ºf Cam. I am by his permiſſion Miſtris here, if ºn And ſince that iam pleas'd Sirjºtiseñough;) ſº ...ii ". Without our troubling him with the Account iſ ºf Of her ſad Story. 1497 tº fººd tº ºp”.g., Ant. Yes, Madam, as toth'Excuſe, but twºrefit fºr He kncw it too, that we might ſerve our ſelves ºf Of his Credit in this j flyiſ,” sº ºff ºf ſix; 2. 1 bili, do ºdw Y | "...wi, --- , , Enter. Henrique. (moſº ºf , Henr.Though'ſ did promiſe the Corrigiãº dº Not to ſtir from his Houſe, till His ºuri; lºv. Toojiſ Yet I could not obtáñírefrºy ſelf. Jºigtſkº iſ: w8. I'm ſo impatient to tºo dthºriči, Tº ºf ºftdeº) Of Don Antonio's ſeeing of mySiſter, a liº W ºn tº And entertaining her inherówn Lodgings; ºi º ºſ. I ſhall not nowbeldagi'th daikºłęgierºgi bn A - . . . Hoºg.ºldſ, 2. qfix *Re; her Tis ſhe herſelf, and Camilla with her: . -º- Wercall my Servants mad, or all agreed . . . . ." - - , - . . . Tabuſe



End of Section 20. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 21
Page Scan 99

Certainly I, or thcy. "- - w: : *-* * - -. • * - --~ : The Adventures of Five Hours. . T'abuſe me , in affirming ſhe was fled #9". o: º alº . - But Don'tarlºs, was he mad too; t ſwear” fli sº t- That he had trac'd her to an other Öufe " ' º ºſº - muſt be Poſſeſs'd; }} º ‘. . ." º º o Or ſome §. - sº \ , , º, 4mt recomes Dºhehrigue; Piñówácāuainthifit With º: iº *} ..[I]}ſi Oj ſić unit int - - * . . . t - cam. I fear wearé undone. º” ºil º!' - \ ºt, Doh Henrique-------" 12, , º, . . . ºvº. A vſ. . ºv • Por: I’m dead the proceed, but how to hinder him------ Ant. Here's a Lady º § * - Henr. Yes, Sir, I ſee who’tis.’ ‘’’.” º º ºdo'ſ *Sinºyºnowher Sir, you willflecasſier º Excuſe my boldneſs. . º : ; , , º º º º ... ſº a º _ &T Hemr. Boldneſs, in what Sir?” ºf 15:11:15.19. ſº } :II'ſ - "...ºn #. * !-- . Here, with your Siſter, arthis i. º º Henr, Lord'Sir, what doydu meaſ: "..." yº. ºrruytherºwāsāºščičiūtying, ſºlº tº $º Which will, I hope ºiſºmyitº" lººp ſº - Withyou in her behalf. : ""º" tº : .I.A." Por. Now all comes out.” . . ." . . . . ." Henr. I underlandyou Sir, ſhe dºes deſire. º Topaſs this night with Porã, tºaſt her oºl, (, In ordering her Nuptial Ceremonies: º **** wº r Lether ſtay here a God's name. ". . - - ~ * * * * * - f, * - º " . . . . . . . . Por. If Hedoes not diſtmblémy Condition . . . . Is not ſodºſperate as I imagin'd, / L. . . . gº - Amt. ſºaretº, º º 4. So early a Confidence will need it, Sir, ; ; " " " Hºnºrismore than enoughsii, that you'deſireit, . Th’Occaſion too does juſtifieher ſtay. ºf ", , , , . . . . . . . . º Amt.” Fis moſt true Sir, the Occaſion did inforce me - - L 2 - Thus ------------ i."º ºº tº

End of Section 21. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 22
Page Scan 100

The Adventures of Five Hours, Thus boldly to preſume upon your Fricudſhip..... ºf Henr. Ha' dong for Havensſake, is it a Novelty tº Think you for Porcia, and hor Cozin-Germin To paſsa Night together?... . . . . . . . . . Ant. Is the ſongara Kinſwomanºflis : . ) Strange ſilver;ºnteinher not to tºllme, , , Q, .. }. relation to him, whom I nam'd him firſt.’, aid. I'd made fine workon't had ſtold himall. . . ) . Hear. She knows I owe her many a Good-turnº. i- ------tº #. o, º, .394, (Loºking on the fadeſ, I'm confident he counterfeits this Calm. , tº \ * ~ * -> - - upon offaii's cgie, and hopegie long. . . . . . . ſº plainer terms; , , cam. ſcannottelſ which of us two he means? But I begin to fear that he kgQwsall. . . . ..ſºſ., . . . . . . * - Henr. Since tisſolate, pray give th; Ladies kave, ‘r, Pinçº & iº. **** To retire to their Cha 9 in Siſter. . . . . Ant. My Brothers Words, and his Behaviour, & * . ºf 2 × . t - . Imply ſome Myſtery; I muſt be filent, º&Aid. Till I diſcover more...... zºlnºk 42 & 3" I. J. : ... yſ Por. Let us begone, ware ſoft if we ſtay! - vg ſtay licré; To diſguiſe his Revenge, until Antonio, . . Andºreñoffic #. gone to Bed. º Çam.But we ſhall ner be able to get out . . . Whilſt they continue in the outward Rooms. - " " . . Por. Yes, by the Garden-dore, but I'm afraid - 'Tis ſhut. . . . * ,-- ºf º º º º ! Jº — Cam. No; now I thinkon't, Flora went that way, And left it open. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Por. Come, lett'sbe gone; I hope Heavendocs ordain Eaſe by that Door which firſt let in my Pain. . . . - - [Exeunt Porcia and Camilla. Amt. - * * . . . •- '-. is ". -, *, *. To be able to repay her to the fillſ. . . . . . . . . . … " I - - - - 3: . . ; (, ) . ſ - .

Page Scan 101

The Adventures of Five Hours. Ant. I'ſ onely make a ſtep Sir, to my Lodging, And then return to you immediately. f :-- Hemr Pray give me leave to wait on you.' . . . Ant. I humbly thank you Sir, I know the way, And ſhall not ſtay above a Moment from you. - Henr. Y'are Maſter here, Sir. . . . . . – ...Ant. I’Indw go ſee whether my Servant Sancho C, sº . Has brought Oğavio to my Apartment, " - - As I direéted him. . . - [ Exit Antonio. “Henr. Heavens ! was there ever ſo ſtrange a Myſtery : Don Carlos he affirm'd that thoſe we fought with Had convey'd Porcia away, and when I come * * To ſeek her in the Houſe I find her miſſing, …" Toſecond this, her Waiting woman Flora . . . Tells mé that ſhe went down, about that time, ſº ºf ſix, ſº ~ Into th’ Garden; Antonio, not long after; ' ' ". "... Aſhrms that he both ſaw, and entertain’d her In her own Apartment, where I now find her, And Camilla with hºr : What can this be?, Theſe ſure are Riddles to poſe an Oedipus; , But if by my own Senſe I am aſſur’d My Honor's ſafe, which was ſo muchin doubt, What matter is it how 'tis brought about, º, ; , , , º, - - * . . . . . . . . c - _º -i " - * }, ſ > * * * * * * * . ~ ii'i º 'º º,' ' ' ', 1 - . . . . .'; " Q { w : …, -i- tº ºr - 2 - 1 - - º - - - - ... ºil.ji o 'º' vº. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
Page Scan 102

The Adventures of Five Hours. . . . . . . .'; ºr gº. 3 a tº ſº THE FIFTH ACT. " . . . - - - ' ' … º. º. 1 . . ." . . . . . ; ; // ; ; ; . . . . . . . . . ſ º . . The SC E N E is , : º lºſs ºf - - . ~ - - • 21 - “º T o WCCA R Lo S's Houſe. - , -, -, *, * . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - , - - ** - - -- . . . . . . . . . Enter Diego, Flora, and Geralºg cºmpanying the chair, , , , greaping 45% thedark. º fit of ºx.” A - …” }ſſ. . . . " . . . . . . . . . ºriº ºf '' Ger. Dº Flora, and Signior Diego, goin there. I MAnd you myFriends,ſet down the Chair i'th door; And when the Party's enterd, pullit to ; , . . . . . . . . 'Twill lock of 't #. done, you may be gone; º' There's Mony for you; I'lgofercha Candle. . . . . bºrº (Diego,and Florage in, and the Chairéeing. )ſet, in the door , Oötavio goes aut into the room, the Chair-men clap to the door, “and go away. . . . . . Enter Oétavio, Diego, Flora, at another door. Oä. What I put in all alone here i'the dark: {; as And the door ſhut upon me! Diego, Flora. i' th' dark. Die. Here am I Sir, and Flora too, unleſs . . . My Senſe offeeling fails me. Oğ. I can't conjećture where we are ; I durſt not. So much as peep out of the Chair, ſince Flora Gave me the warning ; but where e'r I am, 'Tisbetter far than in the Serjeants hands. - Flo. Though now i'th' dark, know well where we are: I have too often walk'd the Streets, Oğavio, f * , - From 2–’= * : * ~ - - -

End of Section 22. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 23
Page Scan 103

The A&#entures of Five Hour.” From your Houſe hither, upon Cupid, Errants, ". . . . Not to know the back door of Carlos's, L ..., ºrf: itſ & Apartment; 'tis there I am ſurew' arqºlow.d.; ſº , O3. Curſe on thee, Flºra!, had'ſt thou loſłthy wits to Not to let me know it ſooner! think'ſt thou … . . . . . . . I ſhould have tamcly ſuffer'd them to bring me, J. L., a Like a poor Bird ſhutinia Cage, t'a place. Hºo iſ ºf Where I muſt look for nothing but Deſtruction. Inº, . Pie. A Gypſie told me by my Palm long ſince, ) is A ſour-fac’d Damſel ſhould be my deſtrućtion. - Flo. Suſpend a while your Apprehenſions, Sir ; You may eſcape before the G º cº e iT The door was wont to open on this ſide ; If not, I have another way in ſtore." Yºº A ºil i. º. 1 ºf O&avidges to the dºor. OH. Flora, Iſcannot makerhebock gaback ºf I \,\! - fºr C E i. ºf Striving to ºpen the dºor, - #: on the otherfide, and coming i in with a Candle; meets with Oétavio, and starting back and fumbling, lets the Candle - fall, then running out again locksfaſt the door. Die. Naythei; iſaith, ware faſt; iheard him give The Key a double Turn. “ ºf 2 ... ." º, º sº." º iſ, ºf ºil Jſ Diego takes #p the Candle. • ere's a fair Trial for your Maiden breaths... . . . ; sº ora blow't in again, let's owe your Mouth º ºſobºr, Wore Light, than yet your Eyes could crimpart. … 3 Flo. Light's caſt away on ſuchán Owl as you; ºr 7: ..., But yet T1 trie. "I lo ºil ºf Lººp'd tº , 4. } 2, ºrii di ji ºf Flora blows the Candleim. . . * Die. Thanks, gehtle Flora, toyour Virgin Puff; gº ºgg 'Tis a Strong breath that can o're-come a Snuff... [Aſide. But I had rather’t had becn let alone: . . . . . . . → *
Page Scan 104

The Adventures of Five Hours. If I muſt needs be ſlain, unleſs it were . . . . . Behind my back, l'd have it i'the dark ; ; ; ; ; ; For I hate to be kill'd in my own preſence. . . . . . . . . . . oà. What muſt wedo Fiord? all my hope's in you. . . Flo. There is yet room for Hope; there's a Back-ſtairs ºf . Beyond that inner Chamber, that goes down . . . . .0, Into the Garden, if thq door boopen, iſ . . . . . . ; As certainly it is, the way is eaſie. ... . . o ſº ſº Oä. Come, let's loſe no time; prethcc guide us Flora. º, ". . . . . . . . . . . . . . [Exeumſ. - . . . º.º.º.º. º.o.º. 2 ºf tº de A* The Scene changes to Dan Henrique's Houſe.” . . . . . . c. 1: Tº ºv: Toº. 9 - Enter Don Henrique. ºf ºrd I ºr iſ º Henr. As well pleas'd as I am, to find my Honor - Leſs Deſperatºthan Ithdught, I cannotrºſt gº.º.o TiH I havedrawn from Porcia a Confeſſion Of the whole Truth, before ſhe goes to bed; She's in her Chamber now; unleſs by new : Enchantments carrica thence. . . . . tº § .*.*.*.*.*.****'. . . . ºvy swº sº, Vº -- x - As he is going towards, Porcia's Chamber sº º -- Emier Carlos inhasſe. . . . . . Carl. I can't imagine what ſhould make Don Henrique Quit the Corrigidors till wercturn'd : ºº il it ºn 3 º : Jº. D. J. One of his Scrvants tells the he's come home. 'vo sº O here he is ; now ſhall I raiſe a ſtorm . . - Aſide. Which (if we do not take a ſpecial care) . . . . Will ſcarceb'allaid without a ſhowr of Blood; , ; ; , , § Yet I muſt venture’t, ſince it ſo imports Our Friendſhip, and the Honor of our Houſe.º. º. Happineſs is a ſtranger to Mankind;... . . . . . . . . . . . And like to a Forc'd Motion, it is ever … . . . . . . . – - - - Strongeſt
Page Scan 105

The Adventures of Five Hours. Strongeſt at the beginning, then Languiſhing . . . With time, grows weary of our company; . . . . But tº Misſºufiº; Weſ&ſubjá are,' ...º.º iſ That like to Natſial motion they prove iſlº ºil º More Vigorous in their Progreſs. " " "º tº Hºvhat meansthis Philoſophical Preamble . . . . . . . . . º - J - ºn 3 Carl. You'1know too ſoon I fear. - - fºllºa º . . From all m'Triquiétudes, that for the future . ." § I dare defie the Malice of my Stars º' " " º To cauſe a new . tº . . . . . . Carl. Cozin, I'm ſo ſurpriz'd with this great change, Thatmy Confuſion does ſuppreſs my Joy; . . . . But ſincey’are ſo much Maſter of your Paſſions, I'l ſparemy Ethicks, and proceed to give you In ſhort the Narrative of our ſucceſs; The Corrigidor (as we did expcćt 'º - 9 Forward to ſerve you in th’Affair'ſ mention'd) ; *. Was pleas'd to go along with me in perſon, º With a ſtrong Bandof Serjeants, to the place, Where I attended by your Servants led him : Cozin,’twas there; it wounds my heart to ſpeak it; And I conjure you ſummon all your Patience : 'Twas there I found--------- Henr. Whom Cozin did you find 2 for ſince I’m ſure . You found not Porcia there ; my Concernments Inyour Diſcoveries are very unlikely To diſcompoſe me. . . - - Carl. I would to Heaven we had not found her there. Henr. What's that you ſay, Cozin, my Siſter there! . Carl. Yes Sir, your Siſter. - Henr. My Siſter that's good iſfaith; ha, ha, ha. Carl. Why do you laugh? is the Diſhonor of M s_ Your & >

End of Section 23. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 24
Page Scan 106

~rºw ºn ºf . As ºr r- ºr rr º'- The Adventures of Fiveſ Hours. - 1: . . . . . . . . . … ." . . . . . -----, Your Family become à Laughing Mattér This is a worſe Extrémé º º tºothº. º º Henr. How can º u; Laug § § Dréath;" Awake for Heavens ſake; jºi yb * Sciſes ; : . . Porcia there ſaid you?... . . . . ". . . . . Carl. Yes Sir, forcii Iſay ; your Siſter Pirèia; ... " 1 : 1 - º żºłº" Pººf ºi, ) And which is mºre, 'twäsingiātī; ºuſe. \\C. .º.º. Henr., Why ſuréyarénºiſſariº, Cozi." Carl. As ſure as you're i. fºr there." º tº Henr. Then you tranſport me, Sir, beyond all patience : Why Cozin, if ſh;has ºffiliation. w - António ſeen, and entertain'd. ićr here,'" . " ' ". . Accompani’dby Camilia; if even now " iicſ them there within; Ist poſſible ". . . . . º You ſhould have found her in Qāavio's Houſe? . . To be here, and there too, at the ſame time, None ſure but famus with his déuble face . . . . Caner unfold this Myſtery. ... " " ' . . . . . ºf Carl. Sir, let me adviſe you; Abuſe not your ſelf: Itell you poſitively I found her there: . . . . . . . And by theſame Token, her Waiting-woman Flora was there attending her. * . Henr. Flora ! dcar Cozin, do not ſtill perſiſt Thus to affirm impoſſibilitics. - 1. Carl. Sure you are making ſome Experiment upon my Temper, and would fainprovoke "#" My Patience to ſome ſuch high Diſorder," That I ſhould ne'r hereafter have the face When you are in your Fits to play the Stoick. Henr. Cozin, I ſwear toyou upon my Honor, 'Tis not above a quarter of an hour, . . . . . . " Since I did ſpeak with Porcia, and your Siſter In that very Apartment, and am now Returning
Page Scan 107

The adventures of Five Hours, Returningtothºmin my Siſter's Chamber.jº.: ſº ºf - car.And Sir, I ſweargoyouſupon my Honor, sº - 'Tis notabove a quarterofan hour, ſº iſ . . . . since Ileft Porcia carried in a Chair From Don oãavio's Houſe, yourman Geraldo, Condućting the Chair-mentomine, and follow'd , , By flora, whilſt I came tº findygºoutº in Tº acquaint you, Sir, with this unpleaſing newssº º But fit for jº. be . . . . . . . Henr. This Queſtion, Gozin, may be ſoon deci d. Pray come along;her Chambº, . off. ..., * } Carl. And my Houſe is but the next door, let's in. º Henr. You'l Quickly find your Error, car.And you’l asſoon be undeceiv'd; but ſtay, Here comes your Servant, whom Ileft to Guard her; ) Heinſtantly convinceyóuof the Truth. - - . . * * * * - Enter Geraldo. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Ger. O Sir! . . . . . . Henr. What brings you hither Geraldo 3 - Ger. o Sir, I bring you ſuch rare news; your Enemy, Your Enemy OHavio-------- I’m out of breath. - Henr. What does the Varlet mean? Ger. Sir, I ſuppoſe Don Carlos has inform'd you Thathe left meto ſee your Siſter Portia, With Flora, and Diego Oğavio's Man Safely convey'd this Houſe. - * cººl. Seehow Dan Henrique, who was iſ the Right. Ger. I did as he commanded me,and put them All three into Don Carlos's Anti-chamber 3 . Porcia in the ſame Chair which brought her thither; And for more ſafety made the door be lockd; - - M 2 Whilſt - Zº - ... .ſº --~~~~ T. --~~~~~~~ ----- - - - - - -— -
Page Scan 108

The Adventures of Five Hours. Whilſt I went down in hałe to fetch a Light. . . . ºr Henr. As fure as Death this Madneſs is ñaion, 5 My Man is now in one of Carlos Fits, . . . . . . . Ger. Returning with a Light a moment after, No ſooner open'd H the door; but Heavens ! . . . Who ſhould I fee there ſtanding juſt before me . . . . In the ſame place where I left forcia, but iſ . . . . Oğavio, your Enemy Oğavio. . . . . . . . . . . Hen. Here is ſome Witch-craft ſure; what can this mean? Ger: Amaz'd at th' ſight, I let the Candle fall; . . . . . And clapt the door to; then I double-lock'd it, And brought away the Key. ". . . . Carl. But how could he get in, if you be ſure Youlock'd the door, when you went out for Lights? Ger. I know not whether he was there before, Orgot in after, but of this l’m ſure , ºr " That there I have him now, and ſafe cnough. Carl. I am ſorry for it. [Aſide, Henr. Let's not, Don Carlos, now perplex our ſelves With needleſs Circumſtances, when and how Thoſe Queries are too Flegmatick for me; If the Beaſt be i' th' ſoil it is enough; Let usgaſsize upon him; he muſt die. Enter Antonio. 4nt. Good Brother, what unhappy Man is he, Whom you ſo poſitively doom to death? I have a Sword to ſerve you in all occaſions Worthy of you, and me. - Henr. His intervening, Carlos, is unlucky, How ſhall we govern ourſelves towards him. In this Affair 3 ſo unfit for his knowledge . Carl. -- --- - - -
Page Scan 109

The Adventure of Five Hours. Carl, Antonio is a Man of ſhining Honor ; . . . But having ſuch a ſhare in this Affront, , , , § Aſid If once he know't, I am afraid he'l bring f. Fuel, not Water to Dom Henrique's Fire. - Don Henrique, you muſt ſuddenly reſolve [To Henrique. What anſwer to return, he's fiot a Man . . . . To be put off with any ſlight Pretcnces; Nor yet to be engag'd in ſuch an Aćtion, Asbears th'appearance rather of Cruelty . . . . Than Honor, and you know, Antonio needs - No frcſh Occaſions to ſupport his Name ; , “Who Dangers ſeck, are indigent of Fame. Aut. I find my coming hath diſorder'd them, ) - There's ſomthingthey would ſain conceal from me; &ſide. All here is diſcompos'd, what er's the matter. , , ) Carl. Perhaps 'twere better to ſuſpend a while The Execution of your juſt Revenge: Time, and mature weighing of Circumſtances , Never did harm in Aćtions of this Nature ; Where one has ſtill the Party in his Power. . . . Henr. A Curſe on your Tame Propoſition Carlos : Carl. “He, who the Rules of Temperance negle&s, “From a Good Cauſe may produce Vile Effečis. Henr. I doubt not of your kind Concurrence, Sir, - - [To Antonio. In all the near Concernments of a Perſon. Alli'd toyouas I am ; but Noble Brother, It were againſt the Laws of Hoſpitality, And Civil Prudence to engage a Gueſt (Newly arriv'd after ſo long a Journey), In an occaſion, Sir, of Blood, and Hazard. Amt. If ſuch be the occaſion, I muſt then Acquaintyou freely, that I wear a Sword , . ºn Which
Page Scan 110

The Adventures of Five Hours, Which muſt not be exckided from your Scrwice; . . I'm ſure you are too Nóble t'imploy yours: "… ... it'ſ In any Cauſe not juſtifid by Honof; I ſº, º iſ But I confeſs there are Affronts ſo great , t , . . . . . . . ...And heightned by ſuch odious Circumſtances, , , , , , , As do releaſe us from the uſual Forms: . . . . . . . . . . ; // Of Generous Revenge; and ſet us free ºr 1... . . . ; ; ; ). To tak't on any Advantage. . . . . . . . . . . . . c : , , , ; Henr. Though with Regret I ſee, Sir, I muſt yield... . . Toyour exceſs of Generoſity 3 ºvº. 2: ...,’ tº ſº... I This onely I ſhall ſay to ſatisfie gººd. . . . . tº * -- Your juſt Reflections; that my Reſentments ſy, Are grounded on Affronts of ſucha Nature, . . . . That as nothing but the Offender's Life ... it j . . . . Cane'r repair them, ſo as to the Forms º ºr a 2: ... . . Of taking that Revenge, they can't admit. . . . . . . Of the leaſt ſcruple. - Ant. Honor's my Standard; and’tis true, that I . Hadrather Fall, than Bluſh for Vićtory; ºr . . . . . . But you are ſuch a Judge of Honor's Laws, , , , , , , That’rwere Injurious to ſuſpect your Cauſe. . . . . . Allow me, Sir, th’honor to lead the way. . . . . - - Exit Antonio and Henrique. Carl. If Porciabetheretoo, (as I believe)', - Twill prove, I fear, a fatal Tragedy; But ſhould ſhe not be there; yet 'tis too much For ſuch a Heart as mine, through Ignorance To have betraida Gentleman, though Faulty, Intoſuch Cruel hands; I muſt go with them; But ſoreſolv'd, as in this Bloody ſtrife - I'lſalvémy Honor, or I'lloſe my Life. . [Exit Carlos. The
Page Scan 111

The Žºventures of Five Hours. f : * .. s tº ºf 1. - c - - w * ... ." - 4 Clſº i ºf °, **** - . . . .” - 3 ºr .” Enter. Oétavio, Dicgo, Flora with a Candle. Flo, Q the unluckineſs! I vow tyou Sir 3, . . . . . . . . before. I have fºrce known that dooré'flock'd oã. There's no Remedy Flora, I am now At the Mercy of my Enemies. . . . . Die. Having broken into another's Ground, 'Tis juſtifaith, you ſhould be puti'th Pound. oã. The Tide Öfny ill Fate isfºln ſo high, "Twill not admit encreaſe of Miſerie; Since amongſt all the Curſes there is none So wounds the Spirit, as Privation, Had ſafely gain'd my Port, and far above , , My Hopes, the precious Treaſure had ſecur'd, For which ſomany Storms I had endur'd; To be ſoſoon from this great Bleſſing torn, That's hard to ſay, if twere firſt Dead, or Born, May doubtleſs ſeemſuch a tranſcendent Curſes, That eventhe Fates themſelves could do no worſe' 5 Yet this Ibore with an erected face, ſº I'...}} 9:3: sº º º “... , -- The Scene changes to Carlos's Houſe. --- -> -- For tisnot where we Lie, but whence we Fell, - The Loſsof Heaven's the greateſt Pain in Hell; . . . When I had ſail'd the doubtfulCourſe of Love, Since Fortune, not my Fault caus'd my Diſgrace; But now my Eyes unto the Eartharebent, Conſcious of meriting this Puniſhment, '' For truſting a fond Maid's Officious Care; * * * * , My Life, and Honor's taken in this Snare; ' ' ' And thus I periſh on this unſeen Shelf, Purſu'd by Fate, and Falſe unto myſelf. * . . . G. ºf * t * * --
Page Scan 112

The Adventures of Five Hours. Flora, when I am dead, be ſure that you ; He pulls out Theſe Tablets give tºrtia; thºre ſhº! find, {#if: - that to thºxtºměřMomčírofmy Lifeſiº 3:17 I conſtantly purſu'd thoſe Noble Ways , Which might Deſerve her, though I could not Have her. Give me the Candle. 2: . . . . | , ; :---- T. V. 3 Oštavio ſets the Candle on a Table, and fits. down as to write in his 7 ablets. . . º º Die. A double Curſe upon all Love in earneſt, ..." All Conſtant Love; 'tis ſtill accompani’d With ſtrange Diſaſters; or elſe ends in that . . . . . . Which is the worſhofall Diſaſters. Marriage." ' ". . Flo. Sure you could wiſh that every body living . . Had ſuch a Soul of Quick-ſilver, as yours, That can fix no where. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Die, Why'rwould not be the worſe for you, dear Flora, Youthen might hope in time to have your Turn," ** As well as thoſe, who have much better Faces. " ' ". . . Flo. You, I preſume Sir, would be one o'th’lateſt Which I ſhould hear of, yet 'tis poſſible . . . . . . . That one might ſeeyou, before you ſhould be welcom, Die.She has Wit,and good Humor; excellent " Ingredients to paſs away the time; And I have kindneſs for her Perſon too, - But that will end with Marriage, and poſſibly Hergood Humor; for I have ſeldom known - The Husband, and the Wife make any Muſick, Though when aſunder they can play their parts; Well, friend Diego, I adviſe you to Look Before you Leap, for if you ſhould be Coupled To a Yoak inſtead of a Yoak-fellow , - 'Tis likely you may wear it to your Grave. Yet, honeſt Diego, now I thinkon't beater, You ºv. . . Ollſ - “S. ºf . .

End of Section 24. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 25
Page Scan 113

Your Dancing, and your Vaulting days are dope, ( , , . Faithall your Pleaſures are three Stories highºff, i. 14 Th'are come up to your Mouth, for you are now For Eaſe, and Eating, th'ongly Joys of Life, 9tſ .*. * - And there's no Cook, nor Drie-N urſe like a wi. . . . . ." - … º.º.º. ºf ..[ Flora overthears him. Fºo. Icould find Reaſons too for Matrimony, a sºlº o A Stale Mata is a º: roach , - . . . Imuſt confeſs it ; and a Waiting-woman Does ongly change a Miſtris for a Maſter; . . . . . I may quit her, 'tis truç, but not my Husbandsºr, Jo O - Andon the other ſide ſhenay quit mesºs, ºſhii ºol And turn mcoff, whenold; and good for nothing. j. jo A Husband's bound to keep me ſtill; In fine, For ought I can pºrctive the Scales are Equal, . . . . I may throw Croſs and Pile, which Life I'd have3 Lºº iſ - The Single Begger, of the Marri'd Slave 3 is nº ...d.º. But heark! the Door within frºm whence we camg to Is newly open'd, or my Eatºdeceive me, ºf its ºntº vº. Die. Methoughts | hºar º, * ... xi : sº [They loºkimo the next Room, and start back. O Sir, ware lºgº.º.º. Coming moſt terribly upon us...i.e., , ; ; ; , Ostºvio.'ſ Oğ. Away you troubleſºme Fool. zºoivº dº yo" - * * - * Hºoid ºf Enter Camilia and Fºia, lººkº, " - the other with a Candle. ... wºº tºo Por. I'm confident nobody ſaw us paſs, º, tº From th'other Houſe. ºr , , ; ; ; , … .º.º. Cam. However, let's gºthrough my Brothºr's Quarter, And open the Back-door into the Stºcti, , oo, -iji ºr 'Tis good in all Events tº have a Retreat ºr ºv, - -- More ways, thanoke. . . . N . . . . . . . . .” * - - - Por. w -
Page Scan 114

- The Adventurer'ſ Firehow. por. O Heavens 1 out ſureſ is cutoff, the Wind Has clapt that doortothorough which we camp... ii., i. - 4 º' iſ 4 dºor claps behind, and both look back Cam. The Accident's unlucky, 'tis a Spring-lock, That opens onely on the other ſide. . . . . . . . . . . Por. Let's on the faſter, and make ſure of th'other. Oğavio here !...) tº iſ, “ . . . . . … º º …o 5 O&avio hearing them ſtarts tº Y up with the Tablets ins hand. oă. Portia in this place may I truſt my Senſes, , . . . lº, , . Or does my Fancy create thºſe Chimeras - Die. Either we Sleep, and Dream extravagantly 5. Or elſe the Fairiès govern in this Houſe. -- e.' " . . . . . [ Flora runs to Porcia. Flo. Ah! deareſt Miſtris, you ſhall never make me Quityeuſo again. . . . . . . . . Por. But can that be Ośavio 2. " . . . . . . Oä. I was Oğavio; but I am at preſent . . . So much aſtoniſh'd, tam not myſelf. . . . . - Cam. What can the meaning of this Viſion be? … • * * * * * * [Oétavio approaches Porcia. Oğ. My deareſt Porcia, how is't poſſible. . . . . To find }. in this place, noble Antonio - - - - - Having ſogenerouſly undertaken Your protećtion? * - - - - - - - Por. Did he not yours ſo too? and yet I find Offavio here, where heismore expos'd ' ' ' ' Than I, toſure deſtruction; I am loath . . . . To ſay 'tis he, who has Betraid us both. . . . . . Oğ, Antonio falſe 2 it is impoſſible. . . Die. It is too evident. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Qā. Peace Slave; he is my Friend, of Noble Blood, Whoſe Fame's above the Level of thoſe Tongues, ~ That ~~~
Page Scan 115

--~. . . . ~ The Adventures of Five Hours. That Barkby Cuſtom at the brighteſt Virtues, a S. As Dogs do at the Moon...º.º. . . . ' . . . --- - ºil, ſº .º." r ~ be . - - ~ * Por: “Howhard it is for Virtue toſuſpect. Ah Ottavio ! we have been both deceiv'd; This vile Antonio is the very Man, To whom my Brother withoutmy Conſent, il ºn . . . . . Or Knowledge has Comraded me in Flanders, Oğ. Antonio the Man to whomy are Qontračºd, , Porcia the Bride whom heiscome to Marry . . . . Por. The very ſame. º' ºr it iſ nº ſº. o. oã. Why didyounot acquaint me with itſooncº F Por. Alas, I have not ſeenyouſince I knew it; ; ºr But thoſe Few hours ſuch Wonders have produc'd, º, Asſurpaſsall Belief, and do require . . . …o'ſ y. . . . ~ More time, than your unſafe Cóndition herº cºop Will allowustomake you underſtand it. [...ºf po Cam. Dear Friends, ſcannotblameyour Apprehenſions, Nor your Suſpition of Antonio's Friendſhip; . . . . . . But I'amſopoſſeſs'd with the Opinion ºf Iºnia Of his great Virtue, that Iſhall asſoon : ... v. ... . . Believe Impoſſibilities, ashis. ºf 2: . . . . . . // . - Apo"acie from Honour. … . . . . . . ſo º, ) Oä. What's her Concernment in Antamia, Potia 3 a , Por.Q. that's the ſtrangeſt part of ourſădStory; no Andwhich requires moſt time to telyº. . ," ... º.º.º.º.º. - i.e. “Window, and a noiſe within. ... Por. See, Flora; at the Window, what's that Light, ºf And Noiſe we hear.ſo tº yo, ſº gº... ..., , , , º ºs º oſ-Eſºta goes to the mindow. Flo. O'Madam we are all undone; I ſce, rº, Henrique, Carlos, and their Servants with Torches, Antonio - Allcominghither,and which wonderful, ..., `- - .º. - - - - N 2 - - ~ * ——

End of Section 25. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 26
Page Scan 116

,- - TZT riſ Y. - . . . . -- " " The Adventures of Fiya Honº Antonio leading thenſ with his Swº drawn. Wºlf'ſ iſ . . . "... Tººlrºam’t, diſtraćted Wºnths, Asiangfalſe?, It is impoſſibkº” , jºy toº ºf ji bºr woh ** .…" - : Lvi º; ºr, - nº.3, and tarning back ſays, zi... . All ſhe has ſaidisiltappearance true sº ºf ſolº of T...ſure ſomebºdón Myſłºry which thus glºvoº 10 Abuſes us; fort ſhall net believg.º.º.º. ºi, can tranſgreſs the Rules of Friendſhip... "... " off. Friendſhip's an Empty Name , made to Deceive Thoſe, whoſe Gºlwatureſtampts them to believe sºo There's moſudythiºon Earth, the beſt that wee!A.º.º. " Canhopeſophere is faint Neutrality...º.º.º. Tºpor. Ye Powers abovel what pleaſure cat ye take: j : To perſecute Subſhitting innºcence; ſº ºf 1 ºrigſ yº. Oğ. Retire, deafrºbraiay to that inăcriſtoomyo": i: ' '. Fößouldthy crucifroiier find thee herº ºf G.W. - Hesſorevolted from Humanity, , ; º' ºr ſº Helmingle thine, withm impurer Blood, ºr f 1:... por. That were a kindo Coñtia&#lethnicºme3 ; : () . Weſtmeet at once Marriage, and Martyrdom. In , , ºt off. Soul of my Life retire. . . º ºil ºf , Por. £will flotleave you; , , , , , ..… . . oã. Thou preſerviſt by ſaving of thy ſelfs:.C. .** For they can murder with (half of me; ºoyi ſi..jºbſ. A hilſt that my better patt furvives in thee. for. I will detoygāivisjo maintain, That differencauſes form the ſame Eßsº … * Tiscourage in you Men, Love in ºxº Slioz int. .nºw slº ºiodijotziesholdof her to leadher away. Oğ. Helpmcºmilaº As ºf y. cº-º-º/ Y.e., cam. You muſt be rul’d, yout Preſence will increaſe ". . YourBrother's Fury, and Qāquio's Danger.º. Zºº;A. twº *. - 5 ºz. . - -- Por. * __*-*.*- - ~! *
Page Scan 117

The Adventures of Five Hours, tº Por.That Argument is Irreſiſtible.: , s: , . . . . . they retire to the other Room, and Qāayio. . . . . .313 waiişoathem to the doorºoH 35 ºf , ºf Die, Nay if you are at that,the Devil take ºf ºº The hindmoſt 3 'tis for your ſake, deareſt Flora, ſº jº * , ºº iſ 3 tº ..[Taking Flora Wythe hand. I ſhun thcſe HoHôtable Occaſions, 13 ºf ſºha goes out with Having no Weapon, Sir, 'tis fit that I wº ºft's t March off withdhºbaggage. …, , , ... ii. o * j, , , , ~ ; : . . . . . . . . ºffix umpiegº, Flora; º Ośī. I'm now upon the Frontiers ºf this Life, (I A y There's but one ſtep to Immortality; i ºri'ſ wrºſłł. T. Añd though my cruclfortune has allow'd me . . . . . ºv. No other Witneſs of my Tragick end, ſº - ... tººl of But my Inhumane Murtherers; yet my Deathi, Ao Shall not Diſgrace either my tº." tº ſetſ of Toth'other Wörld this Hoflor:liwillbòars, ºf , , ...sº - That as I ſtill have Liv'd, and Lov’d, ſolº ºw. I Encounter Death with the ſame Conſtancy...", / …, -" ºvº-º. º.º. ººlini: tº - - - Enter Antonio; Henrique, Čirić and Geraldo, with their . . .eſſ Swords drawn, Antonio àefore thereft. ! .º. - º Ant. Where is the Man whoſe Inſolence, and Folly. ... . Has thus miſled him to Affront my Friend? . . . . . . . yº) • Oğ. Here is the Manthouſeck'ſ, and he, whºm thou? So baſely haſt Betráid: ; 12 y.º. EQétavio drairſ, Ant. Oh Heaveſis: what is't I ſee? it is OHavio, º My Friend, tºº.º. . . . . . . . . . . . . . oã. Nótthy Friend,üºntonio; but 'tis Qāavies ºt Who b thyrierfldie has beenbetraid * \tſ ſoil. Hºriidſ To this forlörn Cºndition; but viløMan 3.2-gig of wºre Thou now ſhalt pay thy Treachery withthy Life, ſº I - ‘. . . . . . . . . [O&tavio makes at Antonio. 2}}. - * - - J. " -- - Amt. ~ a - - - º - ~ *-
Page Scan 118

The Adventures of Five Hours. Aſide. - Aſide. Ant. Holdoãavio; thoughtly injurious Error..." May tranſport thee, it ſhall not mebeyond. The Bounds of Honor; Heaven knowsil thought Of nothingleſs, than what I find, Oğavio In this place, sº " . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Heº. Whatpauſe is this, Antoniº all your Fervour In the Concernments of your Friend, reduc’d ' . ºr ". . To a tame Parly with our Enimy; . . - - Do all the Promiſes, you have made to me, sº * º Tafiſt my juſt Revenge, conclude in this? Off. Dö all the Promiſes you have made to me, ºo Taſſiſt my Virtuous Love, conclude in this? . . . . . . . . . [. Hen.Where is your wontedBravery? where your Kindnek To ſuch a near Allie 2: . . - * - oš Vhere isyourformer Honor where your Firmneſs To ſuch an antient Friend? . . . - 2. Wºmiypifinaed Honorfleer Betwixt theſe equal, oppoſité Engagements Her what, demuthiinayºffrightmyſelf, º, º '…º {... O&avio, An- . • * * * * * > . . . . . . . …, - - - - ºltónio turns an O&avio's ſide, 4. Ant. Wh'attaques Ośavio muſt paſs through mé. Carl. I muſt layhold on this Occaſion. . . . . . . Good Cozin, I conjurgyoutoreſtrain . . . . . . . . . . Yöur Paſſion for a while, there does die hid o Some Myſtery'id this, which once unfolded, , , May poſſibly produce the Means of making, . - -- * That Reconcilable, whichnow ſeems Deſpirate. . Heur, Sweetly propos'd, Sir, an Accommodation Think'ſt thou my Anger's like a Fire of Straw, ... . Onely to Blaze, and thenexpire in Smoakº . . . . . . y Think'ſt thou I can forgºt my Name, and Nation, - Aid Barterfor Revenge, when Honor Bleeds His
Page Scan 119

The Adventures of Five Hoars. – “---------- - --- His Life muſt pay this Inſolence, or mine, 2, ..…I - [ He makes at O&avio º interpºſº, Amt. Mine muſt prote&his, or elſe periſh with him, , , _Henr. Since neither Faith, nor Friendſhip can preyail,. . . 'Tis time to trie what proof you are, Antonio, , , , , , Againſt your own near Intreſt 3 Know, that Man, ; ; ). Whom you protećt sº my juſt Revenge, . . . . Has ſeconded his Inſolence to me ..., tº By foul Attempts upon my Siſter's Honor; . . . . . " Your Porcia's Sir, if this will not enflame you. ºf Porcia endeavours to come out, Camilla holds her." or. This Injury's beyond all Sufferance. Carl. To what exceſs of Folly does our Rage [Aſide. Tranſport us Men I this moſt Important Scºret, Which Tortures could not have made him diſcover sº He (onely to advance his blind Revenge) … . . . Has now unforc’d declared to that ;, From whom, of allmen living, he ought moſt . . . . To have conceal’d it. . . -- " -- " ' ' ' OH. Howl I attemptyour Siſter's Honor Hºrique?, The Parent of your black Deſigns, the Devil, j . . Did nerinvent a mere malicious Falſhood; - 'Tis true, that I have ſerv'd the Virtuous Porcia, - With ſuch Devotion, and ſuch Spotleſs Love, That, though unworthy, yet ſhe has been pleas'd : , , , , To recompence my Paſſion with Eſteem : , º, . . . . By which, ſhe has ſochain'd me to her Service, . . . . . . . . . That here I vow either to Live her Prize, Or if I Die, to fall Loves Sacrifice. . . . . . . Ant. O Heavens ! what's that I hear?thoubleſſed Angel Guardian of Honor, I do now implore, - Thy powerful aſſiſtance to preſerve . . . . That Reputation, which I hitherto. . . . by - - - - - -
Page Scan 120

The Adventures of Five:Hours. | By virtuous Aaionshave maintain'd unblemiſh'd; ºf In vain, Don Henrique, you deſign to change - My Reſolutions; it muſtner be ſaid, tºº. . . . . . . . That Paſſion made Antonio recede . . . . . . From the ſtriót Rules of Honor ; Sir, I tell you, ... . . . Nothing can make the violate my firſt . . . . . . Engagement. . . . .” - . . . . . . . . . . . Henr. Nay, then thou ſhalt Die too, Perfidious Man's - Ho! Geraldo, Pedro, Leonido. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Enter Geraldo, Pedro, Leonido, with their Swords drawn, and joyn with Henrique; Carlos interpoſes. . . . . . Carl. For Heaven'sſake, Cozin, draw not on your ſelf The horrid Infamy of Aſlaſinating tº wº, Perſons of Noble blood by Servić Hands, g : 1. . . . . Henr. Do you Defend then too? Kill'em Iſay. . . . . . Ant. Retireoivio, I'l ſuſtain their ſhock.” - OH. OHavio retire 2- . . . . . . º " . . . . . . . . . Ant. Truſt me you muſt, they will ſurround us elſe; Through that härrow Paſſage they'l Affailus, ºi º Withleſs advaitagd. 1: . . ºf fºo:::::::::::::f cºhey retire fighting off the Stage; Henrique * 2 and his Men perſuing them, and Carlos. , , , , ; ; (endeavºuring to ſtup Don Henrique. . . . . . Henr. What dye give backºye Men of mighty Fame?" Ant. Don Henrique, you ſhall juickly find 'tis Honor , s , Not Fear makesmeretire, ºr ºf . . [Exeunt. - cº-ºº: ". . . . . . . … . . . . . . º Enterpreſently Antonio and Oºtavio at another door, º, º f : . Hºwhich Antonio bolts. . . . . (). • * 4nt. Now we ſhall have a breathing while at leaſt . . . . . Ottavio, and time to look aboutus; . . . . . . . Pºyſe yon other door befaſt. . . . . . . . . . - - oãavio * - \ - *
Page Scan 121

The Adventures of Five Hours. z Oétavio fiels to the door where they went out,and 3 Henrique bounces at the door they came in at. Henr. Geraldo, fetch an Iron Bar to force [Within. The door. - . - _r [ Camilla and Porcia peep out. Cam. Heaven has heard our Prayers;th’are both ſafe here. Por. Let's go to 'em Camilla. - - Cam. 'Tis better to ſtay here a while, and hearken What Reſolution of themſelves they take. - [Antonio goes to both the doors toſse if they befaſt. Amt. So, 'tis now as I could wiſh. . - Oğ. What do you mean, Generous Antonio 2 Ant. To Kill thee now my Sclf, having perform'd What Pre-engagement did exact from me ' . In your Defence gainſt Others; my Love now Requires its Dues, as Honor has had his; There's no Protećtion for you from my Sword, But in your Own, or in your frank renouncing All Claim to Porcia; She is ſo much mine, " That none muſt Breath, and have the Vanity Ofa Pretender to her whilſt I Live. Oā. My Claims to Porcia I ſhall ne'r renounce, But ſtill aſſert them by all noble ways : Yet, Sir, this hand ſhall never uſe a Sword (Without the laſt Compulſion) gainſt that Man, Who has ſo much Oblig'd me; no Antonio, “. You are ſecurely Guarded by the Favours, You have conferr'd upon me. Ant. Sir, let not your pretended Gratitude Enervate your Defence; 'tis not my cuſtom To ſerve my Friends with Proſpećts of Return 5 I therefore, Sir, do freely here acquit you, From all the Obligations, you º pleas'd T w - Q z -
Page Scan 122

* The Adventures of Five Hours. To own from me. N Off. You may, Sir, if you pleaſe, forbear to add New Favours to my’ account; but you can never - Subſtraćt thoſe, which are paſt 3 and till that Debt Befully paid, I ſhall not dare t'appear - I’th' Liſts againſt ſo Generous a Creditor. Ant. Your Scruples are ill grounded; 'twas OHavio (Myantient Friend) whom I deſign'd to Serve; Not that Diſloyal Man, who has invaded My Honor, and my Love; “'Tis the Intent “Creates the Qbligation, not th' Event. oã. I call thoſe Powers, who both Diſcern,and Puniſh, To witneſs for me, that I never knew Youe'r pretended to Don Henrique's Siſler, Before I came within theſe fatal Walls: This I declare, onely to clear myſelf From th’Imputation of Diſloyalty, And to prevent the Progreſs of your Error. Ant. How can I think you ſhould ſpeak Truth to me, Who am a Witneſsy'have been Falſe to her, To whom i. now profeſs ſo high Devotion. Oğ, Ifalſe to Porcial take heed, Antonio, So foul an Injury provokes too much 3 But, Sir, I muſt confeſs I owe you more, Than the Forgivneſs of onegroſs Miſtake. Ant. Rare limpudence I I muſt not truſt my Senſes. Oä. If we cannot adjuſt this Competition, Let us our Fortunes, not our Paſſions charge With this our breach of Friendſhip. - 4nt. Leave your Diſcourſes, and Defend yourſelf; Either immediately Renounce all Claims. Shaking his To Porcia ; or this muſt ſpeak the reſt. . . . . . . {: Oä. Nay, then, this muſt Reply. º [They fight. - They
Page Scan 123

The Adventures of Five Hours. They without bounce at the door, • as if they were breaking it open. Por. Why do I doubt there is no means to ſave him From the preſent danger, but by another, ;. as great, but ſomething more remote; l'I do't. . - {*. lſt they fight, Porcia breaks from Camilla, and unbolts the door, then runs back into herplace. Enter Henrique, Carlos, Leonido, Geraldo, with their Swords drawn. Hen. What's this : Antonio fighting with Oğavio ! This Bravery is exceſſive, Gallant Friends Not to allow a ſhare in your Revenge Tº him, who's moſt concern'd; he muſt not die Without ſome Marks of mine. } Henrique makes at Oétavio, and Antonie - - turns to O&avio's ſide. Amt. Nay, then my Honor you invade anew, And by Aſſaulting him, Revive in mc My Pre-engagements of Prote&ing him Againſt all others. - * Hen. Wły were not you Antonio fighting with him * Were you not doing all you could to Kill him * Ant. Henrique, 'tis true; but finding in my breaſ, An equal ſtrife'twixt Honor, and Revenge; I do in juſt compliance with them both Preſerve him from your Rage, to Fall by mine. . - Carl. Brave Man, how Nicely he does Honor weigh'? . Juſtice her ſelfholds not the Scales more Even. . Henr. My Honor ſuffers more as yet than yours, And I muſt have my ſhare in the Revenge; Either he muſt renounce all º to Porcta, . O - 2 º
Page Scan 124

The Adventures of Five Hours. - - Or Die immediately. . . . . - Ant. It is agreed; that he muſt Doe, or Die: “... But by no other hand, than mine., - . off Ceaſe your Contention, and turn all your Swords Againſt this Breaſt; whilſt Porcia’and l have breath, She muſt be mine, there's no Divorce but Death. - - Henr. I'l hear no more, protećt him if thou canſ Antonio. Kill the Slave,kill him, Iſay, .. - {Hºriº makes at him, and Carlos - “endeavours to enterpoſe. . . . . . Carl. For Heaven's ſake hold a Moment 5 ccrtainly There's ſome Miſtake lies hidden here, which clear'd , º, Might hinder theſe Extremes. . . . . . . . . º - - Henrique and his Servants preſ; , . . . . . . . Antonio and Qćtavio. . . . . . . cam. Theſe Errors muſt be cleard, before they grow. … Toofatal, but I fear your Brother's fury - Will not admit of Reaſon. . . . . por. I’m ſure I’ltry, though it ſhould coſt my life... - * - " ... "… “ . . * * * * * : ". Enter Porcia and Camilla from the Inner Room. 't Por. Don Henrique. - . . . . . . . cam. Antonio, Carlos. . . . . . . Por. Oétavio. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Camilla and) ºniº . . . . . . . . Porcia tº: Hear us but ſpeak. - 'gether. - * -- ~ * Henr. Ha! how came ſhe here 2, . Carl. Did not Itellyou that ſhe was brought hither, By my Direétion; 2, you would not believe me, . . . . . Henr. But how then could OHavio come hither? Carl. Nay, that Heaven knows 3 you heard as well as I Your Man's Relation. . . . * • * : ~ Henr, * * * -
Page Scan 125

The Adventures of Five Hours. - Henr. Ah thouvile Woman that I could deſtroy Thy Memory with thy Life. . . * . . . . ; , [He offers to run at Porcia, Antonio interpoſes. Amt. Hold, Sir, that muſt not be. - • * Henr. What may not I do Juſtice upon her Neither 2 * * * Ant. No Sir ; although I have not yet the Honor – To know who ſhe's, I have this night engag’d - Myſelf, both to Secure, and Serve her. - - Carl. He knows not Parcia; who was i' the right. Don Henrique, You, or I?, . . . . . . . . Henr. He not know Parcia? whom not an hour ſince I ſaw, and ſpoke with, entertaining her . . . . In his Apartment 3 ſure we are Enchanted, - Andall we ſee's Illuſion. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Cam. Allow ºº:: theſe Charms; , Who is't, Oñavio, you pretend to 2 ſpeak. . . . . . . Oä. You might have ſpar'd that Queſtion; ſince none Knows ſo well as you, 'Tis Portta I adore. . . . . . Ant: Porcia's my Wife; Diſloyal Man that Diſt. tº a . . . . . . . [Offers to make at Octavio. Cam. Hold Sir; which is the Porcia you'claim too? Ant. Can you ben doubt of that 2 you know too well The Conqueſt, that you made ſo long ago ... . . - Of my ſurprized heart in Flanders. . . . . . - • 2 "... tº º Carl. Conqueſt! Surpris d! Flanders! what can this mean? - *- ** * * * - * ------- - Henr. New Riddles every moment do ariſe, And Myſteries are born of Myſteries. . . . . Cam, Thanks be to Heaven,our workdraws near anchd; Cozin, it belongs to you to finiſh it. Por. To free you from that Labyrinth, Antonio, In which a ſlight Miſtake, not Rećtifi’d, Has involv’dus all; know, th’ſuppos'd Porcia, - - : - - Whcm
Page Scan 126

The Adventures of Five Hours. Whom you folong have lov’d,’s the true Camilla. cam. Andyou, Don Henrique, know, Oñavio Has always been your Siſter's faithful Lover; And º Feign'da Gallantry to me, His real Paſſion to Diſguiſe from you. Oćtavio and Antonio run to awe 4- - nother and embrace. Amt. Generous Ottavio. - Oğ. Brave Antonio, how happy are we both ! Both in our Loves, and Friendſhips : Ant. Man's Joys done'r to their Perfeótion riſe, Till when by Croſſes heightned, they ſurprize. . . . % Camilla takes Antonio by the hand and leads him to Don Carlos. - Cam. This,tmy dear Brother,is that brave Commander, . To whom you owe your Life, and Liberty 3." And I much more, the ſafety of my Honor. . . . Carl. Is this the Gallant Leader, who reſcu'd us . With ſo much Valour from th’Enemy's hands 2 Cam. The very ſame. - Carl. If you knew him ſo well, why did not you Acquaint me with it ſooner?’twas a fault Camilla. - Cam. Alas, my deareſt Brother, Gratitude ſprawing car- Conſpiring with the Graces of his Perſon, lº “f* So ſoon poſſeſs'd him of my Heart, that I Deſpairinger again to ſee him; and Aſham'd of ſuch a Viſionary Love, Durſt never truſt my Tongue with my own Thoughts. . . 3. Carlos preſents Camilla - to Antonio. - _ Carl.'Tiscnough. - Take here from me the Hand of her, whoſe Heart Heaven,
Page Scan 127

The Adventures of Five Hours. Heaven, and your Merits have long ſince made yours Without my Knowledge; may her Virtue pay - Some part of that, which we both owe to yours. , r * * {}. takes Porcia's hand, and kiſſes it with great reſpeš. - Ant. Here with your kave, and hers Iſcal the Vows, - Of my Eternal Faith unto you both. - Carl. But let's take heed, Antonio, leſt whilſt we Are Joying in our mutual Happineſs, Don Henrique's ſcarcely yet compos'd Diſtemper - - Revive not, and Diſorder us afreſh: I like not his Grim Poſture ; you know well - After a Tempeſt, though the Wind be laid , There oftcn does remain for a good while A dangerous Agitation of the Waves; He muſt not yet be truſted with himſelf. Amt. 'Tis well thoughton, let us go to him. , Oétavio holding Porcia by the hand - - 3 advances towards Henrique. Oä. Here with Reſpećt we wait the Confirmation. Of Heaven's Decrees from your Indulgence, Sir. This Lady, your Incomparable Siſter, . Can witneſs that I never did invade . Your Paſſion for Camilla; and Pedro's death Happen'd by yourmiſtaken Jealouſe; - " The Cauſes of your Hate being now remov’d ..., 'Tis juſt, Pon Henrique, the Effects ſhould ceaſe. Henr. Ifhall coſſult my Honor. . . . . Carl. You cannot take a better Counſellor In this Caſe, than you Own, and Siſter's Honor; . . . 'What, to ſecure them both, could have been wiſh'd Beyond what Fatehath of it ſelf produc’d Henr. “How hard it is to A& upon Conſtraint. * * * * That,

Page Scan 128

The Adventures of Five Hours. That, which I could have VViſh'd, I now would Flie, Since’tis obtruded by Neceſſity. . . . - Amt. Noble Don Henrique, make account of me . . . . To be as truly yours by this Alliance, - * , As if a Brother's Name ſubſiſted ſtill. s Henr. I muſt conſent, I ſee,or worſe will follow. [Aſide. “He is a Foolwho thinks by Force, or skill “To turn the Current of a Woman's Will, . . . . Since fair Camilla is-Antonio's Lot , . . . . . . 1 Porcia yield to Don Antonios Friend. . . Our Strength, and Wiſdom muſt ſubmit to Fatc. . . . . Stript of my Love, I will put off my Hatc. . . . . * * -- - {º: takes Porcia by the hand - and gives her to Oétavio. Here, take her hand; and may ſhe make you, Sir, Happier, than ſhe has done me. . - - . . . . . . . . . . . [They all embrace, but Henrique coldly. Enter Diego and Flora from the inner Room. . . . Flo. Hadſuch Diſorderse'r ſuch a Come-off? Me-thinks 'twould make a Rare Plot for a Play. Die. Faith Flora, I ſhould have the worſt of that 3 For by the Law of Comedy 'twould be My Lot to Marry you. - |- Oš. Well thoughton, Diego, though ſpoken in Jeſt; We cannot do, I think, a better thin . . In Earneſt, than to make them Two ion Hands. What ſay'ſt thou to it, Flora 2 * Flo. Indeed I have had ſo many Frights this night, That I am enafraid to lie alone. . . . . . . . . . . [Diego takes her by the hand. - Die. Give methy Hand Flora, it is a Bargain; . . . I promiſe thee, dear Spouſe, I'l do my beſt To

End of Section 26. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
Section 27
Page Scan 129

The Adventures of Five Hours. To make thee firſt Repent this Earneſt Jeſt. Flo. That time ſhall trie, Carl. Since this laſt happy Scene is in my Houſe, You'l make Collation withmce're we part? - - Amt. A . w - OH. greed, agreed, agreed. Pie. Sir, you had beſt make haſte, clfe what you call Collation, may prove a Breakfaſt, for 'tis , Near twelve a Clock. * -. w 4nt. Thus end the Rare Adventures of Five Hours; Asſometimes Boiſterous Storms in Gentle Showrs. THE EPILOGUE. Diego comes ſtealingin, and isfollowdby Henrique, who ſtays at the Door, and Liſtens. - .. * - . . . . . . . * * * ~ * Die.ſhCme Gentlemen - - J. Let the Dons and Monſieursſay what they will; For our parts, we are for Old Englandſtill. Here's a fine Play indeed, to lay the Scene - º * - 2 - - - - - - In three Houſes of the ſame Tºwn, 9 mean: , . mºhy we have ſeveral plays, where I # * - - . . . . Th’ Devil to tell where the Scene does lie : ºv, , , Sometimes in Greece, and then they make aſtºp To Tranſilvania, thence at one Leap, , . . . . To Greece again; this ſhows a ranging Brain, mhich ſcorns to be confindt'a T.* in Spain. Then
Page Scan 130

The Adventures of Five Hour. - Then for the Plot; * - / The pºſſible Adventures of Five Hours; - 4 copious Deſign, why’ in ſome of ours . . . . . . Many of th’ Adventures are impoſſible, Or if to be atchiev'd, no A.4am can tell Within what time; this ſhows a rare Invention, *hen the Deſign’s above your Comprehenſon. mhilſt here y are treated with a Romance Tale, - And a Plot cover'd mith a Spaniſh Veil. As for the Style; - - - It tº as eaſie 43 4 Proclamation, . . ," , i. º As if the Play were Pen'dforth' whole Nation. None of thoſe thundring Pines, which uſe to crack Qur Breaths, and ſet your Wits upon the Rack. Who can admire this Piece, orthinki: good 2 s. º - There's not ºne Line, bat maybeuhdºñood. . . . . The Raillery; - 43 innocent, as if't had paſt the Teft . . . . º y . . . . of a full Synod: hot one Baudy feaſt; ,1. Nor any of thoſe words of DouéleSenſe, -- hhich makes th' Ladies, to ſhow their Innocence, #: ſºlilºſºgºnik, The Gallant ſhows he understand; the Šºk. But here you have azieceſſatty mºrit, ºs . . . . . . Aſen must have hit themſelves to find the wit: . . . . . . * - * - --- * = a- ". * -- . . . * * - . - - - Faith that's too much; thºre &y my conſent, ºr . . . ‘. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - * * * * * : * We'l Damn the Play. - ... . . . . . . . . . : ' ' ' . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . & - - - , , Henr. Think]: thou, Impºrtinent, . . . ; Pointingto The thºſe who knºw the Pingrºfºſſingingfºrth & hiº 4 Diving Scene, ſhoulder diffrºy this hirih zºº ºf ſouther can want fuchiºriters, who affire sº Topleaſethe judges of that upper Tire. * ** -
Page Scan 131

The Adventures of Five Hours. , r The Knowing are his Peers, and for the reſt Of the Illiterate Crowd (though finely dreſt) s The Author hopes, he never gave them cauſe To think, he'divaſe his Time for their Applauſe. - rou then (moſt equal judges) freely give rour Potes, whether this Play ſhould Die, or Live. v THE EPI Lo Gu E AT Cou RT. M 7° Have paſs'd the Lords, and Commons 3 and are come 2. W At length, Dread Sir, to hear your Final Doom. ’ſir true, Tour Vaſſals, Sir, inay Vote the Laws, Their Sanition comes from rour Divine Applauſe. 7 his Shining Circle then will all ſit Mute, - Till one pronouncefrom you, Le Royle Veut. :- - - º * - - s 2 * r- — - – - ~z. -". - s , ... " - ... " - º - * - - ~ \ F P N I S. - *- º- - 2. - - o: - - | * / * > - - - - - ~ r - - - _2~ A t *- - - A ~ - z / º - * }. 3-2. - - … w - w - - . *~ - ºx - - ſº - - - - w - --- - | -- - . 2- - Y - - !. - - - - - - --- ~ ---- -
Page Scan 132

---------|-|-|-__--|----- ：~ !|-|-·！！*！--~~~~;----±-----+----*-+-+-+---+---+---+---+---+----------------|-·---- ··|-|-|- |------ |-|- - -|-|×·· *|-|- |-·|-·|-·« m. |-·|-！|-·|-|-|- ·~|-· ,|\){' .· |-|-· ！, , !·- ~ ！， ！, ！^， ，----|-·---- •|--|-|-|- v·· ·|-· ·|-|-·|-×+·|- *|-|-· · ·a.·?·|-· v|· |-|-·|-|-_* ！|^|-|-*，|-+ ----|-， ， ,·||- |_ º _ •----·· · ·, ！|-|-|-|-- -|-• •|- |-----·|-！|- |- |--|-|-· -|！|-’,|-|-， , ，---- |--* .·\ \----， !+|-|×|-|-|-… ， ----~· *)•|-- ,, '… *|-|-|-»--（ \ ） --·|-·····' …·|-|--zº,||-…- ·|-|-|-|-|-· ---- |-(..|-}* -|-|-* -*|-·· |·|-*·-！\，* |-|-·|-·····|-·|-----· ·· · · · · ·----… -|-•|-, , ，* .|-|-• , · · · ·|-·- - -·…"! -|-|-|-|-|-· -|-|-·| ， ,· ！ 1· |-， ， ，， , , · *|-* «||-^|-}· |-|-_-^ · |-- · ·|--- «|-·· ,|×|-|-·|-|-，|-v-- ſº ···|-, ！·|-|-|-·|-|- |-·, ！*|-|-|-- ）|-, ,-*|-~|- |-|-|-·|--|-|-----|-|-|- - -|-|-|-|----- |- ·|-|× |-|-·---- v* ：----·|-|-|- |-|-|-% ----- ,- .·， ！· *|-|-r.---- |-… ' , '！|- |-！,^， ， ·|-··|-|-|-|-|- |-\|-·|-|-|-|- |-|-}·（ ） v.|-·→ ·|-|-- -|-}|-|-|-·- -|-. --+ |-|-|-|-！|-' ,|-+… w ···-• • •|-|-！ |-|--·|-' ~| |-|-··- -：|- |- ----\- ：, ， ,··.*·/|-|-|-|-|-|-m.(）|- ·----·|------~| .ſae·， .|--|- ----|-|-·!|- |-|-|- |-|--！|-y |-|-，|-|-|-\-|- ··--------/.-----|-|-. ^！ »| } -}, |-·|-|-， ,|--|-|-|-|-·-|- --*|-|-！|-|-|-|-·\|-|-`-|-|-|-！ |-|-··|-·|-·|-！|-|-·！ ----|-|---|-~ ··----|-|-·|-… •|-----\/* -- „ -|-- --·|-, ！|-«^*|-- - | 9|- --------- -· ·|-|-|-·' ， ！· ·\|-|-|-|-|-|-,^·• 1, *|× |-|-|-|-|- • • • • ~ .|-- N.\， ，* · * *· ·|-, ， , º|-** .· |- |-·|---------, -|-\|-* …|-|-！|- |- , -|-|-•·|-|-|--• .··|-·|-！|- -|-·r.. ^+, -----|-*-·|-|-* …vº, •· · · · · ·|-- -|- |-}，·• ， !+|- ·|- ·|-A |-, -|-|-， ，|-*- - |-|-|-|-|- ··|-|-|-|-|-- |- |-··, ，}v v- ， ！ ·|-/·|-|-|-!|- ！----！！|-, ，·----+ ·|-|-/|-|- |-|-|-|--|-·|-*·· |-· • ¶|- |-·， , ， ，- · -|-|-!··|- |-~ !ae→ ·---- |-… ~~|\. "···, ！/|-, ,·|-|- |-----~~|-|-·，, ，• •|-|-·|-|-·！ |-|- |-|-|-·|-, !*|-·'ſ,|-|-|-|- ~~ ~~- -…|-|-|-|-| .|-·· --' ， .→|-·~,* ...’|-|- ·|- * _ ·.*， ,|-|-|-… *|-|-|-|- |-~· !|·… …|-|-|-|-|-|- |- ·-|-*|-v.|-·|-|-|- |-----, ！· · --|-, ，·|-|- ··|-----·|-|-·-·|-|-|-|- ·|-|-|-----|-|-*|-|-----|-|× |-·! -· · · -|-， ！|-|-|-|- |-» I !- -|-· *, ！|-， ， ， .·~\· -|-|--* ,|-|× |-|-, ，·|-·|-·' .* -·|-· · ·|-ae* … ]|-- º|- -|-·|-·|- --* * *· · · ·， ，· · · · *|· ， , .'. ,， ， ， ， ， ， ,<! -* -|-|-|- |- ··|-||-|- ·|-|-'-, ，|-* -|-|- |-·, ！\ ^·~|----- - -|-|- |-，|-• , ！|- |-|- ：||-·T •|- |-|- ----|-v;！·|-|-··|-···1'|×|-|- -- -|-|*|-*|- |-|-·|-|- |-|-， , ， ，|- |-·----|-|-/· |- ·|-{|-|-\|- - -|-|-|-|-|-|-|- »·• |-|-* |-|-|-|-|-|- - |-！ -• ！|----－r ' ），|-|×··|×\： ~| ~ ----|-|- |-|-·*·→ ·|-}]|- |-·|-···-|- ， ！/-|- -|-+|-|-··- -·！ ! \·|-- ----|-|-|-| ·！-!· ·|-* -:-|-·|-|-·|-·|-|-|-， ！|×· \|-|-|-|-·|-}, !} • »|-*|-----|×\ ·|--·} ）•*|-|--·* |-→ ·|- ·|-|-|-|-· ·|-·|- -<|-|-|- |-|-|-|-|-|-|- |-|-·|-; |- - - ~ º - ---- - - * - - - - - º - w - - º - - r_ - - - -- - - -- / - - |- |-·- ,· |×|-· |-·|- |-|-~~ ~|-|- |- i|-·|- -· v.|-|-， !-1* ,：|-|-· /· |-·|-|-|-|-- … |-----|-|-|-|- |-* ,|-|-|-|- |-~,· ~ . ~|-|~ ·|-|- ·|-|-… / -|- ·|- ----|-|×*}：· |-|- |-|-~ .… • ¡ ¿{·！ |-|--»， ， , }*|-·|- |-|- |-+-|-|- |- ·|- |- |-|- |-·· |-|- ||-|-/* |-|- ·|-



Page Scan 133

Blank page
Page Scan 134

Blank page
Page Scan 135

Blank page
Page Scan 136

Blank page
Page Scan 137

Blank page
Page Scan 138

---- ！ ----v！！！!！ae ŹN/（\&\\?\（\））（\\\/,'\\$\.\?\!\.\， ---- -

Page Scan 139

ſº-JV-7-7 z_v. N2–N. N. Sº, Sr. v. Nº, N, NY, -Y-V, V, x-vº-vº ºrrºr- -Mºw ！！！！！！！！！！!！-：-！ ， ſaeſae|-|- |- -| vºv Wºw ------- --- Scºtz, KººV-7-7R - vºw -> ºv. N } }， } ș)

Page Scan 140

Blank page

This page contains an image.

End of Section 27. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents

End of text. Return to beginning.
