<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../out/TestOdd.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <!--Note, you haven't fully edited the teiHeader for this document -->
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titlestmt>
                <title>The Adventures of Five Hours</title>
                <author>samuel Tuke</author>
                <editor>Lauren Liebe</editor>
                <funder>Texas A &amp; M University Center of Digital Humanities Research</funder>
            </titlestmt>
            <editionstmt>
              <!--This is for the edition published on Digital Restoration Drama-->
                <edition n="1">Derived from OCR.</edition>
                <editor>Lauren Liebe</editor>
                <respstmt>
                    <resp>Text derived from OCR Full Text on HathiTrust at
                      https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc1.31822043035914
                        and encoded by</resp>
                    <name ref="#p1001">Lauren Liebe</name>
                </respstmt>
            </editionstmt>
            <publicationstmt>
                <publisher>Digital Restoration Drama</publisher>
                <address>
                    <addrLine><!--Website goes here--></addrLine>
                    <addrLine>digitalrestorationdrama@gmail.com</addrLine>
                </address>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Distributed
                        under a Creative Commons Attribution-shareAlike 4.0 International
                        License.</licence>
                    <!--What do I have to do to make certain this is available under Creative Commons? -->
                </availability>
                <date><!--Date of publication/upload goes here --></date>
            </publicationstmt>
            <seriesstmt>
                <title>Digital Restoration Drama</title>
            </seriesstmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblFull>
                    <titlestmt>
                        <title>The Adventures of Five Hours</title>
                        <author>samuel Tuke</author>
                    </titlestmt>
                    <publicationstmt>
                        <publisher>Henry Herringman</publisher>
                        <pubPlace>the sign of the Anchor in the Lower Walk of the New Exchange</pubPlace>
                        <date when="1664">1664</date>
                        <edition>second Edition</edition>
                    </publicationstmt>
                    <notesstmt>
                        <note>University of California</note>
                    </notesstmt>
                </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
      <front>
        <titlePage>
          <docTitle ref="#pt169">
            <titlePartMain>
              <seg><h3>The </h3></seg>
              <seg><h1>Adventures</h1></seg>
              <seg><h4>of </h4></seg>
              <seg><h2>Five Hours.</h2></seg>
            </titlePartMain>
            <titlePartDesc>
              <seg><h4>A</h4></seg>
              <seg><h2>Tragi-Comedy</h2></seg>
            </titlePartDesc>
          </docTitle>
          <edition>The second Edition.</edition>
          <epigraph>
            <p>
              <seg><italic>Non ego Ventose Plebis suffragia venor.</italic></seg>
            </p>
            <bibl>
              <author><name type="person" ref="pXXXXX">Horat.</name></author>
            </bibl>
          </epigraph>
          <imprimatur>
            <seg><italic>Febr</italic>. 12. 1662.</seg>
            <seg>IMPRIMATUR</seg>
            <seg><name type="person" ref="pXXXXX"><italic>JOHN BERKENHEAD</italic></name>.</seg>
          </imprimatur>
          <docImprint>
            <seg><name type="place" ref="locXXXXX"><italic>LONDON,</italic></name></seg>
            <seg>Printed for <name type ="person" ref="#pXXXXX"><italic>Henry Herringman</italic></name>, and are to be sold at his shop</seg>
            <seg>at the <name type="place" ref="locXXXXX"><italic>sign of the Anchor</italic></name> in the Lower Walk of </seg>
            <seg>the <name type="place" ref="locXXXXX"><italic>New Exchange.</italic></name> 1664.</seg>
          </docImprint>
        </titlePage>
        <pb n="1"/>
        <salute>
          <head>
            <name type="person" ref="pXXXXX">
              <seg><italic><h5>To the Right HONORABLE,</h5></italic></seg>
              <seg><h2>HENRY HOWARD,</h2></seg>
              <seg><h4>OF</h4></seg>
              <seg><h2>NORFOLK.</h2></seg>
            </name>
          </head>
          <p>
            <seg>Since it is Your Pleasure (Noble Sir) that </seg>
            <seg>I should hold my Fortune from You; like </seg>
            <seg>those Tenants, who pay some Inconside-</seg>
            <seg>rable Trifle in lieu of a Valuable Rent, I </seg>
            <seg>humbly offer You this Poem in Acknowledgment of </seg>
            <seg>my Tenure: and I am well pleas'd with this Occa-</seg>
            <seg>sion to Publish my sense of Your Favours, since it </seg>
            <seg>seems to me a kind of Ingratitude to be Thankful </seg>
            <seg>in Private. </seg>
          </p>
          <p>



            It was bred upon the Terrace-Walks in Your ... Garden at Aldbury; and, if I mistake not, it re- - - - A 2. , -’ sembles : º 2- §§ X : § ;



End of section 4. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 5
Page scan 12

sembles the Place where it was Brought up : The Plot is Delightful, the Elevations Natural, the As. cents Easie, without any great Embellishments of Art. - I design'd the Charaćter of Antonio as a Copy of Your stedy Virtue; if it appear to those, who have the Honor to know You, short of the Original; I take leave to Inform them, that You have not sat to me long; 'Tis possible, hereafter I may Gratific my Country for their Civility to this I say with something more worthy of Your Patronage, and their Indulgence. - - In the Interim I make it my Glory to avow, That had Fortune been Just to me, she could not have Recompens’d the Loyal Industry of my Life with a more illustrious Title, than that which You have been pleas'd to Confer; upon me 3 of TO 11 R FRIEND. To which ( as in Gratitude I am found ) I subjoyn that of * - - Tour most humble servant, - -- s. Tuk P. - - -, - - r | - - ––––-T-- -

End of section 5. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 6
Page scan 13

|! : | : - To my most Honour’d Friend Colonel Tuke, upon his Exem- plary Dramatique Poem the Adven- - * tures of Five Hours. In this we find how Vaft's the scope of Wit, Although restrain'd within the bounds of fit sº The work’s Heroick ; it redeems the stage From flat andfoul,whilst that riforms the Age; what Figures of things rare how well design'd, Of which the noblest sir express your mind; The brave Antonio's words amaz'd us all; From what Pen else could such high Rapturesfall 2. The Geºrous gratefull Maida Fire express'd, which sprang to Flames in ev'ry Manly breast 3 No more spetiators now, w are Ašiors all, With ev'ry Change our Passions rise, or falls, Of all who Live the best discerning King . The sutješ chose for him who best cauld sing 3: . For him whose Muse does Charm the nicºst Ear, , For him who beft could hºrite, and test forbears • 2 s - • * ;1th Fletcher's Nature, Learned Johnson's Art, Of others too the more Transcendent part : Dramatique Laws not only kept but taught, And new Perfestions into Precept brought. ** : * *





End of section 6. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 7
Page scan 14

That Casar's spirit was so long restrain'd, Amazes more than that at length it Reign'd; In this our King is most August, and Great, That Arms, and Arts do make hit Reign compleat; º And you in both may claim an ampleshare, - rour Pen in Peace equals your sword i'th marr. James Long. Upon my Worthy Kinsman Co- lonel Tuke, His Incomparable Play. Would you had not Writ ! but 'tis too late, - Against what is decreed, to Deprecate, The Fates do Limits to each thing dispense, To Poets rage, to Arms, to Eloquence; - Thus the Learn'd Greece, and the more Polish'd Rome, Had bounds like seas; Hitherto shall ye come; And hitherto our stage 3. Olympus top who has once gain’d (which dos the Heavens prop ) can sore no Higher; rour Head has brush'd the spheart, Then 'tis no wonder if you Charm our Ears. rou in Five Hours have here performed more, Than in Five Ages all our Bards before: . . . Nor tell me of another spanish Plot, unless it should to Write it beyour Lot: 'I is not the story makes the smilingfaces , , - . . . But who recites that story with your Graces : hºrite then in pity to th’ abandon'd stage, a ºv But in Another tempt your own free Rage: º “ . . . ----- irhat

End of section 7. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 8
Page scan 15

hhatt hough the serpent bite, and Fools revile, He breaks his Teeth who thinks to hurt your File, - But why would you beso Injurious to The other House 3 all our Old Plays und, 2 4ll our New ones at least For who will write z mºho can indeed, unles; it he in spight? Tou by this One have so improvº, the Trade, 44en will see none unless by you they're made; And yet jesay that you will write no more, - ** swear it too! sir William shut your Door. J. Evelyn. ~ To the Author. * : . . . . . . . . * > . . . . . . . . . . ; . . . - . . . . . - * * * * * *...* * - - s s when our Kings (Lords of the spacious Main) - A Take injust Warrs a Rich plate-Fleet of spain, The rude unshapes Ingots they reduce ' ' Into a form of Beauty, and of use; ' ' ' ', sº º On which the Conqu'rours Image now does shine; Not his whom it belong'd to in the Asiae : so in the mild contentions of the Muse, º (The marr which Peace itself loves and pesºs). so have you Home to as in Triumph trought This Cargazon of spain, with 77 easuresfraught : Y rou have not baselygotten it ºffealth, . Norby Translation borrow'd all its mealth; * . But by a powerfull spirit made it your own; * * *.*. Metall before, Money by you 'tis grown; 'Tis currant now by your adorning it. a With the fair stamp of your Piñorious hit : But

End of section 8. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 9
Page scan 16

- And spain on you shall make Reprisals then. The numerous Theatre has decreedyour Praise, - s But though me praise this Voyage of your Mind, And thongh ourselves Enrich't by it we find, we're not contented yet, because we know . . . . . . . inhat greater stores at bome within it grow ; , , w" haveseen how well you forein Oar refine; Produce the Gold of your own Noëler Mine. - The World shall then our Native Plenty view, And fetch Materials for their hit from you : They all shall watch the Travels of your Pen, - ) A. Cowley. To my Excellent Friend Col. sam. - Tuke, on his Adventures of Five Hours. - - - . º - ** Yº: 4re too happy, sir, and doubly bleft5 * , - At once to please the wiser, and the beft, - And raise the envy of those men who grieve - To see your Play do's, and is like to live; mhile their crude births, for lack of genial fire, No sooner are produced, than expire. , - - But here, good Plot, clean Language, well-weigh’d sense, Challenge applause, and make their own defence. Old Ben. for his Good Play, Illanderstood, Thought it enough to sirear, He knew 'twas good: ~ - - * - . . . . * > º - * - " - * - * * * * * ** * * - * ... . The proper judges to decide the Bayes. . . . . * * * * * * - - - - *. • * * < *, *, * r * --> , , , , , , , , --~ **- Hºt Nººp -- . . . * *** * * * *- * * . . . . . . . . . To

End of section 9. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 10
Page scan 17

To the Author of the Adventures, Tour # Gustoes all our Cooks anda, - - … &c. Perswading him to write again. Hough Darkness were the Midwife to your Plot, I ret that was clear to all who envy'd not sofair a birth 3 begot by Wit, and Art, - Great Nature's Ornaments in everypart : . mhythen shou'dyon profess to write no more z unhappy Issues make a Parent poor. . • * , , , , , , , Tou are so rich in Praise, that there will be ‘’’. More than enoughfor a great Progeny; No dish will taff wellifnot drest by you: º mhose Eagle cMuse to such a height was got That clear eyes only saw, the dull could not Till the Cloud varied; to compleather Fame At lałł shee bravely stoºpt, and kill'd her Game. Envy incites; make good your place once more, Else the windsfavour'd, and you did but sore; Thoughslander move you not, Religion may, 7..#us the Art to please your vertuous way: - For though our ºices have debauch'd the stage More Poets made like you mayflop that rage. mitethen ; forfew elsewill, what's a slight Praise, mhilst Admiration gild, your crown of Bayes 2 " . * * * Lod. Catile. tº | - * -- \ . * * - - * * - ** - . . . . . * . . . . . . . * * - * * • ‘. * To

Page scan 18

To my much Honoured Kinsman Coll. samuel Tuke, on his Adventures, &c. Hat Poet who can his clear thoughts dispense,... When Language is to strive with various sºft, whom well plac'd labours have remov’dfrom blame, Freed of Ambition, though he #and for Fame, . . . May brave Detrašion; and ntºestruples ight, º - ret equal fu.ges with respett invite: *** * * * Conscious of worth he tread; the bending #age, Daring the Censures of this curious Age; - Th’impartial Mullitude (ta do them * ) . . . . .* -- º ...º.º. Not yet concern’d in Fałion,far from Guile * . . . . mhen mov’d to joy, or Pity, heep, or smile; . . . . Ten times the Play recalºrith generau, heat, , , , , Ten times attend, and fresh Applause repeat ; * * * * * 4s Lambs new suckled leap, as Fields lºok gay. , , , , , , After sweet showers, as Bird; salutethe Day; ' ' . . . All but the Owls, and Bats, those sons of Ni ht, - That revell,hout, and brooknor Arts, nor Light. . . . . . Thu, on the banks of Hébrus Orpheusrau'd , , , , , stop the quick stream and move the rootedmond; Hºibhi, Lºsinº,” And favelins flyi 'g in the Air disarm ; -- Birds silent tº: - v -- *- : *** His Notes, which Notes (alas!) amon are drown'd, when frantick Passions, Wine, and shouts conspire Ta rend the Peet, and to break his Lyre : Art lyes oppress'd ; but why do I relate Fables 3 rou need not fear sº hard a Fate CT $ - - - - * - : - - - -- -- A - --- - - - - marian Caves resuand a ... . . . From

End of section 10. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 11
Page scan 19

From English Breasis ; these Isles (milderrate º . . . . of men produce, than grows on rocky Thrace; º * Nor let the Dutch beforward to cºmplain, º º º --. what eye it said they know the scene is spain ; º º º sonorade handsball tear your wreathed Bayes, * * * * * All Mirth with Mirth, and hit repaywithfraise. º ºvº wº. - º -- " -- . . ." t . . . . \\\, , , Chr Was :\, : ...G. . ." - - * > * º, Nº. - - - - * . * , , , •º - * * **t *... ." - - sº - - - * - - … . . . . . . * * * • * * * : * * * * - - -, * ~ * * tº rive - --- - - - -- - ~ - - - -- * , , , , , . . . . - - - - - \ -—— º - - - º º º º, *C. * * * * * To the Author upon the Adven- tures, &c. w Heywhefrientiushalftrathe laws – : Irºf writing well, and each peculiar cause whº, Lºnghage-lth herprººftºff influenº. 9 º'; a - -- - Instills herself into the ravish'd sense ; , , ... ." say 'tis an Art, not by Instruñions taught," " - But freely issuing from a brest that's fraught - mith Prudence, Honour, Nobleness. Why then Amazeth us this off-spring of your pen-f , º, * . . . .'; V. ~. 'Tis true it may do wonders, and redress º' . . . . . . Th"errors, with which the Pulpit, and the Press, ºvºs (Toth' best of Princes ruine ) here of lates º ºr .º.º. Corrupted had both Eloqaence, and states, sº wº, º All this avouching, with the general Qaires a va, . . . . I joyn my’ applause, yet can't with them admire: ' , , , , , , , Thefaculties, sir, of your noblemind. A vs tº º ºsº. - I know so well, and hº fits enshrinºd ºxº vs. º Wirtue with her attendants sº confined ºf ººº sº * * * 3 2. - - That

End of section 11. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 12
Page scan 20

º That in an unaccustom'd way I smile . . . - - - - To see by you impoverish'd ºur Isle. . . . . . . . . . Though then thirpiece be of refinedore, ºf , º, . 'Tis a small grain out of your richer store. º: That which so dazzles in this exc'lent Play The Theatre, it but a single ray . . From the rich treasure of your fancies light Darted; though efficacious, and so bright, That we shall see from thence dispell'd the might Where ignorance envelop'd had the age (Her Luminary being eclips'd the stage) so the sun chases darkness from our sphear, * - E’re in his lustrebekouthsafet'; appear. . . ; ; ; ; ; º William Joyner. - - - - - * +1 1– - sº º .* º . º . > To the Author, upon his finish'd Poem, The Adventures of Five t - -- - * - * * * Houses, &c. - º sº. “ . .º.º. º.º. . . . . Fº: this Agedies want that noble pride, Forwhich bravemenofold were dei §d: And that those persºns who are nobly born, , . . . . . . . . Virtue, which made'em sº, dº turn to scorn: , , , , , , As if that Honor were the child of Fate, . . . . . . . . And vertuous men did supererogate;. s In were compassion to this wretched age . . . . . . . Toubring heroique Vertue dm the stage 3, , , , , , , , , , Hºping her genuine Graces might entice, y \, , , , , These whom her Precepts could not turn from Vice sº

End of section 12. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 13
Page scan 21

4nd though no stranger to those antient rol; which keep the Records of departed souls; ret you not knowing amongst them tosº •'. A nobler Image, copy your own mind; *here you such charming features do discover Jºyour brave souldier, and yourfrithful Lover, The silent Circle were in asuspense, Not knowing where to wish the preference; But as from th' Elements contrariety Almighty Natureforms a harmany; so by the Magick of your Artful Muse, Toufrom your Kivals discords do produce such a delightful concord, that all those whofear'd their Fate, are pleas'd that they werefoes. In whºses rene, andsted Looks wefnd Delight, and monder did possess their mind, º sirii attentionspeaks your praises higher Than the loud Plaudits of #. upper Tire. whilst others writing raise the Vulgar cry, rours, sir, are only prais'dby Extaffe. ‘P O s T s CRIPT. On to all other writers give their due ; - Andforgive those, #. have denyldit you;. 4nd left by your reply their shameshould live, Toustillforget that which you didforgive; * Though (whilst you live) they envy your just praise, They will (when dead) jour Cypress'wreath with Bayes; Good Writers (like good Christians) never have Their #ate ºf Glory till th’ are intheir Grave. ... -- - ? MElpomene. The

Page scan 22

The First scENE is The City of s E V I L. The Prologue E mir, with a Play-B ill in his hand, - and Read (, - This Day being the 15" of December, shall be Aéted a New Play, never Play’d before, call’d The Adventure, of Five Hours. A N E W P L A Y. TH are i'the right, for I dare boldly say, The English stage ne'r had so New a Play; ‘. . . º º The Dress, the Author, and the scenes are New. . . . . . . . . This ye have seen before ye’lsay: 'tis true ; , . * * .. º But tell me, Gentlemen, who eversaw . . . . sº ... . . . . . . 4 deep Intrigue confin'd to Five Hours Law. º, such as for close Contrivance yields to none : \ . . ‘. 4 Modest Wan may praise what's not his own. . . . . . º 'Tis true, the Dress is his, which he submits To those who are, awd those who would be Wits ; Ne'r spare him Gentlemen, for to speak truth, * . He has a per’lous Čews’rer been in routh; And now grown Bald with age, Doating on Praise, He think to get a Periwig of Bays. Teach him what 'tis, ji. Discerning Age To bring his heavy Genius on the stage; ~ : Where jou have seen such Wimble hits appear, That pass'd so soon, onescarce could say th’ were here. Tet after our Discoveries of late . . . . . . . . . . . . Of their Designs, who would subvert the state; sº Tou'l wonder much, if it should prove his Lot, . . . . . . . . To take all England with a spanish Plot; . . . . . . . . . . But if through his ill Conduit, or hard Fate, , , , o … . This Forei. Plot (like that of Eighty Eight ) sº vº º sº. º. should suffer shipwrack in your Narrow seas, - - Tou’l give your Modern Poet his Writ of Ease ; For by th' Example of the King of spain, He resolves ne'r to trouble you again. * . . . . - * * \ The

End of section 13. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 14
Page scan 23

P R O * U E - T H E . Lo G / A T - He Address himself to the Pit. A’. to a dying Lamp, one drop of Oyl - This refers to P. Gives a new Blaze, and makes it live a while; the Authors so th’Aathor seeing his decaying Light, *::::..., | And therefore thinking to retire from sight, - hiº K. Washindred by a Ray from th’ upper sphere, - when his Ma- s Jaff at that time he thought Žižº 3. - jesty recom- He chanc'd to hear his Maieffy once say. mended this He lik'd this Plot: he stai’d ; and writ the Play; Plot to him. so should Obsequious subjećts catch the A4inds Of Princes, as your sea-men do the Winds. If this 4ttempt then shews more Zeal, than Light, "I may teachyon to Obey, though not to Write. - - . . . - -- He loºk H ! he is there himself. Pardon my sight, e looking up - . . and seeing the AMy Eyes were dazled with Excess of Light; - K”, starts. Evenso the sau, who all thing else displays, . . . . • He Kneels. Ishid from us ºth glory of his Rays ; He rises, Hill rou vouchsafe four Presence f rou, that were given To be our Atlas, and support our Heaven 2 - will you (Dread sir) rour Pretions Moments lose- To Grace the first Endeavours of our Muse 2 This with your Character most aptly fairs - Even Heaven it self is pleas'd with the first Fruits. f - - - - * t -- .. - - *\_* < \; DRAM- :

Page scan 24

Dramatis Personae. Porcia. - . Ladies. Camilla. Toung Ladie t - - Don Carlos. A Kind Brother to Camilla. Don Henrique, A severe Brother to Porcia. Don Antonio Pimentel. Contrahed by the Mediation º of Friends to Porcia be- - * - - • fore he saw her. Don Oétavio. secret Gallant to Porcia, but - wº - feigning to be in Love with Camilla. Flora. waiting-woman to Porcia. Ernesto. • sancho. servants to Don Antonio. - z - Diego. servant to O&avio. º sylvio. Geraldo. servants to Don Henrique. . . . Pedro. v The Corigidor, and Attendants. The scene s E V I L f

End of section 14. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 15
Page scan 25

ºsRG /sººr ººz mºr, . . . . * The First Act. THE scene DON HENRIQves ~ * T —- Enter Don Henrique, who is immediately follow'd - - º, by sylvio. tº ºf . . . . . - - … . . . . . . . . . i2. 1 , , , , , sº - . . . . . . sylvio. Ignior, Don Carlos is without. * * * Henr. Wait on him in. Enter. Carlos.io, - ºr v. ... ºf Cº y º f ; # ºv; , , , , , Car. Cozin,to me this day hath longer seem'd than usual, since’tis sofar advanc'd without our seeing one another. Hemr. Methinks so too; but you repair your stay, , By º hither opportunely now 3: ... Yº You have so often born with my Distempers, '' • . 'Tis fit that once at least you º partake - . . . . . . . ** *** - ) wº - Of



End of section 15. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 16
Page scan 26

The Adventures of Five Hours. In the ££a, an # A Heart as t Your Friend has been with the li º Tealous of the Honour of his Fami 5- - . . ly's - **g, *, - - (Yet never blemish'q}\to H ºiced. | º É.i...ºf wººd * Of my good humºur.gº. - (arº hâtereºtfig @##: For a Gentleman Rich, Beautiful, and Young. Car. You know, Don Henrique foºdivers years, rovince charg'd , . A tende: sister, by our Parents will , . . . . . . ; ( Włºś their Cares below)” . To mine committed; Of lovely Porcia, I conclude, that you Cº And to the Malice of theirenvious sex, , , , , You must confess the Confines of their Fame As to her Virtué, I have scenhºt OW still to the world than . ; and (sir) Nearness of blood deceive me , short offew In the advantages that draw Pretenders; Yet thanks to my Temper, Cozin, as well: ; ; G --- d though more º - F.) unkss up from her Childhood, to her Dangerous Age, Without the least Disturbance tothy rest: . . . .” & 3. And when with equal justice I refle&A. £ 2," On the great Modesty and Circumspection . . . w Might well have slept as undisturb’d as I. sº Henr, sir, I complain not of my sisters condućt; . . . But you know well; young Maids are so expos'd . To the Invasion of audacious men, J. C. º. 2: . . . . . . . ." . . . . fºr " Are never safe till guarded by a Husband 3.





Page scan 27

The Adventures of Fiye Hºurs. º We sing and figh One The wisdom of Relations ought to use , - . Preventions of all sorts; but dear Çarks , . . . . . . The Blemish once received, no Washis goods For slains of Honor, but th’Offenders blood. - - - Car. Y’are toosevere a Judge of point of Honor. Henr. And therefore having not longsince receiv'd. , The news, that Don Antonio Pimentel, sº nitrila 3 ºr , Is likely to be here this night from Flanders; tº c. To whom my sister by Welladas means, , , , --, (Our common Friend and Patron) is contračted; y I will not close these eyes: tillº, I have seen tº ºf Her, and my Cares, safe lodgåwithin his arms; ºr, £ar. I find your travels, Cozin, have not cur'd you. Of that iunate severity to Women, x, y, zºº, , , , , \;. to be a National reproach Untous all abr 13, thº º ents, fººt. A lif That miserablé sex . #a i. º.º.d Born onely to be honºrable Prisoners'; . . . ." . . . The more of Quality, the #: 3 ºf . . . Which Gr elty is rºy ºš. º jääurselves. ºnly ºf Whilst by Immuring thºse y ; Lºwes.,.]: y - #. ºivº is ºf: U --- - As cruel is thatóver-cautious - - - -, -, * * * : , . . . . - - - - - - * - " - - - - - * - -- . . . . By Proxy to contra: Párties unknown ... . . . To one and ther; this is ºngly fit #23rººt For soveragi Princes, whósé igh qualitis - "Will not allow of previous interviews; “They sacrifise their Loveto Publick good, * Cosing ºyingress and Boº & A custom, which as yet, never knºw... , 1,… sºn-i 3. . . lls'd between persons of a Lower rank, - . . . . . . . Without a sequel of sad Consequence: . . . . . . sir, understand me right; I speak not this 's . . . . º | - B 2 - By r

Page scan 28

The Adventures of Five Hours. By way of Prophecy; I am no stranger ~ To Don Antonios great reputation, - - , a Which I believeso just, I no way doubt Your sisters being happy in him. - Hen. Don Carlos, let us quit this Argument; I now am going to our noble friend - - And kinsman the Corigidor, to see -- . If he will honor with his Company My sisters Wedding; will you come along? . Car. Most willingly; assoon as I have brought My sister hither, and lefther with yours. . . . . . Henr. I have some business, Cozin, by the way, I'lgo before, and wait you i'th Piazza. { . Your servant, Cozin, . . . . . . ~ +...º." - ... . . . . . . . . . . . [Exit Carlos. This Kinsman º friend, and yet". . . . . Ofall men living, I must hide from him My deep resentments of his sisters scorn 5 ' ' ' ' " That cruel Maid, to wound me to the Heart, Then close her Ears against myjust complaints; But thoughas yet I cannot heal my wound, I may, by my Revenge upon my Rival Divert the Pain; and I will drive it home; - There's in Revenge a Balm, which will appease. The present .# and Time cure the disease. v Enter Porcia. . ." A- Porcia. My heart is so opprest, withfear and grief, That it must break, unless it find relief; ' ' '. The Man I love is forc'd to fliemy sight, And like a Parthian, kills me in his flight: One whom I neversaw, I must embrace, [Exit Henrique. or
Page scan 29

The Adventures of Five Hours. Or else destroy the Honour of my Race. . . . A Brothers Care, more crucl than his Hate; Obowperplex is my unhappy fate 1 - Enter Carlos and Camilla. . . . . . gar,sozin, Ithought my sisterscompany º, Would not displease you, whilst I wait upon Your Brother in a visit. . . . . . Porc. sir, you oblige me with a welcom favours ... I rathershold havefisditcharity, . Tobring a friend to her, whose cruel fate } aside. . . . Has robb'd her of her self. . . . . - Cam. Methinks,'tis pitty that a wall should make The houses two, offriends so entirely one , -- As you, and I, and our two Brothers are, . . . . Porc. If it be true, that Lovers live much more, There where they Love, than where they Breath, i'm sure No walls can sever us, w are still together. - - . . . Car. Were I not muchengag’d, I would not quit so sweeta Conversation; but, sister, , At my return, I'l wait uponyou home. . . . . . . . Porc. For this night, Cozin, pray lether be mine, I begit of you both. - - Car. You may command, we are both yours. w . . . . . . . . [Exit Carlos Port. Mydear Camilla,how I long'd to havee }: the, - - § ned. Wherefreely breathingout my Grief, I might. some mitigation from thy Pitty find; . . . . . ; “But since there's notrue Pitty without Pain;. Why should I Ease, by thy Afflićtion gain Cam. Ah Porcia!...if Compassion suffering be, And to Condole be Pain; my Destiny . . . . Willfull revenge in the same kindafford; should an 3. s.
Page scan 30

The Adventures of Five Hours: w 'to . : . . . . . . . . should I, but my unequal’d griefs relate, ºf...' . . . . ; And you, but equally participate. " : º32: … . " Porc. If yours, as hine, from Love-disaslets rise yo: O Our Fates are more alli'd than Families. - - Cam. What, to our sex, and blooming age can prove Ananguishworthy of our sighs, but Love?", " 'º Porc.”Tis true; Camilla, were your fate like mine, 2 / ! Hopeless to hold, unable to resign. º 'º' ): I º *" Čam! Let's tell our stories, then we soon shallsee; Which of us two excells in Misery. º, ºf Porc. Cozin, agreed: " " . . . . . . tº ºf Cam. Do you begin then. . . . . . . . . ºº: Portº'ou know;Camilla,best,bow generously, ; Aftºiu, How long, and how discreetly, my Ofiavio lººk...ii Hath serv'd me; and what trials of his faith. . . . . . . ** And fervout's did snake, cre I allow'dºrº is 1... sº- The least hope to sustain his noble Love.' . . . . ." … I Cozin, all this you know; ’twas in your House We had our interviews; where you were pleas'd . To suffer feign'd addresses to your self, ºr ºf To cover from mywatchful Brother's eyes," " : *. The real passion which he had for me. ". . . . . . . Cam. My memory in this needs no refreshing. . . . . Porc. And how one Evening (O that fatal hour). My Bºbther passing by Don Carlos house, With his great Friend and Confident Don Pedro sº.sº Did chance to see th' unfortunate Oñavia, f At your Balcony, chtertaining me; -- - - , , Whom not believing there, he took for you; ºn - ºn, Where mad with jealousie, his cruclimature... º.º. i* (Towhich all Moderation is unknown). . . . . . . . . " - - - - - • * Resolves to stamp aliyour Neglects of him, . . . . . In’s suppos'd Rival poor Octavio's heart; . . . . . . . . - - - tº i is ºn ºl. He
Page scan 31

. The Adventures of Five Hous, !, He, and his Friend both draw, Qāavio . . . . . . .” ". Retires, thcy assault him, who in's own defence Does kill Don Pedro, and is forc'dig flie. * ~ * : * ~ * My Brother cruclly pursues him still,... . . . . . . . . . . . With suchinsatiate thirst after rivenge, . . . . s That nothing but Qāavio's blood can Quench; , , - Yet covering still his Rage and Jealousie, . . . . . With the resentment of Dan Pedra's death. . . . . . . . . Cam. Is this the sum of your sad story, Porcia . . . " Is this all? . . . . . --- * . . . . Por. No, no, Camilla, 'tis the Prologue onely, The Tragedy does follow;ithis Tyrant, This cruel Brother, toth'Impetuous Laws . . . . " Of whose Tuition, our deceased.Parents . . . . . * My Person and my Fortune have condemn'd, - * in his unjust suspicion reflies grown," -- . (Which he to palliate Vice with Virtues name, - Does sense of Honor call) takes an Allarm , , . . . . And starts at every shadow ; as if reproach . . . . Attended all the ačtions of a sister, -- - - - | Thoughne’rso Circumspe&; and uses me, As if the Honor of our Family; . - " - Were over-thrown for ever, should my Eyes,” Or Judgment, bebut the least part allow'd * : . . . - In making choice of him should bemy Husband. . . . º). Thereforetofrustrate all my hopes at once, He has already marriºd me by Proxies - - Toone in Flanders, whom I never saw , , Who is this very night expested here. , Cam, Issuch a rigour possible, dear Porcia & Por. Was ever Miserie like mine, Camilla 3 : - - - - - - - Heightned to such extremes, past all relicf: If I acquaint my Brother with my Love -- . . . . fºll T' Oštavio
Page scan 32

The Adventures of Five Hours. . T'OHavio, the man he most does Hate, I must expect the worst cffects offury; If I endeavour to Forget Oğavio, … Even that attempt renews hismemory, And fresh Disquiet gives; If I refuse To marry, I am lost; If I obey, I cast Oğavio and myself away. Two such Extremes of ill, noChoice admit, Each seems the Worst; on which Rock shall I split 2 since if I marry, I cannot survive 3 *. And not to marry; were to die alive. Cam. Your story (I confess) is strangely noving; Yet if you could my Fortuneweighwith yours, In scales of equal sensibility, You would not change your sufferings, for mine. Por. What can there be in Nature more afflićting, Thana Divorce from th’Object of our Love , * - - - For ever, to cmbrace the thingwe Hate ; - Cam. Have you not known that Obječtofyour Love? And entertain'd the Person you estcem? Have you not heard, and answered to his sighs? . . . . Has he not born his Partinallyour Cares tº - Do not you live, and reign within his heart tº . Por. I doubt no more his Faith, than my hard Fate.” “. Cam. But tell me, dearest Porcia, if I love . . . . " ": One, I ne'r shall sce, and suffer as much" " " ... º.º. Without the Means of e'r cyprefing it, … . . . . . . . . As what I suffer is above expression; : . . . . If all my sighs wander in fleeting Air , , , Andne’rcan reach his cars for whom they'rd form'd; If all my Passion, all my killing Cares, º, - - Must be for ever to their Cause unknown; If that their weight must sink me to my Grave; \ Without

End of section 16. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 17
Page scan 33

Off s - "st -- ºr " - . - - " whexaventureof Five Hoº * Without one Groan that he can ever hear, /.º. Or the least hope, that Isshoulder obtain fl. W." tº ºf By Pitty Ease ; or Curé by his Disdain: , ... in gºt If this the state of my Misfortunebe, , ; ; ; *... . . A say, dearest Porca, do you envie me?” . . . . . . . . () Por. What over-cruel Laws ofJDécency ºf Leistoriºt. Have struck you dumb? have you misplacid your Love, #! Oh sucha subječ, a you dare not own tº º Cam, No, the Cause is worthy of the Effect ; , . . . And though I had no Passion for his Person, ºn of tº ing; I were ungrateful if should not give () tº tº y The first place in my Heart to such high Merit. ** . . . . .'' Por. If he has been so Generous, to deserve . . . . . . . . Your Love, why are notyouso Just, tolet º: s - ; : - - - - a . . . .. 5 * , . . . ; W . . . - in Himknow it? . . . . . . . . * - 3, Cam. Tis impossible; "Ah! that dismalwordº ºi Does full state the Difference of our Fortunes: , , . . . . Lost You, in your first Adventure have beencroft, is tº " . But I, before I can set outam lost, ºl... . . Por. Pray make me comprehend this Mystery. ºn 5 Cam.”fist open my wounds afresh, dear Portia, , , , But You must be obey'd--------- . . . [Afteratitlerºs, The Conde de Omniate being sent ºf ºººº... ;- is, Embassadour unto the 'Emperour; … tº ºvº º Vehaving th’honor to benear ally dº º'º To him, by his Lady, (who likewise went tº . . That Journey with her Husband) my Brother . . . Was desir’d by her to make that Voiage; ' ' ' '.' . . . Whose tendernessforme, not sufferinghim ( " . d; To let me staybehind, I wasingag'd ; ºf G is And treated by th' Ambassadress, my Cozin, With more respećt than 1 could ever merit.” Por. she's a Lady, fam'd for great Civility. ... Wilsº ' ' ' ". . . G - Cam, WVe . - *-*. --~~~~ --~~~~ ~~ *-i- 2
Page scan 34

The Adventures of Five Hours. Cam.We had not pass'd much time i'th Emp'ror's Corut, When my dear Brother unexpectedly, .. By urgent business, was call'd back to sevil; And in our return (too near a Garison Ofth Enemies) our Convoy was surpriz'd, And routed by a Party of their Horse. Por. Camilla, you begin to raise my fears. - Cam. We Prisoners made, were hurri'd streight away . To their Quarters, where my malicious Fate - - Made me appear too pleasing to the Eyes Of their Commander ; who at first approach Pretends to Parly in a Lovers style, . . . Protesting that my Face had chang'd our Fortunes, And him my Captive made: But findingsoon How little he advanc'd in his Design By Flattery, and his feign'd submission 3 He shifts his Person, callsme his Prisoner, And swears my Virgin-Treasure was his Prize; And yet protests he had much rather owe it , k Tomy Indulgence, than his own Good Fortune; . . And so through storms and Calms, the Villain still A Pursues his Course to his accursed End; - But finding me inflexible to Threats As well as Fawnings, he resolves to use . . The last, and uncontroled Argument . . . . , , , Of Impious Mcn in Power, Force. . . . . . : … Por. Ahpoor Camilla 1 tell me , where was then . . . Your Brother, at a time of such distress? . , Cam. My Brother he, alas, was long before . . . . . Born away from me, in the first lncounter; . . . . ." Where having certainly behav'd himself As did become his Nation and his Name, Remain'd fore wounded in another House, - - - * * * * - -- . . . . . - - • * * º, Por. Pry- - — , - --- . . A - --~/ - --- ---- - - º - ---- º--- . . - - -
Page scan 35

|f|, The Adventures of Five Hours. 's (m tawi. .P. Pistols go Por. Pr’ythee make hase to free me from this fright. i Cam. The Brute approaches, and by Violence” º, . Endeavours to accomplish his intent; 7. " I Heaveh invoke, and strong Resistance make, But with uncºual force, though Ragesuppli’d Those spirits, which my Fear had put to flight; . . . . Breathless at length with crying out, and striving, ... . .” I spi’d a Dagger by the Villain's side, . . . . . . . . . . . Whichsnatching boldly out, as my last refuge, . . With his own Arms] wound the savage Beast; He, at the stroke, u-seas'd me, and gave back 3. . . . . . (“so Guilt produces Cowardice) then I . . . The Dagger pointing to my breast, crid out , -Villain, keep off, for if thou dostperfist, "... º I'l be myself both sacrifise and Priests." - I boldly now defie thy Lust, and Hate; ". . . . . . . “she that dares Choose to die, hºck, Fate. º: Drums and Trumpets sound, . . . , andºff: To Arms , , , , "… . . . To Arms: The Lustful satyr flies; I stands, . . . ." Fix'd with amazement to the Marble floor, "... ". Holding my Guardian Dagger up aloft, ºf . As if the Ravisher had threatned still. - Por. Ifancy thee, Camilla, in that brave posture • Like a noble statue, which I remember ºr tº To have seen, of the inraged funa, I . . . . . wVºihnderbolt. . . . . Cam, Freed from this Fright, my spirits flow so fast To the forsaken Chanels of my Heart,. . . . . . . . . . . That those who by their orderly access . . . . . . . . Would have supported life, by Throngs oppress. . . . . O're-charg’d with Joy, I fell into a swoon; And what was done in this Parenthesis w C2 is / : * *

End of section 17. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 18
Page scan 36

--- * -- ---Yº ºn • * * ... .Yºu', The Adventures of Five Hours. Is not within the Circle of my Knowledge, . . . . . . Por, Yº have rais'd me to a flighty Expc&ation; ' ' . VVill the Adventure answer it, Camilº º 'º' Cam. At my return to life, op'ning my eyes, Think, dearest Porcia, how I was astonish'd, º' - To find there kneeling by myside, a Man, º, . . . Of a most noble Form, whábowing to me; * ºf Asadam, (says he) y'are welcome to the world 3. ‘’’ ‘’’ Pardon, I pray, the Boldness of a stranger, That humbly sues tyoutoContinue in it; , ; , , , Or if You needs will Leave us, stay at least. tº Till I shall have Reveng'd your wrongs, and thesiº I'l wait upon you to the otherworld, . . . " ``' For You with-drawn; this willa Désertseem, : " And Life a Torment. is: º: * . . . . . . & º ; : Por. High gallantry; Corin, for a first Address. ºlod i Cam, "swasso surpriving, that my Confusion º!, tº Check'd my Reply; but I suppose my Looks. * 'tºº Didspeak the grateful Language of my Heart; º: For I .#. of; enlighten º' * : zºº, c. - His manly Face; but, Ofit soon was elowāgā, "tº Byfresh Åi.º.º. soldiers cry;” tº - . Where's Antonio, th’Enemy is rallid, º' And coming on to give a second Charge; . . . . . . . He started up, and with a Mcen, that mark dºº-ºº! sº The Conflić'twixt his Honor and his Love; tºº Madam, (says he) the soul was never yet sº ... º With such Convulsion from the Body torn; * : * > . . As I from you; buriefits. Herbesºid, sº ... That Don Antonio Pimentel was seemiºs.' "... º º To Follow in Dangers those he ought to Lead; ' " ' " And thus the Vanquish'd, Conqueror Disappear'd , . Leaving that Image stamp'd upon my Heart, " . Tc - - - - - O N
Page scan 37

The Adventºes of Five Hours.AY To which I all the joys mºst sacrifice - - Ofthe poor remnastófmy wretched Life; I - - - If properly to live I mayºbé saidyº ºr 3. she puts her | Whchasmy hopes of sceighináre dead.ift:%;"f*. Por. What said you was his name,éamilla tº }º . º - | Cam. Don Antonio Pimentel, It lºo, .#4 ºf 514 ! Tor. O Heavésis.} º; Izºd ºf , sº - liftºn II.x isºtºlib Lié.1% whº .º. . . . ." Enter Henrique. . . .” - sº tº . , tº - Hen. I’m pleas'd to find º: of your Husband. - Cam. What's that I heatºharshusband [Aside, - Hen. Have you the Letter ready, Idesir'd you - To write to him risenda servant with it,” “º - To meet him on the way;'twill shew Respect. Porc. You know my Qbediende, Brother; ºis; 2.3%. sº . Hen.'Tis well, sister. : Wºrridos Cuoibo º ºxi's lists on 2. ... * * * ... i2.sillºts 2'rofts!," Iyo Y . Enter sylvio. . . ." Logº sº, sº sylv, sir, herº's a servant of Dow Antonio, sº sº. ~ Newly-alighted at the Gate; be's come ovis wo: ºl 'wº Post from his Mastery chargºdiwablettºs fºr You...? ston's Hen. Youndrcould bringinea more welcom News4 xi, Call him in, sylvia ; sister, you may ºf .3.1: … .o. noviº With-draw, and take this time to ask your Cozing:0; Lºº How she likesmy Choice of youtsºlºddilig-Cleathes... Por. My Wedding Gloaghestākhººmisèrable Maid tº The Heathen so to their Reigºd Deities. Eid II . . . Adorn'd the Vićtims they did sacrifice, º is . 1, gºiti i o żº sig Exeunt Percia'éº Camilla, C .e.:3:2 ... isoftw.61 ºil, gº of , gºinter|Ernesto and sylvić.if yº; I sº Ern, signior, Dom Antonio'kisses your hands, And sends me to present this Letter to you. . . . . . **** - He *-

Page scan 38

The Adventures of Five Hours. N. This night, as I expeºted..., 1. And Beautie. [ He gives a Letter to Don Henrique. Don Henrique opens it, and/reming to have , - - - - };. i i , ; , , , , , Hen. I'm glad you left him well; but yet methinks, He writes doubtfully of his being here . - Ern. His Letter, Isuppose, declares his purpose. . ." Henr. I’lanswer’t, and dispatch you presently. - In the mean while go make him welcom, sylvio. ...! is tº 5 Exeunt sylvio and Ernesto at one door, * hand Henrique at the other. A / .…. I , ºf 51..…. . . . * … ." nºw bºil, : ; **'. . . - Enter sylvio, Ernesto, Geraldo, Pedro, with some Cups of Chocolate. . . . . . . . sylv. Meethinks, Camerade, a soop of Chocolate Is not amiss after a tedious Journcy 3.1 : . . . . . . . . . . Your Master's Health.sir. . . [He drinks. Ern. I'ldoyou reason, sir.’ ” “ - sylv. Prayhow longist, Brother, since you left spain Ern. "Tis now five years, and upward, since I went. . . From seuil, with my Master, into Flanders , lyi ººt º' The King's Fencing-school; whereall his subjects, ... . Given to Fighting, are taught the use of Arms, in And notably kept in breath. - i º sylv. Your Master, Iamsure, has got the Fame. º To be aperiousman in that rough Trade...º.º. Ern. He's a brave soldier, Envy must confess it. Pedr. It seems so isfaith, since meerly by the force Of his great Reputation, he can take our Bright YoungMistris so, without a siege. Ern. I hope she'lbe Reveng'd on him ere long, And take him too, by the force of her Wit, - Pedr. - -
Page scan 39

The Adventures of Five Hours. Pedr. shas more thana Child's Portion, sir, of both, I dare assure you. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ." º, sylv. But, pr’ythce, Brother, instrućt me a little, … Tell me, what kind of Country is this Holland, That's so much talk'dof, and somuch foughtfor. . . . Ern. Why, Friend, 'tis a huge ship at Anchor, fraught Withasort of Creatures, made up of Turf, ºn tº And Butter. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Pedr. I pray, sir, what do they drinkin that Country? 'Tis said, there's neither Fountains there, Nor Vincs. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . , , , , , , Ern. This is the Butler sure by his apt question, [Aftd. Fricnd, they drink there a certain muddy Liquor, , , Made of that Grain with which you feed your Mules. . Pedr. What?Barley?can that] .. quench their thirst: Ern. You'd scarce believe it i. dyou but seen a How oft they drink. ..., zºº a zºº (Camerade, Pedr. But, me-thinks, that should make them drunk, Ern. Indeed most strangers do thinkso, butthey 3.” believe it not because they're so, Osteil. * -- ...º.º. tº Ger. A Nationsure of Walking Tuns; the World Has not the like. . . . . . . . . . . . . Ern, Pardon me, Friend, there is but a great Ditch Betwixt them and such another Nation; - If these Good-fellows would but Joyn, and drink That drie, ifaith they might shake hands. F . Prythce, Fricnd, canthºse Dutch Harraccios 1ght? ºr * ~ "... º.º. . . " º * * , #. They can doeven as well, for they can Pay Those that can fight... . . . . . . . . . . . . . sylv. But where, I pr’ythec, do they get their Money : Ern, Oh, Friend, they have a Thriving Mystery; . - ºu They *
Page scan 40

The Mºntereof Fººhoº. They'GHeat their Neighbouring Princes of their Trade, And then they Buy their subjećts for their sqldiet; ºf sylv.Méthinksáàr Athies shotsdbeat these,Dull-Fālows Out of the World.” tº º 'º'; … ºr sºrt ºf | Ern. These pulsfellows will sooner beatpur Armies Out of their-Coutitry; Why, Friend, ready Mouyº, Will do much jº. fºcºmº ºf Than a Ready Wit, I dare assure you. . . ." Mºs º Ger:Whata Göäsname could come into the Heads . Of this People, to make thern Rebell ?” -: * ~ * ~, º sº -: * , ººlºº gº Burwhita Devil made the Noblemen -- * * -- . . - - - - - - - - - - - Rebel? * * * *. 3. J . . ... . . . . . . . . . ... . . . . . , Ern, why that whichhlade the Devil himselfRebel, Ambition. 7". ;:3. !. He zºº is ºf … º. º i J º .*, * * - . sylv. This is a pleasant Fellow ; , sº tº "[Affle. I find that you soldiersdonot want Wit. `sº t * G º º, , , entlemen, your Company's very º -- hº that requires Dispat à. - - - - " …" º * → Pedr. Willyounot mendyour Draught before you go? Ern. I thank you, sir, I have done very well.” “” . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ;--> - - - - - - - . . . . . . [#nt. ºz ºr as ºf tº ºn. Hº"? - . . . . : : . º * -- - - - - - - - ... " T.; - . . . . - * , .* 1: ...," sº ºwn ºr . . . . Cº-ºº! i. i* ºr ºf 3.7 ...! Enter Camilla, Porcia, Flora, , \ -, *, * ~ * : * - - - - - - * c.. " * - .* º º --- ... - Por. Waser Misfortunelketomic, camil, ". Cam, Wase'r Disaster, Porcia, like to minº, rº for. That I must neversee oilvio more...º.º. Cam. That I again must Dom Antoniosce, '... *** - - - . . Never to see him Mine. . . . . . . " º * Por, I, to bemarri'd to the Man I Hate, . . . . . * : * ~ * * ºlfax f. i. I
Page scan 41

The Adventures of Five Hours. Cam. And I, to have the Man I Love, torn from me. Por. I am, by Robbing of my Friend, undone. Cam, And I (alas) by Yielding, ruine both. - Por, Ye Powers, who these intangledfortunes give, Instructus how to Die, or how to Live. . . [she weeps. Cam. Cozin, when we should Aét, then to Complain, Is Childishly to beat the Air in vain. - Thesedescants on Our Griefs do but Perplex, Let's seek the Remedy; You know, our sex This Honor bears from Men, in Exigents Of Love, never to want Expedients. Por. You have awaken'd me, give me your Veil, - Quickly, my Dearest, quickly; and You, Flora, * * Run and see if my Brother be setled ; off Camil- To the Dispatching of Antonio's Man. } ºriº, ºf . . . . . . . . . . . . . . [Exit Flora. Cam. What mean you, Porcia 2 . . . . . . . Por. If once my Brother beset downto write, ºf I may securely reckon one hour mine; ; , i.e. A 2 º His Wits are onely in his Choler quick, º f : . . . . ." And his Hand ready in Revenge 3, he's so . . . Extravagantly |. he distrusts . . . . . . - The Meaning of his own ill-chosen Words, And so at length can hardly fixon any. , º, . . . . . . This Time I will make use of to go see . . . . . … is t - Offavia, and let him know that the last Term Of allour Hopes is ready to Expire , , - unless his VVit, his Courage, and his Love, , , . . . some quick Expedient find for our Relief. . . . . (him?..." cam. Why, How, and VVhere d'you hope to speak with . Por. In his own House, where he does lic conceal’d, "Tis not far off, and I will venture thither. •. Cam, Know you the way 3. - -> . . . . D Par. Not
Page scan 42

The Adventures of Five Hours. Por. Not very well, but Flora's a good Guide. 2 . . . . . . Enter Flora haslily. . . . . . . Flo. O Madam : he's coming already. Por. Ah spiteful Destiny let us retire, - Cozin, into my Chamber. - * 2: - s Exeunt Porcia and Camilla, Enter Henrique and Ernesto. Henr.lf you desire to speak withher, you may. Ern. I should be very glad to tell my Master . . . . . That I have had th’Honour to see his Bride. ' ' ' ... Henr. Where's your Lady, Flora . . . . . . Flor. she's in her Chamber, signior. Henr. Tell her, Antonio's servant does desire . . . . . . . To do his Duty to her, ere he goes. [Exit Flora. Friend, you will find her there, without a Veil, . . . . In her Home Dress, but you are privileg'd ..., For this free Access, by your Relation. ºr º' ºr Whilst you wait on her, I'lgo end my Letter, ºf ºf - - [Exit Henrique." ' - Enter Camilla, Porcia, and Flora. Por.If thou lov'st me get him quickly away, ºsbegº, Flora Beforemy Brother come, and give him º: a Ecitºr. . . - Ernesto addresses himself to Camilla, - seeing her without a Veil. . . . Ern, Madam, I have been bold to beg the Honor. Of seeing you, to make myself more welcome … sº To my Lord, at my return. ". . . - - - -- Por. A rare Mistake, further it, dear Camilla. [Aftde. . Who knows what Goodthis Error may produce Cam, Friend, in what state left you your Lord and mine? & - - - - Erm. As * - < - - - -- ~ -- - -
Page scan 43

- © - - * - The Adventures of Five Hours. Ern. As happy as the Hopes of being Yours - oftº: ; Cam. I would the Malict were ascasily deceiv'd. [Affae. l pray present my Humble service to him: . . . . . Flora, give him the Letter ; Farcwel, . . . . [Exeunt Camilla, Porcia, and Flora. Ern, Now by my Life, she is a lovely Lady; . . . . . - My Master will be ravish'd with her Form; . . . . . I hope the Bargain, which her Brother made, By th’ º: Wellada's Power , . . . . . (Though founded onely in Interest) may prove As happy a Marriage, as any other . . . . Madeafter th’Old fashion, chiefly for Love; And that sorare a Beauty may have power Tobring him back to his right Wits again - From his wildl{avings on an unknown Dame, . . . Whomas he fancies (once upon a time) . He recover'd from a Trance, that is, . . . . . From a sound sleep, to make him Dreamc'rsince. . . . . l'I hastento him with this pleasing news. [Exit Ernesto. *- ~ s : i , is . . . . . . . * * Enter Camilla, Porcia, Flora. . . . ." . . . Cam. My sº could hardly hinder me . . . . From laughing at the Formal Fools mistake; But tellne, did not present your Pers'nage : *- With assurance? the way for both to thrive, . . . . . . Is to makemeyour Representative. . . . . . [smiling. . Por. Most willingly, and I am confident, v_ ) When you, your Charms shall to his heart apply, Youallyour Rivals safely may defie. . . . . . . . . . . Cam. I wish I could be vainenough to hope it. '''''' But, Cozin, my Despairs are so Extreme, . . . I can't be flatter'd, though but in a Dream. . > , ' * - D 2 Flo. As dam - - w
Page scan 44

The Adventures of Five Hours. | - Flo, Madam, do we go, or what a your solve on Por. I must resolve, I see, yet know not what. " Cam. Cozin, take heed, I am afraid you venture" . . . Too much, your Brother cannot tarry long; And, if returning, he should find you missing------- Por, Yºhave reason, the opportunity is lost, What is't a Clock, Flora 2. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Flo. I think near Eight, for the Clock struck seven, Just as Camilla enter'd the Chamber. -, . . . . Por. Quick then, Flora,fetchyour Veil, you shall carry My Tablets to OHavia, there he'l find " " . . . . . The Hour and Place where I would have him meet. ºº - . . . . . . . . . . . . -[Exit Flora. Cam."Tis well resolv’d; but where doyou design Your Meeting . - . . . . . . . . Por. In the Remotest part of all the Garden, " . . . . . Which answers (as you know) to my apartment; And Flora has the Key of the Back-door. . . . . Cam. As the Case stands, you choose the fittest placc. . . . - . . . [Flora returns Weird. ‘Por. Cozin, Ibeg your patience whilst I write. Cam. You,Flora,by this Accident may chance; Flora write, To sce your faithful Lover Diego. in her. Tables Flo. He is a faithful Lover of himself, . . . is Without a Rival, Madam. . . . . sºliº º Cam. Damsel, your Words and Thoughts do not agree; For could we see his Image in your Heart, - --- , , … [..." . 'Twould be a faircr far, than cre his Glass RC fle&ted. - . . . . . . . . . Flo. Madam, I am not yet so very Old, tº ºf . That I should Dote. - ** * * * Cam, Noryct so very Young, but you may Love. . . . Dotage and Love are Cozin-germans, Flora. - ~ Flor. Yes
Page scan 45

The Adventures of Five Howry: Flo.Yes, when we Love, andare not lov’d againy if f For else, I think, they're not soncarakin. ºf . ; º Cam. I've touch'd a Nettle,and have stung myself.[Aside. -- as, 42.... c. 12.4 tº C Porcia?ives Flora the ". ..º.º. should I not play my part, f were to blame,” sº since iº...'...}º 2Madam, has Oğavio the other Key” “. . . ºf º Belonging to the Tablets. º 'º º 'º fººt Por: Yes, yes, I praymake haste. . . . [Exit Flora. Let usretire, Camilia, a little Rest, 19 silº 'º- And Mcditation, may new aids suggest. - - - , -º- ºf . . . . . . . . . ; **, * * * . . . - - - - * *~ - - - - - * , N. A.C.T. . ; : ºil ºr ... ºo ::= [ . .'; 'prº tº Y. & *- * : ... : THE sCENE, ºn . . . . . . . . . - - - J.'il tº - * 2°. " – ; *... . . . . . . " : - The City of s E VI. L. A f. .2” Mº 23rºfit ºf T. Enter Don-Antonio and sanchoin Riding-gloathes.) - * * * . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . *Q}r, we are arriv'd in very goodtime...º.º. . . . ii A \- I did not thinkit would have been so soon, ºn 4 O By an hour at least, but Lovers ride apace. ºf , 9 ‘Why smile you, sáncho º' . . . . sº -- 2 : sam. Faith at the Novelty of your Amours, . Tofall in love with one,you scarcely saw, ºr tº y And marry one, you Neversaw; 'tis pretty: ºo's But we póor Mórtals have another Method. ºf 4n. Y'are very pleasant; this, sancho, is the place,” VVhere I chargd Ernesio to expect me, . . . . . . . WHOm * º
Page scan 46

The Adventures of Fiye Hours. VVhom Isent before to my Brother-in-Law; | But with this Order, not to let him know, tº | -that intended to arrive this Evening; ‘tº surprizes in Love-meetings render Men . . . More welcome, and have more of Gallantry. . . . . sam. since youáre here, sir, Carlier than you thought; - vviº: go shift º:* º And be back here, before Ernesto come; . . . . . . . . . . . Howe're,'tis better, that he wait for you, º, . . . ] Than you for him i'th open street. . . . . . . . . : Am.' Tis wellthoughton; come, let's to the Post-house 1 - jº º sº tº ºr sº [Exeau, r . .312. Enter Don Oćtavio, and Diego. . . . . . oă, Come, Die 'tissipeto quitour Lurking: les - And to iº ºrrºr.” gło, 5 Die. Of what, sir 2 Bats, or Owls, now the sun's set? Call you this making of Love 2 me-thinks,’tis More like making of VVar; marching all night ... -- *:::::::::::::::::::"", . The Enemies Quarters. * - - \ . Oğ.VWhy would's not thouventure as much for Flora : ... Die. No in good faith; i shall venture enough - Ife'r I Marry her; Il run no hazard, is . . . . . . . . . (By my good-will) before-hand. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . OH. That's from your Fear, not Prudence, Diego. * * vº Die. sir, you may call it what you please, but I | | Dareboldly say, there lives not in the world, | A more Valiant Man, than I, whilst Danger . . . . . 1)oes keep its Distance; but when sawcily ºf ... sº. It presses on, then (I confess)'tis true,' ' ' ". . . . . . . . I have accrtain Tenderness for Life, . . . . . . That checks my Ardor, and cnclines my Prudence º, W. . . . . . . Timely
Page scan 47

The Adventure of Five Hours, º, Timely to withdraw. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . OH. Your style is wondrous civil to your self; ; ; ; ; ; How you soften that harsh word, call'd Cowardice; sº I But the Danger is not always evident, º, . . . . . . . WWhen you are peas'd, my Friend, to Run away. … Die, t may be so, sir, HQt to Vulgar eyes; f.º.o But I have such a peircing sight, that canº, ºn 2 Discover Perils cut of others. Ken; , , , , , , … . . . . . WWhich, they not seeing soon enoughto shun, Are forc'dt'Encounter; and then their strugling ºf y. Is, by th'unwarie world, taken for Courage, . . . . . . Oš. You have more Light, Diego, I see, than Heat; º; But I’lallow your VVit and Honesty . . . . . . . . . To come to Composition for your want . . Of Courage; though it be a Quality, Gº tº , , , , , I may have use of; but we lose our time."; ºr nº WVas ever Lover's Fate so rude as mine?: , ; ; 3 - 1 ---> --> Condemn'd to Darkness, forc'd to hºmy Head, º - - / Aswell as Love? and to domea spight, L. g . - Fortune has Contradićtions reconcil'd, cºdex I am at once a Prisoner, and Exil'd, ºr ; c. sº...o - Enter Antonio and sancho. ". Ant, Mc-thinks, Erneffo should not tarry long, tºº. - lfnot already come 3 sancho, how call you …. I ºf , The street there just before us? where you see (, , º, - Yon Gentleman with his Cloak o're his face 3', s' 1 have quite lost the memory of this place. . . . . . . . . . sam. I am as much toseck, as you; sir. … tº . … 4nt. Let us go to him, sancho, and enquire; i. A He has a notable good Meen; me-thinks, ". . . . . . Ine’rsaw an Air more like Ośavio's. - Oğ, unless my eyes do very much deceive me, . 2 : 'Tis
Page scan 48

The Adventures of Five Hours. 'Tis Don Antonio ; if it be he, Diego, – - - There is no danger in his knowing us; º # sill i. He ever was my faithful friend; 'Tis he. 3: fºom b.fore his Ant. You injure me, Ottavio, to be solong Aknowing one, who is so intirely yours. - Oä. Your presence here, noble Antonio, was . sounexpºacă, that shariyārā "fineyami.ac. Believe my eyes; VVhen game you to this Town Ant. I am just now arriv'd. Oğ, I joy to see you here, but should have thought #. to have heard of you at Court, - - Pursuing there the Recompences due ºr . . . . . . . To your transcendent Merit. . . . . . . . . . . . Ant. That is no place for men of my Moralitie. ~ I have been taught, Qātavio, to Deserve , . . . . . . . J. But not to seek Reward; that does prophane ºf ºf The Dignity of Virtue; if Princes . . . . . . . tº ºvº For their own Interests will not advance. . . . . . . . Deserving subjećts, they must raise Themselves : . . . . . By a brave Contempt offortune, sº sº, . . . tº Oä. I'm glad to find in you some seeds yet left to gº ºne Of th’Antient Virtue; may they Fruit produce - Fit to Illustrate;and Instrućt the Age. - - Let me once more embrace you, sir, Welcome, .....'. Brave Leader. sº sº. º. º.º. ...r.o. º. 2:04. Ant. Oh, you must spare your servants; sir. . . . . o. Qā. He has not liv'di'th reach of publick Fame, Who has not heard your noble Character; º; “ This is my house, be pleas'd; sir, to goin, i r ºf . And make it yours; though truly at the present :: * ~ * I am in a very ill condition ºf . . . . . . . . . . . . . . ." To receive the Honor offucha Guest; ºr Having by an unlucky accident, * . Been -- 2. - - -

End of section 18. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 19
Page scan 49

... -- *** -\ ... . . . . The Adventures of Five Hours. Been forc'd of late to keep myself conceal’d. . . . . Ant. I humbly thank you, sir, but cannot yet : Receive that favour, for I here must stay . . . . Expecting the Return of one, ... " . . . . . . . Before to town to my Brother-in-Law. Oś. Have you a Brother-in-law in sevil? . You surprize me much. " . . . . . . . . . . . . An. It is most true, Ottavio, I come hither - A Marri'd man, as far as friends can make me. - OH. since it imports you not to miss your servant, Let us slay here without, untill he come; ". - And then go in, and rest yourself a while. , - > But how go our publick Affairs in Flanders : * . . Amt. I left our Armies in a better state, Than formerly. . . . . . . - OH. And our brave Vellada (I suppose) in great Reputation. - - - - Ant. The Honor of our Country, and the Terror Ofothers; Fortune consulted Reason, When she bestow'd such Favours upon him. - OH. They say he did Wonders at the Relief Of juliers. . . . Ant. It was indeed a famous Aëtion. Ośī. You'l much oblige me, if whilst you expect Your servant here, I might learn from your self some few particulars of your own Aćtions; - Fame speaks Loudly of them, but not Distinétly. Ant." Fame, like Water, bears up the Lighter things, “And lets the Weighty sink; I am notus'd To speak in the First person ; but if needs You'l have a story to É up the time, Tl tell you an Adventure of mine own, > * , Where you'l find Love so ignia with Arms, - That \

Page scan 50

The Adventures of Five Hours. That (I am confident) twill raise your wonder, . How being prepossess'd with such a Passion, I should (upon Prudential motives onely) . . . " Beingag'd (as now you find me) to Marry A Lady whom I never saw. . . . . . Ośī. The Person, and the subjećt, sir, do challenge My best attention. . . . . . . . . Ant. The following Evening to that glorious Day; . . . . . . . . . . . [After a littlepause. Wherein our great Wellada gain'd such Fame, . - - - Against the cautelous Nassam ; some Horse : Were sent from th’Armie, under my command To cover the Limbourg Frontiers, expos'd To th’Enemies Inroads 5 scarce setled there , , I receiv'd intelligence, that a Party . . . ! . Of theirs (about two hundred Horse) were come That very Evening to a neighbouring Village, Intending there to lodge; I instantly Cause sound to Horse, and march to their surprize so luckilie, that by the break of day . . . . . Their Quarters were on fire. . . . . . . Oğ. You had been taught, sir, by our wise General, That Diligence in Execution is * Even above Fortune, Mistris of success. Ant. They made but faint resistance; some were slain, some perish’d in the flames, others escap'd, Giving th' Alarm in Quarters more remote To their Companions drown'd in sleep and Wine; Who, at the Out-cry, and the Trumpets sound, Me-thinks I fancie starting from their Beds, . . . . As pale and wan, as from their Dormitories Those the last Trump shall rouze; differing in this, That they awake to Live, but these to Die. Qš. How unsafe it is to be secure! Aut.Finding —------------- _ ~
Page scan 51

The Adventures of Five Hours. - That Body, which, though Dead , scarce Mor Ant. Finding no more resistance, I made hastel. - To a lofty structure, which I conceiv'd, , , , º, . . . Tobeth likeliest Quarterfor their Chiefs . . . . . Led thither by desire to rescue both; ºf Him, from the soldier's rage; That, from the Fire. - Oä. A care most worthy of a gallant Leader. . . . . Amt. But think, Qāavio, bºws wassurpriz'd, / ; * . - - When, on the floor of a Pavillion, a gº. ...O. ºf Belonging to the Garden of that House, sº to I found a Woman of a Matchless Form, - - - Extended all along. . . . . . . . . a º . “ ºr ; ; ; , off. I easily can divine how such a Heart, , , º, . As harbours in the brave Antonio's breast, tº a May suffer at so sad a spectacle, Ant. At the first sight I didbelieveher Dead s Yet, in that stateso Awful sheappear'd, º º, That I approach'd her with as much Respect 3: . . . . . . . As if the soul had animated still ºf ºººººº, tº alseem’d, But as the sun from our Horizon gone, , . . . . . . . . . His Beams do leave a Tinóture on the skies; . . .I crº Which shews it was not long since he withdrew; ...) so in her lovely face there still appear'd in . . . … ::: º, some scatter'd streaks of those Vermillion Beams 3. i. Whichus’d tirradiate that bright Firmament.... sº, Thus did I find that distress'd Miracle, fºliº, sº Able to Wounda Heart, as ifialive:, . . . . . . . . . . Uncapable to Cure it, as if dead. . . . . . . . . . . . Oğ. I no more doubt your Pitty, than your Wouder. Ant My Admiration did suspend my Aid, `. Till Pasfion join'd to Pitty, made me bold; tº . I kneel'd, and took her in my arms, tº bowd º Her body gently forward; with which motion, .. - - - E 2 A sigh \ \ .

Page scan 52

The Adventures.of Five Hours. - sobreaks the Day; and so do all the Creatures - ~ A sighstole from her; Oth'ravishing sound ! Which being a symptom of remaining life, Made me forget it was a sign of Grief. At length she faintly opens her bright eyes; Rejoice, as I did, at the newborn Light: . . . But as the Indians, who adore the sun, - Arescorch'd by’s Beams, ere Half his Race be Runs so I, who did adore her Rising Eyes, º Found my sclf Wounded by those Deities. Oä. How you have rais'd my Expectation : . . . Pray release me quickly. - - - 2nt. From her fair handa bloody Poniard fell, - Which she held fast during her Trance, as if - - shadonely needed Arms whilst she did sleep, And trusted to her Eyes whilst she did Wake. Where is our Leader? where's Antonio 2 My Love a while disputed with my Honor, . But that the longersetled Power o'r-came, . . . And fear of Future danger to her Person. a \ . What Isaid to her, being a produćtion Of meer Extasic, I remember not; she made meno Reply, yet I discerR'd Ina serener Air of her pale face, some Lincs of satisfaction mix'd with Fear. Oğ. such looks in silence have an Eloquence. But pray goon. - - . . . . - Amt. Rais'd from the ground, and to her self return'd, I stept a fitting distance back; as well Togazeupon that lovely Apparition, , , As to express Respe&t; when at that instant The Trumpets sound a Charge; my soir, crie 5- Made me then seckthe Present for myself; - _ - & 2. / - -
Page scan 53

The Adventures of Five Howrs. Icame uptomy Troops, left in Reserve, As they were ready to receive a Charge From divers squadrons offresh Horse, who being Quarter'd in Neighbouring Villages, had taken Hotly th’Alarm, and came (though then too late) In succour of their friends; Honor and Love Had so inflam'd my heart, that I advanc'd Beyond the Rules of Condućt, and receiv'd so many wounds, that I with faintness fell. Oä. How can this story end 1 . Ant. My soldiers beat th' Enemy, and brought me off, Where surgeons quickly cur'd my Outward Wounds, But the remembrance of that Heroine, - My Inward Hurtskept bleeding stillafresh; Till by the business of the War constrain'd -- To attend my Charge I'th’Army, my despair Of ever finding her, concurring with r The powerfusperswasions of Pellada, I was at length even forc'd to an Engagement Of Marriage with a Lady of this City, Rich, Noble, and, as they say, Beautiful. And so you have me here, come to Consummate Those Nuptial Rites, to which my Interest, And th’Importunity of Friends advice, - O're-rule my judgment, though against my heart. • Oš. A wonderful Adventure! but pray, sir, May I not take the liberty to ask you, - Who may this noble Lady be, to whom The Fates have destin’d so much Happiness? . . - º: I have no Reserves for you, 'tis the sister Of--------- - ... ; ; , Enter -
Page scan 54

The Adventures of Five Hours. Enter Ernesto , and Oötavio re- tires hastly, and covers his face - with his Cloak. . . . . . . Antonio modding to Ośtavio. It is my servant, sir. . . - O#. step to Antonio, Diego, and desire him To send him off. - Ant. I will immediately; Well, Ernesto, º Pº." ntonio, and What good news 2 speak freely. whispers. Ern, sir, as you charg'd me, told your Brother-in-Law, I thought you hardly could be there this night; . . - - - ---- ~ * * * He kisses your hands, and bad metell you, That he expects your coming with impatience; . He charg'd me to present you with this Letter; Th’other is from your beauteous Bride, a person . . ." The most accomplish'd that I ever saw. - - § being yours gave me the privilege - - - - Ofa Domestick, in the free admission Tosee her in her Chamber-dress, without A Veil, either to cover Faults,or hide Perfeótions. Ant. Tell me truly, is she so very handsom? ' ' ' '. Ern. Handsomer far in my opinion, sir, Than all the Bruxels Beauties, which you call - The Finish'd Pieces; but I'l say no more; Let your own Eyes inform you; here's a Key ' Of the Apartment, that's made ready for you; A Lower Quarter, very nobly furnish'd, That opens on st. Vincent's strect. - Ant. Give it me; and go you to the Post-house, And take care that my things be brought from thence. - - - [Exit Ernesto. Oāavio, will you go along with me, t / . - And - *
Page scan 55

The Adventures of Five H.ours. - And be a Witness of my first Address? - - OH. sir, you choose in mean lll Companion - For Nuptial Joys, or any Happiness; - - One, whose Misfortunes to such sad Extremes Are heightned, that the very Mentioning Of Happy hours serves onely to Imbitter The memory of my Lost Joys. Ant. so deep asense of your Misfortunes, sir, Is prejudicial to your self and Friends. - - - Enter Flora in haste. Flo. Where's your Master, Diego 2 . - Pie. There's some Illtowards, when this Bird appears. Agº.. Do you not see him? y’have liv'd too long a Maid. Aside. Flo. I have something to say toyou in private, sir, That requires haste. _* [Goes to O&avio. - [she draws Oétavio affae, and puts up her vail. Oä. What new Accident brings you hither, Flora 2 Flo. These Tablets will inform you, sir, Farewell. . . Die. Will you not stay for an Answer Damself …, Flo.’Tisa Command, not a Question Diego. . . . - Die. short, and sweet, Flora. . . . . . . . . O8. Good Flora stay a Minute; I much fear - It is some new Misfortune. . . . . . . . . . Die. Nay, sir, you may be sure’tis some Disaster, Else it would ne'r have come so Easily, - 2. And so unfought for. - • Off. Will you allow me for a Moment, sir, shºwing to To step into my House, and read a Letter. lantonio. Ant." attefid you in, and wait your leisure, ,- - - - [Exeunt all but Diego. . . Die. These little black Books do more Devils raise, Than all the Figures of the Conjurers. . . . . - 2 * - - What .
Page scan 56

The Adventures of Five Hours. t What can this be I have not seen this Damsel With so busie a face; but here she comes Already, 'twas a quick dispatch. v . \ Enter Flora, and seems to go away in base. Die. A Word, Flora, or a kind Glance at least, What grown cruel P. Diego nobody w you? Flo. This is no time for fooling: Die. Nay, if you be so serious, fare you well; Yet I’l perform the Honor of our street, And bring you to the endon't. . . . . . - Flo. I shall be well holpup with such a squire ; , - If now somewandring Knight should chance t'assaultyou, To bear away your Damsci, what would you do? Die. I'd use no other Weapon but a Torch; I'd put aside your Veil, show him your face, That, I suppose, would guard us both. * Flo. Why, d'you think it would fright him, Diego 2 Die. Ohno, 'twould charm him, Flora. “ Flo. Well, such as 'tis, I'l venture it without Engaging your known Valour. - Die. Faith you may so ; - The face, dear Flora, defends all below. Flo. Away, you Fool ; Good-night to you. - - - [ Exit Flora. Enter Oétavio and Antonio. LOH.What may this be? O my Malignant Fate! The Warning's short, yet she must be Obey'd; / The hour draws near; I must go seek a Friend; QAftd. Her words seem to imply need of a second ; Twere barbarous to engage Antonio - Newly arriv'd, and come on such an Errand. . . . - - -- i. - Noble – -
Page scan 57

The Adventures of Five Houkº Noble Antonio, my confusion's éat, ..º. ºn 9 º' Y º, - To tell you thus abruptly, I must leaveydu: , '73 ... . . Th’occasion's indispensable...in tº ºs liff: i.º.º. 4nt. I must not quit you, sir, I knowtootwell j .º. The Laws of Honor, to desertyounow ::i5 us ... . . . When I my friend in such disorder see, , , , , , , , , Andall the Marks that he is call'd to Danger, - To leave him then-------- Qā. It is a summons from a Lady, sir, Whom I have lov'd with Passion and success; To meet her in her Garden presently: H All is propitious on her part and mine 3, But she's so Guarded by a Tyrant Brother, - so Jealous naturally, and so incens'd By that new Accidentifold you of, , , ; ; ; – tº Which makes mea close Prisoner all the day; 'º' \\ *-*- That to perswade youthere no Danger is - In this Adventure, were to abuse you; , , . . . . . . J . But even for that reason I am bound . Not to consent to the Imbarking you . In an oëcasion that's º 2 º' “... ." To what you come for; Antonio;We must tº ºt. . . As wellté Friends as to our selves be just. . . . . . . . Ant. He ought not to pretend to Friendships name , . . . Whoreckons not Himself and Friend the same. * * * * O3. Friendship with Justice must not disagree; ; , ; That were to break the Virtue's Harmony. Tº , , º, Ant. Who in his Friends Distresses takes no part, tº His Friendship's onely in his Tongue, not Heart... ... . OH. Youfrom a life of Perils hither come tº To find a Nuptial Bed, not seek a Tomb. ºf , ºr, E. i. * . . . . . -- * An My Friending gºd, increr mustbesaid, sº Antonio left him so to goto #1 ! * º oà.Y’are
Page scan 58

The Adventures of Five Hours. Oä, Y'are marri'd, and expose what's not your own. . Ant. Wedded to Honor, that mustyieldtonone. . . . . Oä. I find, Antonio, you must still subdues ºn ..…., , Ant. Ibwmy Triumph tomy Cause, not You. . .”. Come, we lose time, your Mistris must not stay, ºr ºf Oä. Who'sso accompanid, needs not fear his w *: . . " , ºr Lºs & ºf ºi nº in ºf iv. 2.É Exéunt. --------' as; sis...} ), ºf - ** = ºil-----|-- . . . . . . . . . . . - : fººt ºf 3:3: " 'is tº ºr ºf 'A - +. *The sch Nºis, ; : J of º *** - b's tº , , ; * . . . . . . . . jº- * : * '-- - º: c. *. * . ran a wrº. tº as , , T05C HENCRIQA/E’s House. . . . 3 ºf ºil. tº 24, wi: G of it. I Camilla, Porcia, Flora appenina Bakone, in tº º Por. Ome, Cozin, the hour assign'da Çam. Nay, more thanso, for 'tis already nightni Flo. And thanksto your stars sufficiently dapkº, , , Por. To the Clowds you would say, Flºra, for stars, J. In this occasion, would not much befriend us. . . . . Pray, Cozin, when OHavio shall arrive.,i . . . . . . . . - _* *-** . Do you and Flºra watchabove with care; sº For if m cruel Brother should surprizeus------, ‘. . . . . º - Cam, Let usalone to play the sentinels." * . . . . Flo. I'm confident he's abroad, and will not * * > . suddenly return; for Iheard himsay, , , , , , , , ..., He'd pass th’Evening at the Corigidors ; ; ºf . E.; ºf .*. Enter Andthence, youknow, he seldomtomes bomecatly. . v -- ºr " ' ". . . . . . . . . IRD ACT, i. tº . . . . . . . . . . . pproaches, 1.2, .
Page scan 59

ºf ºil c.º. º. i. º. º. º. . . . . Enter Antonip, Qāavio, and Diego, with their fibaks ºr their faces, and their swords.andrawn in their hands. " 4nt. Isitiot something early for Adventures’ º Of this Nature ? s ... : : T. º 'º º 'º. 2 ! i. l º . OR. Tisthe Hourshe appointed. - 4.4% ºf (... *... Ame. How dark’tis grown ºth sudden, there's not one' star appears inabèFirmament.” ". ! #sº i.e. Dié8ómuch the better; forwhen Imustfight ..., I covet no spectators of my Prowess, ºr ºf *IAftd. OH. stay you here, Antonio, PHtepbefores”. ºr , Andgive the sign; when you here the door ºpen,**** Then come on and follow mein. . s: it. "y.º.º. .*.* tº \;. sº **, ºr ; s: " : ; ; ; ; ; *... . . . . Emera theatherfideofthe stage Henrique and Carlos, . . Henr.The Cºrigidors is a pretty place, º' º ... ca. The Walks dosointiceme, falways "...º Weariety self, before stan retire. 'º, Henr. Indeed we have staid longer than we thought sº Andtherefore let's go home the shorterway;”* * The backdoor of my Garden's here at hand..., , , , , car. It willbºbetter thanºgo about ºil Por.Would he were come;I fear the Rising Moon tºove. Will give us little time. . . . . . . .” . . . [O&avig knocks upon the Hill ºf his sword. riºticeletºnkº,X; # , * , , ; ; .W.I. ºf -1 tº º J. in -- Por, I hope are not alone; J. : * º ... . . .” .*** - Oğ. No; . Diego with me, and a Friend.” is . - ºrºsis well;ITopen the door prºfently. tºo. Henr. Come; we are now hard by the Garden gic. E. Oä. Let's to the door; sure she's there by this time Be not afraid Diego. F 2 - - - > Die.

Page scan 60

The Adventures of Five Hours.” Die. Agree that with him that made me, who has Given me a Heart . than my Thumb; ºr º In - Y'had as good command menot to Breath. ..º.º. O3. Comc on 3, what art thou thinking ou? is . . . . . Die. That I see Company, or that my Fear does. 93. Y'are in the right; let's to avoidsusption; the rift ºf Walkºnarlarge still they are ºut of distance, iº Carl think Theard your Garden door opcil.º.º. 5:2 Hemr, I thinksotoos Ha! at this time Gºth'night ºn What £an be the meaning on tº 'lisso, , , . . . . . . . 4nt. They have open'd the doors,'tis time for me...) To follow, surely 9iavia isgonein, , º, .º. - [Antonio moveštawards the door, Por.What stay you for?" [Holding the door half open. - Henr. What's that I hear?. sure 'tis Porcia's voice. . . Por. What mean you to sland there? come in, I say. ---- Henr. Hell and Furies tº ... [He goiste draw his frond. Carl. Be patient, sir, and you will make a clearer ºxº Discovery of your Affront. . . . . . ºf . , º, Por. You may come insecurely, Ottavio: , , ; ºr: - - ... , ; , , , ... [setting ºpen the doore. I have set those will watch my Brothers, soming, i. 4nt. Madam, I am not Otiavia., ºpiº, . . . Por. Not Ottavio 2 who are you then? and who's ...Henr.I can hold no longer; I'mthy Chastiser, spraw: Vile Woman, jë. Chastiser, his sword "Ant. Ha! my Mortal Enemy 2 ... º. ºº Henr. Yes, Villains who cre thouart, thou shalt pay This Treacherse with thy Life. . . . . . . . . . . . 4nt. Vain Man; who ere thouart, know, the Life thou Threaten'st, is Gua . by toogood a sword..., , ***".. † - - * * * * - * * * * * . * - - - - - . . . - Carlos - - - > - - - - • - -- - - s - ~ ---
Page scan 61

The 4. “Five Hoºrs; v.º.º. ºf y Garlos draws, and they all enter the ºf , i. 2 Garden fighting. . . . . . . . . . . . . : Hebr. Make fast the doot: 2: º, ... [To Carlos, Heur, Thouat some desperate Villain hird tº murder. . . . cºy" ºr iºnºsºn the Garden. – º – s; , º, of £ Oétavio and Dicgo came to the door. Ant. Hir’d by Fricndship, and Honor's my sallary.,. Lºrº ºf or ºff, ºff [ Andis. ºf fighting within. , Q3, Fhat's Autonio's *:::::ideniş; - w hat, the door shutºmy Friend engagid sandlºň Excluded , cursed Fate! this sree may help me::" ºr To climb o're; if not, I'Hlje t' him. - Die. You may do so; your noble Edve thas. Wings,' And's ever Fledge; 'tis Molting time withmine:59:1 cºis Yet I’lup too; the hazards not in climbing, [Heclimbº, Here I will sit, and out of dangers reach ºi! ... º.º.º. Exped thełssue, º Aºs off. O -- The scene thanges to a Gardeh;6Ht of." - which they isstić fighting rºl ºf - nich they issue tighting. ... 1 Oğ. Courage, brave Friend; you have Q&avia by you..., Ant:80 seconded;a Coward would grow firm...º. Henr. What is there more of your crue? thenºti; time; To call for help; Höl sylvia, Geralda, • Pedro, come forth, and bring out Torches with you, , , , º ºs º º, ø, º] - Entes sylvionith his starddrain... ºrja sylv. Here am Iysir; my Camerades will follow ºf Assoon as they have lighted their Torches. … [They fight. Ant. How I despise these slaves Oğavio, sº gº. Having you by nic: , sº tºpi, tº sº. [In the Tree. *Dir. sheir swords do clatter travely in the dark. . . . sylv. I’m slain.” ". . . ºst. [sylviofalls. . . . . . . . ." y: Die. Good - z - N lºst O -

Page scan 62

The Adventures of Firehours , Die. Good; that's sylvio's voice; I have ow'd that Fellow A Good-turn this twelve-moutlifºr a Mistake; Breakingmy Head, when he should have Broke a jeast; Nowhé's paid. Gºlfi's 2,812, 12, silo, 1sh ºx{1 \º. ****śHenrique stepping backfalls over sylvio, and ºf loses his smard, and Carlos runs in to him. Car. What! are you hurt?.g., sº I gº ºst. ºw: No, onely if { } Help me to find my sword. ..ºhatºyºgive taºkºyou do well toºkabreath, Whilst you'haweliny left; twislnot belong, sºñº. Now that the Rising Moonlands is somelight,ºf - -- - - inid' [Potgiarºus putto Q&avid. Par:O6tiatio 3 latinotºhismoment flip La Lºs .sº To Freemefrom my mixi Brother's Fury;... I 19, 2 ºf, Or never hopete segme any more L.A.: 2.1 : º, . . . . . . . . Amongst the living. … º.º. º. Lºs : . . . . . ; [Oétavio leads her away by the 4rn. oã,3}}Noblºg ifighty possesºdi, Of º; º; … 2. i Lethim live Wretched, and Detested dić;" Where's my brave Friend? … : “. . .25°º 2...& Ant. You havemeby youtside, lead off your Mistris, I'lsecureyour Retreatº 39 yºxa tºil ºf it, ºvº.º. [Exeumi Oétavio, Porcia, and Antonio. Die. That doubtless is my Master, who vićtorious & ... [In the Tree pointing to those who are going off. Isbravely maréhingoff with his fair Prizes” Ildown, and follow, inventing all the Away is on ºf . º. some handsome Lie t'excusemy Cowardice; , , º, Why liv'd not Ifive thousand years ago, tº ºt; … Being ne'r made for this damn'd Iron Age?"g Lo, ºgº - Hºus ºf six, ºpiego'comes down frºm the Trree, **oº. ' - sºfollows Antonio, º f : \º. - ~ * : *s: . . . Car.But
Page scan 63

The Adventures of Five Hours. Tcar.But whilstmydarekdmetosuccolrygus #zº Our Enemies, Iftargare got away; ºr, st *::::: lic.” I heard the door open, and see none Hergºt tº Lº? Although the Night's much brightergrown than'twas 3. I’l follow, and tract the Villainsifican is g.º.º.o. i. To their Dens; meanwhile take careofyeut $isters, was And (pray) till my pºtastníbassicklerate,...sº ºn, ºr Henr. How I Moderationinthis case lawhat boºk, 1.Y Geraldo, Pedro, ahye cursed Rogues, ºr is sº of - - ...ijº º Gº. ... Enter. servamºrith Tarther...r.º.º. Durstye not shºw.your headstill they wºrégone? Geraldo, light me in, whilst Pedrº looks . . . . . . . . . To his hurt Companion; ah Portia! Porcial, ºr { Exeunt Henrique and Geraldo; Pedro carries ºut sylviofainting with his hurts, Lºla, , , ...I “... *****.*** {, , . . . - The scene Changestbthe City of sEKHL. h; Cº cººl...º.º. ii º ºxº. 2. ºn 3 Enter O&avio, Porcia, Antonio, and a little after Diego, . . . . xiii, and after him Carlos... tº . . . ... ºozººi ºilº ºf fºr Die.sure,that's Antonio bringing up the Rere; spointing to 'sir, th’are but . bears her... .Y.satlº's Most gallantly away; lost nºt fight of me. . . . . . yºshiºglººms fºrgºthiºrºw; A He will by his mistake help me to harbour’em, ... . . - [Exeunt. - … sº 2°. ." . .” ---, º'-' . . . . . . . …ii ººsii Cº. ºffs * * * * * * * * * {{..." -** "tcºminariºsºriºkºlº." …] o' ºf .” ". … ºil toº. 1.1--" ".. The scene changesto Dan Hanrique's House. - - r *: *. Try s. it, . . . . . . . ) * * * *, *..…"? Q. o. ºº Cam, Was there ever such a Disaster, Flºra 3, ... " - . tº - sure
Page scan 64

The Adventures of Five Hours. sure, th'are all dead, so great's thc siknce, sº jº.º.) - Flo. Madam, if I mistakótiot Wºry much; sº tºº tº I heard your Brother's voice amongstem, pºss iºd . Cam, Å. my dear Brother, how thyill-plac'd Friendship upon that Brutal Kinsman has abus’d ... " " ºf Thy Goodness; though my Natural affection I sº or Moves me, Flora, to Pittyhimih.Danger, sº (º) ºn A Yet my Concernment formy Colin Portià ºf sº, Does prevail at present; forcia, Porcia; , , , , , º, Nobody answers. * . . . . . . . - Flo. Madam, let us go down into the Garden. . . . . . Cam. Take heed of that; 'twere to involve myself ºti In this unlucky scandal; 'tis possible, is ºn: . .º.º. Affrighted with the scuffle, she's return'd, 2 × . . . . . . Into her Quartet by the other-door; . . Let us hast thither, sº º 'º'; ' ' | - - -- . . ... [hey gº down and enter upon the stage. } Flo, Oh! Madam, isoea Light, and Don Henrique | Coming this way with his sword drawn, what shall -": ..." . . . . . . . * -- ~~~. . . … .VWe do?,’’. ‘’.A. i. ºst, . ciliº, sº ... yº)". - . . . . ºxº ! Cam. Peace; letushide ourselvesbehind the door, Till we discover his Intentions. - - /* : ! . . . . .'; ...º.º. . º, . . . ." . Enter Henrique, and Geralda with a Torch, and Pedro with a Light; Henrique and Geraldo their suvrdº draws; º' Pedr. sir, I have searth'd all the Rooms of the House, Andamoi sãºr. T. "Tº Tº Henr. Base Infamous Woman ; maybe she's fled Toth'Quarter order'd for Antonio. ºf Pedr, That door is lock'd, his scrvant has the Key. . Henr. Ah this unworthy Wörnand tâustofobº sº I A Brother of the Fruits of all his Care; - And cast this stain on th' Honor of our House; - * But
Page scan 65

The Adventures ºf Five Hour. But ifever get the Fugitive • * Within my reach, "I sacrifice her Blood. . . . . . . . . To the Offended spirits of my Ancestors. . . . . . . . . . Flo. Asadam, dº you hear * … . . . . Cam. I, and tremble, Flora. . . . . . . . . Henr. Call out for her Woman. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Pedr. Flora, Flora. wºn tº . . . Enter Flora. Flo.My good Angelguardme;what would you have sir? Henr. Where's your Mistris, Hussy; ; , . . . . . ; Flo. she told me, sir, bout half an hour since t . . ) she would go down into the Garden. . . . . [Exit Flora. Henr. My shame is certain; ah! the sad condition Of us Men of Honor how unequally, “ . º Our Crosses and our Comfortsmingled are : º, . Our Orphan sisters are no sooner grown. . . . . . . . . Above the Follies of their Childish Age; , , , , , , , During which season Custom does exact . . . . . . Our Watchful Caution overall their A&ions; . . . But they are Grafted on some stranger stock, . . . ; Where they do change both their Aboads, and Names, Without Reflexion in the least Degree - Of Gratitude, on those, who Pain'd themselves To Cultivate their Youths 3 or else become An Hourly Torture tous, whilst the best Continu'd in our Care do never.cease gº Togive the Fears at least of what I feel. Ounjust Heavens! why sufferyouthat they, Who toour Joys of Life such Bubbles are, i. - should add such Weight unto our Griefs, and Care 2 - r Ah 'Porcia; Portia! . . . . . . ºf . , ... . . . G Enter

Page scan 66

The Adventures of Five Hours. - - Enter Carlos. . . . Car. Cozin, I'm much mistaken, or I have ºn In very Little time made a Great Progress Towards your Revenge; I comefrom harbouring The Villains, who have done you this Affront. Cam. It imports to be attentive now. - Henr. Oh, you revive me, may l but once enjoy . . . The Pleasure of my Revenge, though the next Moment were the last Period of my Life, I should depart contented; are the Villains Within our reach * , - - - - - - - Car. Be patient, sir, and I'l inform youfully; You were no sooner up, but I pursu'd Your flying Enemies, hoping the night Grown somewhat Lighter, would enable me (At a convenient distance) to discover The place of their Retreat; one of their Partie, Who was behind the rest, mistaking me . . . For one of his Camerades, bad me come on 3 - saying his Master was but just before; That he had born his Mistris bravely off. We had not past above a street or two, Before he stopt, and at the second House . Beyond the Church in st. Iago's street, He enter'd, and desir'd me to follow him; I making a stand, he grew suspicious, And from my silence guesfing his Mistake, He slipt into the House, and lock'd the door; I having well observ'd the street and House, Return'd with specdtogive you this account. Flo. Oh, Madam, this is Don OHavio's House; Without all doubt they've carri'd Porcia thither. Cam. Peace, Flora, and listen to the sequel. Hºn. Come,
Page scan 67

The Adventures of Five Hoºrs. Hen.Come,Cozin, we loose time;call all my servants; I will besiege the House; if they refuse ºf . , , , To render; I will reduce that Theater 'º';* * * * Of my shame to Ashes, and make their Fort º º Both Theirs and its own sepulchre; There are such Charms in Vengeance, that I do not wonder, " . It is reserv'd for him, who form'd the Thunder. . . Car. Have patience, Cozin, and consult your Reason i. 'Twill soon convinceyou, how unpračicable " And Vain your Proposition is, t'attempt ''' At this time of the night, within a City,. . . . . A House so Guarded. That, indeed, would prove . . . Very like Thunder, which the Clowd destroys ** Wherein’twas form’d, producing onely Noise. - What can the Issuebe, but to Allarm " " The Town ; expose your Person, and your Fortune To th’ Rigour of the Law 5 publish your shame 3 And frustrate your Revenge for ever? ... . . . - Henr. What would you have metarry till these Villains, Who have invaded my House; Affronted My Person; Murder'd my servant; and Robb'd Me of a sister 3 may evade my Vengeance 2 . . . . . . Car. No; fear not that; let me alone to find A certain way to hinder their escape; : * * * * l’l instantly to the Corrigidors, . . . And beg th'assistance of his Authority, To secure these Criminals for the present, & That afterwards the Law may punish them. # , Henr. A fine Proposals why, Cozin, can you think That l'Isubmit a Personal Injury unto a tame Decision of the Law 8 . . . w And having been Affronted by the sword , . . . . To pray the Aid of the Long Robe, and take ~ An

Page scan 68

The Adventures of Five Hours. An Advocate for second car. Your Provocationsgreat, Resentment's just; But, Cozin, the Greater they, the More you standi, scº In need of Moderation, and th’Advice . . . . . . it Of such a Friend, as you have always found me 3. . . Nor can le’r express it more than now, - Infreely tellingyou, you must not suffer ºr " Your Passion to Commandin this occasion; “Passion, § heresoever it contends . . . . . . “To Govern most, there most Destroys its Ends, , , , Henr. Oh how I hate your drie Moralitic | To treat a Friend with sentences; that's raging. In a Feaver 3 you may as well pretend, To teach a Manto sing his Part, th: 'stretchd . . upon a Rack *:::: I’I sºn: die, - Thanerºconsent to publish my Disgrace, Before I have Reveng'd it, . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Car: 'Tis far from my intent; all my design . is onely, how . Conceal your shamg, Till we have got these Villains in our Power. Which can be brought about by no such means, As by demanding Justice against those, . . . . . . . Who did assault your Person, and have slain Your servant; a most plausible pretence. . . . … Will this content you? trust my Condu& Cozin 3 Is not my linterest the same with yours ? . . . . Henr. Well,since it must befo, I pray make haste. . . . Car. Doubt not my diligence; by this I'l prove ºr " Friendship has Fire, and Wings as well as Love, . . . Hen.If you §. move with too much Leisure; Ah tedious Minutes which Revenge does measure I \, [Exit Carlos. Fb. Madam,yiavelcardúciº misdicººds. - Cam.Yes,
Page scan 69

The Adventures of Five Hoters. ~ Cam. Yes, Flora, out of question Porcia's there; ; And if they find her,she is lost forever. " … :: * * Flo. I'le try to Hinder it, though I were sure..., To Perish in th’ attempt ; I am confident tº ... . The House at present is in such confusion, I may run thither without being miss'd. Cam.'Tis well thought on 3 in th’interim I'l retire , To Porcia's Chamber, [Exeunt from behind the door. ...' ... . . . . . . . . . . r, tº ‘Enter Geraldo. . . º . Ger. sir, Don Antonio is just now arriv'd. Hemr. Ha! what's that you say sirrha 2.4. tº ºn. Ger. That Don Antonio, sir, your Brother-in-law ºn. Is without, walking i'th Hall, and bad me . . . . . . . . z Give you notice of it, shall he come in?... . . . . . . . . . . . Henr. Antonio arriv'd O Heavens ! this Circumstance Alone was wanting to complete my shame, , , , … : :º) When he desires to see his Wife, shall I • My self inform so generousa Person, * ~ That she is Run away 3 where shall I find … . . . . A Heart, a Tongué, a Voice, or Breath, or Face . . . . Toutter this unparallel'd Disgrace . . . . . A Ger. What isyour pleasure, sir Don Antonio, i.e. May think it long. . . º' -- . . . ºf . Henr. Wait on him in, but at the same time tell him You cannot find mc; I will leave my House, . . . . . . . . And the discovery of my shame to Fate; , , , , , ºr sº And any Censur; rather undergo', ; , , , , , , , … Thanbé Relater of my own Disgrace ; , , , , Till first I have my Honor's Ransom paid . . . . . . . . In the Vile Blood of that perfidious Maid....., x, sº . . . . . .” Éxit Henrique. Enter Antonio and Ernesto... . . . . .a. Am. Myfriendandhisai Măiţăfºlyiodgå, - 4: . And

Page scan 70

The Adventures of Five Hours. And free from their Adventure 5 'tis now fit To mind my own Engagement; But Ernesto, VVhat can the meaning be of this indecent suffering me to remain without thus long upon my first Arrival? come, let's goo Into the other Rooms. - Ern. Iswear, sir, I'm amaz'd at this great change; 'Tis not above two hours, since I found here - A numerous and well-order'd Family, In all appearance, nowd see the Pages Boult out of the doors, then start back again . . . . Into their holes, like Rabbets in a Warren; . . . . . The Maids lie peeping at the Garret windows,' ' ' ' . Like th' upper Tire of Ordinance in a ship; "-" - All looks disorder'd now; nor can I guess . What may have caus'dsostrangean alteration; But there isee the servant you seat in. ' ' ' ' '. - Enter Geraldo. Ant. Friend, where's your Master? Ger. I cannot tell, sir. - + -- Ant. VVhere is his sister 2 - - - Ger: Intruth I know not, sir; we Men-servants Have little to do in the Ladies Quarters. . 4. . . - - [Exit. Geraldo, Ant. This looks but odly; are you sure Ernesto, Y'have not misguided me to a wrong House? Erm. If you are certain that we are awake , , , Then I am certain this is the same House - Wherein this afternoon I saw, and spoke with Don Henrique and your Bride; by the same Token There was a Lady with her in a Veil; . . . - And this very Room is the Ante-chamber º' . . . . . . - - To
Page scan 71

The Adventures of Five Hours. To her Apartment. . . . . . . . 24at. I should befinely serv'd, if after all This Negotiation, and a tedious Journey, My Pains and Patience should be cast away On some such wither'd sybil for a Wife, As her own Brother is asham'd to show me. * * * - - . . . . . . . . . . . . . [Ernesto Goes towards the doore. Ern. You'lsoon be freed from that fear, sir. . . . . - Amt. How so 2 Erm. Because I see her in the Inner Room, Lying along upon her Couch, and Reading; . . . - : Herface is turn'd the other way, but yet . . . . . Her shape, and Cloathes assureme it is she. . . . Amt. Artsure’tis she - - . . . . . Erm. There are not many like her. . . . . . Amt. If thou best sure’tis she, l'lventure in, Without her Brother's help to introduce me. . . . . . . Ern. she's coming this way, sir. . . . . . Camilla Enters Reading. Cam. Yºhave reason, Dido, and 'tis well remarqu'd, * The Woman, whosuffers her self to Love, “Ought likewise to prepare her self to suffer; There was great Power in your Charms, ~£meas, Tenthrall a Ladies heart at first approach s , . . And make such early and such deep Impressions, . . That nothing, but her death, couldere deface. . . . . ." Alas! poor Didol . . . . . . . . . . . . Ant. What do I see; or do Iwaking dream . . . . . 2. Antonioseeing her,stands as if amaz'd. sure I am asleep; and 'tis a Vision - - Of her, who's always present tomy Thoughts; , , , WWho fearing my Revolt does now Appear T . - * * O t --

Page scan 72

The Adventures of Five Hours. To Prove and to Confirm my Constancy. . . . . . . . . . . When first i saw that Miracle, she scend . . . . . . . . An Apparition, here it must be one, , , , , , , Era. What fit of Frenzy's this, sir why'tis Porcia, A Lovely Living Woman, and your Bride. . . . - Ant. The Blesing is too mighty for my Faith. ... 'Erm. Faith; iner trouble yourFaith in this occasion, Approach herbókily, sir, and trust your sense. . . . . . Ant. As when we dream of some Transporting Pleasure, And finding that we Dream we fear to Wake, º, … . Lest sense should robus of our Fancie's Treasure,' … Andour Delightful Vision from us take 5: ... is ºn . . Bless'd Apparition; so it fares with me.' . . . . . . . . . That very Angel does once more appear, . . . . . . . . To whose Divinity long fince I raisid . . . . . . . An Altar in my Heart, where I have Offer'd . . . . . The constant sacrifice of sighs and Vows. . . . . . My eyes are open, yet I dare not trust’em; * , Bliss above Faith must pass for an Illusion; If such it be, O let me sleep for ever Happily deceiv'd; but Celestial Maid, . . . . º. . If this thy glorious Presence Real be, . . . . . . O let one word of Pitty raise my soul . . . . . . . From Visional Delights, and make me die With solid Joy instead of Extasie. . Ern.’slife he's in one of his old Fits again 3. .. VVhy what d'you mean, sir? 'tis Percia her self. - Cam. I am that Maid, who to your Virtue owes Her Honor then, and her Disquiet since; Yet in my Pain I cannot but be Pleas'd To find a stronger Passion justifi'd , . . . . . By Obligatign; I may avow the Fire, º, . . To which both Love and Gratitude conspire. . . - Ant. Incom- * -
Page scan 73

The Adventures of Five Howr. v. - Ant.Incomparable Creature! can it be? | * * That having süffer'd all, which mighty Love. . . . . . . . . Did er inflict, I now should be repaid ºf Los With fuller Joys, than Love could ever give; ºzº. Fortune to make my Happiness complete, ; - - - - Has joyn'd her Power, and made me find a Bride In a Lóst Mistris, but with this Allay, ºo, º º Of leaving me no Means my Faithto prove, º Y - w f , But how can that consist with so much Passion X if: 'Tis possible the sense of my Distress'd tº Condition might dispose à Gentle heart tº To take Impressions then, which afterwards ºf: 1...sº Time, and your second Thoughts may havel»estroy'd; ; ; But can a Constant Passion be produc’d - From those Ideas Pitty introduc’d 2 tº . . …, Let your Tongue speak your Heart, for should y'abuse me, I shall in time discover the Dcceit ; You may Paint Fire, Antonio, but not Heat. Amt. Madam----------- ... . . . . . . Cam. Hold; be not too scrupulous, Antonio; ; , , Let me Believe it, though it be not True; tº j : . For the chief Happiness, poor Maids receive, sº tº Is when our sºlves we happily Deceive. . . . . . . . . Ant. If, since I first those onquering Eyes beheld, You have not reign'd unrival’d in my Heart; º; ) . May du Despise me, now you are my Own, Which is, I think, all Curses summ'd in one. . . . . . But may your servant, Madam, take the boldness To ask, if you have ever thought of him ; _1 * w * - * * , , t → - - - - Can. A \ since Chance anticipates the Hopes of Love. . . . . ] Cam. The scrvant's Error has misled the Master, ) . . . . . He takes me too for Porcia, bless'd Mistake; . . . ( ..., Affiftmenow Artful Dissimulation; sº ºf Aside.
Page scan 74

The Adventures of Five Hours. Cam. A Love, so founded in a Noble Heart, Has need of no Remembrancer, Antonio; … ." You know your selftoo well; those of your Trade Have skill to Hold, as well as to Invadé. Ant. Fortune has lifted me to such a Height Of Happiness, that it may Turn my Brain, When I look down upon the rest o' th' world... . . . . . VWhat have I now to wish but Moderation. 4 º' To Temper, and to Fix my joys 2 - Cam. I yield as little t'you, noble Antonio, In Happiness, as Affection, but still . . . Porcia must do as may become your Bride, , , And sister to Dan Henrique, in whose absence. - > Alonger Conference must be excus’d. And so I take the freedom to withdraw. -- should I havesaid untill Don Henrique came ... º. His presence would have mart'd my sº side. [Exit Camilla. Ant. Where Beauty and Discretion so combine , , 'Tis Heaven, me-thinks, to find that Treasure mine. - Enter Henrique. . . . . Henr. sure Don Antonio, having long ere this Found out th’infamous Flight of my vile sister, VWill be retir'd to meditate Revenge .. - upon us both : ah Curse I he is there still; I'l slip away ; but, O Heavens ! 'tis too late, He has perceiv'd me. . . . - - - Ant. How, Don Henrique ! avoid your Friend that's cºme so long a Journey tembrace you, and cast : *-ºs Himselfat the feet of your fair sister 2: . Henr. Noble Antonio, you may well imagine The trouble I am in, that you should find A - * *-x.i. My - - - ~/
Page scan 75

The Adventures ofFive Hours. My House in such Disorder, sounfit Yºº 1.3 L º The Honor to receive of sucha Guest.º. tº . , , , , , Ant, "Tis true, Don Henrique, I am much surpriz'd. With what 1 find ; I little did expc& ... . . ºf sº Your sister Porcia should have been----, * : . . . . . ; Henr.Oh Heavens! I'm lost,he has discover'd all, [Aside, 'Tis not, Antonio, in a Brothers power, 8 9-5 tº sº, i. To make a sister of a better Paste, slovº º * * * ~ * - ~ * . . Than Heaven has made her. H. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Ant. In your case specially; for out of doubt, Heaven never made a more Accomplish'd Creature, ps. Henr. What means the Mān º ºxiºidºs Ant. I come just now from Entertaining her: , , Whose Wit, and Beauty so excell all . tº -- Of her fair sex, whom Ihave ever known, o.º.º. 1 . . . That my Description of her would appear Eroii i Aws Rather Detradion, thana Just Report bººp, do Of her Perfeótions. "g. ...— … ºº Henr. Certainly he mocks me; he never could) . . . Have chosen a worse sufferer of scorn 3 ºntºy But I will yet contain myself awhile tº 6 p. * *. To see how far he'l drive it ; sayyou; sir sº, tº That you have seen, and Entertain'd my sister 2. . Ant.Yes, Don Henrique; and with suchfull Contentment, so rais'd above Expression, that I think ºnto sº, ºr /. The Pains, and Cares of all my former Life ºf . , tº Rewarded with Excess, in the Delightº: , , , , Of those few Minutes of her Conversation; . . . . . . . 'Tis true, that satisfaction was abridg'd * - By her well-weigh’d scºerity to give me ºf , º, º A greater Pleasure in the Contemplation Of her discreet Observance of the Rules . Of Decency; not suffering º though now : - 2 - - vº - A * , , - - - -- ~ * - - - Her - *~

Page scan 76

The Adventures of Five Hours. Her Husband, any longer to enjoy. . . . so great a Happiness, you being absent. . . . . . . Hehr. I am confounded; but I must dissemble . MyAstonishment, till I can unfold . . . - The Mysterse; she might have spar'd that Caution,? Aside. But I suppose you’leasily Forgive . . . . . . . . . . ). . An Error on the Better side. . . . ." . . . . . . . . . . . . . Ant. sir, I have seen so much of her Perfeótions,' ' ' . In that short Visit, I shall sooner doubt . . . . . . . . All Definitions in Morality, . . . . . . . . . . Than oncé suppose her capable of Error.º.º. Henr.This Exposition makes it more Obscure: [Aside. - r Innust get him away. sir, is't not time º, I I bring you to your Chamber 2 it is late ; . . . . And I believe that you have need of Rest. . . . ." - Ant. I should accept your offer, were I not . . . . . . Oblig'd, as late as 'tis, to see a Friend.º.º. 1. . . . . . . . Before I go to Bed. to . . . to ºx! Henr.si wait on you, sir, ifyou'lgive me leave. * * Ant. Phumbly thankyou, sir, but can't consent sº To give you so much trouble; I'l returnº). . . . . . Within an hour at fartheft. : : º, … . . . Henr. When cºr you please: y’are wholly Master here. 4nt. I never saw a man so Discompos'd, . . [Affa. Whater thematter is. [...], º, . . dº º 'º', Ernesto, I must make a step to see ºr ºf . , , , , A Friend near hand; bid sancho follow mé; , . . . . And stay you in my Chamber till f come. " " -- . . . . . [Exeunt Antonio, Erneslo. Hemr. Your servant, sir; this sudden salley hence ºf - º! [Henrique waits on him to the door. At this time of the night, and newly’arriv'd From a long Journey, does imbroil me;more. - - But
Page scan 77

The Adventures of Five Hours. - But now I will not longbeinsuspense . . . . . . . I'l to my sister's Chamber. - * * * * *- : * * Enter Carlos as Henrique is going into Porcia's Chamber. Car. Ho Don Henrique, there is haste requir'd : all's, , , Prepard, and if the Quarrie lodg’d shall prove . . . . . . Worthy of our own swords, we may employ them; If not, the sword of Justice shall revenge . . . . . . . . Our Injuries; for the Corrigidor Isready with a band of serjeants. . . . . . . .” Henr. speak softly 3 Don Antonio is arriv'd , And some of his may over-hearus. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Carl. That's very unlucky, but does he know . . . That Porcia's missing 3 . . . Henr. Ithink not yet. . . . .” - . Carl. Come, let's away; we haveno time to lose. Henr, Pray stay awhile 3:l labour with a Doubt º Will burst me if not clear'd before I go. . . . . . . . Carl. What Cozin' will you loose an Opportunity Never to be recover'd are you mad 2 . . . . . . . . . Will you permit the Villains to escape, sº . . . . And laugh at us for ever? come away. " [Hepulls him. - * - - - - . . . . . . . . [Exit Carlos. Henr. Well, I must go; and let time make it out; “The worst Estate of Human Life is Doubt, º, . . . • * - -- ---. * , , tº '. º … " - ... " 1. - ' ' -- ...? : ; ; ; - 2 . . . . " '94 l - - * , ! … a “… ºf - - | - / • * , " ; * * ºf . . . . ." . . -- * ... -- - - - - --- * * * > * ; : } * * * * : * * \ -- -- - - - - - -- +4 ° - - ºr

End of section 19. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 20
Page scan 78

The Adventures of Five Hours. THE FOURTH ACT. . The s C E N E is To Nº. oc TAvio's House. Enter O&avio angrily pushing Diego, and Porcia following. - *Vº thou has undone us , cursed Villain;. Where was thy soul,had Fear quite Banish’d it? And left thee not one grain of commonsense 2, ... . . . . Porc. Was there ever so fatalan Accident 2 . Oś. Why, Traitor, did'st thou not let me know it, As soon as we were come into the House? -- Die, What wouldy' have done if ye had known it then? Oä. I would have sally’d Out, and Kill'd the Rogue, In whose Power thou hast put it to Destroy us; - Can it be doubted, but that longere this He has acquainted Henrique where weare? - . . . . From whose black Rage we must immediately ºf , Expect to encounter all the pernicious Effects of Malice, back'd by sceming Justice; Curse on all Cowards ! better far be serv'd By Fools, and Knaves: they makéless dang'rous Faults. Die. Am I in fault, because I'm not a Cat? How could I telli'th'dark whether that Rascal Was a Knight Errant, or a Recreant Knight? I thought him one of us, and true to Love; Were it not for such Accidents as these That mock Man's Fore-cast, sure the Destinies Hadner been plac'd amongst the Deities. Oä. Peace,cowardly slave; having thus plaid tle Rogue, Art
Page scan 79

The Adventures of Five Hours. Art thou sententious grown did I notRear . . . To stain my sword with such Base Blood, I'd let Thy soul out with it at a thousand wounds, … . . . Die. VWhy then a thousand Thanks to my Base Blood - For saving my Good Flesh. . . . [Aside. Oä. Pardon, my dearest Mistris, this Excess . . Of Passion in your presence. . . . . . . Por. What shall we do Oğavio 2 we are lost For ever ; if we should stay here, my Brother Will be upon usinstantly. Alas! . . - - * } My Own Life I value not Ottavio, . . . . . . . Where yours, my Better life, such hazard runs; . . . But O my Honor O my Innocence - Expos'd to scandal; there's my deepest sense. Oä. Though the Complexion of your Brother's Malice Resemble Hell, it is not Black enough . . . . . . . . . . To casta stain upon your Virgin Whiteness. -- As Contraries compard set Öffeach other, . . . . . The sister's Brightness will expose the Brother. º - Por: O my oãavio ! he is still my Brother; . . . . . But what do you resolve to do 2. - . . . . . . Oğ. Imust resolve and suddenly, but what Iswear (know not, there have been such Turns In my Misfortunes, they have made me giddy. - Por. You must determine, time wastes Ośīavio. . . . . Oä. If I should lead you through the streets, and meet Th’inquisitive justice, I daring not º Tavow myself upon the other score. - You know of, you might that way be in danger; We must not venture’t ; * Run Rascal, and fetch A Chair immediately. * To Diego. . . Due. A pretty Errand at this time oth night; These Chair-men are exceedingly well natur'd , ~ # . Th’are \
Page scan 80

- -, - --- The Adventures of Five Hours. Th’arc likely to obcy, a servant's Orders . . . . . . . . After ten a clock: , ; , . . . . . . . . . [Exit Diego. Oğ. Ye Powers above, why doyelay so great A VVeight on Human Nature, and bestow . . . . - | such an unequal Force to bear Our Loads 2) After a long pursute through all those storms , , . . . Which Hell-bred Malice, or the Power of Fate . . . . . Could ever raise, t'oppose a Noble Love; , , To be at length possess'd of the Rich Mine, 2. - Where Nature seem'd to have lodg’d all her Treasure; And in an instant have it ravish'd from me, . . . . . . Is toorude a Trial for my tir’d Patience, - To sustain; I cannot bear it. , , | - Por. My sense of this Misfortune Equals yours, a But yet I must conjure you to submit º, - To Heavens Decrees; such Resignation , , , , . . . . . 'Tis possible, their Justice may induce The mischief to divert, though ne’rsonear. Oğ. Ah Porcia to part with you! - Por. Loose not your self with me, though we are forc’d To separate, yet we are not Divorc’d. . . . . . . . . . . nº Oä. Whilst our souls ačt by Organs of the sense; *Twixt Death and Parting there's no difference. - Por. Consult your Reason, then you will comply; Making a Virtue of Necessity. º, Oä. Ahlovely Maid, 'twas not allow'd to jove . . . . t ºl -- * . . . . . -- * ~ To hold at once his Reason, and his Love. w * . . . . Enter Diego. . . . . . Die. The Chair is come, sir, just as I expcétéd. . . . . Oći. Where is it - . Die. Even where it was; they arc deeply engag’d At New Cut, and will not leave their Game, - - * , They ~ - / -
Page scan 81

The Adventures of Five Howry. They swear, for all the Dons in sevil. Oä. Acurse upon these Rºgues l’Imake 'em come, Or put some of 'em in a condition... . (; , . To be carrºd themselves. - * * w - . . . . . . . [Oétavio runs out. Die. Madam, though I was never yet unkind - **- : *w---. - Tomy own pººr, I am so much troubled º, º 'º' At the Disquiet my Mistake has brought you; , , . . . . . That could I do it conveniently, ifaith, I could even cudgel my self. * - * : : - . 1.- : - - - - - - - . . . Tor. Away Buffon, is this a time for fooling . . . . . . - - * ----- tº - - . . . x - - - - - - - - - - . . . . . . . . . . .'; º' -- * Enter Antonio and sancho. . . . . Ant. Where is my noble Friend Ośavio 2 " . Die. Did you not meet him at the door, sir . 44t. No. . . . . . . . . . . . . ." Die. He went out just as you canne in. . . . .” Ant. Madam, I might have gone to Bed, but not . . - ; Addresses himself to Porcia. To Rest, without returning to enquire . . . . .º. º. º.º. Anew of Yours, and of my Friends Condition; tº And once more offer you my service. . . . . . . ºccº, Por, I take the boldness in Qāavid's absence º To return his with my most humble Thanks . . . . . For your late generous Assistance of us, nº lºº And for this nºw. Addition to our Debtº gº ºf , º, Ant. Madam, though I have not the Happiness, , º, To be Known to you, yet my constant Friendship f : . ; * , ,- *: - With Oğavio is of an antient Date; , . . .'' And all Occasions where I may express . . . . The Fervour of it, are most welcome to me. . . . . . - I Enter
Page scan 82

The Adventures of Five Hours. - . . . . . . . . . . ºf , º Enter Flora ingreat hase, wº 1. .*.*} r" * - * -- . 1 , ----... -- . 1 ( : « Flo. O Madam----- I'm out of breath with running. Por. What Accident, Flora, brings you hither 2 . " Flo. Asad one, Madam, and requiring haste , , , , , To give you timely notice on't 3 Pongarloss... . . . . Assisted by the light ºth Rising Moon; ' ' ', " ": And by a Mistake º ; : " . . . . . . . Has Trac'd you to this Ho - - Inform'd your Brother of the Place, and Manner . . . Of your Retreat, who is now coming hither ‘’’’ ‘’’ Accompani’d with the Corigidor , , , , a - Toseize on whomsoevershall be found. . . . . . . . Within these Walls, upon pretence of Murder. . Por. O cruel Accident 11 º’’’ ‘’’’ ‘’’ º º k- Flo. Madam, make haste, get . at the backdºor}. Or you will certainly besthet witHall. " " ' "." * for. Howvika Čreature aminow become?” “º For thoughin my own Innocence secure ... . . . . . As to my self, tºothers IshāHap gar 1 (jj Nº. sº sº º º some wicked Womad, that has föğher Honor. so º To purchase Infamy. ...” Yºº "ºº" Flo. They'linstantly behere." si. . . o. 2.; 22. 1 º' Por. O that Oğavio should just flow be absefit tº But to expe&t till he return wºrtin digss, º, ..., Ant. Y. have reason; Asadām; and ifyou'dáté trust" º Your Person totheºonduct of a stranger, . . . . Upon my Honor, Lady, Il secure soi, º' " Or Perish in th’Attempt.” * : * > . . . . ºf to dº º º Por. Generous sir, how shall âwrečićd Māū’,” Abandon'd by her Fate to the pursute " '''''''''' Of an Inhumane Brother, er be able -. Either to Merit, or Requite your Favours? Aut. Madam, and immy hearing . .”. use, and in my hea hg: ". . .
Page scan 83

The Adventures of Five Hours. * \ 4nt. Madam, they're more than Paid in the Admission, And your Acceprance of them will transfer ºn ºf The Obligation, making me the Debtor. ºf Por. To your Protećtion I resign myself, . . . With equal Gratitude and Confidence. . . . . . Ant. Come Madam, there is notime to be lost; , , , Diego, find out your Master presently, ºr ºf . . . º. And tell him, that the Danger not allowing º' ' ' ' ' Qur stay till his Return, I shall convey ºf . . " His Mistrissafely to a Nunnerie. . . . . . for and Flºtayyoubercrobringmeword, : , . " ‘. . . ) What he resolves to d6 in this our despitate - Condition... . . . . .” - [Exit Diego. Flo. Madam, I shall, . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Amt. But stay; I swear I'd like to have committed . . . . A foul Mistake ; the Monastery Gates tº ºr . . . . . . . Will not be open'd at this time of Night, f [Going out Without a firićt Inquiry into the Cause;" {º. - Besides, ’tis possible, that once Lodgºd there, . . . . . she maybéðut of my Friends Power, or mine, Q Ever together thence if it be known... ºf 'i' o? Lady, I have thought better on't 3 tº shall . . . . º Condućt you to my Brother-in-law's house; : . . . . . . . . A Person of such Quality, and Honor, . . . . . . . . As is fit to engage in your Protećtion; º º tº And theremy Wi may have the Happiness . . . . . - Tº accompany you, and pay the Qffices . . . . . Due toygur Virtue, and digress'd Condition: And going to a House º mine, Make account; Madam,’tis to your own Home. sancho,stay you here to attend Oğavio, [Turning to sancho. And guide him the next way to my Apartment; - Here is the Key; I shall have little useon't , , , , * - - I 2 - Having --- - -- `---— —

Page scan 84

The Adventures of Five Hours. Having left Erneffo waiting for methcre. . . .: One word more, sancho; let Offavio know . . . . 'Tis my advice that he come in a Chair; . He by that means may scape Examination, should hc be met with. w Por. Flºra, I pray do you continue here, And if by any accident Očiatio . . . . . "should hindred befrom coming after us . . . Observe his Motions, and where he Fixes; Then return home 5 and I shall find some way . . . . Of sending to you to inform my self. . . . . . . . . . ) º . . . . " - f : . . . . - 7 Flo. I shall not fail t'observe your Orders, Madam. * Ant. Madam, I’m ready to wait on you. - Por. Ah cruel Brother l ah my dear OHavio ! • O how perverse, and rigorous is my Fate J. . Thus to torment me betwixt Love and Hatc.... . . . . . . . . . [Exeunt Antonio, Porcia. , sam,' sis no small Compliment my Master, makes - Your Ladie, and her Gallant, at this time . . . . . . . . 9'th night to quit his Brother-in-laws, and kavej, so fair a B ideas Porcia allalone. . . . . . . a - ; : . . tº * * - - Flo. What? is his Mistris's name Porcia too san. Yes; and if she has but as fair a Hand-maid “. As yourself, I shall soon forget my Damsel j . In the Low-countries. . . . . . . . . . . . . Flo. If your Low-country Damsels resemble us, You would not be put tot to forget first 3. . . . . . . But I believe that you are safe enough; I have not heard such Praises of their Wit, But that wemay suppose they have good Memories. . . . . . - Enter Diego. Die. Is not my Master yet return'd? . . . . .” Flo, No. - Die. -
Page scan 85

The Adventures of Five Hours. Die. Well; now have we an Honorable Cause Towcar the Bcadles Livery; faith, Flora , ; ; ; , , , , If your tender sex had not tº privik'g'd : . . . . . From this harsh Discipline, how prettily Would the Beadles Crimson Lace show upon Thy white back. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Flo.’s won't doso well as on a darker ground; . . 'Twill suit much better with your Tawney hide. sam. I pray, Camerade, is it the Mode in sevil To be Whip'd for Company?, , a. Die. Oh! a well-bred soldier willne'r refuse a such a Civility to an old Friend; … . . . . . . . . . . . . This is a new way of being a scoond, - Toshew your Passive Courage. , > * san. We soldiers do not use to show our Baks. * * Die. Not to your Enemics; but, sir, the Beadle Will prove your Fricnd, for your Blood being Heated With your long Journey, Breathing of a Vein Is very requisite. . . , º, of - sam. W. to Heaven that I were in the Camp again; There we are never stript till we are dead. º - Enter Oétavio, and the Chair-men appear at the door.- Oä. Be sure you stir not thence till I *} To the sirrha, where's Porcia tº . . . . . . . . . Chair-mem. Die. she's fled away i'th'dark, with a Young man Of your acquaintance. - - -- - Öğ, Rascal, leave your fooling, - - Die. There's none i'th case, sir, 'tis the wisest thing she ever did, had she staid your return, she would have fall’n into those very Clutches, In which you will immediately be grip'd, unless you make more haste: Flora is come - - 3 - With
Page scan 86

The Adventures of Five Hours. With allpossible speed, to let you know: ; ; , .º Th'are coming with the justice to lay hold tº 58.2°º , Ofall within this House; upon prºtérice%2% 1 ºn 1* Of a most horrid Murder; be quick, sir ; º' : And save yourself. she's safe in a Nunnerie; 2 sº Condućted thither by Antonto; ºf i ºriº ºf Where, poor Lady, she's dropping for you nowl ' ' More Beads, perhaps, than Tears; , , tº Oä.Peacescreetch-Qwl;Fire consume that Tongue ofthine. What saist thou Villain? in a Nunneries? : . . . . . . 9- Porcia in a Nuhfieries' O Heavens ! nothing ! so º But this was * to make me Desperate; ºf What hope's there left ever together thence, a After such Accidents as these made Publique? . . Ah Flora, is it true that my dear Porcia º . . . . . Is gone into a Monasteryż, , , , ; ; ; º' . . . Flo. Once, sir,’twas so resolv’d, and Diego'sent ºil Togiveyounotice on't: but afterwards "" " ' '. He being gone, they chang'd their Resolutions: º, . . . . There's ºne can telīyou more------ºffilining#sahiho. - - sam. My Mastef bad thesay tolét}jäkiibwº He has convey'd her to his own Apartment, , , In his Brother-in-laws House, a person" soeminent in Qūality, and Credit, tº Bººt º' That the ingaging him in her, and your 2". Hºw sºlº 2 - Protećtion, sir, shay mºdiyºoth ;: º º - Besides, she'lhave thepleasure there of being", º Very well treated by my Master's Bride. 2. *323i º There \el expectybii; sir, and does #39;sº * T .'s (A ** * Your coming in a CHāif,' to avoid Qºsţīondº o In case of any Encounter. . . . . . " " º 2 : ºr wº º Flo. And my walking by, sir, as an Attendant, º, Will pass you without scruple for a Lady; º' ' ' '." - - - - Oğ.I’ _--—--------------- ----
Page scan 87

- The Adventures ofFive Hours - Oğ. I’l take his counsel, he's a generous Friend. " . Come Chair-mgn, away. *Pray, friend, do you guideus. - " - . . . . [* To sancho. Die. up with your Burden Beasts, and fall forth-with To your Half-Trot. - [Exeunt. . . . . . . sThe Chair is carri'd aver the stage, * I vº. - - " - . . . . Diego, sanchº, and Flora fºllow. tº [4 Noise within, Follow, follow, follow, s Enter Carlos, the Corigidor, and Šerkants, pursuing - sancho, Flora, and Diego, ºr . . . . Die. This is one of Don rupid's pretty Jeasis, ... . . . .", W’ are struck upotra shelf before we could, Put out to sea. - - ‘. . . . . . . . . . ." . . . . . Flo. Oh, we are undone Diega: . . . . . - Car. You find, sir; my Conjećtures notill grounded. . [To the Corrigidor. Cor. What are you, sirrha . . . . . . . Die. A Living Creature, very like a Man, -, -, *, * Onely I want a Heart. … º. ** . . . . . . . . . . . . Cor.Y’are pleasant; sirspray Heaven your mirthcontinue. Who is that Woman with the Veil 2 . . . . . . . . . . Die. Lether answerfor her self, sh'has a Tongue, set it but onceagoing, and she's tell All that she knows, and more, º f : ), º wº Cor. Make her discover her face. . . so ºf - [One of the serjeants goes to lift up her Weil. Car. Hold Friend; Cozin, if it should be Porcia, 'Twere not fit to expose her here. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Cor.”Tis very wellconsider'd, go you to her, sº …, , 's Andspeak to herin private. º' sº "º . . . . [Carlos goes towards Flora. Flo. 'Tis I sir , Flora, who being commanded B - - 3 * - y -
Page scan 88

The Adventures of Five Hours. By my Lady--------- : . . . . . Carl, speaksoftly prithec Flora, ’tis cnough; , , , , , I undcrstand the rest, and pitty her ; , ". * * Bid her fit still i'th Chair, l'I do my b, stº To save her from the Fury of her Brother. * Flo. He thinks 'tis Portia thºre, a good Mistake, 2 As de It may secure Oñavio for the present ; a 4. From the hands of this rude Rabble; * sit still, - - * To Oétavio in the Chaire, They take you for my Mistris sir, I’lfollow The Chair, and have a watchful Eye on all. Occasions, that may further your Escape. . . . . . . . … Car. We have found our wandring Nymph. . . Cor. Is it Porcia her self? \ s ) . . . Car. No,'tis her Woman Flora following . . . . . The Chair, wherein they were conveyirg fºr . . . . . To some other place. - Cor. We arriv'd luckily, had we but staid, ". . A moment longer, they had all becn fled. . . . . . ser. Will you have us sce, sir, who's in the Chair ? Cor. Forbear Fellow! 4 Her own Folly' punishment Enough t'a Woman of her Quality, [* To Carlos, Without our adding that of Publique shame. . . . . . . . Carl.’s was luckily thoughton, when you oblig'd Don Henrique to expectus at your House ; ; , . . . . . . For had he come, and found his sistcr thus, . . . . . *Thad not been possible to have restrain'd º * His Pasfion from some great Extravagance. *- ~ ; : Cor. I could not think it fit to let him come; , . . . . For one offuch a spirit could ne'r brock . . . . . . The sightof those had done him these Affronts, Without invading those strićt Rules, which might Rendór his Life obnoxious to the Laws. " .
Page scan 89

– - The Adventures of Five Hours. Tisbetter that a business of this nature, $. 'twixt Persons of such Quality) . . . . . hould rather be reduc’d by Mediation " ' " ..." (If it be possible) to some fair Agreement, Than to a publiqueTrial by the Law, - Or, which is worse, some Barbarous Revenge. . Carl. This Fellow (if l am not much mistaken) ls Donošavid's Man. . . . . [Looking upon Diego. Cor. Who ºrs too, Fričnd 2 Die. To nobody, sir. . . . . . . . . . . Cor. Do not you serve 2 . . . . . . . . . . Die: Yes sir, but my Master is not himself. . . . . - Cor. Take his swordfrom him serjeant. §:# - Die. Diego disarm'd by any other and $... " Than by his own know Friend, it is a Weapon . . . . Of such dire Execution, that Idare not ". . . . . Deliver it, but tothe hands of Justice. . . . . .” y The Corrigdor receives the sword, and 3::::::::::::::: * * signior, pray call for it, when you come home, a And hang't up in your Hall, then under-write, " . This isbold Diego's sword; Q may it be . . . . . . . Ever from Rust, as 'tis from slaughter free. . . . . . . . . . Cor. Thou art a Fellow of a pleasant humour. . . . Die. signior, I never pain myself for Love, ... Or Fame, or Riches, not do i pretend. . . . . . . To that greatsubtilty ºf sense to Eccl.", . . . . . . Before I am Hurt, and for the most part I keep my self out of Harms way. . . . . . . . . . Carl. The Definition of a Philoso her. . . . . . . . Cor.Come, cave your fooling. #ºr, yourMaster? Die. I am afraid we are not to be parted. ". . . . Cor. Whom do you * *Die.
Page scan 90

The Adventures of Five Hours. Die. My Maser, myself, and befººl your Worship Mentions, for sure Öse that had any Wit; Would never serve a Lover Militant ; He had better wait upon a Mountcbank, And be run through the Body twice a week . . To recommend his Balsom. . . ." . -- Cor. This Féllow's an Original.' ' ' ... '" Die. But of so ill a hand, I am not worth . . . ." The hanging up, sir, in my Masters room, , Amongst the worst of your Collection. * > . Enter serjeants with two Foot-men, and two Maid-servants. serj.An't please your Worship,we have search'd the House, . From th’Cellars to the Garrits, and these are all. . . . . *. 2 ... " The living Cattel we can find." cor. Friends take a special care ofthat same Varlet, And the Waiting-woman; we'l find a way” tº To make them tell the Truth, I warrant you. - Flo. O Diego! must we be Prisoners together? Flora. -- - - - tº rºº cor.Come, let's away; but whither to convey her------ To her own House certainly were not fit, ''''' - Because of her incensed Brother. ". . . . . . Car. If you approve it, Cozin, I' carry her ºf . . . To mine; for since wefeek (if possible). "... * * * * The business to compose, she will be there * * * * * With much more Decency, and satisfačtion, sº ***: # , ºt Being in a Kinsmans House, and having there tº My sister to accompany her. . . . . . . . . . . . Cor. This business cannot be in better hands, Than yours; and there I'l leave it, and bid you '''' º ". Good- powly, that forsobadastleBanjºof widº, And less expos'd to Censureofthe world, *: ºn tº
Page scan 91

The Adventures of Five Hours. Good-night. Gºrkyout Šervant Cozin, I wish}: home. . . - º, is . . . . [4; the Corrigidorgoes out. çozin,you may be pleasedto takeyour serjeants Along with you; there are without two servants Belonging to Don Henrique, they'lsuffice º To guard our Prisoners, and with far less notice. … Cor. Come serjeants, follow me. . . . . . . . . . . Carl. Well, you may go about your business, Friends, , gº, c. ºf . [To the Foºt-men and Maids. I'l not be troubled with ye; I am glad ' . . . . . . . We did notfind Qāavio here; though I . . . . . . . Might unaffetted Ignorance pretend, , , . . . . . . I would not bring him (thoughby chance) this End. 12, sº . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . [Extant servants. sam. Well, inwasimº s: i:. . . . . .” - And sincethere is no notice taken of me, to . . . . TI fairly steal away, and give my Master . . . . . . Account of this Misfortune... . . . . [Exit sancho, Carl. Take up the Chair, and follow me... º. º. º. . . - . . . . . . . . . . [They take u the Chair.’ Die. A Lovely Dame they bear, 'tis true,she's something Hairie, but that's a sign of strength. . . . Carl. Make haste, I long to let Don Henrique know, That his lost sisterisby my dexterity . . . . . : Recovered, and hope to findsome means. . . . . . To calm his Furie, and to repossess - My Cozin Porcia, and (if't be possible) ; Oğavio of his good Graces. Come away.... . . - - [The Chair is carri'd off. … Die. How like an Asshe's look, whenop'ning the shell, His Worship finds within sorough a Kernel; . . . - - [Exeunt omnes. ::1 K 2 The ---
Page scan 92

The Adventures ofFive Hours. N The scene Changes to Don Antonio's Apart - ment in Don Henrique's House, Enter Antonio and Porcia. . Ant. Madam, banish all your Fears, you are nowº, safe in this House; be pleas'd to remain here, Jºe Till I shall bring some Lights, and acquaint-Porcia . . With th' Honor she receives in entertaining . so fair a Guest. ." § tº 2 ºzº.º.º. 9 i. Por. Who is't you say you will advertise sir Fºr tº: Ant. My Wife Porcia; have but a little patience ; , , And she shall wait upon you. . . . . [Exit Antonio. Por. Is her name Porciº too I pray Heaven send her A better Fate than her distresled Names-sake... : W.W.s..?. O Oğavio ! O Love! how deat do you; ºf tº Cost me ! where am I brought what House is this? ºf What withiny Fears, and farines, , I have lost 1: ...* All my measures; I can't so much as guess ºk, ... What Quarter of the Town it is waré in, - For to avoid th’Encounter of my Brother, º f * ~ * And his Revengeful Train, we have been forc'd : \sº To make so many Turnings, I am Giddy. . . . . . . . But thanks to Providence I have this comfort, That I am in a place out of his reach. * . . . Enter Antonio with two Lights, and sets them on the Table. Amt. Madam, my Wife will presently attend you, Pardon I pray my absence for a moment. . . . . . . - [Exit Antonio, Por. Now I begin to hope my sighes, and Tears, Have in some sort with the just Heavens prevail'd, z At
Page scan 93

The Adventures of Five Hours. At length to free me-------- *But what do I see : - * ... . . . . . . [* Looking about her. Am I awake, or is it an Illusion?", tº j, Is not this my Brother's House? Is not this ºne . . . The Quarter joining to my own Apartment? . . . . Thcre is no room for Doubt, and my Misfortunes . . . . Arealways Certain; Miserable Créature, sº That I should betlius Bandi'dupand downs...} : . . . . From one Hazardt another, greater still..., tº o Ah cruel Heavens! what have lever done - To deserve this lasting Perfecution? . . But how came I here? brought by oãavio's friend, - Upon whose Virtue 1 did sorelie º 'º, º sº I - That I my Brothers Malice durst defie. * * Canhe betray me? sure I am in a Dream, ºg º But if oğavio--------- O vile suspition! .o. º. . OHavio false 2:rio, Truth and He are pne. Hó. 'Tis possible his Friend may guilty be sº a rººf, ºn tº , , But to what end so base a Treacherie : . . . . . And if Perfidious, how could he be his Friend. . . . . I am confounded with the various forms,º . . . . A Of my Misfortunes, Heightned still the more, ºr ºr ºn The less I can their Hidden Cause explore, ºz. ..., Thisonely's evident, that I must flie º ºs cº, ºr Immediately this fatal place; But why: y : " . . . . . struggle 1 thus with Fate? since Go, or stay", is . . . . Deathseems alike to wait meeveryway. . . [she weeps. *. . . . . . . . . . ; ": – ' '...' ...º. º. º. " . Enter Antonio and Camilla... . . . . . Cam, I wonder much what Lady this can be rºs., . Antonio mentions. * * * * * . . . . . . [Aside. Aut. Pardon, my deardst Mistris, the Liberty Which Iso carly take; but I presume º - - - - - - * * such
Page scan 94

The Adventures of Five Hours, such is yout Generous Tenderness to thoses. . . . . Whose sad Misfortunes, not their Fault, have driven Into Distress, that you will think yourself. . . . . . . . . Oblig'd to him, who gives youthéoccasion, a . . To exercise those Virtues which do Visit. . . . . . . others, but Reside with you : This fair Lady------ - * - - - - But she will best relaxchcrown sad story; , . . . . . . . Whilst Iseek out Dan Henrique, and engage hims; , E., Both to Protećt and serve her with his Credit. . . . . . . . …! 3. i-º, . . . . . . ...[Exit Antonio, « » the Handkerchiffrom her Eyes. ... I Cam. Ha! what's that I see? stay, stay Antonia.v. ºf w ;ºfiº j, q, ...[she runs after 4ntonio. It is not fit Don Henrique,”---- but he's gone, . . . .2 And we are lost for ever. 2', () --------... . . . iii.33. Porc. O Heavens! isthis Antonio, the same Manºo To whom I am Betroth'd; themmy Destruction sº, º Is inevitable. . . . . . . . . . . . . ºf tº jºi:18 Cam. Are you äh Apparition ? or are you...] . . . . . 1 may not yet believe you. ... sº " . . . . . to , ºn 3 Por. You well may Doubt even what you see Camilla; since my Disasters are somew, and strange, . . . . . They sever Truth from Credibility. …, , , , , - Cam. Howisit possible you should be here?: ºº: º * Pºr. I know not how, onely of this 'msure , . I have not long tº xpečt the dismal end r Of my sad Tragedy; since’tis evident The Person that hath led me to this Place, tºº, . . . . This fatal Place, is the abus’d Antonio; . . . . . . . . Who with my Cruel Brother has conspir’d To take away my wretched life, and chose Porcia her self? speak, that wheny have said it thrice ºf This º: Camilla's approach Porcia takes . . . . . . . Nº
Page scan 95

The Adventures of Five Hoºrs. This scene as fittest for their Cruelty,” º' ºf : " :" And thus, stränge Fate!! (through ignorance betraid) I have Protećtion sought from the same Partie, º, . Whom I have injur'd, and have made my Husband Th’onely Confident of his own Affront; e : º, . . . . Who tô accomplish his too just Revenge, "4: . - As well upon my Family, as Person; : " . . . - Gives me up to be Murder'd by my Brother. so whilst I'm branded as a Faithlés, Bride, sº º He’l be detested as a Particide... . . . . . . ºf . , Cam. Prodigious Accident; but wert thou blind Not to know thiné own House unhappy Porcia 2 Por, Alas, how could I in so darka Night; . In such Confusion, and so full of Fear? Tº "... Besides, he brought me in by the Backway, 7 º' Through his own Quarter, where was neither Light, " Nor any Greature of the Family. . . . ." . . . . . . Çam. Although I cannot comprehend the steps ' ' ' ... Of this your strange Adventure,2. Cozin, Your case (as I conceive) is not so desperate. Por. “We easilyperswadeourselves to hope - “The things we wish ; but Cozin, my condition Will not : sºfiarº #: ‘. . . . º 1: . Canyou propose to tempermy. Despair 3 º' . . . . º: $...y Evening Antonio's Man finding meih your Quarter" . . . .” Without a Well (you havingput on mine). . . . . . That he appli’d himself to me; and Hºº'." Byyoi command, ºur person did affème; ºf sº ‘Por. Yes very well. ºr " 'º', Cam. The Master since has by the Man's Mistake Been happily led into the same Error 3'2" dº. . . . . And Inordisabus’d him yet, in hopes º' I * jº ºr t
Page scan 96

The Adventures of Five Hours. Reverseth orderoffic wholečreation, , , , It might produce Advantage to us both. . . . Por. On! he has spoken with my Brother since, Who sure has undeceiv'd him long cre this. . . No, without doubt they having found themselves Affronted both, have both conspir'd my death. . Cam. How Cozin, can that be * if Don Antonio In your Protećtion has engagd himself, . . . . . . . And is OHavio's Fricnd. - Por. Cozin, if you impartially refle&t - On the Affront which I have done, Antonio, , , ; ; You will not wonder much if he recede . From the scarce-troden Path of rigid Honor . . . To meet with his Revenge; and to that end Proceeds thus cautelously, and does feign . . . Not to know me, thathémay disavow Both to Ottavio, and to all the world; , , . . . . . Th’Infamy of Betraying a poor Maid, nº, , , . . . . Toloss of Life and Honor.….. *... . . . . . . . . Cam. Misfortungs make you rave; this vile suspiriono, Is inconsistent with Antoño's Fame : ; , , , ; tº is ºf - - ... ºt - - You may as well believe that Nature will . . . . . . As that Antonio, a Man, whose soul: , , , , , , Is of so strong, and perfºëta Complexion, toº ºf C should gre descend to such a slavish sin, , , . . . . . . . And if we had the leisure, I couldgive you . . . such reasons to convince you of your Error , , . Thatyou wouldeasily acknowledge it. . . . . Por. I had forgother near Concernments for [Aside. 4ntonio. Pardon and Pitty me Camilla; . . . . My mind is by Afflićtions made so Weak, . . . . I'm ready to believe Impossibilities. Can. I Pitty thee with all my heart; but Cozin, . f - - - - I e--- -
Page scan 97

The Adventures of Five Hours, If Antonio not knowing you, nor your .… Relations, should chance to find yout Brother, sº Life z And him inform of what has pass'd, and that - He has convey'd the distress'd Partie hither, . . He presently imagine it is you; i, º, . . . . . . . . And then (I fear)'twillbeimpossible. , , , , , º, ..., (Though he should interpose with all his power) º gº To stop the Torrént; or divert his Rage. ºt. 10, isºs i From breaking in, and executing on us of sº That horrid Particide, which (though too latc.) tº , , , It maybe he himself wºuld exºratºjoti ºgºn, i. Por. There's rºomuchground for what you fear Gamila: But if we ould ségure our selves this night,’ wºr: º, sº There were some hopes that we to morrow may ºf Engage both Don Antonio, and your Brother ºf . . . To find out some Expsdient to fedeeminac ºr ºrj E. . From this deplorable gºndition.jd ºilº tºo jºi..', Cam. Were you onely in pain for your security: , ºo, This night, I know an easie:Remedy ºf , , º, . For that. …,]ºjo ovº 3 ºr sº gº cool iv. H. J.H. Tor. Which way my Dcares}}|... I a... is #if: citik) Cam. Why what does hinder us from making use s (On this occasion) of the secret Door, By which (you know) yon have so often past ºr Into our Piouse #. ingrepkasing Etrands?) is , , , , By this we shals these Bºxfits obtain; , , , , , , , , , Øf safety from your Brothers present Fury," " ' ". And time to try ifdarlos, and Antonio 2 gº Maybe ingag’d tomediate in this Business, a ... . And I have cause rºshink you will not find. : sº...! I r - - ~ !-- 2. Antagioso implacable, as you - Imagine. ". . . . . . . . . . . . . . ºr ºlº. --!º 2. Por. I conceive you Cozin 3 Fool that I was, " . T .* - L. -- 9 ~ *
Page scan 98

The Mdventurer of Five Hoºs, To thinka Heart once Conquer’d by your Eyes. . . . . . shoulder become 4hotherºVirgin's Prizelºst ºi::::/s ºf bºt Jºd is sº, o intoni inid Lºs, - tº Enter. Antonio, .5 bºowººd. Ant, solate; a Guestin's House; that's coine sofary; On such a Business; and not yet come hôtieri º ºs-Aflac, . There's sońetlist gºin't I camoºqomprehend. 2d sºo’s I cannot, Madam, yst find but your bruthtº), 2d, oil of But sure’twill not be longere he return.si: gºi; ºt Then I’lācquaint him with the Accidentºr.' … º. Has made his House this ladie's sauðtiaty, 24.3% ºf *Por. Here is a glympfebfcºmfort; for Ísee 19’s.’" He takes my Cozi for Dan Henrique's sister# 9 aftº O bless'd Mistakeso luckily continu'd ºf yº’ ºf Cam. I am by his permission Mistris here, if ºn And since that iam pleas'd sirjºtiseñough;) sº ...ii ". Without our troubling him with the Account is ºf Of her sad story. 1497 tº fººd tº ºp”.g., Ant. Yes, Madam, as toth'Excuse, but twºrefit fºr He kncw it too, that we might serve our selves ºf Of his Credit in this j flyis,” sº ºff ºf six; 2. 1 bili, do ºdw Y | "...wi, --- , , Enter. Henrique. (mosº ºf , Henr.Though's did promise the Corrigiãº dº Not to stir from his House, till His ºuri; lºv. Toojis Yet I could not obtáñírefrºy self. Jºigtskº is: w8. I'm so impatient to tºo dthºriči, Tº ºf ºftdeº) Of Don Antonio's seeing of mysister, a liº W ºn tº And entertaining her inherówn Lodgings; ºi º ºs. I shall not nowbeldagi'th daikºłęgierºgi bn A - . . . Hoºg.ºlds, 2. qfix *Re; her Tis she herself, and Camilla with her: . -º- Wercall my servants mad, or all agreed . . . . ." - - , - . . . Tabuse



End of section 20. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 21
Page scan 99

Certainly I, or thcy. "- - w: : *-* * - -. • * - --~ : The Adventures of Five Hours. . T'abuse me , in affirming she was fled #9". o: º alº . - But Don'tarlºs, was he mad too; t swear” fli sº t- That he had trac'd her to an other Öufe " ' º ºsº - must be Possess'd; }} º ‘. . ." º º o Or some §. - sº \ , , º, 4mt recomes Dºhehrigue; Piñówácāuainthifit With º: iº *} ..[I]}si Oj sić unit int - - * . . . t - cam. I fear wearé undone. º” ºil º!' - \ ºt, Doh Henrique-------" 12, , º, . . . ºvº. A vs. . ºv • Por: I’m dead the proceed, but how to hinder him------ Ant. Here's a Lady º § * - Henr. Yes, sir, I see who’tis.’ ‘’’.” º º ºdo's *sinºyºnowher sir, you willflecassier º Excuse my boldness. . º : ; , , º º º º ... sº a º _ &T Hemr. Boldness, in what sir?” ºf 15:11:15.19. sº } :II's - "...ºn #. * !-- . Here, with your sister, arthis i. º º Henr, Lord'sir, what doydu meas: "..." yº. ºrruytherºwāsāºščičiūtying, sºlº tº $º Which will, I hope ºisºmyitº" lººp sº - Withyou in her behalf. : ""º" tº : .I.A." Por. Now all comes out.” . . ." . . . . ." Henr. I underlandyou sir, she dºes desire. º Topass this night with Porã, tºast her oºl, (, In ordering her Nuptial Ceremonies: º **** wº r Lether stay here a God's name. ". . - - ~ * * * * * - f, * - º " . . . . . . . . Por. If Hedoes not distmblémy Condition . . . . Is not sodºsperate as I imagin'd, / L. . . . gº - Amt. sºaretº, º º 4. so early a Confidence will need it, sir, ; ; " " " Hºnºrismore than enoughsii, that you'desireit, . Th’Occasion too does justifieher stay. ºf ", , , , . . . . . . . . º Amt.” Fis most true sir, the Occasion did inforce me - - L 2 - Thus ------------ i."º ºº tº

End of section 21. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 22
Page scan 100

The Adventures of Five Hours, Thus boldly to presume upon your Fricudship..... ºf Henr. Ha' dong for Havenssake, is it a Novelty tº Think you for Porcia, and hor Cozin-Germin To passa Night together?... . . . . . . . . . Ant. Is the songara Kinswomanºflis : . ) strange silver;ºnteinher not to tºllme, , , Q, .. }. relation to him, whom I nam'd him first.’, aid. I'd made fine workon't had stold himall. . . ) . Hear. she knows I owe her many a Good-turnº. i- ------tº #. o, º, .394, (Loºking on the fades, I'm confident he counterfeits this Calm. , tº \ * ~ * -> - - upon offaii's cgie, and hopegie long. . . . . . . sº plainer terms; , , cam. scannottels which of us two he means? But I begin to fear that he kgQwsall. . . . ..sºs., . . . . . . * - Henr. since tissolate, pray give th; Ladies kave, ‘r, Pinçº & iº. **** To retire to their Cha 9 in sister. . . . . Ant. My Brothers Words, and his Behaviour, & * . ºf 2 × . t - . Imply some Mystery; I must be filent, º&Aid. Till I discover more...... zºlnºk 42 & 3" I. J. : ... ys Por. Let us begone, ware soft if we stay! - vg stay licré; To disguise his Revenge, until Antonio, . . Andºreñoffic #. gone to Bed. º Çam.But we shall ner be able to get out . . . Whilst they continue in the outward Rooms. - " " . . Por. Yes, by the Garden-dore, but I'm afraid - 'Tis shut. . . . * ,-- ºf º º º º ! Jº — Cam. No; now I thinkon't, Flora went that way, And left it open. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Por. Come, lett'sbe gone; I hope Heavendocs ordain Ease by that Door which first let in my Pain. . . . - - [Exeunt Porcia and Camilla. Amt. - * * . . . •- '-. is ". -, *, *. To be able to repay her to the fills. . . . . . . . . . … " I - - - - 3: . . ; (, ) . s - .

Page scan 101

The Adventures of Five Hours. Ant. I's onely make a step sir, to my Lodging, And then return to you immediately. f :-- Hemr Pray give me leave to wait on you.' . . . Ant. I humbly thank you sir, I know the way, And shall not stay above a Moment from you. - Henr. Y'are Master here, sir. . . . . . – ...Ant. I’Indw go see whether my servant sancho C, sº . Has brought Oğavio to my Apartment, " - - As I direéted him. . . - [ Exit Antonio. “Henr. Heavens ! was there ever so strange a Mystery : Don Carlos he affirm'd that those we fought with Had convey'd Porcia away, and when I come * * To seek her in the House I find her missing, …" Tosecond this, her Waiting woman Flora . . . Tells mé that she went down, about that time, sº ºf six, sº ~ Into th’ Garden; Antonio, not long after; ' ' ". "... Ashrms that he both saw, and entertain’d her In her own Apartment, where I now find her, And Camilla with hºr : What can this be?, These sure are Riddles to pose an Oedipus; , But if by my own sense I am assur’d My Honor's safe, which was so muchin doubt, What matter is it how 'tis brought about, º, ; , , , º, - - * . . . . . . . . c - _º -i " - * }, s > * * * * * * * . ~ ii'i º 'º º,' ' ' ', 1 - . . . . .'; " Q { w : …, -i- tº ºr - 2 - 1 - - º - - - - ... ºil.ji o 'º' vº. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
Page scan 102

The Adventures of Five Hours. . . . . . . .'; ºr gº. 3 a tº sº THE FIFTH ACT. " . . . - - - ' ' … º. º. 1 . . ." . . . . . ; ; // ; ; ; . . . . . . . . . s º . . The sC E N E is , : º lºss ºf - - . ~ - - • 21 - “º T o WCCA R Lo s's House. - , -, -, *, * . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - , - - ** - - -- . . . . . . . . . Enter Diego, Flora, and Geralºg cºmpanying the chair, , , , greaping 45% thedark. º fit of ºx.” A - …” }ss. . . . " . . . . . . . . . ºriº ºf '' Ger. Dº Flora, and signior Diego, goin there. I MAnd you myFriends,set down the Chair i'th door; And when the Party's enterd, pullit to ; , . . . . . . . . 'Twill lock of 't #. done, you may be gone; º' There's Mony for you; I'lgofercha Candle. . . . . bºrº (Diego,and Florage in, and the Chairéeing. )set, in the door , Oötavio goes aut into the room, the Chair-men clap to the door, “and go away. . . . . . Enter Oétavio, Diego, Flora, at another door. Oä. What I put in all alone here i'the dark: {; as And the door shut upon me! Diego, Flora. i' th' dark. Die. Here am I sir, and Flora too, unless . . . My sense offeeling fails me. Oğ. I can't conjećture where we are ; I durst not. so much as peep out of the Chair, since Flora Gave me the warning ; but where e'r I am, 'Tisbetter far than in the serjeants hands. - Flo. Though now i'th' dark, know well where we are: I have too often walk'd the streets, Oğavio, f * , - From 2–’= * : * ~ - - -

End of section 22. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 23
Page scan 103

The A&#entures of Five Hour.” From your House hither, upon Cupid, Errants, ". . . . Not to know the back door of Carlos's, L ..., ºrf: its & Apartment; 'tis there I am surew' arqºlow.d.; sº , O3. Curse on thee, Flºra!, had'st thou losłthy wits to Not to let me know it sooner! think'st thou … . . . . . . . I should have tamcly suffer'd them to bring me, J. L., a Like a poor Bird shutinia Cage, t'a place. Hºo is ºf Where I must look for nothing but Destruction. Inº, . Pie. A Gypsie told me by my Palm long since, ) is A sour-fac’d Damsel should be my destrućtion. - Flo. suspend a while your Apprehensions, sir ; You may escape before the G º cº e iT The door was wont to open on this side ; If not, I have another way in store." Yºº A ºil i. º. 1 ºf O&avidges to the dºor. OH. Flora, Iscannot makerhebock gaback ºf I \,\! - fºr C E i. ºf striving to ºpen the dºor, - #: on the otherfide, and coming i in with a Candle; meets with Oétavio, and starting back and fumbling, lets the Candle - fall, then running out again locksfast the door. Die. Naythei; isaith, ware fast; iheard him give The Key a double Turn. “ ºf 2 ... ." º, º sº." º is, ºf ºil Js Diego takes #p the Candle. • ere's a fair Trial for your Maiden breaths... . . . ; sº ora blow't in again, let's owe your Mouth º ºsobºr, Wore Light, than yet your Eyes could crimpart. … 3 Flo. Light's cast away on suchán Owl as you; ºr 7: ..., But yet T1 trie. "I lo ºil ºf Lººp'd tº , 4. } 2, ºrii di ji ºf Flora blows the Candleim. . . * Die. Thanks, gehtle Flora, toyour Virgin Puff; gº ºgg 'Tis a strong breath that can o're-come a snuff... [Aside. But I had rather’t had becn let alone: . . . . . . . → *
Page scan 104

The Adventures of Five Hours. If I must needs be slain, unless it were . . . . . Behind my back, l'd have it i'the dark ; ; ; ; ; ; For I hate to be kill'd in my own presence. . . . . . . . . . . oà. What must wedo Fiord? all my hope's in you. . . Flo. There is yet room for Hope; there's a Back-stairs ºf . Beyond that inner Chamber, that goes down . . . . .0, Into the Garden, if thq door boopen, is . . . . . . ; As certainly it is, the way is easie. ... . . o sº sº Oä. Come, let's lose no time; prethcc guide us Flora. º, ". . . . . . . . . . . . . . [Exeums. - . . . º.º.º.º. º.o.º. 2 ºf tº de A* The scene changes to Dan Henrique's House.” . . . . . . c. 1: Tº ºv: Toº. 9 - Enter Don Henrique. ºf ºrd I ºr is º Henr. As well pleas'd as I am, to find my Honor - Less Desperatºthan Ithdught, I cannotrºst gº.º.o TiH I havedrawn from Porcia a Confession Of the whole Truth, before she goes to bed; she's in her Chamber now; unless by new : Enchantments carrica thence. . . . . tº § .*.*.*.*.*.****'. . . . ºvy swº sº, Vº -- x - As he is going towards, Porcia's Chamber sº º -- Emier Carlos inhasse. . . . . . Carl. I can't imagine what should make Don Henrique Quit the Corrigidors till wercturn'd : ºº il it ºn 3 º : Jº. D. J. One of his scrvants tells the he's come home. 'vo sº O here he is ; now shall I raise a storm . . - Aside. Which (if we do not take a special care) . . . . Will scarceb'allaid without a showr of Blood; , ; ; , , § Yet I must venture’t, since it so imports Our Friendship, and the Honor of our House.º. º. Happiness is a stranger to Mankind;... . . . . . . . . . . . And like to a Forc'd Motion, it is ever … . . . . . . . – - - - strongest
Page scan 105

The Adventures of Five Hours. strongest at the beginning, then Languishing . . . With time, grows weary of our company; . . . . But tº Missºufiº; Wes&subjá are,' ...º.º is That like to Natsial motion they prove islº ºil º More Vigorous in their Progress. " " "º tº Hºvhat meansthis Philosophical Preamble . . . . . . . . . º - J - ºn 3 Carl. You'1know too soon I fear. - - fºllºa º . . From all m'Triquiétudes, that for the future . ." § I dare defie the Malice of my stars º' " " º To cause a new . tº . . . . . . Carl. Cozin, I'm so surpriz'd with this great change, Thatmy Confusion does suppress my Joy; . . . . But sincey’are so much Master of your Passions, I'l sparemy Ethicks, and proceed to give you In short the Narrative of our success; The Corrigidor (as we did expcćt 'º - 9 Forward to serve you in th’Affair's mention'd) ; *. Was pleas'd to go along with me in person, º With a strong Bandof serjeants, to the place, Where I attended by your servants led him : Cozin,’twas there; it wounds my heart to speak it; And I conjure you summon all your Patience : 'Twas there I found--------- Henr. Whom Cozin did you find 2 for since I’m sure . You found not Porcia there ; my Concernments Inyour Discoveries are very unlikely To discompose me. . . - - Carl. I would to Heaven we had not found her there. Henr. What's that you say, Cozin, my sister there! . Carl. Yes sir, your sister. - Henr. My sister that's good isfaith; ha, ha, ha. Carl. Why do you laugh? is the Dishonor of M s_ Your & >

End of section 23. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 24
Page scan 106

~rºw ºn ºf . As ºr r- ºr rr º'- The Adventures of Fives Hours. - 1: . . . . . . . . . … ." . . . . . -----, Your Family become à Laughing Mattér This is a worse Extrémé º º tºothº. º º Henr. How can º u; Laug § § Dréath;" Awake for Heavens sake; jºi yb * scises ; : . . Porcia there said you?... . . . . ". . . . . Carl. Yes sir, forcii Isay ; your sister Pirèia; ... " 1 : 1 - º żºłº" Pººf ºi, ) And which is mºre, 'twäsingiātī; ºuse. \\C. .º.º. Henr., Why suréyarénºissariº, Cozi." Carl. As sure as you're i. fºr there." º tº Henr. Then you transport me, sir, beyond all patience : Why Cozin, if sh;has ºffiliation. w - António seen, and entertain'd. ićr here,'" . " ' ". . Accompani’dby Camilia; if even now " iics them there within; Ist possible ". . . . . º You should have found her in Qāavio's House? . . To be here, and there too, at the same time, None sure but famus with his déuble face . . . . Caner unfold this Mystery. ... " " ' . . . . . ºf Carl. sir, let me advise you; Abuse not your self: Itell you positively I found her there: . . . . . . . And by thesame Token, her Waiting-woman Flora was there attending her. * . Henr. Flora ! dcar Cozin, do not still persist Thus to affirm impossibilitics. - 1. Carl. sure you are making some Experiment upon my Temper, and would fainprovoke "#" My Patience to some such high Disorder," That I should ne'r hereafter have the face When you are in your Fits to play the stoick. Henr. Cozin, I swear toyou upon my Honor, 'Tis not above a quarter of an hour, . . . . . . " since I did speak with Porcia, and your sister In that very Apartment, and am now Returning
Page scan 107

The adventures of Five Hours, Returningtothºmin my sister's Chamber.jº.: sº ºf - car.And sir, I sweargoyousupon my Honor, sº - 'Tis notabove a quarterofan hour, sº is . . . . since Ileft Porcia carried in a Chair From Don oãavio's House, yourman Geraldo, Condućting the Chair-mentomine, and follow'd , , By flora, whilst I came tº findygºoutº in Tº acquaint you, sir, with this unpleasing newssº º But fit for jº. be . . . . . . . Henr. This Question, Gozin, may be soon deci d. Pray come along;her Chambº, . off. ..., * } Carl. And my House is but the next door, let's in. º Henr. You'l Quickly find your Error, car.And you’l assoon be undeceiv'd; but stay, Here comes your servant, whom Ileft to Guard her; ) Heinstantly convinceyóuof the Truth. - - . . * * * * - Enter Geraldo. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Ger. O sir! . . . . . . Henr. What brings you hither Geraldo 3 - Ger. o sir, I bring you such rare news; your Enemy, Your Enemy OHavio-------- I’m out of breath. - Henr. What does the Varlet mean? Ger. sir, I suppose Don Carlos has inform'd you Thathe left meto see your sister Portia, With Flora, and Diego Oğavio's Man safely convey'd this House. - * cººl. seehow Dan Henrique, who was is the Right. Ger. I did as he commanded me,and put them All three into Don Carlos's Anti-chamber 3 . Porcia in the same Chair which brought her thither; And for more safety made the door be lockd; - - M 2 Whilst - Zº - ... .sº --~~~~ T. --~~~~~~~ ----- - - - - - -— -
Page scan 108

The Adventures of Five Hours. Whilst I went down in hałe to fetch a Light. . . . ºr Henr. As fure as Death this Madness is ñaion, 5 My Man is now in one of Carlos Fits, . . . . . . . Ger. Returning with a Light a moment after, No sooner open'd H the door; but Heavens ! . . . Who should I fee there standing just before me . . . . In the same place where I left forcia, but is . . . . Oğavio, your Enemy Oğavio. . . . . . . . . . . Hen. Here is some Witch-craft sure; what can this mean? Ger: Amaz'd at th' sight, I let the Candle fall; . . . . . And clapt the door to; then I double-lock'd it, And brought away the Key. ". . . . Carl. But how could he get in, if you be sure Youlock'd the door, when you went out for Lights? Ger. I know not whether he was there before, Orgot in after, but of this l’m sure , ºr " That there I have him now, and safe cnough. Carl. I am sorry for it. [Aside, Henr. Let's not, Don Carlos, now perplex our selves With needless Circumstances, when and how Those Queries are too Flegmatick for me; If the Beast be i' th' soil it is enough; Let usgassize upon him; he must die. Enter Antonio. 4nt. Good Brother, what unhappy Man is he, Whom you so positively doom to death? I have a sword to serve you in all occasions Worthy of you, and me. - Henr. His intervening, Carlos, is unlucky, How shall we govern ourselves towards him. In this Affair 3 so unfit for his knowledge . Carl. -- --- - - -
Page scan 109

The Adventure of Five Hours. Carl, Antonio is a Man of shining Honor ; . . . But having such a share in this Affront, , , , § Asid If once he know't, I am afraid he'l bring f. Fuel, not Water to Dom Henrique's Fire. - Don Henrique, you must suddenly resolve [To Henrique. What answer to return, he's fiot a Man . . . . To be put off with any slight Pretcnces; Nor yet to be engag'd in such an Aćtion, Asbears th'appearance rather of Cruelty . . . . Than Honor, and you know, Antonio needs - No frcsh Occasions to support his Name ; , “Who Dangers seck, are indigent of Fame. Aut. I find my coming hath disorder'd them, ) - There's somthingthey would sain conceal from me; &side. All here is discompos'd, what er's the matter. , , ) Carl. Perhaps 'twere better to suspend a while The Execution of your just Revenge: Time, and mature weighing of Circumstances , Never did harm in Aćtions of this Nature ; Where one has still the Party in his Power. . . . Henr. A Curse on your Tame Proposition Carlos : Carl. “He, who the Rules of Temperance negle&s, “From a Good Cause may produce Vile Effečis. Henr. I doubt not of your kind Concurrence, sir, - - [To Antonio. In all the near Concernments of a Person. Alli'd toyouas I am ; but Noble Brother, It were against the Laws of Hospitality, And Civil Prudence to engage a Guest (Newly arriv'd after so long a Journey), In an occasion, sir, of Blood, and Hazard. Amt. If such be the occasion, I must then Acquaintyou freely, that I wear a sword , . ºn Which
Page scan 110

The Adventures of Five Hours, Which must not be exckided from your scrwice; . . I'm sure you are too Nóble t'imploy yours: "… ... it's In any Cause not justifid by Honof; I sº, º is But I confess there are Affronts so great , t , . . . . . . . ...And heightned by such odious Circumstances, , , , , , , As do release us from the usual Forms: . . . . . . . . . . ; // Of Generous Revenge; and set us free ºr 1... . . . ; ; ; ). To tak't on any Advantage. . . . . . . . . . . . . c : , , , ; Henr. Though with Regret I see, sir, I must yield... . . Toyour excess of Generosity 3 ºvº. 2: ...,’ tº sº... I This onely I shall say to satisfie gººd. . . . . tº * -- Your just Reflections; that my Resentments sy, Are grounded on Affronts of sucha Nature, . . . . That as nothing but the Offender's Life ... it j . . . . Cane'r repair them, so as to the Forms º ºr a 2: ... . . Of taking that Revenge, they can't admit. . . . . . . Of the least scruple. - Ant. Honor's my standard; and’tis true, that I . Hadrather Fall, than Blush for Vićtory; ºr . . . . . . But you are such a Judge of Honor's Laws, , , , , , , That’rwere Injurious to suspect your Cause. . . . . . Allow me, sir, th’honor to lead the way. . . . . - - Exit Antonio and Henrique. Carl. If Porciabetheretoo, (as I believe)', - Twill prove, I fear, a fatal Tragedy; But should she not be there; yet 'tis too much For such a Heart as mine, through Ignorance To have betraida Gentleman, though Faulty, Intosuch Cruel hands; I must go with them; But soresolv'd, as in this Bloody strife - I'lsalvémy Honor, or I'llose my Life. . [Exit Carlos. The
Page scan 111

The Žºventures of Five Hours. f : * .. s tº ºf 1. - c - - w * ... ." - 4 Clsº i ºf °, **** - . . . .” - 3 ºr .” Enter. Oétavio, Dicgo, Flora with a Candle. Flo, Q the unluckiness! I vow tyou sir 3, . . . . . . . . before. I have fºrce known that dooré'flock'd oã. There's no Remedy Flora, I am now At the Mercy of my Enemies. . . . . Die. Having broken into another's Ground, 'Tis justifaith, you should be puti'th Pound. oã. The Tide Öfny ill Fate isfºln so high, "Twill not admit encrease of Miserie; since amongst all the Curses there is none so wounds the spirit, as Privation, Had safely gain'd my Port, and far above , , My Hopes, the precious Treasure had secur'd, For which somany storms I had endur'd; To be sosoon from this great Blessing torn, That's hard to say, if twere first Dead, or Born, May doubtless seemsuch a transcendent Curses, That eventhe Fates themselves could do no worse' 5 Yet this Ibore with an erected face, sº I'...}} 9:3: sº º º “... , -- The scene changes to Carlos's House. --- -> -- For tisnot where we Lie, but whence we Fell, - The Lossof Heaven's the greatest Pain in Hell; . . . When I had sail'd the doubtfulCourse of Love, since Fortune, not my Fault caus'd my Disgrace; But now my Eyes unto the Eartharebent, Conscious of meriting this Punishment, '' For trusting a fond Maid's Officious Care; * * * * , My Life, and Honor's taken in this snare; ' ' ' And thus I perish on this unseen shelf, Pursu'd by Fate, and False unto myself. * . . . G. ºf * t * * --
Page scan 112

The Adventures of Five Hours. Flora, when I am dead, be sure that you ; He pulls out These Tablets give tºrtia; thºre shº! find, {#if: - that to thºxtºměřMomčírofmy Lifesiº 3:17 I constantly pursu'd those Noble Ways , Which might Deserve her, though I could not Have her. Give me the Candle. 2: . . . . | , ; :---- T. V. 3 Oštavio sets the Candle on a Table, and fits. down as to write in his 7 ablets. . . º º Die. A double Curse upon all Love in earnest, ..." All Constant Love; 'tis still accompani’d With strange Disasters; or else ends in that . . . . . . Which is the worshofall Disasters. Marriage." ' ". . Flo. sure you could wish that every body living . . Had such a soul of Quick-silver, as yours, That can fix no where. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Die, Why'rwould not be the worse for you, dear Flora, Youthen might hope in time to have your Turn," ** As well as those, who have much better Faces. " ' ". . . Flo. You, I presume sir, would be one o'th’latest Which I should hear of, yet 'tis possible . . . . . . . That one might seeyou, before you should be welcom, Die.she has Wit,and good Humor; excellent " Ingredients to pass away the time; And I have kindness for her Person too, - But that will end with Marriage, and possibly Hergood Humor; for I have seldom known - The Husband, and the Wife make any Musick, Though when asunder they can play their parts; Well, friend Diego, I advise you to Look Before you Leap, for if you should be Coupled To a Yoak instead of a Yoak-fellow , - 'Tis likely you may wear it to your Grave. Yet, honest Diego, now I thinkon't beater, You ºv. . . Olls - “s. ºf . .

End of section 24. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 25
Page scan 113

Your Dancing, and your Vaulting days are dope, ( , , . Faithall your Pleasures are three stories highºff, i. 14 Th'are come up to your Mouth, for you are now For Ease, and Eating, th'ongly Joys of Life, 9ts .*. * - And there's no Cook, nor Drie-N urse like a wi. . . . . ." - … º.º.º. ºf ..[ Flora overthears him. Fºo. Icould find Reasons too for Matrimony, a sºlº o A stale Mata is a º: roach , - . . . Imust confess it ; and a Waiting-woman Does ongly change a Mistris for a Master; . . . . . I may quit her, 'tis truç, but not my Husbandsºr, Jo O - Andon the other side shenay quit mesºs, ºshii ºol And turn mcoff, whenold; and good for nothing. j. jo A Husband's bound to keep me still; In fine, For ought I can pºrctive the scales are Equal, . . . . I may throw Cross and Pile, which Life I'd have3 Lºº is - The single Begger, of the Marri'd slave 3 is nº ...d.º. But heark! the Door within frºm whence we camg to Is newly open'd, or my Eatºdeceive me, ºf its ºntº vº. Die. Methoughts | hºar º, * ... xi : sº [They loºkimo the next Room, and start back. O sir, ware lºgº.º.º. Coming most terribly upon us...i.e., , ; ; ; , Ostºvio.'s Oğ. Away you troublesºme Fool. zºoivº dº yo" - * * - * Hºoid ºf Enter Camilia and Fºia, lººkº, " - the other with a Candle. ... wºº tºo Por. I'm confident nobody saw us pass, º, tº From th'other House. ºr , , ; ; ; , … .º.º. Cam. However, let's gºthrough my Brothºr's Quarter, And open the Back-door into the stºcti, , oo, -iji ºr 'Tis good in all Events tº have a Retreat ºr ºv, - -- More ways, thanoke. . . . N . . . . . . . . .” * - - - Por. w -
Page scan 114

- The Adventurer's Firehow. por. O Heavens 1 out sures is cutoff, the Wind Has clapt that doortothorough which we camp... ii., i. - 4 º' is 4 dºor claps behind, and both look back Cam. The Accident's unlucky, 'tis a spring-lock, That opens onely on the other side. . . . . . . . . . . Por. Let's on the faster, and make sure of th'other. Oğavio here !...) tº is, “ . . . . . … º º …o 5 O&avio hearing them starts tº Y up with the Tablets ins hand. oă. Portia in this place may I trust my senses, , . . . lº, , . Or does my Fancy create thºse Chimeras - Die. Either we sleep, and Dream extravagantly 5. Or else the Fairiès govern in this House. -- e.' " . . . . . [ Flora runs to Porcia. Flo. Ah! dearest Mistris, you shall never make me Quityeuso again. . . . . . . . . Por. But can that be Ośavio 2. " . . . . . . Oä. I was Oğavio; but I am at present . . . so much astonish'd, tam not myself. . . . . - Cam. What can the meaning of this Vision be? … • * * * * * * [Oétavio approaches Porcia. Oğ. My dearest Porcia, how is't possible. . . . . To find }. in this place, noble Antonio - - - - - Having sogenerously undertaken Your protećtion? * - - - - - - - Por. Did he not yours so too? and yet I find Offavio here, where heismore expos'd ' ' ' ' Than I, tosure destruction; I am loath . . . . To say 'tis he, who has Betraid us both. . . . . . Oğ, Antonio false 2 it is impossible. . . Die. It is too evident. . . . . . . . . . . . . . Qā. Peace slave; he is my Friend, of Noble Blood, Whose Fame's above the Level of those Tongues, ~ That ~~~
Page scan 115

--~. . . . ~ The Adventures of Five Hours. That Barkby Custom at the brightest Virtues, a s. As Dogs do at the Moon...º.º. . . . ' . . . --- - ºil, sº .º." r ~ be . - - ~ * Por: “Howhard it is for Virtue tosuspect. Ah Ottavio ! we have been both deceiv'd; This vile Antonio is the very Man, To whom my Brother withoutmy Consent, il ºn . . . . . Or Knowledge has Comraded me in Flanders, Oğ. Antonio the Man to whomy are Qontračºd, , Porcia the Bride whom heiscome to Marry . . . . Por. The very same. º' ºr it is nº sº. o. oã. Why didyounot acquaint me with itsooncº F Por. Alas, I have not seenyousince I knew it; ; ºr But those Few hours such Wonders have produc'd, º, Assurpassall Belief, and do require . . . …o's y. . . . ~ More time, than your unsafe Cóndition herº cºop Will allowustomake you understand it. [...ºf po Cam. Dear Friends, scannotblameyour Apprehensions, Nor your suspition of Antonio's Friendship; . . . . . . But I'amsopossess'd with the Opinion ºf Iºnia Of his great Virtue, that Ishall assoon : ... v. ... . . Believe Impossibilities, ashis. ºf 2: . . . . . . // . - Apo"acie from Honour. … . . . . . . so º, ) Oä. What's her Concernment in Antamia, Potia 3 a , Por.Q. that's the strangest part of oursădstory; no Andwhich requires most time to telyº. . ," ... º.º.º.º.º. - i.e. “Window, and a noise within. ... Por. see, Flora; at the Window, what's that Light, ºf And Noise we hear.so tº yo, sº gº... ..., , , , º ºs º os-Esºta goes to the mindow. Flo. O'Madam we are all undone; I sce, rº, Henrique, Carlos, and their servants with Torches, Antonio - Allcominghither,and which wonderful, ..., `- - .º. - - - - N 2 - - ~ * ——

End of section 25. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 26
Page scan 116

,- - TZT ris Y. - . . . . -- " " The Adventures of Fiya Honº Antonio leading thens with his swº drawn. Wºlf's is . . . "... Tººlrºam’t, distraćted Wºnths, Asiangfalse?, It is impossibkº” , jºy toº ºf ji bºr woh ** .…" - : Lvi º; ºr, - nº.3, and tarning back says, zi... . All she has saidisiltappearance true sº ºf solº of T...sure somebºdón Mysłºry which thus glºvoº 10 Abuses us; fort shall net believg.º.º.º. ºi, can transgress the Rules of Friendship... "... " off. Friendship's an Empty Name , made to Deceive Those, whose Gºlwaturestampts them to believe sºo There's mosudythiºon Earth, the best that wee!A.º.º. " Canhopesophere is faint Neutrality...º.º.º. Tºpor. Ye Powers abovel what pleasure cat ye take: j : To persecute subshitting innºcence; sº ºf 1 ºrigs yº. Oğ. Retire, deafrºbraiay to that inăcristoomyo": i: ' '. Fößouldthy crucifroiier find thee herº ºf G.W. - Hessorevolted from Humanity, , ; º' ºr sº Helmingle thine, withm impurer Blood, ºr f 1:... por. That were a kindo Coñtia&#lethnicºme3 ; : () . Westmeet at once Marriage, and Martyrdom. In , , ºt off. soul of my Life retire. . . º ºil ºf , Por. £will flotleave you; , , , , , ..… . . oã. Thou preservist by saving of thy selfs:.C. .** For they can murder with (half of me; ºoyi si..jºbs. A hilst that my better patt furvives in thee. for. I will detoygāivisjo maintain, That differencauses form the same Eßsº … * Tiscourage in you Men, Love in ºxº slioz int. .nºw slº ºiodijotziesholdof her to leadher away. Oğ. Helpmcºmilaº As ºf y. cº-º-º/ Y.e., cam. You must be rul’d, yout Presence will increase ". . YourBrother's Fury, and Qāquio's Danger.º. Zºº;A. twº *. - 5 ºz. . - -- Por. * __*-*.*- - ~! *
Page scan 117

The Adventures of Five Hours, tº Por.That Argument is Irresistible.: , s: , . . . . . they retire to the other Room, and Qāayio. . . . . .313 waiişoathem to the doorºoH 35 ºf , ºf Die, Nay if you are at that,the Devil take ºf ºº The hindmost 3 'tis for your sake, dearest Flora, sº jº * , ºº is 3 tº ..[Taking Flora Wythe hand. I shun thcse HoHôtable Occasions, 13 ºf sºha goes out with Having no Weapon, sir, 'tis fit that I wº ºft's t March off withdhºbaggage. …, , , ... ii. o * j, , , , ~ ; : . . . . . . . . ºffix umpiegº, Flora; º Ośī. I'm now upon the Frontiers ºf this Life, (I A y There's but one step to Immortality; i ºri's wrºsłł. T. Añd though my cruclfortune has allow'd me . . . . . ºv. No other Witness of my Tragick end, sº - ... tººl of But my Inhumane Murtherers; yet my Deathi, Ao shall not Disgrace either my tº." tº sets of Toth'other Wörld this Hoflor:liwillbòars, ºf , , ...sº - That as I still have Liv'd, and Lov’d, solº ºw. I Encounter Death with the same Constancy...", / …, -" ºvº-º. º.º. ººlini: tº - - - Enter Antonio; Henrique, Čirić and Geraldo, with their . . .ess swords drawn, Antonio àefore thereft. ! .º. - º Ant. Where is the Man whose Insolence, and Folly. ... . Has thus misled him to Affront my Friend? . . . . . . . yº) • Oğ. Here is the Manthouseck's, and he, whºm thou? so basely hast Betráid: ; 12 y.º. EQétavio drairs, Ant. Oh Heavesis: what is't I see? it is OHavio, º My Friend, tºº.º. . . . . . . . . . . . . . oã. Nótthy Friend,üºntonio; but 'tis Qāavies ºt Who b thyrierfldie has beenbetraid * \ts soil. Hºriids To this forlörn Cºndition; but viløMan 3.2-gig of wºre Thou now shalt pay thy Treachery withthy Life, sº I - ‘. . . . . . . . . [O&tavio makes at Antonio. 2}}. - * - - J. " -- - Amt. ~ a - - - º - ~ *-
Page scan 118

The Adventures of Five Hours. Aside. - Aside. Ant. Holdoãavio; thoughtly injurious Error..." May transport thee, it shall not mebeyond. The Bounds of Honor; Heaven knowsil thought Of nothingless, than what I find, Oğavio In this place, sº " . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Heº. Whatpause is this, Antoniº all your Fervour In the Concernments of your Friend, reduc’d ' . ºr ". . To a tame Parly with our Enimy; . . - - Do all the Promises, you have made to me, sº * º Tafist my just Revenge, conclude in this? Off. Dö all the Promises you have made to me, ºo Tassist my Virtuous Love, conclude in this? . . . . . . . . . [. Hen.Where is your wontedBravery? where your Kindnek To such a near Allie 2: . . - * - oš Vhere isyourformer Honor where your Firmness To such an antient Friend? . . . - 2. Wºmiypifinaed Honorfleer Betwixt these equal, opposité Engagements Her what, demuthiinayºffrightmyself, º, º '…º {... O&avio, An- . • * * * * * > . . . . . . . …, - - - - ºltónio turns an O&avio's side, 4. Ant. Wh'attaques Ośavio must pass through mé. Carl. I must layhold on this Occasion. . . . . . . Good Cozin, I conjurgyoutorestrain . . . . . . . . . . Yöur Passion for a while, there does die hid o some Mystery'id this, which once unfolded, , , May possibly produce the Means of making, . - -- * That Reconcilable, whichnow seems Despirate. . Heur, sweetly propos'd, sir, an Accommodation Think'st thou my Anger's like a Fire of straw, ... . Onely to Blaze, and thenexpire in smoakº . . . . . . y Think'st thou I can forgºt my Name, and Nation, - Aid Barterfor Revenge, when Honor Bleeds His
Page scan 119

The Adventures of Five Hoars. – “---------- - --- His Life must pay this Insolence, or mine, 2, ..…I - [ He makes at O&avio º interpºsº, Amt. Mine must prote&his, or else perish with him, , , _Henr. since neither Faith, nor Friendship can preyail,. . . 'Tis time to trie what proof you are, Antonio, , , , , , Against your own near Intrest 3 Know, that Man, ; ; ). Whom you protećt sº my just Revenge, . . . . Has seconded his Insolence to me ..., tº By foul Attempts upon my sister's Honor; . . . . . " Your Porcia's sir, if this will not enflame you. ºf Porcia endeavours to come out, Camilla holds her." or. This Injury's beyond all sufferance. Carl. To what excess of Folly does our Rage [Aside. Transport us Men I this most Important scºret, Which Tortures could not have made him discover sº He (onely to advance his blind Revenge) … . . . Has now unforc’d declared to that ;, From whom, of allmen living, he ought most . . . . To have conceal’d it. . . -- " -- " ' ' ' OH. Howl I attemptyour sister's Honor Hºrique?, The Parent of your black Designs, the Devil, j . . Did nerinvent a mere malicious Falshood; - 'Tis true, that I have serv'd the Virtuous Porcia, - With such Devotion, and such spotless Love, That, though unworthy, yet she has been pleas'd : , , , , To recompence my Passion with Esteem : , º, . . . . By which, she has sochain'd me to her service, . . . . . . . . . That here I vow either to Live her Prize, Or if I Die, to fall Loves sacrifice. . . . . . . Ant. O Heavens ! what's that I hear?thoublessed Angel Guardian of Honor, I do now implore, - Thy powerful assistance to preserve . . . . That Reputation, which I hitherto. . . . by - - - - - -
Page scan 120

The Adventures of Five:Hours. | By virtuous Aaionshave maintain'd unblemish'd; ºf In vain, Don Henrique, you design to change - My Resolutions; it mustner be said, tºº. . . . . . . . That Passion made Antonio recede . . . . . . From the striót Rules of Honor ; sir, I tell you, ... . . . Nothing can make the violate my first . . . . . . Engagement. . . . .” - . . . . . . . . . . . Henr. Nay, then thou shalt Die too, Perfidious Man's - Ho! Geraldo, Pedro, Leonido. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Enter Geraldo, Pedro, Leonido, with their swords drawn, and joyn with Henrique; Carlos interposes. . . . . . Carl. For Heaven'ssake, Cozin, draw not on your self The horrid Infamy of Aslasinating tº wº, Persons of Noble blood by servić Hands, g : 1. . . . . Henr. Do you Defend then too? Kill'em Isay. . . . . . Ant. Retireoivio, I'l sustain their shock.” - OH. OHavio retire 2- . . . . . . º " . . . . . . . . . Ant. Trust me you must, they will surround us else; Through that härrow Passage they'l Affailus, ºi º Withless advaitagd. 1: . . ºf fºo:::::::::::::f cºhey retire fighting off the stage; Henrique * 2 and his Men persuing them, and Carlos. , , , , ; ; (endeavºuring to stup Don Henrique. . . . . . Henr. What dye give backºye Men of mighty Fame?" Ant. Don Henrique, you shall juickly find 'tis Honor , s , Not Fear makesmeretire, ºr ºf . . [Exeunt. - cº-ºº: ". . . . . . . … . . . . . . º Enterpresently Antonio and Oºtavio at another door, º, º f : . Hºwhich Antonio bolts. . . . . (). • * 4nt. Now we shall have a breathing while at least . . . . . Ottavio, and time to look aboutus; . . . . . . . Pºyse yon other door befast. . . . . . . . . . - - oãavio * - \ - *
Page scan 121

The Adventures of Five Hours. z Oétavio fiels to the door where they went out,and 3 Henrique bounces at the door they came in at. Henr. Geraldo, fetch an Iron Bar to force [Within. The door. - . - _r [ Camilla and Porcia peep out. Cam. Heaven has heard our Prayers;th’are both safe here. Por. Let's go to 'em Camilla. - - Cam. 'Tis better to stay here a while, and hearken What Resolution of themselves they take. - [Antonio goes to both the doors tosse if they befast. Amt. so, 'tis now as I could wish. . - Oğ. What do you mean, Generous Antonio 2 Ant. To Kill thee now my sclf, having perform'd What Pre-engagement did exact from me ' . In your Defence gainst Others; my Love now Requires its Dues, as Honor has had his; There's no Protećtion for you from my sword, But in your Own, or in your frank renouncing All Claim to Porcia; she is so much mine, " That none must Breath, and have the Vanity Ofa Pretender to her whilst I Live. Oā. My Claims to Porcia I shall ne'r renounce, But still assert them by all noble ways : Yet, sir, this hand shall never use a sword (Without the last Compulsion) gainst that Man, Who has so much Oblig'd me; no Antonio, “. You are securely Guarded by the Favours, You have conferr'd upon me. Ant. sir, let not your pretended Gratitude Enervate your Defence; 'tis not my custom To serve my Friends with Prospećts of Return 5 I therefore, sir, do freely here acquit you, From all the Obligations, you º pleas'd T w - Q z -
Page scan 122

* The Adventures of Five Hours. To own from me. N Off. You may, sir, if you please, forbear to add New Favours to my’ account; but you can never - substraćt those, which are past 3 and till that Debt Befully paid, I shall not dare t'appear - I’th' Lists against so Generous a Creditor. Ant. Your scruples are ill grounded; 'twas OHavio (Myantient Friend) whom I design'd to serve; Not that Disloyal Man, who has invaded My Honor, and my Love; “'Tis the Intent “Creates the Qbligation, not th' Event. oã. I call those Powers, who both Discern,and Punish, To witness for me, that I never knew Youe'r pretended to Don Henrique's sisler, Before I came within these fatal Walls: This I declare, onely to clear myself From th’Imputation of Disloyalty, And to prevent the Progress of your Error. Ant. How can I think you should speak Truth to me, Who am a Witnessy'have been False to her, To whom i. now profess so high Devotion. Oğ, Ifalse to Porcial take heed, Antonio, so foul an Injury provokes too much 3 But, sir, I must confess I owe you more, Than the Forgivness of onegross Mistake. Ant. Rare limpudence I I must not trust my senses. Oä. If we cannot adjust this Competition, Let us our Fortunes, not our Passions charge With this our breach of Friendship. - 4nt. Leave your Discourses, and Defend yourself; Either immediately Renounce all Claims. shaking his To Porcia ; or this must speak the rest. . . . . . . {: Oä. Nay, then, this must Reply. º [They fight. - They
Page scan 123

The Adventures of Five Hours. They without bounce at the door, • as if they were breaking it open. Por. Why do I doubt there is no means to save him From the present danger, but by another, ;. as great, but something more remote; l'I do't. . - {*. lst they fight, Porcia breaks from Camilla, and unbolts the door, then runs back into herplace. Enter Henrique, Carlos, Leonido, Geraldo, with their swords drawn. Hen. What's this : Antonio fighting with Oğavio ! This Bravery is excessive, Gallant Friends Not to allow a share in your Revenge Tº him, who's most concern'd; he must not die Without some Marks of mine. } Henrique makes at Oétavio, and Antonie - - turns to O&avio's side. Amt. Nay, then my Honor you invade anew, And by Assaulting him, Revive in mc My Pre-engagements of Prote&ing him Against all others. - * Hen. Wły were not you Antonio fighting with him * Were you not doing all you could to Kill him * Ant. Henrique, 'tis true; but finding in my breas, An equal strife'twixt Honor, and Revenge; I do in just compliance with them both Preserve him from your Rage, to Fall by mine. . - Carl. Brave Man, how Nicely he does Honor weigh'? . Justice her selfholds not the scales more Even. . Henr. My Honor suffers more as yet than yours, And I must have my share in the Revenge; Either he must renounce all º to Porcta, . O - 2 º
Page scan 124

The Adventures of Five Hours. - - Or Die immediately. . . . . - Ant. It is agreed; that he must Doe, or Die: “... But by no other hand, than mine., - . off Cease your Contention, and turn all your swords Against this Breast; whilst Porcia’and l have breath, she must be mine, there's no Divorce but Death. - - Henr. I'l hear no more, protećt him if thou cans Antonio. Kill the slave,kill him, Isay, .. - {Hºriº makes at him, and Carlos - “endeavours to enterpose. . . . . . Carl. For Heaven's sake hold a Moment 5 ccrtainly There's some Mistake lies hidden here, which clear'd , º, Might hinder these Extremes. . . . . . . . . º - - Henrique and his servants pres; , . . . . . . . Antonio and Qćtavio. . . . . . . cam. These Errors must be cleard, before they grow. … Toofatal, but I fear your Brother's fury - Will not admit of Reason. . . . . por. I’m sure I’ltry, though it should cost my life... - * - " ... "… “ . . * * * * * : ". Enter Porcia and Camilla from the Inner Room. 't Por. Don Henrique. - . . . . . . . cam. Antonio, Carlos. . . . . . . Por. Oétavio. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Camilla and) ºniº . . . . . . . . Porcia tº: Hear us but speak. - 'gether. - * -- ~ * Henr. Ha! how came she here 2, . Carl. Did not Itellyou that she was brought hither, By my Direétion; 2, you would not believe me, . . . . . Henr. But how then could OHavio come hither? Carl. Nay, that Heaven knows 3 you heard as well as I Your Man's Relation. . . . * • * : ~ Henr, * * * -
Page scan 125

The Adventures of Five Hours. - Henr. Ah thouvile Woman that I could destroy Thy Memory with thy Life. . . * . . . . ; , [He offers to run at Porcia, Antonio interposes. Amt. Hold, sir, that must not be. - • * Henr. What may not I do Justice upon her Neither 2 * * * Ant. No sir ; although I have not yet the Honor – To know who she's, I have this night engag’d - Myself, both to secure, and serve her. - - Carl. He knows not Parcia; who was i' the right. Don Henrique, You, or I?, . . . . . . . . Henr. He not know Parcia? whom not an hour since I saw, and spoke with, entertaining her . . . . In his Apartment 3 sure we are Enchanted, - Andall we see's Illusion. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . Cam. Allow ºº:: these Charms; , Who is't, Oñavio, you pretend to 2 speak. . . . . . . Oä. You might have spar'd that Question; since none Knows so well as you, 'Tis Portta I adore. . . . . . Ant: Porcia's my Wife; Disloyal Man that Dist. tº a . . . . . . . [Offers to make at Octavio. Cam. Hold sir; which is the Porcia you'claim too? Ant. Can you ben doubt of that 2 you know too well The Conquest, that you made so long ago ... . . - Of my surprized heart in Flanders. . . . . . - • 2 "... tº º Carl. Conquest! surpris d! Flanders! what can this mean? - *- ** * * * - * ------- - Henr. New Riddles every moment do arise, And Mysteries are born of Mysteries. . . . . Cam, Thanks be to Heaven,our workdraws near anchd; Cozin, it belongs to you to finish it. Por. To free you from that Labyrinth, Antonio, In which a slight Mistake, not Rećtifi’d, Has involv’dus all; know, th’suppos'd Porcia, - - : - - Whcm
Page scan 126

The Adventures of Five Hours. Whom you folong have lov’d,’s the true Camilla. cam. Andyou, Don Henrique, know, Oñavio Has always been your sister's faithful Lover; And º Feign'da Gallantry to me, His real Passion to Disguise from you. Oćtavio and Antonio run to awe 4- - nother and embrace. Amt. Generous Ottavio. - Oğ. Brave Antonio, how happy are we both ! Both in our Loves, and Friendships : Ant. Man's Joys done'r to their Perfeótion rise, Till when by Crosses heightned, they surprize. . . . % Camilla takes Antonio by the hand and leads him to Don Carlos. - Cam. This,tmy dear Brother,is that brave Commander, . To whom you owe your Life, and Liberty 3." And I much more, the safety of my Honor. . . . Carl. Is this the Gallant Leader, who rescu'd us . With so much Valour from th’Enemy's hands 2 Cam. The very same. - Carl. If you knew him so well, why did not you Acquaint me with it sooner?’twas a fault Camilla. - Cam. Alas, my dearest Brother, Gratitude sprawing car- Conspiring with the Graces of his Person, lº “f* so soon possess'd him of my Heart, that I Despairinger again to see him; and Asham'd of such a Visionary Love, Durst never trust my Tongue with my own Thoughts. . . 3. Carlos presents Camilla - to Antonio. - _ Carl.'Tiscnough. - Take here from me the Hand of her, whose Heart Heaven,
Page scan 127

The Adventures of Five Hours. Heaven, and your Merits have long since made yours Without my Knowledge; may her Virtue pay - some part of that, which we both owe to yours. , r * * {}. takes Porcia's hand, and kisses it with great respeš. - Ant. Here with your kave, and hers Iscal the Vows, - Of my Eternal Faith unto you both. - Carl. But let's take heed, Antonio, lest whilst we Are Joying in our mutual Happiness, Don Henrique's scarcely yet compos'd Distemper - - Revive not, and Disorder us afresh: I like not his Grim Posture ; you know well - After a Tempest, though the Wind be laid , There oftcn does remain for a good while A dangerous Agitation of the Waves; He must not yet be trusted with himself. Amt. 'Tis well thoughton, let us go to him. , Oétavio holding Porcia by the hand - - 3 advances towards Henrique. Oä. Here with Respećt we wait the Confirmation. Of Heaven's Decrees from your Indulgence, sir. This Lady, your Incomparable sister, . Can witness that I never did invade . Your Passion for Camilla; and Pedro's death Happen'd by yourmistaken Jealouse; - " The Causes of your Hate being now remov’d ..., 'Tis just, Pon Henrique, the Effects should cease. Henr. Ifhall cossult my Honor. . . . . Carl. You cannot take a better Counsellor In this Case, than you Own, and sister's Honor; . . . 'What, to secure them both, could have been wish'd Beyond what Fatehath of it self produc’d Henr. “How hard it is to A& upon Constraint. * * * * That,

Page scan 128

The Adventures of Five Hours. That, which I could have VVish'd, I now would Flie, since’tis obtruded by Necessity. . . . - Amt. Noble Don Henrique, make account of me . . . . To be as truly yours by this Alliance, - * , As if a Brother's Name subsisted still. s Henr. I must consent, I see,or worse will follow. [Aside. “He is a Foolwho thinks by Force, or skill “To turn the Current of a Woman's Will, . . . . since fair Camilla is-Antonio's Lot , . . . . . . 1 Porcia yield to Don Antonios Friend. . . Our strength, and Wisdom must submit to Fatc. . . . . stript of my Love, I will put off my Hatc. . . . . * * -- - {º: takes Porcia by the hand - and gives her to Oétavio. Here, take her hand; and may she make you, sir, Happier, than she has done me. . - - . . . . . . . . . . . [They all embrace, but Henrique coldly. Enter Diego and Flora from the inner Room. . . . Flo. Hadsuch Disorderse'r such a Come-off? Me-thinks 'twould make a Rare Plot for a Play. Die. Faith Flora, I should have the worst of that 3 For by the Law of Comedy 'twould be My Lot to Marry you. - |- Oš. Well thoughton, Diego, though spoken in Jest; We cannot do, I think, a better thin . . In Earnest, than to make them Two ion Hands. What say'st thou to it, Flora 2 * Flo. Indeed I have had so many Frights this night, That I am enafraid to lie alone. . . . . . . . . . . [Diego takes her by the hand. - Die. Give methy Hand Flora, it is a Bargain; . . . I promise thee, dear spouse, I'l do my best To

End of section 26. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents
section 27
Page scan 129

The Adventures of Five Hours. To make thee first Repent this Earnest Jest. Flo. That time shall trie, Carl. since this last happy scene is in my House, You'l make Collation withmce're we part? - - Amt. A . w - OH. greed, agreed, agreed. Pie. sir, you had best make haste, clfe what you call Collation, may prove a Breakfast, for 'tis , Near twelve a Clock. * -. w 4nt. Thus end the Rare Adventures of Five Hours; Assometimes Boisterous storms in Gentle showrs. THE EPILOGUE. Diego comes stealingin, and isfollowdby Henrique, who stays at the Door, and Listens. - .. * - . . . . . . . * * * ~ * Die.shCme Gentlemen - - J. Let the Dons and Monsieurssay what they will; For our parts, we are for Old Englandstill. Here's a fine Play indeed, to lay the scene - º * - 2 - - - - - - In three Houses of the same Tºwn, 9 mean: , . mºhy we have several plays, where I # * - - . . . . Th’ Devil to tell where the scene does lie : ºv, , , sometimes in Greece, and then they make astºp To Transilvania, thence at one Leap, , . . . . To Greece again; this shows a ranging Brain, mhich scorns to be confindt'a T.* in spain. Then
Page scan 130

The Adventures of Five Hour. - Then for the Plot; * - / The pºssible Adventures of Five Hours; - 4 copious Design, why’ in some of ours . . . . . . Many of th’ Adventures are impossible, Or if to be atchiev'd, no A.4am can tell Within what time; this shows a rare Invention, *hen the Design’s above your Comprehenson. mhilst here y are treated with a Romance Tale, - And a Plot cover'd mith a spanish Veil. As for the style; - - - It tº as easie 43 4 Proclamation, . . ," , i. º As if the Play were Pen'dforth' whole Nation. None of those thundring Pines, which use to crack Qur Breaths, and set your Wits upon the Rack. Who can admire this Piece, orthinki: good 2 s. º - There's not ºne Line, bat maybeuhdºñood. . . . . The Raillery; - 43 innocent, as if't had past the Teft . . . . º y . . . . of a full synod: hot one Baudy feast; ,1. Nor any of those words of Douélesense, -- hhich makes th' Ladies, to show their Innocence, #: sºlilºsºgºnik, The Gallant shows he understand; the Šºk. But here you have aziecessatty mºrit, ºs . . . . . . Asen must have hit themselves to find the wit: . . . . . . * - * - --- * = a- ". * -- . . . * * - . - - - Faith that's too much; thºre &y my consent, ºr . . . ‘. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . - * * * * * : * We'l Damn the Play. - ... . . . . . . . . . : ' ' ' . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . & - - - , , Henr. Think]: thou, Impºrtinent, . . . ; Pointingto The thºse who knºw the Pingrºfºssingingfºrth & hiº 4 Diving scene, shoulder diffrºy this hirih zºº ºf souther can want fuchiºriters, who affire sº Topleasethe judges of that upper Tire. * ** -
Page scan 131

The Adventures of Five Hours. , r The Knowing are his Peers, and for the rest Of the Illiterate Crowd (though finely drest) s The Author hopes, he never gave them cause To think, he'divase his Time for their Applause. - rou then (most equal judges) freely give rour Potes, whether this Play should Die, or Live. v THE EPI Lo Gu E AT Cou RT. M 7° Have pass'd the Lords, and Commons 3 and are come 2. W At length, Dread sir, to hear your Final Doom. ’sir true, Tour Vassals, sir, inay Vote the Laws, Their sanition comes from rour Divine Applause. 7 his shining Circle then will all sit Mute, - Till one pronouncefrom you, Le Royle Veut. :- - - º * - - s 2 * r- — - – - ~z. -". - s , ... " - ... " - º - * - - ~ \ F P N I s. - *- º- - 2. - - o: - - | * / * > - - - - - ~ r - - - _2~ A t *- - - A ~ - z / º - * }. 3-2. - - … w - w - - . *~ - ºx - - sº - - - - w - --- - | -- - . 2- - Y - - !. - - - - - - --- ~ ---- -
Page scan 132

---------|-|-|-__--|----- ：~ !|-|-·！！*！--~~~~;----±-----+----*-+-+-+---+---+---+---+---+----------------|-·---- ··|-|-|- |------ |-|- - -|-|×·· *|-|- |-·|-·|-·« m. |-·|-！|-·|-|-|- ·~|-· ,|\){' .· |-|-· ！, , !·- ~ ！， ！, ！^， ，----|-·---- •|--|-|-|- v·· ·|-· ·|-|-·|-×+·|- *|-|-· · ·a.·?·|-· v|· |-|-·|-|-_* ！|^|-|-*，|-+ ----|-， ， ,·||- |_ º _ •----·· · ·, ！|-|-|-|-- -|-• •|- |-----·|-！|- |- |--|-|-· -|！|-’,|-|-， , ，---- |--* .·\ \----， !+|-|×|-|-|-… ， ----~· *)•|-- ,, '… *|-|-|-»--（ \ ） --·|-·····' …·|-|--zº,||-…- ·|-|-|-|-|-· ---- |-(..|-}* -|-|-* -*|-·· |·|-*·-！\，* |-|-·|-·····|-·|-----· ·· · · · · ·----… -|-•|-, , ，* .|-|-• , · · · ·|-·- - -·…"! -|-|-|-|-|-· -|-|-·| ， ,· ！ 1· |-， ， ，， , , · *|-* «||-^|-}· |-|-_-^ · |-- · ·|--- «|-·· ,|×|-|-·|-|-，|-v-- sº ···|-, ！·|-|-|-·|-|- |-·, ！*|-|-|-- ）|-, ,-*|-~|- |-|-|-·|--|-|-----|-|-|- - -|-|-|-|----- |- ·|-|× |-|-·---- v* ：----·|-|-|- |-|-|-% ----- ,- .·， ！· *|-|-r.---- |-… ' , '！|- |-！,^， ， ·|-··|-|-|-|-|- |-\|-·|-|-|-|- |-|-}·（ ） v.|-·→ ·|-|-- -|-}|-|-|-·- -|-. --+ |-|-|-|-！|-' ,|-+… w ···-• • •|-|-！ |-|--·|-' ~| |-|-··- -：|- |- ----\- ：, ， ,··.*·/|-|-|-|-|-|-m.(）|- ·----·|------~| .sae·， .|--|- ----|-|-·!|- |-|-|- |-|--！|-y |-|-，|-|-|-\-|- ··--------/.-----|-|-. ^！ »| } -}, |-·|-|-， ,|--|-|-|-|-·-|- --*|-|-！|-|-|-|-·\|-|-`-|-|-|-！ |-|-··|-·|-·|-！|-|-·！ ----|-|---|-~ ··----|-|-·|-… •|-----\/* -- „ -|-- --·|-, ！|-«^*|-- - | 9|- --------- -· ·|-|-|-·' ， ！· ·\|-|-|-|-|-|-,^·• 1, *|× |-|-|-|-|- • • • • ~ .|-- N.\， ，* · * *· ·|-, ， , º|-** .· |- |-·|---------, -|-\|-* …|-|-！|- |- , -|-|-•·|-|-|--• .··|-·|-！|- -|-·r.. ^+, -----|-*-·|-|-* …vº, •· · · · · ·|-- -|- |-}，·• ， !+|- ·|- ·|-A |-, -|-|-， ，|-*- - |-|-|-|-|- ··|-|-|-|-|-- |- |-··, ，}v v- ， ！ ·|-/·|-|-|-!|- ！----！！|-, ，·----+ ·|-|-/|-|- |-|-|-|--|-·|-*·· |-· • ¶|- |-·， , ， ，- · -|-|-!··|- |-~ !ae→ ·---- |-… ~~|\. "···, ！/|-, ,·|-|- |-----~~|-|-·，, ，• •|-|-·|-|-·！ |-|- |-|-|-·|-, !*|-·'s,|-|-|-|- ~~ ~~- -…|-|-|-|-| .|-·· --' ， .→|-·~,* ...’|-|- ·|- * _ ·.*， ,|-|-|-… *|-|-|-|- |-~· !|·… …|-|-|-|-|-|- |- ·-|-*|-v.|-·|-|-|- |-----, ！· · --|-, ，·|-|- ··|-----·|-|-·-·|-|-|-|- ·|-|-|-----|-|-*|-|-----|-|× |-·! -· · · -|-， ！|-|-|-|- |-» I !- -|-· *, ！|-， ， ， .·~\· -|-|--* ,|-|× |-|-, ，·|-·|-·' .* -·|-· · ·|-ae* … ]|-- º|- -|-·|-·|- --* * *· · · ·， ，· · · · *|· ， , .'. ,， ， ， ， ， ， ,<! -* -|-|-|- |- ··|-||-|- ·|-|-'-, ，|-* -|-|- |-·, ！\ ^·~|----- - -|-|- |-，|-• , ！|- |-|- ：||-·T •|- |-|- ----|-v;！·|-|-··|-···1'|×|-|- -- -|-|*|-*|- |-|-·|-|- |-|-， , ， ，|- |-·----|-|-/· |- ·|-{|-|-\|- - -|-|-|-|-|-|-|- »·• |-|-* |-|-|-|-|-|- - |-！ -• ！|----－r ' ），|-|×··|×\： ~| ~ ----|-|- |-|-·*·→ ·|-}]|- |-·|-···-|- ， ！/-|- -|-+|-|-··- -·！ ! \·|-- ----|-|-|-| ·！-!· ·|-* -:-|-·|-|-·|-·|-|-|-， ！|×· \|-|-|-|-·|-}, !} • »|-*|-----|×\ ·|--·} ）•*|-|--·* |-→ ·|- ·|-|-|-|-· ·|-·|- -<|-|-|- |-|-|-|-|-|-|- |-|-·|-; |- - - ~ º - ---- - - * - - - - - º - w - - º - - r_ - - - -- - - -- / - - |- |-·- ,· |×|-· |-·|- |-|-~~ ~|-|- |- i|-·|- -· v.|-|-， !-1* ,：|-|-· /· |-·|-|-|-|-- … |-----|-|-|-|- |-* ,|-|-|-|- |-~,· ~ . ~|-|~ ·|-|- ·|-|-… / -|- ·|- ----|-|×*}：· |-|- |-|-~ .… • ¡ ¿{·！ |-|--»， ， , }*|-·|- |-|- |-+-|-|- |- ·|- |- |-|- |-·· |-|- ||-|-/* |-|- ·|-



Page scan 133

Blank page
Page scan 134

Blank page
Page scan 135

Blank page
Page scan 136

Blank page
Page scan 137

Blank page
Page scan 138

---- ！ ----v！！！!！ae ŹN/（\&\\?\（\））（\\\/,'\\$\.\?\!\.\， ---- -

Page scan 139

sº-JV-7-7 z_v. N2–N. N. sº, sr. v. Nº, N, NY, -Y-V, V, x-vº-vº ºrrºr- -Mºw ！！！！！！！！！！!！-：-！ ， saesae|-|- |- -| vºv Wºw ------- --- scºtz, KººV-7-7R - vºw -> ºv. N } }， } ș)

Page scan 140

Blank page

This page contains an image.

End of section 27. Continue to next section or go to Table of Contents

End of text. Return to beginning.
