
Skip to main content

    Internet Archive Logo
    web
    books
    video
    audio
    software
    images
    search

    uploadUPLOAD
    personSIGN IN

    ABOUT
    CONTACT
    BLOG
    PROJECTS
    HELP
    DONATE
    JOBS
    VOLUNTEER
    PEOPLE

Full text of "A cure for a cuckold : a pleasant comedy, as it hath been several times acted with great applause"
See other formats

■-W-



r . / :m


mm




tv ,S, tiZfSS-»’ -'

.;- tfy'/f&km


H&ssf






O - JZ /o 1540 Webster (J.) and W. Rowley, A Cure for a Cuckold, a pie

sant Comedy *













































I














I




\


JN







¥






•\


/













I




t


'f


*


S





' ■ - • V


V


I





'


r








\








‘


/









1


i













\




i






i











t










*


t




✓










/



A PLEASANT '

COMEDY,

As it bath been feveral times A died
with great Applaufe.


Written by John V V ebster and
Willi am Rowley.


Wlacere Qufio.


/

London , Printed by Tho. Jobnfon, and are to be fold by France
Kirk m * n » a£ his S ^°P at c ^ e S ’g n °f ?**>» Fletchers Head,
over againft the Angel-Inne, on the Back-(ide of
St. Clements, without TmfU-Sttn i66u

&













The Stationer, to the Judicious Reader.

Gentlemen,

I T was not long fince / was onely a Books Reader, and net a Book -
feller , which Quality {my former Employment fomewhat fail¬
ing, and 1 being unwilling to be idle ) / #0?? lately taken

on me. It hath been my fancy and delight (ere fince l knew any
thing) to converfe with Bosks ; and the pie a jure / have taken in thofe
of this nature^ (viz,. Plays) hath bin fo extraordinary, that it hath
bin much to my cofl ; for I have been (as we term it) a Gatherer of
Plays for fame years , and lam confident 1 have more of feveral
forts than any man in England, Books feller, or other : I can at any
time (hew 700 in numbtr , which is within a fmall matter all that were
ever printed. Many of thefe 1 have feveral times ever, and intend
as / fell, to pur chafe more ; All, or any of which, I (hall be ready ei¬
ther to fell or lend to you upon reafenable C onfiderations.

In order to the wereajing of my Store , I have now this Team)
printed andpublifhed three, viz. This called A Cure for a Cuckold,
and another called. The Thracian Wonder ; and the third called.
Gammer Gurtons Needle. Two of thefe three were never p anted,
the third, viz. Gammer Gurtons Needle, hath bin formerly print¬
ed, but it is almoft an hundred years fince. As for this Play, I need
not fpeak^any thing in its Commendation, the Authors names , Web-
fter and Rowley* are ( to knowing men ) fufficlent to declare its
worth : feveral perfons remember the A Ring of it, and fay that it
then p/eafed generally well ; and let me tell you, in my judgement it is
an excellent old Play. The Expedient of Curing a Cuckold^aftsr the
maner fet down in this Play} hath bin tried to my knowledge , and
therefore I may fay Probatumeft. / jhould , I doubt, be too tedious, or elf e I
would fay fomewhat in defence of this , and in Commendation o/Plays in general,
lut I quejlion not but you hav: read what abler Pens than mine have writ in
their Vindication. Gentlemen , I hope* you will fo incourage me in mj beginnings,
that I may be induced to proceed to do you fervice , and that I may frequently have
occafion in this nature, to fubferibe my felj


Your Servant,

Francis Kirkman.





Dramatis Perfonae,


vv°.tf a Juflice of the Peace, Father to An*


Franck ford a Merchant, Brother in Lav to Woodroff.
Lcfsingham a Gentleman, in love with Clare.

Bonvile a Gentleman, the Bridegroom and Husband to
Annabel.

Raymond^

Fuji ace,

Fycnel, and
Grovcr y '

Rcchjield 5 a'

Cernpafs 3 a Sea-man*

Vodfcf ' an<J } two Attorneys.

A Connection


Gallants invited to the Wedding,


oung Gentleman, and a Thief.


Two clients ,

Two Boys. - ■ Vf

A Saylor.

Luce Wife to Franck^ford, and Sifter to Weodroff.
Annabel the Bride, and Wife to Bonvile.

Clare 5 Lefsingham's Miflrifs.

Urfe^ Wife to Cowpafs.

Nurfe

%A Waiting-woman*





A Cur i








A Cure for a Cuckold.


ACT I. SCENE I.

Enter LejJin^ham and Clare.

Lejf. >my^His is a place of feafting and of joy, and as in Tri*
8 umphs and Ovations here, nothing fave Hate and

B pleafure.

Clarey ’Tis confcft.

Lejf. A day of Mirth and folemn Jubile.

Clare. Forfuch as can be merry.

Lejf. A happy Nuptial, fince a like pair of Fortunes fuitablc L
equality in Birth , parity in years, and in afre&ion no way
different, are this day Tweedy coupled.

Clare. Tis a Marriage.

Lejf. True Lady , and a noble prcfident
me thinks for us to follow : why fhould thefe out-ftrip us in our
loves, that have not yet out-gone us in our time.

If we thus loofe our beft , and not to be recovered hours unpro-
fitably fpent , we Thai! be held meer Trewants in Loves fchool.

Clare . That's a ftudy in which I never fhail ambition have to
become graduate. :

Lejf. Lady, you are fad:

this Jovial Meeting puts me in a fpirit to be madefuch.

We two are Guefts invited , and meet by purpofe, not by acci¬
dent ; where’s then a place more opportunely fit, in which wc
may folicite our own Loves, than before this example ?

Clare. In a word, I purpofe not to marry
Lejf' By your favor, for as I ever to rhis prefenc hour have ftr-
died your obferv nce, fo from henceforth I now will ftudy
plainnefs , I have .oved you beyond my felf, mis-fpendedfor
your fake man/ a fair hour, which might have been imployed to
pleafure, or to profit, have negle&ed duty to them from whom
my being came, rnypa-ents; but my hopeful ftadies moft.

I have ftol’n time from all my choice delights, and robb'd my

B fclf,.


kA Curt for a Cuckold •

felf, thinking to enrich you. Matches I have had offered , fome
have told me as fair, as rich, I never thought ’em fo, and loft all
thefe in hope to finde out you , refolve me then for Chriftian
charity. Think you an Anfwerof that frozen nature is a fuffici-
ent fatisfa&ion for fo many more then needful fervices?

Clare. I have faid, Sir.

Lejf. Whence might this diftafte arife ? Be at lea ft fo kinde
toperfeft mein that: Isitoffome diflike lately conceived of
this my perfon, which perhaps may grow from calumny and fean-
dal ? if not that, fome late received Melanchol) in you : if nei¬
ther, yourperverfe and peevifh will, to which I moft imply it;

Clare . Be it what it can, or may be, thus it is ,

And with this Anfwer pray reft fatisfied.

In all thefe travels, windings, and indents,

Paths, and by-paths which many have fought out,

There’s but one onely road, and that alone
To my fruition ; which who fo Andes out,

Tis like he may enjoy me: but that failing,

I ever am mine own.

Lejf. Oh name it, Sweet. Iam already in a Labyrinth until
you guide me out.

Clare . lie to my Chamber,

May you be pleafed, unto your mis-fpent time
To adde but fome few minutes. By my Maid
You fhall hear further from me.

Lejf. lie attend you.

What more can I defire, than be refolv’d
Of fuch a long fufpence. Here’s now rhe period
Of much expedition.

Raym . What? you alone
Retired to privacy,


Exit,


Enter Raymond, Euftace,Lyonel ,
and Grover , Gallants.


Of fuch a goodly confluence, all prepared
To grace the prefent Nuptials ?

Lejf. I have heard fome fay, men are ne’re lefs alone, then
when alone, fuch power hath meditation.

Euft. Oh thefe choice Beauties that are th ; s day affemMed !
But of all, fair Miftrifs Clare , the Bride excepted Hill , fhe bears
away the prize.

Lytn,










\A Cure f»r « Cuckold ,. ^

Ljon. And worthily; for,fcttingoffherprefeac melancholly,
/he is without taxation.

> Grov. I conceive the caufe of her fo fudden difeonrent.

Raym. ’Tis far out of my way.

Grov. lie (peak it then : In ail eftates, profeflions, or degrees
in Arts or Sciences, there is a kinde of Emulation ; likewife fo
in this: There’s a Maid this day married, a choice Beauty. Now
Mr s.CW, a Virgin of like Age, and Fortunes correfpondenr,
apprehending time loft in her that’s in another gained, may upon
this. For who knows womens thoughts g rovv i nco t ^ s ^ ee p
nefs ? Raym. Like enough.

Lejf. You are pleafant, Gentlemen,

Or clfe perhaps, though 1 know many have purfued her Love,
Grov . (And you amongft the reft) with pardon Sir,

Yet (he might caft fome more peculiar eye
On fome that not refpe&s her. Enter Wayting-

Lejf. That’s my fear which you now make woman,
your fport.

Worn, A Letter, Sir. ' Lejf. From whom >

Worn, My Miftrifs.

Lejf, She has kept her promife, and I will read it, chough I
in the fame knovy my own death included.

Worn, Fare you well, Sir. Exit.

Lejf. Prove all thy friends, finde out the heft and neareft ,

Kill for my fake that Friend that loves thee dear eft.

Her fervant, nay her hand and character,

All meeting in my ruine! Read agen,

Prove all thy Friends , finde orn the heft and neareft }

Kill for my fake that Friend that loves the dear eft.

And what might that one be ? Tis a ftrange difficulty.

And it will ask much councel. Exit Lejf

Raym. Lejfingham hath left us on the fudden.

Euft. Sure the occafion was of that Letter fent him.

Lyon. It may be it was fome Challenge.

Grov. Challenge, never dream it: ' Enter Woodroff, Anabel ,

Are fuch things fent by women l Bonvile , Francftjord ,

Ra )r ». ’Twere an Herefie luce, and Kurfe.

To conceive but fuch a thought.

B i Lyon.


A Cun for d Cuckold.

Lyon. Tufh, all the difference
Begot this day, rauft be at night decided
Betwixt the Bride; and Bridegroom. Here both come.

Wood. What did youcall the Gentleman we met
But now in fome diftra&ion ?

Bon. Lejfmgham: A moft approv’d and noble friend of mine
and one of our prime Guefts.

Wood. He feemed to me

Somewhat in minde diftemper’d. What concern]

Thofe private humors ours fo publick Mirth
In fucb a time of Revels ? Midrib Clare,

I mil's her too. Why Gallants, have you iuffered her
Thus to be loft amongft you*?

Anna. Dinner done, unknown to any, fire retir’d her felf.

IVood. Sick of the Maid perhaps, becaufe fne fees
You Miftrifs Bride, h^r School- and Play-fellow
So fuddeniy turned Wife.

Francks ’Twas (hrewdly gueft.

Wood. Go hnde her out: Fie Gentlemen, within
The Muhck playes unto the filent walls,

And no man there to grace it: when I was young,

At fuch a Meeting I have fo beftir’d me,

Till I have made the pale Green-ficknefs Girls
Blufh like the Rubie , and drop pearls apace
Down from their Ivory fore-heads : In thofe days
I have cut Capers thus high. Nay, in Gentlemen,

And (ingle out the Ladies.

Raym. Well advifed. Nay Mrs. Bride, you (hall along with
us • for withour you all’s nothing.

Anna. Willingly, with Mr. Brideg r ooms leave.

Bon. Oh my bed Joy , this day I am your fervanr.

Wood. True, this day ; (he his,her whole life after, fo it fhould
be : onely this day a Groom to do her fervice , for which the full
remainder of his age he may write Maher. I have done it yet,
and fo I hope Rill fhall do. Siller Luce , may 1 p elume my bro¬
ther Franckford can fay as much, and truly ?

Luce. Sir, he may, I freely give him leave.

Wood. Obferve that brother, fne freely gives you leave ;

But


A Cure for a Cuckold.

But who gives leave, the Matter or the. fervanc } ^ ; •

Franck: You *r pleafant, and it becomes you well, but thfs
day molt; that having but one Daughter, have beftowed her to
your great hope and comfort.

Wood, I have one : would you could fay fo, Sitter; but your
barrennefs hath given your husband freedom, if he pleafe, to feek
his pi IF me elfewhere.

Luce. Well, well brother, though you may taunt me that have
never yet been blett with iffue, fpare my husband pray , for he
may have a By-blow, or an Heir that you never heard of.

Franck- Oh he wife, make not my fault toopublick.

Luce Yet htmfel-f keep within compafs.

Frarckj If you love me, Sweet. Luce, Nay I have done.
Wood. But if he have not, Wench, I would he had , the hurt
I wifh you-both. Prithee, thine ear a little.

Nurfe. Your boy grows up, and ’tis a chopping Lad,

A man even in the Cradle. Fran. Softly Nurfe:

Nurfe-. One of the forward!! infants, how it will crow
And chirup like a Sparrow ! I fear fhortly it will breed teeth’,
you mutt provide him therefore a Corral, with a Whittle and a
Chain. Fran. He fhall have any thing.

Nurfe. He’s now quite out of Blankets.

Fran . There’s a Piece, provide him what he wants, onel'y
good Nurfe prithee at this time be filenc.

Nurfe, A Charm to binde any Nurfes tongue that’s living.

Wood. Come, we are mitt among the younger Frye,

Gravity oft-times becomes the fports of youth, efpecially
Acfuch Solemnities, and it were (in

Not in our Age to fhow what we have bin. Exeunt.

Enter Lefsingham fad, with a Letter in hit hand .

Lsff, Amichia nihil dedit natura ma us nec rdrms ,

So faith my Author. If then powerful Nature in all her boun¬
ties fhowred upon mankinds, found none mox rare and precious
than this one we call Friendfhip , oh to what a Monttsr would
- this rrans-fhape me, to be made that he to violate fuch gcodnefs!
To kill any had been a fad Injun$ion , but a Friend ! nay, of all
Friends the moft approved l A Task, hell till this day could ne¬
ver parallel: And yet this woman ha’s a power of me beyond all

ver-


A Curt ftr d cucktld.

vertue, vertue, almoft grace. What might her hidden purpofc .
be in this ? unlefs fhe apprehend fomefantafie that no fuch thing
ha’s being : — and as kinred and claims to Crowns are worn ouc
of the world, fo the name Friend ? ’T may be Twas her conceit.

1 have tryed thofe that have profeffed much for coin; nay fome-
times (lighter courtefies, yet found ’em cold enough, •— fo per¬
haps (lie, which makes her thus opinion d.-If in the former,

and therefore better days, 'twas held fo rare, who knows but in
chcfe lad and Worfer times, it may be now with juftice banifhc
th* earth. I ’m full of thoughts, and this my troubled breft di-
ftemper'd with a thoufand fantafies, fomething I mud refolve.
Tie firft make proof if fuch a thing there be; which having found,
’Twixc Love and Friendfhip 'twill be a brave Fight,

To prove in man which claims the greateft right.

Enter Rdymondy Euftace. Lyonel^ And Grover .

Raym. , What, Mailer Lefsingham l
You that were wont to be compos’d of mirth,

All fpirit and fire-- Alacrity it felf, like the luftre of a late

bright (Lining Sun, now wrapt in clouds and darknefs!

Lyon. Prithee be merry,

Thy dulnefs fads the half part of the houfe,

And deads that fpirit which thou waft wont to quicken,

And half fpent to give Life too.

Lejf. Gentlemen,fuch as hare caafe for fport, I (hall wtfh ever
To make of it the prefent benefit
While it exifts.—Content is ftill fhort breathed,

When it was mine I did fo. If now yours,

I pray make your beft ufeon’e.

Lyon. Riddles and Paradoxes:

Come, come, fome Crotchecs come into thy pate,

And I will know the caufeon’c.

Grov . So will I, or I proteft ne’re leave thee.

Eufl. ’ Tis a bttfinefs proper to my felf, — one that concerns
no fecond perfon.

Grov . How's that ? not a friend ?

Lejf. Why, is there any fuch }

Grov. Do yeu queftion that ? what do you take me for ?

EhJI. I Sir, or me ? ’Tis many monechs ago fince wc betwixt

us


A curt fir 4 CUfkfli.

us interchang’d that name, and of my part ne’re broken?

Lyon. Troth, nor mine.

Rajrn, If you make queftion of a Friend, I pray
Number not me the 1 aft in your accompt,

That would be crown’d in your opinion firft.

Lijf. You all fpeak nobly. Butamongft you all
Can fuchaonebe found ? 1

Raym. Not one amongft,us, but would be proud to wear the
chara£ler of noble Friendfhip.. In the name of which, and of all,
us here prefent, I intreat,expofe to us the grief that troubles you *

Lejf. Ifhall, and briefly : If ever Gentleman funk beneath
fcandal, or his reputation never to be recovered, fuffered, and
for want of one whom I may call a Friend , then mine is now in
danger.

Raym. 1’Ie rede^m’t, though with my lifes dear hazard.

£«/?. I pray Sir, be to us open-breafted.

Lejf'. Then ’tis thus: There is to be performed a Monamachy-
Combat, or Duel, Time, Place, and Weapon agreed betwixt
us. Had it touche my felf , andmyfelf onely, I had then been
happy ; but I by compofition am engag’d to bring with me my
Second, and he too, not as the Law of Combat is , to (land aloof
and fee fair play , bring off his friend, but to engage his perfon ;>
both tnuft fight, and either of them dangerous.

Etiji . Of all things, I do not like this fighting.

Lejf, Now Gentlemen, of this fo great a courtefie
I am at this inftant meerly defticute. Raym. The dme.

Lejf. By eight a clock to morrow.

Raym. How unhappily things may fall out, I am juft at that
hour upon feme lace conceived Difcontents, to atone me to my
father, otherwife of all the reft you had commanded me your
Second, and your Servant.

Lyon, Pray the Place ? Lejf\ Callis-Sands.’

Lytn. It once was fatal to a friend of mine, and a near kinf-
man, for which I vowed then, and deeply too, never to fee that
ground : But if it had been elfewhere, one of them baa before
mine been worms-mear.

GYcv. What’s the weapon ? Lejf. Single-fword.

Grev. Of all that you could name,

. A thing


A Curt for a catffld.

A thing I never praftis’d,—* Had it been Rapier— or that, and
Ponyard, where men ufe rather Height chan force,I had been then
your Man ; being young, I drained the dnews of my arm, dnee
then to me ’twas never ferviceable.

Euft. In troth Sir, had it been a money-matter,

I could have flood your friend, but as for fighting
I was ever out at that. Exetm GalUnts.

Lejf \ Weil, farewel Gentlemen,

But where’s the Friend in all this ? tufh, fhe’s wife,

And knows there’s no fuch thing beneath the moon:

I now applaud her judgement.

Box. Why how now friend, thisDifcontent which now
Is fo unfeafon’d, makes me quefiion what
I ne’re durd doubt before, your Love to me, _)

Doth it proceed from Envy of my Blifs
Which this day crowns me with ? Or have you been
A fecret Rival in my happinefs ?

And grieve to fee me owner of thofe Joys,

Which you could with your own ?

Lejf: Banifhfuch thoughts.

Or you fhall wrong the trued faithful Friendfhip
Man e’rc could boad of, oh mine honor, Sir,

’Tis that which makes me wear this brow of lorrow:

Were that free from the power of Calumny.

But pardon me, that being now a dying
Which is fo near ro man, if part we cannot
With pleafant looks.

Bon. Do but fpeak the burthen, and I proted to take it off from
you, and lay it on my felf.

Lejf. * Twere a requed, impudence without blu'King could not
ask, it bears with it fuel] injury.

Bon. Yet mud I know’c*;

Lejf. Receive it then.— But I increac you dr, not to imagine
that I apprehend a thought to further my intent by you, from you
’tisleaft fufpe&ed. - ’Twas my fortune to entertain a Quar¬
rel with a Gentleman, the Field betwixt us chdleng’d,-—

place and time, and thefe to be performed not without Secon is.
I have rely’d on many feeming friends, but cannot blefs my me-

. 1


Enter Bon -
vile.







A (jure for * cuckold

mory with one dares veneer in my Quarrel.

Bon. Is this all >

Lejf. It is enough to make all temperature

Convert to fury.-Sir, my Reputation

(The life and foul of Honor) is at ftake,

In danger to be loft.— The word of Cowtrd
Still printed in the name of Lefsingbam.

Bon. Not whil^ there is a %onviler— May I live poor,

And die defpifed, not having one fad friend .

To wait upon my Hearfe , if I furvive
The ruine of that Honor.—Sir, the time ?

Lejf. Above all fparc me— for that once known,

You’l cancel this your promife , and unfay
Your friendly proffer.— Neither can I blame you,

Had you confirmed it with a thoufand Oathes,

The Heavens would look with mercy, not with juftiee
On your offence, flhould you enfringe 'em all.

Soon after Sun-rife upon Cattis-frtndf,

To morrow we fhould meet— now to deferre
Time one half hour, I fhould but forfeit all.

But Sir, of all men living, this alas
Concerns you leaft; — For fLall I be the man
To rob you of this nights felicity,

And make your Bride a Widow,— her foftbed
No witnefs of thofe joys this night expefts ?

Bon . I ftill preferre my friend before my pleafure,

Which is not loft for ever—-but adjourned
For more mature employment.

Lejf. Will you go then ? Bon. I am refolved I will.

Lejf. And inftantly? Bon. With all thefpeed celerity can mj&e.

Lejf. You do not* weigh thofe inconveniences this Action
meets with.— Your deparrure hence will breed a ftrange diftra-
dYion in your friends, diftruft of Love in your fair vertuous Bride,
whofe eyes perhaps may never more be bleft with your dear fight!
finee you may meet a grave >and that not amongft your noble An-
ceftors, but amongft ftrangers, almoft enemies.

Bon , This were enough to fihake a weak refolve,

It moves no: me. Take horfc as fecretly

C - As





Kji Cure fgr 4 Cuckold.

As veil well may: my Groom fhali make mine ready
With aU fpeed poffible, unknown to any. Enter Annabel.
Leff. But Sir, the Bride.

An. Did you not fee the Key that’s tounlock my Carckaaet
and Bracelets ? Now in troth I am afraid *tis loft*

No Sweet » Iha'c: I found it lye at random in your

Chamber, and knowing you would mifs it, laid it by: ’cis fafe I
warrant you.

An. Then npy fear's paft: but till vou give it back, my Neck
and Arms are flill your Prifoners.

Ben. But you ftiall findc they have a gentle Jaylor.

An. So I hope. Within y’are much enquired of.

Bon. Sweet, I follow. Dover !

Lejf. Yes, that's the place.

By. If you be there before me, hire a Barque, I fhali not fail
to meet you. Exeunt.

Lejf. Was ever known a man fo miferably bleftasl ? I have*
have no fooner found the greateft geod,man in this pilgrimage of
Life can meet, but I muft make the womb where ’ewas concei¬
ved, the Tomb to bury it, and the firft hour it lives.

The laft it muft breath ? Yet there’s a Fate

That fways and governs above womans hate. Exit.

Explicit . Ail. 1 .


Afttu feemdus. Seen* prim*.

Enter Rochfield a young Gentleman.

Jtoch. A Younger Brother ? ’tis a poor Calling fthough not
X A. unlawful) very hard to live on; the elder fool inhe¬
rits all the Lands, and we that follow Legacies of Wit, and get
em when we can too. Why {would Law (if we be lawful and
legitimate ) leave us without an equal divident ? Or why com¬
pels it not our Fathers elie to ceafe from getting , when they
want to give ? No fure, our Mothers will ne're agree to that,
they love to groan , although the Gallows eccho and groan to-
, gether for us. Fr^m the firft we travel forth, t’other’s our jour¬
neys end. I muft forward, to beg is out of my way, and bor-

' rowing






Acurt fpr 4 CutkfU.

rowing is out of date : The old road, the old high-way *c mud
be, and I am in'c, the place will fervefora yong beginner, for
this is the firft day I fee ope (hop; fuccefs then fwcet L , enter nn ,
I have heard that Thieves adore thee for a Deity. Emr Annabel
I would not purchafe by thee, but to ear, andafervavt.

And Vis too churlifo to deny me meat.

Soft, here may be a booty.

An. HorPd, fayed thou ?

Ser. Yes Miftrifs, with "Leflingham. - ' . . v

An . Alack,I know not what to doubt or fear, I know not well
whether’t be well or ill: but fure it is no cudom for the Groom
to leave his Bride upon the Nuptial day. I am fo yong and igno¬
rant a Scholar, yes, and it proves fo : I talk away perhaps that
might be yet recovered. Prithee run, the fore-path may advan¬
tage thee to meet ’em, or the Ferry which is not two miles be¬
fore, may trouble ’em until thou corned in ken, and if thou doft,
prithee enforce thy voice to overtake thine eyes, cry out, and
crave for me but one word Tore his departure. 1 will not day
him, fay, beyond his pleafurc; nor rudely ask the caufe, if he be
willing to keep it from me. Charge him by all the love. But I
day thee too long. Run, run.

Ser. If I had wings I would fpread ’em now, Miftrifs. Exit.

An. He make the bed fpeed after that I can,

Yet I am not well acquainted with the path:

My fears I fear me will mifguide me too. Exit #

Rock. There’s good moveables I perceive, what ere the ready
Coin be , who ever owns her, foe’s mine now: the next ground
has a mod pregnant hollow for the purpofe. Exit

Enter fervant running over . Enter Annabel^ftcrher Rochfield.

An. I’m at a doubt already where I am.

Roch. lie help you, Miftrifs, well overtaken.

An. Defend me goodnefs. What are you? Rock. Amin;

An. An honed man, I hope.

Roch. In fome degrees hot, not altogether cold.

So far as rank poifon , yet dangerous

As I may be dred: I am an honed thief. ,

An. Honed and Thief hold finali affinity, 1 never heard they
were a kin before, pray Heaven I findeit now.

v -x • Ci Rock.


A Cure for a Cue held.

Rock I tell you my name.

An. Then honeft thief, fince you hare taught me fo, for He en¬
quire no other, ufe me honeftly.

Rocb. Thus then lie ufe you : Firft then to prove me honeft,
I will not violate your Chaftiry, (that’s no part yet of my profef-
fion ) be you Wife or Virgin.

An. I am both, Sir.

Rock This then it feems fhould be your Wedding-day, and
thefe the hours of interim to keep you in rhac double ftate. Come
then, lie be brief, for lie not hinder your defired Hymen : You
have about you fome fuperfluous Toys, which my lanck hungry
pockets would contrive with much more profit, and more pri¬
vacy ; you have an idle Chain which keeps your Neck a Prifon-
er, a Mannacle I take it, about your wrift too. If thefe prove
Emblems of the combined Hemp to halter mine, the Fates take
their pleafure, thefe are fet down to be your Ranfom, and there
the Thief is proved.

An. I will confefs both, and the laft forget; you lliall be
onely honeft in this deed. Pray you take it, I increat you to it,
and then you fteal ’em not.

Rocb. You may deliver’em.

An. Indeed I cannot: if you obferve,Sir, they are both lock’d
about me, and the Key I have not; happily you are furnifbc
with fome inftrument, that may unloofe ’em. \

Rocb. No in troth,Lady, I am but a Frcfb-raan,

I never read further than th*s Book you fee,

And this very day is my beginning too:

Thefe picking Laws I am to ftudyyet.^

An. Oh, do not fhow me that, Sir, ’cis too frightful:

Good, hurt me not, for T do yield ’em freely :

Ufe but your hands, perhaps their ftrength will ferve
To tear ’em from me without much detriment,

Somewhat I will endure.

Rock Well, fweet Lady, y’ are the beft Patient for a young
Phyfician, that I think e’re was practis'd on. lie ufe you as gent¬
ly as I can , as Fm an honeft Thief. No ? wilt not do? do I
hurt you, Lady ? An. Not much, Sir.

Rock I’d be loath at all, I cannot do’t. she draws hisfwird

An.


A Cure for a Cuckold.

An. Na^then you fhall not, Sir. You a Thief,

And guard your felf no better ? No further read ?

Yet out in your, own book ? A bad Clerk, arc you not t

Roch. I by Saint Nicholas, Lady, .fvveet Lady.

An. Sir, I have now a Mafculine vigor, and will redeem my
fdf with pu'rchafe too. What money have you ?

Roch. Not a cfofs, by thisfoolifh hand of mine.

An. No money. ’Twerepity then to take this from thee: I
know thou’lt ufe me ne’re the worfe for this, take it agen, I know
not how to ufe it: A frown had taken*t from me, which thou hadft
nor. And now hear and believe me, on my knees I make the
Protection , Forbear to take what violence and danger muft
diflolve, if I forgo ’em now, 1 do allure you would not ftrike my
head off for my Chain, nor my hand for this, how to deliver ’em
otherwife I know not; Accompany me back unto my houfe, ’tis
not far off, by all the Vows which this day I have tyed unto my
wedded husband, the honor yet equal with my Cradle puritie (if
you will tax mej to the hoped joys the bldfings of thebed,pofte«
rity> or what ought elfe by woman may be pledg’d , I will deli¬
ver you in ready Coin, the full and dearefl efteem of what you
crave. #

Roch. Ha, ready money is the prize I look for, it walks with*
out lufpidon any where, when Chains and Jewels may be flayed
and call’d before the Conflable : Bur,

An. But? Can you doubt? You fa w I gave you my advan¬
tage up : Did youe’re think a woman to be true ?

Roch. Thought’s free , I have heard of iome few, Lady,

Very few indeed.

An. Will you adde one more to your belief l

Roch . They were fewer than the Articles of try Belief; there¬
fore I have room for you, ancrwill believe you. Stay : you*i ran-
fern your Jewels with ready Coin, fo may you do, and thendif-
cover me.

An. Shall I reiterate the Vows I made
To this in’un&ion, or new ones coyn ?

Roch . Neither, He rruft you : if you do deftroy a Thief that
never yet did Robbery, then farewel I, and mercy fall upon me.

I knew one once fifteen years Courtier, oyvFd, and he was bu-

' ried


%jt Cure fir 4 Cuckold.

ried c’rc he took a Bribe: it may be my cafe in the Wdrfer my.
Com e, you know your path back.

An. Yes, I /hall guide you.

Rock . Your arm, lie lead with greater dread than will,

Nor do you fear, tho in chiefs handling ftilL Exeunt.

Enter two Boys f one with * thilde in his Arms.

1 Boy. I fay ’twas fair play.

2 Boy. To fnatch up flakes: I fay you ftiouid not fay fo, if the
childc were out of mine arms.

x B§y. I then thou dft lay about like a man, but the childa will
not be out of thine arms this fire years, and then thou haft a pren-
tifhip to ferve to a boy afterwards. Enter Compafs.

a Boy. So fir, you know you have the advantage of me.
x Boy. Fm fure you have the odds of me, you are two to one.
But foft Jack, who comes here ? if a Point will make us friends,
we’l not fall out.

z Boy. Oh the pity, Vis Gaffer Compos! Theyfaid he was
dead three years ago.

1 Boy. Did not he dance the Hobby-horje in Hackney- Morrice
once?

2 Boy. Yes,yes,at Grecn-goofc Fayr^s honeft and as poor a man.
Comp. Blackwall, fweet BUckwall, do I fee thy white checks

again ? I have brought feme Brine from fea for thee : tears that
might be tyed in a True-love Knot, for they*r frefh fait indeed.
Oh beautiful BUcl^wall! if Urfe my wife be living to this day,
though fhe die to morrow, fweet Fates l
2 Boy . Alas, let’s put him out of his dumps for pity fake:
Welcome home, Gaffer Compafs, welcome home. Gaffer.
b Compafs. My pretty youths, I thank you. Honeft Jack .' what a
little man art thou grown fince I faw thee ? Thou haft got a child
fince, mechinks.

2 Boy. I am fain to keep it, you fee, whofoever got it, Gaffer:
it may be another mans cafe as well as mine.

Comp. Say ’ft true, Jack.: and whofe pretty knave is it ?

2 Boy. One that I mean to make a younger brother if he live
to’t, Gaffer. But I can tell you news: You have a brave Boy of
your own wifes : oh ris a foot to this pig.

Comp . Have I Jackj lie ow thee a dozen of Points for this news

2 Boy •


A Cm for 4 Cud old, , ,

1 Boy. Oh \it a chopping Boy! it cannot chufe you know,Gaf¬
fer, it was fo long a breeding.

Comp. How long, Jatk^ ?

a Boy. You know ’tis four year ago fince you went to fea, and
your childe is but a Quarter old yet.

Comp. What plaguy boys are bred now adays ?
r i Boy. Pray Gaffer, how long may a childe be breeding before
’tis born ?

Comp. That is as things are and prove, childe ; thefoyl has a
great hand in t too , the Horizon, and the Cilme; thefe things
you’I underftand when you go to fea. In fome parts of London
hard by, you fhall have a Bride married today, and brought to
Bed within a moneth after, fometimes within three weeks , a
fortnight. i Boy. Oh horrible.

Comp. True as I tell you Lads : in another place you fliall
have a couple of Drones, do what they can, (Lift Lodgings,Beds,
Bed-fellows, yet not a childe in ten years. a Boy . oh pitiful.

Comp . Nowit varies agen by that time you come at tapping,
Bsdcliffy Lymobotife ^nd here with us at * our chilrden

come uncertainly, as the winde ferves : fometimes here we are
fuppofed to be away three or four year together, ’tis nothing fo;
we are at home and gone agen, when no body knows on’t: if
you’l believe me, I have been at Sun tit as this day, I have taken
the Long-boat (a fair Gale with me ) been here a bed with my
wife by twelve a Clock at night, up and gone agen i # th morning
and no man the wife:, if you’l believe me.

2 Boy . Yes, yes Gaffer, I have thought fo many times that
you or fome body elfe have been at home , I lye at next wall,,
and I have heard a noifein your chamber all night long.

Comp. Right, why that was I, yet thou never fawft me.

2 Boy. No indeed, Gaffer.

Comp, No, I warrant thee , I was a thoufand leagues offe’re
thou wertup. But I have been loath to ask all this while

for dilcomforting my felf, how does my wife > is fhe living ?

2 Boy . Oh never better, Gaffer, never fo lufty, and truly fhe
wears better clothes than flic was wont in your days, efpecially
on Holidays, fair Gowns ,brave Petticoats, and fine Smocks,
they fay that have fecn ’em; and fome of the neighbors reports

' that



. A Curt for a c**y$U. " 7 *

that they were taken up at London.

Comp. Like enough: they muft be paid for,

2 Boy. And good reafon, Gaffer.

Comp. Well Jack^ thou fhalt have the honor on’r, go tell my
wife the joyful tidings of my return.

a Boy . That I will, for fhe heard you were dead long ago. Exit

i Boy. Nay fir, lie be as forward as you,by your leave. Exit.

Comp. Well wife, if I be one of the Livery, I t hank thee,

The Horners are a great Company, there may be

An Alderman amongft us one day, ’tis but changing

Our Copy, and then we are no more to be called

By our old Brother-hood. Enter Compafs bis wife.

Wife. Oh my fweet Compafs , art thou come agen ?

Comp. Oh Urfe, give me leave to fried, the fountain of Love
Will have their courfe; though I cannot fing at firil fight,

Yet I can cry before I fee. I am new come into the world,

And children cry before they laugh, a fair while.

Wife. And fo thou art, fweet Compafs, new born indeed ; for
Rumor laid thee out for dead long fince, I never thought to fee
this face agen. I heard, thou wert div’d to th’ bottom of the fea,
and taken up a Lodging in the Sands, never to come to Blacky wall
agen.

Comp. I was going indeed wife, but I turn’d back : I heard an
ill report of my neighbors, Sharks and Sword-fifhes, and the like,
whofe companies I did not like : come kifs my tears now fweet
Urfe , forrow begins to ebb.

wife. A thoufani times welcome home, fweet Compafs.

Comp. An Ocean of thanks, and that will hold ’em: and Urfe y
how goes all at home ? or cannot all go yet ? Lanck (fill ? will’t
never he full Sea at our Wharf >

Wife. Alas, husband. . ^

Comp. A lafs or a lad, wench, I fhould be glad of both: I did
look for a pair of Compares before this day.

Wife. And you from home ?

Comp. I from home ? why though I be from home , and other
of our neighbors from home, it is not fit all fhould be from home,
fo the town might be left defolate, and our neighbors of Bowe
might come further from the ltacw } and inhabit here.


A Cure for a outlaid.

wife. I'm glad y’are merry, fweec husband.

Comp. Merry? nay, He be .merrier yet, why fhould I be for-
jy ? I hope my bo) *s well, is he not ? I lookt for another by this
time. wife. What boy, husband ?

Comp. What boy? why the boy I got when I came home in
the Cock-boat onenighr, about a year ago ? you have not forgot¬
ten c, I hope? I think I left behinde for aboy, and a boy Imuft
be anfwer’d: I’m lure I was not drunk, it could be no girl.

wife. Nay then Ido perceive my fault* is known . 4 Dearfnan,
your pardon.

Comp . Pardon. Why thou haft not made away my boy , haft
thou ? lie hang thee if there were ne’re a whore in London more,
if thou haft hurt but his little toe.

wife. Your longabfence, wi;h rumor of your death,

After long battery I was furprized.

Comp. Surprized ? I cannot blame thee : BUckjwally if it were
double bUck*walled, can’t hold out always, no more than Lyme~
hufe^oi Shadwell , ortheftrongeft Suburbs about London , and
when it comes to that v woe jba to the City coo.

Wife. Purfued by gifts arid piromifes I yielded : Conftderhuf-
band, I am a woman, neither the firft nor Iaft of fuch Offenders,.
’cis true, I have a childc. <;

Comp. Ha, you ? and what {ball I have then I pray ? wilt not
you labor for me as I fhall do for you ? Becaufe I was outo*th
way when ’twas gotten, fhall I loofe my fhare ? There’s better
Law amongft the Players yet; for a fellow fhall have his (hare
though he do not play that day: if you look for any part of my
four$ Years wages, I will have half the boy;

wife. If you can forgive me, I fhall be joyed at it.

Comp. Forgive thee, for what > for doing me a pleafure f and
what is he that would feem to father my childe
wife. A man ftr, whom in better courteftes we have been be-
holding too: the Merchant, Mr .Franckford,

Comp . lie acknowledge no other courcefies j for this I am be¬
holding to him , and I would requite it if his wife were young
enough. Though he be one of our Merchants at Sea, he fhall give
me leave to be Owner at home. And where # s my boy ? ftiali I
fee him f .




o/ Cure for a Cuckold .

Wife* He s nurft at Bedaal-green : ’tis now too late
1 o morrow He bring you to it, if you pleafe.

Comp. I would thou couldft bring me another by to morrow.

i -a ^ at 3nd C ? bed ’ and * f 9 fair Gale tome,

We 1 hotti meets, and fee forwards.

Let fainting fools lie lick upon their fcorns,

He teach a Cuckold how tp hide his horns. Exeunt

Enter fTeodnf, Franckford, Raymond, Eujttce, Grover.

Lyon el ^ Cl Art , Lhcc

This wants a dr fident, that a Bridegroom (Bould fo drT-
u-eet and decently obferve his Forms; Poftures, all cuftomarv
Rites belonging to the Table, and then hide himfelf from his ex¬
pend wages in the bed. s cx

cxfmple^ LCt tfUS be fo gotten t0<> ’ ic remains not a firft

kft !tbe S et too much, unfmitfut

h “ !ove w **&? b *' h

Erf. Tis more .certain than likely. I know *tis fo.

Groy, Conceal then : the event may be well enoi °h
mod The Bride my daughter, fte’s hidden too: "

This latt hour fhe hath not been feen with us.

Raym. Perhaps they are together.

Erf. And then we make too -drift an inquifition , under cor¬
rection of fair modefty, fhould they be ftoln away to bed toge¬
ther, what would you fay to that ? J °

mod. I would fay, Speed ’em well.

And if no worfe news comes, lie never weep for’e.

How now, haft thou any tidings >

Nurft. Yes forfooch, I have tidings.

»W. Of any one that’s loft?

Nurfe. Of one that’s found agen, forfooth. '

mod. Oh,he was loft, itfeems then l
Eranck* This tidings comes to me, I guefs Sir.

Yes truly does it, fir. ..... . ■

Eaytn. has old Lads work for young Nuffes ?

Erf. Yes, when they groan towards their fecond infancy. •
CUrc. I fear my fclf moft guilty for the abfence of the Bride¬
groom,


Enter Nurfe ^


6#}f'ffc it -CuikiU.

groom : whae cur wills will do with over raft and Headlong pee-
viftnefs, to bring our dalm difcrecions to repentance > Lejfing-
bams midaken, quite out o’th way of my ptirpofe too.

Franck^ Return’d ? Nurfe, And all difcover’d.

Franck^ A fool rid him further off. Let him not
Come near the child.

Nwrfe. Nor fee't, if it be your charge.

Franck^ It is, and drift!y.

Nttrfc. To morrow morning* as I hear, he purpofeth to come
to Bednal-green, his wife with him.

Franck: He ftall be met there; yet if he fore-ftall my com¬
ing, keep the childe fafe. Narfe. If he be the earlier up, he
ftalLarive at the proverb. Exit Nnrfe.

Enter Rockfietd and Annabel .

Wood. So, fo, there’s fome good luck yet,

The Bride’s in fight agen.

Anna. Father, and Gentlemen all, befecch you entreat this
Gentleman with all courtefie, he is a loving kinfman of my Eon*
viles t that kindly came to graculate our Wedding; but as the
day falls out, you fee alone I perfonate both Groom and Bride;
oiiely your help to make this welcome better.

Wood. Mod dearly. Raym . To all, aflure you fir*

Wood. But where’s the Bridegroom, Girl ? We are all ac t
nw-flw here, at a dand, quite out, the Mufick ceafed, and dan¬
cing futbated, not a light hed'amongdus j 1 my Goufin too
as cloudy here as on a wafting-day. 1 J:; ‘

Clare . It is becaufe you will not dance with me,

I ftould then ftake it off.

Anna. *Tis I have caufe to be the fad one now, if any be: but
I have quedion’d with my meditations, and they have rend’red
well and comfortably to the word fear I found : Suppofe this
day hehadlongfince appointed to his foe to meet, and fetch a
Reputation from him (which is the deareft Jewel unto man.) Say
he do fight, I know his goodnefs fuch, that all thofe Powers that
love it are his guard, and ill cannot betide him.

Wood. Prithee peace, thou’lt make us all Cowards to h^ar x
woman indru6fc fo valiantly. Come,the Mufick,Ife dance myfelf
rather than thus put down, what, I am rife a little yet.

D %


Anna.


}%\Cure for:* Cuckold.

Anno. Onely this Gentleman, pray you be free in welcome
too, I cell you I was in a fear when firft I faw him.

Roch. Ha? fhe’l tell.

Anna. I had quite loft my way in my firft amazement, but he
fo fairly came to my recovery, in his kinde condudf, gave me fuch
loving comforts to my fears: ( *cwas he inftru&ed me in what I
fpake) and many better chan I have cold you yet, you fhalJ hear
more anon.

Roch . So, fhe will out with ’c.

Anna. I muft, I fee, fupply both places ftill : Come, when I
have feen you back to your pleafure, I will return to you, Sir: we
muft difcourfe more of my Bonvile yet.

Omnes. A noble Bride ’faith.

Clare . You have your withes, and you may be merry,

Mine have over-gone me. Exeunt.

O >4

Mancnt Roch field, fob#.

3 Roch. It is the tremblingft trade to be a Thief, h’ad need have
all the world bound to the peace , befides the bufhcs, and the
phanes of houfos; every thing that moves he goes in fear of *s
life on. A furr-gown’d Cat, and meet her in the night, fhe ftares
with a Conflables eye upon him ; and every Dog, a Watch-man;
a black Coweand a Calf with a white face after her, lhowslike
a furly Juflice and his Clerk; and if the Baby go but to the bag,
*tis ink and paper for a Minimi# : Sure I fhall never thrive on*c,
and it; may beJjhall need take no care, / may be now at my
journeys end, or but the Goals di ; ftance , and fo co’th t* ®ther
place : /truftawoman with a fccr.et worth a hanging, is that
well ? / could finde in my heart to run away yer. And that were
bafe coo, to run from a woman ; f / can lay claim to nothing but
her Vows, and they faall ftrengthen me* Enter Annabel.

Anna. See fir, my promife, there’s twenty Pieces, the full va¬
lue / vow, of what they coft. ( ' •

Roch. Lady, do not trap me like a Sumpter-horfe, and then
fpur-gall me till l break my winde : if the Conftable be at the
door, let his fair ftaflf appear, perhaps 1 may corrupt him with this
Gold. i

Anna. Nay? then if you miftruft me : Father, (Enter all # before ,
Gentlemen, Mr. Raymond , Enflace. «nd a, Saylor -

mod.


V* Cure f«r 4 Cuckold,

Wood, How now, what’s the matter* Girl ?

Anna. For fhame will you bid your Kinfman welcomer V
No one but / will lay a hand on him,

Leave him alone, and ali a revelling.

Wood, Oh, is'that it. Welcome* welcome heartily, /thought
the Bridegroom had been return’d. But 1 have news, Annabel:
this fellow brought it. Welcome Sir,why you tremble methinks,
Sir. Anna, Some agony of anger \i$ y belie.yp it, his enter¬
tainment is lb cold and feeble.. ' f * v n a j , ,'

Raym. Pray be cheer’d, Sir. : : ; *

Roch. I’m wondrous well, fir* ’twas the Gentlemans miftake.

Wood . ’Twas m/hand fhook belike, then you muft pardon
Age, I was differ once. But as I was faying, I ihould by promifc
fee the Sea to morrow, ’cis meant for Phyfick as low as Lee or
Margets : I have a Veffel riding forth , Gentlemen, ’tis called
the God-fpeed too , though I fay’t, a brave one, well and richly
fraugbred ; and lean tell you The carries a Letter pfJMprt in
her mouth too, and twenty roaring Boys on both Tides oh her,
Star-board and Lar-board.. What fay you now, to make you all
Adventurers ? you fhall have fair dealing,that He promife you.

Raym, A very good motion, fir I begin, there’s my ten pieces.

Euft . I fecond ’em with thefc.

Grov, My ten in the third place.

Rock. And Sir, if you refufe not a proftet’dlove, take my ten
Pieces with you too. , •

Wood. Yours, above all the reft, Sir.

Anna. Then make ’em abots, venter ten more.

Roch. Alas Lady , ’tis a younger brothers portion * and all in
one Bottom. o : * . ,

Anna. At my encouragement, Sir, your credit (if you want
Sir ) fhall nor lit down under that fum return’d.

Eocb. With all my heart, Lady. There Sir: So, fhe has fifhc
for her Gold back, and caught it ; / a:n no thief now.

Wood . / fhall make here a pretty Affurance.

Roch. Sir, /fhall have afuittoyou.

Wood. You arc likely to obtain it then, Sir.

Roch. That 1 may keep you company to Sea, and attend you
back ; / am a little travel I’d.


Wood ,



■Woei. And heartily thartk ybti too, fir.

Amid. W^hy, that's wellTaid: pray you be merry,thottgh your
Kinfmanbe abfenc, lam here, the vvorfi part of hint , yet that
{hall ferye to give you welcome rtb morrov^ may ftiow you what
this night will not, and be full affured,
llnlefs your twenty Pieces be ill lent.

Nothing (hall give you caufe of Difcontent.

There’s ten more, Sir.

Rocb. Why fhould Ifear? Fouterotft, lie be merry nowfpice
of the Hang-man. Exeunt .

Finn Aflat fee undue.

ACT j. SCENE i.

Enter Lcjftngham and BonviU.

Ben.X ]\ 7"£ are firft r'th field: I think your Enemy is ftaid at
V V Dover, or fome other Port, we hear not of his land¬
ing. Lejf* I am confident he is come over.

Bon . You look methinks frefh coloured.

Lejf* Like a red Morning, friend , that (fill forctels a ftormy
day to follow : But mechinks now I obferve your face, that you
look pale, there’s death in’t already.

Men* I could chide your error, do you take me for a Coward >
A Coward is not his own friend , much lets can he be another
mans. Know, Sir, I am come hither to inftru& you by my gene¬
rous example , to kill your enemy , whofe name as yet I never
queftion'd. Lejf. Nor dare I name him yet,for dis-heartning
you,. Bon . I do begin to doubt the goodnefs of your Quarrel.

Lejf* Nowyouhav’t; for I proteftrhat I muft fight with one
from whom in the whole courfe of our acquaintance, I never did
receive the leatt injury.

Bon. It may be the forgetful Wine begot fomefudden blow,
and thereupon *ds Challenge, howe’re you are engaged; and for
my pare I will not, take your courfe, my unlucky friend , to fay
your Confcience grows pale and heartlefs, maintaining a baa
Caufe: fight as Lawyers plead, who gain the beft of reputation
when they can fetch a bad Caufe fmoothly off: you are in, and
muft through. ' Lejf.



A Ctirt for *; cuckold,

Lejf. Oh my friend', the nobleft ever marl had: when my fare
threw me upon this bufinefs, I made trial of divers had proteft to
me much love ,, and found their friendftvp like the effects that
kept our company together, Wine and Riot: giddy and finking
I had found ’em oft, brave Seconds at pluralities of Healths,buc
when it came to’th proof, my Gentlemen appeared to me as pro*
mifingand failing as cozening Lotteries 5 but then I found this
Jewel worth a thoufand Counterfeits : I did but name my En¬
gagement, and you flew unto my fuccor with that chearfulnef?,
as a great General hafles to a Battel, when that the chief of the
adverfe pare is a man glorious, but of ample fame: you left your
Bridal-bed to finde your Death-bed, and herein you moft nobly
expreft, that the affection ’tween two loyal friends is far beyond
the love of man to woman, and is more near allied to eternity.
What better friends part .could befhowed i’th world ? it tran-
feends all ! My father gave me life, but you Band by my honor
when ’tis failing, and nobly under-propt it with your fword. But
now you have done me all this fervice, how ? how fhall I requite
this ? how return my grateful r.ecompence for all this love > For
it am I come hither with full purpofe to kill you.

Bon. Ha? Lejf. Yes: I have no oppofite i’th woyld tyit
your felf: There, read the Warrant for your death.

Ben. ’Tis a womans hand.

Lejf. And ’tis a bad hand too: the moft of’em fpeak fair, write
foul, mean vvorfe. Bon . Kill me ! away, you jeft.

Lejf. Such jeft as your fharp-witted Gallants ufe to utter, and
loofe their friends; Read there how I am fetteredin a womans
proud Command : J doLovc madly, and muft do madly: dead-
lieft Hellebore or vomit of a Toad is qualified poyfon to the ma¬
lice of a woman. Bon. And kill that friend ? Strange \

Lejf. You may fee, Sir, although the Tenure by which Land
was held in Villenagebe quire extindj: in England, yet you have
women there at this day living, make a number of (laves.

Bon. And kill that friend? She mocks you upon my life, fhe
does Equivocate : her meaning is, you cherifh in your bread ei¬
ther felf-lovc, or pride, as your beft friend, and (be wiflaes you’d
kill that.

Lejf. Sure her Command is more bloody ; for (be loathes me,

and


A Cure f or a Cuchld.

and has pur,- as fhe ima'gines r this ithpoflible task, forever to be
quit and free from me; but fuch is the violence of my affe&ion,
that I mud undergo it. Draw your fword, and guard yourfelf,
chough I fight in fury, I fhali kill you in cold blood, for I proteft
'cis done in heart-fofrow. V

Bon, lie not fight with you , for I have much advantage ; the
truth is, I wear a privy Coat.

Lejf, Prithee put it off then, if then bee’d manly. _ -

Bon, The defence I mean, is the juftice of my Caufe that
would guard me, and fly to thy dedru&ion: what confidence thou
weareft in a bad caufe, I am likely to kill chee.if I fight* and then
you fail to effe6I your Mrs. bidding, or to enjoy the fruit of Vj I
have ever wifht thy happinefs, and vow I nsw fo much aifeft it in
compaffion of my friends forrow, make thy way to it.

Lejf, That were a cruel Murder.

Bon, BelievVtis ne’re intended otherwife, when *tis a womans
Bidding. Lejf, Oh the necefiity of my fate.

Boh, You fhed tears.

Lejf, And yet mud on in my cruel purpofe : a Judge methinks
looks lovelyed when he weeps, pronouncing of deaths Sentence:
how I dagger in my refolve ! guard thee,for I came hither to do,
and not to fuffer; wilt not yet be perfwaded to defend rhee ?
turn the poinr, advance it from the ground above thy head, and
let it underprop thee otherwife, in a bold refidance.

Bon. Stay. Thy injunction was, thou fhouldd kill thy friend,

Lejf, It was.

Bon, Obferve me, he wrongs me mod, ought to offend me lead,
and they that fludy man, fay of a friend, there’s nothing in the
world that’s harder found ,. nor fooner led : thou earned to kill
thy friend, and thou mayed brag thou had don’t; for-here for ever
all friendship dyes between us, and my hearc for bringing forth
any effe^fls of love, diall be as barren to thee as this fand we
tread on; cruel, and ineondant as the Sea chat beats upon this
Beach, We now are fevered: thus had thou (lain thy friend, and
fatisfied what the Witch thy Mrs. bad thee. Go and report that
thou had fliin thy friend. Lejf, I am ferved right. . *

Bon, And now that I doceafeto be thy friend,I will fight with
thee as thine enemy, Icame not over idly to do nothing.

Ltjf.


U. Cure for a Cuckold.

Lejf. Oh friend !

Bon. Friend? The naming of that word dial! be the quarrel.
What do 1 know but that thou loved my wife > and faina ft this
plot to divide me from her bed , and that this Letter here is
counterfeit ? Will you advance Sir.

Lejf. Not a blow ; ’tvvould appear ill in either of us to fight:
in you unmanly; for believe it Sir, you have difarmed me already,
done away all power of reiiftance in me , it would fhow beaftly
to do wrong to the dead : to me you fay, you are dead for ever,
loft on C tUis-fands , by the cruelty of a woman ; yet remember
you had a noble friend , whofe love to you fhali continue after
death : fhali I go over in the.fone Barque with you ?

Bon. Not for yon town of Lallis , you know ’cis dangerous living
at Sea, with a dead body. : .

Lejf. Oh you mock me, may you enjoy alLyour noble wifhes.
* Bon. And may you finde a better friend then I, and better
keep him. Exeunt*

Enter Nurfe > C$mpdfs y dnd his Wife.

Nurfe . Indeed you mult pardon me, Goodman Compufs ,1 have
no authority to deliver, no not to let you fee the Childe: to tell
you true, I have command unto the contrary.

Comp. Command. From whom? Nuafe. By the father of it.

Comp. The father; Who am I?

Nurfe. Not the father fure. The Civil Law has found it o-
therwife. Comp . The Civil Law: why then the Uncivil Law

fhali make it mine agen; lie be as dreadful .as a Shrove-tucfdap
to thee, I will tear thy Cottage but I will fee my Childe.,

Nurfe . Speak but half fo much agen, lie call theConftable,
and lay Burglary to thy charge.

mfe. My good husband , be patient. £nd prithee Nurfe let
him fee the Childe. .

Nurfe. Indeed I dare not : the father firft delivered me the
Childe, he pays me well, and weekly for my pains, and to his ufe
I keep it. Comp* Why thou white Baftard-breeder, is not this
the mother? Nurfe. Yes, I grant you that.

Comp. Doft thou ? and I grant it too : And is not the Childe
mine own then by the wifes Coppy-hold ?

Nurfe . The Law muft try that. r

Comp,


E


? \jA Cure for a Cuckold.

Cmp. Law ? Doft think He be but a Father in Law ? all the
Law betwixt Blackball and Tuttle-ftr refund there’s a pretty deal,
{Lall not keep it from me mine own flefh and blood ? who does
ufe to get my children but my felf ? ..

Nnrfe. Nay,you mud look to that, I neVe knew you get any.

Comp, Never ? put on a clean Smock and try me, if thou da-
reft, three to one I get a Baftard on thee ro morrow morning be¬
tween one and three. < ' .

W»rfe. He fee thee hangd firft. Enter Franckford

Comp. So thou (laalt too. and Luce.

Nurfe . Oh here’s the father, now pray talk with him.

Francks Good morrow Neighbor: morrow to you both.

Comp. Both ? Morrow to you and your wife too.

Franck I would fpeak calmly with you.

Comp . I know what belongs to a Calm and a Storm too. A
cold word with you: You have tyed your Mare in my ground.

Franck- No, ’twas my Nag. ‘

Comp. I will cut off your Nags tayl, and make his rump make
Hair-buttons, if c*re I cake him there agen.

Franck- Well fis, bat to the Main.

Comp . Main. Yes, and lie clip his Main coo , and crop his
ears too, do you mark ? and back gaul him, and fpur-gaul him,
do you note ? And flit his Nofe , do you fmell me now, Sir >
Unferitch his Barrel, and difcharge his Bullets : He gird him till
he ftinks, you fmell me now I’m fure.

Franck You are toe-rough neighbor, to maintain.

Comp. Maintain ? you fhall not maintain no ehilde of mine,
my wife docs not bcftowher labor to that purpofe.

Franck You are too fpeedy: I will not maintain

Comp. No marry fbali you nor.

Franck The deed to be lawful: I have repented it, .and to
the Law given fatisfa&ion,-. my purfe has paid for’t.

Bcmp. Your purfe : Vwas my wifes purfe. You brought in
the Coin indeed, but it was found hafe and counterfeit.

Franck I would treat colc-ecwith you, if you bcprcafed.'

Ccmp. Pleaded? yes I am pleated Well enough , ferve me fo
ftiU : I im going agen tofea one of thefe days, you know where I
dwell, yet you 1 but ioofeyour labor, get as many children as

yett


_ ^ Cure for * ottfyld.

you can,yeu fhall kfeep none of them, Frank* You are mad.

Comp. If 1 be horn-mad, what’s that to you ? ‘

Franck 1 leave off milder phrafe, and then tell you plain you
are a Comp. A whac ? what ami? Fr. A Coxcomb.

Comp. A Coxcomb ? I knew ’twould begin with a C.

Tra»ck The childe is mine,I am : he father of it; As it is paft
the deed,*tis paft the fhame,I do acknowledge, and will enjoy it.

Comp. Yes, when you can get it agen , is it not my wifes la¬
bor ? I’m fure (he's the mother, you may be as far off the father
as I am ; for my wife’s acquainted with more Whore-makers be-
ftdes your felf, and crafty Merchants too.

Wife. No indeed husband, to make my offence both leaft and
moft, I knew no other man, he’s the begetter, but the childe is
mine, I bred and bore it, and I will not loofe if.

Luce. The childe *s my husbands, Dame, and he muff have it:
I do allow my fufferance to the deed,in lieu I never yet was fruit¬
ful to him, and in my barrennefs excufe my wrong.

Comp. Let him dung his own ground better at home, then if
he plant his Reddifh roots in my garden * lie eat 'em with bread
and Salt, though I get no Mutton to ’em; what tho your husband
lent my wife your diftaff, (lull not the yarn be mine ? lie have
the head,let him carry the (pindle home agen.

Fr. Forebear more words, then let the Law try it: mean time
Nurfekeep the childe, and to keep it better here take more pay
beforehand. There’s money for thee.

Ctmp. There’s money for me too, keep ic for me, Nurfe :give
him both thy dugs at once: I pay for thy right dug.

A Turf, t^have two hands you fee , Gentlemen this does but
fhow how tnekw will hamper you: even thus you mud be ufed.

Fr. The law fhall fhow which is the worthier Gender : a
School-boy can do*t. ,

Comp. lie whip that School*»boy thar declines the childe from
my wife and her heirs : do not I know my wifes cafe the Gen*
the Cafe , and that’s as great a cafe as can be.

Fr. Weil, fare you well, we fhall meet in another place..
Corns Luce Exit..

Comp. Meet her in the fame place agen if you dare, and do
your worft: muft we go to law for our Childrennow a days? No

Ez mmcl






A Cure f$r a Cue hid.

rve [& the Lawyers grow rich ; but ere the Law flhall have
a Lymb, a Leg,,a Joynt, a Nayl,

I will fpend more then a whole childe in getting,

Some win by play, and others by, by betting. Exeunt.

Enter Raymond, Eufiace , Lyonel , Grover , Annabel, Clare .
Lyon. Whence was that Letter Tent ? Am. From Dover ^Sir
Lyo». And does that facisfieyott what was the caufe of his going

Am. It does: yet had he onely fent Lhis it had bin fufficient.
Ray. Why, what’s that ? 1 ; v ' \ '

Ann. His Will wherein he has eftared me in all his land. ~
Enfl. He s gone to fight. Lyon. Leffinrham fecond certain
Am. And Pam loll, loft in’t for ever.

Clare. Oh fool Lejfingham , thou haft miftook my initiation
utterly, utterly mi Hook it, and I am mad, ftark mad with my own
thoughts, not knowing what event their going or e will come too;
ns too late now for my tongue to cry my heart mercy, would I
could be fencelefs till I hear of their return: I fear me both are
loft. Ray Who fhould it be Leffwghams °one to fight with l
Euft. Faitn I cannot polfibly conjeifture.

Ann. Miserable creature ! a Maid, a Wife, and Widow in the
compafs of two days. Ray . Arc you fad too ?

Clare. I am not very well, Sir. Ray. I muft puc life in you.
Litre. Let me go, Sir.

R*y. I do love you in fpight of your heart.

CUre. Believe it there was never a fitter time to exprefs it •
for my heart ha* a great deal of fpight iiu.

Ray. I will difeourfe to you fine fancies.

Clare. Fine fooleries,will you not?

Ray. By thishand I love you, and will court you.

Clare. Fie, you can command your tongue, and I mv ears to
hear you no further.^ . • , - . ;

(?%’ 2 !1 .? y J e j Ut ‘ 1C n 0n ’ , Ent.fVooJrojf,RocbfcilJ,

ine s oft o th hindges ftrangely. and a fay lor.

*? d j. P*“ghter^ood news. An. What is my husband heard of?
L ,d T hjt s th ebunnefs; but von have here a Coufin you,
way be mainly proud of,an ! I am forry ’a‘ s by you" husbands kind¬
red,not your own, that we might boaft to have fo brave a man in
' .* our





A Cure fora CutJ^Id.


our Allyance.

An». What To foon return’d?you have made bur^fhort voyage
howfoever you are to me moll welcome.

Roch. JLady thank?, Tis you have made me yoar own creature,
of all my being fortunes and poor fame , if I have purchas’d any,
and of which I no way boaft, next the high providence, you have
bin the fote creatrefs.

Ann. Oh deer Coufin,you arc'grateful above merit, wbatoc-
cafion drew youTo foon from Sea }

Wood. Such an occahon, as I may blef$ Heaven for, you thank
their bounty, and all of us be Joyful. Ann. Tell us how.

Wood. Nay daughter, the difeourfe will beft appear in his rela¬
tion, where he fails, lie help;

Roch . Nottomoleft your patience with recital of every vain,
and needlefs Circumflance,’twas briefly thus; Scarce having
reacht to Margets, bound on our voyage, fuddenly in view ap¬
peared to us three Spanifli men of War, thefe having fpied the
English Crofs advance, faluteus with a piece to have us ftrike,
ours better fpiriced and no way daunted , at their unequal oddes,
though but one bottom , returned ’em fire for fire : the fight
begins, and dreadful on the fudden, ftill they proffered to board
us, flill we bravely beat ’em off.

Wood. But daughter, m irk the Event.

Roch. Sea room we got, our fhip being fwift of fay t, it hefp-t us
much,yet two unfortunate fhot,one flruckthe Captains head off,
and the other with an unlucky fplinter laid the Mafter dead on
the hatches; all our fpirits then failed us.

Wood. Not all, you fhall hear further* daughter*

Roch. For none was left to manage, nothing now was talkt of
but to yeild up fhip and goods, and mediate for our peace.

Wood. Nay Couf.proceed.

Roch. Excirfe me,Ijntreat you* for what's more, huh already
pa ft my memory.

Wood. But mine it never can: Then he flood up, and with his
oratory made us agen to recolledl our fpirits fo late dejected.

Roch. Pray Sir. , ? >

Wood. He fpeak’c out; by unite confent f then the command
was his, and r cwas his place now to beftir him, down he went be¬
low







A (fare for a cuckold.

low, and put the Lin-docks in the Gunners hands, they ply their
ordinance bravdy, then agen up to the decks; courage is there
renewed, fear now not found amongft us: within lefs then four 1
hoOrs fight two of their (hips were funk, both foundered, and
foon (wallowed: not long after the three begins to wallow,lyes on
the Lee to (lop her leakes, then boldly we come ©a, boarded and
took her, and (Tie's now our prize.

Sayl. Qf this we were eye witnefs.

Wood. And many more brave boys of us, befides my felf for one;

• never was,Gentlemen,a Sea fight better mannaged.

Roch. Thanks ;o Heaven we have faved our own, dammaged
the enemy, and to our Nations glory,we bring home honor and
profit.

Wood, In which Coufin Rochfclld , you as a venturer have a
doable (Bare, befides the name of Captain , and in that a fecond
benefit, but moft of alj, way to more great employment,

Roch. Thus your bounty hath been to me a blefimg.

Ray . Sir, we are all indebted to your valor, this beginning may
•make us of fmill venturers, to become hereafter wealthy Mer¬
chants.

Wood. Daughter and Gentlemen , this is the man was born to
to make us all, come enter, enter; vve will in and feaft, he’s in

the Bridegrooms abfence my chief gued. Exemt .

Finis Attw Tertii,


ACT. 4. SCENE 1.

Enter Compafs , Wife y Lyonel , and Pettifog the Attorney

and one Boy.

Comp! "T^Hree Tuns do you call this Tavern? it has a good
JL neighbor of Gmld-hall> Mr .Pettifog. Show a room boy.
Boy. Welcome Gentlemen. Comp, what ? art thou here
Hodge! Boy. I am glad you are in health, fir.

Comp. This was the honed Crack~roap fird gave me tidings of
my vvifes fruitfulnefs. Art bound Prenticef Boy. Yes, Sir.

Comp. Mayeft thou long jumble Baftard mod artificially, to
the profit of thy Mafter ? and pleafure of thy Midrifs.

Boy. What Wine drink ye, Gentlemen ?

Lyo».



A Cure for a Cuckold.

Lyon. What Wine reltifhes your paliate, good tit. Pettifog f

Pet . Nay, ask the woman.

Comp, • Ellegatx for her, I know her Diet.

Pet, Believe me, I con her thank for’r, I am of her fide.

Comp. Marry, and reafon, fir ^ we have entertain’d you for
our Atonaey. Boy . A Cup of neat Alleganr?

Comp. Yes, but do not make it fpeak Welch, boy.

Comp. Pm no Metheglin in r, ye rogue. °^t)aper's'

Boy. Not a drop, as I am true Britain.

Enter Franckford, Euflace, Line , and Mr. Dodge a Lawyer
to another Table , and a Drawer.

Fr. Show a private room, Drawer. Dr. Welcome Genrlemen.

Etifl. As far as you can from nctffe, boy.

Dr. Further this way then, fir; for in the next room there are
three or four Fifh-wives tak ; ng up abrablingbulinefs.

Fr. Let’s not fit near them by any mean*.

Dodge. Fill Canary, firrah.

Fr. And what do you think of my Caufe, Mr. Dodge f

Dodge. Oh we fhall' carry it moft indubitably : you have mo¬
ney to go through with the bufnefs, and ne’re fear it but we’l
crownce ’em, you are the true Father.

Lace. The mother will confefs as much.

Dodge, Yes Miftrifs, we have taken her Affidavit. Look you
lir, here's the Anfvver to his Declaration.

Fr. You may think flrange, fir, that I am at charge to call a
Charge upon me: but Vis truth, I made a Purchaf- lately, and hr
that I did efface the Childe, ’bout which I’m iued, Joynt-purcha-
ferina /1 the Land I bought : now that’s one reafon that I fhould
have care, befides the tye of blood, to keep the Childe under my
■wiftgV an( ^ ^ ee it carefully inftru&ed in rhofe fair Abilities may
make it worthy hereafter to be mine , and enjoy the Land I have
provided for’e.

Lace. Right, and I councel'd you to make that Purchafe ; and
therefore He not have the Childe brought up by fuch a Coxcomb
as how lues for him , he’d bring him up onely to be a Swabber:
he was born a Merchant and a Gentleman, and he fliall live and
diefo-.

Dodge^


A Cure for 4 cuckold.

Dodge. Worthy Miftrifs, I drink to you: you arc a good wo¬
man, and but few of fo noble a patience. Enter 2 B*y .

Enter boy . Score a quart of Allegant t’o h’ Wocelmkj

Enter i Boy l\e a Mujiclan.

i Boy. Will you have any mufick. Gentlemen?

Comp. Mufickamongft Lawyers ? here's nothing but difcord.
What, Rafe l here’s another of my young Cuckoes I heard laft
April , before I heard the Nightingale: no mufick, good Rafe :
here boy, your father was a Taylor, and methinks by your leering
eye you fhould cake after him. A good boy , make a leg hand-
fomly, fcrape your felf out of our company. And what do you
think of my Suit, fir?

Pet. Why, look you, fir : The Defendant was arrefted firft by
Latitate in an Aftion ©f Trefpafs.

Comp. And a Lawyer told me it fhould have been an Aflion
of the Cafe, fhould it not wife ?

Wife. I have no skill in Law, fir: hut you heard a Lawyer fay fo.

Pet. I, but your Ailion of the Cafe is in chat point too tieklifh.

Comp . But what do you think, fhall I overthrow my adverfary?

Pet. Sans queftion: The childe is none of yours: what of that?
I marry a widow is pofleft of a Ward, fhall not I have the tuition
of that Ward ? Now fir, you lye at a ftronger Ward ; f otparttu
fequitur ventrem , fays the Civil Law: and if you were within com-
,pals of the four Seas, as the common Law goes, the childc fhall
be yours certain. . *

Comp. There’s feme comfort in that yet. Oh your Atorneys
in Guild-hall have a onetime on'e.

Lyon . You are in effe.il both Judge and Jury your felves.

Comp . And how you will laugh at your Clients when you fit
in a Tavern, and call them Coxcombs, and whip up a Caufe, as a
Barber trims his Cullomers on a Chrilhnafs Eve, afnip, a wipe,
and away.

Pet. That’s ordinary,fir: you fhall have ^he like at a Ni[i Prim.
Oh you are welcome, Sir. Enter 1 Client ;

i Client. Sir, youTbe mindful of my Suit.

Pet. As I am religious, lie drink to you.

1 Client. I thank you. By your favor, Mifirifs. I have much
bufinefs and cannot ftay; but there's money for a quart of Wine.
^ * Comp.


A Curt ftr a CutkoU.

Comp . By bo means. #

1 Client. I have faid, Sir. Exit . Enter 2 CPent.

Pet. He’s my Client fir, and he muft pay; this is my tribute.

Cufiom is not more truly paid in the Sound of Denmark*

% Client. Good fir, be careful of my bufinefs.

Pet. Your Declaration’s drawn, fir: lie drink to you.

2 Client . I cannot drink this morning 5 but there’s money for
a pottle of Wine, Pet . Oh good fir.

a Client. I have done, fir* Morrow,Gentlemen. Exit,
Comp . We fhall drink good cheap, Mr. Pettifog.

Pet. And wedate here long you’d fay fo\ 1 have fate here m
this Tavern but one half hour, drunk but three pints of wine, and
what with the offering of my Clients in that fin*ort time, I have
got nine fhi Mings clear, and paid all the Reckoning.

Ljonr Almoft a Counceljors Fee.

Pet. And a great one as the world goes in Guild-ball; for now
our young Clerks fihare with ’em, to help ’em to Clients.

Comp. I don’t think but that the Cucking-ftool is an enemy to
a number of brables,that would elfe be determined by Law.

Pet . ’Tisfo indeed,fir: My Client that came in now, fues his
neighbor for kicking his Dog, and ufing the defamatory fgqechesj,
Come out Cuckolds curr,

Lyon. And what fhall you recover upon this fpeech ?

Pet . In Guild-haR I allure you, the other that came in was an
Informer, a precious knave.

Comp. Will not the Ballad of Flood that was prefi, make them
leave their knavery ? '

Pet. I(e tell you how he was ferved: This Informer comes in¬
to Turnball-flreet to'a Vi$ual!ing''houfe,and there falls in league
with a Wench.

Comp. A or Bronftrops , I learnt that name in a PTy.

Pet. Had belike fome private dealings with her, and there got

a Goofe.

Comp. I would he had got two,I cannot away with an Informer
Pet. Now fir, this fellow in revenge of this, informs againfi the
Bawd that kept the houfe, that (lie ufed Cannes in her houfe; but
the cunning Jade comes me into’th Court, and there de,poles

that fhe gave him true tVinehefler meafure.

/p • • Comp,






A Cure for d Cuckold.

Comp. Marry,1 thank her with all my hcarr for’t. Ext.Drawer

Draw. Here’s a Gentleman, one juHice Woodroff esquires for
Mr. Franckford. Fr . Oh, my brother and the other Compre-
irjifer come to take up the bufinefs.

Enter Conn cellar and Woodruff*

Wood We have conferred and labored for your peace , unlefs
your Hubbornefs prohibit it; and be allured,as we can determine
it, the Law will end, for we have fought the Cafes.

Comp. If the Childe fall tomyfhare, I am content to end up¬
on any conditions, the Law fhall run on head-long elfe.

Fr. Your purfe mud run by like a Foor-min then.

Comp . My purfe fhall run open mouth’d at thee.

Conn. My friend, be calm, you fhall hear the reafons: I have
Hood up for you, pleaded your Caufe, but am overthrown, yet
no fun her yielded than your own pleafure ; you may go on in
Law if you refufe our Cenfure.

Comp. I will yield to nothing but my Childe.

Com. ’Tis then as vain in us to feek your peace , yet take the
reafons with you : This Gentleman firft fpeaks, a JuHice to me,
and obferve it, A childe that’s bafe and illegitimate born , the
father found, who (if the need require it) fecures the charge and
dammage of the Parifh but the father ? who charged with educa¬
tion but the father i then by dear confequence he ought for what
he pays for, to enjoy. Come to the Hrength of reafon,upon which
the Law is grounded : the earth brings forth, this ground or that,
her Crop of Wheat or Rye, whether fhall the Seeds-man enjoy
the fheaf, or leave it to the earth that brought it forth? The
fummer tree brings forth her natural fruit, fpreads her large
arms, who but the lord of it fhall pluck Apples, or command the
lops? or fhall they fink in:o the root agen ? *iis Hill mod deer
upon the Fathers part.

Comp. All this Law I deny , and will be mine own Lawyer.
Isnot the earth our Mother ? And fhall not the earth hive all
her children agen ? I would fee that Law durft keep any of us
back, fheThive Lawyers and all firfVhothey be none of her beH
children. My wife is the mother, and fo much for the Civil-law.
Now I come agen, and y’are gone at the Commotvliw : fuppofe
this is my ground y I keep a Sow upon it, as it might be my wife,

. 1 y.OU:


A. fure for a cuckold\

you keep a Boar, as ic might be my adverfary here; your Boat
comes foaming into my ground , jumbles with my Sow, and wal-
lowes in her mire, my Sow cryes week* as if fhe had Pigs in her
belly, who fhall keep thefe Pigs? he the Boar,or fhethe Sow ?

Wood. Paft other alteration, I am changed , the Law is on the
Mothers part. Conn. For me,I am ftrong in your opinion,
I never knew my judgement erre fe far, I was confirmed upon the;
other part, and now am flat againfl it. mod. Sir you muft

yeild^ believe it there’s no Law can relieve you.

Fr. I found it in my fclf : well fir, the childe *s your vvifes, lie
ftrive no further in it, and being fo neer unto agreement, let us
go quite through to*t; forgive my fault, and I forgive my char¬
ges, nor will I take back the inheritance I made unto it.

Comp, Nay, there you fhall finde me kinde too, I have a pot¬
tle of Claret, and a Capon to fupper for you ; but no more Mut¬
ton for you, not a bit.

Ray. Yes a fhoulder, and we’l be there too, or a leg opened
With Venifon fawce.

Comp . No legs opened by your leave; nor no fucb fawce.

Wood. Well brother, and neighbor, I am glad you are friends.

Omnes. All, all joy at it. - r Exeunt Wood.Fr.and Lawyers.

Comp. Mrfe> come kifs Urfe y all friends.

Ray. Stay fir,one thing I would advife you,’tis Councei worth a
Fee,tho I be no Lawyer, *tis Phyfick indeed, Sc cures Cuckoldry,
to keep that fpightful brand out of yoar forehead, that it fhall
not dare to meet or look out at any window to you > 'tis better
then an Onion to a green wound i’th lef^ hand made by fire, it
takes out fear and all.

Comp. This were a rare receipt, lie content you for your skill.

Ray M ^ke here a flat divorce between your felves,be you nohuf-
band, nor let her be no wife, within two hours you may falute
agen,wooe,and wed afrefh,and then the Cuckold's blotted. This
medicine is approved.

Comp. Excellent,and I thank you :Urfe, I renounce thee, and I
renounce my felf from thee ; thou art a Widow, Ur[e I will go
hang my felf two hours, and fo long thou ilia It drown thy felf,
then will wc meet agen in the Peafe-field by Bi{kop<-Hall , and
as the Swads and the Cods fhall inttru# us, wc'i talk of a new

F i ‘ matter.


‘ A Curt for 4 Cuckold. -

matter. Wife. I will be ruled, fare you well,fir. Exit wife.

Comp. Farewel widdow, remember time and place, change
your Clothes too, do ye hear, widow? Sir, I am beh olding to your
good Councel.

Raj. But you 5 ! not follow your own fo far I hope ? you faid
you’d hang your felf. '

Comp, No I have devifed a better way, I will go drink my felf
dead for an hour , then when I awake agen, I am a frefh new
man, and fo I go a wooing.

Ray. That’s handfome, and He lend thee a dagger.

Comp. For the long Weapon let me alone then. Exeunt.

Enter Lejfingleam and Clare.

Clare. Oh (ir, are you return'd ? Ido expeil to hear Grange
news now.

Lejf. I have none to tell you, lam onely to relate I have done
ill at a womans bidding, that's I hope no news:yet wherefore do
I call that ill, begets my abfolute happinefs ? you now are mine,
■I muft enjoy you folely. Clare. By what warrant?

Lejf. By your own coalition, I have been at CallU y performed
your will, drawn my revengful fvvord , and flain my neerefl and
beft friend i’th world I had, for your fake.

Clare . Slain your friend for my fake? Lejf. A mod fad truth.

Clare. 'And your bed friend? Lejf. My chiefed.

Clare. Then of all men you are mod miferable, nor have you
ought further’d your fuit in this, though I enjoyn’d you to’t,for I
had thought that I had been the bed edeemed friend you had i’th
world. Lejf. Ye did not with 1 hope,that I fhould have murder’d
you? Clare. You fhall perceive more of that hereafter:But I pray
fir tell me , for I do freeze with expectation of it, it chills my
heart with horror till I know what friends blood you havefacri-
ficed to your fury and to my fatal fport, this bloody Riddle? who
is it you have (lain? Lejf. Bonvile the Bridegroom.

Clare. Say ? Oh you have druckhim dead thorough my heart,
in being true to me , you have proved in this the falfed Traitor:
oh Iamlod for ever: yet wherefore am I lod ? rather recovered
from a deadly witchcraft, and upon his grave I will no: gather
Rue,but Violets toblefs my wedding Brewings; good firrell me,
are you certain he is dead? Lejf. Never, never to be recovered.


Of Curt fer a Cuckold .

Clare . Why now fit, I do love you , with an entire heart,T
could dance methinks, never did Wine or mufich dir in woman,
a Tweeter touch of Mirth, I will marry you, indandy marry you.

Lejf. This woman has drange changes, you are ta’ne drangely
with his death.^

• Clare . He give the reafon I have to be thus extafied with
joy : know dr, that you have flain my deered friend, and fataleft
enemy. Lejf. Mod drange !

Clare. ’Tis true, you have ta’ne a mafs of Lead from off* my
heart, for ever would have funk it in. defpair; when you beheld
me yederday, I dood as if a Merchant walking on the Downs,
fhould fee Tome goodly Veffel of his own funk ’fore his face i’th
Harbor, and my heart retained no more heat then a man that
toyles, and vainiy labors to put out the dames that burns his houfe
to’th bottom. I will tell you a drange concealment, fir, and till
this minute never revealed , and I will tell it now, finding and
not bludiing; I did love that Btnvyle , (not as I ought, but as a
woman might that’s beyond reafon,) I did doat upon him, tho
he near knew oft, and beholding him before my face wedded
unto another, and all my intered in him forfeited, I fell into de¬
fpair, and at that indant you urging your Suit to me, and I
thinking that I had been your onely friend i’th world , I heartily
did wim you would have kill’d that friend your felf, to have en¬
ded all my forrow, and had prepared' it, that unwittingly you
jfhouId have don’t by poifon. Lejf. Strange amazement!

Clare. The efre&s of a drange Love. Lejf. ’Tis a dream fure. ,

Clare. No ’tis real fir, believe it. Leff. Would it were not.

Clare. What fir, you have done bravely, *ds your Midrifs that
tells you, you have done fo.

Lejf. But my Confidence

Is of Councel ’gaind you , and pleads otherwife :

Vertue in her pad anions glories dill,

Buc vice throwes loached looks on former ill.

But did you love this Bonvile ?

Clare. Strangely fir, almod to a degree of madnefs.

Lejf. Trudawoman? never henceforward, T will rathe; cfuft
the winds which Lapland Witches fell to men, all that theyjiave

is feign’d, their teeth,their hair, their blufihes,nay their confidence

v to©


A cure (qt a cutkolJ.

too rs feigned,let 'em paint,load themfelves with Cloth of Tiflue,
they cannot yet hide woman , that will appear and difgrace all.
The neceffity of my fate 1 certain this woman has bewitched me
here, for I cannot chufe but love her. Oh how fatal this might
have proved, I would it had for me, it would not grieve me, tho
my fwordhadfplit his heart in funder , I had then deftroyed one
that may prove my Rival ; oh but then what had my horror
bin, my guilt of confcience ? I know fome do ill at womens bid¬
ding i’th Dog-days, andrepent all the Winter after: no,Iaccount
it treble happinefs that Bonvlle lives, but *tismy chiefeft glory
that our friendfhip is divided.

Clare . Noble friend, why do you talk to yourfelff

Lejf. Should you do fo,you’d talk to an ill woman,fare you well,
for ever fare you well ;’ I will do fomewhat to make as fatal
breach and difference in Bonvlles love as mine, I am fixt in’c, my
mehnchollv and the devil fhaii fafhion’t.

Clare . You willno' leave me thus ?

Lejf. Leave you for ever, and may my friends blood whom
you loved fo deerly, for ever lye impoftumed in your bread, and
l*th end choal* you. Womans cruelty
This black and fatal thread hath everfpun,

It muft undo, oc elfe it is undone. Exit .

Clare . I am every way loft, and no meanes to raife me, but
bleft repentance : what two unvalued Jewels am I at once de¬
prived of f now I fuffer defervedly, there’s no profperity fettled,
Fortune plays ever with our good or ill,

Like Crofs and Pile, and turns up which die will.

Enter Benvlle. Friend ?

Clare . Oh you are the welcomed under heaven : LeJJingham
did but fright me, yet I fear that you are hurt to danger.

Bon. Not a fcratch. Clare. Indeed you look exceeding
well, methinks. Bon, I have bin Sea-fick lately, and we count
that excellent Phyfick. How docs my Annabel?

Clare. As well fir, as the fear of fuch a lofs as your efteemed
felf,wili fuffer her. Bert. Have you feen Lejfwgham fince he re¬
turned? Clare . He departed hence but now, and left w thme
a report had almoft kill’d me.

Ben. What was that ? Clare* That he had kill'd you.

Ben.


Cure for a Cuckold. <

Ben. So he has. Clare. You mock me.

Bon. He has kill’d me for a friend , for ever filenc't all amity
between us; you may now go and embrace him, for he has fulfil¬
led the purpofe of that Letter. Gives her a Letter .

Clare . Oh I know’c. She gives hint another

m And had you known this which I meant to have lent you an hour
’fore you were married to your wife, the Riddle had been con-
ftrued. Bon. Strange l this expreffes that you did love me.

Clare. With a violent afFeftion.

Bon . Violent indeed ; for it feems it was your purpofeto have
ended it in violence on your friend : the unfortunate LejJingham
unwittingly fhouid have been the Executioner.

Clare. ’ Tistrue. Bon. And do youlbve me ftill l

Clare. I may eafily confefs it, fince my extremity is fuch that
Imuft needs fpeak or die.

Bon. And you would enjoy me though I am married ?

Clare. No indeed no: I fir: you are to deep with a fweer Bed¬
fellow would knit the brow at that.

Bon. Come, come, a womans telling truth makes amends for
her playing faife. You would enjoy me l

Clare . If you were a Batchelor or Widower,,

Afore all the great Ones living.

Bon. But ’tisjmpoflibleto give you prefent fatisfa&ion/or my
Wife is young and heal, hful; and I like the fummer and the har-'
veil of our Love, which yet I have not tailed of, fo well, that and
you’l credit me, for me her days fhall lie’re be fhortned: let your
reafon therefore turn you another way , and call to minde with
bed obfervance, the accompliilit graces of that brave Gentleman
whom late you fent to his deftruftion: A man fo every way de-
ferving , no one a&ion of his in all his life timee’re degraded
him from the honor he was born too; think how obfervant he’i-
prove ro you in nobler requefi, that fo obeyed you in a bad one;
And remember that afore you engaged him to an a6l
Of horror, to the killing of his friend ,

He bore his fteerage true in every part,

Led by the Compafs of a noble heart.

Clare. Why do you praife him thus ? You faid but now he was
utterly loft toyou; now’t appears you are friends, elfe you’d

not-


A Curf for a Cuckold.

not deliver of him fucK a worthy commendation.

Bon. You miftake, utterly miftake that I am friends with him,
in fpeakingthis good of him : To what purpd'fe do I praiie him ?.
oneiy to this fatal end , that you might fall in love ajtid league
with him. And what worfe office can Idoi’th world unto my
enemy, than tqendeavor by all means poflibie to marry him unto
a Whore ? and there I think fhe (lands.

Clare . Is Whore a name to be beloved ? «if not, what reafon
have I ever to love that man puts it upon me falfely ? You have
wrought a (Irange alteration in me: were I a man, I would drive
you with my fword into the field , and there put my wrong to fi-
lence. Go, y’arc not worthy to be a womans friend in the leaf!:
part that concerns honorable reputation; for you are a Liar.

Bon. I will love you now with a noble obfervance, if you wfll
continue this hate unto me : gather all thofe graces from whence,
you have fain yonder, where you have left ’em in Lejjingkam , he
that muftbe your husband; And though henceforth I ceafe to be
his friend, I will appearhis nobleft enemy, and vverk reconcile¬
ment’tween you.

Clare. No,you fhall not, you fihall not marry him to a Strum¬
pet ; for that word I (liall ever hate you.

'fiem.Lejf. And for that one deed,

I fhall ever love you. Come, convert your thoughts
To him that bed deferves ’em^Le/fwgham.

It’s moft certain you have done him wrong,

But your repentance and companion now
May make amends: difperfe this melancholly,

And on that turn of Fortunes Wheel depend,

When all Calamities will mend, or end. Exeunt.

Enter Compafs, Raymond, Ettflace , Ljonel , Grover.

Comp. Gentlemen, as you have been witnefs to our Divorce,
You fhall now be evidence to our next meeting,

Which I look for every minute, if you pleafe Gentlemen.

Ray. We came for the fame purpofe, man.

- Comp. I do think you’l fee me come off with as fmooth
A forehead, make my Wife as honeft a woman once more,

As a man fomecimes would defire, I mean of her r^nk,

And a teeming woman as fhe has been. Nay furely I


D*


XA Cure for a Cuckold.

Do think to make the Chiide as lawful achiidetoo,

As a couple of until irried people can beget; *nd tec
It be begotten when the father is beyond Sea, as this
Was: defeat note. Enter Wife.

Eufl. ’Tig that we wait for.

Comp. You have waited the good hour: fee,fhe comes,a little
room I befeech you„fiience and obfervation.

Raj. All your own, fir.

Comp. Good morrow fair Maid.

wife. Mifiaken in both fir, neither fair, nor Maid.

Comp. No? a married woman.

Wife. That’s it I was fir, a poor widdow now.

• Comp. A widdow? Nay then I muft make a little bold with
you, ’tis a kin to mine own cafe,I am a wivelefs husband too,how
long have you been a widow pray? nay, do not weep.

Wife. I cannot chufe to think the lofs I had.

Comp. He was an honeft man to thee it feems.

Wife. Honeft quoth, a,oh. Comp. By my feck , and thofe
are great lofles, an honeft man is not to be found in every hole,
nor every ftreet, if I took a whole parifh in fometimes I might
fay true, for ftincking Mackarel may be cried for new.

Ray . Some what fententious.

Etift. Oh, filence was an Article enjoyned.

Comp. And how long is it fince you loft your honeft hus¬
band ? Wife. Oh the memory is toofrcfh, and your fight makes
my forrow double. Comp. My fight ? why was he like me?

Wife: Your left hand to your right, is not more like.

Comp. Nay then I cannot blame thee to weep, an honeft man
I warrant him, and thou hadft a great lofs of him ; fuch.Y pro¬
portion, fo limb’d, fo coloured, fo fed.

Ray. Yes faith, and fo taught too.

Eufl. Nay, will you break the Law ? s

wife. Twins were never liker. -

Comp. Well, I love him the better, whatfoever is become of
him, and how many children did he leave thee at his depirture ?

Wtfe. - Onel y one fir. ; . . j ? .v

Comp. A Boy, or a Girl ? wife. A Boy, Sir.

Comp, juft mine one cafe ftill: my wife,reft her iouljleft me a

G - > ' Boy


A Curt fir 4 Cucfald.

Boy too, a chopping Boy I warrant.

wife, Yes if you call ’em fc. **

Comp. I, mine is a chopping Boy , I mean to make either a
Cook or a Butcher of him,for thofe are your chopping *Boys. And
what profelfion was your husband off

wife. He went to Seat*, fir, and there got his living.

Comp. Mine own faculty too , and you pn like a man of that
profeiffon well ?

Wife. For his fweet fake whom I fo deerly loved, more deerly
loft, I muft think well of it.

Comp . Muft you? Ido think then thou muft venter to Sea
once agen, if thoul’c be rul’d by me.

Wife . Oh Sir, but there’s one thing more burdenfome to as,
then moft of others wives, which moves me a little to diftafteir,
long time we endure the abfence of our husbands, i'omeumes
many years, and then if any flip in woman be , as long vacations
may mike Lawyers hungry, and Tradefmen cheaper penny¬
worths afford,(then otherwife they would for ready coin) fcandals
fly out, and we poor fouls branded with wanton living, and in-
continency, when alas ( confider ) can we do withal? •

Comp . They are fools, and not faylors that do not confider
tha r , I’m Cure your husband was not of that minde, if he were like
me.

Wife. No indeed, he would bear kinde and honeflly.

Comp . He was the wifer, alack your land and frefli-vvater men
Never underftand what wonders are done ac Sea ; yet
They may obferve a fhore, that a Hen having tafted
The Cock, kill him, and fhe {hall lay Egg* afterwards.

Wife . That’s very true indeed.

Comp. And fo may women, why not ? may not a man get two
or three children at once ? One muft be born before another, you
know.

wife. Even this difcretion my fweet husband had:

You more and more refemble him.

Comp . Then if they knew what things are done at fea, where
The Winds themfelves do copulate, and bring forth iflue,

As thus: In the old world there were but four in aft,

As Nor, Eaft, Sou, and Weft : thefe dwelt far from one another.

Yet


s*A Cure for a Cuckold .

Yet by meeting they have ingendred Nor-Eaft, Sou-Eaft,
.Sou-Weft, Nor-Weft, then they were eight; Of them
Were begotten No&-Nor-Eaft, Nor-Nor-Weft, Sou-Sou-Eaft,
Sou-Sou-Weft, and thofe two Sows were Sou-Eaft and Sou- Weft
Daughters, and indeed there is a family.now of 3 2 of ’em,

Thac they have fill’d every corner of the world, and yet for
All this, you fee thefe baudy Bdlows-mendqrs when they
Come afhore, will be offering to take up Womens coats
In the ftreet.

Wife* Still my husbands diferetion!

Comp. So I fay, if your Land-men did underftand that we fend
Windes from Sea, to do our commendations to our wives, they
would not blame you as they do.

Wife. We cannot help it.

Comp. But you fhall hdpic. Can you love me, widow ?

Wife. If I durft confefs what Ido think, fir,

I know what I would fay.

Comp . Durft confefs? Why whom do you fear ? here’s none
but honeft Gentlemen my friends; let them hear, and
Never blufh for’t.

wife* I fhall be thought too weak to yeild at firft.

Ray. Tu(h v that’s nicenefs; come, We heard all the reft,

The firft true ftroke of love finks thee deepeft,

If you love him, fay fo.

Comp. I have a Boy of mine own, I tell you that afore-hand,
You fhall not need to fear me that way.

Wife. Then I do love him.

. Comp So here will be m an and wife to morrow then,what though
We meet ftrangers, we may love one another
Ne’r the worfe for that. Gentlemen, I invite
You all to my Wedding.

Omnes. Wei all attend it.

Comp. Did not I tell you, I would fetch it off fair, let any
Man lay a Cuckold to my charge, if he dares now.

Ray . ’Tis (lander who ever does it.

Comp. Nay, it will come to Petty Laffery at leaft, and without
Compafsof the general pardon coo, or lie bring him to a
Foul ftieet, if he has ne’re a clean one, or let me

G i Heas




A Cure for i cuckold.

Hear him that will fay I am not father to the childe I begot.'
Eufl. None will adventure any of rhofe.

Comp . Or that my wife that .fhall be , is not as honeft a wo¬
man, as fome other mens wives are ?

Ray. Noqueffion of that.

C cmp. How fine and {leek my brows are now ?

Euft. I when you are married, they’l come to rhemfelves agen.
Comp. You may call me Bridegroom if you pleafe now.

For the Guefts are bidden.

Cmnes. Good Mailer Bridegroom.

Comp. Gome Widow then, ere the next Ebb and Tide,

If I be Bridegroom, thou ihah be the Bride. Exeunt %

F'mii Atm quartii.


. V ■ ■ f , .... *

ACT. 5. SCENE 1.

Enter Rochficld and Amabel.

Elieve me, I was never more ambitious, or covetous, if
I may call ic fo, of any fortune greater than this one,
but to pehold his face.

Am. And now’s the time; for from a much feared danger as
I heard, he’s late come over.

Koch. And not feeriyou yet ? ’cis fome unkindnefs.

Ann. You may think it fo ; but for my part, fir, I account it
none; what know I bur fome buiinefs of import and weighty con-
fequence, more near to him than any formal Complement to me,,
may for a time detain him : I prefume no jealoufie can be afperff
©nhim, for which hecannor well Apology.

Roch. You are a Creature every way oompteat,

As good a Wife, as Woman ; fo. whofe fake
As I in duty am endeer’d to you,

So fhall I owe him fervice. Enter LeJJingham.

Leff. The ways to Love, and Crowns, lye both through blood,
for in ’em both all Lets muft be removed , it could be fliled no
true ambition elfe. Iam grown big with pro ed: Pro;efl, Laid 1?
Rather with fudden mifehief ; which without


A fpec-



A Cure for * cuckold.

A fpeedy birch fills me with painful throwes, * \

And I am now in labor. Thanks occafion
That giveft me a fie ground to work upon,

It fhould he Rochficld , one lince our departure
It Teems ingrafted in this.Family:

Indeed the Homes Minion, fince from the Lord
To the lovvert Groom , all with unite confent
Speak him To largely. Nor as it appears
By this their private Conference, is he grown
Leal! in the Bric’es opinion. A foundation
On vyhich I will eredl a brave Revenge.

Ann. Sir, What kinde Offices lyes in your way
To do for him, I fhall be thankful for,

And reckon them mine own.

Roch. In acknowledgement I kifs your hand, fo with a grati¬
tude never to be forgot, / take my leave.

Ann. 1 mine of you, with hourly expedition
Of a long-lookt for husband. Exit .

Roch. May it thrive according to vour willies.

Lejf. Now’s my turn. Without offence, Sir, may I beg your
name ?

Roch. ’Tis that / never yet denied to any,nor will to you that
feem a Gentleman : ’tis Rochficld .

Leff. Rochfitld ? You are then the m a whofe noblenef?, ver-
tue, valor, and good parts, have voice’d you loud. Dover and
Sandwich , Marget, and all the Coattisfuli of you: but more,
as an Eye-witnefs of all thefe, and wkb molt truth, the Mailer
of this houfe hath given them large expreffions.

- Roch. Therein his love exceeded much my merit.

Leff. That’s your modefty:

Now / as one that goodnefs love in all men,

And honoring that which is but found in fev^

Defire ro know you better.

Roch. Pray your name ?

Leff. Leffingham. Roch . A friend to Mr. Bonvile >

Lejf. In the number of thofe which he efteems moft dear cg
him, he reckons me not laft.

Roch. So / have heard.

• , Lef.


A Curt for 4 Cuckold.

Lejf. Sir, you have caufe to blefs the lucky Planet
Beneath which you were born, ’twas a bright ftac
And then fhined cleer upon you, for as you
Are every way well parted, fo I hold you
In all defigns m irk’t to be fortunate.

Roch. Pray do not flretch your love to flattery,

*T may call it then in queflion; grow I pray you
Tofome particulars.

Lejf. I have obferved but late your parting with the Virgin
Bride, and therein feme affe&ion. Roch . How ?

Lejf. With pardon, in this I Kill applaud your happinefs, and
praife the bletfed influence of your flars : for how can it be pof-
fiblethat fhe,unkindly left upon the Bride-day,and difappointed
of thofe Nuptial iweets that night expeded , but fhould take the
occafion fo fairly offered ? Nay, and Hand excufed afweliin de-
reflation of a fcorn, fcarce in a husband heard of, as feleftinga
Gentleman in all things fo compleat, to do her thofe negle&ed
offices, her youth and beauty juftly challenged?.

Roch. Some plot to wrong the Bride, and I now
Will marry Crafc with Cunning, if he’l bite,

He give him line to play on: wer’t your cafe
You being young as I am, would you intermit
So fair and fweet occafion?

Lejf. Yet mif-coneeive me not, I do intreat you ;

To think I can be of that eafie wit,

Or of that malice to defame a Lady,

Were (lie fo kinde fo to expofe her felf,

Nor is fhe fuch a creature.

Lejf. On this foundation I can build higher ftifl,(fir I beleiv’c)
I hear you two call Coufins; comes your kindred
By the fVoodrojfs , or the Bonviles ?

Roch. From neither, ’tis a word of courrefie
Late interchanged betwixt us, otherwife
We are forreign astwo flrangers. ^ Lejf. Better flilL

Roch. I would not have you grow too inward with me
Upon fo fmall a knowledge; yet to farisfie you,

And in fome kinde too to delight my felf,

Thofe Bracelets and the Carckanet fhe wear s ,

She




A Cure for 4 Cuckold,

She gave me once.

Lejf. They were the firft, and fpecial Tokens paft betwixt her
and her husband.

Rock. ’Tisconfeft: what Ihavefaid , Ihavefaid : Sir, you
have power perhaps to wrong me,or to injure her; this you may
do, but as you are a Gentleman I hope you will do neither.

Lejf Truft upon’t. Exit Richfield.

If I drown lie fink Come along with me ; Enter Woodroff,

For of all miferies I hold that chief.

Wretched to be, when none co-parts our grief.

Here’s another Anvile to work on: I mult now
Make this my Mafter-piece ; for your old Foxes
Are feldomta’ne in Springes.

mod. What, my Friend !

You are happily returned ; and yet / want
Somewhat to make it perfe&; Where’s your Friend,

My Son in Law? Lejf. Ohdirl

Wood. I pray fir refoive me; for I do fuffer ftrangely till I know
if he be in fafety.

Lejf'. Fare you well: ’ Tis not fie
1 fhould relate h*s danger. ,

Wood. I muft know ’t. I have a Quarrel to you already,
for enticing my Son in Law to go over: Tell me quickly, or/
fhall make it greater.

Lejf. Then truth is, he’s dangeroudy wounded.

Wood. But he’s not dead / hope ?

Lejf: No fir, not dead; yet fure your daughter may take li¬
berty to chufe another.

Wood. Why that gives him dead.

Lejf. Upon my life Sir, no; your Ton’s in health
As well as / am.

Wood. Strange! yon deliver Riddles.

Lejf. I told you he was wounded, and’tis true.

He is wounded in his Reputation. t . # <

./told you likewife, which / am loth to repeat.

That your fair Daughter might taka liberty
To embrace another. That’s the conference
That makes my beft Friend wounded in bis Fame,


/ 1 d Cure for, a Cuckold .

This Is all I can deliver;

Wood. T mud have more oft; ' *

For Ido fweat already, and lie fweat more ; ;

*Tis good they fay to cure Aches, and o’th fudden
I am fore from head to foot, let me cade the word.

Lejf. Know Sir, if ever there were truth in falfhood, „

Then'cis mod true, your Daughter plays mod falfe
With Bonvile , and hath chofe for her Favorite
The man that now pad by me, Rochfield.

Wood. Say f I would thou hadd lpoke this on CaRU-f<tnds y
And I within my Sword and Ponyards length
Of that falfe throat of thine. I pray fir, tell me
Of what Kin or Alliance do you take me
To the Gentlewoman you late mentioned?

Lejf. You are her Father.

Wood. Why then of all men living, do you addrefs
This Report to me, that ought of all men breathing
To have been the lad o’th Rowl, except the husband,

That fhouid have heard of’r ?

Lejf. For her honor Sir, and yours ;

That your good Councel may reclaim her.

Wood . J thank you.

Lejf. She has departed fir, upon my knowledge,

With Jewels, and with Bracelets, the fird Pledges,

And confirmation of th’unhappy Contract
Between her felf and husband.

Wood. To whom? Lejf. To Roch field.

Wftod. Be not abufed : but now,

Even now I faw her wear eYn. . x

Lejf. Very likely ; ’cis fit, hearing her husband is returned,
Thst ‘he fhouid re-deliver ’em.

Wood. But pray fir tell me,

How is it likely fhe could part with’em,

’VVhen they are loekt about her Neck and Wrifis*

And the Key with her husband ?

Lejf. Oh fir, that’s but pra&ife ;

She has got a trick to ufe another Key

Bcfides her husbands.

Wood.


A C un for * cuckold, > 1

Wood. Sirrah, you do lie; T

And were I to pay down a hundred pounds
For every Lie given, as men pay Twelve pence
And worthily, for .Swearing , I would give thee
The Lie , nay though it were in the Court of Hone*

So oft, till of the Thoufands I am worth,

I had not left a hundred. For is’t likely
So brave a Gentleman as Rochfeld is,

That did fo much at Sea to fave my life,

Should now on Land iliorten my wretched days,

In ruining my Daughter? A rank Lie!

Have you fpread this to any but my felf ?

Lejf. I am no Intelligencer.

Wood. Why then *tis yet afecret?

And that it may reft fo, Draw ; lie take order
You Thai! prate of it no further.

Lejf. Oh, my Sword

Is enchanted, Sir, and will not out o’th Scabbard :

I will leave you, fir; yet fay not I give ground,

For ’tis your own you (land on. Enter Bonvile dr Clare ,

Clare herewith Bonvile ? excellent! on this
I have more to work. This goes to Annabel ,

And it may increafe the Whirlwinde. Exit.

Boh. How now, Sir f Come, I know this choler bred in you
For the Voyage which I took at his entreaty ;

But I muft reconcile you.

Wood. On my credit

There’s no fuch matter. I will tell you Sir,

And I will tell it in laughter : The Caufe of it
Is fo poor, fo ridiculous,To impotfible V
To be believed ! Ha, ha, he came even now
And told me that one Rochjield , now a Gueft
( And moft worthy Sir, to be fo) inmyHoufe,

Is grown exceedingly familiar with my Daughter.

Bon. Ha? .?

Wood. Your wife, and that he has had favors from her.

Bon. Favors ?

- H ' Love*


A Cure for a CuckoM.

Love-tokens I did call ’em in my youth;

Lures to which Gallants Ipread their wings, and (loop

In Ladies bofoms. Nay, he was fo falfe

To Truth and all good Manners, that thofe Jewels

You lockt about her Neck, he did protefi

She had given to Rochfield ? Ha l mechinks o\h fudden

You do change colour. Sir, I would not have you

Believe this in leaft part: My Daughter’s honeft,

And my Guefs is a noble Fellow : And for this
Slander deliver’d me by Lejfmgham ,

I would have cut his throat.

Bin. As I your Daughters,

If I finde not the Jewels ’bout her.

CUre. Are you retu ned

With the Italian Plague upon you, Jealoufie ?

Wood. Suppofe that Lejfmgham fiiould love my Daughter*
And thereupon faihion your going over,

As now your Jealoufie , the Wronger way
So to divide you, there were a fine Crotchet !

Do you ftagger (fill ? If you continue thus, Enter Rochfield
I vow you are not worth a welcome home and Annabel

Neither from her, nor me. See, here fhe comes.

CUre. I have brought you home a Jewel.

Ann. Wear it your felf;

For thefe I wear are Fetters, not Favors.

Clare. I lookt for better welcome.

Roeh . Noble fir, I mull wooe your better knowledge ?

Bon. Oh dear fir,

My Wife will befpeak it for you.

Rich. Ha ? your Wife.

Vfood. Bear with him, fir, he’s ftrangely off o’th hinges.

Bon. The jewels are i’ch right place ; but the Jewel
Of her heart fiicks yonder. You are angry with me
For my going over.

Ann. Happily more angry for your coming over.

Bm. I fent you my Will from Dover ?

Ann. Yes Sir. Bm 0 Fetch it.


Ann,


A C»re for a Cuckold.

Ann. I fliall Sir, but leave your Self-will with you.
VV>od. This is fine, the woman will be mad coo."
Bon. Sir, I would fpeak with you.

Roch. And I with you of all men living.

Bon. I mu ft have fatisfaddion from you.

R9cb. Sir, it growes upon the time of payment.
Wood. What’s chat ? what’s that ? He have no whifp

Entor Amabel with a Will
An. Look you, there’s the Pattenc
Of your deadly affeddion to me.

Bon. Tis Wellcome,

When 1 gave my lelf for dead, I then made over
My Land unto you, now I finde your love
Dead to me, I will alcer’t*

An. Utevour pleafure,

A man may make a garment for the Moon,

Rather then fit your Conftancy.

Wood. How’s this? Alter your Will.

Bon. ’Tis in mine own difpofing,

Certainly I will alcer’c.

Wood. Will you fo my friend ?

Why then I will alter mine too.

I hacfeftated thee, thou peevifh fellow,

In forty thoufand pounds after my death,

I can finde another Executor.

Bon. Pray fir, do,

Mine He alter without queftion.

Wood. Doeft hear me?

And if I change not mine within this two hours,

May my Executors cozen all my kindred
To whom I bequeath Legacies.

Bon. I am for a Lawyer, fir,

Vfood* And I will be with one as foon as thy felf*
Though thou rideftpofle to’th devil.

Roch. Staylet me follow, and cool him.

V'E'ood. Oh by no means,

You’l put a quarrel upon him for the wrong 3

B a


A Cure for a Cuckold.

H ’lir e No y bdiev g e Sr, he's my mjht friend.

Wood. On come, I know the way of c; . • -

Carry it like a French quarrel privately whifper
Appoint to meet, and cut each others throats
With Cringes and Embraces , Iproceit
I will nor fuflfer you exchange a word

Without I over hear r. Exit Woo'dr off .‘ Richfield.

«t trareComake fine work now. . *'

Nav you are like to make a fineribmifinels of c
a";. Come, come, 1 mull fowderyou together.

An. You? why I heard r

A bird ling lately, you are the onely cau.e

Works the divifion.

Clare- Who ? As thou ever loved ft m w ^ ,

For I long, though I am a Maid, for t.

An. Lejjwgbam. firft cau f e

Clare. Why then I do prorett my ‘

Of the wrong, which he has put upon V^oi. both^

Which pleale you to walk in, I A’ | a

this toy!

tevets tee, Uf.ll

mod. sir, have 1 not raid I love you ? if I have,

You may bcliev’tbefore an Oracle,

For there’s no trick in’t, but the honeft fence.

Roch. Believe it, that I do, hr.

I fay you muft not fight with my ion
Roch Not fight with him, fir ?

I grant you may oe vfroi^w,


Exeunt.




Curs fer a Cuckold.

" ''I

So is my childe, but he is the husband,you know, ')

The womans lord, and muft not always be told
Of his faults neither, I fay you muft not fight.

Roch. lie fwear it,if you pleafe fir.

Wood. And forfvvear I know’t
E’re you lay ope the fecrets of your valour,

’Tis enough for me I faw you whifper,

And I know what belongs toft.

Rtch. To no fuch endj aflure you. ' Enter Lejfwgham

Wood, I fay you cannot fight wL h him.

If you be my friend for I muft ule you,

Yonder’s my foe, and you muft be my Second,

Prepare the Slanderer, and get another
Better then thy felf too ; for here*s my Second,

One that will fetch him up, and fierk him too.

Get your tools, I know the way to Callu-fa*ds y
If that be your Fence-fchool,hee’l fhow you tricks ’faiths
Hee’l let blood your Calumny, your beft guard
Will come to a Peccavl I believe.

Lejf. Sir, if that be your quarrel,

He’s a party in it, and muft maintain

The fide with me, from him I colle&ed

All thofe Circumftances concern your Daughter,

His own tongue’s confeftion. Y

Wcod, Who from him?

He will belie to do thee a pleafure then,

If he fpeak any ill upon himfelf, >

I know he ne’re could dp an injury.

Roch. So pleafe you, lie relate it, fir.

Enter Bonvile , Annabel^ Clare.
i Wood. Before her husband then, and here he is
In friendly pofture with my Daughter too;

I like that well. Son Bridegroom, and Lady Bride,

If you will hear a man defame himfelf,
f For fo he muft if he fay any ill,) then liftem
Bon. Sir, I have heard this ftory > and meet with your opi¬
nion in his goodnefs, the repitition will be needlefs.


A C m for A cuckold.

■ Etch. Your Father has noc, Sir. Ilebebrief in the delivery.

FFood. Do, do then, I long to hear it.

Roch. The firft acquaintance I had with your Daughter,

Was on the Wedding-Eve.

Wood. So, ’tis not ended yet, methinks.

Roch. I would have robb’dher. Wood. Ah, thief.

Roch . That Chain and Bracelet which fhe wears upon her, lEe
ranfom’d with the full eKleetn in Gold, which was with you my
Venture. FFood. Ah, thief agen.

Roch. For any attempt againft her honor, I vow I had no
Thought on. Wood. .An honeft thief ’faith yet,

Roch. Which Hie as nobly recompenc’d, brought me home,
And in her own difcretion thought it meet,

For cover of my fhame, to call me Coufin.

FFood. Call a thief Coufin ? Why,and fo fhe might, '

For the Gold fhe gave thee, fhe ftole from her husband ,

*Twas all his now, yet ’twas a good Girl too.

Roch . The reft you know, fir.

VFood. Which was worth all the reft, thy valor Lad ; but He
have that in Princ, becaufe I can no better utter it.

Roch. Thus (Jade unto my Wants, and fpurred by my Necef-
fities) I was going, but by that Ladies councel I was ftaid; (for
that Difcourfe was our familiarity.) And this you may take for
my Recantation, I am no more a thief.

VFood. A blefsing on thy heart,

And this was the firft time I warrant thee too.

Roch. Your charitable Cenfure is not wrong’d in that.

Wood. No, I knew ’c could be but the firft time at moft ]

But for thee (brave Valor) I have in ftore,

That thou .fhalc need to be a thief no more.

Soft Muftck^ Ha? What’s this Mufick ?

Ron. It chimes a Jep^^toyour Wedding, fir, ifthisbeyour
Bride. • - • ' .

Lejf. Can you forgive me f fome vvilde diftca&ions had over¬
turned my own condition, and fpilt the goodnefs you once knew
in me, but I have carefully recovered it, and overthrown the fury
cn’c. Clare, It was my caufe chat you were fo poffeft, an d all

thefe


Kd r Cure ftr a cuckold. , ;

thefe troubles have from my peevifia will original : i do repent,
though you forgive me not.

Lejf. You have no need for your repentance then which is due
to it: all’s now as at firft it was wifnt to be.

Wood. Why, chat’s well faid of all fides. But foft, this Mufick
has fome other meaning : Another Wedding towards, Good
fpeedj good fpeed.

Enter Compafs and the four Gallants , Bride between Franckjord
and another , Luce^ Ntirfe , and Childe.

Comp. We thank you, hr.

Wood. Stay flay, our neighbor Cempafs, is’t not ?

Cemp. That was, and may be agen to morrow, this day Mafler
Bridegroom.

Wood. Oh ! give you Toy- But.fir, if I be not miflaken , you
were married before now; how long is*c fince your wife died ?

Comp. Ever fince yefterday, fir.

Wood. Why, flic’s fcarce buried yet then.

Comp. No indeed, I mean to dig her grave foon, Ihadnolei*
fure yet. Wood. And was not your fair Bride married before?

Wife ; Yes indeed, fir. Wood. And how long fince your huf-
band departed ? wife. Jufl when my husbands wife died.

Wood. Blefs us H)men y are not theie both the fame parties ?

Bon. Moft certain,fir. Wood . What Marriage call you this ?

Comp. This is called Shedding of Horns, fir. VWood. How?

Lejf. Like enough, but they may grow agen next year.

Wood. This is a new trick. Comp. Yes fir,becaufe we did
not like the old trick. Wood. Brother, you are a helper in
this defign too. Fr. The Facher to give the Bride, fir.

Comp. And I am his fen, fir, and all the fons he has; and this
is his Grand-childe, and my elder brother, you’l think this ftrange
now. Wood. Then it feems he begat this before you ?

Comp. Before me ? not fo fir, I was far enough off when 'twas
done; yet let me fee him dares fay, this is not my Childe, and
this my father. Bon. You cannot fee him here, I think fir.

Wood. Twice married 1 Can it hold?

Comp. Hold? It fhould hold the better, a wife man would
think, when ’tis ty’d of two knots.


Wood ,


A cure for a Ctftkfld.

'Wood,. Methinks it fhould rather unloofe the firft,

And between ’em both make up one Negative.

Euft. No fir, for though it hold on the contrary, yet two Af¬
firmatives make no Negative. Wood. Cry you mercy, fir.

Comp. Make what you will, th s lit tie Negative was my wifes
laying, and I A form it to be mine own.

Wood.Thls proves the marriage before fubftantial,havingthis iflfue

Comp* s Tis mended now fir; for being double married , I may
now have two children at a birth, if I can get ’em. D’ ye think
lie be five years about one, as I was before ?

Enfo The like has bin done for the loCs of the Wedding-ring,
And to fettle a new peace before disjoynred.

Lyon . But this indeed fir, was efpecially done, to avoid the
word of Scandal, that foul word which the fatal Monologifi can¬
not alter. Wood. Cuckoo. Comp. What’s that, the Nigh¬
tingale ? Wood. A Night-bird, much good may do you, fir.

Comp. lie thank you when I’m at Supper. Come Father,
Childe, and Bride ; and for ybur part Father, whatfoeverhe, or
he,or t’other fays, you fhall be as welcome as in my t’other wifes
days, x ^ Fr. I thank you, fir.

Wood . Nay, take us with you, Gentlemen:

One Wedding we have yet to folemnize,

The firft is ftill imperfedf. Such troubles

Have drown’d our Mufick: but now I hope all’s friends.

Get you to Bed , and there the Wedding ends.

Ccmp. And fo good night, my Bride and lie to bed:

He that has Horns, thus let him learn to fhed. Exennt »

FINIS .


If any Gentlemen pie ofe to repair to my Hotifeafore[aid , they may
he ftirnifhed with all manner of Engllfh.or French Hiflories , Roman¬
ces , or Poetry ; which are to he fold , or read for reafonahle C onfide-
rations , J ■ ■ ...
