
Skip to main content

    Internet Archive Logo
    web
    books
    video
    audio
    software
    images
    search

    uploadUPLOAD
    personSIGN IN

    ABOUT
    CONTACT
    BLOG
    PROJECTS
    HELP
    DONATE
    JOBS
    VOLUNTEER
    PEOPLE

Full text of "The feign'd curtizans, or, A nights intrigue. A comedy. As it is acted at the Dukes theatre. Written by Mrs. A. Beh"
See other formats

• 'A THE

Feigned Curtizans

OR,

A Nights Intrigue.

A




As itisAcftedatthe

Dukes Theatre.



Written by Mrs. <*J. *B SH&(.



Licenfed Mar.ij.t 679. ROG ER 12ESTR 4NG JS.

L J\JZ) Ssj^

Printed fovfacob Tonfon at the fudges Head
ii\ Chancery^Lane near Fleet ^fireet. 1 6yp»






. ' . '-■'



.



< '




-■ r—


~W' ' ''-


..•■


*f \


■■:■ ■?}


h ■ ' ■•


•


5 \r




he

pi?






■ : -



i-



** ■



.



'htftiiS



\ 70! I .









.



Mrs. ELLE^CqVI^

Madam,

TI S no wonder thu hitherto I followed not the
good example of the believing Poets, fince lefs
faith and zeal then yon alone can infpire, had
wanted power to have reduc't me to the true wor-
fliip : Your permiffion, Madam has inlightened ra^
and I with fhame look back on my pall: Ignorance^
which fuffered me not to pay an Adoration longj
fince, where there was fo very much due, yet even
now though fecure in my opinion, I make this Sa-
crifice with infinite fear and trembling, well know-
ing that fo Excellent and perfect a Creature as your
felf differs only from the Divine powers in this j the
Offerings made to you ought to be worthy of you,
whilft they accept the will alone ; and how Madam,
would your Altars be loaded, if like heaven you
gave permiflion to all that had a will and defire to
approach 'em, who now at diftance can only wiih
and admire, which all mankinde agree to do ; as if
Madam, you alone had ths pattern: from heaven to
ingrofs all hearts 5 and even thofe diftant flaves
whom you conquer with your fame, pay an equall
tribute to thofe that have the bleifing of being woun-
tied by your Eyes, and boaft the happinefs of be-

A 2 holding



The Epijlle Dedicatory.

holding you dayly 5 infomuch that fucceeding ages
who mall with joy furvey your Hiftory (hall Envy
us who lived in his, andfaw thofe charming won-
ders which they can only reade of, and whom we
ought in charity to pity, fmce all the Pi&ures, pens
or pencil [s can draw, will give give 'em but a faint
Idea of what we have the honour to fee in fuch ab-
folute Perfection ■-, they can only guefs She was infi-
nitely fair, witty, anddeferving, but to what Vafi:
degrees in all, they can only Judge who liv'd to
Gaze and Liflen j for befides Madam, all the
Charms and attra&ions and powers of your Sex, vow
have Beauties peculiar to your felf, an eternal fweet-
nefs y youth and ayr, which never dwelt in any face
but yours, of which not one unirnitablc Grace could"
be ever borrow'd, or affumed, though with never
fo much induftry, to adorn another, they cannot
fteal a look or fmile from you to inhance their own
beauties price, but all the world will know it yours 9
fo Natural and (o fitted are all your Charms and Exp-
ediencies to one another, fo inrirely defend and
created to make up in you alone the moft perfect
lovely thing in the worlds you never appear but you
glad the hearts of all that h we the happy fortune to
fee yoUj as if you were made on purpofe to put the
whole world into good Humour, whenever you
look abroad,, and when you fpeak, men crowd to
Men with that awful! reverence as to Holy Oracles
or Divine Proprieties, and bears away the precious
words to tell at home to all, the attentive family,
the Graceful! things you utter'd "and cry, but oh fte

ffoke.



lm zpijue Dedicatory.

fpeke with fuch an Ayr y fo gay, that half the bean-
tys loji in the repetition. 5 Tis this that ought to'
make your Sex vain enough to defpifethe malicious
-world that will j How a woman no wit, and blefs
our felves for living in an Age that can produce fo
wondrous an argument as your undeniable felf, to
fhame thofe boafting talkers who are Judges-, of no^
thing but faults.

But how much in vain Madam, T endeavour to
tell you the fence of all mankinde with mine, fince
to the utmoft Limits of the Univcrfe your mighty
Con que fts are made known : And who can doubt
the Power of that -Illuftrious Beauty, the Charms of
that tongue, and the greatnefs of that minde, who
has fubdu'd the mo ft powerfull and Glorious Mo-
narch of the world : And fo well you bear the ho-
nours your were born for, with a greatnefs fo unaf-
fected, an aftabillity fo eaiie,an Humor fo foft, fo far
from Piide or Vanity, that the moft Envious & moft
difafFefted can finde no caufe or reafon to wifh you
lefs,Norcan TOaven give you: more,whotus cxpreft
a partieuLr care of you every way,and above all in
beftowing on the world and you, two noble Bran-
chesy who have all the greatnefs and fweetnefs of
their Royal and beautiful ftock:, and who give us too
a hopeful Profpecl: of what their future Braveries
will perform, when they fhall fhoot up and fpread
themfelves to th t degree, that all the leffer world
may finde rtpofe beneath their {hades °, and whom
you have permitted to wear thofe glorious Titles
which you your fel£*Generoufly negleSed, well

knowing;;



Jhe hpiflle Dedicatory.

knowing with the noble Poet ; 'tis better far to me-
rit Titles then to wear 'qm.

Can you then blame my Ambition, Madam, that
lays this at your feet, and begs a San&uary where al!
pay fo great a Veneration ? 'twas Dedicated yours
before it had a being, and overbufy to render it
worthy of the Honour,made it lefs grateful ^ and Po-
etry like Lovers often fares the worfe by taking r too
much pains to pleafe ; but under fo Gracious an In-
fluence my tender Lawrells may thrive, till they be-
come fit Wreaths to offer to the Rays that improve
their Growth: which Madam, I humbly implore,
you ftill permit her ever to do, who is,



Madam.



Your moft humble,



and Moft Obedient Servant,

I

■■■ . ■ • • '



J. Tehn.



The



4?4» < £ < !?<&^^*^4 , 4?*i?*!?4? 4?'-*t? 4* 4*'4? ^Mip 4»'4? 4* 4» 4» 4» 4» «$>

The PR OLOG U'E,
Spoken by Mrs. Currer.



THe devil take this curfed plotting Age,
'T has ruin d all our Plots upon the Stage ;
Sufpicions, New Elections, Jealousies,
Frefli Informations, New discoveries,
Do fo employ the bufie fearful Town ,
Our hone ft calling here is uf clefs grown; \
Each fool turns Politician now, and wears
A formal face, a?id talks of State-affairs ;
Makes Alls, Decrees, and a new <*JModell draws
For regulation both" of Church and Laws ;
Tires out his empty noddle to* invent
What rule and method } s befl in government;
"But Wit as if 'twere Jefuiticall,
Is an abomination to ye all:
To what a wretched pafs will poor Flays come,
This rnuft be damn d, the Tlot is laid in Rome \

'Tis hard~^*yei-^
Not one awongftye all Tie undertake,
Ere thought that we fhonldfuffer for Religions fake -
Who wou'dhave thought that wou'dhave been th'occafion^
Of any contefi in our hopeful I Nation?
For my own principles, faith, let me tell ye
Tme fill of the Religion of my (fully >,
And till thefe dangerous times they'd none to fix on y
But now are fomething in meer contradiction,
Andpioujly pretend, thefe are not days,
For keeping sJMiftreffss and feeing Flays.
Who fays this Age a Information wants,
When Betty Currer's Lovers all turn Saints?
hW * In vain alas I flatter, fwear, and vow,

Tou'l fcarce do any thing for Charity now:
Tet I am handfome fiilL ftill young and mad,j

Can wheadle, lie, diffimbte, ph 'egad, >

As well and artfully as en 1 did, 3 t

Tet not one Conquefl can I gain or hope,

No Prentice, not a Foreman of a Shop,

So that I want extremely New Supplies ;

Of my lafi Coxcomb, faith, thefe were the Vriti^



Jnd by the tatter 'd Bnftgnes yen may kpow,

Tkefe [foils were of a Vittory long ago:

Who won'dhave thought fuch hellifh times to' lie JeeHy

When Ifbou'd be neglefbed at eighteen ?

That T outh andBeautyfhorfd be quite undone,

A Pox-Hfon the Whore of Babylon.



The A<5tors Names*



Mr' Noms,
Mr. Crosby.



Italians.
MorifinL An Old Count Uncle to fulio,

Julio. His Nephew, a young Count, con-

tracted to Laura Lucretia.

A young Count contracted to
Marcella,-deform'd, revengeful.

Crapine. ^JMorijinPs man.

Vetro. Suppos'd Pimp to the two Cur*

tezans,

Englilh.

Sir Harry Fillamour. In love with Marcella. •
Mr. Galliard. In love with Cornelia.

Sir Signal I Buffoon. A fool.
Mi. Underbill. W.Tickktext, His Governour*

Jack^ Sir Signals man.

Women,
Laura Lucretia.



Mr. Cftlloe . Ottavio.



Mr. Liegh,



Mr. Smith.
Mr. Betterton.
Mr. Ifykss.



Mrs Lee.



Mrs Oarer.

Mrs 'Barry.
Mrs Norris.



Marcella.

and
Cornelia.

Phillifa,



Mrs Seymour. Sabina,



A young Lady of Quallity,contract-
ed to Julio, in love with Galliard^
and Sifter to Ollavio*

Sifters to ?#//<>, and Nieces to Mo-
hfini, pals for Curtizans by the
Names otjEuphemia & Silvianett*

Their Woman.

Confident to Laura Lucretia.



i



Pages, Mufick, Footmen, and Bravo's.



— I



SCENE, &§N6



CO

THE



FeignMCurtizans,

OR,

A D^tqHTS l^T'RiqVB.



ACT I. SCENE I.

Enter Laura, Lucretia, and Silvio richly dreft ; Antonio attending.
Coming all in in hafie.

Silvio.

MAdam, you need not make fuch hafte away, the Stranger
that follow'd us from St. Peters Church, purfues us no
longer, and we have now loft fight of him: Lord who
wou'd have thought the approach of a handibme Cavalier
fhould have pofleft Dona Laura Lucretia with fear ?

Lou. 1 do not fear my Silvio, but I wou'd have this new Habitation
which I've defign'd for love, known to none but him to whom I've de-
ftin'd my heatt : — a ah wou'd he know the Conqueft he has made,
{_ Afide.~] Nor went I this evening to Church with any other Devotion,
but that which warms my heart for my young Englifh Cavalier, whom
1 hop't to have feen there, and I mull finde fbme way to let him know
my paflion which is too high for fouls like mine to hide.
Silv. Madam, the Cavalier's in view again, and hot in the purfuit
Lau. Lets hafte away then, and Silvio do you lag behinde, 'twill
give him an opportunity of Enquiring, whilft 1 get out of fight, — -be
lure you conceal my Name and Quality^ and tell him — any thing but
truth — tell him I am La Silvianetta the young Roman Curtizan, or
what you pleafe to hide me from his knowledge. £ Exeunt La,u.

Eiiter Julio and Tage in Purfuit.

Jul. Boy fali you intodifcourfe with that Page, and learn his Ladys
Name- — whilft I purfue her farther. £ Exeunt Jul.

Page falutesS*/™*, who returns it, they go out as talking to
each other.

B Enter



2 The Feign'd Cnrti%ans^

Enter Sr Harry Fillamour and Galliard.

Fill. He follows her dole, whoe're they be : I fee this tra<fb of Love
goes forward (bill.

Gall. And will whilft there's difference in Sexes. But Harry the wo-
men, the delicate Women I was fpeaking of?

Fill. Prethee tell me no more ot thy fine Women, Franks, thou^gfl
not been in Rome above a Month, and thou'aft been a Dozen times in
Love as thou calFft it : to me there is no pleafure like Conftancie.

Call. Conftancy ! and woudft thou have me one of thofe dull Lovers
who believe it their Duty to Love a Woman till her Hair and Eyes
change Colour for fear of the Scandalous Name of an inconftant ! No,
my Paffion like great Vi&ors hates the lazy flay, but having vanquifht,
prepares fornewConquefts.

Fill. Which you gain as they do Towns by Fire, lofe'emeven in
the taking, thou wo'tgrow Penitent and weary of thefe Dangerous
follys.

Gall. But I am yet two young for both : Let old Age and infirmity

bring Repentance, there's her feeble Province , and even then

too we finde^no Plague like being depriv'd of dear Woman-kinde. ■

Fill. I hate Playing about a Flame that will confume me.

Gall. Away with your Antiquated Notions, and let's once hear
fence from thee .• Examine but the whole World Harry, and thou wilt
findea Beautifull woman the defire of the Nobleft, and the reward of
the Braveft.

Fill. And the common Prize of Coxcombs : times are alter'd now,
Frank^why elfe fhou'd the Virtuous be cornuted, the Coward be careft,
the Villain role with Six, and the Fool lye with her Ladyfhip.

Gall. Meer Accident Sir : and the kindnefs of Fortune, but a Pretty
witty young Creature, fuch as this SUvianetta, and Fupbemia, is cer-
tainly the greateft bleffwg this wicked World can affora us.

Fill. I believe the Lawful enjoyment of fuch a Woman, and honeft
too, wou'd be a bleffing.

Gall. Lawful enjoyment ! Prethee what's lawful enjoyment, but to
enioy'em according to the generous indulgent Law of Nature ^ en-
joy'em as we do Meat, Drink, Ayr and Light, and all the relt of her
common bleffings ^—therefore prithee dear Knight,Iet me govern thee
but for a day, and I willfhew thee fuch a Signiora, fuch a Beauty, an-
other manner of piece then your fb admired Vitterboan, Dona Marcella,
of whomyou boaft fo much..

Fill. And yet this rare piece is but a Curtizan, in courfe plain Eng-
liih, a very Whore !■ — <

Who filthily expofes all her Beaufcys to him can give her moft, not
Love her belt

Gall.



Of, A Nights Intrigue. ^

Gait, Whe faith, to thy comfort be it fpoken, fhe does diftribute
her charms at that eafy rate.

Fill. Oh the vaft diftance between an innocent paffion, and a poor
faithlefs Luft.

Gall. Innocent Paflion at Rome ! Oh 'tis not to be nam'd but in fome
Northern Climat : to be an,Anchoret here, is to be an Epicure wGrecn-

l<md\ impoffibillities Harry !

— M£ Sure thou haft been advifing with Sir Signal 'Buffoons Gover-
nor ! that formal! piece of nonfenfe and Hipocrifie.

Fill. No faith, I brought the Humour along with me to Rome, and
for your Governor I have not feen him yet,though he lodge in this fame
Houfe with us, and you prorais'd to bring me acquainted with long
fince.

Gall. Pie do't this very minute 1

Fill. No, I'me oblig'd not to engage my felf this Evening, becaufe
I expect the arrival of Count Jh%o\ whole Iaft Letters affur'd me wou'd
be to night.

Gall. JulioX What the young Itallian Count you made me acquain-
ted with laft Summer in England ?

Fill. The lame, the Ambafadors Nephew, a good youth and one
lefteem.

Enter Julio.

Jul. I hope my Page will bring intelligence who this beauty is.

Fill. Hah, Julio \ Welcome dear Friend. ^Embraces him.

Jul. Sir Harry Fillamour ! how glad am I to meet you in a Country
where I have power to repay you all thofe Friendfhips I receiv'd when I
was a ftranger to yours.

Monfieur Galliard too^ nay then I'me fure to want no diverfion whilfb
I ftay in Rome. £ Salutes Galliard.

Fill. But pray, what made you leave England lb foon ?

Jul. E'ne the great bulinefs of Mankinde, Matrimony, I have an
Uncle here who has provided me Fetters which I mnft put on, he fays,
they will be eafy, I lik't the Character of my Miftrefs well enough, a
brave Malculine Lady, a Roman of Quality, Dona Laura Lucretia, till.
as luck wou'd have it at my arrival this Evening, ftepping into S.Peters
Church, I law a woman there that fir'd my heart, and whom I fol-
low'dto herhoufc ;but meeting none that cou'd inform me who ihe
was, I left my Page to make the difcovery, whillt I with equal impati-
ence came to look out you ; whofe light I prefer even to a new Amour,
relblving not to vilit home, to which I have been a ftranger this leven
years, till Lhad kift your hands, andgain'dyourpromifeto accom-
pany me to Vitterbo.

Fill Vitterbo ! is that your place of Refidence?

Jul. Yes j 'tis a pretty Town,and many noble Familys inhabit there,
ftor'd too with Beauties,at leaft,'twas wont to be : have you not ieen it?

B % G*"



4 The Feign d Curti^ans,

Gall. Yes ! and a Beauty there too lately for his repofe, who has
made him figh and look ib like an Afs ever fince he came to %ome.

Jul. I'me glad you have fb powerfull an argument to invite yoa
back, I know ihe mult be rare, and of quality that cou'd engage your
heart.

Fill. She's both, it moft unluckily fellout, that I was recommended
by a Perfbn of Quality in England to a Nobleman at Vitterbo, who be-
ing a man of a temper frank and gallant, receiv'd me with lefs Cere-
mony then is ufMl in Italy. I had the freedom of the Houfe, one of the
fineft ^Y/^'s belonging to Vitterbo, and the pleafure to fee and con-
verfe at a diftance, with Oneofthelovelieftperfons in the World, a
Neece of this old-Counts.'

Jul. Very well, and cou'd you lee her but at diftance, Sir ?

Fill. Oh, no, 'twas all I durll defire, or ihe durll give ^ I came too
late to hope ^ (he being before promisM in Marriage to a more happy
man, the ConCummation of which waits only the arival of a Brother
of hers, who is now at the Court of France, and every day expected.
Enter Petro like a Barber.

Gall. Hah! Signior Petro :

Fill. Come Sir, we'l take a turn in the i'th gallery, for this pimp
never appears but Frances defires to be in private.

Gall. Thou wrong'it an honelt ingenious fellow to call him pimp.

Tet. Ah Signior, what his worfhip pleafes !

Gall. That thou art I'le be fworn, or what any mans worlhip
pleafes, for let me tell ye Harry y he is capacitated to oblige in any quali-
ty •, , for Sir, he's your brokering Jew, yourTencmg, Dancing and Ci-
villity-Malter, your Linguift, your Antiquary,, your Bravo, your Pa-
thick, your Whore, your Pimp, and a thoufand more Excellencies he

has to fupply thenecefiities of the wanting flranger. Well firrah

What defigne now upon Sir SzjWand his wife Governor ; — -What
do you reprefent now ?

Pet. A Barber Sir.

Gall. And why a Barber^ good Signior Petro ?
' Pet: Oh Sir, the fooner to take the heights of their judgments, it
gives handfome opportunities to commend their faces, for if they are
pleafed with flattery, the certain fign of a fool's to be moil tickled when
moll commended, I conclude 'em the fitter for my purpofe ; they al-
ready put great confidence in me, will have no Mailers but of my recom-
mending, all which I fupply my felf, by the help of my feveral di£-
guifes^ by which and myinduflry, I doubt not but to pickup a good
honeft painfull livelihood, by cheating thefe two Reverend Coxcombs

Gall. How the Devil got'ft thou this credit with 'em ?

'Pet. Oh eafily Sir, as knaves get eftates, or fools employments.

Fill. I hope amongft all your gpod qualities you forgot not your



more natural one of pimping,



Tet,



Or, A Nights Intrigue. 5

Pet. No, I allure you Sir, I have told Sir Signal Buffoon \ that no
Man lives here without his Inamorata, which very word has fo fir'd
him, that he's refolv'd to have an /namorata, whatever it coft him,
and as in all things elfe I have in that too promis'd my afliftance.

Gall. If you affile him no better then you have done me he may ftay
longenoughforhis Inamorato.

Pet. Why faith Sir, I lye at my young Lady night and day, but (he

is fo loath to part with that fame Maiden-head of hers yet but to

morrow night Sirther's hopes.

Gdl. To morrow night ! Oh 'tis an Age in Love ! defire knows no
timebuttheprefentj'tisnowl wilh, and now I wou'd enjoy, a new
day ought to bring a new defire.

Pet, Alas Sir Tme but an humble Bravo.

Gdl. Yesthou'rtapimp, yet want'ft the art to procure a longing
lover the woman he acfores, tho'buta common Curtizan- — Oh con-
found her Maidenhead — She underftands her trade too well to have
that badge of Innocence.
Pet. I offered her her price Sir-^

Gall. Double it, give anything, For that's the bed receipt / ever
found to foften womens hearts.

Pet. Well Sir, fne will be this Evening in the Garden, of Medtoes
Villa, there you may get an opportunity to advance your intereft — *
/ mult itep and trim Mr „ Tkkjetext, and then am at your ferviee !

Q Exit Petro.
Jul. What is this Knight and his Governor who have the blefled for-
tune to-be manag'd by this Squire ?

Fill. Certain fools Galliard makes life on when he has a minde to
laugh : and whom / never thought worth a vifit fince / came to Rome :
and he's lLke to profit much by his Tra veils, who keeps company with
all the Englim, efpecially the Fops.

Gall. Faith Sir, / came not abroad to return with the formallity of a
Judge :, and thefe are fuch anditotes againft Melancholy as wou'd make
thee fond of fooling. Our Knights Father is even the firit Gentle-
man of his Houfe, a fellow, who having the good Fortune to be much
a fool and knave, had the attendant blefling of getting an Eitate of
lome eight thoufand a year, with this Coxcomb to inherit it -, who ( to
agrandize the Name and Family of the Buffoons ) was made a Knight,
but to refine throughout and make a compleatFop, was fent abroad
under the Government of one Mr. Tickletext his zealous Fathers Chap-
lain, as errant a block-head as a man wou'd wilh to hear Preach : the
Father wifely forefeeing the eminent danger that young Travellers
are in of being perverted to Popery. .
Jd. 'Twas well confider'd.

Gall. But for the young Spark there is no defcription can reach him \
\is only to be done by hinifelf-,letitfuffice 'tis a pert, fawcy, con-

x ceiteel \



£ The Feign 9 d Cur titans,

ceited Animal, whom you fhall juft now go fee, and admire, for he
lodges in the houfe with us. d

Jttl. With ail my heart,I never long'd more for a new acquaintance.

Fill. And in all probability mall fooner defire to be rid on't.
aloone.— \^€xemt.

SCENE II.

Ilrawsoff, and discovers Mr. Tickletext a Trimming, his hair
under a Cap, a cloath before him, and Petro Snap his finger 7,
takes away the Bafon, and goes to wiping his face.

Tickletext and Petro.

Vet. Ah che Bella! Bella! I fwear by thefe fparkling Eyes, andthefe
foft Plump dimpl'd cheeks, there's not a Signior a in all Rome, cou'd
me behold 5 em, were able to ftand their Temptations, and for La
Silvimetta, my life on't ihe's your own.

Tick, Teze, teze, fpeakfoftly ! — but honeft Barberacho, do I, do
I indeed look plump, and young,-$md frefh and — hah !

l>e t . Ay Sir, as the Rone Morn, young, as old Time in his Iiifan-
cie, and plump as the Pale-fac't Moon.

Ticks He — Whe this Travelling mull needs improve a Man, — ■
Whe how admirably well fpoken your very Barbers are here,

C Afide. 3 — but Barber acho, did the young Gentlewoman fay ihe

lik't me ? did Ihe Rogue ? did ihe ?

Pet. Adoatedonyou Signior, doatedonyou.

Tick; Whe, and that's ftrange now, in the Autumn of my Age too,
when Nature began to be impertinent, as a man may fay, that a

young Lady fnou'd tall in love with me — »- — {jtAJide. • .

Whe Barber acho, I do not conceive any great matter of Sin only in vifi-
ting a Lady that loves a man, hah.

"Pet. Sin Sir, 'tis a frequent thing now adays in Perfons of your
Complexion.

Tick; Efpeeially here at Rome too, where 'tis no Scandal.

Pet. Ay Signior, where the Ladys are Priviledgd, and Fornication
Licenc*t.

Ticks Right ! and when^tis Licensed "'tis Lawful^andwhen "'tis Lawful it can-
be no Sin : befides Barberacho, I may chance to turn her, who knows !
Pet. Turn her Signior, Alafs any way, which way you pleafe.

Tick: He he he ! There thou wert knavilh, I doubt- — but I mean
Convert her Nothing elfe I profefs Barberacho.

Pet. True Signior, true, fhe's a Lady of an eafy Nature, and an
Indifferent Argument well handled will do't- — ha- — f combing out

here's your head of Hair here's your Natural Frize ! his Hair.

Andliich an Ayr it gives the Face ! So Signior— -Now you have

the utmoft my Art can do. . L **h s *w*y &e cloth and bows.

Tick.



Or, A Nights Intrigw. j

Tkki Well Signior : — and where's your looking-glafs.

Vet, My looking-glafs.

Tickz Yes Signior your Looking-glafs ! anEnglifli Barber wou'd as
foon have forgotten to have fnapt his fingers, made his leg, or taken
his Money, as have negle&ed his looking-glafs.

Pet. Aye Signior, in your Countrey the Laiety have fo little ho-

nefty, they are not to be trufted with the taking off your Beard unlefs

you fee't done, — -but heres a Glafs, Sir, Lg*ws him the Glafs.

QTick. Sets himfelf and [mirks in theGlafs, Pet. fianding behinde

him, making horns and grimace s^ which Tick, fees in the Glafs ^

gravely rijes ,, turns towards Petro.

Tick. Whe how now, Barberacho, what Monftrous faces are you
making there ?

Pet. Ah my Belly, my Belly, Signior: ah, 6his Wind-Collick ! this
Hypocondriach does fo torment me ! ah

Tick; Alafs poor Knave; certo^ I thought thou hadft been lome-
what uncivil with me, I profefsl did ^

Pet. Who I Sir, uncivil ? 1 abufe my Patrone ? — -I that have al-

molt made my felf a Pimp to ferve you ?

Tick* Teze teze, honeft Barberacho \ no, no, no, all's well, all's
well : — but hark y'- — you will be difcreet and fecret in this bufinefs
now, and above all things conceal the knowledge of this Gentlewoman
from Sir SignaU and Mr. Galliard.

Pet. The Rack Signior, the Rack fliall not extort it.

Tick. Hold thy hand there's fomewhat for thee, [_giveshim

but (hall I Rogue fhall 1 fee her to night ? — • — - money.

Pet. To night Sir, meet me in the Piatza D^hifyagnia, about 10 a

Clock, Fie meet you there, but 'tis fit Signior — that I mould

provide a Collation, 'tis the Cuftom here Sir. — • —

Tick, Well, well, what will it come to,- — here's an Angel— —

Pet. Whe Sir 'twill come to — about—for you wou'd do't han-
fomely — -fbme twenty Crowns. .

Tick: How man, twenty Crowns ?

Pet. Ay Signior, thereabouts.

Tick: Twenty Crowns — -Whe 'tis a Sum, a Portion, a Revenue.

Pet. Alafs Signior, 'tis nothing with her, — -(he'le look it out in an
hour,— — ah fuch an Eye ! fo fparkling, with an Amorous twire— - thus

Sir — then Ihe'le kifs it out in a moment, fuch a Lip , lb red, fo \

round, and fo plump, fo loft, and fo — - — -

Tickz -.Why has me, has (he, Sirrah — hah — here, here, prethee
take Money, here, and make no words on't— go, go your way, go—
but to entertain Sir <%«**// with other matter, pray fend his Matters
to him 5 if thou canft help him to Matters, and me to Miftrefles, thou

Jhali be the good Genius of us bptfi: but fee wher^ he comes.— ->

'•' ■--'■■■' i ***i*}_ ■ Sir"



8 The Feign'd Cnni%ans^

Enter Sir Signall.
Sir Sig. Hah ! Signior Illnftriffimo 'Barberacho, let me hugg thee my

little Miphffiopbibttcho de yee fee here, how fine your Brokering

Jew has made me, Scgnior %abbi Manafeth-Ben—Nebiton, and fo

forth ; hah View me round — « — » £ turns round.

lick. I profefs 'tis as fit as if it had been made for you.
Sir Sig. Made for me— — Whe Sir, he f wore to me by the old Law,
that 'twas never worn but once, and that but by one high-German
Prince — 1 have forgot his name — for the Devil can never remem-
ber thefe damn'd Hogan-Mogan Titles . £ a fart.
Tickz No matter, Sir.

Sir Sig. Ay, but I fhou'd be loth to be in arty mans clothes, Were
he never fb high a German-Prince, except / knew his name tho.

Tick^ Sir, 1 hold his Name unneceflary to be remembred, fb long
as 'twas a Princely penniwortb, — •'Barberacho get you gone, and fend
the Matters. [ Ex. Petro.

Sir Sig. Why how now Governour ! how now Signior Tickletext !
prethee how cam'ft thou fo tr anfmografi'd, ha ? whe thou look'ft like
any new-fledg'dC/v/?^.

Tick. Do I, away you flatter, Eb/?

Sir Sig. As I hope to breathe, your face mines through your pow-
der'd hairs like you know what on a barn-door, in a frofty morning.
Tick. What a filthy comparifon's there for a mart of my coat.
Sir Sig. What, angry — Corpo di me, I meant no harm, — Come,
(hall's to a Bonaroba, where thou fhalt part with thy pufilage, and
that of thy beard together.

Tick, How mean you Sir, a Curtizan, and a Romifh Curtizan ?

Sir Sig. Now my Tuter's up, ha ha ha, and ever is when one

names a whore ; be pacifi'd man, be pacifi'd, / know thou hat'ft 'em
worfe then beads or holy-wa'er.

Tick. Away you are fuch another Knight — but leave this Naughty
difcourfe, and prepare for your Fencing and Civility-Matters, who
are coming,

Sir Sig. Ay, when Governour, when \ oh how I long for my Civili-
ty-Matter, that I may learn to out-complement all the dull Knights

and Squires in Kent, with a Servitore Hidichimo Nofigniora Bellijfima,

bafe le Mane, de vosjigniorafenfa mia Ilhiflrijfimo, cafpeto de Bacco, and
ib Pie run on, hah Governor, hah ! won't this be pure ?
Tick; Notably Ingenious, I profefs!

Sir Sig. Well Pie fend my Stajfiera for him incontinente . — he^Jack —
a — CazjQ> what a Damn'd Englifh name is Jack] let me fee — I will
call feim — Giovanni, which is as much as to fay John ! — -he Gio-
vanni. £ Enter Jack.
Ttckc Sir, by your favour his Englifh Proteftant-Name is John Pep-
per \ and Pie call him by ne're a Popiih name in Chriftiandom.

Sir&£.



Or, A Nights Intrigue^ p

Sir Sig. Pk call my own man Sir, by what name I pleafe Sir -, and
let me tell you Reverend Mr. Tickletext, Ifcorn to be ferv'd by any
man who's name has not an Acho, or an Oucho, or lome ItMlimo at the
end on't — .therefore Giovanni Peperacho is the name by which you fhaff
be diftinguilht and dignify'd hereafter.

Tick. Sir Signal!, Sic Signally let me tell you, that to call a man out
of his name is unwarantable, for Peter is call'd Peter, and John, John,
and Pie not fee the poor fellow wrong'd of his name for nere a GiWm-
m in Rome.

Sir Sig. Sir I tell you that one Itallian Name is worth any two En~
glifh names in Europe ; and Pie be judg'd by my Civility-Mafter.

Tick, Who mail end the difpute, if he be of my Opinion.

Sir Sig Mnlto vollemiero, which is as much as to fay, with all my
heart. . •

Jacks But Sir, my Grandmother .wou'd never own me if I fhould
change the curfen name (he gave me with her own hands, an't pleafe
your Worfhip.

Sir Sig, He i?e/?/V*! Pie have no more of your Worfhip, firrah, that
old Englifh Sir Reverence, let me have you call me Signior Jlluflrifimo,
or Patrona Me* — »or

Tick, I> that I like well enough now : — but hold, lure this is one
of yourMafters.

Enter Petro drefi like a French Fencing Mafier*

Pet. Signior Barber acho has fent me to teach you de Art of Fencing,

Sir Sig. Wujhijfimo Signior Monfieur, I am the Perfbn who am to
learn.

Ticks Stay Sir ftay, — letmeaskhimfbms few queftions firft, for
Sir / have play'd at Back-Sword and couM have handled ye a weapon
as well as any man of my time in the Univerflty.

Sir Sig. Say you fb Mr. Tickletcxt, and /'faith you fliall have about
with him. QTick. Gravely goes to Petro.

Tick. Hum — hum — -Mr. <JMonfieur — -pray what are the CJuards
that you like beft?

- Pet . Monfieur, eder de Quart or de Terfe, dey be both French and
itallian ; den for your Parades, degagements, your advancements,
your Eloynements, andRetierments: dey be defame - 7

Tick, Cart and Horfe, what new found inventions and words have
we here, — -Sir I wou'd know, whether you like St. Georges Guard or
not.

'Pet. Mon-^—Monfieur, Mettcvous en Guard ! take de Flurette.

Sir Sjg. Nay faith and troth Governor thOu (hat have a Rubbers
with him . X Tick. Smiling refufis.

Tick, Nay certoSh Signal?-* »andyet you mall prevail ;— well Sir,
come your T ^ays ? [Takes the jiuret.

C Pet,



tp The Feign'd Cnrti%ans^

Yet, Set your right foot forward, turn up your hand fo — dat be
de Quart — 'Now turn it dns- — and dat be de Terfe.

Tick. Hocus, Pocus, Hickfius, Doxius- — here be de Cart and here
be de Horfe — why what's all this for, hah Sir— and where's your guard
all this while ?

Sir Sig* Ay Sir where's your Guard Sir, as my Governor fays, Sir,
hah?

Tkkz Come, come, Sir, I muft inftruft you I fee — Come your ways
Sir. —

Pet. aATande aTa?ide itmpew, — truft de right hand and de right
leg forward together. — ■

Ticks. I marry Sir, that's a good one indeed ! what fhall become of
my head then Sir, what Guard have Heft for that good Mr. Monfieur,.
hah?

Pet. AhMorblew, is not dis for every ting ?

Tick, No marry is it not Sir, St. Georges Guard is the belt for your
head whilftyou live, :as thus Sir.

Pet. Dat Sir, ha ha dat be Guard for de Back-Sword.

Tick, Back-fword Sir, yes, Back-fword, what mould it be elfe.

Pet. Anddisbede Single-Rapier..

Tick. Single-Rapier with a vengeance, there's a weapon for a
Gentleman indeed ;, is all this ftir about Single-Rapier ?

Pet. Single-Rapier / What will you have for de Gentleman, de
Gudgellforde Gentleman?

Tickz No Sir, butlwou'dhave it for deRafcally French -man who
comes to abufe perfons of Quality with Paltry Single-Rapier. — Single

Rapier ! Come Sir, come, put your felf in your Cart and your

Horfe as you call it, and I'le ihew you the difference.

Undreffes himfelftill he appears in a Ridiculous Poflure.

Pet. Ah Monfieur me fall run you two three times through de body,
and den you break a me head, what care 1 for dat : — -Pox on his ig-
norance ! \_Afide.

Tick. Oh ho Sir, do your worlt Sir, do your worfl: Sir.

They put themfelves into fever l al Guards, and Tick, beats Pet. about
the Stage ,EnterGa\\. Fill, and Jul.

Pet. Ah Monfieur, Monfieur, will you kill a me ?

Tick- Ah zJMonfieur where be your Carts now and your Horfe, Mr.
Monfieur, hah ! and your Single-Rapier Mr. Monfturhdh]

GaU.\ Why how now Mr. Tkkletext, what mortal wars are thefe ?
-Ajax and Vliffes contending for Achittis his Armour ?

Pet. If i be not reveng'd on him, hang me : [ Afide.

Sir Sig. Ay, why who the Devil wou'd have taken my Governor
for fo tall a man of hands, but Corpo <fe«Mr.. Galtiard, I have not
feen his Fellow.



Or, A "Nights Intrigue. 11

Tick. Ah Sir, time was, I wou'd have play'd ye a Match at Cudgells
with e're a Sophifter in the Colledge, but verily I have forgotten it,
but here's an impudent French-man that wou'd havepaft Single-Ra-
pier upon us.

Gall. How, nay a my word then he deferv'd to be chaftis'd fort.*-*
!> — but now all's at peace again -, Pray know my kinfman, Sir Harry
Fillamour.

Sir Sigi To baco les manos, Signior II faJlrijUmo Cavalier^ — —and yours
Signiors who are Mdto bien V'mito ;

Tjck. Oh Lord Sir, you take me Sir— in fuch a pofture Sir—as I
proteft I have not been feen in this many years.

£ Drsjfmg himfelfwhilfl be talks.

Fill. Exercife is good for health Sir.

Call. Sir Signal, you are grown a perfect Itallian ? Well Mr. Tickle*
text you will carry him home a moftaccompliuYt Gentleman I fee !

Tick. Hum, verily Sir though I fay it, for a man that never travell'd
before, I think I have done reafbnably well;— -1'Ie tell you Sir — -it
was by my directions and advice, that he brought over with him, — -
two Englifh knives, a thoufand of Englifh pins, four pair ofjerfey
ftockings, and as many pair of Buck-skin Gloves*

Sir Sig-. Ay Sir, for good Gloves you know are very fcarce comodi-
ties in this Country*
ffil. Here Sir at Rome, as you fay, above all other places.

Tick. Certo meer hedging-Gloves Sir, and the clouterleft feams.- — \

Fill. Very right Sir, — -and now he talks of Rome,- — 'Pray Sir give
me your opinion of the place ? — *are there not Noble buildings here ?
rare ftatues, and admirable Fountains ?

Tick- Your buildings are pretty buildings,but not comparable to our
Univerfity-buildings \ your Fountains I confefs are pretty Springs, -
and your ftatues reafbnably well carv'd— —but Sir, they are fo ancient
theyareofnovallUe! then your Churches are the worft that ever I
faw — -that ever I faw.

Gall. How Sir, the Churches, why I thought Rome had been famous
throughout 2W Europe for fine Churches.

Fill. What think you of St* Peters Church Sir, Is it not a glorious
ftrutture ?

Tick. St. Peters Church Sir, you may as well call it St. Peters Hall Sir \
it has neither Pew, Pullpit, Desk, Steeple, nor Ring of Bells, and call
you this a Church Sir? no Sir, Pie fay that for little England, and a fig
for't, for Churches, eafy Pulpits [ Sir Sig. (peaks , and fleeping Pews,]
they are as well order'd as any Churches in Chriftiandom : and finer
Rings of Bells Sir, Pam fure were never heard.

Jul. Oh Sir there's much in what you fay.

C 2 Fill-



io. the Feigned Cmti%ans,

Fill. But then Sir, your Rich Altars, and excellent Fiftures of the
greateft Matters of the World, your delicate Mufick r and Voices,
make fome amends for the other wants.

Tick. How Sir ! tell me of your Rich Altars, your guegaws and trin-
kets, andPopifhFoperies! with a deal offing-fong — -when I fay give
me Sir five hundred dole changes rung by a let of good Ringers, and
I'le not exchange 'em for all the Anthens in Europe : and for the Fi-
gures Sir, they are fuperftition, Idolatrous, and flat Fopery.

Fill. I'le convince you of that errour that perfwades you harmlefi
Pictures are Idolatrous.

Tick. How Sir, how Sir, convince me, talk to me ofbeingxonvinc't
and that in favour of Popery ; No Sir, by your favour I fhall not be
convinc't, convinc't quoth a — -No Sir far you well an you be for con-
vincing, come away Sir Signally far you well Sir, far you well-— con-
vin'ct. Lgoes ont.

Sir Big. Ha, ha, ha, lb now is my Governor gone in a Fuftian-fume 7
well, he is ever thus when one talks of whoring and Religion, but
come Sir walk in,, and I'le undertake my Tutor ihailbeg your pardon-
and renounce his Englifh ill-bred opinion y Nay, his Englilh Churches
too- — all but his own Vicaridge.

Fill. I have better diverfion Sir I thank you — come Julio, are you.
tor a walk in the Garden of zJHedicesVilla* 'tis hard by ? — ■

Jul. I'le wait on you- — [Ex. Fill . and Julio.

Sir Sig. How in the Garden of Medices Villa — but harkey Galliard,
will the Ladies be there, the Curtizans ! the bona robots^ the inamora-
ta; V, and the Bell ingrato's, . hah ?
. gall. OhdoubtlefsSir^ [Ex. Gall

Sir Sig. I'le ene bring my Governor thither to beg his Pardon, on.
purpofe to get an Opportunity to fee the fine Women ^ it may be I may
get alight of my new Miftrefs, Dona Silvianetta whom Petro is to bring
me acquainted with. [Exeunt,



'...;:..•-■

. . : ' • I



Or, A Night f Intrigue. 1 3



ACT II. SCENE I.

Inter Murifmi and O&a vio .

D#.T> Y Heaven I will not Eat, nor fleep, nor pray for anything but
JDfwift and fure Revenge, till) have found zJMarcella, that falie
deceiving Beauty or her Lover, my hated Rival Fillamour ! who wan-
ton in the Arms of the fair Fugitive laughs at my mamefull eafmefs,
and crys, thefejoys were never meant for tame OBavio !

Enter C rapine.

tJMur. How now (rapine ! What no news, no news of my Neeces
yet, Marcdla nor Cornelia ?

(rap. None Sir.

Oct. That's wondrous ftrange,ft?/»*'.f a place of that general rntelli-
gence, methinks thou might'it have news of f xh Trivial things as wo-
men, amongft the Cardinals Pages;, i'le undertake to learn the Region
deftato, and prefent juncture of all affairs in Italy of a common Cur-
tizam

Mar.^ Sirrah-firrah, let be it your care to examine all the Nunnerys,
for my own part not a petticoat fhall efcape me.

■OB., My taskjhall be for Fittamore. £ Afide,

Mar. 1'le only make a vifit to your lifter Lena Laura Lncmia, and
deliver her a Letter from my Nephew J 'alio , and return to you pre-
iently. C Going om y isftafd by OcTavio*

QB. Stay Sir, defer your vifit to my filler Laura, fhe is not yet to
know of my being in Town, 'tis therefore I have taken a lodging in_
an obfcure Itreet, and am refblv'd never to be my felf again till I've re--
deenrM my Honour. Come Sir, lets walk. — .

Enter to them as they are going out, Marcella and Cornelia, drefi
like Carti^ansy P hilipa and attendance.

Mar. Stay ftay, what women are thefe ?

OB. Whores Sir, and fb 'tis ten to one are all the kind, only thefe
differ from the reft in this, they generoufly own their trade of fin,
which others deal by ftealth in : they are Curtizans. [ Exeunt.

*JHar. The Evenings (oft- and calm,- as happy Lovers thoughts :
And here are Groves where the kind meeting Trees
Will hide us from the Amourous gazing croud.

Or. .What ik>uM we do there, figh till our wandering Breath,' ?
Has rais'd a gentle gale amongft the houghs - 7
To whole dull melanchpllyMuiicICjV/e .

-Laid



1 4 The Feign'd Curti%ans,

Laid on a Bed of Mofs, and new fall'n leaves,
Willreade the difmalltale of Eccho'sLove !
. — -No, 1 can make better life of Famous Ovid I

£ Snatches a little Boekjrom her.
And prethee what a pox have we to do with Trees,
Flowers, Fountains, or naked ftatues ?

Mar. But prethee mad Cornelia lets be grave and wile, atleafl e=
nough to think a little.

Cor. On what? your Engliih Cavalier, Fillamour, of whom you tell
fb many dull Itories of his making Love! Oh how I hate a civil whi-
ning Coxcomb !

Mar. And fo do I, I'le therefore think of him no more.

Cor. Good Lord ! what a damnable wicked thing is a Virgin grown
up to woman.

Mar. Why art thou fuch a fool, to think I love t\\\$Fillamour ?

Cor. It may be not at Rome, but at Vitterbo, where men are fcarce
you did-, and did you follow him to Rome, to tell him you cou'd Love
no more ?

*JMar. A too forward Mzid Cornelia, hurts her own fame, and that
ofallherfex.

Cor. Her Sex, a pretty consideration by my youth, an Oath I mail
not violate this dozen year, myfex fhou'd excufe me, if to preferve
their fame, they expected I fhou'd ruin my own quiet : in chufing an
ill favourd Husband, fuch as Ottavio before a young handlbme Lover,
fuch as you fay FilUmoiir is.

Mar. I wou'd fain perfwade my ielf to be of thy minde, but the

World Cornelia.

Cor. Hang the malicious World— >

*JMar. And there's fuch charms, in wealth and Honour too !

Cor. None half lb powerfull as Love, in my opinion, 'life Si ler thoH
art beautifull, and haft a Fortune too, which before I wou'd lay out
upon fb fhamefull a purchafeas fuch a Bedfellow for life as OElavio •, /
wou'd turn errant keeping Curtizan, and buy my better fortune.

Mar. That word too ftartles me.

Cor. What Curtizan, why 'tis a Noble title and has more Votaries
then Religion, there's no Merchandize like ours, that of Love my filter!
—and can you be frighted with the vizor, which you your felf put on^

Mar. Twas the. only difguife that cou'd fecure us from the fearch
of my Uncle and OBavio, our Brother Julio is by this tooarriv'd, and
I know they'l all be dilligenty— «and fome honour I was content to facri-
cife to my eternal repofel

Cor. Spoke like my filter, a little impertinent Honour, we may
chance to lofe 'tis true, but our right down honefty, I perceive yoiiatte
relblv'd we fhall maintain through all the dangers of Love and Gal-*

lantrjr ;



Or, A Nights Intrigue. 15

lantry y— -though to fay truth I finde enough to do, to deFend my
heart againit fome of thole Members that Nightly ferinade us : and
daily mow themfelves before our window, Gay as young Bridegrooms
and as full of expectation.

Mar. But is't not wondrous, that amongft all thefe crowds we
mould not once fee Fillamour, I thought the charms of a fair young
Curtizan, might have oblig'd him tolbme curiofity at leaft.

Cor. Ay ! and an Englifh Cavalier too, a Nation fo fond of all
new Faces.

Mar. Heaven, if 1 mould never lee him, and 1 frequent all publique
places to meet him •-, or if he be gone from Rome, if he have forgot
me, or fome other Beauty have imploy'd his thoughts ! — ■

Cor. Wheif ail thefe if 7 s and or's cometopafs, we have no more
to do then to advance in this fame glorious Profeffion, of which now
we only feemto be : — in which to give it its due, there are a thoufand
fatisfa&ions to be found, more then in a dull virtuous life ! Oh the
world of dark Lanthorn men we fhouMhave; theSerinades, the Songs,
thefighs, the Vows, the i refents, thequarels, and all for a look or a
fmile, which you have been hitherto ib covetous of, that Petro iwears
our Lovers begins to fu (pectus for fome honeft gilts ; which by fome is
accounted much the lewder fcandal of the two, — therefore 1 think
faith we mult ene be kinde a little, to redeem our reputations.

Mar. However we may rally, certainly there's nothing fo hard- to
woman, as to expofe her felf to villainous Man.

Q>r. Faith Sifter, if 'twere but as eafy to fatisfy the nice fcruples of
Religion, and Honour, 1 ihould finde no great difficulty in the reft, — ■
befides another argument I have, our money's all gone, and without a
Miracle can hold out no longer honeftly.- — -

Mar. Then we muft fell our Jewels !

Cor. When they are gone, what Jewell will you part with? next,

Mar. Then v/e muft. - —

Cor. What, go home to Pitterbo, ask the Old Gentleman pardon,
and be receiv'd to Grace again, you to the embraces of the amiable
O5iavio •, and I to St. Teretids, to whiftle through a Grate like a Bird

in a Cage,- — fori fhall have little heart to ling.: but come let's

leave this fad talk, here's men — -let's walk and gain new Conqueft,
/ love it dearly. — - — • SI Wtjlk, down the Garden,

Enter Gail. Fill, and Jul. See the Women,

Gall. Women! and by their garbo for our purpofe too — » — they're
Curtrzans, lets follow 'em.

FtU. What fhall we get by gazing but difquiet, if they are fair and
honeit, we look and perhaps may figh in vain ' ? if beautiful and loofe,
they are not worth regarding.

Gal/,



\6 The Feign d Curti%ans,

Gall. Dear Notional Knight, leave your latirical Foperies, and be

at leait good hnmour'd, and let's follow 'em.

Jul. /'ie leave you in the purfuit, and take this opportunity, to
write my Uncle word of my arrival : and wait on you here anon.

Fill. Prethee do fo : hah, whofe that with fuch an equipage ?

[Exit. Jul. Fill, and Gall. going after. Marcella and Cor. meet
]ufi entring, Laura with her £quipage y drefl like a man.

Gall. Pox,lettheTradefmen ask, who cringe for fuch gay Cufto-
mers, and follow us the women !

£ Exit Fill, and Gall, down thefcem. Lau. looking after ''em.

Laur. 'Tis he, my Cavalier ! my Conqueror : Antonio, let the
Coaches wait ! — >and Hand at diftance all ! Now Silvio, on thy life for-
get my Sex and quality, forget my ufelefs Name of Laura Lucretia, and
call me Count of — *

Silv. What Madam?

Jjau. Madam ! ah foolifh Boy ? thy feminine courage will betray

us all; but — call me — -Count — ^San's Genre; and tell me Silvio,

Howisitlappear!

How dolt thou like my fhape — my face and drefs ?
My Mien and Equipage, may I not pafs for man ?
Looks it en I rime, and Mafculine,

Silv. Now as 1 live you look all over what you wi(h ; and fuch,as will
beget a reveranceand Envy in the men, and Paffion in the women, but
what's the caufe of all this transformation ?

Lau. Love ! Love ! Dull boy, cou'dit thou not guefs 'twas Love |
that dearEnglefe I mint enjoy my Silvio.

Silv. What he thatadores the fair young Curtizan.

Lau, That very he,my window joyns to hers, and 'twas with charms
Which be'ad prepared for her, he took this heart,
Which met the wellcome Arrows in their flight.
And fav'd her from their dangers,
Oft I've returnd the vows he' as made to her
And lent him pleas'd away ;

When through the Errours of the Night, and diftance
He has miftook me for that happy wanton,
And gave me Language of fo loft a Power,
As ne're was breath'd in vain to liltening Maids.

Silv. But with permiffion,Madam,how does this change of PetticOte
for Britches, and mifting houfes too, advance that Love ?

Lau. This habit, befides many opportunities 'twill give me, of
geting into his acquaintance, lecures me to from being known by any
of my Relations mRome •, then I have chang'd my houfe for one fb
neer to that of SUvianettas, and fo like it too, that even you and I
have oft miftook the entrance •, by which means Love, Fortune, or

Chance •,



Ury A Nights intrigue. %j

chance, may with my induftry contrive fbmc kinde miftake that may
make me happyer then the reft of woman kinde.

Sifo. But what (hall be referv'd then for Count JhUq, whofe laft
letters promife his arrival within a day or two, and whom you're then
to Marry ?

Lau. Reierv'd for him ! a wife ! a wife my Silvio t
That unconcern'd Domeftique NecelTary,
Who rarely brings a heart, or takes it loon away:

Silv. But then your Brother Count OBavio, do you not fear his jea*
loufie ?

Lau. Ottavio ! Oh Nature has let his Soul and mine at odds,
And I can know no fear, but where I Love !
Silv, And then that thing that Ladys call their Honour—
Lau. Hononr, That hated Idoll, even by thofe
That fet it up to worfhip : No,
I have a Soul my Boy, and that's all Love ! ~
And Pie the Tallent which Heaven lent improve ?

[_ Going onty meets Marcella and Corneli a folio wed by Gall, and Fill.
Sil. Here be the Curtizans, my Lord ?

Liter. Hah, Silvianetta and Euphemia ! purfu'd too by my Cavalier,
Pie round the Garden, and mix my felf amongft 'em,

L Exeunt with her train*
Max. Prethee Sifter let's retire into the grove, to avoid the purfuit
of thefe Cavaliers ?

Cor. Not I, by thefe killing Eyes! l'le Hand my ground were there
a thoufand, all Arm'd with Conquering Beauty ?
Mar. Hah — -Now on my Confcience yonders FiUamonr !
Cor. Ha ! Fillamour !

Mar. My courage fails me at the fight of him' — -I mult retire.
Cor. And l'le too my Art of Love !

£ Mar. retires and leans againfi a Tree, Cor. Walkj about reading*
Gall. 'Tis fhe, 'tis SUvianetta ! Prethee advance that thou maiffe
behold her and renounce all hon eft women : fince in that one young
finner there are charms, that wou'd excufeeven to thee all frailty j

Fill. The forms of Angells cou'd not reconcile me
To women of her trade.

Gall. This is too happy an opportunity, to be loft in convincing thy
Angularity,- — [_Gz\\: gees bowing by the fide of Cornelia, Fill.

walks about in the Scene.
— -If creatures fo fair and charming, as your felf had any need of pray-
er, I fhou'd believe by your profound attention you were at your Even-
ings Devotion.

Cor. That you may finde your miftake, in the opinion of my charms.
Pray believe I am fo, and ought not to be interrupted.
GaJl. I hope a Man may have leave to make his Devotions by you,

D at



iB Ihe reign a Lnrti%ans^

at Ieaft, without danger or offence ?

Cor,, I know not that, I have reafbnto fear your devotion may Be:
ominous, like a Blazing Star, it comes but feldom, — but ever threat-
ens mifchief, Pray Heaven I mare not in the calamity : ,

Gall. Whe I confefs Madam,, my lit of zeal does not take me often,
but when it does, 'tis very harmlefle and wondrous hearty.- — .

Cor. You may begin then, I fhall not be fo wicked as to difturb
your Onions.

Gall. Wou'd I cou'd be well aifur'd of that, for mine's devotion of
great neceffity, and the bleffing I pray infinitely for, conferves me - y
therefore in Chriftian Charity keep down your eyes, and do not mine
a young mans good intentions, unlefle they wou'd agree to fend kinde
looks, and fave me the expence of prayer.

Cor. Whichwou'd be better laid out you think upon feme other
bleffingo

Gait. Whe faith 'tis good, to have a little bank upon occafion,
though I hope I lhall have no great need herearter,< — if the charming
Silvianettabt but kinde, 'tis all I ask of Heaven.

Cor. You're very well acquainted with my Name I find J

Gall. Your Name! 'tis all I have to live onl
Like cheerfull Birds, 'tis the firft tune I ling,
To wellcome in the day •
The Grovesrepeat it, and the Fountains Purle it,
And every pretty found that fills my ear,
Turns all to Si-kianettal |] Fill looks a while an Marcella,

Fill: G alitor d, look there— — -look on that lovely woman ; ''usMw-
cflta ! the Beautif ull zJPfarcella ! ■ Q Offers to rm to her 9 Gall . holds him,

GaH: Hold ! Marcella ! where I

Fill. That Lady there ! did'ft ever fee her equall ?

6W/.— Whe faith as you fay Harry, that Lady is beautifull — -and
make us thankfull — kinde, whe 'tis Eufhen-i.i Sir, the very Gurti-
zan, I wou'd have fhow'd you.-

Fill Forbear, I am not fit for mirth..

Gall. Nor I in humour to make you merry,
I. tell ye — -yonder woman — -is a Curtizan.

Fill Do not prophane nor rob Heaven of a Saint !

Gall. Nor you rob mankinde of fuch a bleffing, by giving it to Hea-
ven before its time.- — I tell thee 'tis a whore ! a fine defirable expen-
Jtve whore.

Fill By Heaven it cannot be ! 1'le fpeak to her, and call her my
JMtrceUtt,. and undeceive thy leud opinion. L Offers to go, he holds him.

Gall. Do, falute her in good Company for an honeft woman- — do
■* — -and Ipoil her markets : -^'twill be a pretty civil fpightful Comple-
ment, and no doubt well taken j-^-pome Fie convince ye Sir,

£ Goes and f nils Philipa,
~ — Hearkey



• : Or, A Nights Imrigni* tp

~ Harkey thou kinde help-meet for man — thou gentle childe of
Night — What is the price of a Night or two of pleafure, with yon-
der Lady — Euphemitt, Iraean, that Roman Gurtizan. —

Fill. Oh Heavens/ aCurtizan!

Phil. Sure you're a great ftranger in Rome, that cannot tell her price.

GalL Iamfo — -Name it prethee, here's a young Englilh purcha*
f e r — Come forward man, and cheapen for your felf, — ■ [_?Hlhhinu

Phil. Oh fpare your pains, me wants no cuftomers.— — H flings awaf.

Fill. No No, it cannot, mult not be, Marcdla\
She has too much Divinity about her,
Not to defend her from all imputation,
Scandal woU'd die to hear her name pronounc'fc

Phil. Believe me, Madam, he knows you not, I overheard all he
faid to that Cavalier, andfinde he's much in Love!

Mar. Not know me, and in love ! pumfh him Heaven forfalfhood !
but Tie contribute to deceive him on, and ruin him with perjury.

Fill. I am not yet convinc't, Pie try her farther ! [Goes to her bowing,
~— but, Madam, is that Heavenly beauty purchasable ? lie pay a
heart rich with men wounds, and flames. — :

GalL Not forgetting the Money too good lad, or your wounds and
flames will be of little ufe 1 £ Gall, goes to Cornelia.

Mar. He tells you truth, Sir, we are not like the Ladies of your
Country, who tire out their men with loving upon the fquare, heart
for heart, till it becomes as dull as Matrimony, to women of our
profeflfion there's no Rethorick like ready Money, nor Billet-Doux
like Bill of Exchange.

Fill. Oh ! that Heaven fhou'd make two perfons fo refembling,
And yet fuch different fouls — - — » £ Looks on her.

— 'sdeath how (he darts me through with every look,
But if me fpeak me heals the wound again :

Enters Ocl;avio, with followers.

Oft a. Hah, my Rival Fillamour here ! fall on — 'draw Sir, — aacrfay
I gave you one advantage more and fought thee fairly.

£ Draws onf ill. Fill, fights him out ; the Ladies run off ; Gait.
Falls on the followers^ with whom whilfi he is ingaged , Enters
Julio, draws and afffls him : and Laura at the fame time on the
other fide ; SnterVtXXQ dr -efl like a Civility- Mafier ; Sir Signal
and Tickletext, Sir Signal climbs a Tree $ Tick.rattf his head in
ajmjhf and lies on his hands and knees, Pet. ajfifts Gall, and
fights out the BraviPs : Pet. re-Enters.

Lau. Hah my Cavalier ingag'd amongft the (laves.

Vet. My Ladys Lovers ! and fet upbn by Oftavio ! we mult be
dilligent in our affairs! Sir Signal where are ye ! Signior Tickletext \ I
hope they have not milcarried in the fray ?

C Z SbSifr



2Q The Feign 9 d Cnrti%ans J

SirS#. Oh vot Servitor vosSignoria, mifcarried, no the fool has wit
enough to keep out of harms way. [_ Comes downfromthe Tree-.

Pet. Oh very difcreetly doneSignior.

{_Sees Tick, in a bujli, pulls him out by the heels

Sir Sig. Whe how now Governor what afraifloffwords*
. Tick. No Sir, I am not afraid of Swords, but I. am afraid of danger.

f Enter: Gall, embracing Laura/ after y em, Jul. and FilL v -
s Fill, looks about..

Gall. This bravery Sir was wondrous ! !

Lau. 'Twasonly juftice Sir you being opprefl: with odds.

Fill. She's gone ! (he's gone in Triumph with my Soul..

Jul:. What was the matter Sir, how came th\s mifchief ?

B'/^.GheafilySir ^ I did but look, and iniinitly lov'd !

Jul And therefore were you drawn upon, or was it feme old Pique'

Fill. I know not Sir, Oh tell not me of quarrels.
The woman friend, the woman has undone me !
- Gall. Oh a bleiled hearing! T'me glad of the reformation Sir, you-
were fbfquemifh forlboth, that a whore wou'd not down -.with ye ! no,
'twou'd ipoil your Reputation. — ■

Fill. A whore ! wou'd I cou'd be convinc't flie were fb, 'twou'd call .
my Virtue home and make me man again !

Gall. Thou ly'ft — thou'itas weak a Brother as the beJt on's, and
believe- me Harry, thefe fort of Damfells are like witches,, if they"
once get hold of a man, he's their own till the charm be ended \ you
guefs what that is Sir ?"

Fill. Oh Franks hadft thou then felt how teidi-rly me preft my hand
in hers ; as if (lie wou'd have kept there for ever, it wou'd have made
thee mad, ftarkmad in Love ! — and nothing bat Marcella cou'd have
charm'd me :, C Afide .

Gall. Ay Gad, J'ie warrant thee, — well thou malt this night en-
joy her.

Fill. How!

Gall. How, W he faith £/^ry, enethe old' way, 1 know no other,
Whe thou (halt ly with her man ! come let's to her.

Ftll. Away,let's follow her inftantly. [_ Going cutoff opt by Sir Signal.

Enter Sir Sig. Tick. Petro.

Sir Sig.- Signior, I have brought Mr, Tickle text, -. to beg your par-
don^— -Sir.

Fill. I've other bufmefs Sir- *, C Goes out.

Gall. Come let's follow him,- and you my generous Cavalier, muft
give me leave to beg the Honour of your friendftrip.

Lau. My inclinations Sir, have given you more — -pray let me
waitpn you to your Lodgings, left a farther iniblence ihou'dbe offcr'd
you.-

£aU.



Or, A Nights Intrigue, %\

Gall. Sir you oblige too faft •, [They go- out.

Sir Sig. Ah cheDeavilo zXyles thefe hot-brain'd fellows, fure they're
Drunk.

Pet j Oh fee Signior,Drunk, for a man of Quality — 'tis intolerable.

Sir Sig, Ay: Whe how fo Signior Morigorofo.

Pet. Jmbriaco, had made it a fine fpeech indeed.

Sir Sig. Whe faith,. and fo it had, as thus, ach Deavilo Ailes thefe

hot-brain'd fellows, fiire they are imbriaco^ — now wou'd not I be
Drunk for a thouland. Crowns: imbnacko founds Cinqa-.it par cent bet-
ter,— —Come Noble Signior, let's <*Andiamo a Qifa, which is as much
as to fay, let's amble home. —

Tick^ Introth, wondrous expert — Ctrto Signior he's an apt Schollar ,

Sir Sig. Ah Sir, you lhail fee, when 1 come to my civillities.-- — -

Tet. Where the firft lefHn you fhall learn, is, how to give, and
Bow to receive, with a Bon-Grace !

Tickj That receiving leflbn I will learn my felf -,

Tet. This unfrequented part of the Garden, Signior will fit oar pur-

pofe as well as your Lodgings,- — -Firft then Signiors your addreis,

[Puts himfflf in the middle*
[. Petl'O bows on both fides, they do the lilze.
• — Very well ! that'sat the approach of any perfon of Qua li:y - .after
which you muft take out your Snuff-Box.

Sir Sig. Snuff-Box : whe we take no fnuffSignior.

Bet. Then Sir by all means you muft learn : for befides the mode
and gravity of it, it inviveatesthe Pericranium ! that is fapientiat's the
brain, — that is, infpires wit, thought, invention, underftanding, and
the like — -you conceive me Signiors [ c h owing.

Sir Sag-. Mofl profoundly Signior.-^ — - [ Bowing,

Pet. — Then Signiors, it keeps you in confidance, and countinance!
and whilit you gravely feem to take afiiufh, you gain time to anfwer
to the purpofe, ( and in a politique polture as thus. ) — to any in-
tricate queition,

Tick. Hum — -ccrto I like that well - 7 and 'twere admirable if a man
were allow'dto tase it when he's out in's Sermon.

Pet. Doubtlefs Signior jou might, it helps the memory better then
Roiemary, therefore I have brought each of you a 'Snuff-Box.

Sir Sig. By no means : Excufe me Signior.. [ Refufesto take? em.-

Pet. Ah Bagatells Signior, Bagatells, and now Signiors, 1'le teach
you how to take it, with a handfome Grace, Signior your hand ; —
and yours Signior. [ Laysfnujf on their hands.

— So now draw your hand to^ and frow under your Notes, and
fnuffit hard up : — Excellent well,

[They dawball their Nofes, and make grimaces andfneexje.
SirS*g. Methinks Signior, this fnuffftinks molt damnably : Pray
what fcent do you call this? .

... iflp-



vya The Feign d Curti%ans^

Pet. Cackamarda Orahgate, a rare perfume He affiire ye, Sir.

Sir Sig. Cackamarda Orangate, and 'twere not for the Name of C*ck#-
marda, andfo forth, a man had as good Wave a Sir Reverence at his
Nofe. E Sneezes, often be crys bonprovache.

Pet. Bonprovache- — 'Signior, you do not underitand it yet, bon-
provache.

Sir Sig. Whe Sir 'tis impoffible to endure this fame Cackamarda t
W he Aflaffetteda is Odoriferous to it. C Sneezing.

Pet. 'Tis your right Duke Piquame, believe me :^-but come Sig-
niors wipe your Nofes and proceed to your giving leflbn.

Sir S/>. As how Signior.

Pet. Whe prefentwe with fomething that — Diamond on

your finger ! to Ihew the manner of giving handfbmely : "

(~ Sir Sig. givei it him,
' — Ohfy, Signior— between your Finger and Thumb — thus—
with your other Fingers at a diftance — -with a ipeech, and a bow. —

Sir Sig. 1 'Ittftrijfimo Signior, the Manifold Obligations. — -

<Pet. Now a fine turn of your hand — thus — Oh that fets off the
prefent, and makes it fparkle in the eyes of the receiver. — -

C Sir Sig. turns his hand.

Sir&jj-.— Which you have heap't upon me, —

Pet. There flouriih again. [He flourishes.

Sir Sig. Obliges me to beg, your acceptance of this fmall prefent*
which will receive a double Luftre from your fair hand* Q Gives it him.

Pet. Now kifs your fingers ends, and retire back with a bow :

Tickz — Moft admirably performed.

Sir Sig. Nay Sir Ihavedocity in me, tho' I fay't : come Governor
let's lee how you can out-do me in the Art of presenting.

Ticf^ Well Sir, come, your fnufKtox will ferve inftead of my Ring,
will it not ?

Pet. By no means Sir, there is fuch a certain Relation between a
FingerandaRing, that no prefent becomes either the giving or the
receiving hand half ib well.

Sir Sig, Whe 'twill be reftor'd again, 'tis but to practice by.

Pet. Ay Signior, the next thing you are to learn is to receive.

Tick. Molt worthy Signior, I have fb Exhaulted the Cornucopia of

your favours, [ Flourijhes 3 and tafted lo plenteoufly of the

fullnefle of your Bounteous Liberallity, that to retalliate with this
fmall Jem — is but to offer a fpark, where I have received a beam of
fuperabundant fiin-fhine. — ■ £ Gives it.

Siv Sig. Moft Rhetorically perform'd, as I hope to breath, Tropes
and fugers all over.

Tick. Oh Lord, Sir Signal.

1>et. Excellent — Now let's fee if you can refufe, as civilly as you
gave, which is by an Obltinate denial ; ftand both together, —

---41ittTrious



A Nights Intrigue* p&-

- — Iluftrious Signiors, upon my honour my little merrit has not inti-
fcled me to the Glory of fb fplendid an offering ; Trophes worthy to
be laid only at your Magnanimous feet.

Sir Sig. Ah Signior, No No,

Pet. Signior Tickietext. [He offers, they re fufe going backyard.

Tick.. Nay cert o Signior ! — -

Pet. With what confidence can I receive fo rich a preient : Signior
Tickietext, ah— Signior. —

Sir Sig. I vow Signior 1'me afhamed you fhou'd offer it.

Tick. In verity, and lb ami, fcfiitt going back-, he follows.

Pet. Pardio ! Baccus, moft incomparable.

Tick. But when Signior are we to learn to receive again.

Tet. Oh Sir that's always a ledbn of it felf :-^but now Signiors,
Pie teach you how to Act a ftory.

Sir Sig. How ! Inw Signior to Act a ftory ?

Pet. Ay Sir, No matter for words or fen fe, fb the body perform its
part well.

Sir Sig. How, tell a ftory without words, whe this were an excel-
lent devife for Mr. Tickietext, when he's to hold forth to the Congre-
gation, and has loft his Sermon-Notes- — whe this is wonderful 1. — •

Pet. Oh Sir, I have taught it men born deaf, and blinde, look ye

ftand clofe together, and obferve clofer yet : '[ Getsbetweem "*em.

• — acertainEclejaftio, Plump, and Rich — [Makes a figne of being fat >
Riding along the Rode,. — meets a [ Galloping about the Stage.

Paver ftrapiao, — un Pavero ftrapiao, Paure ftrapiao : ftrapiao

• ftrapiao ftrapiao : — • [ Puts himfelfinto the Tofture of a lean

Elemofuna per un Faure B g ggw > his hands right down by his

ftrapiao, par a Moure de fides,— and picks both their Pockets,

Dievos at laft he begs a Julio — -Neinte ! [ Maizes the fat Bifiop ~J

— then the Paure ftrapiao begs a Mezo Julio. — ■ [ lean ] Neinte [fat 3
. — iunc bacio. — [lean ~~\ — -Niente — [fat ~] — at laft he begs his Blefc
fing — and fee how willingly the Eclefiaftico gave his Benediction ;

[ Opening his Arms hits them both in the face.
— Scufa fcufa mea Patrona's— [ Begs their pardon,

Sir Sig. Yes very willingly, which by the way he had never done
had it been worth a farthing.

Tickc Marry I wou'd he had been a little fparing of that too, at this
time,— -[fneez.es 2 afhameon't, it has fturifthis fame (fackamerda a-
gain moft foully.

Tet. Your pardon Signior, — - but come Sir Signall — let's fee how
you will make this filent relation. — -Come ftand between us two —

Sir Sig. Nay let me alone for a memory — come.

Pet. I think. 1 have reveng'dmyBackfword-beating. L'g oeso ff'

Sir Sig, Un paurco ftrapado— plump and rich — no, no, the Eccle-
fiaftico meets wi paureo ftrapado-— and begs a Julio.



2 4 *■ *>* ** *fg# » CHYti%ant y

Tick. Oh no Sir, the ftrapado begs the Jfcifo.

Sir 5^. Ay, Ay, and the Eclelaftico crys Niente— {.fnaps his nail.
unmeze Julio ! — Niente — un Bacoi, Niente,your blefling then Signior
Ecclefaftico {_ (pre ads out his arms to giv e his blefling — and hits Tick .

T«4 Adds me, you are all a little too liberal of this fame bene-
diction.

Sir Sig. Hah— but where's Signior sJMorigorofo ? what is he gone ?
— but now I think on't 'tis a point ofgood manners to go without ta-
king leave.

Tick. It may be ib, but I wilh I had my Ring again, I do not like
the giving leflbn without the taking one, whe this is picking a mans
pocket certo.

Sir Sig. Not fo Governor, for then I had had a confiderable loiTe :

look ye here,- how \_ feeling in his Pocket [] how — -£ in another ]

how — gone? gone as I live / my money Governor 7 all the Gold
Barber acho receiv'd of my Marchant to day- — all gone.— —

Ticki Hah — and mine — all my flock, the money which I thought
to have made a prefent to the Gentlewoman, Jiarberacho was to bring
me too — [_aftde~] — -undone undone — -Villains, Cutpurfes — Cheats,
oh run after him.

Sir Sig. A Pox of all filent ftories ': Rogue, Thief — undone.



ACT III. SCENE I.

Enter Julio and his Page.

Jul. ttOw / the Lady whom I followed from St. Peters Church
Jt~X a Curtizan?

Pag. A Curtizan my Lord, fair as the Morning, and as young.

Jul. I know flie's fair and young, but isfhe to be had boy ?

Pag. My Lord fhe is — her Footman told me, fhe was a Zittella.

Jul. How a Zittella / — a Virgin, 'tis impoffible.

Pag. I cannot fwearitSir, butfo he told me ? he faid Ihe had a
world of Lo vers : her Name is Silvianetta Sir, and her Lodgings — •

Jul. I know't, are on the Corfo ; a Curtizan / and a Zittella too ?
a pretty contradiction / but Pie bate her the laft, fo I might enjoy her
as the firft, what ere the price be, I'me refblv'd upon the adventure •,
and will this minute prepare my felf. £ Going off^ enters Mur. and Octa.
— hah — does the light deceive me, oris that indeed my Uncle, in

earneft conference with a Cavalier: 'tis he Pie ftep afide till he's

pair. , left he hinders this Nights diverfion : £ Goes afide

Mur. I fay 'twas rafhly done, to fight him unexamin'd.

. OB.



Or 5 A Nights Intrigue. 25

OB. I need not ask, myreaibnhasinform'dme, andl'me convinc'fc
where ere he hasconceald her, that fhe is fled with Fillamottr.

Jul. Who is't they fpeak of ?

Mar. Well well, furemy Anceftors committed fbme horrid crime,
againft Nature, that (he fenc this Pelt of woman -kind into our Family,

two Neecesformy fhare,—— by Heaven a proportion iufficient to

undo fix Generations.

Jul. Hah ! two Neeces, what of them? \_Afide.

Mur. I am like to give a blefled account of 'em to their Brother Ju-
lio my Nephew, at his return, there's a new plague now, — but my
comfort is I (hall be mad and there's an end on't. £ Weep.

Jul. My curiofity mult be fatisfied, — have patience Noble Sir,- — *

Mur. Patience is a flatterer Sir, — -and an Afs Sir, and Pie have none
on't — hah what art thou ?

Jul. Has five or fix years, made ye lofe the remembrance of your
Nephew Julio !

Mur, Julio ! wou'd I had met thee going to thy Grave. £ Weep

Jul. Why fo Sir?

Mur. Your fillers Sir, your filters are both gone. — > £ Weeps,

Jul. How gone Sir?

Mur. Run a way Sir, flown Sir,

Jul. Heavens / which way ?

Mur. Nay, who can tell the ways of fickle women,- — in ihort Sir,
your tifcer Marcella was to have been Married, to this Noble Gentle-
man,- — -Nay was contra&ed to him, fairly contracted in my own
Chappel, but no fooner was his back turn'd, — but in a pernicious
Moon-light Night (he (hews me a fair pair of heels, with the young
Baggage your other filter Cornelia^ who was jult come from the Mo-
nastery where I bred her, to fee her filter married.

Jul. A curie upon the Sex, why mult mans honour
Depend upon their Frailty ?

—Come- — give me but any light which way they went,
And I will trace 'em with that care full Vengeance,

Oft. Spoke like a man, that underltands his Honour,
And I can guefs how we may finde the Fugitives.

Jul. Oh Name it quickly Sir!

Oft. There was a youngCavalier (brne time at Vitterbo-,

Who I confefs had charms, Heaven has denied to me
That trifle Beauty, which was made to pleafe,
Vain fooliih Woman, which the brave and wife,
Want leafure to defign :

Jul. And what of him !

OB. This fine gay thing came in your filters way, and made that
conqueft Nature meant luch fools for : and Sir ihe's fled with him.

Jul Oh (how me the Man, the daring hardy Villain,

E Bring



aA me Fiign d Curu%&nr $

Bring me but in the view of my Revenge^r— «3nd if I fail to take it >.
Brand me with ever! ailing I nfamy .

Oil. That we mull leave to Fortune, and ourlnduftry,
-r— Come Sir, lets walk and think beft what to do.. — ■

[_ Gemgdown the Scene, Enter Fill* and Gall.

F ill, . Is not that Julio— -Boy run and sail him back .

£ Ex. "Boy re-enters with Jul,

Jul. Oh FjllamoMr, Pve heard fuch killing news fmce.lalt 1 left thee.

Fill. Whatprethee?

Jul. 1 had a fifter Friend-i — dear as my life,
And bred with all the Virtues of her Sex;
No Veitals at the Holy fire employ'd themfelves
In innocenter bnfmefle then this Virgin ^
Till Love ! the Fatall Feaver of her heart, . _
Betraidher harmlefle hours :*
And juftupon the point of being Married,
The thief itoie in, and Rob'dus of this treafure :
She's left her Husband, Tarents, and her Honour,
And's fled with the bale ruiner of her Virtue.

Fill. And lives the Villain durfl affront ye thus?

Jul. He does!

Gall. Where, in what diflant World?

Jul. I know not. *

Fill, WhatishccaiPd?

Jul. I know not neither,- — fomeGoddire«ftme to the Ravifher - !•
And if he fcape ...my rage !
May Cowards point me out, for one of their tame herd.

Fill. Inall yoitr. quarellslmufl joyn my fword.

Gall. And if you want, — here's another Sir, — that though it be not
oftetf drawn in anger,nor cares to be,fhall not be idle in good company.

Jul, I thank ye both, and if I have occafion, will borrow their af
fiftance, butl mult leave you for a minute,- 1'le.wait on you anon.—

£ They all three xtalkju down theflreet talking^
Enter Laura, with her Equip age.

Lau. Beyond my wifh, l'me got into his Friendfhip>
But oh how diflant Friendship is from Love !
That*s all bellowed on. the fair Proftitute !
— — Ah Silvio, when he took me in hisArmes, „
Prefling my willing Bofome to hisbreail,
Kifling my cheek, calling me Lovely youth.
And wondering how fuch Beauty, and fuch bravery.,
Met in a Man fo young ! ah then my Boy !
Then in that happy minute ,
How neer was I to telling all my foul,
My bluihes and my %hs, were all prepar'd



Or, A Nights Intrigue. wf

My Eyes caft down my trembling lips juft parting,—'

But ftill as I was ready to begin,

He crys out Silviamifa I

And to prevent mine, tells me all his Love!

- — But fee — -he's here. — - £ Fill. WGall, coming up the fane*

Gall. Come lay by all fullen unrefolves ! for now the hour of the
Berjeare approaches, Night, that was made for Lovers !
- — -Hah ! my dear Sans Cmrl my life ! my foul /my joy i
Thou art of my opinion !

Lou. Pme fure I am what are it be 7

Gall. Whe my Friend here, and I have lent and paid our Fine for a
Jmall Tenement of pleafure, and I'me for taking prefent poflMion •,
—-but hold- — -ifyoufhou'dbeaRivallafterall/

Lau. Not in your Sifoianetta ! My Love has a Nice appetite,
And mult be fed with high uncommon delicates,
I have a Miftrels'Sir, of quality /
^air/ as imagination, paints young Angells/
Wanton and gay as was the firft farina .
That charm'd our belt of Poets,
Young as the Spring, and cheerfull as the Birds
That wellcomcinthe day!
Witty as fancy makes the Revelling Gods,
And equally as bounteous when me blefles !

(jail. Ah for a fine young whore, with all the le charms ! but that
fame quality allays the joy, there's fach a dam'd ado with the Obligati-
on, that half the pleasures loll in Ceremony,
— -Here ! for a thoufand Crowns I raign alone,
Re veil all day in Love without controls

— -But come to our bufineft, I have given order for Mufick, Dark
Lanthorns, and Piftolls. £ This while Fill, ftands findying.

Fill. — -Oeath if it fliou'd not be tJManella now ! [~ Paufing afide.

Gall. Pretheeno more confidering, — -refblve and let's about it.

Fill. I wou'd not tempt my heart again ! for Love
What ere it may be in anothers breaft,
In mine, 'twill turn to a Religious fire !
And fo to burn for her ! a common Miftrefs,
Wou'd be an Infamy below her pra&ice /

GalL Qhif that be all, doubt not Harry but an hours converfation
mthEuphemiaj will convert it to as lewd a flame, as a man wou'd wifh.

Lan. What a coyles here about a Curtizan! what ado to perfwade
a man to a blefling all Rome is languilhing for in vain : — ^Come Sir,
we mult deal with him, as Phylitians do with peevim children, force
him to take what will cure him !

Fill. And like thofe dam'd Phyfitians, r kill me for want of method,
bo, I know my own diftemper belt, and ydtfr applications will make
*»e mad. E 2 Gdl



a 8 The Feign 9 d Curti%ans,

Gall. Pox on% that one cannot love a womanlike a man, but one
mull love like an Afs.

Lah. S'hart, He be bound to ly with all the women in %ome, with
lefs ado then you are brought to one.

Gall. Hear ye that Henry, s'death art not aiham'dtobe inltrudted

by one fo young ! but fee- — -the ftar there appears, — the ftarthat

conduct thee to the (liore of blifs

She comes let's feel thy Q MarcellaW Cornelia above.

Heart ! /he comes /

So breaks the day on the glad Eaftern Hills !

Or the bright God of Rays from Thetis Lap : — ■

A Rapture now dear lad, and then fall too,, for thou art

Old dog at a long Grace.

Fill. Now I 'me meer man again, with all his frailties,- — « £ A(ide.
■ — Bright lovely creature/

GalL Damn it, how like myLadysEldeft Son was that.

till. May 1 hope my facrifice ! may be accepted by you ? — by Hea-
ven it mull be me ! ftill Ihe appears more like. [Afide.

Mar. I've only time to tell you Night approches,
And i h\:n I will expect you, f Enter Crapine, gaz.es on the Ladys.

Crap. 'Tisfhe, Donna Marc e Ha on my life, with the young wild
Cornelia ! — hah— yonders theEnglifh Cavalier too, nay then by this
hand l'le be paid for all my fruitlefs jants : for this good news — flay
let me mark the Houfe. —

Mar. Nowtomydifguifel £Ex. Marcella.

Gall. Andhaveyounokindemerlagetofend to my heart j cannot
this good Example, inftruct you how to make me happy ? ;

Cor. Faith ftrangerl mult confider firft, /he's, skillfull in the Mar^
chandize of hearts, and has dealt in Love with fo good fuccefs hitherto,
me may lofe on venture, and never mifs it in her flock, but this is my
firll, and fhou'd it prove to be a bad bargain, I were undone for ever.

Gall. I dare fecure the goods found, —

(or. And I believe will not Iylong upon my hands..

Gall. Faith, that's according as you'l difpoie on't Madam, — for let
me tell you — gad a good handfome. proper fellow, is as flaple a comr-

modity as any*s in the Nation, but I wou'd be referv'd for your

ownufe! faith take a temple to Night, andasyoulikeit,thewhole
peece, and. that's fair and honeft dealing I think; or the Devils in't.

Cor. Ahftranger,- — you have been fb over- liberal of thole fame
famples of yours, that I doubt they have fpoild the fale of the reft,- — ■
cou'dyou not afford think ye, to throw in a little Love and constancy - r
to inch out that want of honefly of yours.

Gall. Love ! oh in abundance !
By thofedear Eyes, by thatfbft fmiling Mouth y
JBy eyex fecret grace, thou halt about thee,



i



Or, A Nightslnirigite. ^p

/ love thee with a vigorous, eager paffion,

Be kinde dear Sslvianetta— prethee do, .

Say you believe and make me bleft to Night?

. Crap. SUvianettal lb, that's the Name fhe has rifl'd for Cornelia, 1
perceive.

Cor. If I fhou'd be lb kind-hearted! what good ufe wou'd you make
of fo obliging an opportunity ?
Gall. That which the happy Night was firft ordain'd for.
Cor. Well Signior 'tis coming on, and then He try what courage

thedarknefs will infpiremewith: — till then — Harwell.

Gall. Till then athoufand times adieu.- — : Q "Blowing up kjffes to her.
Phil. Ah Madam we're undone,* — yonders Crapine your Uncles
Valiet.— ■

Cor. Now a curie on him ; fhall we not have one Night with our
Cavalier— let's retire, and continue to out-wit him, or never more

pretend to't, Adieu Signior Cavalier remember Night . —

Gall. Or may 1 lofe my fenfe to all Eternity.

£ Kijfes his fingers and bows, floe returns it for a while.
Latt. Gods, that all this that looks at leaft like Love,
Shou'd be difpenc't to one infenfible !
Whilft every fillable of that dear vallue,
Whifper'dto me, Wou'd make my foul all Extafy,
-—Oh fpare that Treafure for a gratefull purchafe j
And buy that common ware with trading Gold,
Love ! is too rich a price : — 1 (hall betray my felf.— £ Afide*.

Gall. Away, that's an heretieial opinion and which this eertain
Reafon muft convince thee of:
That Love is Love, where ever beauty is,
Nor can the Name of whore, make beauty lefs.

Enter Marcella like a Man, with a Cloakabout her.
<lJMay. Signior, is your Name F Mainour ?

- Fill. It is, what wou'd you Sir.

Mar. I have a letter for you — -from Vitterbo^A your Marcella Sir.

\_<.iuesithim\

Fill. Hah Vitterbo\ and Marcella !

It fhocks me like the Gholtof fome forfaken Miftrefs,,
That met me in the waytohappinefs,

With fome new long'd for Beauty ! £ Opens it, reads.

Mar. Now I fhall try thy Virtue, , and my Fate. — - [_zAfide.

Fill. What is't that checks the joy, that fhou'd furprize me at the
receipt of this !
Gall. How now ! what's the cold fit coming on ? £ Pawfes,

Fill I have no power to go — where this— —invites me- — :
By which I prove, 'tis no encreafe of flame that warms my heart,
But a new fire jult kindled from thpfe— eyes-*

r ~ ' "•' ■ '"" ' Whole-



5© The Feign* d. CnnHans,

Whofe rayes I finde more piercing then MafceMi.

Gall. — Ay Gad a thoufand times— prethee what'sthe matter. -

<JMar. Ohthisfalfe — *-fhuIyman — wou'd I had leafure fuc
ToberevengMforthisinconftancy! ^Jftde.

fill. — But ftill flie want's that Virtue I admire !

Gall. Virtue ! s'death thou art always fumbling, upon that dull
ftring that makes no Mulick : — What Letters that ? [ reads. J If the
firft Confeflion I ever made of Love be grateful! to you, come arm'd
to night with a friend or too •, and behinde the Garden of the Foun-
tains, you will receive—— hah Marcellal — Oh damn it, from your
honeft woman! — -Well I fee the devil's never To bury with a man,
as when he has refolv'd upon any goodnefs ! s'death what a rubs here
in a fair call, — how is't man - Alegremente ! bear up, defy him and
all's his works.

Fill. But I have fworn, fwornthat I lov'd MarcelU I and Honour
Friend obliges me to go, take her away and marry her,
* — And I conjure thee toaffift me too.

Gall. What to night, this Night, that I have given to Sihianettal
and you have prom is r d to the fair — Enphemia !

Lau. lfhefhou'dgo,heruinsmy defign, ka/Sjw/e.

- — Nay if your word Sir — be already paft. — -

Fill. 'Tis true, I gave my promife to Enphemia ! but that to women
of her trade, is eafily ablblv'd.

Gall. Men keep not Oaths for the fakes of the wile Magiftrates, to
whom they're made, but their own Honour Harry : And is't not much
agreatererimetoRoba Gallant, hofpitablemanof his Neece, who
has treated you with Confidence, andFriendftiip, then to keep touch
with a well meaning whore, my Confdencious friend !

Lau. Infinite degrees Sir !

Gall. Befides, thou'ft an hour or two good, between this and the
time requir'd to meet <(Jftfarcelia.

Lau. Which an induftrious Lover, wou'd manage to the beft ad-
vantage.

» Gall. That were not given over to Virtue, and conftancy — two
the belt excules I know for idlenehe.

Fill. — Yes — I may fee this woman.

Gall. Whe God a marcy lad !

FUl. - — And break my chains, — if poflible.

(jail. Thou wilt give a good efTay to that l*le warrant thee,
Before Ihe part with thee ! come let's about it.

C They go out on either fide offfthperfwadixg him*

Mar. He's gone ! the Curtizan has got the day. £ Jfidc w Mar.
Vice has the ftart of Virtue, every way,
And for one blefFmg ftoneft wives obtain,
The happyer Miftrefs does a thouland gain \

That



vr, JL mgms mtrigw* - 51

Tie home-r-^and practice, all their Art to prove,
That nothing is fo cheaply gain'd as Love ! £ Exam.

Call. Stay what farce is this,— prethee let's lee a little, {offering to go

£ Enter Sir Signal, Mr. Tickletext, with his Coke ty'd
about him, a great Inkzhorn ty'd at his Girdle , and a great Folio
under his Arm, Petto drefi lik?an ^Antiquary i,

—■How Now Mr. Tickletext r whatdreftas if you were going a Pill-
grimage to Jerusalem. .

Tick. I make no fuck prophane Journeys, Sir. * ".

(jail. But where have you been Mr. Tickletext.

Sir Sig. Whe Sir, this moil Reverend and Renowned Antiquary v
has been fhowingus Monimental Rarities and Antiquities.

Gall: 'tis Petro that — Rogue!

FilU — But what Folio have you gotten there Sir, Knox, or Cart-
Wright?

Pet. Nay if he be got into that heap of Nonfenfe, l'le fteal oft and
undrefs. \_Afide. QS£. Petro. QTick. Opening the Book-

TicJ^Afmall VollumSir, into which I tranfcribe the moil memorable
and remarkable tran factions of the day.
Lou. That doubtlefs mint be worth feeing.

Fill. [Reads'] April the Twentieth, arofe a very great ilorm of
Wind, Thunder, Lightning, and Rain, — which was a ihrew'd fign
of foul weather. .

Fill. The 22th. 9 of our 12 chikens getting loofe, fiew over-bord,
the other three miraculous efcaping, by being eaten by me, that Mor-
ning for breakfaft.

Sh Sig. Harkey Galliard — thou art my Friend, and 'tis not like a
man of Honour, to conceal any thing from on's Friend, — know then I
am the moll fortunate Rafcall, that ever broke bread,— —I am this
Night to vilit firra — the fineft, the moll delicious young Harlot, Muni
—•under the Rofe — in all Rome ! of Barber acho's acquaintance.

Gall- — «Hah — my woman on my life 1 and will fhe be kind !

Sir%. Kind, hang kindneffe man, 1'me refolv'd upon conquell by
parly or by force.

Gall.: Spoke like a Roman of the firft Race, when Noble Rapes not -•
whining CourtChip, did the Lovers buflnefs.

Sir Sig. Sha Rapes man! I mean by force of mony, pure dint of
Gold faith and troth : fori have given 500 Crowns enterance already,,
& Par DiosBaccus 'tis tropoCaro—*tropo Caro Mr. Cjalliard,

Gall. And what's this high priz'dLadys Name Sir?
Sir S*jr. La Sifoiamita-, — and Lodges on the Corfi, not far from St, 1
James's of the incurables— very weft fcituatedi'n cafedifafter^hah.--



gs The £ eign d Cnrti%anSf

gall. Very wejl, — -and did not your wife worfhip know, this Silvi-
anetta was my Miftrefs ?
• Sir Sig. How'! his Miftrefs ! what a damn'd noddy was : to name her!

Gall. Deye hear fool! renounce me this woman inftantly, or Pie
firft difcover it to your Governor, and then cut your throat Sir.

Sir%. Oh Dohx Ment~-~m?s: Ga/liard — Renounce her, — Corpo
demi that I will foul and body if fhe belong to thee man. — ■

Gdl. No more— -look to'c, -— look you forget her Name— or but
to think of her —fare well— [ Nods at him.

Sir Sig. Fare well quoth ye — ? tis well I had the Art of diflembling
after all, here had been a iweet Broyl upon the Coaft elfe.^ —

JUL Very well, I'le trouble my felf to reade no more, fince I know
you'l be fb kinde to the world to make it publique ?

Tick^ At my return Sir, for the'good of the Nation, I will Print it,
and I think it will deferve it.

Lau. This is a precious Rogue, to make a Tutor of.

Till. Yet thefe Mooncalfs, dare pretend to the breeding of our
youth, and' the time will-come, I fear, when none fhall be reputed to
travel like a man of quality, who has not the advantage of being im-
pos'dupon, by one of inefe Pedantique Novices, who inftru&s the
young heir, in what himfeli is molt profoundly ignorant of.

Gall. Come, 'tis dark and time for our defign, — -your fervant Signi-
ors. C Exemt Fill . Gall . and Lau .

Lau. I'le home, and watch the kind deceiving minute, that; may
conduct him by miitaketo me.

Enter Petro, like Barberacho, juftas Tick, and Sir Sig. are going out,.

Sir Sig. Oh Barberacho \ we are undone ! Oh the Diavillo take that
Mafter you lent me.

Pet. Mafter , what Mafter ?

SirS/g-. Whe Siguier Morigorofo !

Pet. Mor — -*ofo — what (hou'd he be?

Sir Sig. A Civillity-Mafter he fhou'dhave been, to have taught us
good manners, — but the Cornuto cheated us molt damnably, and by
a willing miftake taught us nothing in the world but wit.

Pet. Oh abominable knavery ! whe what a kinde of man was he ? —

Sir Sig, - — whe— much liich another as your felf:

■Tick. Higher, Signior, higher !

Sir Sig. Aye fomewhat higher but juft of his pitch.

'Pet. Well Sir, and what of this man ?

Sir Sig. Only pick't our pockets, that's all.

Ticks Yes, and cozen'd us of our Rings.

Sir 5^. Ay, and gave us Cackamarda Orangata for fnuff.

Tkk. And his bleffing to boot when he had done.

Sir Sig, A veng'ance on't, I feel it {till.

Pet.



Or, A Nights Intrigue. 3*3

'Pet. Whe this 'tis to do things of your own heads, for I fetit no

ibch Signior Morofb-— but Fie fee what I can do to retrive 'm 1 ami

now a little in hafte, farwell. — ■ ^Offers to go. Tick.goes out

by him and jogs him.

Ticks. Remember to meet me— farewell Barberacho.

£ Goes out, Sir Sig. pulls him,

Sir Sig. Barberacho — is the Lady ready ?

Tick* Is your money ready?

Sir Sig, Whe now, tho I am threatned, and kiil'd, and beaten, and
kickt about, this intrigue I muft advance / [afide ] — -but dolt think
there's no danger ?

Pet. What in a delicate young amorous Lady, Signior?

Sir Sig. No, No, mum, I don't much fear the Lady, but this fame
mad fellow Cjalliard, 1 hear, has a kinde of a hankering after her— -
Now dare not / tell him what a difcovery / have made. Q Afide.

Vet. Let me alone to fecure you, meet me in the Piatza Defpagnia^
as loon as you can get your felf in order ; where the two fools fhall
meet, and prevent eithers coming. £ Afide,

Sir Sig. Enough, — -here's a Bill for 500 Crowns more upon my
Merchant, you know him by a good token, I loltthe lalt lum you re-
ceiv'd for me, a pox of that handfell, away here's company.

E<&. Pet. Snter O&avio.

Now will I difguiie my felf, according to the mode of the Roman Ina-
morato's ; and deliver my felf upon the place appointed. £ ExSir Sig.

Oft. On the £>/* didft thou lee 'em ?

Crap. On the Corfo my Lord,in difcourfe with three Cavaliers,one of
which has given me many a Piftol, to let him into the Garden a Nights
ztVuterbo: to talk with DonaMarcetta, from her Chamber window,
I think I (houkl remember him.

OH. Oh thatthought fires me, with anger fit for rcfy Revenge, [Afide.
And they're to Serinade 'em thou fay'ih

Crap. I did my Lord! and if you can have patience till they come,
you will fmdeyour Rival in this very place, if he keep his word.

OEl. I do believe thee, and have prepared my Bravos to attack him :
if I can Ad but my Revenge to Night, how (hall I worfhip Fortune !
keep out of flght, and when I give the word be ready all. I hear feme
coming let's walk offa little. — >

[Enter Marcella in mans clothes, and Philipa as a woman, with
aLanthornOO:. and Crap, go off the other way.

Mar. Thou canft .never convince me, but if (rapine faw us, and
gaz'd fo long upon us, he mult know us too, and then what hin-
ders but by a dilligent watch about the Houfe, they will furprize us,
ere we have fecured our lei ves from 'em.

Phil. And how will this, expoilng your, felf to dangerprevent 'em.

F Afar,



3«i The Feign'd Cnni%ans^

*JMar. Mydefignenowis, to prevent FUlammrs coming into dan-
ger, by hindring his approach to this houfe : I wou'd preierre the
kindeingrate with any hazard of my own : and 'tis better to dy©
then fall into the hands of Ollavio. I'me defperate with that thought,

and fear no danger ! however be you ready at the door, and when

Iringadmitme.: — ha — who comes here. — .

£ Enter Tiekletext with a Periwig and Cravat of Sir Signals : A
Sword by bis fide, and a dim \Lanthorn, Jhe of em hers, 'J-ookjon
him and zoes out.

T^.Aman! now am I though an old flnner, as timerous as a
young thief, 'tis a great inconvenience in thefe Popilh Countrys, that
a man cannot have liberty to fteal to a wench without danger y not
that I need fear who fees me except C/alliard^ who fufpecting my bufi-
nefs, will go neer to think I am wickedly inclin'd,. Sir Signal! have left
hard at his ftudy, and Sir Henry is no Nocturnal Inamorato, unlefs
likemehedifiembleit,: — well Certo 'tis a wonderfull pleafure to de-
ceive the World : And as a learned man well obferv'd, that the fin , of
wenching lay in the habit only : I having laid that aiide, Timothy Tiekletext
principal holder forth of the Covent Garden Conventicle, Chaplain of
Buffoon-Hall m the County o£Kent r is free to recreate himfelf.

£ Enter Gall, with a dark^Lanthorn.

GaS: Where the devil is this Fillamour ? AndtheMufick : which
way cou'd he go to lofe me thus !. [~ Look* towards the door.

—•he is not yet come.- —

Tick. Not yet come, — that mult be Ttarberacho ! where are ye

llonelt 'Barber acho where are ye? groping towards Gall. ,

Gall. , Hah ! . Barberacb; ? that name I am fare is us'd by none but
Sir Signal and his Coxcomb Tutor, it mult be one of thofe- — where
are ye Signior, where are ye ? J2 Goes towards him, and opens the Lan-

thorn — ~and fimts itftraight.
- — -Oh 'tis the Knight,- — -are you there Signior?

Tick. Oh art thou come, honeft Rafcal- — -conduct me quickly, con-
duct me to the Beautifull and fair Sihiamtta ! £ Gives him his hand.

Gall.. Yes, when your dogfhips damn'd, Sdvianetta .! S'death is fhe
a whore for fools ! Q Draws.

Tick. Hah Mr. Galliard,. as the devil wou'd have it : — »I'me undone
If he fees me ! £ He retires haftily, Gall, gropes for him .

Gall. Where are you Fop : Buffoon ! Knight !

{^Tiekletext retiring haftily runs again ft Octavio, who is juft en-
tering, almo ft beats him. down, OCt.ftrikeshimagoodblow, beats
himbackand draws : Tick, gets clofe up in a corner of the ft age ^
OCt. gropes for him as Gall, does, andboth meet and fight with
each other.

=—What dare you draw,-- -you have the impudence to be valliant

then



Or, A Night f Intrigue. $*

tbenin the dark, £daeyfafs 2 I w:ou'd not kill the Rogue, — death you
can fight then, when there's a woman in the Cafe /

OB. I hope 'tis Fillamow ! [afide 5) you'le finde I can, and pofll'bly
may fpoil your making love to Night !

gall. Egad fweet heart and that maybe, one civ-M thrufl will do't ;
— And 'twere a damn'd rude thing todifappoint fo fine a woman, — -
therefore I'le withdraw whilft l'me well. £ He flips out,

\_ Enter Sir Signal, with a MafqueradingCoat over his clothes, with-
out aWigg or Cravat, with a darl^Lanthorn.

Sir % . Well I have molt neatly efcapt my Tutor 5 and in this di£
guil-dsry the de/iito claim his own, — >ah-Caficto de Deavifa ! — >
What's that - ? C ^Advancing foftly 9 and groping with his hands, meets
the point of Qdu. fword, as he is groping /or Gall.

OB. Tray tor dareft thou not ftand my fword ! \ .

Sir5/>. Hah! fwords! noSignior— fatfa wwSignior, — !

j~ Hops to the door : zsfnd feeling for his way with his out-flrecht
Arms, runs his Lanthorn in Julio's face who isjufl entering \
finds he's opposed with a good pujlj backward, and flips afide into k
corner over againfl Tickletext : Julio meets QCtw'io and fights
him A Od:. falls, Julio opens his Lanthorn and fees his mifiake.

Jul. Is it you Sir?

OB. Julio \ from what miftake grew all this violence ?
Jul. That I fhou'dask of you, who meet you arm'd againffc me.
OB. I find the Night has equally deceiv'd us •, and you ace fitly
come ! to (hare with me the hopes of dear Revenge 1

\_ Gropes for his Lanthorn which is dropu

Jul. l'de rather have purfu'd my kinder pafiion !
Love ! and defire ! that brought me forth to Night !

OB. I've learnt where my falfe Rival is to be this Evening,
And if you'l joyn your fword, you'l finde it well imploy'd.

Jul. Lead on, /'me as impatient of Revenge as you. — -

OB.. Come this way then, you'l find more aids to ferve_us. £ Go out.

Tick, — 'Sol thanks be prais'd all's ftill again, this fright were e-
nough to mortify any Lover of lefs magnanimity then my felf,- — -well
of all fins, this itch of whoring is the moil hardy, the moft impu-
dent in repulies} the molt vigilant in watching, moft patient in wait-
ing, molt frequent in dangers : in all difafters but difappointment,
a Philofopher ! yet if 3arberacho come not quickly, my Philofophy
will be put to't ce rto. £ This while Sir Signal is venturing from his poft 9
lifiening andflowly advancing towards the middle of the fi age.

Sir Sig. The coaft: is once more clear, and / may venture my carcafs
forth again, — thoughfuchafalutationas the laft, wou'd make mc
very unfit for the matter in hand, — -the battoonl cou'd bear with the

F 2 Fortitude



%$ TheFeigri > dCHrti%atrf J

Fortitude and courage of Hero : But thefe dangerous (harps /nevcc
lov'd-, what differentrancounters have / met withall to Night, Corpo ds>
me ; a man may more fafely pafs the gulf of lyons, then convoy himfelf
into a Bawdy houfe in Rome, but / hope all's palt, and / will fay with
Alexander : : VivM Efperance en defpetto del Fatto. Q advances a little.

Tick Sure I heard a Noife, — No 'twas only my furmife /

XjTheyboth advance fo ft ly, meeting jufl in the middle of the Stage^,
and coming clofe up to each other ! both cautioujly flart back' And
ftand atipto in the po flare of fear,, then gently feeling for each
other, {after liflening and hearing no noife ) draw back their
hands at touching each others f\ and Jhrinking up their Jhonlders^
makegrimafes of more fear i

' Tick. Que Squefi'o.

Sir5*j\ Hah a mans voice ! — Pie try iFI can fright him hence! \_Afide,
Vna Malladette Spirito Incarnate ! \_lna horrible tone.

Ticks Hah, Spirit to Incarnate ! that devils voice I fhou'd know / £ afide .

SirS*>. SeeSignior! Vna.fpirito\ which is to 13$%* un fpiritalo, lmor*
tallo Incorporalla, .Inanimate, Imaterialle, T.hilofophicale, Invifible — %)n in-
telligible Diavillo ! ' £ In the fame tone.

Tick. Ay ay, 'tis my hopefull pupill ! upon the lame defign with
me, mylifeon'c, — Cunning young whoremaiter / — l'Je cool your

courage good Signior Diavillo I if you bethe Diavillo I have nnacer-

taina Imaterialle Invifible Conjuratione, that will fo neatly lay your Inani-
mate unintelligible Diavillojhip.- [~ Pulls oat his wooden fword,

SirS;V. How ! hemuftneedsbe valliant indeed that dares fight with*
the devil. ^Endeavours toget away, Tick, beats him about the fla<re.

Ah Signior Signior Mia ! ah Cafpetode Baccus, hecormtto,! am

adamn'd filly devil that have no dexterity in vanishing.

£ Gropes and finds the door going out r meets juft entring Fillamour

Galliard with all the t^idufick- he retires andftands clofe.

— Hah, — what have we here new mifchief. —

[_ Tick, and heflands againfleach other ', on either fide of the ft age.
Fill. Prethee how came we to lofe ye ?

Gall. I thought I had follow'dye, — but 'tis well we are met agahv
come tune your pipes, — • Q They play a little. Enter Marcclla as before.
*JWar. This mult be he. [Goesupto^enu

Gall: COmecome, your Song boy your Song.

iWhilft ^tisfmging Enter O&a vio, Julio r Crapine, and Bravo's !



The:



A Night f Intrigue. g 7

-''-■••' 1 ■■■"--.

The SONG.

• • ■ ■ ■

Crude AmorSy Crudo Amore, 1\j\% r
II mio Core non fa per te 5

Sujfrir non vo tormenti

Senza mai fperar mar ce * - ,- - A ,

Belta che (ia Tiranna,

Bolt a che fa Tiranna

Dell meo ojfettb recetto non e

II tuo rigor fingunna

Se le pene

he catene
lent a auowere at mio Vie

ee Crude I Amore 7, •
II mio Core nonfaperte.S *"' ,



• -v - ;



Lufinghiero , Lufinghiero , 7 , r
Pui non Credo altatuafeS
Jb'incendio del tuo face
Net mio Core put vino none
Belta che U die Lttoce-
Belta che li die Luoce
Ma il rig or V Ardor e s bands
Ionon fato tuo gioce

Ch 'il Vdeno

JDelmiofeno
Vergorofo faggito fe ne..
See fee Crude I Amore 1 ^.
//.' mio Core non fa per te. \

®$i. 'Tis they we look for, draw and be ready .< —

T.ick± Hah draw — then there's no fafty here certo. EAfide.

£ O&avio Julio andtheir party draw, and fight with Fill, and Gall.
MsiQ^Vizingages on their fide, all fight, the Mufickconfufedly a-
mongfi.^em^ Gall, lofes his fword , and in the hurry gets a
Bafe Viol^andhappens toftrike Tickletext, who is getting away — .
his head breaks its way quite through^ and' it hangs about his neck^_
they fight out.
Enter Petro with a Lanthorn. Sir Signal fiands'clo'fefiilL,
Tick- Oh undone; undone, where am I, where am I.
Pet. Hah — that's the voice of my- Amorous Ananias,-— or I am'
miftaken- — what the devil's the matter. [ Opens his Lanthorn. .

—Where are ye Sir,- — hah cutsib— what newfouud jpiUory havec
we here?:



3 3 - The Feign'd CurtJ%anf y

Tick. Oh honeft Barberacho undo me, undo me quickly.

Vet. Sol defign Sir, as faft as 1 can-— tor lofe my aim there Sir

there : all's well — I have fee you free, come follow me the back way,
into the houfe. ,£ Ex. Petro and Tickletext.

Enter Fillamour WMarcella, with their [words drawn Gall, after 'em.

Gall A plague upon 'em, what a quarters here for a wench, as if
there were no more i'th Nation, — wou'd I'de my fword again.

L Gropes for tt.
Mar. Which way mall I direft him to be fafer ^ — -how is it Sir, I
hopeyouarenot hurt.
Fill. Not that I feel, what art thou asks't Co kindly.
Mar. A fervant to the Roman Curtizan, who lent me forth to
wait your coming Sir, but finding you in danger jjrax'd it with you, — -
come let me lead you into fafety Sir. —

Fill. Thou'il been too kinde to give me caufe to doubt thee.
Mar. Follow me Sir, this key will give us entrance through the
• Garden. Q Sxemt.

Enter O&avio with his [word in his hand.

OB. ! Oh what damn'd luck had I fo poorly to be vanquifh't

when all is hufht, I know he will return,— therefore Tie fix me here,
till 1 become a furious Itatue— -but I'lereach his heart.

Sir Sig. Oh lamentivolo fato — -What bloody Villains theie Popifh
/tall ians are.

Enter Julio.
OB. Hah — /hear one coming this way — ■
hah — the door opens too, — and he makes towards it— -pray Hea-
ven he be the right : for this /'me fure'sthe Houfe?
Now luck an't be thy will, f Fallows Julio towards the door foftly^

Jul. The Rogues are fled but howfecure / know not, —
And /'le purfue my firft defign of Love,
And if this Silmanctta will be kind.— *

£ Enter Laura from the houfe in a Nightgown.
Lau. Whi'ft— ^who is't Names Silvianettal

Jul. A Lover and her .flave..^r- , \_She- take shim by the hand.

i_Lau. Oh is it you,- — are you efcapt, unhurt?
Come to my bofome--and be fafe for evex^.

Jul. 'Tis Love that calls, and now Revenge mufb ftay,— -this hour
is thine fond Boy, ■ the next that is my own /'legive to anger.— ~

OB. Oh ye pernicious pair,^ — &\ quickly change the Scene of
Love into a ruffer and more unejspe&ed entertainment. -



Or^ A Nights Intrigue* 3 p

£ She lea&fylio «f, OdL.fd&WJcltf^ttityfrnt thtdocr upon'* em.

Sir Sig. thrufis out his head to hearken % ke'afo mbody arid advances.

Sir Sig. Sure the devil raigns to N^gftt, ^duM'twere fhelter'd and
let him raign fire and Brimftdne, for p'afs the ftreets / dare not — this
fhou'd be the honfe^-dr here abouts Pme fure *tis,,— hah — what's
this — a ftring-^-dfa Bell I hope — -Pie try to. enter \ and if J am-
miilaken'tis.but,cryiHgconUcentia! X_Rings8mer Philipa.

Ml Whofe there?

Sir Sig. 'Tis I- 'tis L, let me in quickly. — t

Phil. Who— the Engiifh Cavalier.

Sir S&. The fame 1 am right — I lee I was expected."

Phil. Pme glad you re cotic,- give me 5 our hand. —

Sir Sig. I am fortunate at laft,- — -and "therefore will fay with the
Famous Poet.

— — No happinefs 'ike that achiv'd with danger,
Which once o'recome— Pie ly 2tRack and Manger. £ Exeunt.

:



ACT iV. SCENEI.

Enter Fillamour and Galliard, as in Silvianetta's apartment,

■ ■
&ill.-A t_j Ow lplendidly thefe Common women live,
J^j[How rich is all we meet with in this Palace,'
And rather feems th' Apartment of fome Prince,
Then a Receptickle for lull and fhame.

(jail. You fee Harry , ail the keeping fools are not in our dominions ,
but this grave this wife people, are Miftrefs riden too.

Fill. 1 fear we have miitdok the houfe, and the youth that brought
us in may have deceived us, on lome other defign, however whilit <.'ve
this — cannot fear./— £ Draws, .

Gall. A good caution, and /le Hand upon my guard with this, but
fee. — here's one will put us out of doubt. {_ Pulls a piftol out of his pocket.
Fill. Hah ! the fair Inchantrefs ! £ Enter Mar. richly and loojlydrefi.
Mar. What on your guard my lovely Cavalier ! lyes there a danger
In this Face and Eyes, that needs that rough refiftancei
— -Hide hide that mark of anger from my fight,
And if thou woud'ftbe abfolute conqueror here,
Put on fcfr. looks with Eyes all languishing^
Words tender, gentle fighs, and kind defires, .

Gall. -Death * with whan undonce^n'he hears ail tiMs Part-thoU ppA-
felt— poxwhydd^ndtaafvyeriiier?' • !

, ■" .'■ '■ '•• ' ■■' ; : " '*

■



40 The Feign\d Cnrti^ans^

Mar. I hope he will not yicld,^— \- {.Apde. \

— Heftandsunmov'd,— <&

Surely I was miftaken in this face,
And i believe in charms that have no power.

Gall. S'death thoudeferveftnotfucha Noble creature,— .
Pie have 'em both my felf. — [ lAfide.

Fill. — Yes / thou halt wonderous power,
And I have felt it long. [ Fawfogly.

Mar. How/

gall. — I've often feen that face — but 'twas in dreams :
And fleeping lov'd Extreamly /
And waking— fight to find it but a dream,
The lovely Phantom vanifh't with my {lumbers,
But left a ftrong Idea on my heart ;
Of what I finde in perfect Beauty here,
— But with this dirference, fhe was Virtuous too t

Mar. What filly Ihe was that !

Fill. She whomldream't 1 Lov'd,

Mar. You only dream't that ihe was Virtuous too I
Virtue it felf 's a dream of fo flight force,
The very fluttering of Loves wings deftroys it,
Ambition, or the meaner hope of intereft, wakes it to nothing,
In men a feeble Beauty, makes the dull {lumber Off,

Gall. Egad me argues like an Angell Harry !

Fill. What haft thou'ft made, -to damn thy felf fo young !

Halt thou been long thus wicked ? haft thou fin'd paft Repentance,
Heaven may do much, to fave fo fair a Criminal,
Turn yet and be forgiven !

Gall. What a pox doft thou mean by all this canting ?

Mar. Avery pretty Sermon, and from a prieft fo gay,
It cannot chufe but edify. .

Do Holy men ofyour Religion Signior, wear all this Habit,
Are they thus young, and lovely? fure if they are,
Your Congregation's all compos'd of Ladys,
The Layety muft come abroad forMiftrelfes.

Fill. Oh that this charming woman were but honeft !

Gall. T were better thou wer'tdamn'd •, honeft/
Pox thou doft come out with things fo malapropo—

Mar. Come leave this Mask of roolifh modefty,
And let us haft where Love and Mufick call's \
Mufick / that heightens Love / and makes the foul,

Ready for foft impreffions /
Gall. So, fhe will do his bufinefs with a Vengeance I. ,
Fill. Plague of this tempting woman fhe will ruin me/

I finde weak Virtue melt from round my heart,

To



Or, A Nights Intrigue. ^.i

To give her Tyrant Image a PofTeffion :
So the warm Sun, thaws Rivers Icy tops,

Till in the ftream he fees his own bright face 7

Gall. Now becomes on apace,' — «how is'tmy friend,

Thou ftand it as thou'dft forgot thy bufinefshere /

— The woman Harry ! the fair Curtizan /

Canft thou withftand her charms ? I've buflnefs of my own,

Prethee fall too— -and talk of Love to her.
Fill. Oh I cou'-d talk Eternity away,

In nothing elfe but Love / — cou'dft thou be honeft?

Mar. Honeft / was it for that you fent two thoufand Crowns.
Or did believe that trifling; fum fufficient,
To buy me to the fla very ofhonefty,

(jail. Hold there my brave Virago.

Fill. No, Iwoullfacrifice a Nobler Fortune,
To buy thy Virtue home !

Mar. What fhou'd it idling there !

Fill. Whe make thee conltant to fbme happy man,

That wou'd adore thee for't.

*JWar. Unconfcionable/ conftant at my years ?

Oh t* were to cheat a thoufand \

Who between this and my dull Age of Conftancy,
Expe&thediftributionofmy Beauty,

Gall. 'Tis a brave wench, — * ^Afide^

Fill. Yet charming as thou art, the time will come
When all that Beauty like declining flowers,
Will wither on the ftalk, — but with this difference,
The next kinde Spring, brings youth to flowers again,
But faded Beauty never more can bloom,
— If intrefl make thee wicked, I can fupply thy prides —

Mar. Curfe on your neceflary tram 1 — which I defpife, but as 'tis
ufefull to advance our Love !

Fill. Is Love thy bufinefs, who is there born fo high,
But Love and Beauty equals ,
And thou maift chufe from all the wilhing world ?
This wealth together wou'd inrichone man,
Which dealt to all wou'd fcarce be Charity,

Mar. Together ! 'tis a Mas wou'd Ranfbme King's S
Was all this Beauty given, for one poor petty Conqueft-,
■' — I might have made a hundred hearts my flaves,
In this loft time of bringing one to Reafbn. — ■
Farewell thou dull Phiiofopher in Love ;
When Age has made me wife, — Lie fend for you again.

t Offers to go Gait, fo Ids her.
G Galh



jg : The Feign* d Curt hearts £

Gall. By this good light a Noble glorious Whore !

Fill. Oh ftay,— <I muft not let fuch Beauty fall,
- — A whore- — confider yet, the charms of Reputations
Theeafe, the quiet and content of innocence,
The awfull Reverence, all good men will pay thee,
Who as thou art will gaze without reipecV
——And cry-^—what pitty 'tis fhe is — a whore — -

Mar. O you may give it what courfe Name you pleafe ;
But all this youth and Beauty ne're was given,
Like. Gold to Mi fers, to be kept from ufe. . [Going oat..

Fill. Loft loft, — paft all Redemption.

GW/. : Nay, Gad thou (halt not lofe her (by— I'le fetch her back,..
And thou malt ask her pardon. [Rims out after her.

Fill. By Heaven 'twas all a dream/ an Aiery dream/

The Vilionary pleafure difappears, and l'me my lelf again,

— 'Je fly, before t'edrowfy fit ore' take. me.-..

Q Going out, Ecter Gall, and then Marcella.

Gall. Turnback — (he yields, fhe yields to pardon thee, gon — -

Nay hang me if ye part. £ Runs after him, ftill his Pifiol in his handy.

tjl'iar, Gqh-— I have no leafure now for more diiTembling.

j~ Takes the Candle and goes in,

EnterVetro, leading in Air. Tickletext, m by dark±

Pet. Remain here Siguier whilfl I ftep and fetch a light.

Tick- Do lb, dofo honeifc Barhrachol— — well my efcape even now
0>m Sir Signal was Miraculous/ thanks' to my prudence and prowefs,
^ad he difcover'd me, my dominion had ended ^ and my Authority
^een of non effect certo, r Philipa ,at the door puts in Sir Signal .

Phil. Now Signior yo're out of danger, lie fetch a Candle, and let
my Lady, know of your being here / C Ex. \ hiL

j~ Sir Sig. advances a little*
Enter Petro with a light, goes between 'em and fl arts.

Tick. Sir Signal !-—

Sir Sig. My Governor !

Pet. f he two fools met .! a pox of all ill luck ': now fhallt lofe my
credit with both my wife Patrons, my Knight I cou'd have put off, with
a fmall Harlot of my own, butmy Levite having feenmy Lady Cornelia
that is La t Silvianetta, — None but that Sufanna wou'd fatisfy his Elder-
fhip : but now they have both fav'd me the labour of a farther inventi-
on to difpatch 'em.

Sir%. I perceive my Governor's as much confounded as my Telf^
- — -I'le take advantage by the forelock , be very impudent and put it
apon him faith* — -Ah Governor, will you neYer leave your whoring I
never be ftayd, fober aad difcreet as I am,



Or, *A Nights Intrigue. 45

Tick Sofo, undone undone, juft my Documents to him. —

£ Walks about ', Sir Sig. follows.

Sir Sig. And muft I neglect my pretious ftudys, to follow" you, in
pure zeal and tender care of your perfon / will you never confider
where you are? in a lewd Papifh Country .'amongit the Romifh Hea-
thens, — and. for you a Governor, a Tutor, a director of unbridled
youth, a Gown-man, a Polititian, for you 1 fay to be taken at this un-
righteous time of the Night,in a flaunting Cavaliero drefs,an unlawful
weapon by your fide, going the high way to Satan to a Curtizan / and
to a Romifh Curtizan ! Oh abomination, Oh fcandalum infiniti.

Tick Paid in my own Coyn /

Pet. So, /'le leave the dsvil to rebuke fin, and to my young Lady,
for a little of her affiftance, in the management of this affair.

[Exit. Pet. Tick.

Ticks — J do confefs, — I grant ye I am in the houfe of a Curti-
zan, and that I came to vifit a Curtizan, and do intend to vifit each
Night a feveral Curtizan : — till I have finifht my work. — >

Sir Sig. Every Night one! Oh glutton!

Tick — My great work of Converfion, — upon the whole Nation,
Generation, and Vocation, of this wicked provoking'fort of woman-
kinde , calPd Curtizans : — I will turn 'em— yes I will turn 'em, — for
'tis a rfiame that Man — fhou'd bow down to thofe that worhhip Idols !

and now I think Sir, 1 have fufficiently explain'd the bufinefs in

hand, — as honeft Barberacho is mywitnefs !— And for you — to —
icandalize — -me — withfo naughty an interpretation — afflidteth me
wonderfully. '• , |~ PhIIs out bis hankerchief and weeps.

Sir Sig. — Alas poor Mr. Tichletext, now as I hope to be fav'd it
grievesmy heart to fee him weep, — faith and troth now, I thought
thou had'ftfbme Carnal affignation, — -but nere ftir I beg thy pardon
and think thee as innocent as my felf, that I do — but fee the Ladys,
here s'life dry your Eyes man ! [ Enter Cornelia Phil, and Pet.

Cor. Icou'dbeattheefor being thus miftaken, — and am refolv'd
to flatter him into fome mifchief, to be Reveng'd on 'em for this dif-
appointment, go you and watch for my Cavalier the while,

Tick Is (he come Nay then turn me loofe to her. — -

Cor. My Cavalier ! £ Jddrefmg to Sir Sig. Tick, pulls him by and /peaks.

Tkk — Lady. — •

Sir Sig. You Sir, whe who the devil made you a Cavalier,' — moft
Totentifimo Signiora, I am the man of Title, by Name Sir Signal Buffoon,
fole Son and heir to Eight Thoufand pound a year.' — -

Tick Oh Sir, are you the man fhe looks for ?

Sir Sig. I Sir, No Sir, I'de have ye to know Sir, Ifcorn any woman
be fhe never fofair, unlefs her defignebe honeft and Honourable !

Cor. The man of all the World I've chofen out, from all the wits
and Beauties I have feen j— to have moft finely beaten !

G 2 Six Sig.



44 The Feign' d Curti&dnf,

Sit Sig. How! in Love with me already, — fhe's damnable hand-
fome too, now wou'd my Tutor were hang'd a little for an hour or two,
out of the way. £ aAfide.

Cor. Why fly you not into my Arms, [_fhe afproching, he filming.

Thefe Arms that were defign'd for loft embraces ?"

Sir Sig. Ay, and if my Tutor were not here, the devil take him
that wou'd hinder 'em, — and I think that's civil egad ! .

Tick* Whe how now Barber acho y what am I cuzend then, and is Sir
Signal the Man in favour L - Q Afide to Petro.

Pet. Lord Signior, that fb wife a man as you cannot perceive her

meaning ^ fort he devil take me if I can, — £ Afide. ] Whe this

is done to take offall fufpition from you — and lay it on him; — don's
you conceive it Signior !

Tick, Yes hooeft Rogue, — Oh the witty wagtail, — •/ have a part
to play too, that fhall confirm it — -young Gentlewoman. —

Cor. Ah bell ingrate, is'tthus you recompence my fuffering Love J
to fly this beauty fb ador'd by all, that flight the ready conqueft of the
world to truft a heart with you, ah — Traditor Gruella.

Sir Sig. Poor heart, it goes to the very foul of me to be fb eoy and*
fcornfull to her that it does, but a pox on't her over-fondnefs will di£.
cover alL

Ticks Fly, Ay, young man ! whifft yet thou haft a fpark of virtue
mining in thee, fly the temptations of this young hypocrite ^ the love-
that fhe pretends with fo much zeal and ardour , is indecent, unwar-
rantable, and unlawful ! firffc indecent as fhe is woman — for thou art

woman and beautiful woman yes, very beautifull woman ! on

whom nature hath fhew'd her heighth of excellence intheout-work*,
but left the in unfinifht, imperfect and impure.

Or. Heavens, what have we here /

Sit Sig. A pox of my Sir Dominie, Now. is he befide his Text, and
will Ipoil all.

Tick* Secondly,llnwarrantable • by what authority doft thou feduce
with the allurements of thine eyes,and the conjurements of thy tongue,,
the waftings of thy hands, and the tinklings of thy feet, the. young
men- in- the Villages I,

Cor. Sirrah! how got this madman in? feizehim, and take him
hencer

Six Sig. Corp de mi my Governour tickles her notably i'faith- — but
lhad he let the care of my foul alone to night, and have let me taken
care of my body, 'twould have been more material at this time.

Tick: Thirdly, Unlawful' — -.

Or. Quite . diffracted ! in pity take him hence, and leade him into
darknefle, 'twill fute his madnefs.beft.



Or, A Nights Intrigue. 45

Tick; How,diftra<fted! take him hence /

Pet. This was lucky — -I knew fhe wou'd come again — -take him
hence — yes, into her bed-chamber — pretty device to get you to
herfelfSignior.

Tick- Why but is it — nay, then I wili facillitate my departure — ■
therefore I fay — oh molt beautifull and tempting woman —

j~ "Beginning to f reach again a

Cor. Away with him, give him clean ftraw and darkneffe,
And chain him fall for fear of further mifchief.
Pet. She means for fear of Iofing ye.
Tick. Ah baggage ! as faft as fhe will in thofe pretty arms,

£ Going to leadebim off.

Sir. Sig. Hold^hold man, Mad faid ye ha, ha, ha mad / whe

we have a thoufand ofthefe in England that go loofe about theftreets,
and pafs with us for as ibber difcreet religious perfons- — ■
Asa man fhafl wilh to talk nonfenie withall.

Pet. You are miftaken Signior, I fay he is mad' — ftarkmady

S'xrStg. Prethee Barberacho what doft thou mean

Pet. To rid him hence that fhe maybe alone with you — -'slife Sir,
you're madder then he — don't you conceive — -

Sir Stg. Ay, say!' my* I confeffe, Iljultriffima Signiora, my Gover-
nour has a Fit that takes him now and then, a kinde of a frenzy,—-*
afigary — a whimfie a maggot that bites always at naming of Po-
pery: fo — he's gone. Belliffimo Signiora, — you have molt ar-
tificially remov'd him and this extraordinary proof of your affeclir

on isaligneof fome (mall kindenefle towards me, and though I was
fomething coy and referv'd before my Governour , Excellentifiimo,
Signiora, let me tell you, your love is not caft away.
Cor. Oh Sir you blefle too faft ! but will you ever love me — ■
Sir Stg. Love thee ! I and lie with thee too, Molt Magnanimous
Signiora, and beget a whole Race of Roman Julius Gefdrs upon thee 5
nay, now we're alone, turn me loofe to impudence, i'faith.

Q ruffles her. Enter Philipa in hafte,fhutting the door after her, .

PhiL'Qh Madam here's the young mad Engiifh Cavalier got into
the houfe, andwill not be deny'd feeing you.

Cor. This was lucky /

Sir Sig, How the mad Engiifh Cavalier / If this fhou 5 d be our young
Count Galiiard now — I were in afweet taking- — oh I know by my
fears 'tis he; oh prethee what kinde of a manner of man is he?

Phil: Ahandfbme — refolute — -brave- — bold- —

Sir Sig. Oh enough enough— Madam — I'le take my leave-^I fee-
you are- — fomething bufie at prefent,- — -and Pie — .

Cor. Not for the World,.- — Philipa—- bringin the Cavalier— that;
you may fee there'snone here fears him Signior. „



t>-



a 6 1 be t eign d Lum%ans^

Sir Sig. Oh hold hold, — Madam you are miftaken in that point,
for to teli you the truth, I do fear, — having — a certain — averfion
or Antipathy, — to— Madam— a Gentleman — whe Madam they're
the very Monfters of the Nation, they devour every day a Virgin. —

Cor. Good Heavens ! and is he fuch a Fury !

Sir Sig. Oh and the veryelt Belzebub,— befides Madam he vow' d my

Death, if ever he catch me neer this houfe, and he ever keeps his

word in cafes of this Nature,— Oh that's he, f Knocking at the door.

■ I know it by a certain trembling inftinft about me, — Oh what fhall I

do. — ■

Cor. Whe— I know not,— can you leap a high window ?

Sir Sig.— He knocks again,— I proteft Pme the worft Vaulter in
Ghriftendom, — have ye no moderate danger,— between the two ex-
treams of the window or the mad Count ? no Clofet,— fear has dwin-
dl'd me to thefcantlingofa Moufehole.

Cor.— Let me lee,' — 1 have no leafure to purfue my Revenge farther,
and will reft fatisfy'd with this,— for this time — [ Afide,
— -Give me the Candle, and whilft Philipais conducting the Cava-
lier to the Alcove by dark,- — you may have an opportunity to flip out,
■• — ^perhaps there may be danger in his being leen, — • £ Afide.

——farewell fool. i C Ex. Cornelia with the Candle, Phil, goes to

the door, lets inGzll. takes him by the hand.

Gall. Poxon't my Knights bound for Vitterbo, and there's no per*
fwading him into fafe harbour again, — -he has given me but two
hours to difpatch matters here, — -and then Pme to imbark with him
upon this new difcovery of honourable Love, as he calls it, whole ad-
venturers are fools, and the returning Cargo, that dead Commodity
calfd a wife ! a Voyage very futable to my humour, — who's there ?

Phil. A Slave otSilvianettas, Sir give me your hand. — -

\_ Ex.Overtheflage. Sir Sig. goes out foftly.

£ The Scene changes to a Bed Chamber Alcove, Petro leading in
Tickletext.

Pet. Now Signior you're fafe and happy •, in the Bed-Chamber of
your Miftrefs.< — who will be here immediately I'me Aire, Tie fetch a
light and put you to bed in the meantime.—

Ticks Not before fupper I hope honeft T^arberacho !

Pet. Oh Signior that you mail do lying, after the manner of the
Ancient Romans.

Tickj Certo, and that was a marevllous good lazy cultome. [Ex.Vet.

Enter Philipa with Galliard by darh^ — «

Phil. My Lady will be with you inftantly . Lgoes &&•

Tick* Hah, fure I heard fbme body come foftly in at the door : I hope
'tis the young Gentlewoman ! C Hfc advances forward.

Gall.



Or, A "Nights Intrigue. 47 -

GdU Silence /and Night ! Love and dear opportunity ! .

£ In afofttoae.
Joyn all your aids to make my Silvia kinde,

For I am fild with the expecting blifs, £ Tick, thrufts his head out to liften*
And much delay, or difappointment kills me.

Ttcki Difappointment kills me, — and me too certo.- — 'tis fiie.- —

Q Gropes abeut, .
(jail. Oh hade my fair, hafte to my longing Amis, —
Where are you dear and lovely ft of your Sex? ■ ,

Tick That's I, that's \ mi Alma ! mea core mea vita ! f

[_ Groping and peaking low* .

Gall. Hah- — -art thou come my life ! my foul / my joy ! — -

£ Goes to embrace, Tick, they meet and hifs,
— S'death what's this a bearded Miftrefs ! Lights lights there, quickly
lights, -Nay curfe me if thou fcap'ft me.™

Q Tick, fir aggies to get away, he holds him by the Qravat and Peri-
wig , Enter Fctro with a Candle.

Gall. Barberacho, — confound him, 'tis the fool ! whom I found this
Evening about the Houfe, hovering to rooft him here/ — hah — what
the devil have! caught — a Tarter ? Efcap't again ! the devil's his con-
federate. — [Groping*
[Vet. puts out the Candle, comes to Tick, unties his Cravat behind,,
andhe flips his head out of the Periwig andgets away, leaving both
in Gall.'s hands.

Vet. Give me your hand, Tie leade you a back pair of ftairs through

the Garden.

Ticki Oh any way to lave my Reputation- — -oh —

Gall. Let me but once more grafp thee, and thou (lialtrinde more

fafety in the Devils clutches ! none but my Miftrefs ferve ye.

|T Gropes out after him.

£ Pet. with Tick, running over the flage, Gall, afteSem, with the Cravat
andPerewigin one hand, his Pifiol in t'other.

Enter Vhilipz with a light. , ,

Phil. Mercy upon us, what's the matter — -what noife is this — hah
a Piftol-'-what can this mean ? [APiftolgoes off.

Enter Sir Signal, running.

Sir Sig. Oh fave me, gentle devil, fave me, the ftairs are fortify'd' :
witk Canons and double Culverins ; I'mc purfu'd by a whole Regiment r
ofarm'dmen/ here.sgold, gold in abundance ! fave me-—

Phil. What Canons ? what arm'd men ?

Sir Sig . Finding my felf purfu'd as I was groping my way -through: \
the Hall} and not being able to finde the door, I made towards the :



4$ Tfe Feign d Cnrii%ans y

ftairs again, at the foot of which I was faluted with a great gaun— *
a pox of the courteiie.

Gall. C Without ] Where are ye Knight, buffoon, dog of [Egypt ?
. Sir Sig. Thunder and Lightning ? 'tis Galliards voice — ■

Phil. Here, Hep behinde this hanging — there's a Chimney which
may ihelter ye till the ftorm be over, — if you be not fmother'd before.

£ Puts him bchinde the Arras, — Enter Gall, as before ^
and Corn, at the other door.

Cor. Havens! what rude noife is this ?

Gall. Where have you hid this fool, this lucky fool?
He whom blinde chance, and more ill -judging woman
Has rais'd to that degree of happinefTe
That witty men mull figh and toyl in vain for.

i Cor. Wat fool, what happinelfe ?

Gall. Ceafe cunning falfe one to excufe thy felf,
See here the Trophees of your fhameful choice,
And of my ruine, cruel— fair— deceiver !

Cor. Deceiver Sir, of whom in what defpairing minute did I

fwear to be a conftant Miftrefs ? to whatduii whining Lover did I vow
and had the heart to break it.

Gall. Or if thou hadft, I know of no iuch dog as wou'd believe
thee , no, thou art falfe to thy own charms, and haft betray'd'em
To the poflefTion of the vileft wretch
That ever Fortune curft with happinefs •,
Falfe to thy joys, falfe to thy wit and youth
All which thou'ft damn'd with fo much careful induflry
To an eternal fool,
That all the arts of love can ne're redeem thee !

'Six' Sig. Meaning me, meaning me : £ Peeping oat of the Chimny

his face blacht.

Cor. A fool, what indifcretion have you feen in me, fhou'd make ye
think I wou'd choofe a witty man for a lover, who perhaps loves out
his moneth in pure good husbandry, and in that time does more mif-
chief then a hundred fools :, ye conquer without refiftance, ye treat
without pity, and triumph without mercy ; and when you're gone,
the world crys— (lie had not wit enough to keep him, when indeed
you are not foolenough to be kept! thus we forfeit both our Liber-
ties and difcretion with you villanous witty men-, for wifedom is but
good iuccefs in things, and thofe that fail are fools !

Gall. Molt glorioufly difputed !
You're grown a Machi villian in your Art.

Cor. Oh neceflary Maxims only, and the firft Politiques we learn
from obfervatiori — I've known a Curtezan grown infamous, deip'is'd 1
decay'd, and ruin'd, in the poffeflion of you witty men, who when fhe

had



Or, A Nights Intngut. 4^

had the luck to break her chains, and caft her net forfSoIs, has liv'd in
ftate, finer then Brides upon their wedding-day, and more profufe then
the young amorous Coxcomb that fet her up an idoll.

Sir Sig. Well argu'd of my fide, I fee the Bagage loves me !

£ Peeping out with a face morefmutted.

Gall. And haft: thou ! oh, butprethee Jilt me on^
And fay thou haft not , deftin'd all thy charms,
To iuch a wicked ufe;

Is that dear Faceand Mouth for Haves to kifs :
Shall thofe bright Eyes be gaz'd upon, and ferve
But £o reflect the Images of fools?

Sir Sig. That's I ftill. £ Peeping more blacks

Gall. Shall that fbft tender bofome be approcht,
By one who wants a Soul, to breathe in languifhment,
At every kifs that prefles it.

Sir Sig. Soul, what a pox care I for Soul,— as long as my perfoa
is fo Amiable. —

Gall. — -No, Renounce that dull difcretion that undoes thee,
Cunning is. cheaply to be wile, leave it to thole that have
No other powers to gain a Conqueftby,
It is below thy charms \ —
— Come fwear,' — and be forfworn moft damnably,—
Thou haft not yielded yet \ lay 'twas intended only,
And though thou ly'ft, by Heaven I mult believe thee, —
■ — Say, — halt thou — given him — all ?

Qor. I've done as bad, we have difcourftth' affair,
And 'tis concluded on. —

Gall. As bad! by Heaven much worfe/difcours'd with him,
Were't thou fo wretched, lb depriv'd of feme,
To hold difcourfe with fuch an Animal ?
Darmi it ! the fin is ne're to be forgiven !
— Had'it thou been wanton to that lewd degree,
By dark he might have been conducted to thee ^
Where filentiy he might have ferv'd thy purpofe,
And thou had'It had fome poor excufe for that !
But bartering words with fools admits of none.

Cor. I grant ye, — had I talk't fenfe to him, — which had been enough
to have loft him for ever. . - , .

Sir Sig. Poor Devil, how fearfull 'tis of lofingme ! [J Afide.

Gall. That's lome atonement for thy other, fins,— come break thy
word and walh it quite away. - 7

Sir Sig. That cogging won't do my good fnerid, that won*t:^OA'
Gall. Thou fhalt be juft and perjur'd, and pay my heart the Jefe&of
Love you owe it. ! > .- ..

Car. And wou'd you have the heart— »to make a whore of me ?

H Gall.



$& The Fetptd Curii%ansi

GalL With all toy Soul,i ^hdthfiiO^vils in't if I f$% gt#<f thee a
greater proof of my paffioho .,,,.; _ - j - J -;

&r. I rather fear you wou'd deboch me^ into <that dull fiave call'd a
wife:

GalL A wife ! have I no Conscience, no Honour in me !
Frethee believe I wou'd not be to wicked,-^-

No, my defiresare generous land Noble,

To fet thee up, that glorious infblent thing,

That makes mankinde fucMIaves ! almighty Curtizan !

Come.! to thy private Chamber let'us haite,

The facred Temple of: he God of Love !

And confecrate t hy po wer ! | Offers to bear her ffi

for. .Stay, do you., take me then for what I feemV : ; : . /

GalL, Pme fure I do ! and wou'd not be ra iftaken for a Kingdome ! -
Rut if thwart not ! I can foon mend that fault,
And make thee fb^- — come— I'me impatient to begin the Experiment,

Q Offers again to carry her off, ,

Cor. Nay then 1 am in earneit,- — 'hold miftaken ftranger ! — I an? of
Noble birth! and fhou'd I in one haplefs loving minute^ deftroy the
Honour of my Houfe, ruin my youth and Beauty / and all that virtuous
Education, my hoping parents gave me?

GalL Pretty diflembPd pride and innocence ! and wounds no iels
thenXmiles ! — come let us in, — where I will give thee leave to frown
and Jilt, fucrrpretty frauds advance the appetite. XPffws again*

Cor. By all that's good I am a Maid of Quality ! .

Bleft with a Fortune equal to my Birth !

Gall. I do not credit thee, or if 1 did/
Jor once 1 wou'd difpence with Quality,
And to exprefs my Love ! take thee with all thefe faults !

Or. And being fo, can you expect Tie yield ?

G4L The fooner for that Reafonifthou'rt wife $
The Quality will take avVay the (caudal, — -
Do not torment me longer.-— - £ Offers to lead her -again,

Cor. Stay and be undeceiv'd, — I do conjure yew—

Gall. Art thou no Curtizan?

Cor. Not, ,on my life nor do intend to be !

'Gall. ' 'No proftitate.7 nor doft intend to be ?

Cor. By all that's good, I only feign'd to be fo / . ■.:!

GalL No Curtizan ! haft thou deceiv'd me then ?
'Tell nte thou wicked*- — honeft couzening Beauty !
Why did'ft i hou draw me i% withfuch a fair pretence^
Why fuch a temping preface to invite, &ii3

Andthe whole piece foufefefs and unedifying ?
- — •Heavens! not a Curtizan!
^\hyWt^t\iy window Wft thou take my vows,

" " ' _ And



A Nights Intrigue. 51

-And make fuchkinde returns? Oh damn your quality, what honeft
\Xfhore but wou ? d have fcorn'd thy cunning.

Cor. I make ye kinde returns !

Gall. — Perfwade me out of that too .' 'twill be like thee !

(br. By all my wifhes I never held difcourfe with you*— but this Even-
ing fince I fir(t faw your face !

Gall. Oh the Impudence of Hone fty and quallity in woman !
A plague upon 'em both, they have undone me,
Bear witnefs Oh thou gentle Queen of night,
Goddefs of fhades, ador'd by Lovers molt \
How oft under thy covert (he has damn'd her felf,
With feigned love to me ! £ inyajfion.

Cor. Heavens / this is Impudence, that power I call to witnefs too
how damnably thou i njur'ft me ; £ **£&>

Gall. You never from your Window talk't of love to me ?

Cor. Never.

Gall. So, nor you're no Gurtizaa \

Cor. No by my life!

(jail. So, nor do intend to be, by all that's good 4

Cor. By all that's good never.

Gall. So,- — and you are reall honeft, and of quallity ■'?

{or. Or may/ ftili be wretched /

Gall. So, then farewell honefty and quallity ! — S'death what a
nighty what hopes, and what a Miftrifs ; have I all loft for honefty
and quallity 1 C offers to go.

Cor. Stay.—*

Gall. I will be wreck- 1 firit,^— let go thy hold ! C infwy.

— Unlefs thou wouldft repent. — ■ C * n ^f°fi tone.

Cor. I cannot of my fixt refolves for Virtue !
——But if you could but — love me — Honourably — ■
Fori afTum'd this habit and this drefs

Gall. To cheat me of my heart the readyeft way !
And now like Gaming Rooks , unwilling to give o're till you have
hook't in my laft ftake my body too, you couzcn me withhonefty,-^—
ohDamn the dice — >I'le have no more on't I, the game's too deep for
me ! unlefs you play'd upon the fquare, Or / cou'd cheat like you—
farewell Quallity i — • Lgoes mt.

Cor. He's gone, Pbillipa run and fetch him back y -
I have but this fhort night allow'd for Liberty !
Perhaps to morrow I may be a Have ? | Ex. Philh

—Now a my Confcience there never came good of this troublefbme
virtue — -hang't / was too ferious ? but a Devil on't he looks fb Char-
mingly-*-rand was fb very preffing I durffc trufc my gay Humour and
gOpJ^LureRO ftrtber 1 r X.Shemlki^ont,Sir Signal

pe$s and then cmes out,
H 2 Sir Sig,



j* 3 The Feign* d Curt i%ans.

Sir % He's gone !-— fc~~-ha ha ha—
as I hope to breath Madam, you have moft neatlfdifp^tcht him y poor
fool — to compare his wit and his perfbn to mine.

Cor. Hah, the Coxcombe here ftill.

Sir Sig. Well this-Countenance of mine never fail'd me yet :

Cor. Ah [Looking about on him fees his face blacky

fqueeks and runs away.

Sir Sig. Ah,Wlie what the Deavilo's that for,
*— 'Whe 'tis I, 'tis I ill >ft Screnijfimo Signiora ! QGall, returns rftf^Philipa,

Gall. What noife is that, or is't fome, new deligne.
To fetch me ba€k again ?

Sir Sig. How ! Galliard return'd !.

Gall. Hah / whiatartthou ? a .lortall or a Devil ■?■'.

Sir Sig. How ! not know me ? now. mightl pafs upon him moft dam-
tily for a Devil , but that I have been beaten out of one Devilihip iU
ready, and dare venture no more Conjurationing.

Gall. Dog, what art thouT — not fpeak / Nay then 1'le inform my
ielf, and try if you be ftefh and blood. [ Kicks him, he avoids.

Sir Sig. No matter for all this — 'tis,better to be kicic't then difcove-
red, for then I fhali be kill'd: ?- — and I can facriEce a limb or two. to
my reputation at any time /

Gall. Death, 'cis the fool,the fool for whom I am abus'd and jilted,,
'cis fome revenge to dilappoint her cunning, anddrive the Have before
me-— —Dog ! were you her Iaft re ferye.-- — [ kicks him Joe kgeps in his cry.

Sir Sig. Still I fay Muni L .. .
(L*///Tlie Afle will ftill appear through all difguifes,..
Nor can the Devils fhapefecure the fool - — f Kicks him he runs ohkos

„ Cor. enters and ho Ids Gall , .

Cor. Hold Tyrant — ■ - .

Gall. Oh Women 1 Women I fonder imy our Appetites :
Then Beafts \ and more unnatural ! ;
For they but couple with their kinde, . but .you m
Promifcuoutly fhufle your Brutes together

Thejbp of bufinefs. with the lazy Gown-man- — -the learned Aile with-'
theJlUterate wit. The empty coxcombe with the- Pollititian, asDu'L
and infignificantas hcj from the gay fool mademorea beaftby fortune
to all the loath'd infirmities of Age ! .

•— T^EareweJl — I fcorn to crowd with the dull Herdv! Or graze upon<
the ; common -where they batten-r— . [Gees&utr

EilL J know he, loves,, by this concern I know it,
And will noUet him part djfatisfy'jd ! . [Goes mt. i

$r± '* — ,-By all that's good I love him more each ' [J Ente£ J Mdrcella^
moment^nd know be;? deftin'd to be mine.— -

— — what;



Or± A Nights Intrigue. £3

—-What hopes ajMarcella, what i'ftwe next fhall do?

zfWar. Fly to our laftxeferve,come let's hafteanddrefs ! in that difc
guife we took our. flight from Fitterbo in, — and fomthing— Irefolve !
- Cor. My foul informs me what ! — I ha't ! a project worthy of us
both — Which whilft wedrefs Tie tell thee, — and by which
My dear Marcella we will ftand or fall,
'Tis our laft flake we fet j and have at all.- — •



ACT V. SCENE I.

Enter Petro, Tickletext, from the Garden. .



7kk T f Afte honeft Barber acho, before the day difcover us to the
JtjLwicked world, and that more wicked (jalliard \

Pet. Well Senior, of a bad turn 'twas a good one, that he took
you for Sir Signal ! the- fcandjl Jys at his door now Sir,- — -fo the Lad-
dlrsfaft, you may now mount and away. — ■

Tick. Very well go your ways, and commend me honeft Barber acho
to the young Gentlewoman ! and let her know as foon as 1 may be cer-
tain torun no hazard in my Reputation, Tie vilit her again ! .
Pet., I'le warrant ye Signior for the future .'
Tick. So, now get you gone left we be difcover'd 1

Pet . Farewell Signior, a-bon- viage.- {_ Sx. v et. Tick, defcendsl

Tick. Tis marvellous dark, and I have loft my Lanthorn in the fray !
n <jroping~] — hah- — where abouts ami — hum — .what have we here!
*- — ah help help help ! C ftumhles at the Well, gets hald of the rope

1 fhall be drown 'd, fire! and'flides down inthe "Bucket.

fire, fire, for I have .water enough / Oh for fome houfe, — fome ftreetj
nay wou'd %omt\t felf were a fecond time in flames', that my delive-
rance might be wrought by the neceffity for. water, — -but no human:
help is nigh oh. . \_ Enter Sir Sig. m before.

Sir Sig. Did ever any Knight adventurer,' run through fo many dif-
afters in one Night ! my worlhipful carkafs has been cudgel d molt
plentifully, firft bang'd for a coward, which by the way was none of
myfault,! cannot help Nature ! then elawd away for a Diavilb ! there I .
was th e fool ! but who can help that too / frighted with GalVi coming
into an Ague, then chimney'd into a Feavor, where 1 had a fine regale
of foot} a perfume which nothing but my Cacamarda Or ungate coa' d \
excel) ll and which I Jiade by>-~{ifmfs ^.my.fmelling has defac'd. Na-
tures • mage, and a fecond time made me be fufpected for a devil !—
Setiiie fee,-^ ~ ^Qpnshis Lwtfom and look?, w his hands,

\ '". ' 'tis: - A



£4. The Fcigtfd Cnni%ant^

— 'tisfo— Tammaclentypicklel ifmyfacebeof the fame peice* I
am fit to fcare away old BeUehub himfelfefaith : g Wipes his face.

—-Ay — 'tisfo — like to like quoth the devil to the Collier / well
Tie home, fcrub my felf clean if podible, get me to bed, devife a haud-
fome lye to excufe my long ftay to my Governor and all's well, and the
man has his Mare again ! [jhutsbis Lanthorn and gropes away, runs a*

gainfithe Well,
—que quefto [_ feels gently."}
make me thankmli tis fubftantial wood ! by your leave —

[~ Opens his Lanthorn.
how! a Well! fent by providence that I may wafti my felf, left peo-
ple fmoke me by the fcent, and beat me anew for ftinking:

\^fe t s down his Lanthorn,pulls of his Masking coat } and goes to draw water.
'Tis a damnable heavy Bucket, now do 1 fancy I mall look when I am
warning my felf, like the figneof the Labour in vain.

Tick. So my cry is gone forth, and ! am delivered by Miracle from
this Dungeon of death and darknefs : this cold Element of deftru*
clion. — ■
Sir Sig. Hah — fure I heard a difmal hollow voice.—

f Tick, appears in the Bucket , above theWeH.
Tick- What art thou com'ft in charity.—

Sir Sig. Ah le Diavtllo ! le Diavillo ! le DiaviUo.- >

f Lets go the Bucket , iartd is running frighted away.
{ Enter Fillamour and Page, he returns.

■ — How a man ! was ever wretched wite fb miferable, the devil at one
hand, and a Roman Night-walker at the other ! which danger fhall I
choofe !— • E Gets to the door of the houfe.

Tick, So, Tarn got up at Iaft— thanks to my Knight, for I am fure
'twas he ! hah he's here — lie hear his bufinefs. £ Goes neer to Fillamour.

Fill. Confound this woman! this bewitching woman,
I cannot fhake her from my fullen heart,
Spight of my Soul I linger here abouts ;
And cannot to Vitterbo.

Tick- Very good ! a dainty Rafcall this !

. Enter Galliard with a Lanthorn, as from Silvia's houfe, held by Philipa.

Fill. — Hah who's this coming from her houfe, perhaps 'tis Galliard \\
Gall. No Argument fhall fetch me back by Heaven ?
Fill. 'Tisthe mad Rogue!

■Tkki Ohhord'tis<jalliard\ and angry too, now cou'di but get off
and leave Sir Signal to be beaten, 'twere a rare projecT:,— but 'HsJ im-
poffible without difcovery. rnfo bnoooi £ i , ■

Fill. But will you hear her Signior .'

Gall.



Of, A Nights Intrigue. , $3

Gall. That is, will ( J lofe more thncaboBt he*7 plagne onM -j^ve
thrown away already iuchSongs^ 'and'-fcnefes^tocb-.MadrigaJij raridTo-
ftesj fueh Night walks, fighs, and direfuULovers looks, as wou'd have
mollify 'd any- woman of Conscience and Religion! said now to be popt
"ith mouth with Quality/ well if ever you catch me lying with any
but honeft well meaning Damzelis hereafter hang me .-—farewell old
fecret farewell ! • [I JE.v. Philipa.

— Now am afham'd of being enzend fo .damnably, Fillamour that
virtuous Rafcall will fa laugh at mel s' heart cou'd i but have debaucht
him, we had been on equall terms,— .but I muft help, my- felf with ly-
ing,, and fwear have — a —

Fill. You (hall not need, Pie keep your couniel Sir! •.

Gall. Hah — eflevQusla.!. — . IT'

Tkk± How Fillamour all .this while, fome comfortyet, I am not the
©nlyprofeffor thatdifTembles! but how to getaway.—

Gall. Oh Harry^the molt damnably defeated ! \_Anoife offwords^

Fill. Hold / what noife is that ! two men coming this way as from
the houle of the Curtizans.

(T Enter Julio backyards fighting Odc&vio and bravo s !

Gall. Hah on retreating, — .'sdeath I've no fvvord !

Enter Julio and ORavio fighting.

Fill. Here's one / I'le take my Pages ! f Takes the Boys [word.

Gall. Now am I mad for milch ief, here hold my Lanthorn Boy / <

[_.They fight on Julio's fide, and fight Octavio out at tother fide !
Enter Laura aad Sabina / at the fore-door — which is the fame,
where Sir Signal ftands, Tick, growing up that way J finds Sir
Sig . jnfl entering in : Lau . and Sab . pafs over the ft age .

( Sir%. Hah a door open ! I care not who it belongs too, 'tis bet-
ter dying within doors like a man then in the ftreet. like a dog !

[Going in Tick, in great fear comes up and pulls him.

Tick-.. Signior ! a gentle Signior r whoe're ye are that owns this Man-
fion, I befeech you to give protection to a wretched man ! half dead
with fear and injury !

Sir Sig. Nay, I defy the devil to be more dead with fear then I !~Sig-
jjioryou may enter ! perhaps 'tis fome body that wil make an excuie

for us both, but hark they return ! ■ 35

X. And both go in : juft after Laura <«#^ Sabina enter. .

Lau. He's gone ! he's gone ! perhaps for ever gone, tell me thou

filly manager of Love! how got this Ruffian in, how was itpoflible •
without thy knowledge 4 ^-he cou'd get admittance.

Sab. Now as I hope to live and learn Iknow not Madam ! unlefs hs
ibllow ? dyoulvto-yo%letintk Cavalier^ which being by dark he

ealily;



$6 The FeigrCd Cnrti%ans 9

eafily conceal'd hlmfelf •, no doubt fome Lover of the SUvitrtetta't vrho
miftaking you for her ! took him too for a Rival !

Lau. 'Tis likely, and my Fortune is too blame, my curled Fortune
Who like Mifers, deals her fcanty bountys with fo flow a hand,
That or we dy before the bleffing falls,
Or have it fnatcht ere we can call it ours !
L Raving, 3 To have him in my houfe, to have himkinde !
Kind as young Lovers when they meet by ftelth :
As fond as Age to Beauty /and as foft,
As Love and wit cqu'd make impatient youth,
Preventing even my wifhes and defires, -

■ — Oh Gods ! and then ! even then to be defeated,
Then from my ore joy'd Arms to have him fnatch't \
Then when our vows, had made our freedome lawfully
What Maid cou'd fuffer aforprife fo cruel /
— The day begins to break, — go fearch the ftreets, •
And bring me news he's fafe or i am loft. £ Enter Gall. FiH. W Julio.

Fill. Galliard ! where 2rt thou/

gall. Here fafe and by thy fide. — ■

Lau. 'lis he /

Jul. Who ere he were, theRogue fought like a fury, and but for
your timely aid Pde been in fome danger /

Fill. But Galliard, thou wert telling me thy adventure with Silvia-
netta ! there may be comfort in't.

Lau. So, now t fhall hear with what concern he ipeaks of me.-[ afide.

Gall. Oh damn her, damn her /

Lau. Hah/ [zAfide.

Gall. The very'ft jilt that ever learnt the Art.

Lau. Heavens !

Gall. Death the whore took me, for fome Amorous Englifh Elder
Brother/ and was for Matrimony in the devils name ! thought me a
loving fool, that nere had feen fo glorious a light before / and wou'd
at any rate enjoy /

Lau. Oh Heavens /lam amaz'd / How much he differs from the
thing he was, but a few minutes fince. £ Afide.

Gall. And to advance her price, fet up for Quality / -nay fwore fhe
was a Maid / and that Ihe did but Act the Curtizan /

Lau. Which ton he feem'd to give a credit too,— —oh the for-
fworndiilembler.

Gall. But when I came to the matter then in debate, (he was for
'Honourable Love forfooth, and wou'dnot yield no marry wou'd Ihe,
not under a Licence from the Parfon of the Parifli.

Jul. Who was it prethee, 'twere a good deed to be lb reveng'd on
her/ . . •.!;■;■

Gall. Pox on her no, I'mefurefhe'sadamn'dgipfie, for at the fame
. - time



Or, A viig\)U intrigue, 57

time ihe had her Lovers in relerve, lay hid in her Bed-Chamber,

Lou. 'Twas that he took unkindly,.
And makes me guilty of that rude Addrefs!

Fill. Another Lover had fhe !

Gall. Yes, our Cqxcomb Knight Buffoon? laid by for a relliihing h,u
in cafe Iprov'd not feafbn'd to her minde.

Loh. Hah! he knew him then/

Gall. But damn her, fhepafTes with the ;Night, the day will bring
new Objects.

till. Oh I do not doubt it Frank}.

Lau. Falfe and inconftant ! Oh I fhall rave Stilvio. — -[ Afide to Sil v.
Enter Cornelia ! in ^JMans Cloatheswitb a Letter.

Cor. Here be the Cavaliers ! give me kinde Heaven but hold of him >
:and if I keep him not, I here renounce my charms of wit and Beauty ?
« — Signiors, is there a Cavalier amongft ye call'd FiUamow*

Fill. I own that name ;; what wou'd you Sir.

Cor. Only deliver this Signior.

\_ Fill. goes afide opens his Lanthorn and reads, Jul. and Gall talk^afide.

Fill. Q Reads. 2 He only tell you I am Brother to that CMarcella
whomyou'have injur'd.^ to oblige you to meet me an hour hence, in
the Piaz^o Dcfpagnia ! I need not fay with your fword in your hand,
fince you will there meet, — Julio Sebafiiano, Murifmi : — hah / her
Brotherfure — return'd from Travel, Q Afide.

■ — Signior— I will not fail to anfwer it as hedefires, £ to Cornelia.
I 'letake this opportunity to Ileal ofFundifcover'd, Q Afide going out.

Cor. So I've done my filters bufinefs, now for ray own.

Gall. But my good friend, pray what adventure have you been on
to Night.

Jul. 'Faith Sir, 'twas like to have prov'd a pleafant one, I came juft;
now from the Silviamtta, — -the fair young Curtiian.

Cor. Hah ! what fa id the man — -came from me 5 £ zAfide.

Gall. How Sir, you with Sihianetta ! when ?

Jul. Now, all the dear live long Night.

Cor. A pox take him, who can this be? — - [zAfide,

Gall. This Night ! this Night ! that is not yet departed !

Jul. This very happy Night : — -I told you I law a lovely woman at
St. Peters Church.

gall. You did fo.

Jul. I told you too I follow'd her home, but cou'd learn neither her
Name nor quality, but my Page getting ino the acquaintance of one
of hers, brought me news of both: her Name S/7w'^ttrf, her quality a
Curtizan 1

Cor. I at Church yefterday! Now hang me if I had any fuch devout
thoughts about me, whe what a damn'd fcandalous Rafcall this.

I M



gJJ The Feign d CuWHanf^

Jd. Fill'd with hopes of fuccefs, at Night I ma'de fier' a #fflfi$ft!
under her window had a skirmilh with Tome Rival, wlio Was th&t fe-
rinading her :

Gall. Was't he that fought us then^ ^Afide~] but it feems

you were not miitaken in the houfe, — on with your ftory pray — -death
I grow jealous now, — £ J fide"] you came at Night you (aid .?— ^

Jd. Yes,, and was receiv'd at the door, by the kind Siivianuta, Who
foftly whifper'd'me, come to my bofome and be lafe for ever ! and
doubtlefs took me forfome happier man.

Lai*. Confufiononhim, 'twas my very language !' [Afide raving..

Jul. Then Jed me by dark, into her Chamber !

Cor.. Oh thisdamn'd lying. Rafcall ! I do this ? f Aftde.

Jd. But oh the things, the dear obliging things, the kinde the fair,
young charmer. Paid and did..

Galli To thee !

Jd. Tome.

GalL Did Silvianctta do t\m> SilvianettatheCurttzzn..

Jd. Tliatpafles Sir for fuch, butis indeed ofquality.

Cor. This ftranger is the devil ! how fhou'd he know that fecret elfe.

Jd; She told me too 'twas for my fake alone, whom from the firft
minute (he faw, me Lov'd 7 me hadafium'd that Name and that diP
^guife, the looner to invite me.

Lau, 'Tis plain, the things I utter'd 1— oh ity heart' /

(jail. Curie on the. publique jilt, the very flattery me wou'd' have
palt on me.

Cor ! Pox'take h i nl, I muft dr a won Mm, 1 cannot hold / £ Afide.

CjalL Was ever. fuch a whore.

Lau, , Oh that Iknew thisman, whomby.mi1r.ake ! L^fid e °

i iaviQit all the fecrets of my foul too / £AJide,

Jd, I preft for fomething more then dear exprefllons,
And found her yield apace,
But lighing told me, of a fatal! Contract,
She was obiig'dto make to one ihe never law, .
And yet if I wou'd vow to Marry her, when Ihe cou'd prove to •
Merrit it, Ihe wou'd deny me nothing.

Lau. "TwasT, by Heaven that needle fs fool Was L .

'Jul. Which J with Lovers eager joy performed,
And On myknees utter'd the hafty words,
Which me repeated ore and gave me back !

Gall, So, he has fwallow'd with a vengeance the very Bait /he had
jpepar/d for me, or any body that wou'd bite. j^Apde,

■Jd. But ere. I cou'd receive the dear reward of all my vows,
I was drawn upo% by a man that lay hid in her Chamber :
Whether by chance 6e defign 1 knovtf not, who fought' $$$&$
Aijd Was the^mc^att found me eagag'd with- .



Oi; 5 A Nights Intrigue. * *

•€br. ApleafantRafcallthis, as ere the devil taught his leflbn too-

Gall So, my comfort is fhe has jilted him too molt damnably.

Cor. 'Sliie I have anger enough to make me valiant, why fhou'd I
not make ufe on't, ancfceat this lying Villain whilfl; the fit holds.

GalL And you defign to keep thele vows, though you're contraded
to another woman ?

Jul. I neither thought of breaking thofe, or keeping thele,
My lbul was all imploy'd another way.

fyati.- — -Itlhall be fb, — Silvio — -I've thought upon a way that
muft redeem ail,— hark and obferve me.- — -

£ Takes Sih and whifpers to him. '

Jul. But Pme impatient to purfue my adventure,
Which I muft endeavour to do, beforethelightdifcoverthe miftake;
* — Farewell Sir. [ Ex. Julio,,

Gall. Go and be ruin'd quite, fhe has the knack of doing it.

Sih. I*le warrant ye Madam lor my part. £ Ex. Laura /

GAL — I have a damn'd hankering after this woman, why cou'd
notl-have put the cheat on her, as Julio has, I Hand as little on my
word as he ! a good round Oath or two had done the bufinefs, — -but a
pox on't I lov'd too well to be fo wife. £ Silvio comes : $ to him,

Sab. Conlicentia Signior / Is your name Galliard f

Gall. I am the man fweet-heart,- — -let me behold thee — hah—
Sans Cow's /Page.

Sab. A dews of his Lanthorn, what fhall I fay now ? ^Afide.

—Softly Signior, I am that Page whofe chiefeft bufinefs is to attend
m y Lords Miftrifs Sir.

Cor. His Miftrefs : whofe Miftrefs, what Miftrefs -,s'life how that lit-
tle word has nettled me! L^fide liftening clofe.

Gall. Upon my life the woman that he boafted of. [Afide hugging
——a fair young Amorous — Noble — Wanton a— • himfelf*

And Ihe wou'd ipeak with me my lovely boy ?

Sab. You have prevented the commands I had. 'but fhould my Lord
know of it ;—

Gall. Thou wert undone ! I underftand thee —
And will be as fecret as a ConfeiTor — -
As lonely lhades, or everlaiting Nighty— come lead the way.- — -

Cor. Where I will follow thee, though to the bed of her thou'rt go-
ing too, and even prevent thy very bufinefs tSere.— -• £ A fide.

Exeunt*
Enter Lau$a ashefore in aTtyght-goypn. . Scene, &£Chamber»
La*. Now for a power that never yet was known
;iTP.$aon this ftranger quickly into love,

I 2



6o The reigvd Curti%ans,

Aflift my eyes thou God of kind? defires ;
Infpire my language with a moving force
That may at once gain and fecare the Victory,- Enter SiL

Sab. Madam your Loyers here : your time's' b$t fhort, confider too 1
Count Julio may arrive /

Lan. Let him arrive ! having fecur-M my felf of what I love,
Pie leave him to complain his unknown lofle.
Tp/careleiTe winds as-pitrylefs as t : Sabina fee the Rooms
Be fill'd with lights 7 whilft I prepare my felf to entertain him.
Darjyiefs ftjal-1 n^'re deceive me, more- — - Q Enter' to SiL GzW.gaz.irig

about him Cor. peeping at the door.

Call. All's wonderous rich,- — Gay as the Court of love,
But ftill and filent as the (hades of death ^ ,

—Hah Muiick ! and Excellent ! U>°fi Mufick vphiffl they fie ak.

Poxon : t — -hut wh'ere's the woman- — -T need no preparation.- — •

Cor. No you are always provided for fuch incountersand can fall too
Sans Ceremony,' — -butl may fpoil you ftomack, ^ASongxumng,

Call. A voice too^ , by Heaven and*cis a fweet one •
Grant {he.be young and Vie excuie the reft.
Yet vie for pleafure with the happyeft Roman ! ;'*

\TheSong as byXj&xm^after which fo ft Muficktilljhe- enters,



E



TKe S Q N G By a Perfon of Quality

''csffewellthe World and-mortnl caress

The rayifht Strephon cry'd^
As full of joy and fender tears
He lay by t hWlhjBle :
Let others toyl for wealth andfarne r ^
Whilflnot.one thought of mine r
At any other blifs fhallaim^ ' ,

"But thofedear arms, butthofe dear arms of thine* „






Still let me gazje on thy bright eyes^ ; *

Andhear thy charming tongue^ .
J nothing askj' increafe my joys •;
But thai to feel 'em dong;
In clofe embraces let pu lye,
*Arid \ fiend \owr lives to Homt^
Then let us both together dye
Aid ht each ethers > be mfa ethsn Tmfc >
■".■'"' ! i

5 *— »Dcaifei.



Or 5 A Nights- Intrigue. $\

* — Deatjvl amfir'd already with her voice. — 3

Cor. So, I am litee to thrive,—- [[ Znter Julio.

JhU What meafrlhefe lights in every room, as if to make the day
without the Sun : and quite deftroy my hopes !~hah Galliardhcre i

Cor. A man ! grant it fome Lover, or fome Husband Heave 11/
Or any thing that will but fpoil the fpofty
The Lady / oh blaft her / how fair flie is.

[EnterLzui'2. with her Lute drefl in a carelefs rich drcfs 1 followUby
Sabina to whom fie gives her Lute.

Jul. Hah! 'tis the fame woman 1 fcSies Julio mdftm-s.

Laic A ftranger here !• what Art can help me now. — • [5k paitfes.

Gall. By all my joys a lovely woman T tis>

Lau. Help medeceipt, diilembling, all that's woman — -

fjj She- ft arts and gaz.es 0/7 Gail, fulling Silvio.

Cor. Sure 1 fhou'd know that face.. — •

Lau. Ah look my Silvio ! is't not he / — it is !.
That fmile, that Air, "that meen, that Bow is his/
'Tis he by all my hopes, by all my willies !

GalL- He, yes yes,. I am a He, I thank my Mars I
And never bleft'em half fo much for being fa,
As for the dear variety of woman /

Cor. £urfe on her charms iheeU make him love imearneit.

Laa. It is my Brother / and report was falfe / [Cooing towards him.

Gall How her Brother /GadTme fbrry we're ib neer akin with all
My foul , for I anrdamnably pleas' d' with her /

Lau. Ah why do ye lliun my Arms — -or are ye Ayr / \
And not to be inclos'd in human twines — ■
Perhaps you are the Ghoft. of that dead Lord /
That comes to whifper vengance to my foul.

Lau. Shart / a Ghoft ! this is an odd preparative to love. (AjUe r

Cor. ' Tis Laura i my Brother Jdiah Miftrefs, and Sifter to O&avio I

Gall. Death, Madam, do not fcare away my. love, with tales of
Ghofts, and fancies- of the dead, Lie give ye proofs I'me living lo-
ving man, as errant an Amorous a Mortal! as heart can vvifli j — I hope
fte will not jilt me- too.. : ; £ A fide,

-Cot. Soil.he ism his oommonproof for all Arguments
Ifihe (hou'd take him at his word now, and fhe'l be fare to do' t. . .
. Lau., Amiable ftranger pardon the miftake !
And charge it on mypaffion for a Brother 1 - ;
Devotion was not moreretir'd then L r <
Veftals, or widovv'd Matrons when they, weep-j ,
Tij^asa fatall chance /law in ypu 5..
TJk dear refemblanceofaMurther'd Brother! ijtmpsp.



6.2 The Feign' d Cuni%ms^

Jul. What the devil can fhe mean by this. [Jfide,

Lau. I durft not truft my eyes, yet ftill I gafc'd,
And that encreas'd my faith you were my Brother,

But fmce thsy err'd, and he indeed is dead,
Oh give me leave to pay you all that love,

That tenderne fs and paffion that was his ! £ Weeping.

_ Or. So, I knew (lie wou'd bring matters about fome way or other*
ohmifchiefmifchiefhelpme ! 'slife I can be wicked enough when I
have no ufe on't, and now I have, i'me as harmlefs as a fool.

X^As Gall, is earneft'fy talking to Lau. Julio pulls him by thefleeve,

Lau. Oh fave me ! lave me from the Murderer !

Jul. Hah !

(jail. A Murderer where !

Lau. I faint, I dye with horror of the light

Gall. Hah — «my friend a Murderer ! fure you miftake him Madam,
he faw not Rome till yefterday, — -an honeft youth Madam and one that
knows his diftance upon occafion ! — -'slife how cam'ft thou here— —
prethee begone and leave us !

JhI. Why do you know this Lady Sir.

Gall. Know her ! — a- — ay ay — man — and all her Relations, fhe's
of quality,- — withdraw withdraw — -Madam — 'a— he is my friend
and ihall be civil. — -

Lau. 1 have an eaiie faithfor all you fay, — but yet however inno-
cent he be or dear to you, I beg he woul'd depart — he is fo like my
brothers Murtherer, that one look more wou'd kill me

Jul. A Murtherer ! charge me with cowardife,with Rapes or Trea- :
fbns — Gods a Murtherer/

Cor. A devil on her ! me has rob'd the fex of all their arts of cun-
ning.

Gall. Pox on't thou'rt rude ! go, in good manners go- — •
•** Lau. I do conjure ye torture me no more,
If yoii wou'd have me think you're not that Murtherer.
Be gone — and leave your Friend to calm my heart
Into fome kinder thoughts !

Gall. Ay, ay, prithee go ! He be fure to do thy bufinefsfor thee *

Cor. Yes, yes, you will not fail to do a friendly part no doubt' —

Jul. 'Tis but in vain to ftay — 1 fee me did miftake her man ■
lafb Night, and 'twas to chance I am in jdebt for that good fortune \~ —
I will retire to mow my obedience Madam ! * i -' :> g m ; ri ■:.':.," ■

C Ex. Jul. Gall, going to the doorwiMim.

Lau. He's gone and left me Miftrefs of my wifh !
Defcend ye little winged Gods of Love,



Or r AWghf/Imigne. 6y

2Merii£% all our^iiive&'at his heart \

C Gall, returns, jhe tales' hiiH by the hand,
— — Advarice thou dearer to my foul then kindred,
Thou more then Friend or Brother,
Let meaner Souls born bafe conceal the God I
Love owns his Monarchy within my heart,
So Kings thatdaign to vifit humble roofs ■:
Enter di%uis'd, but in a Noble Palace,
Own their great Power, and fhow themfelves in glory.

Gall. I amall tranfport with this flidain blifs,
And wantlbme kinde allay to fit my Soulforrecompence.

Cor. Yes, yes, my forward friend you (hall have an allay,. if all my
Art can do't, to damp thee even to dilappointment. .

Gall. My Souls all wonder now, let us retire,
And gaze till I have foftend it to Love. £ Going out is mttby Cor. .

Cor, Madam!

Lau. More interruption / hah.- — > [_Turns„

Cor. My Matter the young Count Julio,

Lau. Julio I ~

Gall. Whatofhirr. %A$*}

Cor. Being jult now arriv'd at Rome I

Lau. Heavens /arriv'd! \_nAfide>

Cor. Sent me to beg the Honour of waiting on you,

Lau. Sure Itranger youmifbake /- —

Cor . If Madam you j are Laura Lueretia ! — •

GalL ... Laura Lueretia ! by Heaven the very woman-he's to marry,

ZAfids.,

Lau. This wou\i furprife a Virgin lefs refolv'd,
But what have I to do with ought but Love ! £Afide a .

—-And can your Lord imagine this an hour,
To make a ceremonious vifit in !

Gall. Ridte's by Love ! ' or is't fome trick again. £ sXJide . .

Cor. Madam, where vows are pad, the 1 want of ceremony may be.
pardon'd!

Lau. I donot ufe to have my will difputed 5 ;
Begone and let him know Pie be obey'd !

Cor. 'SlifeJhe'l out-wit me yet, fjjfjtJOfc .

Madam I fee this nicenefs is- not general^ ,
■ — You can except fome Lovers.

GalL My pert young confident depart, and ler your Mafteff-know
fie'lfinde a better welcome from the fair vain Curtizan, faSthimettul :
where he has part the Night and given his vows. ;

Lau. Dearly devis'd and I rrkift take the hint. . ^AfZde fritting, .

Cor. He knowsrnefurey and-feytfall this to plagueuie, ... g AjUt. ,
My Lord, my Matter, with a Curtizan ! he's butjtjit now : ari €& 7



■ &'S



6\ The Feign'd Curti%ans 9 -

Gall. A pretty focward favvcy lying boy this ! and may do well in
time, — -Madam believe him not, 1 faw his Matter yefterday,- — -con-
vert with him, — •' know him he's my friend !•— 'twas he that parted
hence but now, — -he told me all his paflion for a Curtizan, fcarce half
an hoar iince.

Cor. So!

Lau. 1 do not doubt it, oh how I love him for this feafanable.lye,

And can you think I'le fee a perjur'd man, £ To Cor.

Who gives my intreft in him to another,

Do i not help ye out moil Artfully. — £ And laughing to Gall.

Cor. I fee they are refolv'd to out face me.

Gall. Nay vow'd to marry her !

Lau. Heavens to marry her !

Cor. To be conquer'd at my own weapon too, — lying 'tis a hard
cafe! [.Afide.

gall. Go boy you may be gone, you have your Anfwer childe,
And may depart — corns Madam let us leave him.

Cor. Gone / no help, death I'le quarrel with him, — nay fight him,
■ — Damn him, — rather then loofe him thus, — ftay Signior£ J nils him.

You call me boy,- — but you may finde your felf miftaken Sir, — •

And know. — V ve that about me may convince ye, Q Showing his [word.
• — 'Thas done fome Execution !

Gall. Prethee on whom or what ? fmall Village curs /
The barking of a Maftive wou'd unman thee. £ Offers to go.

Cor. Hold — follow me from the refuge of her Arms !
As thou'rt a man, I do conjure thee do't :
: 1 hope he will, Tie venture beating for't. £ Afide.

gall. Yes, my brisk- — little Rafcal — «I will — a

Lau. By all that's good you (hall not ftir from hence, ho who waits
there, Antonio, Silvio, Gafpcro,[_ Enter all"} — take that firce youth and
bear him from my fight.

Cor. You ihall not need, 'slife thele rough Rogues will be too hard

forme, — 've one prevention left,' farewell,

Main; thou fupplyherwithas feable Art,

As I fhou'd do, were I to play thy part. {_ Goes out with the reft.

Gall. He's gone ! Now lets redeem our blelfed minutes loft. \_Gom
Scene changes to the Street. — ■ Piazo Defpagnia \

Enter Julio alone.

JhL Now by this breaking daylight I cou'd rave, I knew fhe mi-
ftook me laft Night which made me ib eager to improve my luckey

minutes, fureGW/;Wisnottheman, Hong to know the miftery,

■ hah who's here — Fillamour.]

£ Enter Fillamour met by Marcella in Mans Clothes y they pafs hf
each other— -cock^andjufile.

Mar. I take it — you are he I look for Sir !

m.



Or, A Nights Intrigue. $*

Fill. My Name is Fiilamom,

/ Alar. Mine,- Julio Sebaftiano Murifini.

JhL Hah, my Name by Heaven. £JJlde,

FilL I doubt it not, fince in that Lovely face,
I fee the charming Image oiMarcella !

JhL Hah.

Mar. You might, ere Travel ruffed me to man,
—I fhou'd return thy praife whilft Ifurvey thee,
•But that I came not here for Complement,— draw.— C Draws,

till. Why caufe thou'rt like Marccllat
Mar. That were fuflncient realbn for thy hate,
But mine's becaufe thou baft betray'd her bafely j
& — She told me all the ftory of her Love,
How well you meant, how honeftly you fwore,
And with a thoufand tears imploy'dmy Aid :
•To break the contract fhe was forc't to make,
T' Ottavio, and give her to your Arms.
I did, and brought you word of our defign,
- — I need not tell ye what returns you made •,
Let it fuffice my Sifter was neglected,
Neglected for a Curtizan, — -a whore /
I watcht and law each circumftance of falfliood,
Jul, Damnation / what means this?
Fill. I fcorn to fave my life by lyes or flattery s,
But credit me, the Vifit that I made,
Idurft have fwom had been to my vJMarcella I
Her Face, her Eyes, her Beauty was the fame,
Only the bufmefsof her Language differ'd,
And undeceiv'dmy hope.

Mar. In vain thou think'ft to flatter me to faith, —
When thou'dft my Sifters Letter in thy hand, which ended that difpute
Even then I faw with what regret you read it :
What care you took to difobey it too, —
The Ihivering Maid, half dead with fears aud terrors of the Night,
In vain expected a relief from Love or thee,
Draw that I may return her the glad news I have reveng'd her.

JhL Hold much miftaken youth J 'tis I am JW*0,thou Fillamour know^ft
my Name, knows I ari v'd but yefterday at Rome, and heard the killing
news of both mj Sifters flights, Marcella and Cornelia, — -and thou art
lome Impofturc. [To Marcella,

Mar. Ifthis now fhou'd be true, I were in a fine condition.—
Fill. Fled! Marcella fed \
JhL 'Twas fhe I told thee yefterday was loft,
But why art thou concern'd,-— explain the Miftery /
Fill. I loy'd her more then life .' nay even than Heaven !

K And



£6 The Feign'd Cmti**<ms,

And doft thou qneftion my concern for her,
Say how /aid why ! and whether is {he fled/

Jul. Oh wou'd 1 knew, that I might kill her in her Lovers Arms,
Or if I found her innocent, reilore her to Oftavio I

Ft 11.. To Oftavio! and is my friendmip of fo little worthy
You cannot think I merrit her.

Jul. This is fome trick between 'em ! but I have fworn moil folemn-
ly, have fworn by Heaven aud my Honour to relign her, and 1 will

do'tor dye, there fore declare quickly, declare where fhe's, or I will

leave thee dead upon the place. f Te Marcella.

Mar. So, death or Oftavio, a pretty hope full choice this.

Fill. Hold! by Heaven you (hall not touch a fingle hair, thus — -
will 1 guard the fecret in his bofome. [Tuts himfelf between y em draws.

Jul. 'Tis plain thouft injur'd me, and to my Honour lie facrifice

my friendihip, follow me. Q Enter Petro and Cornelia.

Mar. Ah Petro, fly fly fvvift and refcue him. — C Exmnt Pet. with his

Or. Oh have / found thee, fit for my purpofe too. {word in his hand.
Come hall along with me,. — thou mull prefent my Brother JhIio in-
ilantiy, or i am loft, and my projects loft, and my mans loft, andallV
loft. Enter Petro.

Pet. Vitloria, Fiftoria, your Cavaliers and Conqueror t the other
wounded in his fword hand, was eafily difarm'd.

Afar. Then lets retire, if I am feen i'me loft, — Petro ftay here for
the Cavalier, and conduct him to me to this houle •,- — I muft beipeedy
now. —

Cor. Remember this is Julio X \_Vomting to Marcella !

J } et, 1 know your deiign and warrant ye my part : — hdh Oftavio..
Enter O&aviQy Murifini, and Crapine.

Oft. Now cowardife that everlafting infamy, dwell ever on my face, .
that men may point me out that hated Lover, that few his Miftrefs
falie, Hood tamely by whilft fhe repeated vows / nay was fo infamous
fo dully tame, to hear her fwear her hatred and averfion, yet ftill I
calmly liftend / though my fword were ready, and did not cut. his
throat for't.

Mm. \ thought, you'd faid you'd fought.

Oft. Yes,. 1 did route at laftand wak'dmy wrongs,.
But like ah Afs a patient fool of Honour,
I gave him friendly. Notice! wou'd kill him \
And fought like prizers not as angry Rivals.

Mftr. Why that was hanfome, — -I love fair play what wouM yop
elie have done !

Oft. Have fall'nupon him like a fudain ftorm^ ££»m' Pet. and Fill
quick unexpected in his height of Love: -^-^feer — .fee yonder ! or I'me
miftaken by thisglimeringSay ©f that is FUlamaur^ now lenteringigt
her door, 'tis he % my Fevenge !«— whatfay you £i& '

Mm*



Or, A Nights Intrigue. 67

Mur. By th' Mafs I think it was he, Enter Julio.

OB. Julio I've caught the wantons in their toyl,
I have 'em faft, thy fifter and her Lover. ^Smbraceshim.

Jul. Eternal fhame light on me, if they fcape then /
OB. Follow me quick, — whilft we can get admittance.
Jul. Where — ^here.'

OB. Here, — come all and fee her fhame and my Revenge.
Jul. And are you not miftaken in the houfe.
OB. Miftaken !/faw the Ra vi [her enter juft now, thy Uncle faw it
£00, oh my ExcefTive joy, come if / lye — fay /'me a dog a Villain !

\_ Exeunt as into the Houfe.
Scene changes to a Chamber, Enter Sir Signal — a little groping.
Sir Sig. There's no finding my way out,— and now does fear make
me fancy,* — this fome /nchanted Caftle. — • [ Enter Tick, liftening.
Ticks Hah an /nchanted Caftle 1

Sir Sig. Belonging to a monfterous Giant ! who having fpirited a-
way the King ofTropicivopicans Daughter, keeps her here inclos'd, and
that / wandering Knignt am by fickle Fortune fent to her deliverance.

[ Tick, liftens.
Tickz How's that! fpirited away the King of Tropicipopicans daugh-
ter ! blefs me what unlawful! wicked nefs is pra&ic'd, in this Romifh
Heathenifh Countreys ! [_Afide.

Sir Sig. And yet the devil of any dwarfe Squire or Damzel have /
met with yet : — wou'd / wereclenlilyofFa thisbufinefs, — hah lights

as / live /and people coming this way / blefs me from the Giant, —

Oh Lord what fhall /do. > C Ealls on his knees.

Tick. I fear no Giants, having juftice on my fide, but Reputation
makes me tender of my perfbn ! — hah ^—what's this a Curtain : /'le
winde my felf in this, it may fecure me !

{_ Winds himfelf in a window Curtain.
Sir Sig. They're entering, what fhall / do — hah — here's a cor-
ner ! defend me from a Chimney.

][' Creeps to the corner of the Window, and feels a fpace between Tick.
legs and the corner. creeps in andftands up juft behind Tickletext.
Snter Gall, leadinghamz ! Sab. with lights juft after 'em I Jul.
Ort. Mur. W Crap.
OB. Juft in the happy minute.

Gall, /'vefworn by every God /by every power divine ! to Marry
thee ! and fave thee from the Tyranny of a forc't ContracT:, — Nay Gad
if /loofe a fine wench for want of Oaths this bout the devil's in me.
OB. What think ye now Sir.

Jul. Damnation on her, let my rage at liberty ! C Mur. holds him.
that /may kill 'em both !
Mtr. I fee no caufe for that, fhe may be virtuous yet
08. De ye think as fuch to pafs her ofFon me,

K 2 Of



68 The Feigtfd Curti%attf 7 .

Or that /'le bear the infamy of your Family,
No/fcornhernow, but can revenge my Honour on a Rival!
Mur. Nay: then Pie lee fair play, — turn and defend thy life, [goes to
Jul. Whilft I do jufticeon the Proftitute ! —hah — ■ Gall, who turns.
Defend me 'tis the woman that I Love., £ Hegjz.es IJhe runs to Gall.
Lau. OBavio !

OB. Laura! my fitter / perfidious lhamefnll ! — £ Offers n kill her.
Jul. Hold ! thy fitter this ? that fitter i'me to marry ! (wretched.
Lau. i s this then Julio ! and do all the powers conlpire to ■ make me
OB. May I be dumb for ever /

£ Holds his /word down and looks fadly, Jul. holds Lau. by one hmd
fie ads with OOi. with the other. Enter Fillamour and Pet.

Bill. Hah Galliard /in danger too • ! £ Draws..

\_fiepsto 'em iMwc. puts between, ■
OB. Fillamour here, how now what's the matter friend.

\_they talkyehilft Enter Marcella and Cornelia.

Gor. Hah new broyls, fure the devil's broke loofe to Night! — -my

Uncle as 1 live ! \JAm. pleads between. Fill. tf»d Odlavio.

Mar. A^ndOBaviol where mall we fly for fafety /

{or. Fie ene truft to my Breeches/ 'tis too late to. retreat ! — 'slife

here be our Cavaliers too, nay then nere fear falling into the Enemies

hands /

Fill. J , I fled with Marcella ! had I been blett with fo much Love
from her, I wou'd have boaftcd on't 'ith face of Heaven.
-Mur. La ye Sir. UToOflaviol

Fill. The lovely Maid, I own I Tiave a paffion for,
But by the powers above the flame was facred,
And wou'd no more have patt the bounds of Honour,
Or hofpitallity / then I wou'd bafely Murther ! and were Ihefree,
I.wou'dfrom all the World make her for ever mine.
o&Jur. . Look ye Sir, a plain cafe this.
Gall. He tells ye fimple truth Sir.

OB. Was it not you, this fcarce patt Night I -fought with- here, in-
die houfe by dark ! juft when you had exchanged your vows with her!
Lau. Heavens ! was it he ? £zAfide.

Fill. This minute was the firtt I ever entred here /
Jul. 'Twas I Sir, was that interrupted Lover, — andthis the LadyJ
Lau. And mult ,< yield at laft. • [^Afide*

OB. Wonders and Ridies !

Gall. And was this the SilmanettaSlr ? you told the ftory of ! L/lyly* ,
Jul. The fame whom inclination, friends and, deitiny, ;
Confpire to make me bleftwith.

Gall. So many difappointments m one Night, wou'd make a man.
turn honeft in fpight of Nature \ C $j? Sig. peeps from behind.

ShSig. Some comfort yet,, that I am not the only fool defeated..'



Or, A Nights Intrigue* 69,

OB. Tme fatisfied ! [ to Fill. ] — but what cou'd move you Sir,—
F to Gall. 2 to injure me ! one of my Birth and Quality !

Gall. Faith Sir I never Hand upon ceremony when there's a woman
in the cafe, — -nor knew I 'twas your Sifter : Or if I. had 1 fhou'd alik'd
her nere the worfe for that, had ihe been kind.

Jul. It is my bufinefs to account with him,
And! am fatisfy'd he has not injur'd me ! he is my friend V
GalL That's frankly laid ! and uncompel'd I fwear Ihe's innocent !
OB. If you're convine't ! I too am fatisfy'd /
And give her to you whilft that faith c ntinues ! [_ Gives himher,

Lau. And mufti, mull I force my heart to yield/ \_Afide.

And yet his generous confidence Obliges me ! r Afide.

OB. And here 1 vow / "by all the facred Powers, L Kneels. ~] that pu-
nifh perjery, never to fet my heart on faithlefs woman I- — Never to
Love nor Marry ! [_Rifes. ~] Travel lhal be my bufinefs, — thou my
Heir! [ToM^.

. Sw Sig. So, poor foul, I warrant he has been defeated too 1
v Mar. MarcelU Sir will take ye at your word !

F.IL Adarcella !
. Mar. Who owns with blufhes truths fhou'd beconceal'd,but to pre-
vent more mifchief, — that I was yours Sir was agaitift my will, froOtt.
my foul was F^.wwri ere you claim da right in me :> though I nere.
fawor helddilcourie withhim^ butat an awful! d:fta;ice, — nor knew
lie of my Might.

OB. 'do believe, and give thee back my claim, 1 fcorn the brutal
part ofLove / ihenobleit body where the heart is wanting.

\Jfhcy all talkjtfide, Cornelia Games, up to Galliard!

Cor. Whe how now Cavalier ! how like adifcarded favorite do you

look now, who whilft your Authority lafted laid about ye j domi-

neerd huft andblufterd, as if there had been no end on't, now a man'

may approach ye without terror ! you fee the meats fnatcht out of

your mouth Sir, the Lady's difpos'd on / who's Friends and Relations-,
you were lb well acquainted with.
Gall. Peace boy, Iihallbeangryelfe. — •

Q>r. Have you never a caft JVliftrefs that will take compaflion on';
you : faith what think you of the little Curtizan now /
Gall. As ill as ere 1 did ! what's that -to thee.
Cor. Much more then you're aware on Sir,-^— and faith to tell yotf
truth l'me no f.r vant to Count Julio ! but ene a little michievous inftru-
ment Ihe fent hither to prevent your making Love to Derm Laura !

(jail. *Tis (he herfeli, — hov cou'd that beauty hide it felf lb long
from being Known ! ^Afide.~$ — • Malicious little dog in a Manger^.
that wou'd neither eat, nor fuffer the hungry to feed them fe Ives L vvliat
fpitefull devil cou'd move thee to. treat a Lover thus .' but \ am: pretty
well reveng'd on ye I ,
%m Onnje!



jo The Feign* <t Curt i% ms \

Gall. You think I did not know thofe pretty Eyes I that lovely. Mouth
I have fo often kilt in cold imagination !

Cor. Softly tormentor ! £ They talkafide.

Mat. In this difgufe we parted from Fitterbo ! atended only by Petro,
and FhiLpa ! at Rome we took the Title and habit of two Curtizans j
both toihelter nsfrom knowledge, and to Oblige Fillamour tovifit us,
which we beliv'd he wou'd in curioiity, and yefterday it fo fell out as
we defirM !

Fill. How ere my eyes might be impos'd upon, you fee my heart was
firm to its firft object, can you forget and pardon the miftake !

Jul. She fliall ! and with Ottavio's — and my Uncles leave, thus

make your Title good. — . £ Gives her to Fill.

Oft. 'Tis vain to ftrive with deftiny ! [_ (jives her.

Mar. With all my heart, but where's firndia all this while !

Gall. Here's the fair ftragler Sir.

£ Leads her to Mur. he holds his Cane up at her.

Mnr. Why thou baggage, thou wicked contriver of mifchief, what
excufe hadft thou for running away, thou hadft no Lover ?

Cor. 'Twas therefore Sir t went to finde one / and if I am not mifta-
ken in the mark/tis this Cavalier I pitch upon for that ufe andpurpoie.

gall. Gad 1 thank ye for that,' — I hope you'l ask my leave firft,
I'me finely drawn in efaith ! — have / been dreaming all this Night,
of the pofTeflion of a new gotten Miftrefs, to wake and finde my ielf
nooz'd to a dull wife in the morning.

Fill. Thou talkft like a man that never knew the pleaflires thou di£
pifeft ; faith try it Fran^nd thou wilt hate thy palt loofe way of living.

(or. And to encourage a young fetter up,/ do here promife to be the
molt Miftrifs like wife, — -you know Signior / have learnt the trade,
though /had not ftock to pra&ice, and will be as expenfive, /nfolent,
Vain Extravagant, and /nconltant, as if you only had the keeping
part, and another the Amorous Afignations, what think ye Sir.

Fill. Faith fhe pleads well 1 and ought to cary the caufe !

Gall. She fpeaks Reafon ! and Ane refolv'dtotruft good Nature *
— give me thy dear hand. — - [They alljoyn to give it him, he kjffes if.

Mur. And now you are both fpeed, pray give me leave to ask ye a
civil queftion ! are you fure you have been honeft, if you have 1 know
not by what Miracle you have liv'd .

Pet . Oh Sir as for that, I had a fmall ftock of cam, in the hands of
a cuple of Englifh Bankers, on Sir Signal Buffoon.

Sir Sig. Sir Signal Buffoon ! what a pox does he mean me trow.

C Peeping.

Pet.— And one Mr. Tick&etextl

Tick- How was that,- — >certo my Name !

£ Peeps out and both fee each other their faces, being ahfe together one
at one fide the Curtain, and t other at tother,

GtlLaadFiU. Ha ha ha! v . Six Sig.



Or, A Nights Intrigue, jt

Sir Sig. And have I caught you efaith Mr, Governor !
Nay nere put in your head for the matter, here's none but friends mun /

Gall. How now what have we here !

Sir Sig. Speak of the devil and he appears !

\_ Pulls his Governor forward,

Tkkj Iamnndone! — but good 'Sir Signal do not cry whore iirft ! as
the old proverb fays /

Sir Sig. And good Mr. Governor, as another old proverb fays, do
not let the kettle call the Pot black-ars !

Fill. How came you hither Gentlemen/

SirS*£. Whe/ faith Sir divining of a wedding or two forward, I
brought Mr. Chaplain to give you a call of his Office, as the faying is.

Fill. What without Book Mr. Tickjetext^

Cor. How now .' fare you miftake, thefe are two Lovers of mine.

Sir Sig. How Sir your Lovers ! we are none of thole Sir, we are Eng-
lishmen !

Gall. You miftake Sir Signal, this is Silvianetta !

Sir5^.and7ltc^. How/ [Afide,

Gall. Here's another fpark of your acquaintance,-do you know him;

Tick. How Barhracbo ! nay then all will out. — ■

Gall. Yes, and your fencing and Civility-Mafter.

Sir Sig. Ay, — whe what was it you that pickt our pockets then,—
and cheated us !

Gall. Moft damnably, — but fince 'twas for the fuppiy of two fair
Ladys, . all mall be reftor'd again.

Tick, Some comfortthat.

Fill. Come lets in and forgive all, 'twas but one Nights Intrigue, in
which all were a little faulty /

Sir Sig. And Governor, pray let me have no more dominering and
Ufurpation ! But as we have hitherto been honeft Brothers in iniquity,,
fo let's wink hereafter at each others frailties !
Since Love and women eafily betrajrman,
Erom the grave Gown-man to the bufy Lay-mam .



■



. -



■' Mi •v. v. ■ i \ .'■.,•: : ; '■'■■, . . ..

3 " ~ ' T



» EPl L O Gil E,

i '

Spoken by Mr. Smith.



SO hard the 'Times are, andfo thin the Town,
Though bnt one Playhoufe, that mnft too lie down %
And when we fail what will the Poets do}
They live by us as we are kept by yon :
When we disband, they no more Tlays will write ;
'But make Lampoons, and Libellye infpigh't - r
Difcover eachfalfe heart that lies within.
Nor <iJMan nor Woman Jhall in private fin ;
Theprecife whoring Husbands haunts betray, ~J
Which the demurer Lady to repay, >

Jn his own coin does thejufi debt defray. J

The -briskjyoung Beauty linkt to Lands and zAge,
• M \\ Shuns the dull property, and flrokes theyouthfull Page ;

And if the fir ipling apprehend not foon,
Turns him afide and takes [he brawny Groom,
Whilfl thekinde manfe true a Husband proves,
To think^all' swell done by the thing he loves ;
Knows his a Cuckold, yet content to bear
What 'ere Heaven fends, or horns or lufiy heir ;
Fops of allforts he draws more artfully,
Then ever on the Stage did Nokes or Leigh :
zAnd Heaven he praised when thefe are fear ce, each Brother
O'thpen, contrive tofet on one another :

Thefe are the ejfetls of angry Poets rage,
^Drivenfrom their Winter-Quarters on the Stage,
And when we go, our Women vanifo too,
What will the well-fiedg d keeping Gallant do ?
And where but here can he expect to finde, 7

A gay young Dam' fell managd to his minde, >
Who ruines him andyet feems wondrous kinde. ~»
One infolent and falfe, and what is worfe,
Governs his heart and manages his pur fe ;
tJMakes him whate^reflrfd have him to believe^
Spends his Efiate, then learns him how to live ;
J hope thefe weighty confiderations will
Move ye to keep us all together fiill ;
To treat us equal to our great defert,
<iAndpay your Tributes with a franker heart,
Jfnot, th'aforefaid Ills will come, and we mufi part.

FINIS.



-..-.,
