
Skip to main content

    Internet Archive Logo
    web
    books
    video
    audio
    software
    images
    search

    uploadUPLOAD
    personSIGN IN

    ABOUT
    CONTACT
    BLOG
    PROJECTS
    HELP
    DONATE
    JOBS
    VOLUNTEER
    PEOPLE

Full text of "Marriage a-la-mode. A comedy. As it is acted at the Theatre-Royal. Written by John Dryden, servant to His Majesty"
See other formats

Digitized by the Internet Archive

in 2011 with funding from

LYRASIS Members and Sloan Foundation



http://www.archive.org/details/marriagealamodecOOdryd



MA





i






A-la-Mode.

A

C O M E D Y.

AskisAdtedatthe
THEJTR E-RO Y A L.



Written by JOHN DKYDENy Servant
to His Majefty.



.< — Quicquidfnm ego, quamms

Infra Lucilli cenfum ingeniumque, tamen me
Cum magnk vixijfe, invito, fatebitur ufque
Invidia, &* fr a gili qntfrens iUidere dentem
Offendetfolido.

Horat. Serm.



LONDON,

Printed by T. N. for Henry Herringman, and are to be
fold at the Anchor in the Lower Walk of
the New Exchange. 1673.









34 1 r



CD



%15.




To the %ight Honourable,
The E a r l of

ROCHESTER.



My Lord,

Humbly Dedicate to Your Lord-
(hip that Poem , of which you
were pleas'd to appear an early
Patron* before it was A&cd on
the Stage. I any yet go fmher,
with your pennillion, and fay,
That it receiv'd amendment
from your noble hands, e're it was fit to be prefented.
You may pleale likewife to remember, with how
much favour to the Authour, and indulgence to the
Play, you commended it to the view of His Majefty,

B 2 then




then at Wind/or , and by His Approbation of it in
Writing, made way for its kind reception on the
Theatre. In this Dedication therefore, I may feem to
imitate a Cufiom of the Ancients, who offer'd to their
Gods the Fii filings of the Flock, which I think they
call'd Ver Sacrum^ becaufe they help'd 'em to increafe.
I am fure, if there be any thing in this Play, wherein
I have raised my felf beyond the ordinary lownefs of
my Comedies, I ought wholly to acknowledge it
to the favour* of being admitted into your Lordfhip's
Converfation. And not onely I, who pretend not to
this way, but the beft Comick Writers of our Age,
will joyn with me to acknowledge, that they have
eopy'd the Gallantries of Courts, the Delicacy of Ex-
preffion, and the Decencies of Behaviour, from your
Lordfhip, with more fuccefs, then if they had taken
their Models from the Court of France, JBut this, my
Lord 3 will be no wonder to the world, which
knows the excellencie of your Natural parts, and
thofe you have acquir'd in a Noble Education.
That which with more reafon I admire, is, that be-
ing fo abfolute a Courtier, you have not forgot,
either the ties of Friendfliip, or the praclife of Gene-
rofity. In my little Experience of a Court (which I
confefs I defire not to improve ) I have found in it
much of Intereft, and more of Detraction : Few men
there have that aflurance of a Friend, as not to be
made ridiculous by him, when they are abfent.
There are a midling fort of Courtiers, who become

happy



happy by their want of wit * hat they fupply that
want* by an excefs of malice to thofe who have it.
And there is no fuch perfecution as that of fools :
they can never be considerable enough to be talk'd
of themfelves } fo that they are fafe onely in their
obfcurity, and grow mifehievous to witty men, by
the great diligence of their envy, and by being al-
ways prefent to reprefent and aggravate their faults^
In the mean time they are forc'd, when they endea-
vour to be pleafant, to live on the Offalls of their
Wit, whom they decry, and either to quote it y
( which chey do unwillingly^ or to pafs it upon others
for their own. Thefe are the men who make it their
bufinefs to chafe Wit from the Knowledge of Princes,
left it (hould difgrace their ignorance. And this kind
of malice your Lordfliip has not fo much avoid ed ; as
fur mounted, But if by the excellent temper of a
Royal Matter, always more ready to hear good than
ill, if by his inclination to love you, if by your own
merit and addrefs, if by the charmes of your Con-
verfation, the Grace of your Behaviour, your know-
ledge of Greatnefs and Habitude in Courts, you
having been able to preserve your felf with Honour
in the midft of fo dangerous a Courfc ; yet atleaft
the remembrance of thofe Hazards has infpir'd you
with pity for other men, who being of an inferiour
Wit and Quality to you, are yet Perfecuted , for be*
ing that in Little, which your Lordfliip is in Great.
For the auarrel of thofe people extends k felf to any

thing



thing of fenfe \ and if I may be fo vain to own it
amongft the reft of the Poets, has fome tunes reach'd
to the very borders of it, even to me. So that, if our
general good fortune had not rais'dup your Lord-
(hip to defend us, I know not whether any thing had
been more ridiculous in Court, than Writers. 'Tis
to your Lordfhip's favour we generally owe our Pro-
tection and Patronage: And to the Noblenefs of
your Nature, which will not fuffer the leaft (hadow.
of your Wit to becontemn'd in other men. You
have been often pleas'd not onely to excufe my im-
perfections, but to vindicate what was tolerable in
my Writings from their cenfures And what I never can
forget,you have not onely been careful of my Repu-
tation, but of my Fortune. You have been Sollicitous
to fupply my negleft of myfelf; and to overcome
the fatal Modcfty of Poets, which fubmits them to
perpetual wants 3 rather then to become importunate
with thofe people, who have the liberality of Kings
in their difpodngj and who dimonouring the Bounty
of their Matter, fuffer fuch to be in necellky, who
endeavour at lead: to plealehim : and for whole en-
tertainment He has generoufly provided, if the Fruits
of His Royal favour were not often ftopp'din orher
hands. But your Lordihip has given me occafion,
not to complain of Courts, whii'il you are there. I
have found the effefts of your Mediation in all my
Concernments \ and they were fo much the more
noble in you, becaule they were wholly volunrny.

I became



I became your Lordfhip's (if I may venture on the
Similitude) as the world was made, without knowing
him who made it j and brought onely a paffi ve obe-
dience to be your Creature. This Noblenefs of yours
I think my felf the rather oblig'd to own, becaufe
otherwife it muft have been loft to all remembrance :
for you are endued with that excellent quality of a
frank Nature, to forget the good which you have
done.

But, my Lord, I ought to have confider d, that
you are as great a Judge, as you are a Patron • and
that in praifing you ill, I fhall incurre a higher note
of ingratitude, then that I thought to have avoided.
I ftand in need of all your accuftom'd goodnefs for
the Dedication of this Play : which though, perhaps,
it be the beft of my Comedies, is yet fo faulty, that I
(houldhave fear'dyou, for my Critfck,if I had not
with fome policy given you the trouble of being my
Proteflor. Wit feems to have lodg'd it felf more
Nobly in this Age, than in any of the former: and
people of my mean condition, are onely Writers,
becaufe fome of the Nobility, and your Lordfliip in
the firft place, are above the narrow praifes which
Poefie could give you. Butletthofe who lovetofee
themfelves exceeded, encourage your Lordfhipin fa
dangerous a quality : for my owl* part> I muft confefs,,
that I have fomuch of felf intereft, as to be content
with reading fome Papers of your Verfes * without
defiring you ftiould proceed to a Scene ©x Play : with



the common prudence of thofej who are worfted
in a Duel , and declare they are fatisfied when
they are firft wounded. Your Lord(hip has but ano-
ther ftep to make, and from the Patron of Wit, you
may become its Tyrant: and Opprefs our little
Reputations with more eafe then you now protect
them. But thefe, my Lord, are defigns, which I am
fore you harbour notj anymore then the French
King is contriving the Concjueft of the Swiffers. 'Tis
a barren Triumph, which is not worth yoUr pains ,
and wou'd onely rank him amongft your Slaves, who
is already,
b-j'biovs <

My Lord,






r .



Tour Lordjbips

■■''■•-■'
:

1

Moft obedient and mod

faithful Servant ,

■ - .

■ • r

John Dry den.

■

The





LOrd^ how reform d and quiet we are grown ,
Since all our Braves and all our Wits are gone :
F of -corner now is free from Civil War :
White- Wig and Vi%ard mahg no longer jar.
France? and the Fleet 5 havefwept the Townfo clear y
That we can AB ifi peace, and you can hear.
'Twas a fad fight, before they march' d from home y
To fee our Warriours, in Red Waftecoats, come,
With hair tucked up, into our Tireing-room.
But 'twas more fad to hear their lafi Adieu 9
The Women fob 9 d, andfwore they would be true ',
Andfo they were, as lon% as e're they coud: ,

But powerful Guinnee cannot be witbfiood, I

And they were made of Play houfeflefb and blond.
Fate did their Friends for double nfe ordain,
In Wars abroad^ they grinning Honour gain, )

And Mifireffes,for all thatjiay, maintain. *

a Now



Now they are gone, 'tis dead Vacation here r
For neither Friends nor Enemies appear.
Poor pen five Punhjtow peeps ere Plays begin,
Sees the bare Bench, and dares not venture in :
But manages her lali Half- crown with care.
And trudges to the Mall, on foot, for Air.
Our City Friends fo far will hardly come,
They can take up with Pleafures nearer home ;
And fee gay Shows, andgawdy Scenes elfewhere :
For weprefume they feldom come to hear.
But they have now tan up a glorious Trade,
And cutting Moor cr aft, flruts in Mafquerade.
There's all our hope, for we /hall (how to day,
A Mafquing Ball, to recommend our Play :
Nay^ to endear 'em more, and let 'em fee,
We fcorn to come behind in Courtefie,
We 11 follow the new Mode which they begin,
And treat 'em with a Room, and Couch within :
For t hat s one way, how ere the Play fall jhort,
T oblige the Town, the City } and the Court.



Perfons



;



■



,-~iS~^-- / -



Terfons Reprefented.
MEN.

By

Tolydamafo Ufurper of Sicily Mr. WmterfhalL

Leonidasytke Rightful Prince, un-? MrK ■ na fion.

known—- * •■ -S

Argaleon, Favourite to Tolydamas—- Mr. hydalh
Hermogenet, Fofter-father to Leo-} a f ^

nidas—- —-» ' ■ . — — y

Eubulu^i his Friend and Companion Mr. Watfon.
Rhodvphil, Captain of the Guards- - Mr. Mohutt,
Palamede, a Courtier ■ Mr. Hart,

WOMEN.

By
Palmyra, Daughter to the Ufurper* - Mrs. Coxe.

Amalthea, Sifter to Argakon Mrs. James.

Doralice^ Wife to Rbodopkil-*^ Mrs. MarfbalL

Melantha, an ArTefled Lady Mrs. BovetelL

Thilotis, Woman to Melantha Mrs. Reeve.

Belifa, Woman to Dor alice -Mrs. Slade.

Artemis, a Court-Lady-- .< -Mrs. VphilL

Scene, SIC1LIE.



MARRIAGE



ws*




I A G E



/\— let—




.



ACT I. SCENE I.

Wallas near the Court.



tier.




Enter Doralice and BeliZa.

Eliza, bring the Lute into this Arbor 3 the Walks
are empty : I would try the Song the Princefs
Amalthea bad me learn. 7 hey go w andjfng*



i.



WHyJhould afooliJI) Marriage Vow
Which long ago was made^
Oblige us to each other now
When Tajjicn is decay 3 d?
We lovd, and we Icv'dj as longaswecoud^

Till our love was hvd cut in us both:
But cur Marriage is dead when the Vleafire is
'Twos Pleafurefirft made it an Oath*



B



tf



% Marriage aAa-Mode*

jf I have Tleafures for a Friend^

And farther love infiore^
What wrong has he whofe joys did end,

And who coudgive no more ?

'Tk a. madnef that he

should be jealous of me,

Or that Ijhowd bar him of another :

For all we can gain ,

Is to give our felves pain,

When neither can hinder the other.

Enter Palamede, in Riding Habit, and hears the Songs-
Re- enter Doralice and Beliza.

Bel. Madam, a Stranger.

Dor* I did not think to have had witneiTesof my bad fing*
ing.

Tola. If I have err'd, Madam, I hope you'l pardon the curi-
ofity of a Stranger % for I may well call my felffo, after five
years abfence from the Court : But you have freed me from one
error.

Dor. What's that, I befeech you*

Tola. I thought good voices, and ill faces, had been infepa-
rable 5 and that to be fair and fing well, had been onely the
priviledge of Angels.

Dor. And how many more of thefe fine things can you fay
to me ?

Pala. Very few, Madam, for if I (hould continue to fee you
fome hours longer : You look fo killingly, that I (hould be
mute with wonder.

Dor. This will not give you the reputation of a Wit with me :
you travelling Monfieurs live upon the ftock you have got a-
broad, fbr.thefirft day or two : to repeat with a good memo-
ry, and apply with a good grace, is all your wit. And, com-
monly,



Marriage a4a*Mode. 3

monly, your Gullets are few'd up, like Cormorants* When
you have regorg'd what you have taken in, you are the leaned
things in Nature.

Pala. Then, Madam, I think you had bed make that ufe of
me «, let me wait on you for two or three days together, and you
(hall hear all I have learnt of extraordinary, in other Coun-
treys : And one thing which I never fawtill I came home, that
is, a Lady of a better voice, betterface, and better wit, than
any I have feen abroad. And, after this, if I (hould not declare
my felf moil: paffionately in love with you, I (hould have lefs
wit than yet you think I have.

Dor, A very plain, and pithy Declaration* I fee. Sir, you
have been travelling in Spain or Italy ^ or fome of the hot Coun-
treys, where men come to the point immediately. But are you
fure thefe are not words of courfe? For I would not give my
poor heart an occafionof complaint againftme, that I engag'd it
toorafhly, and then could not bring it off.

Pala, Four heart may truft it felf with me fafely 5 I fhall ufe
it very civilly while it flays, and never turn it away, without fair
warning to provide for it felf.

Dor, Firft, then, I do receive your paffion with as little con-
sideration, on my part, as ever you gave it me, on yours. And
now fee what a miferable wretch you have made your felf.

Pala, Who, I miferable ? Thank you for that. Give me love
enough, and life enough, and I defie Fortune.

Dor, Know then, thou man of vain imagination, know, to
-thy utter confufion, that I am vertuous.

Pala, Such another word, and I give up theghoft.

Dor. Then, to ftrike you quite dead;, know, that I am marry'd
too.

Pala. Art thou marry 'd $ O thou damnable vertuous Wo-
man ?

Dor. Yes, mi rry'd to a Gentleman } young, handfome, rich,
valiant, and with all the good qualities that will make you de-
fpair, and hang your felf.

Pala, Well, in fpight of all that, I'll love you : Fortune has
cut us out for one another } for I am to be marry'd within thefe
three days. Marry 'd pall: redemption, to a young, fair, rich, and

B 2 vertuous



i Marriage a4a*Mode.

vettuousLady : And, it (hall go hard, but I will lave, my Wife
as little, as I perceive you do your Husband.

Dor. Remember I invade no propriety : My fervant you ate
onely till you are marry 'd.

TaU. In the mean time., you are to forget you have a Hus-
band.

Dor. And you, that you are to have a Wife.

Bel. Afide to her Lady. O Madam, my Lord's juftat the end of
the Walks 5 and, if you make not hade, will difcover you.

Dor. Some other time, new Servant, we'll talk further of the
premiiTes 5 in the mean while, break not my firft commandment,
that is, not to follow me.

Tola, But where, then, (hall I find you again >

Dor. At Court. Yours for two days. Sir.

Paid. And nights, T befeech you. Madam.

Exit Doralice and Beliza.

TaU. Well, 1*11 fay that for thee, thou art a very dextrous
Executioner 5 thou haft done my bufinefs at one ftroke : Yet I

muft marry another and yet I muft love this 5 and if it

lead me into fome little inconveniencies , as jealoufies, and
duels, and death, and fo forth 5 yet while fweet love is in the
cafe. Fortune do thy worft, and avant Mortality.

Enter Rodophil, whofeemsj'pcakjng to one within.

Rho. Leave 'em with my Lieutenant, while I fetch new Or-
ders from the King. How? Valamedc ! Sees Valamedc.

Vala. Rhodophil /.

Rho. Who thought to have feen you in Sicily ?

Vala. Who thought to have found the Court fo far from
Syracufe .<?

Rho. The King beft knows the reafon of the progrefs. But
anfwer me, I befeech you, what brought you home from
travel?

Pala. The commands of an old rich Father.

Rho. And the hopes of burying him i

Mala. Both together, as you fee, have prevail'd on my good

nature.



Marriage aM-Mode, 5

aature. In few words. My old man has already marry 'd me ,
for he has agreed with another old man 3 as rich and as covetous
as himfelf } the Articles arc drawn, and I have given my con-
fent, for fear of being dif-inherited 5 and yet know not what
kind of woman I am to marry.

Rho, Sure your Father intends you fome very ugly wife 5 and
has a mind to keep you in ignorance , till you have (hot the
gulf.

Fala. J know not that 5 but obey I will, and mud.

Rho. Then, I cannot chufe but grieve for all the good Girls
and Curtizans of France and Italy : They have loft the moft
kind-hearted, doting, prodigal, humble fervant, in Europe.

Pala. All I could do in thefe three years, I ttay'd behind you,
was to comfort the poor Creatures, for the lofs of you. But
what's the reafon that in all this time, a friend could never
hear from you ?

Rho. Alafs, dear Falamede, I have had no joy to write, nor
indeed 1 to do any thing in the World to pleafeme : The greateft
misfortune imaginable is fain upon me.

Fala. Prithee, what's the matter >

Rho. In one word, Iammarry'd} wretchedly marry 'd $ and
have been above thefe two years. Yes, faith, the Devil has had
power over me, in fpight of my Vows and Refolutions to the
contrary.

Fala. I find you have fold your felf for filthy lucre 5 (he's
old, orill-condition'd.

Rho. No, none of thefe: I'm fure fhe's young 5 and, for her
humor, (he laughs, rings, and dances eternally 5 and, which is
more, we never quarrel about it, for I do the fame.

Fala. You're very unfortunate indeed : Then the cafe isplain,
(he is not handfome.

Rho. A great beauty too, as people fay.

Fala. As people fay ? Why, you (hould know that beft your
fel£

Rho. Ask thofe, who have fmelt to a ftrong perfume two years
together, what's the fcent.

Fala, But here are good qualities enough for one wo-
man.

Rho



6 Marriage aM-Mode.

Rho. . Ay, too many, Pahimedejf I could put 'em into three or
four women, I (hould be content.

rda. O, now I have found it, you diflike her for no other
reafon, butbecaufe fhe's your wife.

Rho. And is not that enough? All that I know of her per-
fections now, is only by memory ; I remember, indeed, that
about two years ago I lov'd her pafiionately 5 but thofe golden
days are gone, PaUwede : Yet I lov'd her a whole half year,
double the natural term of any Miftrefs, and think in my con-
science I could have held out another quarter 5 but then the
World began to laugh at me, and a certain fhame of being out
of fafhion, feiz'd me : At laft, we arrived at that point, that there
was nothing left in us to make us new to one another : yet (till
I fet a good face upon the matter, and am infinite fond of her
before company 5 but, when we are alone, we walklike Lions
in a room, (he oneway, and I another: and we lie with our
backs to each other fo far diftant, as if the famionof great Beds
was onely invented to keep Husband and Wife fufficiently
afunder.

Pala. The truth is, your difeafeis very defperate ♦, but,though
you cannot be cur'd, you may bepatch'dupalittle} youmuftget
you a Mi ftrefs, Rhodophil : that, indeed, is living uponCordials,
but, as fi(t as one fails, you mu(t fupply it with another. You're
like aGamefler, who has loft his eftate 3 yet, indoingthat, you
have learn'd the advantages of Play, and can arrive to live
upon't.

Rho, Truth is, I have been thinking on't, and have juft re-
folv'd to take your counfel 3 and, faith, confidering the damn'd
difadvantages of a marry d man, I have provided well enough,
for a poor humble (inner, that is not ambitious of great
matters.

PaU, What is (he ; for a Woman?

Rho. One of the Stars of Syracufc , I affure you : Young
enough, fair enough , and, but, for one quality , Juft fuch a
woman as I would wifh.

Pala^ O Friend, this is not an age to be critical in Beauty :
when we had good (tore of handiome women , and but few
Chapmen, you might have been more curious in your choice;

but



^Marriage a4a*Mode. J

but now the price is enhanc'd upon us, and all Mankind fet up
for' MiftrefTes, fo that poor little creatures, without beauty,
birth, or breeding, but onely impudence, go offat unreafonable
rates." and a man, in thefe hard times, fnaps at em, as he does
at Broad-gold, never examines the weight, but takes light, or
heavy, as he can get it.

Rho, But my Miftris has one fault that's almofi; unpardonable 3
for, being a Town-Lady, without any relation to the Court, yet
(he thinks her felf undone, iffhebenotfeen there three or four
times a day, with the Princefs Amalthea. And for the King, fhe
haunts, and watches him fo narrowly in a morning, that (he pre-
vents even the Chymifts who befet his Chamber, to turn their
Mercury intohisGold.

Pala. Yet, hitherto, me-thinks, you are no very unhappy man.

Rho. With all this, (he's the greateft Goffip in Nature, for,
befides the Court, (he's the moft eternal Vifiter of the Town ::
and yet manages her time fo well, that fhe feems ubiquitary.
For my part, I can compare her to nothing but the Sun 5 for^
like him, (he takes no reft, nor ever fets in one place, but to rife:
in another.

Tala. I confefs (he had need be handfome with thefe qualities. .

Rho, No Lady can be fo curious of a new Fafhion, as (he is of
a new French-word 5 (he's the very Mint of the Nation 5 and ?
as faftas any Bullion comes out of France , coins it immediately,
into our Language.

Pala, And her name is

Rho. No naming 5 that's not like a Cavalier :
Find her, if you can, by my defeription j and I am not To ill a--
painter, that I need write the name beneath the Pidture.

PaU. Well, then, how far have you proceeded in your love ? '

Rho. 'Tis yet in the bud, and what fruit it may bear I cannot
tell 5 for this infurTerable humour, of haunting the Court, is fo
predominant, that fhe has hitherto broken all her aflignations »
with me, for fear of miffing hervifits there.

Pala. That's the hardeft part of your adventure r but,
for ought Tfee, Fortune has us'd us both alike 5 I have a (Irange ■*
kind of Miftris too in Court, befides her I am to marry.

Rho, You have made hafte to be in love then > - for, if I am \

nott



8 Marriage aAa-Mode.

not miflaken, you are but this day arriv'd.

rata. That's all one, I have feen the Lady already, who has
charm'd me, feen her inthefe Walks, courted her, and receiv'd,
for the firft time, an anfwer that does not put me into defpair.

to them ; Argaleon., Amalthea, Artemis.

I'll tell you at more leifure my adventures. The Walks fill
apace, I fee. Stay, is not that the young Lord Argaleen^ the
Kings Favourite?

Rho. Yes,and as proud as ever,as ambitious,and as revengeful.

Tala. How keeps he the Kings favour with thefe qualities >

Rho. Argaleon s father help'd him to the Crown : befides, he
gilds overfall his vices to the King, and, (landing in the dark to
him, fees all his inclinations, interefts and humours, which he
fo times and foofhs, that, in efFefr, he reigns.

Tala. His fitter Amalthea^who^l ghefs, ftands by him, feems not
to be of his temper.

Rho. O, (he's all goodnefs and generofity.

Arga. Rhodophil, the King, expects youeameftly.

Rho. 'Tis done, my Lord, what he commanded : I onely wait-
ed his return from Hunting. Shall I attend your Lordfttp to
him ?

Arga. No } I go firft another way. [Exit hajltly,

Tala. He feems in hafte, and difcompos'd.

Amal. to EUiod. after afiort rvhijper. Your friend ? then he
muft needs be of much merit.

Rho. When he has kis'd the King's hand, I know he'll beg the
honour to kifs yours. Come 3 Fatamede,

Exeunt Rhodo. andPzh. bowitigto AmaL

Arte. Madam, you tell me mod furprifing news.

Amal The fear of it, youfee,
His difcompos'd my brother j but to me
All that can bring my Country good, is welcome.

Arte. Tt feems incredible, that this old King
Whomallthe world thought chi!dlefs,
Should come to fearch the fartheit parts of Sftttyy
In hope to find an Heir.

AmaL



Marriage a. la-Mode. 9

Amd.To lefTen your aftonifhment, I will
Unfold forae private paflages of State,
Of which you yet are ignorant : Know, flrft,
That thi? Folydamas, who Reigns, unjuftly
Gain'd the Crown.

Arte. Somewhat of this I have confus'dly heard.

Amal. I'll tell you all in brief: Theagenes,
Our la ft great King,

Had, by his Queen, one onely Son, an Infant
Of three years old, calFd, after him, Theagenes $
The General, this Volydamm^ then marri'd :
The publick Feaftsfor which were fcarcely paffc.
When a Rebellion in the heart of Sicily
Call'd out the King to Arms. ,

Arte, • —Tclydamas

Had then a juft excufe to ftay behind .

Amd. His temper was too warlike to accept it :
He left his Bride, and the new joys of marriage,
And folio w'd to the Feild. In Ihort, they fought.
The Rebels were o'rcome \ but in the Fight
The too bold King receiv'd a mortal wound.
Whenheperceiv'd his end approaching near.
He call'd the General, towhofe care he left
His Widow Queen, and Orphan Son 5 then dy'd-

Arte, Thenfalfe Polydamas betray'd histruft?

Amd. He did j and with my father's help, for which
Heav'n pardon him, fo gain'd the Soldiers hearts,
That in few days he was faluted King:
And when his crimes had impudence enough
To bear the eye of day, * :
He march'd his Army back to Syracnfe.
But fee how heav'n can punifh wicked men
In granting their defires : the news was brought him
That day he was to enter it, that Eubulm^,
Whom his dead Matter had left Governour,
Was fled, and with him bore away the Queen,
And Royal Orphan ■$ but, what more amaz'd him,
His wife, now big with child; and much detefting

C Her



io Marriage a-U'Mode*

Her husband's prafrifes, had willingly
Accompani'd their flight.

Arte, How I admire her vertue I

Awal ■ .What became

Of her, and them, fince that, was never known 3
Onely, fomc few days fince, a famous Robber
Was taken with fome Jewels of vail: price,
Which, when they were delivered to the King,
He knew had been his Wife's 3 with thefe, a Letter,
Much torn, and fulli'd, but which yet he knew
To be her writing.

Arte. . — Sure from hence he leam'd

he had a Son.

AmaL- It was not leftfo plain/

The Paper onely faid,lhe dy'd in childbed :

Eut when it fhould have mention'd Son, or Daughter,

Juft there it was torn off.

Arte. »» Madam, the King,

to them Polydamas, Argaleon, Guards and Attendants.

Arga. The Robber, though thrice Rack'd, confefs'd no mor^
But that he took thofe Jewels near this place.

Poly. But yet the circumftances ftrongiy argue,
That thofe, for whom I fearch, are not far off*

Arga. I catinot eafily believe it-

Arte. No,

You would not have it fo. [afide.

Voly. Thofe I employ'd, have, in the neighbouring Hamletr,
Amongft the Fiflbers Cabins, made difcovery
Of fome young perfons, whofe uncommon beauty,
And graceful carriage, make it feem fufpicious
Theyarenot whatthey feem : I therefore fent
The Captain of my Guards, this morning eirly,.
With orders to fecure and bring 'em to me,-

E/itct
*-\



Marriage aM+Mode. h

Enter Rhodophil and Palamede.

C here he is. Have you perform s d my will ?

Rho. Sir, thofe whom you commanded me to bring 3
Are waiting in the Walks.

Poly, — ■ — — — -— Conducl 'em hither.

Rho, Firftj give me leave
Tobegyour notice of this Gentleman.

Poly. He feems to merit it. His name and quality ?
Rho, Palamede^ fon to Lord Cleodemm of Palermo,
And new returned from travel.

^^mtdQapproaches^and kneels tokjfsthe Kings hand.

Poly. « — «- " You 're welcome.

I knew your father well, he was both brave
And honed 3 we two once were fellow-foldiers
In the lad Civil Wars.

Tola. I bring the fame unqneftion'd honefty
And zeal to ferve your Majefty , the courage
You werepleafed to praife in him.
Your Royal prudence, and your Peoples love,
Will never give me leaveto try like him
In Civil Wars, I hope it may in Foreign.

Poly, Attend the Court, and it (hall be my care
To find out fome employments worthy you.
Go ? -Khodophil 9 and bring in thofe without.

-[Exeunt, Rho, & Pala,

Rhodophil returns again immediately \and with him
Enter Hermogenes, Leonidas, and Palmyra.

Behold two miracles / C Looking ehrnefily on

Of different fexes, but of equal form : {Lzoxx.ahd Palmyra.

Somatehlefsboth, that my divided foul

Canfcarce!y afk the Gods a Son, or Daughter,

For fearof lolmgone. If from your hands.

You Powers, I (hall this day receive a Daughter,

Argaleon, (he is yours 5 but, if a Son,

C 2 Then



i% Marriage a 4a- Mode.

Then Amalthcas love (hall make him happy.

Arga. Grant, heavn, this admirable Nymph may prove
That ilTue which he feeks.

Amal. Venus Vrania, if thou art a Goddefs,
Grant that fvveet Youth may prove the Prince of Sicily,

P^.Tell me,old man, and tell me true,from whence [to Her,
Had you that Youth and Maid )

Her. t From whence you had

Your Scepter, Sir : I had 'em from the Gods.

Toly*. The Gods then have notfach another gift.
Say who their Parents were.

Her. . -My Wife, and I

Arga. It is not likely, a Virgin of fo excellent a beauty
Should come from fuch a Stock.

Amal. Much lefs, that fuch a Youth, fo fweet, fogracefu-ij
Should be produc'd from Peafants.

Her. Why, Nature is the fame in Villages,
A ad mucbmore fit to form a noble ifliie
Where it is lead: corrupted.

Voly. He talks, too like a man that knew the world
To have been long a Peafant. But the Mack
Will teach him other language. Hence with him.

\_Asthc Guar dare carrying him atoafi his Ferrule falls offl.
Sure I have feen that face before. Uermogenes I
'Tishe, 't'she whofled away with Eubulus^
And with my dear Eudoxia.

Her. Yes, Sir, I am Hermogencs.
And if to have been loyal be a crime.,
I (land prepared to fuffer.

Voly. If thou would ft live, fpeak quickly,
W hat is become of my Eudoxia ?
Where is the Queen and young Thea,gctics .<?
W here Eubulm i and which of thefe is m ine ? (rointing to Leon.

Her. Eudoxia is dead, fo is the Queen, \ and Palm.

The infant King herfon,and Eubulus.

Toly. Traitor, 'tis falfe: produce 'era, or— — •

Hir. - — ■— ■ , , Once more

$ tell you, they are dead 5 but leave to threaten,

For



Marriage aM-Mode. re

For you (hall know no further.

Poly, Then prove indulgent to my hopes, and be
My friend for ever. Tell me, good Hermogenes^
Whole Son is that brave Youth }

Her Sir, he is yours.

P0/7.FOQI that lam, thou fee'ft that fo I with it,
And fo thouflatter'ft me.

Her, r By all that's holy.

Poly, Again. Thou canft not (wear too deeply ,'..
Yet hold, 1 will beleive thee : — — yet Idoubt.

Her, You need not, Sir.

Argil, Beleive him not 3 he fees you credulous,
And would impofehis own bafe iflue on you,
And fix it to your Crown.

AmaL Behold his goodly Chape and feature. Sir,
Methinks he much refembles you.

Arga. I fay, if you have any iflue here,.
It mult be that fair creature 5
By all my hopes I think fo.

AmaL Yes, Brother, 1 believe you by yoar hopes.
For rhey are all for her.

Poly Call the Youth nearer.

Her. Leonidas^ the King would fpeak v^ith you„

Poly t Comenear,and be notdazled with the fplendor^
And greatnefs of a Court.

Leon. I need not this incouragement,
lean fear nothing but the Gods.
And for this glory, after I have feen
The Canopy of State fpread wide above
In the Abyfs of Heaven, the Court of Stars,
The blulhing Morning, and the riling Su^
What greater can I fee ?

Poly 4 This fpeaks thee born a Prince, thou art (Embracing,
thy felf \hi#J»

That riling Sun, and (halt not fee on earth,

A brighter then thy felf. All of you witnefsj.

That for my fon I here receive this Youth,

This brave, this » ■■ ■ but I jriuft not praife him ftifther>

Beeaufe,



j^ Marriage ^4a-Mode.

Becaufe he now is mine.

Leon, I wonnotj Sir, believe [Jipeelwg,

That I am made your fport 5
Fori find nothing in my felf, but what
Is much above a (corn h -I dare give credit
To whatfoe'r a King, like you, can tell me.
Either I am, or will deferve to be your Son.

Arga, I yet maintain it is impoflible
This youngman fhould be yours > for, iFhe were.
Why fhould HermagenesCo long conceal him
When he might gain fo much by his difcovery?

Her, I ftay'd a while to make him worthy, STo the

Si r D of you. iKing;

But in that time I found

Somewhat within him;, which Co movM my love,
I never could refolve to part with him,

Leon, You afk too many queftions, and are [To Argaleon.
Too fawcy for afubjecl:.

Arga. You rather over-adl your part, and are
Too foon a Prince.

Leon. Too foon you'l find me one.

Poly, Enough, Argaleon 5
I have declar'd him mine: and you, Leonidas^
Live well with him I love.

Arga. Sir, if he be your Son, 1 may have leave
To think 5 our Queen had Twins 3 look on this Virgin }
Hermogcnes would envioufly deprive you
Of half your treafure.

Her. > — Sir, (he is my daughter.

I could, perhaps, thus aided by this Lord,
Prefer her to be yours 5 but truth forbid
Ifhouk! procure her greatnefs by a Lie.

Poly. Come hither, beauteous Maid : are you not forry
Your father will not let you pafs for mine?

Palm. I am content to be whatheav'n has made me.

Poly. Could you not wjfh your felfa Princefs then .?

Palm. Not to be Sifter to Leouidm.

Poly. Why, my fweet Maid ?

PaIpj.



tSMarridge a4tuMode. 15

Taint* Indeed I cannot tell 3

But I could be content to be his Handmaid.

Arga. I with I had notfeen her. [ Ajtde.

Palm, I muft weep for your good fortune 5 £ to Leonidas.
Pray pardon me, indeed I cannot help it.

Leonidas^ (alas, 1 had forgot,
Now I muft call you Prince) but muft I leave you ■>

Leon. 1 dare not fpeak to her 5 for if I fhould, £ Afide,

I muft weep too.

Voly. No, you (hall live at Court P fweet Innocence^
Andfee him there. Hermogenes^
Though you intended not to make me happy^
Yet you (hall be rewarded for th'event.
Come, my Leonidas , let's thank the Gods 5
Thou for a Father, I for fuch a Son. [Exeunt all bnP

Leonidas and Palmyra.

Leon. My dear Taimyr a^ many eyes obferve me.
And I have thoughts fo tender, that I cannot
In publick fpeak 'em to you: fome hours hence
I (hall (hake offthefe crowds of fawning Courtiers,
And then ! - [Exit Leonidas; ._

Talm. Fly fwift ; you hours,you meafure time for me in vain.
Till you bring back Leonidas again.
Befhorternow 5 and to redeem that wrong.
When he and I are met, be twice as long. [Exit,



ACT IL SCENE L

Melantha and Philotk

fhil. f^Ount Rhodophil's a fine Gentleman indeed. Madam 5
V_y and I think deferves your affection.
Mel. Let me die but he's a fine man % he fin gs, and dances
' en



t6 Marriage a*la-Mode.

en Francois, and writes the Billets dmx to 3 miracle-

Phil. And thofe are no fmall tallents, to a Lady that under-
ftands,and values the French ayr, as your Ladifhipdoes.

Mel. How charming is the French ayr I and what an etonrdy
bete is one of our untravel'd Iflanders ! when he would make his
Courtto me, let me die, but he is juft JEfop's Afs, that would
imitate the courtly French in hisaddreffes } but, in (lead of thofe,
comes pawing upon me, and doing all things fo mal a droitly,

Phil. Tis great pity Rhodophil's a married man, that you may
not have an honourable Intrigue with him,

Hid, Intrigue, Philotis ! that's an old phrafe $ I have laid that
word by : Amour founds better. But thou art heir to all my caft
words, as thou art to my old Wardrobe. Oh Count Rhodophil !
Ah mon cherl I could live and die with him,

■"Enter Palamede and a Servant,

Ser. Sir, this is my Lady.

Pala. Then this is (he that is to be Divine, and Nymph, and
; Coddefs,and with whom I am to bedefperately i^love.

£ Bows to her, delivering a Letter,

This Letter, Madam, which fprefentyou from your father,
has given me both the happy opportunity, and the boldnefs, to
kifs the fairefi hands in Sicily.

Mel, Came you lately homPalermo, Sir }

Fata. But yefterday, Ma9am.

Mel, Q Reading the Letter] Daughter, receive the bearer of this
Letter ) as a Gentleman whom 1 have chofin to make you happy y
( O Venm ', a new Servant fent me ! and let me die but he has the
ayre of a gallant homme) his father is the rich Lord Cleodemus,
our neighbour : ifuppofe you I find nothing difagreeable in hif per-
fin or his converfe 5 both which he has improv d by travel. The Trea-
ty is already concluded^ and I pall be in Town within thefe three
days 5 fi that you have nothing to do^ but to obey your careful
Father.

C^Pala.) Sir, my Father, for whom I have a blind obe-
dience*



Marriage a- la-Mode* 17

3ience,ha| commanded me to receive your paffionate addreffes,
butyoumufl: alfo give me leave to avow, that I cannot merit
'em, from fo accomplifh'd a Cavalier.

TaU. I want many things, Madam, to render meaccompliuYd}
and the firfl: and greateft of 'em, is your favour.

Mel. Let me die, vhilotis, but this is extremely French *■> but

yet Count Bhodofhil A Gentleman, Sir, that un-

derftands theOvwd^Wfowell, who has hanted thebeft con-
ventions, and who (in (hort) has voyag'd, may pretend to the
good graces of any Lady.

Tola, ^ffde) Heyday ! Grandmond! converfaUon I voyagdl
and good graces \ I .find my Miftris is one of thofe that tun mad
in new Trench words.

Mel. Ifuppofe, Sir, you have made the tour of France 5 and
having feen all that's fine there, will make a confiderable re-
formation in the rudenefs of our Court : for, let me die., but
an unfafhion'd, untravel'd, meer Sicilian^ a Bete 5 andhas no-
thing in the world of an honete homme.

Tula. I muftconfefs. Madam, that -

Mel. And what new Mi nonets have you brought over with
you! their Minouets are to a miracle ! and our 'Sicilian Jigs are
to dull and fad to 'em !

Tala. For Minouets , Madam ~

Mel. And what new Plays are there in vogue? and who
danc'd beft in the lafl: Grand Ballet > Come, fweet Servant,
you (hall tell me all.

Tala. (Afide) Tell her all ? why, fheafksall, and will hear

nothing To anfwer in order, Madam, to your demands—

Mel. I am thinking what a happy couple we (hall be ! for you
(hall keep up your correfpondence abroad, and every thing
that's new writ, in France, and fine, I mean all that's deiicate ?
and bun tovme, we will have firft.

Tala. But, Madam, our fortune

Mel. I underftand you. Sir j you'l leave that to me: for the
mennage of a family, I know it better then any Lady in Sicily,
Tala. Alas, Madam, we — 1 —

Md. Then, we will never make vifits together, nor fee a
Play, but always apart j you (hall be every day at the King's

D LtvL



iS Marriage 4 Ja* Mode.

L ev^ and I at the Queen's 5 and we will never meet, but in the
Drawing-room.

Phil. Madam, thenew Prince is juftpafs*d by the end of the
Walk.

Mel. The -new 'Prince, fay'ftthou? Adieu, dear Servant 5 I
ha ve not made my court to him thefe two long hours. O, 'tis

thefweeteft Prince ! fo obligeant, charmant, raviffant, that

Well, I'll make hafte to kifs his hands 5 and then make half a
fcore vifits more, and be with youagain in a twinkling.

{Exit, running with Philotis.

Pala. ( Solus ) Now heaven, of thy mercy, blefs me from this
tongue ; it may keep the field againft a whole Army of
Lawyers^ and that in their own language, French Gihberijfj.
Tis true, in the day-time, 'tis tolerable, when a man has field-
room to run from it •-> but, to be (hut up in a bed with her, like
two Cocks in a pit 5 humanity cannot fupportit: I muft kifs
all night, in my own defence, and hold her down, like a Boy
at cuffs, nay, and give her the rifing blow every time (he begins
to fpeak.

Enter Rhodophih

But here comes Rhodephil. 'Tis pretty odd that my Miftris
fhould fo much refemble his : the fame News-monger, the fame

paffionate lover ofa Court, the fame ■ But Bajla^ fince I

mull: marry her 9 I'll fay nothing, becaufe he (hall not laugh at
my misfortune.

Rho* Well, Palamede^ how go the affairs of love? You've
feen your Miftris ?

Pala. I have (o.

Rho. And how, and how? has the old Cupid^ your Father,
chofen well for you < is he a good Woodman >

Pala. She's much handfomer then I could have imagin'd : In
fliort, I love her, and will marry her.

Rho. Then you are quite off from your other Miftris ?

Pala. You aremiftaken. I intend to love'em both, as a rea-
sonable man ought to do. For,finceall women have their faults,
and imperfecliaais/tis fit that one of 'era (hould help out t'other.

Rho.



Marriage a Ja<> Mode, ip

Rhfi. This were a bleffed Do&rine, indeed, if our Wiv,es.
would hear it 3 but, they're their own enemies : if they would
fufFer us but now and then tn make excurfions* the benefit of
our variety would be theirs, inftead of one continue lazy,
tyr'd love, they would, in their turns, have twenty vigorous,
fre(hj and adtive loves.

Pata. And I would ask any of 'em 3 whether a poor narrow
Brook;, half dr r y thebeft part of the year, and running ever one
way, be to be compar'd to a lufty Stream, < that has Ebbs and
Flows? : -'' '.—

Rho, Ay 5 or is half fo profitable for Navigation }

Enter Dorahce, walking bj/ and reading,

Pala. Ods my life, Rhodophil> will you keep my counfel j
Rho, Yes; where s the fecret?

Pala, There 'tis. J^&bfoxwg Doralice.

I may tell you, as my friend,/^ fe^Scc. this is that verynu-
mencal Lady, with whom lam in love.

Rho* By all that's vertuous, my Wife ! [Afide*

Pala. You look ftrangely : how do you like her ? is (he not
veryhandfome?

Rho. Sure he abufes me. [Ajide.

Why the devil do you ask my judgment > [To him

Pala. You are fo dogged now, you think no man's Miftris

handfome, but your own. Come, you (hall hear her talk too}

fliehaswit, I affure you.

Rho. Thrs is too much, Palamede. [.Going bach^

Pala. Prethee do not hang back (6 1 of an old <PuI/wg J*
try'd Lover 3 thou art themoft bafhful fellow ! "}form

Dor. Were you fo near, and would not [Jookingufr

fpeak, dear Husband >

Pala, Husband, quoth a 1 1 have cut out a fine piece of work
formyfelf. \ . [Aftde.

Rho. Pray, Spoufe, how long have you been acquainted with
this Gentleman ?

Dor. Who, I acquainted with this Stranger ?
To my beft knowledge, I never faw him before.

D 2 Enter




io Marriage a4a<>Mode.

I

Enter Melantha, at the other end.

Pdla. Thanks, Fortune, thou haft help'd me; [Jftde*

Rho. Palawede, this muft not pafs fo r I muft know youfMi-
ftris a little better.

Tola. It (hall be your own fault elfe. Come, 1*11 introduce
you.

Rho* Introduce me! where? ^Pointing to Melantha, who

Lfwiftly pajjes over the Stages

Tata, There. To my Mi ftris.

Rho. Who > Melantha !

heavens., I did not fee her.

Fala r But I did : I am an Eagle where Hove 5

1 have feen her this half hour.

Dor. (Ajide.') I find he has wit, he has got offfo readily 5 but
it would anger me, if he fhould love Melantha.

Rho. (Aftde) Now I could e'en wifh it were my Wife he
lov'd : I find he's to be marri'd to my Miftris.

Pala. Shall I run after, and fetch her back again, to prefent
you to her?

Rho. No, you need not 5 1 have the honour to have fome fmall
acquaintance witfe her.

Pala. (Aftde.') O Jupite'ri what a blockhead was I not to find
it out ! My Wife that muft be, is his Miftris. I did a little fufpecl:
it before^ well, Imuftmarry her, becaufe (he's handfome, and
becaufel hate to be dis-inherited for a younger Brother, which
lam fure Ifhall he if I difobeys and yet I muft keep in with
R/jodophil} becaufe I love his W ife.

(Ti?Rhodo. ) Imuftdefire you to make my tfxcufe to your
Lady, if I have beenfo unfortunate tocaufe any miftake 5 and,
withall, to beg the honour of being known to her.

Rho. O, that's but reafon. Hark you^ Spoufe, pray look up-
on this Gentleman as my friend 5 whom, to my knowledge, you
have never feen before this hour.

Dor. I'm fo obedient a Wife, Sir, that my Husbands com-
mands (hall ever be a Law to me.

•

Enter-



Marriage a4a* Model 2r

Enter Melantha again, hafiily, andrms to embrace Doralice..

Mela. O, my dear, I was juft going to pay my devoirs to you 3
I had not time this morning, for making my Court to the King,
and our new Prince. Well, never Nation was fo happy, and all
that, in a young Prince 5 and he's the kindeft perfon in the
World to me, letme diejif he is not.

Dor. He has been bred up far from Court, and therefore--.

Mel. That imports not : Though he has not feen the Grand
mond^ and all that, let me die but he. has the air of the Court,
moft abfolutely.

Tola. But yet. Madam, he —

Mel. O, Servant, you can teftifie that I am in his good Graces,
Well, I cannot daylong with you, becaufe I have promised him

this Afternoon to -^ But hark you, my dear, I'll tell you

a Secret. Whifters to Doralice*

JLho, The Devil's in me, that I muft love this Woman. Afide*

Fala, The Devil's in me, that I muft marry this Woman,

Mak

Mel. Raifingher Voice. So the Prince and I But you muft

make a Secret of this, my dear, for I would not for the World
your Husband fhould hear it, or my Tyrant, there, that muft
be.

Tala. Well, fair impertinent, your whifper is not loft, we hear
you. AfidL-

Dor. lunderftand then, that—

Mel, V\\ te>l you, my dear, the Prince took me by the hand,
and prefs'd it al a derobbie b becaufe the Ring was near, made' the
douxyeux tome, and, z#J#itfe, faidathoufand Gallant^riesj on
let me die, my dear.

Dor. Then I am iureyou > ---■--'
jWe/. You are miftaken,mydear*.

Dor. What before I fpeak ?

Mel. But I know your meaning} you think, my dear, that!
affum'd fomething of fierte into my Countenance, to rebute him ;
bur, quite contrary, I regarded him, I know not how to exprefs
it in our dull Sicilian Language, d#&ayr wlpifflh aud faid no-
thing-



\i Mdrruge aAa-Mode.

thing but ad autn> ad 4*tfre,and that it was all grimace \ and would
notpafsuponme.

Enter Artemis : Melantha/ea her, and runs away
from Doralice.

to Aretemk, My dear, I muft beg your pardon, I was juft
making a loofe from Doralice, to pay my refpe&s to you : Let
me die, if I ever pafs time fo agreeably as in your company, and
if I would leave it for any Lady's in Sicily.

Arte. The Princefs Amalthea is coming this way.

Enter Amalthea : Melantha runs to her*

Ml. O dear Madam ! I have been at your Lodgings, in my
new Galeche, fo often, to tell you of a new Amour , betwixt
two perfons whom you would little fufpecl: for it , that, let me
die, if one of my Coach-horfes be not dead, and another quite
tyr'd, and funk under the fatigue.

Amah O^Melantha^ lean tell you news, the Prince is coming
this way.

Mel. The Prince, O fweet Prince I He and I are to

and I forgot it. Your pardon, fweet Madam, for my ab-

ruptnefs. Adieu, my dears. Servant, Redophil ■> Servant, Ser-
vant, Servant All. Exit running,
Amal, Rodophilt a word with you. Whifpers,
Dor. to Pala. Why do younot follow your Miftrefs, Sir?
Pala. Follow her > Why, at this rate (he'll be at the Indies
within this half hour.

Dor, However, if you can't follow her all day, you'll meet
her at night, I. hope }

Pala. But can you, in charity, fuffer me to be fo mortify 'd,
without affording me fome relief > If it be but topunifh that
fignof a Husband there 5 that lazy matrimony, thatdull infipid
tafte, who leaves fuch delicious fare at home, to dine abroad,
on worfe meat, and to pay dear for't into the bargain.

Dor. All this is in vain : Allure your felf, 1 will never admit
df any vifit from you in private,

Pala.



Marriage a*la*>Mode. 2|

Tata, That is to tell me, in other words, my condition is
defperate.

Dor* I think you in fo ill a condition, that I am refolved to
pray for you, this very evening, in the clofe Walk, behind the
Terras ■> for that's a private place, and therel am fure no body
will difturb my devotions. And fo, good-night, Sir. [Exit*

Fala, This is tne neweft way of making an appointment, I
ever heard of: let women alone to contrive the means 5 1 find
we are but dunces to *em. Well., I will not be fo prophane a
wretch as to interrupt her devotions .5 but to make em more
efre&ual, I'll down upon my knees, and endeavour to joyn my
own with em. [Exit*

Amah (to Rhodophil) I know already they do not love each
other j and that my Brother ad"ts but a iorc'd obedience to the
Kings commands j fo that, if a quarrel fhould arife betwixt the
Prince and him, I were moftmiferable on both (ides.

Rho. There (hall be nothing wanting in me. Madam, to pre-
vent fo fad a confequence.

Enter the King 9 Leonidas, the King whiff ers Amalthea.

{tohimfelf) I begin to hate this Tatamede, becaufe he is to
marry my Miftris^ yet break with him I dare not, for fear of
being quite excluded from her company. 'Tis a hard cafe
when a man muft go by his Rival to his Miftris : but 'tis at
worft but ufing him like a pair of heavy Boots in a dirty jour-
ney, after I have foul'd him all day, 111 throw him off at
night. [_ Exit.

Amal, Qto the King) This honour is too great for me to hope*

Poly. You fhallthis hour have theaffurance of it.
LeonldaS) come hither X you have heard,
I doubt not, that the Father of this Princefs
Was my mod faithful friend, while I was yet
A private man 5 and when I did affume
This Crown, he ferv dme in that highattempt.
You fee, then, to what gratitude obliges roe 5
Make your addreffes to her.

Leon. Sir, 1 am yet too young to bea Courtier 5

I&ouJ3



24. Marriage a-la-Mode.

I fhould too much betray my ignorance,
And want of breeding, to fo fair a Lady.

Amd. Your language fpeaks you not bred up in Defar-ts 9
But in the foftnefs of fome Afian Court,
Where luxury and eafe invent kind words.
To cozen tender Virgins of their hearts.

Voly. You need not doubt
But in what words foe're a Prince can offer
His Crown and Perfon, they will bereeeiv'd.
You know my pleafure, and you know your duty.
Leon, Yes, Sir, I fhall obey, in what lean.
Voly, In what you can, Leonidas .<? Confider,
He's both your King, and Father, who commands you.
-Befides, what is there hard in my injunction ?
Leon, 'Tis hard to have my inclination fore'd.
I would not marry. Sir $ and, when I do,
I hope you'll give me freedom in my choice.

poly. 'View well this Lady,
Whofe mind as much tranfeends her beauteous face.,
Asthatexcelsall others.

Amal, My beauty, as it ne'r could meritlove.
So neither can it beg : and, Sir, you may
Beleive that, what the King has offer'd yoa,
I (hould refufe, did I not value more
Your perfon then your Crown.

Leon, — Think it not pride 3

Or my new fortunes fweli me to contemn you 5
Think lefs, that I want eyes to fee your beauty 3
And leafl: of all think duty wanting in me
T'obey a father's will : but

Voly, — But what, Leomdas k

Forlmuftkaowyourreafon} andbefure
It be convincing too.

Leon. Sir, ask the Stars,

Which have impos'd love on us, like a fate.
Why minds are bent to one, and .fly another ?
As>k why all beauties cannot move all hearts >
For though there may

Be



Marriage aAa-Modt. if

Be made a rule for colour, or for feature ,
There can be none for liking.

Poly. LeonidaS) you owe me more
Then to oppofe your liking to my pleafure.

Leon* I owe you all things, Sir 5 but fomething to©
I owe myfelf.

Toly. You fhall difpute no more $ I am a King,
Andlwillbeobey'd.

Leon. You are a King, Sir j but you are no God >
Or if you were, you could not force my will.

Toly. But you are juft, you Gods j O you are juft, [Apde

In punching the crimes of my rebellion
With a rebellious Son !
Yet I can punifh him, as you do me.
Leonidat) there is no jetting with
My will : Ine'r had donefo much to gain
A Crown, but to be abfolute in all things.

Amal. O, Sir, be not fo much a King, as to
Forget you are a Father : Soft indulgence
Becomes that name. Though Nature gives you pow'r.
To bind his duty, 'tis with filken Bonds :
Command him, then, as you command yourfelf :
He is as,much a part of you, as are
Your Appetite, and Will, andthofe you force not.
But gently bend, and make 'em pliant to your R.eafon.

Toly. It may be I have us'd too rough a way :
Forgive me, my Leonidas 5 I know
I lie as open to the gufts of paffion,
As the bare Shore to every beating Surge .•
I will not force thee, now 3 but I intreat thee,
Abfolve a Father's vow, to this fair Virgin :
A vow, which hopes of having fuch a Son
Firftcaus'd.

Lem.Show not my difobcdience by your pray'rs.
Fori muft ftill deny you, though I now
Appear more guilty to my feif, than you :
1 havefome reafons, which I cannot utter,
That force my difobediencej yet I mourn

E To



%6 Marriage a4a-Mode^

To death, that the firft thing you e'r injoyn'dme,
Should be that onelyone command in Nature
Which I could not obey.

Poly. I did defcend too much below my felf
When I intreated him. Hence, to thy Defart,
Thou'rt not my Ton, or art not fit to be.

Amd. Great Sir, I numbly beg you, make not me [kneeling.
The caufe of your difpleafure. I abfolve
Your vow : far, far from me, be fuch defigns 5
So wretched a defire of being great,
By making him unhappy. You may fee
Something fo noble in the Prince his nature,
As grieves him more not to obey, then you
That you are notobey'd.

Toly .. Then, for your fake,

I'll give him one day longer, to confider

Not to deny 5 for my refolves are firm

As Fate, that cannot change. [Exeunt King and Amz\.

Leon. ■■ -And fo are mine.

Thisbeauteous Princefs^ charming as (he is.
Could never make me happy : I muft firft
Befalfeto my Palmyra, and. then wretched.
But* then, a Father's anger !
Suppofe hefhould recede from his own vow,
He never would permit me to keep mine.

Enter Palmyra 3 hrgdzon following ber 3 a little after.

See, (he appears!

I'll think no more of any thing, but her.
Yet I have one hour good ere I am wretched.
But, Oh! ArgaUon follows her ! fo night
Treads on the foot-fteps of a Winter's Sun,
And ftalks all-black behind him.

Falm O Leonidas,

( For I muft call you (till by that dear name )
Freemc from this bad man.

Leon, I hope he dares not be injurious to you.

Arga,



Marriage aAa-Mode, %y

Arga. I rather was injurious to my felf,
Then her.

Leon. That muftbe judg'dwhenl hear what you faid,

Arga. I think you need not give your felf that trouble :
It concern'd us alone.

Leon. You anfwer fawcily, and indire&Iy :
What intereft can you pretend in her ?

Arga, It may be. Sir , I made her fome expreflions
Which I would not repeat, becaufe they were
Below my rank, to one of hers.

Leon. What did hefay. Palmyra f

Valm. I'll tell you all : Firft, he began to look.
And then hefigh'd., and then he Iook'd again $
At laft, he faid my eyes wounded his heart :
And, after that, he talk'd of flames, and fires }
Andfuch ftrangewords^ thatlbeliev'd he conjur'd.

Leon. O my heart ! Leave me 3 Argaleon,

Arga. Come, fweet Palmyra^
I will inftruct you better in my meaning :
You fee he would be private.

Leon, — . Go your felf.

And leave her here.

Arga. Alas, (he's ignorant,

And is not fit to entertain a Prince.

Leon. Firft learn what's fit for you 5 that's to obey.

Arga. I know my duty is to wait on you,
A great King's Son, like you, ought to forget
Such mean converfe.

Leon. — What > a difputing Subjedt?

Hence 5 or my fword (hall do me juftice, on thee,

Arga Yet I may find a time — - (Going:

Leon. What's that you mutter, \jfiing after him,

Tofindatime?

Arga. -To wait on you again

(softly) In the mean while I'll watch you.

[_ Exit y and watches during the Scevc.

Leon. How precious are the hours of Love in Courts !
In Cottages, where Love has all the day,

E 2 Full,



2 8 Marriage a4a~Mode.

Full D andateafe, he throws it half away.
Time gives himfelf, and is not valu'd, there 5
But fells., at mighty rates, each minute, here.
There, he islazy,unemploy'd > and flow-,
Here, he's more fwi ft '•> and yet has moue to do.
So many of his hoursin publickmove.
That few arc left for privacy, and Love.

Talm. The Sun, methinks, fhinesfaint and dimly, here}
Light is not half fo long, nor half fo clear.
But, Oh ! when every day was yours and mine,
How early up ! what hafte he made to fhine !

Leon. Such golden days no Prince muft hope to fee 5
Whofe ev'ry Subject is more blefs'd then he.

Talm Do you remember, when their tafks were done.
How all the Youth did to our Cottage run ?
While winter-winds were whittling loud without,
Our chearful hearth wascircled round about :
With ftrokes in afhes Maids their Lovers drew.
And ftill you fell to me, and I to you.

Leon. When Love did of my heart poffefiion take,
I was fo young, my foul wasfcarce awake :
I cannot tell when firft I thought you fair 5
But fuck'd in Love, infenfibly as Ayre\

Talm. I know too well when firft my love began.
When, at our Wake, you for the Chaplet ran :
Then I was made the Lady of the May,
And, with the Garland, at the Goal did fray:
Still, as you ran, I kept you full in view?
I hop'd, and wifh'd,and ran., methought,foryou.
As you came near, I haftily did rife.
And ftretchd my arm out-right, that held the prize.
The cufrom was to kifs whom I fhould crown :
You kneel d'-> and, in my lap, your head laid down.
I bluftYd. and bluuYd, and did the kifs delay :
At laft, my Subjects fore'd me to obey 5
But, when I gave the Crown, and then the kifs,
I fcarce had breath to fay. Take that and this.

Icon. I felt ,the while, a plcaling kind of fmart 5

The



Marriage aM^Mode. %*

Tlie kifs went, tingling, to my very heart.
When it was gone, the fenfe of it did ftay > J?
Thefweetnefscling'd upon mylips all day, >
Like drops of Honey, loath to fall away. «a

Palm. Life, like a prodigal, gave all his ftore
To my firft youth, and now can give no more.
You are a Prince, and, in that high degree,
No longer muft converfe with humble me.

Leon. 'Twas to my lofs the Gods that title gave 5
A Tyrant's Son is doubly born a Slave;
He gives a Crown 5 but, to prevent my life
From being happy, loads it with a Wife.
Talm. Speak quickly , what have yourefolv'd to do \
Leon.To keep my faith inviolate to you.
He threatens me with exile, and with fhame,
To lofemy birth right, and a Prince his name 3
But there's a bl effing which he did not mean.
To fend me back to Love and You again.

Palm. Why was not la Princefs for your fake >
But Heaven no morefuch miracles can make;
And, fince That cannot. This muft never be 5
You (hall not lofe a Grown for love of me.
Live happy, and a nobler choice purfue ,
I ftiall complain of Fate } but not of you.

Leon. Can you fo eafily without me live )
Or could you take thecounfel which you give ^
Were you a Princefs would you not be true >
Palm. I would 3 but cannot merit it from you.
Leon. Did you not merit, as you do, my heart 5
Love gives efteem 5 and then it gives defert.
But if Ibafely could forget my vow,
Poorhelplefs Innocence, what would you do .<?

Palm. In Woods, and Plains, where firft my love began,
There would I live, retir'd from faithlefs man t

V d fit all day within fome lonely (hade.

Or that clofe Arbour which your hands have made:

V d feairch the Groves, and ev'ry Tree, to find
Where you had carv'dour namcsuponthe rind 1

Youe



}o Marriage a4a~Mode.

Your Hook, your Scrip, all that was yours, I'd keep,

And lay 'em by me when I went to fleep.

Thus would I live: and Maidens, when I die,

Upon my Hearfe white True-love-knots (hould tie :

And thus my Tomb (hould be infcrib'd above.

Here the forfaken Virgin r efts from love, i

Leon. Think not that time or fate fhall e'r divide

Thofe hearts, which Love and mutual Vows have ty'd :

But we muft part 5 farewell, my Love.

Talm, .Till when >

Leon. Till the next age of hours we meetagen.

Mean time we may

When near each other we in publick ftand.

Contrive to catch a look, or fteal a hand:

Fancy will every touch, and glance improve 5

And draw the mod fpirituous parts of Love.

Our fouls fitclofe,and filently within 5

And their own Web from their own Intrals fpin.

And when eyes meet far off, ourfenfe isfuch.

That Spider-like, we feel the tender'ft touch. [Exeunt*



X ACT III. SCENE I.

Enter Rhodophil, meeting Doralice^W Artemis.
Rhodophil and Doralicc embrace.
'W-$' <
Rho. Ti M Y own dear heart !

IV J Dor. My own true love ! [shejfarts back.

I had forgot myfelfto be fo kind 5 indeed I am very angry
with you, dean you arc come home an hour after you ap-
pointed: If you had (laid a minute longer, I was juft consider-
ing, whether I (hould (tab, hang, or drown my felf.

£ Embracing him.

Rho. Nothing but the King's bufinefs could have hinder'd

me 5 and I was fo vext, that f. was juft laying down my Com-

miffion,



miflion, rather then have fail'd my Dear. [j&Sftng for hand.

Arte* Why, this is love as it (hould be, betwixt Man and
Wife : fuch another Couple would bring Marriage into fathi-
on again. But is it always thus betwixt you }

Rho, Always thus ! this is nothing. I tell you there is not
fuch a pair of Turtles in all Sicily 5 there is fuch an eternal
Cooing and killing betwixt us, that indeed it is fcandalous be-
fore civil company.

Dor. Well, if I had imagin'd, I (hould have been this fond
fool ; I would never havemarri'd the manllov'd: Imarri'dto
be happy 5 and have made my felf miferable, by over-loving.
Nay, and now, my cafe is defperate 5 for I have been marry'd
above thefe two years, and find my felf every day worfe and
worfein love : nothing but madnefs can be the end on't.

Arte. Doat on, to the extremity, and you are happy.

Dor. He deferves fo infinitely much, that, the truth is, there^
Can be no doating in the matter 5 but to love well, I confefs, is
a work that pays it felf: 'tis telling gold 5 and after flaking it
for ones pains.

. Rho.-hy that I (hould be a very covetous perfon $ for I am
ever pulling out my money, and putting it into my pocket
again.

Dor, O dear Rhodophil I

Rho. Ofweet Dor dice ! £ Embracing each other.-

Arte, ( Ajide)Nay y l am refolv'djl'll never interrupt Lovers :
Til leave 'emas happy as I found 'em. [ steals away,

Rho, What, is (he gone } ' [Looking up;

Dor. Yes, and without taking leave.

Rho. Then there's enough for this time [Parting from her.

Dor. Yes fure, the Scene's done, I take it.

They walk^ contrary ways on the Stage $ he with his hands
in his pocket, whijiling : fie, fnging a dull melon-
cholly tune.

' Rho. Pox o ' your dull tune, a man can't think for you.
Dor. Pox o' your damn'd whittling $ you can neither be com-
pany to me your felf, nor leave me to the freedom of my own*
fancy.

Rho* .



32 Marriage a*la-Mode.

Rho. Well ; thou art the mod provoking Wife !
Dor. Well, thou art the dulleft Husband, thou art never to
be provok'd,

Rho. I was never thought dull, till T marry *d thee 5 and now
thou ha ft made an old knife of me,thou haft whetted me fo long,
till I have no edge left.

Dor. I fee you are in the Husbands faflhion 5 you referve all
your good humours for y our Miftrefles, and keep your ill for
your wives.

Rho. Prethee leave me to my own cogitations 5 I am think-
ing over all my fins, to find for which of them it was I marry *d
thee.

Dor. Whatever your fin was, mine's the punifhment.
Rho. My comfort is, thou art not immortal 5 and when
that blefled, that divine day comes, of thy departure, I'm
refolv'd I'll make one Holy-daymore in the Almanack, for thy
fake.

Dor. Ay,youhad need make a Holy-day forme, for Iamfure
you have made me a Martyr.

jj/w.Then,fetting my victorious foot upon thy head, in the
firfthour ofthyfilence, (that is, the firft hour thou art dead,
for I defpair of it before) I will fvvear by thy Ghoft, an oath as
terrible to me, as styxis to the Gods, never more to be in dan-
ger of the Banes of Matrimony.

Dor. And I am refolv'd to marry the very fame day thou
dy'ft, if it be but to (how how little I'm concern'd for thee.

Rho. Prethee, Doralice^ why do we quarrel thus a-days ? ha >
this is but a kind of Heathenifh life, and does not anfwer the
endsofmarriage. If I haveerrd, propound what reafonable
atonement may be made, before we flcep, and I (hall not be
refractory: but withall confider, I have been marry'd thefe
three years, and be not too tyrannical.

Dor. What fhouldyoutalkof a peace abed, when you can
givenofecurity for performance of Articles ?

Rho. Then, fincewe muft live together, and both of us ftand
upon our terms, as to matter of dying firftjetus make our felves
as merry as we can with our misfortunes.

Why



Marriage aM* Mode. <£

Why there's the devil on't ! if thou couldft make my enjoy-
ing thee but a little lefs- eafie, ora little more unlawful, thoa
fhouldft fee, what a Termagant Lover I would prove. I have
taken fuch pains to enjoy thee^Doralice, that I have fan ci'd thee
all the fine women in the Town, to help me out But now
there's none left for me to think on, my imagination is quite
jaded. Thou art a Wife, and thou wilt be a Wife, and I can
make thee another no longer. [Exit RhodophiJ.

Dor. Well, fince thou art a Husband, and wilt be a Husband*
I'll try if I can find out another ! 'Tisa pretty time we Women
have on't, to be made Widows, while we are marry 'd. Our
Husbands think it reafonable to complain, that we are the
fame, and the fame to them, when we have more reafon to com-
plain, that they are not the fame to us. Becaufe they cannot
feed on one difh, therefore we muftbe ftarv'd. 'Tis enough that
they have a fufficient Ordinary provided, and a Table ready
fpread for 'em: if they cannot fall too and eat heartily, the
fault is theirs 5 and 'tis pity, me-thinks 5 that the good crea-
ture fhould be loft, when many a poor (inner would be glad
©n't.

Enter Melantha, and Artemis to her.

Mel. Dear, my dear, pity me 5 I am fo chagrin today, and
have had the moft fignal affront at Court ! I went this after-
noon to do my devoir to Princefs Amalthea^ found her, con-
vers'd with her, andhelp'd to make her court fome half an
hour 5 after which, (he went to take the ay r, chole out two
Ladies to go with her, that came inafterme, and left me moft
barbaroufly behind her.

Arte. You are the lefsto be piti'd, Melantha^becauCe you fub-
ject your felf to thefe affronts, by coming perpetually to CourL,
where yovfehavenobufinefs nor employment.

Mel. I declare, I had rather of the two, be raillfd^ nay, md
traittk at Court, then beDeifi'd in the Town: for, afiuredly,
nothing can be fo ridtcnle^Qsa meer Town-Lady.

Dor. Efpecially at Court. How I have feen 'em crowd and
fweat in the Drawing-room, on a Holiday-night / for that's

F their



54- Marriage aJa^Mode.

their time tofwarm, and invade the Prefence. O, how they
catch at a bow, or any little falute from a Courtier, to make
fhow of their acquaintance! and rather then be thought to be
quite unknown., they court'fie to one another; but they take
true pains to come near the Circle, and prefs and peep
upon the Princef?, to write Letters into the Countrey how
(he was drefs'd, while the Ladies that ftand about make their
court to her with abufing them.

Arte. Thefeare fad truths, Melantha } and therefore I would
e'en advife you to quit the Court, and live either wholly in
the Town , or, if you like not that, in the Countrey.

Dor. In the Countrey ! nay, that's to fall beneath the Town 5
for they live there upon our offals here : their entertainment of
wit, is onely the remembrance of what they had when they
were laft in Town 3 they live this year upon the laft years
knowledge, as their Cattel do all night, by chewing the Cud
of what they eat in the afternoon.

Mel. And they tell, for news, fuch unlikely ftories^ a letter
from one of us is fuch a prefent to 'em, that the poor fouls
wait for the Carriers-day with fuch devotion, that they cannot
fleep the night before.

Arte. No more then I can, the night before I am to go a
journey.

Dor. Or I, before! am to try on a new Gown.

Mel. A Song that*s ftale here, will be new there a twelve-
nioneth hence,, and if a man of the Town by chance come
amongfc 'em, he's reverenced for teaching em the Tune.

Dor A friend of mine, who makes Songs fometimes, came
lately out of the Weft, and vow'd he was fo put out of coun-
tenance with a Song of his 5 for at the rlrft Countrey- Gentle-
man's he vifited, hefaw three Tailors crofs-leg'd upon the Ta-
ble in the Hall, who were tearing out as loud as ever they
could fing.



.After the pangs ofadejperate Lover \ &c.



and all that day he heard nothing elfe, but the Daughters of
the houfeand the Maids 3 humming it over in every corner,and
the Father whittling it. j r te*



Arte* Indeed I have obfqrv'd of my felf, that when T am out
* of Town but a fortnight, lam fo humble, that I would receive
a Letter from my Tailor or Mercer for a favour.

Mel. When I have been at grafs in the Summer and am
new come up again, methinks I *m to be turnd into ridicule by
all that fee me, but when I have been once or twice at Court,
I begin to value my felf again, and to defpife my Countrey -
acquaintance.

Arte. There are places whereall people may be ador'd, and
we ought to know our felves fo well as to chufe em. .

Dor. That's very true , your little Courtiers wife, who fpeaks
to the King but once a moneth, need but goto a Town- Lady 5
and there (he may vapour, and cry. The King and J 3 at every
word. Your Town-Lady,who is laugh'd at in the Circle,takes
her Coach into the City, and there (he'scall'd your Honour,
and has a Banquet from the Merchants Wife, whom fhe laughs
at for her kindnefs. And, as for my finical Cit, (he removes
but to her Countrey- houfe, and there infults over the Coun-
trey Gentlewoman that never comes up , who treats her with
Frumity and Cuftard, and opens her dear bottle of Mirabilis
befide>for a Jill-glafs of it at parting.

Arte, At laft, I fee, we (hall leave Melantha where we found
her h for, by your defcription of the Town and Countrey, they
are become more dreadful to her, then the Court, where fhe
was affronted. But you forget we are to wait on the Princefs
Amalthea. Come, Doralice.

Dor. Farewell, Melantha;

Mel. Adieu, my dear.

Arte. Yousreoutof charity with her, and therefore I (hall
not give your fervice.

Mel. Do not omit it, I befeech you 5 for I have fuch a ten-
der for the Court, that I love it ev'n from the Drawing-room
to the Lobby, and can never be rebutee by any ufage. But,
hark you 5 my Dears, one thing I had forgot of great con-
ferment.

Dor. Quickly then, we are in hafte,

Mel. Qo not call it my fervice, that's too vulgar } but d o my
haife mains to the Princefs Amalthea 5 that is Sftritvelk !

F 2 Dor*



3<$ Marriage kAa*Mode.

Dor. To do you fervice then, we will prendre the Carrojfe to
Court, and do your Baife mains to the Princefs Amalthea, in
your phrafe spirituelU. [ Exeunt Artemis and Doralice.

Enter Philotis ; with a Paper in her hand.

Mel. O, are you there, Minion } And, well, are not you a
moft precious damfe!,to retard all my vifits for want of lan-
guage, when you know you are paid fo well for furnifhing me
with new words formy daily converfation } Let me die, if F
have not run the rifque already, to fpeak like one of the vul-
gar 5 and if I have one phrafe left in all my (tore that is .not
thrid-bare & ufi> and fit for nothing but to be thrown to
Peafants.

Phil, Indeed, Madam, I have been very diligent in my vo-
cation 5 but you have fodrain'dall the French Plays and Ro-
mances, that they are not able to fupply you with words for
your daily expences.

Mel, Drain'd ? what a word's there !
Efuife'e, youfot you. Come, produce your morning's work.

Phil. 'Tis here, Madam. Q shows the Paper.

Mel. 7 my Venus I fourteen or fifteen words to ferve me
a whole day ! Let me die, at this rate I cannot laft till night.
Come, read your works: twenty toonehalf of 'em will not
pafs mufter neither.

Phil. Sottifes. [Reads.

Mel. Sottifes : bon. That's an excellent word to begin with-
all : as for example 5 He, or (he faid a thoufand Sottifes to me.
Proceed.

Phil. Figure : as what a figure of a man is there !
Waive, and Naivete.

Mel. Naive ! as how }

Phil. Speaking of a thing that was naturally faid> It was fo
naive : or fuch an innocent piece of Simplicity 5 'twas fuch a
xaivete.

Mel. Truce with your interpretations : make hafte.

?hil. Foible, Chagrin^ Grimace^ Embarrafjc, Double entendre,
Equivoque, Efclaircifjensent^ Suitt^ Bevt*e,Facon } Panchant, Coup
if tetwrdj, a nd Midi cute. MeL



Marriage a^Mode. 57

Mel. Hold, hold ^ how did they begin?

Phil. Thef began at Sottifes^ and ended en Ridicule.

Mel. Now give me your Paper in my hand., and hold you
my Glafs, while I pradtife my poftures for the day.

[ Melantha laughs in the Glafs.
How does that laugh become my face }

phiL Sovereignly well. Madam.

Mel. Sovereignly ! Let me die, that's not amifs. That word
(hall not be yours, I'll invent it, and bring it up my felf : my
new Point Gorget (hall be yours upon't : not a word of the
word, I charge you.

Phil. I ara dumb, Madam.

Mel. That glance, how futesit with my face?

[ Looking in the Gl aft again*

Phil. 'Tis fo languijjant .

Mel. LanguiJJantl that word (hall be mine too, and my laft
Indian-Gown thine for't.
Thatfigh? : [Look/ again i

Phil. 'Twill make many a man figh, Madam. 'Tis a meer In-
cendiary.

Mel. Take my Guimp Petticoat for that truth. If thou haft
more ofthefephrafes, let me die but I could give away all my
Wardrobe., and go naked for 'em.

Phil. Go naked > then you would be a Venus y Madam. O Ju-
piter ! what had I forgot } this Paper was given me by Rhodo-
phil'sPage.

Mel. .(Reading the Letter} — Begthe favour from you.

. Gratifie my paffion- —fo far -affignation

— in the Grotto behind the Terras — clock

this evening Well, for the Billets doux there's no man

in Sicily muft difpute with Rhodephih they are fo French, fo
gallant, and Cotendre, that I cannot refift the temptation of the
affignation. Now go you away, vhiloth $ it imports me to
pra&ife what I (hall fay to my Servant when I meet him.

[Exit Philotis.
Rhodophil, you'll wonder at my arTuranee to meet you here 5
let me die,\ I am fo out of breath with coming, that I can ren-
der you no peafen of it. Then he will make this -repartees

Madam [



•$& Marriage a* la- Mode.

Madam;, I have no reafon to accufe you for that which is To
great a favour to me. Then I reply, But why have you drawn
me to this folitary place i let me die but 1 am apprehenfive of
fome violence from you. Then, fays he 5 Solitude, Madam, is

moft fit for Lovers 5 but by this fair hand. , Nay,

now I vow you're rude, Sir. O fie, fie, fie , I hope you'l be

honourable? You'd laugh at me if I (hould, Madam~—

What do you mean to throw me down thus ? Ah me ! ah,ah,ahv

Entcr Polydamas, Leonidas, and Guards,

O Venus I the King and Court. Let me die but I fear they
have found my foible , and will turn me into ridicule.

[Exit running,

Leon. Sir, I befeech you.

Poly, !-■ : • m — Do not urge my patience,

Leon, I'll not deny
But what your Spies informed you of, is true :
I love the fair Palmyra 5 but I lov'd her
Before I knew your title to my bloud.

Enter Palmyra, guarded.

See, here (he comes 5 and looks, amid'fther Guards,
Like a weak Dove under the Falcon's gripe.

heav'n, I cannot bear it.

Poly, ,„ ~* Maid, come hither.

Have you prelum' d fo far, asto receive
My Son's affecKon ?

Palm. Alas, what fhall I anfwer ? to confefs it
Will raife a blufh upon a Virgin's face 5
Yet I was ever taught 'twas bafe to lie.

Poly, You've been too bold, and you muft love no more,

Talm. Indeed I muft \ I cannot help my love 5

1 was fo tender when I took the bent,
That now I grow that way.

Poly, He is a Prince 5 and you are meanly bor.i.
Leon, Love eitheriinds equality, or makes it :

Like






Marriage aM*Mod$i

Like death, he knows no difference in degree*,

But plains, and levels all.

Talm. Alas., I had not render'd up my heart,

Had he not lov*d me firft} but he prefer 'd me

Above the Maidens of my age and rank ,

Still fhun'd their company, and ftillfbughtmjaej

I was not won by gifts, yet (till he gave >

And all his gifts, though fmall, yet fpoke hisjove.

He pick'd the earlieft Strawberries in Woods,

Theclufter'd Filberds, and the purple Grapes .-

He taught a prating Stare to fpeak my name 5

And when he found a Meft of Nightingales,

Or callow Linnets, he would (how 'emme^

And let me take 'emout.

Toly. This Is a little Miftris, meanly born,

Fit onely for a Prince his vacant hours.

And then, to laugh at her fimplicity,

Not fix a paffion there. Now hear my fentence>
Leon. B.emember, ere you give it, 'tis pronounc'd

Againftus both.

: ¥oly. Firft, in her hand
There (hall be plac'd a Player's painted Sceptre,
And, on her headj a gilded Pageant Crowns
Thus (hall (he go.

With all the Boys attending^! 1iey Triumph 1
That done, be put alone into a Boat,
With bread and water onely for three days,
So on the Sea (he (hall be fet adrift.
And who relieves her. dies*

Falm. I onelv beg that you would execute
The laftpart firft : let me be put to Sea 5
The bread and water, for my three days life,
I give you back, I would not live folong ,
But let me (cape the (hame.

Leon.hock to me,Piety 5 and you, O Gods,look to my pietj^
Keep me from faying that which misbecomes a fan?
But let me die before I fee this done.
Poly. If you for ever will abjure her fight£



£o Marriage aAa^Mode.

I can be yet a father •, (he (hall live.

Leon. Hear, O you Pow'rs,is this to be a father >
I fee Yi« all my happinefs and quiet
You aim at, Sir j and take 'em :
I will notfave ev'nmy Palmyras life
At that ignoble price 5 but Fit die with her.

Palm. So had I done by you.
Had Fate made me a Princefs : Death, methinks.
Is not a terrour now 5

He is not fierce, or grim, but fawns, and fooths me 5
And Aides along, Mke Cleopatra's Afpick,
OfPring his fervice to my troubled breaft.

Leon. Begin what you have purpos'd when you pleafe.
Lead her to fcorn 3 yourtriumph (hall be doubled.
As holy Priefts

In pity go with dying malefa&ours,
So will I (hare her fhame.

Poly. You (hall not have your will fo much 5 firft part 'era,
Then execute your office.

Leon. ■ . No 5 Flldie

In her defence. [Draws his [word*

Palm. . Ah, hold, and pull not on

A curfe, to make me worthy of my death :
Do not by lawlefs force oppofe your Father,
Whom you have too much difobey'dfor me.
Leon. Here, take it, Sir, and with it, pierce my heart :

[ Prefenting hisfaord to his father upon his knees.
You have done more, in taking my Palmyra.
You are my Father, therefore I fubmit.

Poly. Keep him from any thing he may defign
Againft his life, whil'ft the firft fury lafts \
And now perform what I commanded you.

Leon. In vain 5 itTword and poifon be deni'd me,
I'll hold my breath and die.

Palm. Farewell, my laft Leonidas i, yet live 3
I charge you live, till you believe me dead.
I cannot die in peace, if youdie firft.
If Jik?'s ablefling,you (hall have it laft.

Poly.



Marriage aM~ Mode. a\

Poly* Go on with her, and lead him after me.

Enter Argaleon haftily, with Hermogenes.

Arga. I bring you, Sir, fuch news as mufi: amaze you,
And fuch as will prevent you from an a&ion
Which would haverendred all your life unhappy.

Poly, Hermogenes^ you bend your knees in vain,

[Hermogenes kneels.
My doom's already paft.

Her. I kneel not for Palmyra^ for I know
She will not need my pray'rs • but for my felf :
Witha feign'dtalelhave abus'd your ears,
And therefore merit death 5 but fince, unforc'd,
Ifirftaccufe my felf 5 I hope your mercy.

Poly. Hafteto explain your meaning.

Her. Then ,in few words. Palmyra is your daughter*

Poly. How can I give belief to this Impoftor ?
He who has once abus'd me, often may.
I'l hear no more.

Arga J For your own fake, youmuft.

Her. A parent's love ("for I confefs my crimej
Mov'd me to (ay, Leonidas was yours }
But when I heard Palmyra was to die.
The fearofguiltlefsbloud fo ftung my confcience, ,
That T refoiv'd, ev'n with my (hame, to fave
Your daughter's life.

Poly, But how can I be certain, but that intereft,
Which mov'd you firft to fay your fon was mine,
Does not now move you too, to fave your daughter }

Her. You had but then %iy word 5 I bring you now
Authentick teftimonies. Sir, in fhort,

[_ Delivers on his knees a Jewel^ and a Letter.
If this will not convince you, let me fuffer.

Poly. I know this jewel well 5 'twas once my mothers,

\Lookjng firft on the Jemh
Which, marrying, I prefented to my wife.
And this, O this 3 is my Eudocia's hand.

G ibis



a i Marriage a4a*Mode.

This was the pledge of love given to Eudocia> [Reads;

Who^dying, to her young Palmyra leaves it :

And this when you, mydeareji Lor^ receive.

Own her, andthinhjon me, dying Eudocia.

Take it 5 'tis well there is no more to read, [Y<9 Argaleon.

My eyes grow full, and fwim in their own light.

[He embraces Palmy ra.
palm. I fear, Sir, this is your intended Pageant.
You fport your felf at poor Palmyra's coft 5
But if you think to make me proud,
Indeed I cannot be fo : I was born
With humble thoughts, and lowly, like my birth.
A real fortune could not make me haughty.
Much lefs afeign'd.

Poly. This was her mother's temper.

5 have too much deferv'd thouQiouldftfufpecl
That I am not thy father 5 but my love
Shall henceforth fhow I am. Behold my eyes,.
And fee a father there begin to flow :
This is not feign'd. Palmyra.

Palm. I doubt no longer. Sir y you are a King,
And cannot lie : falfhood's a vice too bafe
To find a room in any Royal breaft ^
I know, in fpight of my unworthinefs,
lam your child 5 ror when you would have kuTd me,
Methought I lov'd youthen.

Arga. Sir, we forgetthe Prince Leonid as,
Hisgreatnefs fhould not ftand neglected thus.

Poly. Guards, you may now retire : Give him his fword,
And leave him free.

Leon, Then the firft ufe I make of liberty
Shall be, with your permiffion, mighty Sir ;
To pay that reverence to which Nature binds me.

[kneels to Hermogenes.
Arga. Sure you forget your birth rhu9 to mifplaee
This aft of your obcdence 5 you fhould kneel
To nothing buttoHeav'n,andtoa King,
Leon % I never (hall forget what Nature owes}

No*



Marrkge aJa~Mode. y»

Nor be afham'd to pay it j though my father
Be not a King, 1 know him brave and honeft 5
And well deferving of a worthier fon.

Poly. He bears it gallantly.

Leon, Why would you not inftru&mejSir^before £Ti> Hernh
Where I (hould place my duty >
From which, if ignorance have made me fwerve,
I beg your pardon for an erring fon.

Faint. IalmoftgrievelamaPrincefs, fince
It makes him lofe a Crown.

Leon. And next, to you, my King, thus low I kneel,
T' implore your mercy 5 if in thatfmall time
I had the honour to be thought your fon,
I pay'd not Ariel: obedience to your will :
I thought, indeed, I (hould not be compell'd.
But thought it as your fon 5 fo what I took
In duty from you, I reftor'd in courage 3
Becaufe your fon (hould not be fore '3.

Poly. You have my pardon for it.

Leon. To you, fair Princefs, I congratulate
Your birth 5 of which lever thought you worthy : -
And give me leave to add, that I am proud
1 he Gods have pick'd me out to be the man
By whofe dejected fate yours is to rife 3
Becaufe no man could more defire your fortune,
Or franklier part with his to make you great.

Fdm. I know the King, though you are not hisfor^
Will frill regard you as my Fofter- brother,
And Co conduct you downward from a Throne,
By flow degrees, fouqperceiv'd and foft,
That it may feem no fall : or, if it be,
May Fortune lay a bed of down beneath you.

Poly. He (hall be rank'd with my Nobility,
And kept rromfcorn by a large penfion giv n him.

Leon. You are all great and Royal in your gifts 3 Xj>oveing>
But at the Donor's feet I lay em down:
Should I take riches from you, it would feem
As I did want a foul to bear that poverty

G z T&



a a Marriage aAa^Mode*

To which the Gods defign'd my humble birth:

And (houldl take your Honours without merit,

It would appear, I wanted manly courage

To hope 'em, in your fervice, from my fword. !

Toly. Still brave, and like yourfelf.
The Court (hall (hine this night in its full fplendor,
And celebrate thisnew difcovery.
Argakm* lead my daughter : as we go
I (hall have time to give her my commands.
In which you are concern'd. [_ Exeunt all but Lconidas.

2Le^«.Me^hinks I do not want
That huge long train offawningfollowers 3
Thatfwept a furlong after me.
Tis true, I am alone 5

So was the Godhead ere he made the world.
And better ferv'd Himfelf, then ferv'd by Natare.
And yet I have a Soul

Above this humble fate. F could command.
Love to do good '■> give largely to true merit 3
All that a King fhould do: But though thefe are not
My Province, I have Scene enough within
To exercife my vertue.
All that a heart, fo fix'd as mine, can move.
Is., that my niggard fortune ftarves my love. {Exit,

SCENE II.

Palamede and Doraliceweef .• fierokh a Bookjn her hand,
feems to ft art at pght of him.

£>er. v I v Is a ftrange thing that no warning will ferve your
Jt turn j and that no retirement will fecure me from
your impertinent addrefles! Did not I tell you* that I was to
be private here at my devotions }

Fala. Yes 5 and you fee I have obferv'd my Cue exactly : I
am come to releive you from them. Come, (hut up, (hut up your
Book 5 the man's come whoistofupply all your neceffities.

Don



^Marriage a-L'Mode. ajj

Dor. Then, itfeems, you arefo impudent to thinl^it was an
aflignation.^ this, I warrant, was your lewd interpretation of
ray innocent meaning. ■' .

pala. Venus forbid that Ifhould harbour fo unreafonable a
thought of a fair young Lady, that you fhould lead me hither
into temptation. I confefs I might think indeed it was a kind of
honourable challenge, to meet privately without Seconds, and
decide the difference betwixt the two Sexes 3 but heaven
forgive me if I thought amifs.

Dor. You thought too. Til lay my life on' t, that you might
as well make love tome, as my Husband does to your Miftris.

Pala, I was fo unreafonable to think fo too.

Dor. And then you wickedly inferr'd, that there was fome
juftice in the revenge of it: or at leaft but little injury 3 for a
man to endeavour to enjoy that, which he accounts a blefting,
and which is not valu'd as it ought by the dull poffeffbur. Con-
fefs your wickednefs, did you not think fo >

Pala. I confefs I was thinking fo, as faft as T could 5 but you
think Co much before me, that you will let me think nothing*

Dor, 'Tis the very thing that I deftgn'd : I have foreftall'd all
your arguments, and left you without a word more, to plead
for mercy. If youhave any thingfartber to offer, ere Sentence

pais PoorAnimalj I brought you hither onely for my

diverfion.

Pala. That you may have, if you'll makeufe of me the right
way j but I tell thee, woman, I am now part talking, t <

Dor. But it may be,I came hither to hear what fine things you
could fay for your felf.

Pala. You would be very angry, to my knowlecge, if I

fhould lofe Co much time to fay many of 'em — By this

hand you would

Dor. Fie D Palamede^ \ am a woman of honour.

Pala. I fee you are ; you have kept touch with your affigna-
tion: and before we part, you fhall find that I am a man of ho-
nour- yet I have one fcruple of confcienee

Dor. I warrant you will not want fome naughty argument
or other to fatisfie your felf I hope you are afraid of be-
traying your friend >

Fafeh



aa, Marriage aM-Mode.

" r J%. j Of betraying my friend! I am more afraid of being
%etrSy*d'b'y you to my friend. You women now are got into
the way of telling firft your felves : a man who has any care
of his reputation will be loath to truft it with you.

Dor. O you charge your faults upon our Sex .* you men are
like Cocks, you never make love, but you clap your wings,
and crow when you have done. N

Pala. Nay, rather you women are like Hens 5 you never lay,

but you cackle an hour after, to difcover your Neft But

I'll venture it for once.

Dor. To convince you that you are in the wrong. Til retire
into the dark Grotto, to my devotion, and makefo little noife,
that itffoallbeimpoffiblefor you to find me.

Pala, But if I find you — — —

Dor. Ay, if you find me But Til put you to fearch

in more corners then you imagine.

[ She runs ;//, and he after her,
■ ■■' • "

Enter Rhodophil and Melantha.

Mel. Let me die, but this folitude, and that Grotto are fcan-
dalous; I'll go no further j befides,you have a fweet Lady of
your own. '

Rho. But afweetMiftris^now and then, makes my fweet La-
dy fo much more fweet.

Mel. I hope you will not force me ?

Jtho. But I will, if yoiidefireit.

VaU.Cwithm) Where the devil are you 5 Madam ? ; S'death,
I begin to be weary of this hide and feek : if you ftay a little
longer, till the fit's over, I'll hide in my turn, and put you to the
finding me.

[He enters^ and fees Rhodophil and Melantha.
How ! Rhodophil y and my Miftris !

Mel. My Per vaht to apprehend me ! this is Surprcnant aii der-
nier.

Rho. I muO: on } there's nothing but impudence can help
me out. -

Pala. RhedophH, How came you hither in Co good com-
pany } Rho.



Marriage a-ta~ Mode. ^

Rho, As you tee, Palamede $ an effect of pure friendfhijys I
was not able to live without you.

Pala. But what makes my Miftris with you?

Rho. Why, I heard you were here alone, and could not in ci-
vility but bring her to you.

Mel. You'll pardon the effe&sof apaffion which I may now
avow for you, if it tranfported me beyond the rules of bieu
feanee,

Pala. But who told you 1 was here ? they that told you that,
may tell you more, for ought I k&offt

Rho.O> for that matter, we had intelligence.

Pala. But let me tell you, we came hither fo very privately,
that you could not trace us.

Jtho. Us? what us? you are alone.

Pala. Us ! the devil's in me for miftaking : me, I meant. Or
us 3 that is, yon are me 3 or'I you, as we are friends | that's us .

Dor. Palamede, Palamede f Within.

jJ^.IQiouId know that voice ? who's within there, that
calls you?

Pala. Faith I can't imagine 5 I believe the place is haunted.

Dor. Palamede, Palamede , All- cocks hidden. [Within,

Pala. Lord, lord, what (hall I do ? Well, dear friend, to let
you fee Ifcorntobe jealous, and that I dare trufc my Miftris
with you, take- her back, for I would not wiWingly have her
frighted, and I am refolv'd to fee who's there 5 I'll not be
dantedwitha Bug-bear, that's certain: prethee difputeit not,
it (hall be fo % nay, do not put me to fwear, but go quickly t
there's an effed of pure friendftiip for yon now:

Enter Doralice, and looks ama% s d feeing them.

.
Rho. Doralice I I am thunder-flrruck to fee yon here.
Pala. So am 1 1 quite thunder- (truck. Was it you that caird 1
me within? ( I mutt be impudent. )
Rho. How came you hither, Spoufe >

Palir. Ay, how came you hither ? And, which is more, how
could you be here without my knowledge?
Dor, (fo her husband) O^Seatlemanjhave I caught you i'faith?

have



ij.8 Marriage a f U< Mode.

have I broke forth in ambufh upon you ! I thought my fufpi-
cions would prove true.

#£<?. .Suspicions ! this is very fine;, Spoufe !
Frethee what fufpicions ?

Dor. O, you feign ignorance: why, of you and Melantha;
herehave I ftaid thefe^two hours, waiting with all the rage of
a paffionate, loving wife, but infinitely jealous, to take you
two in the manner \ for hither I was certain you would come.

Rho. But you are miftaken, Spoufe, in theoccafion} for we
came hither on purpofe to find Palamede^ on intelligence he
was gone before, .

Pala. I'll behang'd thenifthe famepartywho gave you in-
telligence, t was here, did not tell your wife you Would come
hither: nowlfmcll the malice on't On both fides.

Dor. Was it fo, think you? nay, then, I'll confefs my part
of the malice too. As foon as ever I fpi'd my husband and Mc-
lanthacome. together, I had a ftrange temptation to make him
jealous in revenge} and that made me call Palamede^ Pala*
mede. as though there had been an Intrigue between us.

Mel. Nay, I avow, there was an apparence of an Intrigue be-
tween us too.

Pala, To fee how things will come about !

Rho. And was it onely thus, my dear Doralice ? [_ Embraces.

Dor. And did I wrong none, Rhodophil, with a falfe fufpi-
cion ? [Embracing him .

Pala.(Afide) Now am I confident we had all four the fame
defign : 'tis a pretty odd kind of game this, where each of us
phys for double (lakes: this is juft thruft and parry with the
fame motion } lam to get his Wife, and yet to guard my own
Miftris. But lam vilely fufpitious, that, while I conquer in the
Right Wing, I (hall be routed in the Left: for both our women
will certainly betray their party, becaufe they are each of them
for gaining of two, as well as we 5 and I much fear,

Iftheir neceflkies and ours were knowa,

They have more need of two^then we of one.

[_ Exeunt > emlrachi£ one another.

ACT



Marriage aM'Mode. A.p



ACT IV. SCENE I.



Enter Leonidas, mufing^ Anaalthea following him.

Amal. tr Onder he is, and I muft fpeak, or die 5

X And yet 'tis death to fpeak 3 yet lie muft know
I have a paffion for him, and may know it
With a lefs blufh 3 becaufe to offer it
To his low fortunes, (hows I lov'd before,
His perfon,not his greatnefs.

Leon, Firft fcorn'd, and now commanded from the Court !
The King is good 3 but he is wrought to this
By proud Argaleons malice, ij
What moredifgrace can Love and Fortune joya
T' inflid upon one man ? I cannot now
Behold my dear Palmyra : (he, perhaps, too
Is grown afham'd of a mean ill-plac'd love.

Amd. Affift me, Venus^ for I tremble when [ Aftde*

I am to fpeak, but I muft force my felf.

Sir, I would crave but one (hort minute with you, [to hint.
And fome few words. ,,.„.,,

Leon, -——The proud Argaleons fitter ! [Ajide.

Amah Alas, it will not out 3 fhame ftops my mouth. [Aflde.
Pardon myerrour. Sir, I wasmiftaken.
And took you for another.

Leon, In fpight of all his guards, I'll fee Palmyra 5 [Afide.

Though meanly born,lhave a Kingly Soul yet.

Amal, Iftand upon a precipice, where fain [Ajtde*

1 would retire, but Love ftill thrufts me on :
Now I grow bolder, and will fpeakto himi
Sir, ^tis indeed to you that I would fpeak, [to him,

And^if ,

Leon. O, you arefent to fcorn my fortunes 3

II Your



50 Marriage aM-Mode.

Your Sex and Beauty are your priviledgej
But fhould your Brother

Amal. Now he looks angry, and I dare notfpeak,.
I had fome bufinefs with you, Sir,
But 'tis not worth your knowledge.

Leon. Then 'twill be charity to let me mourn
My griefs alone, for I am much diforder'd.

Amal. 'Twill be more charity to mourn 'em with you h
Heav'nknowsl pity you.

Leon. Your pity. Madam,

Is generous, but 'tis unavailable.

Amal, You know not till 'tis tri'd.
Your forrows are no fecret 5 you have loft
A Crown, and Miftris.

Leon. . Are not thefe enough i

Hang two fuch weights on any other foul,
And fee if it can bear 'em.

Amah More, you are baniftYd, by my Brother's means^
And ne*r muft hope again to fee yourPrincefs$
Except as Prisoners view fair Walks and Streets,
Andcarelefs Paflengers going by their grates^
To make 'em feel the want of liberty.
But,worfe then all,

The King this morning has injoyn'd his Daughter _
T' accept my Brother's love,

Leon, m « Is this your pity ? •

You aggravate my griefs, and print 'em deeper
In new and heavier ftamps.

Amal 'Tisas Phyficiansftiowthe defperateill
T* indear their Art, by mittigating pains
They cannot wholly cure: when you defpair
Of all you with, fome part of it, becaufe
Hnhop'd for, may be grateful b and fome other

Leon. What other >

AmaL Some other may
My (hame again has feizd me, and I can go £«*/£&.

No farther •

Leon. Thefe often failing, fighs, and interruptions,

Make



Marriage aM*Modei

Make file imagine you have grief like mine :
Have you ne'r lov'd >

Amal. ~- 1 } never : 'tis in vain 5

I muft defpair in filence. [Ajide.

Leon. You come as I fufpefted then, to mock,
At leaft obferve my griefs: take it not ill
That I muft leave you, {j*~&>w&

Amal. You muft not go with thefe unjuft opinions.
Command my life, and fortunes 5 you are wife,
Think, and think well, what I can do to ferve you.

Leon. I have but one thing in my thoughts and wifhes :
If by your means I can obtain the fight
Of my ador'd Palmyra 5 or, what's harder,
One minutes time, to tell her, I die hers. £ shefiarts bac\ %

I fee I am not to expect it from you 3
Nor could, indeed, withreafon.

Amal. Name any other thing : isAmalthea
So defpicable, (he can ferve your wifhes
In this alone?

Leon m If I fhouldaskofheavn,

I have no other fuit.

Amal, To (how you, then, I can deny you nothing,
Though 'tis more hard to me then any other,
Yet I will do't for you,

Leon. Name quickly, name the means,fpeakmy good AngeL
Amal. Be not fo much o'rjoy'd s for, if you are,
I'll rather dye then do t. Tfeis night the Court
Will be in Mafquerade -,
You (hall attend on me ■> in that difguife
You may both fee and fpeak to her.
If you dare venture it.

Leon. Yes, were a God her Guardian,
And bore in each hand thunder, I would venture.

Amal. Farewell then h two hours hence I will expect you :
My heart's fo full, that I can ftay no longer. £ Exit*

Leon. Already it grows dusky 3 I'll prepare
With hafte for my difguife. But who are thefe ?

H 2 Enter



X



5i Marriage Ma+Mode.

Enter Hermogenes rfff^Eubulus.

Her. Tis he 5 we need not fear tofpeak to him*

Eub. Leonidas,

Leonidas Sure I have known that voice.

Her. You have fomereafon, Sir 3 'tis Eubulus^
Who bred you with the Princefs 5 and, departing,
Bequeathed you to my care.

Leon. My Fofter, Father ! let my knees exprefs ^Kneeling.
My joys for your return !

Eub. Rife, Sir, you rauft not kneel.

Leon, < ■ ■■ E'r fince you left me^

I have been wandring in amaze of fate^

Led by falfe fires of a fantaftick glory.

And the vain luftreof imagin'd Crowns,

But, ah ! why would you leave me ? or how could you

Abfentyourfelf fo long >

Enb.VW giveyouamoftjuft account of both:
And fomething more I have to tell you, which
I know muft caufe your wonder 5 but this place.
Though almoft: hid in darknefs, is not fafe.
Already I difcern fome coming towards us [Torches appear.

With lights, who may difcoverme. Hermogenes^
Your lodgings are hard by, and much more private.

Her. There you may freely fpeak.

Leon. ...Letusmakehafte 3

For fome affairs, and of no fmall importance.

Call me another way 0v [Exeunt.

Enter Palamede and RJiodophil, with Vizor Mafquesin
their hands ■, andTorches before 'em.

Tata. We fhall have noble fport to night, Rhodophilj this
Mafqueradingis a moft glorious invention.

Rho, I believe it was invented firft by fome jealous Lover,
to difcover the haunts of his Jilting Miftris 3 or, perhaps, by
fome diftreffed fervant, to gain an opportunity with a jealous
man's wife. Tala.



Marriage a A& Mode. 53

Tata, No, it muft be the invention of a woman, it has formich
offubtilty and love in it.

Rho. lam fure 'tis extremely pleafant $ for to go unknown, is
the next degree to going invifible.

Tala. What with our antique habits., and feign'd voices, do
you know me? and I know you? Methinks we move and
talk juft like fo many over-grown Puppets.

Rho. Mafqueradeis onely Vizor-mafque improved, a* height-
ni-ng of the fame fafhion.

Bala. Noj Mafquerade is Vizor-mafque in debauch 5 audi
like it the better for't : for, with a Vizor-mafque, we fool our
felves into courtfhip, for the fake of an eye that glancd} or a
hand that (role it felf out of the glove fometimes, to give us a
fample of the skin .* but in Mafquerade there is nothing to be
known, (he's all Terra incognita, and the bold difcoverer leaps
afhoar, and takes his lot among the wild Indians ^wA Salvages^.
without the vile confederation of fafety to his perfon, or of
beauty, or whokfomenefs in his Miftris.

Enter Belizai

Rho, Beliza, what make you here ?

Bel. Sir, my Lady fent me after you, to let you know, (he
finds her felf a little indifpos'd, fo that (he cannot be at Court,
but is retird to reft, in her own appartment, where (he (hall!
want the happinefsof your dear embraces to night.

Rho, A very fine phrafe, Beliza to let me know my wife de-
fires to lie alone.

Tala. I doubt, Rhodophil, you take the pains fometimes to in-
firucl: your wife's Woman inthefe elegancies.

Rho. Tell my dear Lady, thatfince I muft be fo unhappy as
not to wait on her to night 3 I will lament bitterly for herab-
fence. Tis true, I (hall be at Court, but I\will take no diver-
tifement there* and when I return to my folitary bed, if lam
fo forgetful of my paffion as to deep, I will dream of her 5 and
betwixt fleep and waking, put out my foot towards her fide,
for mid-night confolation 5 and not rinding her, I. will figh, and
imagine my felf a mult defolate widower.



SbL Marriage aM- Mode.

Bel. I (hall do your commands, Sir. [Exit,

Rho. (Aftde) She's fick as aptly for my purpofe, as if (he had
contriv'd ft fo : well, if ever woman was a help-meet for man,
my Spoufe is to 5 for within this hour I received a Note from
Melantha> that (he would meet me this evening in Mafquerade
in Boys habit, to rejoyce with me before (he etitred into fet-
ters 3 for I find (he loves me better then Pafawede, onely becaufe
he's to be her husband. There's fomething of antipathy in the
word Marriage to the nature of love, marriage is the meer
Ladle of afFe&ion., that cools it when 'tis never (b fiercely bod-
ing over.

P^.Dear Rhodophil> I mud needs beg your pardon 5 there is
an occafion fall'n out which I had forgot : I cannot be at Court
to night.

Rho. J^ezvPalamede^ lam forry we (hall not have one cour(e
together at the herd } but I find your Game lies (ingle : good
fortune to yoti with your Miftris. [Exit.

Pala. He has wifti'dme good fortune with his Wife : there's
no fin in this then, there's fair leave given. Well, I mud go vifit
the fick 3 I cannot refift the temptations of my charity. O what
a difference will (he find betwixt a dull refty Husband, and a
quick vigorous Lover ! he fets out like a Carrier's Horfe, plod-
ding on, becaufe he knows he mu(t ; with the Bells of Matri-
mony chiming fo melancholly about his neck, in pain till he's at
his journeys end, and difpairing to get thither, he is fain to for-
tifie imagination with the thoughts of another woman : I take

heat after heat, like a well-breath 'd Courfer, and a* But

hark, what noife is that ? fwords ! [ Clajhing of Swords within.

Nay, then have with you. £ Exit Palamede.

Re-enter Palamede^/^rvhodophil.^W Doralice m niatishahiu

Rho. Friend, your relief was very timely, otherwife I had
been opprefs'd.

Pala. What was the quarrel >
Rho. What I did, was in refcue of this Youth.-
Pala. Whatcaufe could he give'em ?
Dor, The caufe was nothing but onely the common caufe

of



tSMarriage a4d*Modk ff

of fighting in, Mafquerades: they were drunk, and I was

fober.

6 Rbo. Have they not hurt you >

Dor, N05 but I am exceeding ill, with the fright on't,

Pala. Let's, lead him to fome place where he may refrefb
himfelfi

Rho, Do you conduct him then* _

Pala.(AJtde ) How ciofe this happens to my defign of going
to Dor aim b for; I am confident (he was fick on purpofe that I
ffaouldvifither* Hark you, Rhodophil, could not you take care
of the (tripling P I am partly engag'd to night*

&bo. You know I havebufinefs: but come. Youth, if it mud
befo.

Dor* (ToRhodophil) No, good Sir, do not give your felf that
trouble 5 I (hall be lafer, and better pleas'd with your friend
here.

Rho, Farewell then 7 once more Iwi(h you a good adven~~
ture.

Tata. Damn this kindnefs/ now mufti be troubled with*
this young Rogue, and mifs my opportunity with Doralice.

{ Exit Rhodophil alone,

\Palamede with Doralice*

-

SCENE II;

Enter Polydamat*

ArgaUon counfel'd well to banifli him y
He has, I know not what$
Of greatnefs in his looks, and of high fate,
Thatalmoft awes me 5 but I fear my Daughter*
Who hourly moves me for hinr, and I mark'd
She figh'd when I but nam'd Argaleon to her*
But fee, the Mafkers : hence my cares, this night,
At leaft take truce, and find me on my pillow*



$6 Marriage a'ld*Mode.

Enter the Frincefs in Mafquerade^ mth'Ladies: at the other end
Argaleon -and Gentlemen in Mafqnerade : thenheoriidzs lead-
ing Amalthea. ihe King fits. A Dance. After the Dance^

Amal. £ To Leonid as) That's the Princefs &
Ifaw the fy,ai?it<ere (he put it on. *Q .

Leon., I know her by athoufand other figns.
She cannot hide fo much Divinity.
Difguis'd, and filent, yet fqme graceful motion
Breaksfrom her, and (nines round her like a Glory,

t^>* Palmyra,

, Aptal. Thus (lie reveals her felf, and knows it not :
Like Love's Dark-lantern I direft his (reps,
And yet he Tees not that which gives him light.

Takn, I know you 5 but, alas, Leonidas^ [to Leonidas.

Why ffiduld you tempt this danger on yourTelf?

Leon. Madam, you know me not, if you believe
I would not hazard greater for your fake :
But you, rfear, are chang'd. \y ". "

Palm. No, I am ftill the fame 5
But there are many things became Taimyr a 1

Which ill becomethe Princefs.

Leon. J-I —I asknothing

Which Honour will not give you* leave to grant :
One hours. (hort audience^ at my fathers houfe.
You cannot fure refufe me.

Palm. Perhaps I (hould, did I confult flrid: vertue 5
But fomething mud be given to Love and you.
When would you I (hould come? /

Leon. This evening, .with the fpeedieft opportunity.
I have afecrettodifjfovertb yoa, : ^

Which will furprife, and_ pleafe you.

Palm. . , • ' ■ . ; ■'■ ■ ' ' ■ • 'Tis.enough* . U na 1 w i ■.'..'

Go now 5 for we may be obferv'd and known.
I truft your honour-, give me not accalioa
To blame my felf, or you.

Leon.



Marriage aAa^Modi. *j

Leon* You never (hall repent your good opinion.

L Ki JJ es her h4nd, and Exit
Arga. I cannot bedeceiv a •, that is the Princefs :
One of her Maid s betray 'd the habit to me 5
But who was he with whom (he held difcourfe >
Tis one (he favours 3 for he kifs'd her hand.
Our (hapes are like 3 our habits near the fame ?
She may miftake, and fpeak.tome for him.
I am refolv'd, I'll fatisfie my doubts,
Though to be more tormented . [Exit

SONG.:



1.

W'fliVft Alexis lay preft
In her Arms he lovd beji 9
With his hands round her nec\,
And his head on her breaft ,
Be found the fierce pleafure too hafty to ft ay,
And his foul in the tempeft juji flying away.

2.

When Coelia faw this 5

With a fight and a kjfs ,

she cryd, Oh my dear , 1 am robbed of my hlifis

'Tis unkind to your Love , and unfaithfully done^

To leave me behind yon , and die all alone.



The Youth, though in hafte 9

And breathing his lofts

In pity dyd flowly, "while fije dy'd more f aft %

TiU at length Jhe cry s d, Now^ my dear, now kt us go 9

Now die 9 my Alexis , and I will die tm

I 4. Thm



5,8 Mstrriage aAa^Mode*

4-

*lhus intrancd they did lie]

Till Alexis did try

To recover new breathy that again he might die }

then often they did 5 but the more they did fo,

The Nymph did more qnic^ and the shepherd more flow .

Mother Dance- After it^ Argaleon re-enters^ and
jlands by the Princefs.

J aim, Leonidasjwhat means this quick return > £To Argai

Arga. O heav'n ! 'tis what I fear'd.

Palm. Is ought of moment happen d finceyou went }

Arga, No, Madam, but I underftood not fully
Your 1 aft commands.

Palm. ~. And yet you anfwer'd to 'em*

Retire 5 you are too indifcreet a Lover .-

I'll meet you where I promis'd. [Exit*

Arga. O my curft fortune ! what have I difcover'd >
But I will be reveng'd. [Whifpersto, the King;

Poly. But are you certain you are not deceiv'd }

Arga. Upon my life.

Poly, -Her honour is concern'd.

Somewhat I'll do > but I am yet diftra&ed,
And know not where to fix. I wifh'd a child.
And Heav'n 3 in anger, granted my requeft.
So blind we are, our wifees arefo vain,
That wHat we moft defire, proves moft our pain*

^Exeunt omncs*



I SCENE



Marriage aM'Mode.
SCENE III.



An Eating-houje, Bottles of Wine on the table, Palamede 3
and Doralice in Man s habit.

Dor. (AJMe) Now cannot T find in my heart to difcover my
felfj though I long he fhould know me.

Fata. I tell thee, Boy, now I have feen thee fafe 5 I mud be
gone : 1 have no leifure to throw away on thy raw converia*
tion : I am a perfon thatunderftand better thin gs ; I.

Dor, Were la woman. Oh how you'd admire me/ cry up
every word I faid,and feme your face into a fubmiflive fmile -, as
I have feen a dull Gallant act. Wit, and counterfeit pleafantnefs,
when he whifpers to a great Perfon in a Play-houfe} fmile,.
and look brilkly, when the other anfwers, as if fomething
of extraordinary had pad: betwixt 'em ? when, heaven
knows, there was nothing elfe but. What a clock does your
Lordfhip think it is } and my Lord's repertee is,'Tis almoft Park-
time: or, at moit 3 Shall we out of the Pit, and go behind the
Scenes for an Act or two ? And yet fuch fine thingsas thefe,
would be wit in a Miftris's mouth.

Tala. Ay, Boy? there's Dame Nature in the cafe: he who
cannot find wit in a Miftris, deferves to find nothing elfe, Boy.
But thefe are riddles to thee, child, and I have not leifure to in-
flruct thee 5 I have affairs to difpatch, great affairs} I am a man
of bufinefs.

Dor. Come ? youfhallnotgo: you have no affairs but what
you maydifpatch here, to my knowledge.

Pala.l find now, thou art a Boy of more underfranding thea
I thought thee 5 a very lewd wicked Boy : o' my conscience
thou wouldft debauch me 3 and haft fome evil defigns upon my
perfon.

Dor. 'You aremiftaken, Sir 5 I would onely have you (how
me a more lawful reafonwhy you would leave me, then I can
why you fhould not, and I'll not flay you, for I am not fo
young., but I underftand the neceffities of flefh and bloud.;

I 2 'and



60 *5M bridge aJd'Adode.

and the preffing occafions of mankind, as well as you.

Tala. A very forward and underftanding Boy ! Thou art in
great danger of a Pages wit, to be brifk at 14, and dull at 20,
But I'll give thee no further account 5 I mud, and will go.

Dor. My life on' t, your Miftris is not at home,

Fala. This Imp will make me very angry.
I tell thee ? young Sir, (he isathome 5 and at home for me 5 and,
which is more, (he is abed for me, andfickfor me.

Dor. Foryouonelyi?

Tala, Ay, for me onely.

Dor, But how do you know (he's fick abed }

Tola, She fent her Husband word fo.

Dor, And are you fuch a novice in Love, to believe a Wife's
meiTage to her Husband >

Tala. Why, what the devil fhould be her meaning elfe >

Dor, It may be 3 to go in Mafquerade as well as you 5 to ob-
ferve your haunts and keep you company without your know-
ledge.

Tala, Nay, 111 truft her for that .* (lie loves "me too well, to
difguife her fe If from me.

Dor, If I were (he, I would difguife on purpofe to try your
wit 3 and come to my fervant like a Riddle, Read me, and
take me.

Tala, I could know her in any lhape : my good Genius
would prompt me to find out a handfome woman: there's
fomething in her, that would attract me to her without my
knowledge.

Dor. Then you make aLoad-ftone ofyour Miftris?

Tala. Yes, and I carry Steel about me, which has been fo of-
ten touch'd, that it never fails to point to the North Pole.

Dor. Yet ftill my mind gives me, that you have met her dif-
guis'd tonight, and have not known her.

Tala. This is the moft pragmatical conceited little fellow, he
will needs underftand my bufinefs better then my felf. I tell
thee, once more, thou dolt not know my Miftris.

Dor. And I tell you, once more, that I know her better then
you do.

Tala, The Boy's refolv'd to have thelaft word,

I find



Marriage a-Ia-Mode. ^ tf r

I find I mufl: go without reply. Wxiu,

Dor. Ah mifchief, I have loft him with my fooling. Palamede,
Palamede.

Be returns, sht plucks off her Perruke, and puts Hon
again when he knows her.

Pala, O Heavens ! is it you. Madam ?

Dor. Now, where was your good Genius, that would prompt
you to find me out?

Pala. Why, you feel was- not deceiv'd 5 you, your felf,
were my good Genius.

Dor, But where was the Steel, that knew the Load-ftone >
ha>

Pala. The truth is, Madam, the Steel has loft its vertuej and:
therefore, if you pleafe, we'll new touch it.

Enter Rhodophil $ and Melantha in Boys habit. RhodophiL
fees Palamede kijfing DoraliceV hand.

Rho. Palamede again ! am I fall'n into your quarters ? What ?
ingaging with a Boy } is all honourable ?

Pala, O, very honourable on my fide. I was juft chaftifing
this young Villain ■> he was running away, without paying his
fhare of the reckoning.

Rho. Then I find I was deceiv'd in him.

Pala.Yes, you are deceiv'd in him ,* 'tis the archeft rogue, if
you did but know him.

Mel. Good. Rhodophil, let us get offial-a derohhle, for fear I
fhould be difcover s d.

Rho. There's no retiring now j I warrant you for difcovery i
now have I the oddeft thought, to entertain you before your-
Servants face, and he never the wifer 5 'twill be the prettieft jug-
ling trick to cheat him when he looks upon us^

Mel, This is the ftrangeft caprice in you*

Pala. (To Doralice) This Rhodophil s the unluckieft fellow to
me ! this is now the fecond time he has bar'd the Dice when we
were juft ready to have nick'd him 3 but if ever I get the Box
again- ~*_^ dm..



6% Marriage a- la-Mode.

Dor. Do you think he will not know me?
Amllikemyfelf?

Fala. No more then a Pi&ure in the Hangings.

Dor. Nay., then he can never difcoverme, now the wrong fide
of the Arras is turn'd towards him.

rala. At leaft, 'twill be Come pleafure to me, to enjoy what
freedom I can whilehe looks on j I will ftorm the Out- works of
Matrimony even before his face.

Rho, What Wine have you there, Falamede?

Fala. Old Chios > or the rogue's damnM.that drew it.

Rho.. Come, to the moil: conftant of MiftreiTes, that I believe
is yours, Falamede.

Dor. Prayfpare your Seconds $ for my part I am but a weak
Brother.

Fala. Now,tothe trueft of Turtles $ that is your Wife, Rho-
dophil that lies fick at home, in the bed of honour.

Rho. Now let's have one common health, and fo have done.

,Dor. Then, for once, I'll begin it. Here's to him that has the
faired Lady of Sicily inMafquerade to night.

Tala. This is fuch an obliging healthj'llkifs thee, dear Rogue,
for thy invention. [.^ijjes her.

Rho. He who has this Lady, is a happy man, without difpute.
-I'm mod concern'd in this, lam fure. Q Afide.

Tala. Was it not well found out, Rhodophil?

Mel. Ay, this was bientrouve'e indeed.

Dor. (fo Melantha,) I fuppofe I (hall do youa kindnefs to en-
quire if you have not been in France, Sir }

Mel. To do you fervice. Sir.

Dor. O, Monfieur, vol valet bien humble. £ Saluting her.

Mel, Votre efclaue^ Monfieur^ de tout Mon Cceur.

[ Returning thefalute.

Dor, I fuppofe, fweet Sir, you are the hope and joy of fome
thriving Citizen, who has pinch'd himfelf at home, to breed
you abroad, where you have learnt your Exercifes, as it ap-
pears moft aukwardly, and are returned with the addition of/a
new-lac'd bofom and a Clap, to your good old father, who
looks at you with his mouth, while you (pout French with your
Man Monfieur..

Fala.



Marriage a*U>-Mode. <d$

Pala. Let me kifs thee again for that, dear Rogue.

Mel. And you, I imagine, are my young Matter, whom your
Mother durft not truft upon fait water, but left you to be your
own Tutour at fourteen, to be very brisk and entreprenant^ to
endeavour to be debauch'd ere you have learnt the knack
©n't, to value your felf upon a Clap before you can get it, and
to make it the height of your ambition to get a Player for
your Miftrfeo-

Rho. (embracing Mel. ) O dear young Bully, thou haft tickled
him with a repertee i'faith.

Mel. You are one of thofe that applaud our Countrey Plays>.
where drums, and trumpets, and bloud, and wounds, are wit.

Bho. Again^my Boy Met me kifs thee moft abundantly.

Dor. You are an admirer of the dull French Poetry, which
is fo thin P that it is the very Leaf-gold of Wit, the very Wa-
fers and whip'd Cream of fenfe, for which a man opens his
mouth and gapes, to fwallow nothing .• and to be an admirer
of fuch profound dulnefs, one muft be endow'd with a great
perfection of impudence and ignorance.

Pala. Let me embrace thee rnoft vehemently.

Mel. 1*11 facrifice my life for French Poetry. ^Advancing.

Dor. I'll die upon thefpotfor our Countrey Wit.

Bho. ( to Melantha. ) Hold, hold, young Mars ■; Palamede^
draw back your Hero.

Pala. 'Tis times I fhall be drawn in fora Second elfe at the
wrong weapon.
- Mel. O that I were a man for thy fake !

Dor . You'll be a man a s foon as I (rial V

Enter a Mejjengerto Rhodophih

MdeffiSiti the King has inflant buiiuefs withyoUo
1 fawthe Guard drawn up-by your Lieutenant
Before the Palace-gate, ready to march.

Rhod. 'Tis fomewhat fodain > fay that Jam coming.

Q Exit MeJJenger*
Now, Valamede^ what think y ou-.of this fport }
This is fome fuddain tumult .* will you along!

Pala.'



Tata* Yes, yes, I will go 5 but the devil take me if ever I was
lefs in humour. Why, the pox, could they not'-have ftaid their
tumult till to morrow ? then I had done my bufinefs, and been
ready for 'em. Truth is, I had a little tranfitory crime to have
committed firft ? and I am the word man in the world at repent-
ing^till a (in be throughly done : but what (hall we do with the
two Boys ?

Rho. Let them take a lodging in the houfe till the bufinefs be
over.

Dor, What, lie with a Boy > for my part, I own it, I cannot
endure to lie with a Boy.

Pala, The more's my forrow, I cannot accommodate you with
abetter bed-fellow.

Mel .Let me die, if I enter into a pair of (beets with him that
hates the French,

Dor. Pifh, take no care for us, but leave us in the ftreets 5 I
warrant you, as late as it is, I'll find my lodging as well-as any
drunken Bully of 'email.

Rho, Til fight in meer revenge, and wreak my paffion [Ajide.
On all that fpoil this hopeful affignation.

Pala. I 'm fure we fight in a good quarrel:
Rogues may pretend Religion, and the Laws 5
But a kind Miftris is the Good old Caufe. f Exeunt.

SCENE IV.

Enter Palmyra, Eubulus, Hermogenes.

Tain/. You tell me wonders 5 that Leonids
h Prince Theagenes, the late King's Son.

Eub. It feem'd as ftrange to him, as now to you,
Before I had convine'd him j But, befides
His great refemblance to the King his Father,
The Queen his Mother lives, fecur'd by me
In a Religious Houfe h to whom each year
I brought the news of his increafing virtues.
My laft long abfencefrom you both, was caus'd

By



Marriage aM-Mode.

By wounds which, in my journey, I receiv'd,
W hen fet upon by thieves 3 1 loft thofe Jewels
And Letters, which your dying Mother left.

Her, Thefamehe means, which, fince, brought to the Kiflgj
Made him firft know he had a Child alive ;
'Twas then my care of Prince Leonidas
Caus'd me to fay he was th'UfurpersSon 3
Till 3 after fore d by your apparent danger
I made the true difcovery of your birth,
And once more hid my Prince's.



[Exennt ambo.



•



Enter Leonidas.

Leon, HertnogeneS) and Enbulus^ retire 5
Thofe of our party, whom I left without,
Expect your aid and counfel.

Palm, I fhould ^Leonidas, congratulate
This happy change of your exalted fate 3

But, as my joy, fo you my wonder move 5
Your looks have more of Bufinefs,then of Love :
And your laft words fome great defign did (how.

-Leon. I frame not any to be hid from you.
You, in my love, all my defigns may fee 3
But what have love and you defign'd for me ?
Fortune, once more, has fet the ballance right »•
Firft, equalfd us. in lownefs 3 then, in height.
Both of us have fo long, like Gamefters, thrown,
Till Fate comes round, and gives to each his own,
As Fate is equal, fo may Love appear :
Tell me, at lea ft, what I muft hope, or fear,

Palm, After fo many proofs, how can you call
My love in doubt? Fear nothing 3 and'hope, all,
Think what a Prince, with honour, may receive,
Or I may give, without a Parents leave.

Leon, You give, and then reftrain the grace you (how 5
As oftentatious Priefts, when Souls they wooe,
Promife their Heavn to all, but grant to few.
But do for me, what I have dar*d for you.

K I did



£6 Marriage a la-Mode,

I did no argument from duty bring :
Duty's a Name \ and Love's a Real thing.

Palm. Man's love may, like wild torrents, over- flow*
Woman's as deep, but in its banks muft go.
My love is mine , and that I can impart ■>
But cannot give my perfon, with my heart.

Leon. Your love is then no gift :
For when the perfon it does not convev,
Tis to give Gold., and not to give the Key.

Palm. Then afk my Father.

Leon —He detains my Throne :

Who holds back mine, will hardly give his own.

Palm. What then remains r

Leon .That I muft have recourfe

To Arms 5 and take my Love and Crown, by force.

Hermogenes is forming the defign ,

And with him, all the brave and loyal joyn.

Palm. And is it thus you court Palmyra's bed >
Can (he the murd'rer of her Parent wed >
Defift from force : fo much you well may give
To Love, and Me, to let my Father live.

Leon. Each aft of mine my love to you has fhown 5
But you, who tax my want of it, have none.
You bid me part with you, and let him live $
But they fhould nothing afk, who nothing give.

Palm, I give what vertue and what duty can,
In vowing ne'rtowed another man.

Leon. You will be forc'd to be Argaleons wife.

Palm. I'll keep my promife, though I lofe my life.

Leon. Then you lofe Love, for which we both contend 3
For Life is but the means, but Love's the end.

Palm. Our Souls (hall love hereafter.

Leon. m 1 much fear, j?

That Soul which ccu'd deny the Body here, >

To tafte of love, would be a niggard there. ^

Palm. Then 'tis paft hope : our cruel fate, I fee,
Will make a fad divorce 'twixt you and me.

For, if you force employ, by Heav'n I fwear,

And



Marriage a3a+ Wmi f $j

And all blefVd Beings, •

Lew*- — — ■ — Your ra(h Oath forbear . J

Palm. 1 never „....—

Leon* Hold once more. But, yet, as he

Who fcapes a da dang'rous leap, looks back to fee 3

So T defire. now I am pafl: my fear.

To know what was that Oath ou meant to fwear;

Palm. I meant that if you hazarded yom life^
Or fought mv Father s,ne'r to be your Wife.

Leon, See now. Palmyra^ how unkind you prove 1
Could yon D with fo much eafe, mi (wes r nvy f< jve ?

P^/«?. You force me with your ruinous defign.

Zei*. Your Fathers life is more your care, then Mine.

Palm. You wrong me: 'tisnot$ though it ought to be 5
You are mv Care, heav'n knows, as well as he*"

Leov \ f now the execution I delay,
My H -nr and my Subjedts, I betray.
All < b p :r'd for the juffc enterprize 5
And the whole City will to morrow rife.
The Leaoers of the party are within.
And Enhulns has fworn that he will bring.
To head their Arms, the perfon of their King.

Valm. In telling this, you make me guilty too 3
1 therefore muftdifcover what I know:
What Honour bids you do, Nature bids me prevent 3
But kill me firft, and then purfue your black intent.

Leon, Palmyra^ no • you (hall not need to die 3
Yet I'll not truftfo ftridl: apiety.
Within there.

'Enter Eubulus. *-

"■•.:•■ mI-A

Enbnlm^ a Guard prepare 3



Here, I commit this pris*ner to your care.

{_ Kijfes Palmyra'/ hand 5 then gives it to Eubulus*
Palm. LeonitiaS) I never thought thefe bands
Could e'r be giv'n me by a Lovers hands.

Leon. Palmyra) thus your Jujge himtelf arraigns 3 \kmeling,

K2 He



6$ Marriage kAa^Mode.

He who impos'd thefe bonds, dill wears your chains:
When you to Love or Duty falfe muft be,
Or to your Father guilty, or to me, 3

Thefe chains, alone., remain to fet you free. 5

[ Noife of fwords clajhing.

Poly, (within*) Secure thefe, firft 5 then fearch the inner room.

teou. From whence do thefe tumultuous clamours come?

Enter Hermogenes, hajiily]

Her, We are betray 'd -■> and there remains alone
Thiscomfort 3 that your perfonk not known.

Enter the King, Argaleon, RhodophiI,Palamede, <?//<#<& 5
fome like Citizens as prifoners.

Poly. What mean this midnight-confultations here, !

Where I, like an unfummon s d gueft, appear?

Leon. Sir

Arga, „T here needs no excufe 5 'tis underftood 3

You were all watching, for your Prince's good.

Poly, My reverend City- friends, you are well met \
On what great work were your grave wifdoms fet i
Which of my actions were you fcanning here?
What French invafion have you found to fear?

Leon, They are my friends } and come, Sir, with intent
To take their leaves before my banifrrment.

Poly, Your exile, in both fexes friends can find :
I fee the Ladies, like the men, are kind. [Seeing Palmyra.

Palm, Alas, I came but .— . [kjieelingo

Poly, , — Addenot to your crime

A lie: I'll hear you fpeak fome other time.
How? Eubulusl nor time, nor thy difguife,
Can keep thee, undifcover'd, from my eyes.
A Guard there $ fejze 'em all.

Rbo. Yjekl^Sir 3 whatufe of valour can be fhown?



Pal. 0ne ? aiadunarrn'd o agamfta multitude J

G£or



Marriage aM'Mode* gp

for a fword !

[He reaches at one of the Guards Halberds , andisfeiz?d behind.

, 1 wnot lofe my breath

In fruitlefs pray'rs 3 butbegafpeedy death,

jWztf.Ofpare Leonidas, and puniftime.

Toly. Mean Girl, thou want'ftan Advocate for thee.
Now themyfteriousknot willbeunty'd 5
Whether the young King lives, or where he dy'd ;
Tomorrows dawn (hall the dark riddle clears
Crown all my joys 3 and diffipate my fear. [Exeunt omnes.



ACT V. SCENE I.



••



Palamede, Straton. PaJarnede with a Letter
jn his hand.

Pal. >"TpHis evening, fay'ft thou? will they both be here >
1 Stra. Yes Sir 5 both my old Matter, and your Mi
ftris's Father: the old Gentlemen ride hard this journey • thev
fay, it (hall be the laft time they will fee the Towns and' both
of 'em are fopleas'd with this marriage, which they have con-
cluded for you, that I am afraid they will live fome years long-
er to trouble you, with the joy of it. P
Pal. But this is fuch an unreafonable thing, to impofe upon
-me to be.marri'd to morrow 5 'tis hurrying a man to execution
Without giving him time to fay his pray'rs. '
Stra. Yet, if I might ad vife you, Sir, you (houldnot delay it •
tor your younger Brother comes up with 'em, and is got alrea-
dy into their favours. He has gain'd much upon my old Ma-
tter, by finding fault with Inn-keepers Bills, and by ftarving
us,andourHorfes, to (how his frugality; and he is very well
i**th your Miftris's Father, by giving him Receipts for the
^ptene, Gout, and Scurvy, and other infirmities of old age.
^4/JE'Jl rout,him D andhtt Countrey education : Pox on him,

Iremember



7© Marriage a. la-Mode.

I remember him before I travell'd, he had nothing in him but
meer Jocky \ us'd to talk loud, and make matches, and was all
for the crack of the field : fenfe and wit were as much banifrYd
from his difcourfe, as they are when the Court goes out of
Town to a Horfe-race. Go now and provide your Matter's
Lodgings.

Stra. Tgo, Sir. [Exit.

Tal. It vexes me to the heart, to leave all my defigns with
Z>oralicc unfinifh'd 5 to have flown her fo often to a mark, and
frill to be bob'd at retriever if I had but once enjoy'd her,
though I could not have fatisfi'd my ftomach. with thefeaft, at
leaft I (hould have reliQYd my mouth a little > but now- »

Enter Philotis.

ThiL .Oh, Sir 3 you are happily met 5 I was coming to find
.' you.

Pal. From your Lady, I hope.

Phil. Partly from her '■> but moreefpecialiv from my felf : (he
has juft now receiv'd a Letter from her Fathet, with an abfo-
lute command to difpofe her felf to marry you to morrow.

Pal. And (he takes it to the death }

ThiL Quite contrary .* the Letter could never have come in
a more lucky minute ; for it found her in an ill humour with a
Rival of yours, that (hall be namelefs, about the pronuncia-
tion of a French word.

Pal. Count Rhodophil 5 never difguife it, T know the Atnvitr :
but I hope you took the occafion to ftrike in for me ?

Phil. It was my good fortune to do you fome fmall fervice in
it 5 for your fake I difcommended him all over : cloaths, per-
fon. humour, behaviour, every thing} and to fumup all, told
her,It was impoflible to find a marri'd man that was otherwife 5
for they were all fo mortifi'd at home with their wives ill
humours, that they could never recover themfelvesto be com-
pany abroad.

Pal. Mod divinely urg'd !

Phil. Then T took occafion to commend your good quali
ties: as y the fweetnefs of your humour, the comelinefs of your

perfon,






Marriage aM^Mode, j\

perfon, your good Meene, your valour 5 but, above all, your
liberality.

Pal. I vow to Gad I had like to have forgot that good qua-
lity in my felf, if thou had'fl: not reraember'd me on't : here are
five Pieces for thee,

Phil. Lord, you have the fofteft hand, Sir ! it would do a
woman good to touch it : Count RhodophiFs is not half fo foft 5
for I remember I felt it once, when he gave me ten Pieces for
my New-years gift.

Pal. O, I underftand you. Madam } you (hall find my hand as
foft again as Count Rhodophil's: there are twenty Pieces for*
you. The former was but a Retaining Fees now I hope youl
plead for me.

Phil. Your own merits fpeak enough. Be fure onely to ply
Her with French words , and TIL warrant you'll do your bu-
finefs. Here are a lift of her phrafes for this day : ufe s em to her
upon all occafions, and foil her at her own weapon 3 for fhe's
like oneofthe old Amazons^ (he'l nevermarry, except itbethe
man who has firft conquer'd her.

Pal. I'll be fure to follow your advice : but you'll forget to
further my defign.

Phil. What,doy:ou think I'll be ungrateful? •'

But, however, if you diftruft my memory, putforae to- -

ken on my finger to remember it by : that Diamond there
would do admirably.

Pal. There 'tis 3 and I a(k your pardon heartily for calling ;
your memory into queftion: I allure you I'll truft it another-
time, without putting you to the trouble of another token.

Enter Palmyra and Artemis.

Art. Madam, this way the prifoners are to pafs 5
Here you may fee Leonidas.
Palm, Then here 111 ftay, and follow him to death. •



Enter



y% Marriage a<la*Mode*

Enter Melantha haflily.

Mela. ; here's her Highnefs !
Now is my time to introduce my felf, and to make my court to

her, in my new French phrafes. Stay, let me read my catalogue

fuitte^ figure 3 chagrin , naivete, and let me die for the Parenthefts
ofall.

Pal.(afide) Do, perfecute her 5 and Til perfecutetheeas faft
in thy own dialed.

Mel. Madam the Princefs ! let me die 5 but this is a moft hor-
rid fpedtacle, to fee a perfon who makes fo grand a figure in the
Court, without the Suitte of a Princefs, and entertaining your
Chagrin all alone 5 (Naivete (hould have been there, but the dis-
obedient word would not come in. )
Palm. What is (he, Artemis ?

Art. An impertinent Lady, Madam 3 very ambitious of being
known to your Highnefs.

Pal. (to Melantha ) Let me die, Madam, if I have not waited
you here thefe two long hours, without fo much as the sttitte
ofafingle Servant to attend me $ entertaining my felf with my
own Chagrin^ till I had the honour to fee your Ladifhip, who
are a perfon that makes fo conflderable a figure in the Court. '
Mel. Truce with your douceurs , good fervant 3 you fee I am

addreffing to the Princefs 5 pray do not cmbarrafs me-

embarrafsmel what a delicious French word do you make me
lofe upon you too !

(To the Princefs') Your Highnefs, Madam, will pleafe to par-
don the 'Eevaie which I made, in not fooner finding you out to
be a Princefs; but let me die if this Eclaircifjemcnt which is
made this day of your quality, does not ravilh me 3 and give

me leave to tell you —

Pal. But fii ft give me leave to tell you, Madam, that I have
fo great a tender for your perfon, and fuch afanchant to do

you fervice, that —

Mel. What, muft 1 ftill be troubled with your Sottifes?
(There's another word loft, that I meant for the Princefs, with

a mifchief to you ^) But your Highnefs, Madam .

Pah But your Ladifhip, Madam- — — Enter



Marriage aAa-Mode. 75

■

Enter Leonidas guarded, and led over the Stage.

! ■-

Mel. Out upon him, how he looks. Madam ! now he's found
no Prince, he is the ftrangeft figure of a man 5 how could I
make that Coup d' etourdy to think him one >

Palm. Away, impertinent— My dear Leonidas l

Leon. My dear. Palmyra!

Palm. Death (hall never part us 5
My Deftiny is yours. £ He fried off $ fie follows.

Mek Impertinent! Oh I am the mod unfortunate perfbn
this day breathing: that the Princefs (hould thus rornpre en
vijiere. without Gecafion. Let me die but 1 11 follow her to death,,
till I make my peace.

Pal. (holding her) And let me die, but I'll follow you to the
Infernal s till you pity me.

Mel. ( turning towards him angrily) Ay, 'tis long of you that
this Malheur is fall'n upon me , your impertinence has put me
out of the good graces of the Princefs, and all that, which has
ruin'd me and all that, and therefore let me die but I'll be re«
veng'd, and all that.

Pal.Fa^on, fa$on, you muft and (hall love me, and all that 3
for my old man is coming up, and all that $ and I am defefperi
an dernier, and will not be disherited, and all that.

Mel. How durftyou interrupt me fo mal apropos, when you
knew I wasaddreffing to the Princefs }

Pal. But why would you addrefs your felf fo much a contrt*
temps then }

Mel. Ah mal pejie I

Pal. Ah I* enrage!

phil.Radotfofiezwus, de grace, Madame '-, vous Hes bien en cole-
re pour peu de chofe. Vonsn entendezpasla raillerie gall ante,

Mel. Ad* antres, ad' autres : he mocks himfelf of me, he abufes
me : ah me unfortunate ! [cries!

Phil You miftake him. Madam, he does but accommodate
his phrafe to your refin'd language. Ah, quil eji un Cavalier ac-
complyl purfue your point. Sir . [To him.

Pal. Ah qftilfait beau dans ces boccages 5 [ Singing.

L Ah



74 Marriage a4^Mcd$.

Ah que le del donne un bean jour !

Therel vvasw'ithyou v .witha^^«/^ . ' ,.

Mel. Let me die now, but this finging is fine, and extremely
French in him.* [Lttfghs.

But then, that he (hould ufe my own words, as it were in con-
tempt of me, I cannot bear it. tptjfyg*

Tal.CabeauxfejtMrs>cesidQUxramxges~ — , \jSifjging*

Mel. Ces beaux Sejours, cesdoux ravages, {singing after him.
Ces beaux fej ours, nous i'nvitent a V amour ! Let me die but he
angs'.etf Cavalier'&nd fo humours the Cadence. [_ L <Mghing,

Vol. Voy^naClymene, voy Jbubsce ihejhe Ringing again;

$' evmbaifer ces oifeaux amoreuxl Let me die now, but that
was fine. Ah. now, for three or four brifk Frenchmen, to be
put into Mafquing habits, and to fing it on a Theatre, how
witty it would be! and then to dance helter skelter to a Chanfon
aboire: toute la tern, toute U terre eji a moyl what's matter
though it were made, and fung, two or three years ago in Ca-
karets^howit would attra&the admiration ; efpecially of every
one that's an eveil/el

Mel. Well, 1 begin to have a tender for you , but yet, up*

on condition, that — when we are marri'd, you __

[Pal. fings, while fie fpeakj.

Vhil. You muft drown her voice : if (he makes her French
conditions, you are a Have forever.

Mel. Firft, will you engage i that

Pal. Fa, la, la, la, 8cc. [Louderl

Mel. Will you hear the conditions ?

Vol. Mo 5 I will hear no conditions! I am refolv'd to win
you en Francois ■ to be very aiery, with abundance of noife,
and no fenfe : Fa, la, la, la, 8cc.

MeU Hold, hold: I am vanquifh'd with your gayete d'efprit.
I am yours, and will be yours, fans nulie referve^ ny condition :-
and let me die, if I do not think my felf the happieft Nymph in

Sicily My dear French Dear, ftay butAmi?juite t till 1 rac-

com t»odc my felf with the Princefs , and then I am youvsijuff

a la mort.

Allans done • . ■ \ Exeunt Mel. Phi Jot*

Pal. (Solus, fanning himfelf with hi shst) I never thought be-
fore



| fore that wooing was fo laborious' an exercife $ if. (he were
worth a' : million, I have deferv'd her j and now, me-thinks
too 3 with taking all this pains for her, I begin to like her. 'Tis
fo ( 3 1 have known many, who neyer car'd for Hare nor Par-
tridge, but tjhpfe they caught themfelves would ; eat heartily:
the pains* and the ftory a man tells of the taking of 'em, makes
t^.meat go down more pleafantly. Beiides, la ft night I had
a fweet dream of her, and, Gad, (he I have once dream'd of ; f
am ftark mad till I enjoy her., let her be never fo ugly.

mm k ■■■-■ ■- ' ii£Oi fi' c-i

n\kd* .Biter Doralice,
• . : ' .' \3ft1W all ■ ■ .

iDor. Who's that you are (b mad to enjoy, Palamede .3

Pal. You may earn 1 y imagine that, fweet Doralicti ■.

Dor. More eaftly theri youshink I can : : I met jufts now with
a certain man, who came to you with Letters, from a certain
©Id Gentleman, y clipped your father 5 whereby I am given to
underftand, that to morrow you are to take an Oath in the
Church to be grave henceforward, to go ill-drefs'd and flovenly 3
to get heirs for your eftate 3 and to dandle 'em for your diver-
(torn v ! and, in ihort^ that Love and Courtftiip are, to be no
more.

Pal. Now have I fomuch fhame to be thus apprehended in
the manner, that I can neither fpeak nor look upon you -, I have
abundance of grace in me, that I find .* But if you have any
fpark of true friendship in you, retire a little with me to the
next room, that has a couch orbed in't, and beftowyour cha-
rity upon a poor dying man: a little comfort from a Miftris^'
before a man is going to give himfelf in Marriage, is as good
asalufty dofe of Strong-water to a dying Malefa&our 3 it takes
away the fenfeof hell, and hanging from him.

Dor, No,good Falamede, Imuft not be fo injurious to your
Bride: 'tis ill drawing from the Bank to day, when all your
ready money is payable to morrow.

Pal. A Wife is onely to have the ripe fruit, that falls of it
felf 3 but a wife man will always prefer ve a (baking for a
Miftris. r I ...

Dw-JBmta Wife for the firft quarter is a Miftris.

L 2 Tal.



j6 £\dwriage : a^ Model

Prf/.But wrrenthe fecond comes.

Dor. When it does come, you are fo given to variety, that yt_
would make a Wife of me in another quarter.

Pal. No, never, except I were married to you ; marri'd peo*
pie can never oblige one another $ for all they do is duty, and
confequently there can be no thanks : but love is more frank
and generous then he is honeft$ he's a liberal giver, but a
curfedpay-mafter.

Dor. 1 declare f will hare no Gallant ■> but, if I would, he
fhould never be a marri'd man 5 a marri'd man is but a Miftris's
faalf-fervant, as a Clergy-man is but the King's half- fubj eft: for
a man to come to me that fmells o' th' Wife / s s life, I wou d as
loon wear heroldGown after her, as her Husband.

Pal. Yet Visa kind offafhionto wear a Princefs ca ft (hoes,
you fee the Countrey Ladies buy 'em to be fine in them.

Dor. Yes, a Princefs (hoes may be worn after her, becaufe
they keep their fafhion, by being fo very little us'd> but gene-
rally a marri'd man is the creature of the world the moft out
of fafhion > his behaviour is dumpifb, his difcourfe his wife
and family, his habit fo much negle&ed, it looks as if that were
marri'd too , -his Hat is marri'd, his Perruke is marri'd, his
Breeches are marri'd,and if we could look within his Breeches,
we fhould'find him marri'd there too.

Pal. Ami then to be difcarded forever? pray do but mark
how terrible that word founds ■> For ever ! it has a very
damn'd found, Doralice.

Dor. Ay, forever! it founds as hellifbly to me, as itcan do
to you, but there's no help for't. -

Pal. Yet if we had but once enjoy'd one another 5 but then
onceonely, is worfethen not at all: it leaves a man with fuch
a lingring after it.

ZX-r.For ought I know 'tis better that we have not 3 we
might upon trial have lik'd each other lefs, as many a man and
woman, that have lov'd as defperately as we, and yet when
they came to pofieffion, have figh'd 3 and cri'd to themfelves.,
kthisall>

Pal. That ;s onely, if the Servant were not found a man of
ah-is world , butif, upon irial, we bad not lik'd each other we

had



Marriage aAa-Mode. yj

h&d certainly left loving 5 and faith, tint's the greater happi-
nefs of the two.

Dor. J Tis better as 'tis j we have drawn off already as much
of our Love as would run clear 5 after pofleffing, the reft is
but jea!oufies y and difquietSi, and quarrelling, and piecing.

Pal, Nay, after one great quarrel, there's never any found
piecing, the love is apt to break, in the fame place again.

Dor. I declare I would never renew a love $ that's like him
who trims an old Coach for ten years together, he might buy
a new one better cheap.

Pal. Well, Madam, I am convinced, that 'tis befi: for us not
to have enjoy'd 3 but Gad, the ftrongeft reafonis, becaufe I
eann'c help it.

Dor. Theonely way to keep us new to one another, is never
to enjoy,as they keep grapes by hanging 'em uponaline, they
muft touch nothing i f you would preferve 'emfrefh.

Pal. But then they wither, and grow dry in the very keeping >
however I (hall havea warmth for you, and an eagernefs, every
time I fee you 5 and if I chance to out-live Melantha --• t

Dor. And if I chance to out-live Rhodophil .

Pal, Well, I'll cherifh my body as much as I can upon that
hope. Tis true, I would not direftly murder the wife of my
bofomej but to kill her civilly, by the way of kindnefs. 111 put
as fair as another man : I'll begin to morrow night, and be very
wrathful with her 5 that's refolv'don*

Dor, Well, Palamede, here's my hand, Til venture to beyour
fecond Wife, for all your threatnings.

Pal. In the mean time Til watch you hourly^ as I would the
. rif>enefsof a Melon, and I hope you'll give me leave now and
then to look on you, and to fee if you are not ready to be
cut yet.

Dor. No, no, thatmuft not be, Pahmede^ for fear the -Gardener
Should come and catch you taking up the glafs.

Enter RhodophiL -

Kho. (Afide) Billing fo fweetly! now I am confirm'd in my
fulgieions^ I mud put an end to this, ere it go fethes?; £4/^ e *

0>'



j% Marriage a-la^Mode*

.- ( To Dor dice ) Cry you mercy, Spoufe 5 I fear I have vakti*
rupted your recreations.

Dor. Whatrecreatioas?

Rho. Nay, noexcufes, good Spoufe 5 Ifaw fair hand convey'd
to lip, and preft, as though you had been fqueezing foft wax
together for an Indenture. Palamede^ you and I muft clear this
reckoning $ why would you have feduc'd my wife? 1

pal. Why would you have debauch'd my Miftris I

Rho. What do you think of that civfl couple, that play'd at
a Game call'd. Hide and Seek, laft evening, in the Grotto >

Pal, What do you think of that innocent pair, who made it
their pretence to feek for others, but came, indeed, to hide
themfelves there ?

■Rho. Ml things confider'd, I begin vehemently to fufpec}
that the young Gentleman I found in your company laft night,
was a certain youth of my acquaintance.

Pal, And I have an odd imagination, that you could never
have fufpe&ed my fmall Gallant, if your little villanous French-
man had not been a falfe Brother.

Rho. Farther Arguments are needlefss Draw off; I (hall
fpeak to you now by the way of Bilbo.

[Claps his hand to hisfword.

Pal. And I (hall anfwer youby the way of Danger-field.

£ Claps his hand on his,

D^. Hold, hold 5 are not you two a couple of mad fighting
fools, to cut one another's throats for nothing }

Pal. How for nothing > he courts the woman I muft marry.

Rho. And he courtsyou whom I havemarri'd.

Dor. But you can neither ofyou be jealous of what you love
not.

Rho. Faith I am jealous, and that makes me partly fufpecl:
that! love you better then I thought.

Dor. Pifti ! a meer jealoufie of honour;

Rho. Gad lam afraid there's fomething elfe in*t$ for Pala-
/We has wit, and if he loves you, there's fomething more in ye
then I have found.* fome rich Mine, for ought I know, that I
have not yet difcover'd.

Pal. 'S life, what's this ? here's an argument for me to love

MeUntha 3



• - Marriage \a Aa~Mo<de. ^p

Melavthtih £mWh$L$\bv& her, and he has wit too, and, for
ought I know, there may be a Mine : but, if there be, I am re-
folv'drildigfor't.

Dor. ( toRhod. ) Then I have found my account in raifing
your jealoufie : O ! 'tis the moffc delicate (harp fa wee to a cloy'd
ftomach $ it will give you a new edge, Rhodophil.
. Rho. And a new point too, Doralm 5 if I could be fure thou art
honed.

Dor. If you are wife, believe me for your own fake : Love
andReligion havebut onethingto truft to $ that's a good found
faith. Confider, if I have play'd falfe, you can never find it out
by any experiment you can make upon me.

Eho. No } Why, fuppofe I had a delicate fcrew'd Gun ; if I left
her clean, and found her foul, I (hould difcover,to my coft s (he
had been (hot in.

Dor. But if you left her clean, and found her onely rufty,
you would difcover, to your (hame, (he was onely fofor wane
offtiooting,

Fal.Rhodofhi% you know me too well, to imagine Ifpeakfor
fear 5 and therefore in confideration of ourpaft friendfhip, I
will tell you, and bind it by all things holy, that Doralice is
innocent.

Rho. Friend, I will believe you, and vow the fame for your
Melantha \ but the devil on't is, how we (hall keep 'em {0.

Pal. What doft think of a blefled community betwixt us four,
for the folace of the women, and relief of the men ? Methinks
it svouldbe a pleafant kind of life: Wife and Husband for the
ftanding DiCh, and Miftris and Gallant for theDefert.

Rhod. But fuppofe the Wife and the Miflns fhould both long
for the ftanding Difb 3 how foould they be fatisfi'd together >

Pal. Infuch a cafe they muftdraw lots t and yet that would
not do neither 5 for they would both be wifhing for the long-
eft out }

Rho. Then I think, Palamede : we had as good make a firm
League, not to invade each others propriety.

Pal. Content, fay I. From henceforth let all ads of hoftility
ceafe betwixt us 5 and that in the ufual form of Treaties, as
well by Sea as by Land 3 and in all Fre(h waters,

Dor,



8 o . Marriage a 4a~Mode.

Dor. I will addebut one Provifo> That who ever breaks the
League, either by war abroad, or by negle&at home, both the
Women (hall revenge themfelves, by the help of the other
party. -

Rho. That's but reafonable. Come away, Dor dice 5 I ha
a great temptation to be fealing Articles in private.

Palam. Haft thou fo ? [Clap him on thefoonlder.

Fall on, Machdnjjl
And curftbe he that rlrft cries, Hold, enough.

Enter Polydamas, Palmyra, Artemis, Argaleon : after them,
Eub ulus 3 and Hermogenes, guarded*

Palm. Sir, on my knees I beg you.
' Vol, Away, I'll hear no more.

Palm, For my dead Mother's fake 5 you fay you Iov 3 dJher 9
And tell me I refemble her. Thus (he
Hadbegg'd.

Pol , — — -And thus had I deny'd her.

Palm. You muft be merciful.

Arga. — You muft be conftant.

Pol. Go, bear 'em to the torture, you have boafted
You have a King to head you : I would know
To whom I muft refign.

Enb, This is our recompeace

Forferving thy dead Queen.

Her.* And education

Of thy daughter.

Arga. You are too modeft, in not naming all
His obligations to you : why did you
Omit his Son., the Prince Leonidas?

Pol. Thatlmpofture
I had forgot ^ their tortures (hall be doubled.

Her, You pleafeme, Iihall die thefooner.

Eub. No '■> could I livean age, and ftill be rack'd,
I ftill would keep the fecret.

£ As the) are going off^

Enter



Marriage a~ld*Model 81

. ■ . . • _

E**er Leomdas^r^-

.' '
Law. Oh whither do you hurry inn ce!

If you have any juftice, fpare their live* , *

Or if I cannot make you juft, at Ieaft

I'll teach you to tuorepurpofeto be cruel.

Palm. Alas, what does he feek !

Leon, Make me the objecl: of your hate and vengeance t
Are thefe decrepid bodies worn to ruine,
Juft ready, of themfelves, to fall afunder,
And to let drop the foul,
Are t* e fitfubje&s for a Rack, and Tortures >
Where would youfaften any hold upon 'em?
Place pains on me; united fix 'em here j
I have both youth, and ftrength, and foul to bear 'em :
And if they merit death, then I much more 5
Since 'tis for me they fuffer.

Her. — Heav'n forbid

We fhould redeem our pains, or worthlefs lives,
By our expofing yours.

Eub. Away with us : Farewell, Sir.
lonely fuffer in my fears for you.

Arga. So much concern'd for him ? then my [Ajtde

Sufpicion s true.

[Whifyers the King,']

Palm. Hear yet my laftrequeft, for poor Leonidash
Or take my life with his.

Arga. Reftfatisfi'd} Leonidas is he. [To the King.

Pol. I am amaz'd : what rauft be done >

Arga. Command his execution inftantly 5
Give him noc leifure to difcover it 3
He may corrupt the Soldiers.

Pol. Hence with that Traitour 3 bear him to his death :
Hafte there, and feemy will perform'd.

Leon, Nay, then Fll die like him the Gods have made me.

Hold, Gentlemen 3 I am — —

[_Argaleonyr op fos mouth.
M Argi t



3f *ZWw$#g< a4a<>Mode.

Arga. Thou art a Traitor 5 'tis not fit to hear thee.

. Leon. I fay I am the- _ [ Getting loofe a little.

Arga. So 3 gag him, add lead' him off.

[Again flopping his month.

f Leonidas, Hermogenes, Eubulus, led of.
[Polydamas ana Arga'leon follow. '■ ' r 1

Palm, Duty and Love, by turns poflefs my foul.
And druggie for a fatal victory:
I will difcover he 's the King 5 Ah, no .*
That will perhaps fave him 5
But then I am guilty of a. father's ruine.
What (hall I do. or not do? either way
I muft deftroy a Parent, or a Lover.
Break he^rt $ for that's the lead of ills to me.
And Death the onely cure. ' - [swoons

Arte. Help, help the Princefs.

Rho. Bear her gently hence, where (he may
Have more fuccour. [she is born off Arte, f off ows her.

[ Shouts toithin^ andclafhing offooras.

Vd. What noife is that ?

Enter t\ma\thea y mnn7ng,

^/#<z/.Oh,Gentleoien,if you have loyalty.
Or courage, (how it now : Leonidas
Broke on the fudden from his Guards, and hatching
A fword from one, his back againft the Scaffold,
Bravely defends himfelf 5 and owns aloud
He is our long loft King, found for this moment 3
But, if your valours help not, loft for ever.
Two of his Guards, mov'd by the fenfe of virtue,
Are turn'd for him, and there they ftandat Bay
Againft an hoft of foes.

Rho. . Madam, no more 5

Welofetime : my command, or my example,
May move the Soldiers to the better caufe.

You'll



You'll fecond me > , , J fj ^ _ ...»...- [> Pal.

Pal. Or die with you : no Subject e'r can i meet
A nobler fate^ then at, his Sovereign's feet. ^Exeunt,

£ Clajl)ing offwords witUn^ Hind flouts.

Enter Leomdas^ho^ophi^Palamedea Ei}J3ulus r; <

Hermogenes, and their ^ arty x v0 or io us t . , .,, -

Polydamas *W Argaleon, dijarmd.

Leon. That I furvive the dangers of this day,
Next to the Gods, brave friends, be yours the honour.
And let Heay'n witnefsfor me, that my joy
Is not more great for this my right'reftor'd,
Than 'tis, that I have power to recompenee
Your Loyalty and Valour. Let mean Princes
Of abjed fouls, fear to reward great a&ibns >
I mean to (how.

That whatfoe'rfubjecrs^ like you, daremerit ;
A King, like me, dares give . —

Rho. Youmakeusbldh, we have deferv'd fo little.

Pal. And yet inftrucl: us how to merit more.

Leon. And as I would be juftin my, rewards,
Sofhouldlin my punishments $ thefe two,
This the Ufurperof my Crown, the other
Of my Palmyra's love, defer ve that death
Which both dehWd for me.

Pol. • .And we expect it.

Arga. I have too long been happy to Jive wretched.

Pol, And I too long have governed, to defire
A life without an Empire.

Leon. You are Palmyras father 5 and as fuch,
Though not a King, (hall have obedience paid
From him who is one. Father, in that name,
All injuries forgot, and duty bwn*d. [Embraces him.

Pol. O, had I known you could have been this King,
Thus God-like, great and gpod,l (hould have wiuYd
T'have been dethron d before. 'Tisnow Hive,
And more then Reign 3 now all my joys flow pure,

M 2 Unmixd 1



84. Marriage a4a*Mode.

Unmix 'd with cares^and undifturb'd by confcience'

Epttr Palmyra,, Amalthea, Artemis, Doralicei
and Melantha.

Leon.Ste, my Palmyra comes ! the frighted bloud
Scarce yet recall'd to her pale cheeks.
Like the firft ftreaksof light broke loofe fronrdarknefs,

And dawning into blufhes Sir, you faid, [to Polyda.

Your joys were full} Oh, would you make minefo !
1 am but half- reftor'd without this bleffing.

Pol. The Gods, and my Palmyra,make you happy.
As you make me. [Gives her hand to Leonidas.

Ydwy. % Now all my prayers are heard:

I may be dutiful, and yet may love.'

Virtue, and patience, have at length unravelled ^

The knots which Fortune ty'd.

Mel.Let me die, but HI congratulate his
Majefty : how admirably well his Royalty
Becomes him ! ! Becomes ! that is luy fied> but our damn'd Lan-
guage ex preffes nothing. „

Pal. How } does it become him already? 'twas but juftnow
you faid, he was fuch a figure of a man^

Mel. True, my dear, when he was a private man he was a
figure j but fince he is a King, methinks he has aiTum*d another
figure : he looks fo grand,and fo Auguft.

[Going to the King.
VaU Stay, fray 5 I'll prelent you when it is more convenient.
I find I rauft get her a place at Court 5 and when (he is once
there, (he can be no longer ridiculous 5 for fhe is young enough,
and pretty enough, and fool enough, and French enough, to
bring up a fafhion there to be affected.

Leon, (to RhodophilJ Did (he then lead you to this brave
attempt ?
(To Amalthea ) To you, fair An/althea, what I am,
And what all thefe, from me, we joyntly owe :
Firft, therefore, to your great defert, we give

Your



^Marriage aM^Mode, %f

Your Brother's life * but keep him under guard.
Till our new power be fetled. What more grace
He may receive, (hall from his future carriage
Be given, as he deferves.

Arga. I neither now defire, nor will deferve it 5
My lofs is fuch as cannot be repaired.
And to the wretched, life can be no mercy.

Leon. Then be a prifoner always : thy ill fate,
And pride will have it fo : but fince^ in this, I cannot 9
Jnftructme, generous Amahhea^ how
A King may ferve you,

Amd. — I have all I hope,

And alllnowmuftwifh 5 I fee you happy.

Thofe hours I have to live, which Heav'n in pity

Will make but few^ I vow to fpend with Veftals.-

Thegreateftpart 3 in pray'rs for you 3 the reft

In mourning my unworthinefs.

Prefs me not farther to explain my felf 3

'Twill not become me, and may caufe your trouble.

Lean, Too well I underftand herfecret grie£ [^Apdei

But dare notfeem to know it. Come [ To Palmyrav.

my faireft,

Beyond my Crown, I have one Joy in ftore 5

To give that Grown to her whom I adore.

[Exeunt ommst



Epilogue.




fa




'




Not wu

Which men ofeajie Phlegme\ with care compoje*
Tour Poet's of Jiiff words , and limber fenfe\
Born on the confines of indifference.
But by examples drawn^ idaretofay^
From moji of you, who hear^ andfee'the Flay,
There are more Rhodophils in this Theatre^
More PalamedeS; and feme few Wives, I fear.
But yet too far our Toet would not run,
Though 'twas well offer d, there was nothing done*
He would not quite the Womari s frailty bare,
Butjiript 'em to the wafie, and left 'em there.
And the men's faults are lefs fcuerely fijown ,
For he confidersthat himfelj is one.
Sbmejlabbing Wits, to bloudy Satyr bent,
Would treat both Sexes with lefs complement-:
Would lay the Scene at home, of Husbands tell,
For Wenche s, taking up their Wives t th' Mel/,
And a brishJ>out which each of them did want,
Made by mifiake of Mijiris and Gallant,
Our modefi Authour, thought it was enough 
To cut you off a Sample of the fluff':
Hcfpar'dmy fiame, which you, Tmfure, would not,
For you were all for driving on the Plot :
Toufigh'd when I came in tobreak^thefport,
And jet your teeth when each defign fell 'port.
To Wives ; and. Servants all good wifies lend,
But the poor Cuckold feldom finds a friend.
Since therefore Court and Town will take no pity ,
J huwbly caft my felf 'upon the City ;

F I 3S£ I S.



RICE UNIVERSITY LIBRARY
P. O. Box 1892
Houston, Texas 77001
