
Skip to main content

    Internet Archive Logo
    web
    books
    video
    audio
    software
    images
    search

    uploadUPLOAD
    personSIGN IN

    ABOUT
    CONTACT
    BLOG
    PROJECTS
    HELP
    DONATE
    JOBS
    VOLUNTEER
    PEOPLE

Full text of "The Indian emperor, or, The conquest of Mexico by the Spaniards. Being the sequel of the Indian queen. By John Dryden, Esq"
See other formats

THE



Indian EmpefOBi*

THE CONQUEST OF



I






BY THE



SPANIARDS



Being the Sequel of the Indian Queen.




By John Dryden Efq* 5



The Third Edition.



Dum relego fcripfiffe pudtt y quia plurima cerno
Mequoque, qui feci, judice, digna lini. Ovid.



LONDON,

Printed for H. Uerringman, at the Sign of the Blew Anchor inths
Lower Walk of the New Exchange, 1670.



•) , • • .-*•... > .. - ...

. . . ... , . .-.- . . ,

.... . at .• 1 1 • •






' " "



, /.i <



3 V







To the moft Excellent and molt Illuftrious
princefs Anne Dutchefs of Monmouth,
and c Bucclugh f Wife to the moft Illuftrious
and High-born Prince fames Duke of
Monmouth,

May it pleafe your Grace,

H E favour which Heroich^plays have lately
found upon our Theaters, has been wholly de-
riydto them from the countenance and appro-
bation they have receivd at Court. The moft
eminent Perfons for Wit and Honor in the Royal Circle
having fo far owned them, that they have judgd no way
fofit as Verfe to entertain a Noble Audience, or to exprefs
a noble paffion. And amongji the reft which have been writ-
ten in this h^nd, they have beenfo indulgent to this Poem y
as to allow it no inconfider able place. Since, theref or e,t&the
Court 1 owe its fortune on the Stage • fo, being now more-
pnblichjy exposed in Print, I humbly recommend it to your
Graces ProteUion, who by all k^&wing perfons are efleemd
a Principal Ornament of the Court. But though the rank
which yon hold in the Royal Family, might diretl the Eyes
of a Poet to yon, yet your Beauty andGoodnefs only could:
detain and fix them. High ObjeBs may attraSi the fight \
hut it looks up with pain on craggy Rocl^s and Barren
Mountains ^and continues not intent on any objeB, which is
wanting infibades and greens to entertain it. Beauty, in
Qourts 7 isfo necejfary to thejonngjhat thofe who are with-

m0t



The Epiftle Dedicatory.
out it, feem to be there to no other purpofe then to wait on
the triumphs of the fair y to attend their nf&tions in ob»
fcurjty, as the Moon and Stars do the Sun by day: or, at
beft, to be the refuge of thofe hearts which others have
defpisd, and by theunworthinejsofboth, to give and
takg a mi fer able comfort. But as needful as Beauty is
Virtue, and Honour are yet more : the Reign of it with-
out their fupport is unfafe and Jhort like that of Tyrants.
Every Sun which looks on Beauty wafts it; and, when
once it is decaying, the repairs of Art are of as fbort con-
tinuance, as the after Spring, when the Sun is going far-
ther from us. This, Madam, is its ordinary Fate y but
yours which is accompanied by Virtue, is not fubjeQ to that
common deJiiny.Tour Grace has not only a long time of Youth
in which to flour ijh, but you have lihgwife found the way by
an untainted preferyation of your Honour ', to make thatpe-
rift) able good more lofting. And if Beauty, lihgWines^ could
be prefervd by being mixt and embodied with others of
their own nature, then your Graces would be immortal fince
no part of Europe can afford a paraleltoyour Noble Lord,
in mafcnlive Beauty, and in goodlinefs ofjhape. To re-
ceive the bleffings and prayers of Mankind, you need only to
b.efeen together : we are ready to conclude that you art a pair
of Angels fent below to make Virtue amiable in your p erf on s,
or to fit to Voets when they would p leaf ant ly inJlruSt the
Age^ by drawing goodnefs in the moft perfeSi and alluring
Jhape of Nature. But though Beauty be the Theme, on which
Poets loye to dwell, I muji be fore d to quit it as a private
praij efface you have defer vd thofe which are more pub-
lick. For Goodnefs and Humanity, which Jhine in yon, are

Virtues



The EpifHe Dedicatory.

Virtues which concern Mankind : and, by a certain hind of
interefl, all people agree in their commendation, becaujejhe
profit of them may extend to many. 'Tisfo much your in*
clination to do good, that you flay not to be ask^d; which
is an approach fo nigh the Deity , that Humane Nature
is not capable of a nearer. 'Tis my Happinefs that I can
te&ijie this Virtue by my own experience \ fince 1 have fo
great an averfwn from folli citing Court-Favours, that I
am ready to looh^ on tbofe as very bold, who dare grow rich
there without defert* But I beg your Graces pardon for
affuming this Virtue of Modefly to my fe If which the
jequel of this Difcourfe will no way jujlifie. For in
this Addrefs I have already quitted the Char after of a
tnodefl Man, by prefenting you this Poem as an achgow*
ledgment, which flands in need of your protection \ and
which ought no more to be efleemd a Prefent^ then it is
accounted bounty in the Poor y when they beflow a chilAon^
fome wealthy Friend, who can give it better Education*^
Off-fpringsofthis Nature are like to be fo numerous with -
me, that I mufl be forcd to fend fome of them abroad;^
only this is liig to be more fortunate then his Brothers,^
becaufe 1 have landed him, on a Hofpitablejhore. 'Under-
your Patronage, Montezuma hopes he is more fafethemim-
his Native Indies : and therefore comes to throw him f elf f
at your Graces feet, paying that homage, to your Beauty r
which he refused to the violence of his Conquerors* He>
begs only that when he /hall relate,: his fufferings,.yom
will eonftder he is an Indian Prince, and not expert any*
other Eloquence from his fimpfieiiy, then that, withmhichi
hm griefi- hav&:fmnipiMhimr His* jfyryris^ perBapTf



The Epifile Dedicatory.
'the <rreat eft, which was ever reprefented in a Poem of this
nature \ (the aSiion of it including the Difcovery and
Conqueft. of a new World.) In it I have neither wholly fol-
lowed the truth of the Hiftory, nor altogether left it : but
have taken all the liberty of a Poet, to add, alter, or dimi-
■ tiifh, as I thought might heft conduce to the beautifying of
my Worh^ It being not the bufinefs of a Poet to reprefent
Historical truth, but probability. But I am not to mal^e the
juftification of this Poem, which 1 wholly leave to your
Graces mercy. *Tis an irregular piece^ if compard with
many 0jf Corneilles, and, if I may make a judgement of it y
written with more Flame than Art j in which it reprefents
the mind and intentions of the Author, who is with much
more Xeal and Integrity, than Defign and Artifice,

MADAM,

O&obertheia*

Your Graces moft Obedient
andmofifgj^ed Servant,

John Dr yd en.



r ■ f

•



Con-



T



Connexion of the Indian Emperonr to the Indian Queen.

HE Conch (ion of the Indian Queen, ( partof which Poem was wri*
by me) left little matter for another Story to be built on it, there re-
maining but two of the confiderable Char&ers alive,(w'2> Monte-
zuma and Orazia , thereupon the Author of this thought it necefTary to pro-
duce new perfons from thofe two •, and confidering that the late Indian Queen
before (he lov'd Montezjtma, liv'd in clandeftine Marriage with her General
Traxalla •, he has raifedfrom them a Son and two Daughters, fuppofed to be
left young Orfbans at their Death : On the other^ide, he has given to Mon-
tezuma and Orazia ^.wo Sons and a Daughter, all now fuppofed to be grown
up to Mens and Womens Eftate ■ and their Mother Orazia (for whom there
was nofurther ufe in the (lory) lately dead.

So that you are to imagine about twenty yesrs elipfed fince the Corona-
tion of Montezuma-^ who, in the truth of the Hiftory, was a great and glo-
rious Prince; inwhofe time hapned the Difeoveryand Invafion of Mexico
by the Spaniards ; under the conduft of Hernando C-ortez, y who, joyning with
the Traxallan Indians, the inveterate Enemies of Montezuma, wholly fub-
verted that flourifhing Empire; theConqueft ofwhictys the SubjeAofthis
Dramatique Poem.

I have neither wholly followed the 11 ory, nor varied from it j and,as near as
I could, have traced the Native Simplicity and ignorance of the Indians, in re-
1 uion 10 European C uftoms : The Shipping, Armour, Horfes, Swords, and
Guns of the .y/wttrfr^beingasnew to them, as their Habits and their Lan-
guage were to the Chriftians.

The difference of their Religion from ours, I have taken from the Story it
felf; and that which you find of it in the 'fir ft and fifth Ads,rouching the fuffer-
mgsand conftancy of Montezuma'm his Opinions,I have only illuftrated, not
alterd from thofe who have written of it

The Names of the Perfons Reprefented.

r Mcntezuma, Emperourof Mexico.
\Odmar, his Eldeft Son,
Indians Men, sGuyornar, his younger Son.

;Orbellan, Son to the late Indian Queen by TraxalU. ,
( High Prieft of the Sun.
r Cydaria, Montezumas Daughter.

Women * XJ^ {Sifters, and Daughter to the late Indian Quern,
, Cortez^ the Spanifb General.

Spaniards. ) ^A«*.T C ommanden under him.
( Ftzarro, J

The Scene MEXIC o and two Leagues about it,

b prologue;





Lmighty Critiques \ whom our Indians here
Worfeipjtifl as they do the Devil^ for fear.
1 In reverence to your pow*rI come this day
to give yon timely warning of our Play.
The Scenes are old^ the Habits are the fame,
We wore laft year before the Spaniards came:
Now if you flay ^ the Blood that fe all be feed
From this poor Play y be all upon your head.
We neither promife you one Dance or show,
then Plot and Language they are wanting too:
But you j kind Wits, will thofe light faults excufe ►
thofe are the common frailties of the Mnfe 5
Which who obferves he buys his place too dear :
For 'tis yourbufinefs to be coufendhere.
thefe wretched fpiesof witmuB then confefs
they take more pains to pleafe themfe foes the lefs.
Grant us fuch Judges , Phoebus we requefi,.
Asjiill miftake themfelves into a jeji 5
Such eafte Judges^ that our Poet may
Himfe If admire the fortune of his Play.
And arrogantly >, a>s his fellows do,
think, he writes well, becaufe he pleafesyou* ,
this he conceives not hard to bring about
3f all of you would joyn to help him out.
Would, each man take but what he underjtandsj
Ami have the reji upon the Poets hands.



THE



THE



ndian Emperour



ACT 'I SCENE I.

The Scene, A pleafant Indian Countrey.

Enter CorteZj Vafquez, Pizarro, with Spaniards and Indian? of

their party,

Cort 'jf*\'N what new happy Climate are we thrown,
i iSo long kept fecret, and fo lately known >
^-^ As if our old world mod eftly withdrew.
And here, in private, had brought forth a new I

Vafq. Corn, Wine, and Oyl are wanting to this ground.,
In which our Countreys fruitfully abound :
As if this Infant world, yetunarray'd.
Naked and bare, in Natures Lap were laid.
No ufeful Arts have yet found footing here 5
But all untaught and falvage does appear.

Cort. Wild and untaught are Terms which we alone
Invent, for fafhions differing from our own :
For all their Cuftoms are by Nature wrought.
But we, by Art, unteach what Nature taught.

Viz. In Spain our Springs like old Mens Children, be
Decay d and wither 'd from their infancy:
No kindly fhowers fall on our barren Earth,
To hatch the feafon in a timely birth.
Our Summer fuch a RufTet Livery wears.
As in a Garment often d yd appears.

B 2 Con,



CO

Cort, Here Nature fpreads her fruitful fweetnefs round,
Breaths on the Air, and broods upon the ground.
Here days and nights'the only feafons be,
The Sun no Climat does fo gladly fee :
When forc'd from hence, to view our parts, he mourns 5
Takes little journeys, and makes quick returns.

Vafq. Methinks we walk in dreams on Fairy Land,
Where golden Ore lies mixt with common fand 5
Each downfalof a Flood the Mountains pour
From their rich bowels, rolls a filver fhower.

Cort. Heaven from all ages wifely did provide
This wealth, and for the braved Nation hide,
Who with four hundred Foot and forty Horfe,
Dare boldly go a New-found World to force.

Tt%. Our Men, though valiant, we (hould find too few,
But Indians joyn the Indians to fubdue 5
Taxallan, (hook by Montezuma's powers
Has torefid his forces, call'd in ours.

Vafq. Rafhly to arm againft fo great a King.
I hold not fafe, nor is it jud to bring
A War, without a fair Defiance made.

Viz* Declare we fird our quarrel : then invade.
Cort. My felf, my Kings AmbafTador, will go 3
Speak Indian Guide J how far to Mexico}

Ind. Your eyes can fcarce fo far a Profpeet make.
As to difcern the City on the Lake.
But that broad Cauf-way will direct your way,
And you may reach the Town by noon of day.

Cort. Command a party of our Indians out,
With a drift charge not to engage, but fcout 5
By noble ways we Conquedwill prepare.
Fir ft offer Peace, and that refus'd., make War. ■; Exeunt,



SCENE



(3)
S C E N E IF.

Jt Temple^ and the High Triefl with other Triefts^

To them an Indian.
In&i Hafte Holy Prieft, it is the Kings command.
High Tr, When fets he forward ?

Ind. He is near at hand.

HighPr. The Incenfe is upon the Altar plac cl.
The bloody Sacrifice already paft.
Five hundred Captives faw the rifingSun.
Who loft their light e're half his Race was run.
That which remains we here muft celebrate.
Where far from noife, without the City Gate,
The peaceful power that governs Love repairs.
To feaft upon (oft vows and filent pray'rs.
We for his Royal prefence only ftay,

To end the Rites of this fo folemn day. Exit Indian.

Enter Montezuma 5 his eldeft Son Odmar 5 his
Daughter Cydaria, Almeria, Alibech, Or-
bellan, and Train, they place themfdves.
Highrr. On your birth-day, while we ling,
To our Gods and to our King,
Her, among this beauteous quire,
Whofe perfections you admire,
Her, who faireft do s appear.
Crown the Queen of all the year.
Of the year and of the day,
And at her feet your Garland lay.

Odm. My Father this way does his looks direct.
Heaven grant he give it not where I fufpedr.

Montezuma rifes, goes about the Ladies.^
length flays at Almeria and bows
Mont* Since my Orazia's death I have not feea
A Beauty fo deferving to be Queen.
As fail Altnerta.



. ...



Aim, .Sure Ire will not know yio far "Brother

My birth I to that in jur'd Princefs owe, \and Sifter afide.

To whom not only he his love deny'd.
But in her fufFerings took unmanly pride-

Alib. Since Montezuma, will his choice renew.
In dead Orazias room electing you.
'Twill pleafe our Mothers Ghoft that you fucceed
To all the glories of her Rivals bed.

Aim, If news be carried to the (hades below,
The Indian Queen will be more pleas'd, to know
That I hisfcornson him, who fcorn'dher, pay.

Orb. Would you could right her fome more noble way.

{she turns to him who is kneeling
all this while,
Mont. Madam,this pofture is for Heaven defignd^Kneelitig.
And what moves Heaven I hope may make you kind.
Aim. Heaven may be kind 5 the Gods uninjur'd live,
And crimes below coft little to forgive.
By thee, Inhumane, both by Parents dy'd 3
One by thy Sword, the other by thy pride.

Mont. My haughty mind no • fate could ever bow,
Yet I muft ftoop to one who fcorns me now :
Is there no pity to my fufFerings due }

Aim. As much as what my Mother found from you;
Mont: Your Mothers wrongs a recompence (hall meet,
I lay my Scepter at her Daughters feet-

Alm, He, who does now my lead Commands obey.
Would call me Queen, and take my pow'r away.

odm. Can he hear this, and not his Fetters break i
Is Love fo pow'rful, or his Soul fo weak?
lie fright her from it. Madam, though you fee
The King is kind, I hope your modefty
Will know what diftance to the Crown is due.
Aim. Diftance and modefty prefcrib d by you ?
Odm. Almeria dares not think fuch thoughts as thefe.
Aim, She dares both think and a&what thoughts (he pleafe.
*Tis much below me on his Throne to fit 3
But when I do, you (hall petition it.

Odf/r*



m

Odm. % Sir, Almeria does your bed partake.,
I mourn for my forgotten Mothers fake.

Mont, When Parents Loves are order'd by a Son,
Let ftreams prefcribe their Fountains where to run.

odm. In all I urge, I keep my duty ftill.
Not rule your Reafon, but inftruft your Will.

Mont. Smallufe of Reafon in that Prince is fhown.
Who follows others, and negle&s his own.

Almeria toOrbellan and Alibech, who aye
this while whispering to her.
Aim. No, he (hall ever love, and always be
The fubjeft: of my i'corn and cruelty.

Orb. To prove the lafring torment of his life.
You muft not be his Miftrefs, but his Wife.
Few know what care an-Husbands peace deftroys^
His real griefs, and his diffembled joys.

Aim. What mark of pleafing vengeance could be (howr%
If r to break his quiet lofe my own ?

Orb. A Brothers life upon your Love relies.,
Since I do homage to Cydaria's Eyes :
How can her Father to my hopes be kind
If in your heart, he no examr le find }

Aim. To fave your life Tie fuffer any thing.
Yet Fie not flatter this tempeftuous King 5
But work his ftubborn Soul a nobler way.
And, if he love, Tie force him to obey.
I take this Garland, not as given by you, [jfrMontez,

But as my merit, and my beauties due.
As for the Crown that you, my Have, poffefs.
To fhareit with you would but make me lefs.

Enter Guyomar hafiily.
Odm. My Brother Guyomar ! methinks I fpye
Haft in his fteps, and wonder in his Eye.

Mont. I fent thee to the frontiers, quickly tell
The caufe of thy return 5 are all things well >

Guy* I went 3 in order, Sir, to your Command,..
To> view the utmoft limits of the Land :

Ta



CO

To that Sea-fhore where no more world is founds

But foaming billows breaking on the ground 5

Where, for a while, my Eyes no object, met

But diftant Skies that in the Ocean fet :

And low-hung Clouds that dipt themfelves in R.ain

To (hake their Fleeces on the Earth again.

At laft, as far as I could call: my Eyes

Upon the Sea, fomewhat, methought, did rife

Like blewiGimifts, which (till appearing more,

Took dreadful (hapes, and mov'd towards the (Tiore.

Mont, What forms did thefe new wonders reprefent >

Guy. More (Irange than what your wonder can invent.
The object I could firft diftinctly view
Was tall ftraight Trees which on the waters flew 3
Wings on their fides inftead of leaves did grow.
Which gather'dall the breath the winds could blow:
And at their roots grew floating Palaces,
Whofe out-bow J d bellies cut the yielding Seas.

Mont, What Divine Moafters, O ye gods, are thefe
That float in Air, and flye upon the Seas !
Came they alive or dead upon the Chore ?

Guy. Alas, they hVd too fure, I heard them roar ;
All turn'd their fides, and to each other fpoke,
I law their words break out in fire and fmoke.
Sure 'tis their voice that thunders from on high,
Or thtfe the younger Brothers of the Sky.
Deaf with the noifcl took my hafty ijight.
No mortal courage canfupport the fright.

High ?r. Old Prophecies foretel our fall at hand,
When bearded men in floating Caftles land, -
1 fear it is of dire portent.

Mont. Go fee

What it forelhows, and what the gods decree.
Mean time proceed we to what Rites remain 3
Odmm\ of all this prefence does contain,
Give her your wreath whom you efteem mod fair.

f>dm. Above the reft I judge one Beauty rare




And



(?)

And may that Beauty prove as kind to me He gives Alibscli
As I am fure fair Alibech is (he. the wreath.

Mont. YoxxGuyomar muftnext perform your part.-

Guy. I want a Garland, buttle give a heart:
My Brothers pardon I rauft firft implore,
Since I with him fair Alibech adore.

odm. That all fhould Alibech adore 'tis true,
But fome refpedt is to my Birth-right due.
My claim to her by Elderfbip I prove.

Guy. Age is a Plea in Empire, not in Love,

Odm. I long have (laid for this folemnity
To make my paffion publick.

Guy, So have I.

Odm. But from her Birth my Soul has been her Slave,
My Heart receiv'd the wounds which firft (he gave :
I watcht the early glories of her Eyes,
As men for day-break watch the Eaftern Skies.

Guy, It feems my Soul then mov'd the quicker pace,
Yours firft fet out, mine reach'd her in the race.

Mont. Odmar^ your choice I cannot difapprove 5
Nor juftly Guyomar^ can blame your Love.
To Alibech alone refer your Suit,-
And let herfentence finifh your difpute.

Alik You thihk me. Sir, a Miftrefs quickly won^
So ibon to finifh what is fcarce begun ;
In this furprife I can no judgement make :
'Tis anfwering Riddles ere, I'm well awake : •

If you oblige me fuddenly to chufe.
The choice is made, for I muftbothrefufe.
For to my felf I owe this due regard
Not to make Love my gift, but" my reward j
Time belt will (how svhofe fervic.es will laft.

Odm. Then judge rny future fervice by my. paftj ...
What Khali be by what I was, you know :. , ■

That Love took deepeft root which firft did grow.

Guy. That Love which firft was fet will firft decay.,
Mine ofafremer date will longer ftay.

Odm. Still you forget my Birth.

C Cny t



(8)

Guy. « -But you, ffee,

Take care ftillto refrefh my memory.

Mont. My Sons, let your unfeemly difcordceafe,
?f not in friend fhip, live at leaft in peace.
Vrbellati) where you love beftow your wreath.

Orb. My Love I dare ev'n in whispers breath*

Mont. A vertuous Love may venture any thing.

Orb. Not to attempt the Daughter of my King*

Mont. Whither rs all my former fury gone >
Once more I have Traxallas Chains put on,
And by his Children am in triumph led, !
Too well the living have reveng'd the dead ?

Aim. YouthinWly Brother born your Enemy
He's of Tax alias Blood, and fa am f.

Mont. In vain 1 ftrive,
My Lyon-heart is with Loves toyls befet,
Strugling, I fall frill deeper in the Net. ,'
€ydaria your new Lovers Garland take,
And' life- him kindly for your Fathers fake;

€yd» So ftrong a hatred does my nature fway.
That fpight of duty I mufl difobey.
Befldes you warn'd me ftill of loving two,
Can 1 love him already loving you c

Enter a Guard haftify

Btont. You look amaz'd as if fome fudden fear

Had feiz'd your hearts^is any danger near \

i* Guard. Behind the covert where this Temple (lands,
Thick as the (hades, there iflue (warming bands
<Of ambufh'd men, whom by their Arms and Drefs,
Tobe Taxcttlan Enemies I guefs. Another Enters.

? Guard. The Temple, Sir, isalmoft compaft round.

Mont. Some fpeedy way for paffagemult be found,
Make to the City by the Poftern Gate,
fie either force my victory, or Fate 3
A glorious death in Arms He rather prove 2
Thanftay to pertfu tamely by my Love.



Jht.



(?)

' . .. I

An Allawte within. Enter Montezuma ,Odmar, Guyoraar,Alibedr
Orbellan, Cydaria, Almeria 3 <# jwr/MiyTaxallans,

M?/tf. No fuccor from the Town >

Odm. None, none is nigh.

Guy. We are inclos'd, and muft refolve to die.
Mont. Fight for revenge now hope of life is paft,
But one ftroke more and that will be my laic.

Enter Cortex, Vafquez, Pizarro, to the Tax-
allans, Cortez, flays tbfipt. jffft faIIingon,

Cort. Contemn'd* my orders broke even inmy fight ! ) To w
Did I not ftri&ly charge you fhould not fight } ( Indians*

Ind. Your choller, General, does unjuftly rife,
To fee your Friends purfue your Enemies 5
The greateft and raoft cruel foes we have
Arethefe whom you would ignorantly fa ve*
By ambufrYd men, behind their Temple laid,
We have the King of Mexico betray'd.

Cort. Where banifh'd Vertue, wilt thou (hew thy face
If treachery infedtsthy Indian race !
Difmifs your rage, and lay your weapons by :•
Know I protedt them, and they (hall not dye.

Ind. O wond'rous mercy Ihown to foes diftreft 1

Cort. Call them not fo, when once with oddsoppreft,
Nor are they Foes my clemency defends,
Until they have refused the name of Friends 1
Draw up our Spaniardsby themfelves, then fire To Vafq.

Our Guns on all who do not ftraight retire.

Ind. O mercy, mercy, at thy feet we fall, Ind. Reeling*

Before thy roaring gods deftroy us all >

See we retreat without the leaft reply, The Taxallan's retire,

Keep thy gods tilent, if they fpeak we dye,

Mont. The fierce Taxallanslay their weapons down,
Some miracle in our relief is (hown.

Guy, Thefe bearded men, in fhape and colour be
Like thofe J faw come floating on the Sea. [Mont, \neeU fo Con;

C 2 Mm&



Mont. Patrotf of Mexico and god of Wars,
Son ofthe Sun, and Brother of the Stars.

Cort. Great Morarch, your Devotion you mifplace.,

Mont. Thy Anions fhew thee born of Heavenly Race,.
If then thou art that cruel god, whofe Eyes
Delight in Blood, and Humane Sacrifice,
Thy dreadful Altars, \ with Slaves will ftore,
And feed thy Nofrrils with hot reeking gore 5
Or if that mild and gentlegodthou.be,
Who doft mankind below with pity fee
With breath of Incenfe T will glad thy heart 3
But if like us^ of mortaffeed thou art^
Prefents of rareff Fowls, and Fruits Fie bring.,
And in my Realms thou (halt be more then King.

Cort. Monarch-of Empires, and deferving more
Then the Sun fees upon your Weftern fhore 5.
Like you a man, and hither, led by Fame^
Not by conftraint but by my choice. I: came .5
AmbalTador of Peace y ifPeaccyou chufe,
Or Herauld of a War, if you refufe.

MonU Whence or from whom doftthou thefe offers bring ?.

Cort. From Charles .the Fifth, the Worlds, moft potent King,

Mont. Some petty Prince, and one of little Fame,
For to this hour I never heard his name .*
The two great Empires of the World I.know,
That of T&ru y . and this of Mexico 5
And fince the earth none larger does afford,
This Charles isfome poor Tributary Lord.

Cort. You fpeak of that fmall part of Earth you knew,,,
?ut betwixt us and you wide Oceans flow,
And wa try defarts of fovaft. extent,
That paffing hither, four full Moons we (pent.,

Mont. But fay, what news, what offers doftthou bring

From fo remote,and fo unknown a King ? (thinks fit.
Vafq, Spams mighty Monatch 3 to whom Heaven tvhiuy^ fpeaif
That all the Nations of the Earth fubmit, andgilno %#&£&

3fo gracious- clemsncyj does condefcend tcrtdn'mg Cydaria

On thefe conditions to become your Friends Jg j^j*



y-






Firft, that of him you (hall your Scepter hold,
Next, youprefent him with your ufelefsGold:
Haft, that you leave thofe Idols you adore.
And one true Deity withPray'rs implore.

Mont, You fpeak your Prince a mighty Emperor,
But his demands have fpoke him Proud, and Poor 3
He proudly at my free-born Scepter flies.
Yet poorly begs a Mettal I defpife.
Cold thou may 'ft take, whatever thou canft find.,
Save what for Sacred ufes is dehgn'd :
But, by what right pretends your King to be
This Soveraign Lord of all the World, andme.^

Fiz. The Soveraign Prieft, ^— .

Who reprefents on Earth the pow'r of Heaven*,
Has this your Empire to your Monarch given.

Mont, 111 does hereprefent the Powers above ,-
Whonourifhes debate, not Preaches Love >
Befides, what greater folly can be (hown ?•
He gives another what is not his own.

Vafq. His pow'r muft nee dsunqueftion'd be below.
For he in Heaven an Empire can beftow.

Mont. Empires in Heaven he with more eafe may give.,
And you perhaps would with lefs thanks receive 5
But Heaven has need of no fuch Vice-roy here,
ft felf beftows the Crowns that Monarchs wear.
• riz. You wrong his power as you miftake our end,
Who came thus far Religion to extend.

Mont, He who Religion truly underftands
Knows its extent muft be in Men, not Lands,

Odm, But who are thofe that truth muft propagate
Within the confines of my Fathers ftate ?

Vafq, Religious Men, who hither muft be fent
A3.>awful" J guides»of Heavenly. Government 5
To teach you Pennance, Fafts, and Abftinence,.
To punifh Bodies for the Souls offence.

Mont. Cheaply you fin, and punifh crimes withea%
Mo£ as th' offended, but th' offenders gleafe,



Firft injure Heaven, and when its wrath is due,
Your felves prefcribe it how to punifh you.

Odm. What numbers of thefe Holy Men muft come >

Viz. You (hall not want, each Village (hall have feme*
Who, though the Royal Dignity they own,
Are equal to it, and depend on none.

Cny^ Depend on none 1 you treat them fure in ftatc,
For 'tis their plenty does their pride create.

Mont. Thofe ghoftly Kings would parcel out my pow'r,
Andallthefatnefsof my Land devour j
That Monarch fits not fafely on his Throne,
Who fuffers any pow'rtofhock his own.
They teach obedience to Imperialfway,
But think it fin if they themfelves obey.

Vajq. It feems then our Religion you accufe,
And peaceful homage to our King refufe.

Mont. Your gods I flight not, but will keep my own,
My Crown is abfolute, and holds of none 5
Icannot in abafe fubje&ion live.
Nor fufFer you to take though I would give.

Cort. Is this your anfwer, Sir >

Mont, This as a Prince,

Bound to my Peoples and my Crowns defence,
I muft return, but, as a Man by you
Redeem'd from death, all gratitude is due.

Cort, Honour requir'd that Ad, ev'n from a Foe,
But what I did were I again to do,
ThatReafon whichinclind my Will before
Would urge it now, for Love has nYd it more.
Is no way left that we may yet agree >
Muft I have War, yet have no Enemy ?

Vafq- He has refus'd all terms of Peace to take.

Mont. Since we muft fight, hear Heav'n., what Prayers I make,
Firft to preferve this antient State and me,
But if your doom the fall of both decree,
Grant only he who has fuch Honour fhown,
When I am Duft, may fill my empty Throne.

- Cort.



C'3>

Cort. To fnake me happier than that with can d%
Lies not in all your gods to grant,but you 5
Let this fair Princefs but one minute ftay,
A look from her will your obligements pay.

Exeunt Montezuma, Odmar, Guyomar, Orbellan,
Almeria, and Alibecru
Mont j to Cyd. Your Duty in your quick return be ftiown,
Stay you, and wait my Daughter to the Town. To lis Guards*
Cydaria is goings but turns atid looks back, upon Cortez.,
who is looking on her all this while.
Cyd. My Fathers gone, and yet I cannot go,

Sure I have fomething loft or left behind !' A fide,

Cort, Like Travellers who wander in the Snow,

Ion her beauty gaze till I am blind. Afi'de*

Cyd. Thick breath, quick pulfe, and heaving of my heart,
All figns of fome unwonted change appear :
I find my (elf unwilling to depart,

And yet I know not why I would be here.
Stranger you raife luch ftorms within my breaft.

That when I go, if I muft go again j
Fie tell my Father you have rob'd my reft,
And to him of your injuries complain*
Cort. Unknown, I fwearthofe wrongs were which I wrought
But my complaints will much more juft appear,
Who from another World my freedom brought,

And to your conquering Eyes have loft ft here.
Cyd. Where is that other World from whence you came i
Cort. Beyond the Ocean, far from hence it lies.
Cyd. Your other World, I fear, is then the fame
That Souls muft go to when the body dies.
Bat what's the caufe that keeps you here with me }

That I may know what keeps me here with you?
Cort* Mine is a Love which muft perputual be,
If you can be fo Juft as I am true. Enter Orbetlaqji

Orb. Your Father wonders much at your delay.
Cyd, So great a wonder for fo fmall a ftay !
Orb. He has commanded you with me to go.
Cyd. Has he not fent to bring the Granger too?

, &rb,



04)

Qrh. IF he to morrow dares in fight appear,
His high-placMLove, perhaps may coft him dear.

Cort. That word was never fpoke to Spaniard yet.
But forfeited his Life who gave him it}
Haft quickly with thy pledge of fafety hence,
Thy guilt's prote&ed by her innocence.

Cyd. Sure in fome fatal hour my Love was born.
So loon o'rcaft with abfence in the morn !

Cort. Turn hence thofe pointed glories of your Eyes,
For if more charms within thofe Circles rife.
So weak my Venue, they fo ftrong appear,
I (hall turn ravifher to keep you here. Exeunt omnts*



t ACT II.

SCENE, The Magicians Cave.

Enter Montezuma, High Prieft,

Mont. "\j OT that I fear the utmoft Fate can do,

I \ Come I th* event of doubtful War to know 3
For Life and Death are things indifferent,
Each to be chofeas either brings content j
My fearch does from a nobler Motive fpring 5
Love rules my heart, andisyour Monarchs King 5
I more defire to know Algeria's mind,
,Then all that Heaven has for my ftate defign'd.

High Pr. By powerful Charms which nothing can withftand,
Tie force the Gods to tell what you demand.
Charm.

Thou Moon, that aid'ft us with thy Magick might.
And ye fmall Stars, the fcattered feeds of light.
Dart you pale beams into this gloomy place,
That the fad powers of the Infernal race .
May read above what's hid from Humane Eyes,
And in vour Walks, fee Empires fall and rife.

And



And ye immortal Souls, who once were Men a
And now refolv'd to Elements agen.
Who wait for mortal frames in depths below,
And did before what we are doom'd to do 5
Once, twice, and thrice, I wave my Sacred wand,
Afcend, afcend, afcendat my command.

An Earthy Spirit rife.

Spir. In vain, O mortal men your Prayers implore
The aid of powers below, which want it more :
A God more ftrong, who all the gods commands.
Drives us to exile from our Native Lands *
The Air fwarnmhick with wandring Deities,
Which drowiily like humming Beetles rife
From their lov'd Earth, where peacefully they flept,
And far from Heaven along pofleffion kept.
The frighted Satyrs that in Woods delight,
Now into Plains with prick'd up Ears take flight}
And fcudding thence, while they their horn-feet ply
About their Sires the little silvanscvy.
A Nation loving Gold muft rule this place,
Our Temples ruine, and our Rites deface :
To them, O King, is thy loft Scepter given,
Now mourn thy fatal fearch, for fince wife Heaven
More ill then good to Mortals does d'ifpenfe,
It is not fafe to have too quick a fenfe. De fiends,

Mont, Mourn they, who think repining can remove
The firm Decrees of thofe who rule above ,
The brave are fafe within, whoftill dare dye,
When e're I fall Fie fcorn my deftiny.
Doom as they pleafe my Empire not to ftand,
Fie grafp my Scepter with my dying hand.

High Pr. Thofe Earthy Spirits black and envious are,
lie call up other gods of form more fair : — —
Who viflons drefs in pleafing Colours (till,
Set all the good to (how, and hide the ill*
Kalib, afcend, my fair-ipoke fervant rife.
And footh my Heart with pleafing Prophecies.

D Kalik



cm

Kalib afcetids all in white in the Qiape
of a Woman, and fings.
Kalib. I looh^A and fare within the Book^ of Fate,
Where many days did lower.
When lo one happy hour
Leap up, andjmil dtojavethy fnkjng States

Aday pall come when in thy power
Thy cruel Foes p all be *,
Then pall thy hand he free,
And -thou in Peace •■Jbalt Raign :
But take, tale that opportunity, ,
Which once refus'd will never come again. Defends,

Mont. I (hall defervemy Fate if Irefufe
Thar happy hour which Heaven allots^ to ufe *,
But of my Crown thou too much care doft take.
That which I value more, my Love's at (lake.

High Pr. Arife ye fubtle Spirits that can fpj^
When Love is entet'd in a Femalseye *,
You that can read in the midft ofdoubt 3
And in the midft of frowns can find it out 5
You that can fearch thofemany corner'd minds,
Where Womans crooked fancy, turns, and winds?
You that can Love explore, and truth impart.
Where both lye deeped hid in Womans heart,

Arife • The Ghofis of Traxalla and Acacis arife,

they fi and fill and point at Montez.
High Pr. I did not for thefe Ghaftly Vifionsfend,
iJbeir fudden coming does fome ill portend.*

Begon, -begon, they will not dif- appear,

My Soulisfeiz'd with an unufual fear.

Mont. Point on, point on, and fee whom you can fright^
Shame and Confufion feize thefe (hades of night 3
Ye thin and empty forms am I your fport > theyfmile.

If you were flefh

You know you durft not ufe me in this fort.

TheGhofi of the Indian Queen rifes betwixt

theGhofs with a Dagger in her Breaji,

16**. Ha! Ifel



Cl7)

I fee! my Hair grow (UfF, my Eye-balls rowl ?
This is the only form could tfhake my Soul.

Ghoft. The hopes of thy fucceflefs Love refgne^
Know Montezuma, thou art only mine $ ( i

For thofewho hereon Earth their paffi on jhow.
By death for Love, receive their right below.
Why dofi thou then delay my longing Arms >
Have Cares, and Age, and Mortal life fitch Charms !
The Moon growsfickly at the fight of day,
And early Cocks havefummond me away ;
Tet He appoint a meeting pi ace below
For there fierce winds ore duskje Vallies blow
Whofe every puff bears empty fijades away,
Which guidelefs in thofe dark Dominions fir ay.
Jufi at the entrance of the Fields below
Thoufialt behold a tall blac^Poplar grow,
Safe in its hollow trunks I will attend ,
Andfeize thy Spirit when thou dofi defend. Defends.

Mont. Fie feize thee there, thou MefTenger of Fate :
Would my fhort Life had yet a fhorter date !
I'm weary of this flefh which holds us here,
And daftards manly Souls with hope and fear 3
Thefe heats and colds (till in our breafts make War,
Agues and Feavers all our paffions are. Extnvt.

SCENE, II

Cydaria and Alibech, betwixt the two Armies,
-
Mb. Bleffings will Crown your Name if you prevent
That Blood, which in this Battel will be fpent 5
Nor need you fear fo jufta fute to move,
Which both becomes your Duty and your Love.

Cyd But think you he will come? their Camp is near,
And he already knows I wait him acre.

Alib. You are^too young your power to underftand,
Lovers take wing upon the lead Command %
Already he is here. Enter Concz and Vafquez to them

D 2 Cort,



(.8)

Cort. Methinks like two black ftorms on either hand,
Our Spanifi Army, and your Indians ftand 5
This only fpace betwixt the Clouds is clear.
Where you, like day, broke I oofe from both appear.

Cyd. Thofe clofing Skies might ftill continue bright,
But who can help it if yotri make it night >
The Gods have given you power of Life and Death,
Like them to fave or mine with a breath. j

Cort. That pow'r they to your Father did difpofe,
'Twas in his choice to make us Friends or Foes.

Alib. Injurious ftrength would Rapine ftill excufe^
By ofFring terms the weaker muft refufe -,
Andfuch as thefe your hard conditions are.
You threaten Peace , and you invite a War.

Cort. If for my felf to Conquer here I came.
You might perhaps my actions juftly blame:
Now I am fent, and am not to difpute
My Princes orders, but to execute.

Alib. He who his Prince fo blindly does obey.
To keep his Faith his Vertue throws away,

Cort. Monarchs may erre, but fhould each private breft
Judge their ill Acts, they would difpute their beft.

Cyd. Then all your care is for your Prince I fee,
Your truth to him out-weighs your Love to me 3
You may fo cruel to deny me prove,
But never after that, pretend to Love,

Cort. Command my Life, and I will foon obey,
To fave my Honour, I my Blood will pay.

Cyd. What is this Honour which does Love controul i

Cort. A raging fit of Vertue in the Soul 5
A painful burden which great minds muft bear,
Obtaind with danger, and pofleft with fear.

Cyd. Lay down that burden if it painful grow,
You'l find without it. Love will lighter go.

Cort. Honour once loft is never tobe found.

Alib. Perhaps he looks to have both paflions crown'd i
Firft dye his Honour in a purple Flood,
Then court the Daughter in the Father's Blood.

Cort.



Op)

Cort. The edge of War Tie from the Battle take.
And fpareher Father's Subjects for her fake.

Cyd. I canot love you lefs when I'm refus'd,
But I can dye to be unkindly us'd 5
Where (hall a Maids diffracted Heart find reft.
If (he can mifs it in her Lovers breft ?

Cort. I till to morrow will the fight delay,
Remember you have conquer'd me to day.

Alib. This grant deftroys all you have urg'd before,
Honour could not give this, or can give more 5
Our Women in the foremoft ranks appear,
March to the Fight and meet your Miftrifs there:
Into the thickeft Squadrons (hemuft run.
Kill her, and fee what Honour will be won.

Cyd. I muft be in the Battle, but Fie go
With empty Quiver, and unbended Bow 5
Not draw an Arrow in this fatal ftrife.
For fear its point (hould reach your Noble life. [ Enter Pizarro.

Cort) No more, your kindnefs wounds me to the death,
Honour be gone, what art thou but a breath >
I'le live, proud of my infamy and (hame,
Grac d with no Triumph but a Lovers name >
Men can but fay, Love did his reafon blind,
And Love's theNobleft frailty of the mind.
Draw offmy Men, the War's already done.

Viz. Your Orders come too late, the Fight's begun,
The Enemy gives on with fury led,
And fierce Orbellan combats in their head.

Cort. Hejuftly fears a Peace with me would prove
Of ill concernment to his haughty Love 5
Retire, fair Excellence, 1 go to meet <

New Honour, but to lay it at your feet.

Exeunt Cortez ; Vafquez, Pizarro-

Enter Odmar and Guyomar to Alibech and Cydaria.

Odm, Now, Madam, fince a danger does appear
Worthy my Courage, though below my Fear,

Give



(20)

Give leave to him who may in Battel dye.
Before his Death to ask his deftiny.

Guy. He cannot dye whom you command to live,
Before the Fight you can the conqueft give 5
Speak where you'l place it f , \ .

Alib Briefly then to 'both, *

One I in fecret love, the other loath 5
But where I hate, my hate I will not fhovr.
And he I love, my Love (hall never know 5
True worth (hall gam me, that it may be fed,
Defert, not fancy, once a Woman led .
He who in fight his courage (hall oppofe
With moftfu-ccefs againft his Countreys Foes,
From mefhall all that recompenfe receive
That Valour merits, or that Love can give :
*Tis true my hopes and fears are all for one.
But hopes and fears are to my felf alone,
Let him not (hun the danger of the ftrife,
I but his' Love, his Countrey claims his Life.

Odm. All obftacles my Courage (hall remove.

Guy. Fall on, fall on.

Odm, -For Liberty.

Guy.^— For Love. Exeunt^ the Women following.

SCENE Changes to the Indian Countrey.

Enter Montezuma attended by the Indians.
Mont . Charge, charge, their ground the faint Taxallans yield.
Bold in. clofe Ambufh, bafe in open Field :
The envious Devil did my Fortune wrong :
T bus fought, thus Conquered I when I was young. Exit .

Alarm, Enter Cortez Bloody.
Cert, Furies purfue thefe falfe "taxallans Flight,
Dare they be Friends to us, and dare not Fight i
What Friends can Cowards be, what hopes appear
Of help from fuch, who where they hate (how fear !
Enter Pizarro, Vafquez.
Pit, The Field grows thin, and thofe that now remain,
Appear but like the lhadows of the Slain.



Vajq.



Vafq . The fierce old King is vanifrYd from the Place ,
And in a Cloud of dull: Purfues the Chafe.

Cort. Their eager Chafe diforder'd does appear.
Command ourHorfe to charge them in the rear j \To Vafq.
You to our old Caftillian Foot retire , * To Piz.

• Who yet ftand firm, and at their backs giv^e Fire.

Exeunt feverally, j
Enter Odmar and Guyomar meeting each other in the'BatteL

Odm. Where haft thou been fince firft the Fight be^an,
Thou lefs then Woman in the (hape of Man j

Guy. Where I have done what may thy Envy move.
Things worthy of my Birth., and of my Love.

Odm, Two bold Taxallans with one Dart I flew.
And left it flicking ere my Sword I drew..

Guy. I fought not Honour on fo bafe a Train 3
Such Cowards by our Women may be flams
I feird along a man of Bearded face,
His Limbs all cover'd with afhining cafe:
So wondrous heard, andfo fecureof wound 5
It made my Sword, though edg'd with Flint, rebound.

Odm. I kill'd a double man,theone halfe lay
Upon the ground, the other ran away. Gunsgoe off within*

Enter Montezuma out of breathy with him Alibech
and an Indian.

Mont. All's loft —

Our Foes with Lightning and with Thunder fight,
My Men in vain fhun death by (hameful Flight ,
For deaths Tnvifible come wing'd with Fire,
They hear a dreadful noife and ftraight expire.
Take, gods, that Soul ye did in fpight create,
And made it great to be unfortunate :
-111 Fate forme unjuftly you provide.
Great Souls are Sparks of your own Heavenly Pride I
That lull: of power we. from your god-heads have.
You're bound to pleafe thofe Appetites you gave.

Enter Vafquez^dPizarro with Spaniards,

Vafq* Fiz,arro,\\\2iV e hunted hard to day 3
Into our toyls the no bleft of the prey 5

Seize



O)

Seize on the King, and him your Prifoner make, * . .
While I in kind revenge my taker take.

Pizarro with two goes to attacque the Kirfg Valquez
with another to feize Alibech.
Guy. Their danger isalike, whom (hall I free >
Odm. fie follow Love.
Guy. — — — He follow Piety.

Odmar retreats from Vafquez with Alibech off the
Stage j Guyomar Fights for his Father.,
Guy. Fly, Sir, while I give back that life you gave.
Mine is weUioft.., if I your life can fave.

Montezuma Fights eff Guyomar ntahjng hn
retreat \ flays.
Guy. *Tis more than Man can do to fcape them all,
Stay, let me fee where nobleft I may fall.

He runs at Vafquez, kfeized behind and taken.
Vafq. Conduct him off,
And give command he ftri&ly guarded be.

Guy. In vain are guards. Death fets the valiant free.

Exit Guyomar with Guards.
Vafq. A Glorious day ! and bravely was it fought,
Great Fame our General in great dangers fought j
From hisftrong Arm I faw his Rival run,
And in a crowd, th' unequal Combat fhun.

Enter Cortez leading Cydaria, whofeems weeping,
and begging of him,
Cort. Mans force is fruitless., and your gods would fail
To fave the City, but your Tears prevail 5
Tie of my Fortune no advantage make,
Thofe Terms they had oncegiv'n, they ftill may take;

Cyd. Heaven has of right all vi&ory deilgn'd,
Where boundlefs powr dwells in a will confin'd 3
Your Spanifh Honour does the World excel.
Cort. Our greateft Honour is in loving well.
Cyd, Strange ways you pra&ife there to win a Heart,
Here Love is Nature, but with you 'tis Art,
Cort. Love is with us, as Natural as here,
But fetter 'd up with Cuftoms more fevere 3

In



(*3 )

In tedious Courtfhip we declare our pain.
And e're we kindnefs find, firft meet difdain;

Cyd. If Women love, they needlefs pains endure.
Their Pride and Folly, but delay their Cure.

Cort. What you mif-call their Folly, is their care.
They know how fickle common Lovers are :
Their Oaths and Vows are cautioufly believ'd,
For few there are but have been once deceiv-d.

Cyd. But if they are not trufted when they vow,
What other marks of paffion can they (how.<?

Cort. With Feafts, and Mufick 5 all that brings delight,
Men treat their Eares, their Palates, and their fight.

Cyd. Your Gallants fure have little Eloquence,
Failing to move the Soul, they court the Sence :
With Pomp, and Trains^ and in a crowd they woe,
When true Felicity is but in two }
But can fuch toys your Womens paffion move f
This is but noife and tumult, 'tis not Lqve.
Cort. I have no reafon, Madam, to excufe
Thofe wayesof Gallantry I did not ufej
My Love was true, and on a Nobler fcore.

Cyd, Your Love ! Alafs ! then have you lov'd before }
Cort. 3 Tis true I lov'd, but foe's Dead, (he's Dead,
And I fhould think with her all Beauty Fled,
Did not her fair refemblance live in you,
And by that Image, my firft Flames renew.

Cyd. A happy Beauty whofoe're thou art !
Though dead thou keep'ft poffeffion of his Heart 5.
Thou mak'ft me jealous to the laft degree, -
And art my Rival in his Memory 5
Within his Memory, ah, more then fo.
Thou Liv'ft and Triumph'ft ore Cydaria too.

Cort. What ftrange difquiet has uncalm'd your breft;.
Inhumane fair, to rob the dead of reft !
Poor Heart ! She (lumbers in her filent Tomb,
Let her poffefs in Peace that narrow Room.

E Cyd*



cm

Cyd. Poor heart, he pitties and bewails her death f
Some god, much hated Soul, reftore thy breath
That I may kill thee, but fome eafe 'twill be,
Fie kill my felt for but refembling thee.

Cort. I dread your anger, your difquiet fear.,
But blows from hands fo foft who would not bear >
So kind a paftion why ihould I remove I
Since jealoufie but (hows how well we love.
Yet jealoufie fo ftrange I never knew,
Can (he who loves me not difquiet you/
For in the Grave no Paffions fill the Breft ;
'Tis all we gain by Death to be at reft.

Cyd. That (he no longer loves, brings no relief,
Your Love to her (till lives, and that's my grief.

Cort. The object of defire once ta'ne away,
Tis then not Love, but pity which we pay.

Cyd. 'Tis fuch a pity I (hould never have,
•When I muft lye forgotten in the Grave \
I meant to have oblig'd you when I dy'd,
That after me you (hould love none befide,
But you are falfe already.

Cort. — If untrue.

By Heaven my faKhood is to her, not you.

Cyd. Obferve fweet Heaven, how falfly he does fwear^
You faid you lov'd me for refembling her.

Cort, That Love was in me by refemblance bred,
But (hows you chear'd my forrows for the Dead.

Cyd. You (till repeat the greatnefs of your grief.

Cort. If that was great, How great was the relief?

Cyd. The firft Love (till the ftrongeft we account.

Cort. That feems more (hong which could the firft furmountt
But if you ftill continue thus unkind,
Whom I love beft, you by my Death (hall find*

Cyd. If you (hould die, my Death (hould yours purfue,
But yet I am not fatisfi'd you're true.

Cort 4, Hear me ye gods, and puni(h him you hear.
If ought within the World I hold fo dear.

Cyd. You would deceive the gods and me, (he's dead,
And is not in the World 3 whofe Love I dread. Name



C^9)

Name not the world, fay nothing is fo dear.
Cert* Then nothing is, let that fecure your fear.
Cyd. ! Tis Time rauft wear it off, but I muft go.
Can you your conftaricyin abfencefhow/

Court, Mif- doubt my conftancy and do not try 5
But ftay and keep me ever in your eye.

Cyd. If as a Prifoner I were here, you might
Have them infilled on a Conqu'rours right,
And ftay'd me here 5 but now my Love would be
Th'erTeft of force, and I would give it free.

Cort. To doubt your Vertue or your Love were fin 5
Call for the Captive Prince, and bring him in.
Enter Guyomar bound and fad.
You look, Sir,as your Fate you could not bear. \to Guyomar,
Are spanijh Fetters then fo hard to wear >
Fortune's unjuft, ftie ruines oft the brave,
And himwhofhould be Victor, makes the Slave.

Guy. Son of the Sun, my Fetters cannot be
But Glorious for me, (ince put on by thee}
The ills of Love, not thofe of Fate I fear,
Thefe I can brave, but thofe I cannot bear ,
My Rival Brother, while I'm held in Chains^
In freedom reaps the fruit of all my Pains.

Cort. Let it be never faid, that he whofe bred
Is fill d with Love, fhould break a Lovers reft 5
Hafte, lofe no time, your Sifter fets you Free,
And tell the King, my Generous Enemy,
I offer ftill thofe termes he had before,
Only ask leave his Daughter to adore.

Guy, Brotherfthat Name my breaft (hall ever own&He em-
The Name of foe be but in Battels known •> ) i braces

For fome few dayes all Hoftile A&s forbear, him.

That if the Kingjconfents, it feem not fear 5
His heart is Noble, and\ great Souls muft be
Moft foug t and Qourtep in Adverfity.
Three dayes I hope the wlfht fuccefs will tell.

Cyd* Till that long tinie.

Cort.- — Till that long time, farewel. Ex Severally,

E'2„ ACT.



(it)

ACT. III.

SCENE, Chamber Royal.

Enter Odmar and Alibech.

Odm. **1 ^He gods fair Alibech, had fo decreed 5

Nor could my Valour againft Fate facceed 5
~ Yet though our Army brought not conquefthom;
I did not from the Fight inglorious come :
IF as a Victor you the brave regard,
Succeflefs Courage then may hope reward.*
And I returning fafe, may juftly boaft < Enter -Guy emir

To win the prize which my dead Brother loft j behind him.

Guy. No,no, thy Brother lives, and lives to be
A Witnefs, both againft himfelf and thee 5
Though both in fafety are return'd agen,
I blufh to ask her Love for vanquifht Men.

odm. Brother, Fie not difpute, but you are brave.
Yet I was free, and you it feemes a Slave.

Guy, Odmar, 'tis true , that I was Captive led
As publickly is known, as that you fled •>
But of two (names if (he muft one partake,
I think the choice will not be hard to make.

Odm. Freedom and Bondage in her choice remain,
Dar'ft thou expect (he will put on thy Chain ?

Guy. No, no, fair Alibech, give him the Crown,
My Brother is return'd with high Renown.
He thinks by Flight his Miftrefs muft be won.
And claims the prize becaufe he beft did run.

Ahb.Ycmr Chains were glorious,and your Flight was wife ?
But neither have o'recome your Enemies :
My fecret wifhes would my choice decide,
But open Juftice bends to neither fide.

Odm. Juftice already does my right approve,
If him who loves you moft, you moft fhould love.

My



" _ '-..■'

My Brother poorly from your aid withdrew
But I my Father left to fuccour you.

Guy, Her Country fhe did to her felf prefer,
Him who fought beft, not who defended her 3
Since (he her intereft for the Nations wav'd,
Then I who fav'd tire King, the Nation fav*d 5
. You aiding her, your Country did betray,
I aiding him, did her commands obey.

odm. Name it no more, in Love, there is a time
When dull Obedience is the greateft Crime 5
She to her Countries ufe refignd your Sword,
And you kind Lover, took her at her word 3
You did your Duty to your Love prefer.
Seek your reward from Duty, not from her.

Guy. In acting what my t)uty did require,
Twas hard for me to quit my own defire,
That Fought for her, which when I did fubdue
'Twas much the eafier task I left for you.

Alib, odmar> a more then common Love has fhown.
And Guyomars was greater, or was none.
Which I fhould chufe, fome god direct my breft,
The certain good, or the uncertain beft :
I cannot chufe, you both difpute in vain,
Time and your future Acts muft make it plain 5
Firfl: raife the Siege, and fet your Country free,
I not the Judge, but the reward will be. ~

To them , Enter Montezuma talking with Almeria
and Orbellan.
Mont, Madam, I think with reafon I extol
The Vertue of the. Spanijh General 3
Whea all the gods our Ruine have fore-told,
Yetgeneroufly he does his Arms with-hold,
And offering Peace, the firft conditions make.

Aim. When Peace is offer'd J tis too late to take 3
For one poor lofs to ftoop to termes like thole.
Were we o'r«come. What could they worfe impofe }■
Go, go, with homage your proud Victors meet,
Go lie like Dogs 3 beneath your Matters Feer 3

Go



Go and beget them Slaves to dig their Mines,
And groan for Gold which now in Temples {bines *,
Your fhameful (lory (hall record of me,
The men all crouch'd, and left a woman free.

Guy. Had I not Fought, or durft not Fight again,
I my fufpecled Counfel ftiould refrain:
For I wilh Peace, and any termes prefer
Before the la ft extremities of War.
We but exafp rate thofe we cannot harme,
And Fighting gains us but to dye more warmer
If that be Cowardife, which dares not fee
The infolent effects of Victory.
The rape of Matrons, and their Childrens cries 3
Then I am fearful, let the brave advife.

odtn. Keen cutting Swords, and Engines killing far,
Have profperoufly begun a doubtful War :
But now our Foes with lefs advantage Fight,
Their ftrength decreafes with our Indians Fright. '

Mont. This Noble Vote does with my wifh comply,
I am for War.

Aim. And fo am I.

Orb —And I.

Mont. Then fend to break the truce, and Tie take care
To chear the Souldiers, and for Fight prepare.

Exeunt Montezuma, Odmar, Guyomar, Alibech.

Aim. to Orb. 'Tis now the hour which all to reft allow, Almeria
And fleep fits heavy upon every brow j [ft a J s Orbellan.

In this darkfilence foftly leave the Town,! Guyomar returns
And to the Ge»eraZ/tent/tis quickly known3 and hears them
Diredt your fteps.* you may difpatchhim ftrait,
Drownd in his fleep, and eafiefor his Fate.*
Befides, the truce will make the Guards more flack.

Orb, Courage which leads me on, will bring me back :
But I more fear thebafenefs of the thing.*
Remorfe, you know, bears a perpetual fting.

Aim. For mean remorfe no room the Valiant finds,
Repentance is the Vertueof weak minds 5
For want of judgment, keeps them doubtful ftill.
They may repent of good, Who can of ill ?

But



C 2§ ■)

But daring Courage makes ill anions goocL»

'Tis foolifti pity fpares a Rivals blood 3

You (hall about it firaight. -—_-.£*<!»*/ Almeria, Orbellan>

Q H y t . Would they betray

His fleeping Vertue, by fo mean a way !
And yet this Spaniard is our Nations Foe,

I wi(h him dead but cannot wifh it fo*

Either my Country never muft be freed,

Or I confenting to fo black a deed.

Would Chance had never led my fteps this way.

Now if he dies I murther him, not they 3

Something muft be refolv'd e're 'tis too late,

He gave me freedom. Tie prevent his Fate. [Exit Guyomar,

SCENE II. A Camp.

Enter Cortez alone in a Night-gown.

Cort. All things are hufh'd, as Natures felf lay dead,
The Mountains (eem to nod their drowfie head 5
The little Birds in dreams their Songs repeat.
And fleeping flowers, beneath the night- dew fweat>
Ev'n Luft and Envy fleep, yet Love denies
Reft to my Soul, and {lumber to my Eyes.
Three dayes I promis'd to attend my Doom,
And two long dayes and nights are yet to come :
s Tis fure the noife of fome Tumultuous fight, Noife wiihix,.
They break the truce, and fally out by Night.

Enter QvheWm flying in the dark^ his Sword drawn,

Orb. Betray'd ! purfu'd ! Oh whither (hall I fly >
See, fee, the juft reward of Treachery ->
I'm fure among the Tents, but know not where,
Ev'n night wants darknefs to fecure my fear.

Comes near Cortez who hears him*

Cort, Stand, who goes there }

Orb. — Alafs, What (hall I fay I jfJei.

A poor Taxallan that miftook his way. To him,.

And wanders in the terrours of the night,

CorU



Cort. Souldier thou feem'ft afraid whence comes thy fright .>

Orb. The iniblence of Spaniards caus'd my fear,
Who in the dark p.urhzd me- entring here.

Cort. Their Crimes (hall meet immediate puniftiment,
But fray thou i'afe within the Generals Tent.

Orb. Still worfe and worfe.

Cort. Fear not but follow me,

Upon my Life Fie fet thee fafe and free.

Cortez leads him in^ and returns.
To him Vafquez,Pizarro, and Spaniards with Torches-.

Vafq. O Sir thank Heaven, and your brave Indian Friend
That you are fafe, Orbellan did intend
This night to kill you fleeping in your Tent,
But Cuyomar^ his trufty Slave has fent,
Who following clofe his filent (reps by night
Till in our Camp they both approach 'd the light,
Cry'd feize the Tray tor, feize the Murtherer :.
The cruel Villain fled I know not where 3
But far he is not, for he this way bent.

Viz. Thin raged Souldiers feek, from Tent to Tent,
With lighted Torches, and in Love to you,
With bloody Vows his hated life purfue.

Vafq. This Meflenger does fince he came relate,
That the old King, after a long debate j
By this imperious Miftrefs blindly led,
Has given Cydaria to Orbellan s Bed.

Cort. Vajquez, the trufty Slave with you retain,
Retire a while, Tie call you back again, [Exeunt Vafq. Piz.

Cortez at his Tent door.
Cort. Indian come forth, your Enemies are gone,
And I who fav'd you from them, here alone.
You hide your Face, as you were ftill afraid.
Dare you not look on him who gave you aid?
Enter Orbellan holding his Faceafde.
Orb. Moon flip behind fome Cloud, fome Temped rife
And blow out all the Stars that light the Skies,
To (hroud my ftiame.

Cort.



fjtf-)

Cort. In vain you turn afide,

And hide your Face, your Name you cannot hide §
I know my Rival and his black defigne.

Orb % Forgive it as my paflions fault, not mine.

Cort. In your excufe your Love does little fay.
You might havetSkena much nobler way.

Orb. 'Tistrue, mypaffionfmall defence can make,
Yet you muft fpare me for your Honours fake 3
That wasengag'd tofet me fafe and free.

Cort. TwastoaStranger^ not an Enemy/
Nor is it prudence to prolong thy breath.
When all my hopes depend upon thy death-



.Yet none (hall tax me with bafe perjury,



Something Tie do, both for my felf and thee 3
With vow'd revenge my Souldiers fearch each Tent,
If thou art feennone can thy death prevent.
Follow my fteps with filence and with hafte.

They go out 9 the Scene changes > to the Indian
Covntrey, they return.
Cort. Now you are fafe, you have my out-guards paft.
Orb. Then here I take my leave.

Cort. -Orbellan^ no,

When you return, you to Cydaria go.
Tie fend a Meflage.

Orb. Let it be expreft,

I am in hafte.

Cort. rie write it in your Breft Draws.

Orb. What means my Rival >
Cort. Either Fight or Dye,
Flenot drain Honour to a point too high }
I fav'd your Life, now keep it if you can,
Cydaria (hall be for the braveft Man 5
On equal terms you (hall your Fortune try,
Take this and lay you flint-edg d Weapon by 5 c Gives him
I'le arm you for my Glory, and purfue » \a£voord*

No palm, but what's to manly Vertue due.
Fame with my Conqueft, (hall my Courage tell.
This you (hall gain by placing Love fo well.

F Orb.



•.C.3.2>

Orb. Fighting with you ungrateful I appear.
Cort. Under thatfhadow thou wouldft hide thy fear?
Thou wouldft: poffefs thy Love at thy return,
And in her Arms my eafie Vertue fcorn..

Orb. Since we muft Fight, no longer iltaie delay.
The iYtoon (bines clear, and makes a paler day.

They Fight ^ Orbellan is wounded in the Hand
his Sword falls out of it.
Cort. To Courage, even of Foes, there's pity due
It was not I, but Fortune vanquiuYd you 5 J Throws his
Thank me with that, and fo difpute the prizeX&tnrd acain
As if you fought before Cydarias Eyes.

Orb. I would not poorly fuch a gift requite.
You gave me not this Sword to yield, but Fight 5
But fee where yours has forc'd its bloody way^Heftrivts to hold.
My wounded Hand, my Heart does ill obey. 1 it, but cannot.

Cort Unlucky Honour that controul'ft my will !
Why have I vanquiuYd, fincel muft not Kills
Fate fees thy Life lodg'd in a brittle Glafs,
And looks it through, but to it cannot pafs*

Orb. All lean do is frankly to confefs,
I wifh T could, butcannotlove herlefs 5
To fwearl would refigne her were but vain,
Love would recall that perjur'd breath again 5
And in my wretched cafe 'twill be more juft
Not to have promised , then deceive your Truft.
Know, if I live once more to fee the Towa,
In bright Cydaria's Arms my Love Tie crown.
Cort. In fpight of that I give thee Liberty,
And with thy perfon leave thy Honour free 5
But to thy wifhes move afpeedy pace,
Or Death willfoon o'retakethee in the Chafe.
To Arms, to Arms, Fate (hows my Love the way,
Fie force the City on thy Nuptial day. Exeunt feverally*

SCENE



(33)
SCENE, III. Mexico.

Enter Montezuma, Odmar 5 Guyomar, Almeria.

Mont. It moves my wonder that in two days fpace,
This early Famine fpreads fofwift a pace.

odm. 'Tis, Sir, the general cry, norfeems it ftrange.
The face of plenty fhould fo fwiftly change :
This City never felt a Siege before,
But from the Lake receiv'dits daily (lore.
Which now (hut up, and Millions crowded here,
Famine will foon in multitudes appear.

Mont. The more the number, ftill the greater (hame.

Aim. What if fome one fhould feek immortal Fame
By ending of the Siege at one brave blow?

Mont. That were too happy !

Aim. Yet it may be fo,

What if the Spanifl) General ihould be (lain >

Guy. Juft Heaven I hope does other ways ordain.

Mont. If flainby Treafon I fhould mourn his Death.
Enter Orbellan and whijpers his Sifter.

odm. Orbellan feems in hafte and out of breath.

Mont. Orbellan welcome, you are early here.
A Bridegrooms hafte does in your looks appear.

Almeria Afide to her Brother,

Aim. Betray'd ! no, 'twas thy Cowardife, and Fear,
He had not fcap'd with Life had I been there j
But fince fo ill you acl: a brave defigne,
Keep clofe your fhame. Fate makes the next turn mine.
Enter Alibech, Cydaria.

Alib. O Sir, if ever pity touched your Rreft,
Let it be now to your own blood expreft:
In tears your beauteous Daughter drowns her fight.
Silent asdews that fall in dead of night.

Cyd. To your commands I ftrid obedience owe.
And my laft A£t of it I come to (how 5
I want the Heart to dye before your Eyes,
But Grief wilifinifli that which Fear denies,
* F 2 Mm,



Cn)

Aim. Your Will fhould by your Fathers Precept move.
Cyd, When he was young he taught me truth i n Love.
Aim. He found more Love then he deferv'd, 'tis true,
And that it feems is lucky too to you>
Your Fathers Folly took a head-ftrong cnurfe,
But I'lerule yours, and teach you love by force*
Enter MefTenger.
Meff. Arm, Arm., O Ring, the Enemy comes on,
A (harp atTault already is begun 5
Their Murdering Guns play fiercely on the Walls.
odm, Now Rival, letus run where Honour calls.
Cay. I have dtfcharg'd what gratitude did owe,
And the brave Spaniard is again my Foe. {^Exeunt Odmzr and
Mont Our walls are high,and multitudes defend : Guyomar.3
Their vain attempt muft in their ruine end j
The Nuptials with myprefence (hall be gracd.
Alib. At leaft but ftay till the atTault be paft.
Aim, Sifter, in vain you urge him to delay,
The King has promis'd, and he (hall obey.

Enter Second Meflenger.
Meff 2. Fromfeveral parts the Enemy's repell'd^
One only quarter, to th*alTault does yield.

Enter Third Meflenger.
Meff.% , Some Foes are enter'd , but they are (b few,
They only Death, not Victory purfue.

Orb, Hark y hark, they (hout !
From Vertues rules T doe too meanly fwerve:
I by ny Courage will your Lovedeferve.

Mont. Herein the heart of all the Town Tie ftay ?
And timely fuccour where it wants, convey.

Anoife within, Enter Orbcllan^ Indians driven in^Qotttx
after them, and one or two Spaniards.
€ort He's found, he's found, degenerate Coward ftay :
Night fav'd thee once, thou (halt not fcape by day. .} Kills

Orb. O I am kill 'd— * Dyes. ^Orbellam

Enter Guyomar and Odmar.
Guy. Yield, generous Stanger, and prefer ve you life \ He is
Why chute you death in this unequal ftrife * r befit*

Almeria



(35)

Almeria and hXfozchfeem to weep over Orbellans body.

Cort, What nobler Fate could any Lover meet,
Ifallreveng'd,and at my Miftrefs feet>

Th y fall onhim and bear him down Guyomar takes
his Sword,

Alib. He's paft recovery 5 my dear Brother's flain :
Fates hand was in it, and my care is vain.

Aim, In weak complaints you vainly waft your breath :
They are not Tears that can revenge his Death,
Difpatch the Villain (trait.

Cort. The Villain's dead.

Aim, Give me a Sword, and let me take his Head.

Mont, Though, Madam, for your Brothers lofs I grieve.
Yet let me beg,

Aim. — His Murderer may live 2

Cyd. 'Twas his Misfortune, and the Chance of War.

Cort. It was my purpofe, and T kill'd him fairs
How could you fo unjuft and cruel prove,
To call that chance which was the ad of Love,*?

Cyd. I call'd it any thing to fave your life :
Would he were living ftill, and I his Wife j
That wi(h was once my greateft mifery :
But 'tis a greater to behold you dye.

Aim, Either command his Death upon the place.
Or never more behold Almerms face.

Guy. You by his Valour, once from Death were freed r
Can you forget fo Generous a deed > [To Montezuma*,.

Mont How Gratitude and Love divide my breft/
Both ways a'ike my Soul isrob'd of reft.

But let him dye can \ his Sentence give }■

Ungrateful, muft he dj/e by whom I live ?
But can I then Almerias tears deny !
Should any live whom (he commands to dye?

Guy. A pproach who dares .* he yielded on my word 5
And as my Prisner, Ireftore his Sword > \G%vu his Swordo,
His life concerns thefafety of the State,
And I'le preferve it for a calm debate.

Motifs



Mont. Dar'ft thou rebel falfe and degenerate Boy >
That Being which Igave, I thus deftroy.

Offers to fyll hmyOdmavJieps between,

odm. My Brothers blfood'f cannot fee you (pill,
Since he prevents you but from doing ill:
He is my Rival, but his death would be
For him too glorious, and too bafe for me.

Guy. Thou (halt not conquer in this noble ftrife :
Alas, I meant not to defend my Life:
Srike, Sir, you never pierc'd a Bread more true ,
3 Tis thelafl: Wound I ere can take for you.
You fee I live but to difpute your will 3 i
Kill me, and then you may my Prisoner kill.

Cort. You (hall not, Gen'rous Youths, contend for me :
It is enough that I your Honour fee,
But that your Duty may no blemilh take,
I will my felf your Fathers Captive make:
When he dares ftrike I am prepar'd to fall : r Gives his Sword
The Spaniards will revenge their General. \ to Montezuma.

Cyd. Ah you too haftily your Life refigne.
You more would love it if you valued mine !

Cort. Difpach me quickly, I my Death forgive,
T (hall grow tender elfe, and wi(h to Live :
Such an infectious Face herforrow wears,
I can bear Death, but not Cydarias Tears.

Aim. Make hafte, make hafte, they merit Death all three :
They for Rebellion, and for Murder he.
See, fee, my Brother's Gho(t hangs hovering there.
Ore his warm Blood, that (teems into the Air,
Revenge, Revenge it cries.

Mont. And it (hall have 5

But two days refpite for his Life I crave :
If in that fpace you not more gentle prove:
Me give a Fatal proof how well I Love.
Till when youGuyon/ar, your Pris'ner take 5
Beftow him in the Cattle on the Lake :
In that fmall time, I (hall the Gonqueft gain
Of thefe few Sparks of Vertue which remain :

Then



Then all who (nail my head-long paffion fee.

Shall curfe my Crimes, and yet (hall pity me. [Exeunt omnes.



ACT. IV.

SCENE, ^ Prifon.

Enter Almeria, and an Indian, theyfpeak^ entring.

Ind. A Dangerous proof of my refpeft I (how.

f\ Aim. Fear not, Prince Guyomar (hall never know *
While he is abfent let us not delay 5
Remember 'tis the King thou doft obey.

Ind. See where he deeps.

£Cortez appears Chain d and laid afleep^

Ainu Without my coming wait :

And on thy Life fecure the Prifon Gate [Exit Indian.

[she plucks out a Dagger ^ and approaches him a
Spaniard awake, thy Fatal hour is come :
Thou (halt not at fuch eafe receive thy doom.
Revenge is fure, though fometimes (lowly pac'd,
Awake, awake, or fleeping, fleep thy lafr 8

Cort. Who names Revenge >

jlm. — Look up and thou (halt fee.

Cort. I cannot fear fo fair an Enemy.

Aim. No aid is nigh, nor canft thou make defence :
Whence can thy Courage come ?

Cort. From Innocence.

Aim. From Innocence i let that then take thy part,

Still are thy looks aflur'd,* have at thy Heart:

[Holds up the Dagger C
I cannot kill thee : fure thou bear'ft fome Charm, [Goes back*.
Or fome Divinity holds back my Arm.
Why do I thus delay to make him Bleed^ [Afide^

Can I want Courage for fo brave a Deed }
I*ve (hook it off, my Soul is free from fear, [Comes,- again U
And lean now ftrikeany where, — but here ,

Hi*



•



His fcom of Death how ftrangely Hoes it move !

A mind Co haughty who could chnfe but love ! [Goes off.

Plead not a Charm, or any Gods command,

Alas it is thy heartthat holds thy hand :

In fpight of me I love, and fee too late

My Mothers Pride muft find my Mothers Fate :

Thy Countrey's Foe, thy Frother's Murtherer,

For fhame, Almeria, fuch mad thoughts forbear :

It w'onnot be, if I once more come on, [_Coming on again.

I fhall miftakethe breaft, and pierce my own.

[Comes with her Dagger doxon Kt
Cort, Does your revenge-malicioufly forbear
To give me Death, till 'tis prepar'dby fear t
If you delay forthat, forbear or ftrike,
Fore-feen and fudden Death are. both alike

Aim. To (how my Love would but increafe his Pride :
They have mod: power who moft their paffions hide. Ajide.
Spaniard, I muft confefs I did expecl:
You could notmeetyour Death with fuch neglect
I will defer it now, and give you time :
You may repent, and I forget your Crime.

Cort, Thofe who repent acknowledge they did ill :
Ididnot unprovokd, your Brother kill.
Aim. Petition me, perhaps. I may forgive.
Cort. Who begs his life, does not deferve to live.
Aim, But if 'tis given, you 1 not refufe to take?
Cort', I can live gladly for Cydaria slake.
Aim. Does fhe Co wholly then poflefs your mind }
What if you fhould another Lady find,
Equal to her in Birth, and far above
In all that can attract, or keep your Love,
Would you fo doat upon your flrft delire^
As not to entertain a nobler fire ?

Cort. I think that perfon hardly will be found,
With gracious form and equal Vertue crown'd :
Yetifanothercould precedence claim,
My fixt defires could find no fairer aim.

Aim*



(39)

Aim. Dull ignorance., he cannot yet conceives
To fpeak more plain, fhame will not give me leave. fjAi
— Suppofe one lovd you whom even Kings adore : fclo&w,
Who with your Life, your Freedom would reftore,
And add to that the Crown of Mexico :
Would you for her, Cj/darias Love forego >

Cort. Though (he could offer all you can invent,
Icouldtiot of my Faith, once vow'd, repent.

Aim. A burning bluih has cover'd all my face 3
Why am I forc'd to publifh my difgrace }
What if I love, you know it cannot be.
And yet 1 blufn to put the cafe 'twere me. •.
If I could love you, with a flame fotrue
I could forget what hand my Brother flew — .
— . --Make out the reft, — I am diforder'd fo
I know not farther what to fay or do :
— But anfwer me to what you think I meant.
Cort. Reafon or Wit no anfwer can invent :
Of words confus'd who can the meaning find ?
Aim. Diforder'd words (how a diftemper'd mind.
Cort. She has oblig'd me fo, that could I chufe,
I would not anfwer what I mud refufe* [^Ajide.

Aim. —■ His mind is (hook, — fuppofe I lov'd you, fpeak.
Would you for me Cj/darias Fetters breaks

Cort, Things meant in Jeft, no ferious anfwer need.
Aim.- But put the cafe that it were fo indeed.
Cort) If it were fo, which but to think were Pride,
My confrant Love would dangerouflybetry'd :
For fince you could a Brothers death forgive,
He whom youfave, for you alone (houldlive :
But I the moll: unhappy of mankind, :
E're T knew yours, have all my Love refign'd :
5 Tis my Own lofs I grieve^ who have no more 5
You go a begging to' a bankrupts door.
Yet could I change, as fure I never can,
How could you love fo infamous a Man ">
For,Love once given from her, andrilac'din you,
Would leave no ground I ever could be true.

G Aim,




(4o)

Aim. You conftrued me aright, 1 was in Jeft.*

And by that offer meant to found your breftj

XS hich fmce I find fo conftant to your Love,

Will much my value of your worth improve.

Spaniard aflure your felf you (hall not be

Oblig'd to quit Cydaria for me 5

*Tis dangerous though to treat me in this fort,

And torefufe my offers, though in fport. {Exit AtmeriaJ.

Cort. In what a ftrange condition am Ileft, [Coxt, folus..
More than I wi(h I have, of all I wifh bereft !
In wifhing nothing we enjoy ftill moftj
For even our wifh is in poffeffion loft :
Reftlefs we wander to anew defire,
And burn our felves by blowing up the Fire ?
We tofs and turn about our Feverifh will,
When all our eafe muft come by lying ftill &■
For all the happinefs Mankind can gain
1% not in pleafure, but in reft from pain.

Goesitt) and the Scene dofes uyon him a

S C E N E IF. Chamber R<yaL.

Enter Mbntezuma,Odmar,Guyomar, Alibech.

Monti. My Ears are deaf with this impatient croud*

Odm, Their wants are now grown mutinous and loud ••.
The General's taken, but the Siege remains 5
And their laft food our dying Men fuftains.

Guy. One means is only left, I to, this hour^
Have kept the Captive from Algeria's pow'r:
And though by your Command (he often fent
To urge his doom, do ftill his death prevent.

Mont. That hope is paft : him I have oft afTail'd*
But neither threats nor kindnefs have prevailed 5
Hiding our wants, I ofFer'd to releafe
His Chains, and equally conclude a Peace:
Be fiercely anfwer'd, I had now no way
But to fubimit, and without terms obey:

ItoM



(4»)

I told him he in Chains demanded more
Then he impos'd in Vi&ory before :
Hefullenlyreply'd, he could not make
Thefe offers- now"* Honour muft give, not take.'

Odm, Twice have I fallyed, and was twice beat backs
What defp'rate courfe remains for us to take !

Mont. If either Death or Bondage Imuftchoofe,
Tie keep my Freedom, though my Life I lofe.

Guy. Tie not upbraid you that you once refus'd
Thofe means you might have then with Honour us'd :
Vie lead your Men, perhaps bring Victory :
They know to Conquer beft, who know to Dye.

\_Exeuht Montezuma, Odmari
Alib. Ah me, what have I heard/ ftay Guyomar^
What hope you from this Sally you prepare }

Guy. A death, with Honour for my Countries good :
And to that ufe your felf defign'd my blood.

Alib, You heard, and I well know the Towns diftrefs ?
Which Sword and Famine both at onceoppreft „•
Famine fo fierce, that what's deny'd Man's ufe,
Even deadly Plants, and Herbs of pois'nous juice
Wild hunger feeks ••> and to prolong our breath,
We greedily devour our certain death .•
The Soldier in th' affault of Famine falls 5
And Ghofts, not Men, are watching on the Walls,

As Callow Birds — \

Whofe Mother's killM in feeking of the prey.
Cry in their Neft,and think her long away 5
And at eachleafthat ftirs, each blaft of wind j
Gape for the Food which they muft never find :
So cry the people in their tmfery.

Guy And what relief can they erpecl: from me?
Alib. While Montezuma fleeps, call in the Foe :
The Captive General your deiigne may know :
His Noble Heart, to Honour ever true,
Knows how to fpareaswellas tofubdue. 'P- -< * ■■
Guy, What I have heard I bJnlh to hear .-and grieve
Thole words you fpoke I muft your words believe j

G 2 I to



I to do this / I, whom you once thought brave, •
To fell my Countrey, and my King enflave?
All I have done by one foul ad deface,
And yield my right to you by turning bafe>
What more could Qdmar wilh that I fhould do ...'..
To ldfe your Love, then you perfwade me to i .'■
No, Madam, no, I never can commit
A deed fo ill, nor can you fuffer it :
*Tis but to try what .Vertue you can find
Lodg'd in my Sou], ■.«,..'

Abb. I plainly fpeak my mind 5
Dear as my Life my Vertue Ilepreferve:
But .Vertue you too fcrupuloufly ferve:
Ilov'd not more then now my Countrey s good,
When for its fervice I em ploy 'd: your -Blood:
But things are alter'd, I am (till the fame, '
By different ways, ftill moving to one fame 3
And by difarming you, I now do more
Tofave the Town, then arming you before.

Guy. Things good or ill by circumftances be, j ( -j "
In you 'tis Vertue, , what is Vice in' me.

Alib. That ill is pardon' d which does good procure.

Guy. The good's uncertain, but the ill is fure.

Alib. When Kings grow ftubborn, flothful, or unwife,
Each private man for publick good (bould rife.

Guy, Take heed, fair Maid, hew Mpnarchs you accufe:
Sucrr reafons none but impious Rebels ufe :
Thofe who to Empire by dark paths afpire.
Still plead a Call to what they moft defire 5
But Kings by free confent their Kingdoms take,
iStricl: as thofe facred Ties which Nuptials make 5 7

And what e're faults in Princes time reveal.
None can be Judge where can be no Appeal.

Alib. In all debates you plainly let me fee
You love your Vertue beft, but odmar me.
Go, your miftaken Piety purfue :
I'll have from him what is deny'd by you 5

With



1. x..



With my Commands you (hall no more be grac'd 3
Remember, Sir, this trial was your laft.

Guy. The gods infpireyou with a better mind j
Make you more juft, and make you then more kind i
But though from Vertues rules I cannot part
Think I deny you with a bleeding Heart :
'Tis hard with me whatever choice I make 5
I muft not merit you., or muft forfake :
But in this ftraight, to Honour He be true.,
And leave my fortune to the gods and you.

Enter Meffenger privately.

Mejf. Now is the time 5 be aiding to your Fate y
From the Watch-Tower,, above the Weftern Gate,
I have difcern'd the Foe fecurely lye,
Too proud to fear a beaten Enemy:
Their careless Chiefs to the cool Grottoes run,
The Bowers of Kings, -to fhade them from the Sun,

Guy, Upon thy life difclofe thy news to none 5.
Fie make the Conqueftor the fhame my own.

[Exit Guyomar^^MefTenger,
Enter Odmar.

Alib. I read fome welcome meffage in his Eye :
Prince Odmar comes : Fie fee if he'l deny.
Odmar I come to tell you pleafing News,
I beg'd a thing your Brother did refufe.

Odm. The news both pleafes me and grieves me too 5
For nothing, fure, fhould be deny s d to you :
But he was bleft who might commanded be 5
You never meant that happinefs to me.

Alib. What he refus'd your kindnefs might beftow,
But my Commands, perhaps, your burden grow.

Odm* Could T but live till burdenfome they prove,
My Life would be immortal as my Love.
Your wifh, e're it receive a name, I grant*

Alib. 3 Tis to relieve your dying Countries want }
All hopes of iuccor from your ^rms is paft.
To fave us now you muft our Ruine haft 5

Give



(44)
Xj'ive up the Town 3 and to oblige him more,
The Captive General's liberty reftore.

Odm. You fpeak to try my Love, can you forgive
Sofoon to let your Brother s Murd'rer live >

Alib. Orbeliatj) though my Brother did difgrace
With treacherous Deeds, our Mighty Mothers Race 5
And to revenge his Blood fo juftly fpilt,
What isit lefs than to partake his Guilt ?
Though my proud Sifter to revenge incline,,
I to my Countrey's good my own refigne.

Odm. To fave our Lives our freedom I betray

— Yet fince I promised it I will obey 5

Tie not my Shame nor your Commands difpute :

You fhall behold your Empire s abfolute. [Exit Odmar.

Alib. I fhould have thank'd him for his fpeedygrants
And yet I know not how, fit words I want :
Sure! am grown diftradred in my mind,
That joy this grant fhould bring I cannot find .•
The one, denying, vex'd my Soul before •,
And this, obeying, has difturb'd me more:
The one with grief, andflowly did refufe.
The other, in his grant, much hafte did ufe :

He us'd too much 4 and granting mefo foon,

He has the merit of the gift undone :
Methought with wondrous eafe,hefwallow'd down
His forfeit Honour, to betray the Town :
My inward choice was Guyomar before,

But now his Vertue has coofirm'd me more ■

1 rave, I rave, for Odmar will obey.

And then my promife muft my choice betray.

Fantaftick Honour, thou haft fram'd a toyl

Thy felf,to make thy Love thy Vertues fpoil. [Exit Alibech.



SCENE



C40 v

scene in.

A pleafant Grotto difcover'd : in it a Fountain fp outing] round
about it Vafquez, Pizarro, and other Spaniards lying carelejly
unarm % and by them many Indian Women, one of which
fings the following Song*

SONG.

Ah fading joy, how quickly art thou paft }■

Tet we thy ruine hajii
As if the cares of Humane Life were few

We feek, out new ,
And follow Fate which would too f aft furfur

See how on every bough the Birds exprefs*
In their fweet notes their happinefs
They all enjoy, and nothing fpare 3
But on their Mother Nature lay their care ,
Why thenfhould Man, the Lord of all below

Such troubles chufe to hgows
As none of aU his SubjeUs undergo £

Bark, hark^ the Waters fall, fall, faU\
And with a murmuring found
Dafi, dafh, -upon the ground,

to gentle flumbers call, #*

After the Song two Spaniards arife and dance a Sara-
band with Caftanietas •* at the end of which, Guyomar
and his Indians enter, and e're the Spaniards can recover,
their Swords, feize them..

Guy. Thofe whom you took without in Triumph bring*.
But fee thefe ftreight conducted to the King.

Viz,. Vajquez, what now remains in thefe extreams £
Vafq % Only to wake us from our Golden Dreams.

Vim*



— —



C # ) •

Viz. Since by our fhamful conduct we have loft
Freedom, Wealth., Honour, which we value moft,
I wKhthey would our Lives a period give :
They live too long who Happinefs out-live.

[Spaniards are ltd out:
i. Ind. See, Sir* how quickly your fuccefs is fpread :
The King comes marching injthe Armies head. ;

Enter Montezuma, Alibech 3 Odmar, teifcontentedi
Mont.Now all the gods reward and blefs my §on:[Embracing.
Thou haft this day thy Fathers Youth out-done.

Alib. Juft Heaven all Happinefs upon him ftiower,
Till it confefs its will beyond it's power.

Guy. The Heavens are kind, the gods propitious be,
I only doubt a mortal Deity :
I neither fought for Conqueft., nor for Fame,
Your Love alone can recompe nee my Flame.

Alib. I gave my Love to the moft brave in War 3
But that the King muft judge.
Mont. Tis Guyomar.

[Soldi ersjhout^ A Guyomar ; c2°c,
Mont. This day your Nuptials we will Celebrate -,
But guard thefe haughty Captives till their Fate:
Odmar^ this night to keep them be your care.
To morrow for their Sacrifice prepare.

Alib. Blot not your Conqueft with your Cruelty.
Mont. Fate fays we are notfafe unlefs they dye':
The Spirit that foretold this happy day.,
Bid me ufe Caution and avoid delay :
Pofterity be jufter to my Fame $
Nor call it Murder, when each private Man
In his defence may juftly do the fame :
But private perfons more than Monarchs can :
All weigh our Acts, and what e r feems unjuft,
Impute not to Neceffity, but Luft.

[Exeunt Montezuma, Guyomar, and Alibech,
Odm. Loftand undone ! he had my Fathers voice,
And /4///wZ>feem'dpleas'd with her new choice :
Alas 5 it was new ! too too late I fee,

Since



(47)
Since one (he hated, that it muft be me.™— ; ^

L. T feel a ftrange Temptation in my will

To do an action, great at once and ill .•

Vertue ill Treated from my Soul is fled 5

I by Revenge and Love am wholly led:

Yet Confcience would againft my rage rebel; — — .

_ Confcience, the foolifh Pride of doingweli I

Sink Empire, Father Perifh, Brother Fall,
Revenge does more than recompence you all.

Conduct the Prisoners in —

Spaniards you fee your own deplor'd Eftate [Enter Vafquez ?
What dare you do to reconcile your Fate?7Pizarro.
Vafq. All that Difpair, with Courage joyn'd can do.
Odm. An eafie way to Victory iPe (how :
When allare buried in their Sleep or Joy,
Tie give you Arms, Burn, Ravifli, and Deftroy 5
For my own (hare one Beauty I defign.
Engage your Honours that (he (hall be mine.
Viz. I gladly Swear.

Vafq. .Andl^ butlrequeft

That, in return, one who has touch 'd my Breit,
Whofenamel know not, may be given to me,

odm. Spaniard 'tis jufl: i (he's yours whoe're (he be.
Vafq. The night comes on : if Fortune ble& the bold
I (hall poflefs the Beauty.

Viz. I the Gold. [^Exeunt omnes t

SCENE, IV. AVrifon.

Cortez difcovered, bound : Almeria talking with

him.

Aim. I come not now your conftancy to prove,
You may believe me when I fay I Love.

Cort. You have too well inftru&ed me before,
In your intentions to believe you more.

Aim. I'm juftly plagu'd by this your unbelief.
And am myfelfme caufeof my own grief :

H But



)

But to beg love, Icarmot ftoop fo low 5

It is enough that you my paffion know :

'Tis in your choice 5 Love me, or love me notS Lays hold on

I have not yet my Brother's Death forgot. Xthe Dagger.

Cert, You Menace me and Court me in a breath .•
Your Cupid looks as dreadfully as Death.

Aim. Your hopes, without* are vanifrYd into fmoke ':'
Your Captains taken, and your Armies broke.
Cort. Tn vain you urge me with my miferies:
When Fortune falls, high Courages can rife.
Nowfhouldl change mylove,it Would appear
Not the effedt of gratitude, but fear.

Jim. lie to the King, and make it my Request,
Or my Command that you may be releaft 5
And make you judge, when I have fet you free.,
Who bed: defer ves your paffion, I, or (he.

Cort. You tempt my FYith fo generous away,
As without guilt, might conftancy betray ,
But Tm fo far from meriting efteem,
That if f judge Imuft my felfe condemned
Yet having given my wOrthlefs heart before.
What Imuft ne'r poffefs I will adore 5
Takemy devotion then this humbler way $
Devotion is the love which Heaven we pay. [Kijfesher hand Q

Enter Cydaria.
Cyd. May I believe my Eyes 1 whatdolfee?
Is this her Hate to him, his love to me!
'Tis in my breaft (he (heaths her Dagger now.
Falfe Man, is this the Faith > is this the Vow? [to him.,

Cort. What words, dear Saint, are thefe I hear you ufe >
What Faith, what Vows are thofe which you acenfe?

Cyd. More cruel than the Tyger o're his fpoil 5
And falfer than the weeping Crocodile:
Can you add vanity to Guilt, and take
A Pride to hear the Conquefts which you make ?
Go publifh your Renown, let it befaid
You have a Woman., and thatlov'd P betray'd,

Corp



cm

Cort. Wkhwhatinjufticeismy Faith aecuVd £
Life, Freedom, Empire, I at once refus'd 5
And would again ten thoufand times for you.

Aim. She'l have too great content to find him true 5
And therefore fince his Love is not for me,
rie help to make my Rivals mifery. £ jfi ££

Spaniard^ I never thought you falfe before : [To him.

Can you at once two Miftreffes adore > •,

Keep the poor Soul no longer in fufpence,
Your change is fuch as does notneed defence.
Cort. Riddles like thefe I cannot underftand !
Aim, Why fhould you blufh ? (he faw you kifs my hand.
Cyd, Fear not, 1 will, while your firft Love's deny 'd,
Favour your (hame, and turn my Eyes afide 3
My feeble hopes in her deferts are loft :
I neither can fuch power nor beauty boaft :
I have no tyeupon you to be true,
But that which loofned yours, my Love to you.
Cort. Could you have heard my words!

Cyd. Alas, what needs

To hear your words, when I beheld your deeds ?
Cort. What (hall I fay ! the Fate of Love is fuch,
That (till it Cees too little or too much..
That act of mine which does your paffion move
Was but a mark of my Refpecr, not Love. »
Aim. Vex not your (elf excufes to prepare:
For oneyou love not is not worth your care.

Cort, Cruel Almeria take that life you gave 5
Since you but worfe deftroy me, while you fave.

Cyd. No y let me dye and He my claim refigne '■>
For while I live, methinks you (hould be mine.

Cort, The bio odieft Vengeance which (he could puriue.
Would be a trifle to my lofs of you. v

Cyd. Your change Was wife : for had (he been deny 'd,
A fwift Revenge had follow'd from henPride :
You from my gentle Nature had no Fears,
AH my Revenge is only in my Tears. .. •

H 2 : Cort.



Cort, Can you imagine 1 fo mean could prove-,
To fave my Life by changing of my Love?

Cyd. Since Death is that which NaVrally we fbun ?
You did no more then \ perhaps had done.

Cort, Make me not doubt, Fair Soul, your conftancy 5
• You would have dy'd for Love,and lb would I.

Aim. You may believe him y you have feen it provd..
Cort. Can I not gain belief, how Ihaveiov'd?
What can thy ends> malicious Beauty, be :
Can he who kill'dthy Brother live for thee?

£ A noife of Glajhing of Sword f;
QVafquez within^ Indians againft him,
Vafq, Yield'Skves or die^our Sword (hall force our wayQ»# &»
Ivd.We cannot,though o're-powr'd,our truft betray[withiw.
Cort, 'Tis Vafquez voice, he brings me Liberty.
Vafq.ln fpight of Fate I le fet my General Free: ^within*.
Now Vifroryforus, the Town's our own.

Aim* Allhopes of fafety and of love are gone .•
As when fome dreadful Thunder-clap is nigh.
The winged Fire (hoots fwiftly through the Skie,
Strikes andconfumes e're fcarce it does appear.
And by the fuddain ill, prevents the fear :-
Such is my ftatein this amazing wo>
It leaves no pow'r to think, much lefs to do :
.But (hall my Rival live, (hall (he enjoy-
That Love in Peace I labour'd to deftroy ? [Aj/de*

Cort. Her looks grow black as a tempeftuous wind 5
Some raging Thoughts are rowling in her mind.

Aim. Rival, I muftyour jealoufie remove,
You (hall, hereafter, be at reft for Love-
Cyd, Now you are kind.
j/^_^^-He whom you love is true/
But he (hall never be poffeit by you.

[Draws far Dagger ^and runs towards her,
Cort. Hold, hold, afa barbarous Woman ! flie,ohflie!
Cyd, Ah pity, pity, is no fuccor nigh I.
Cort. Run , run behind me, there you may be fure^
While I have Life I will your Life fecure.

[Cydmagets behind him. Aim.



Aim. On him or thee light Vengeance any where :

[she fiabs and hurts him,
- — What have I done } I fee his Blood appear !

Cyd. It dreams, it dreams from every Vital part :
Was there no way but this to find his Heart >

Aim. Ah! Curfed Woman, that was ray defigne L
This Weapons point (hall mix that Blood with mine !

[Goes to ftab herfelf^ and being within
his reach he fnatches the Dagger*
Cort. Now neither Life nor Death are in your power.
Aim. Then fullenly Fie wait my Fatal hour.

Enter Vafquez and Pizarro with drawn Swords..

Vafq. He Lives, he Lives.

Cort. Unfetter me with fpeed,

Vafquez^ I fee you troubled that I bleed :-
But tis not deep, our Army I can head.

Vafq, You to a certain Victory are led ,
Your Men all Arm'd, ftand filently within:
I with your Freedom, didthe work begin.

Viz. What Friends we have, and how we came fo ftrong 3
We'l foftly tell you as we march along.

Cort . In this fafe place let mefecure your fear : [To Cydav
No clashing Swords, no noife can enter here.
Amidft our Arms as quiet you (hall be
As Halcyon Brooding on a Winter Sea.

Cyd. Leave me not here alone, and full of fright-
Amidft the Terrors of a dreadful night :
You judge, alas, my Courage by your own;,
I never durft in darknefs be alone i
I beg, I throw me humbly at your Feet —

Cort. You muft not go where you may dangers meet*
Th' unruly Sword will no distinction make :
AndBeauty will not there give wounds, but take.

Aim. Then ftay and take me with you | though to be,
A Slave to wait uponyour Victory.
My Heart unmov'd, can noife and Horror bear:
Parting from you is all the Death I fear.

tortk



Govt. Almeria^us enough I leave you free :
You neither muft ftay here, nor go with me.

Aim. Then take my Life, that will my reft reftore:
Tis all I ask for faving yours before.

Cort. That were a barbarous return of Love*

Aim. Yet, leaving it, you more inhumane prove : .
In both extreams T fome relief (houid find :
Oh either hate me more, or be more kind.

Cort. Life of my Soul do not my abfence mourn :
But ch ear your Heart in hopes of my return. [To Cydaria,
Your Noble Fathers Life, (hall be my care }
And both your Brothers I'm oblig'd to fpare.

Cyd. Fate makes you Deaf while I in vain implore,
My heart forbodes I ne'r (hall fee you more:
I have but one requeft, when I am Dead
Let not my Rival to your Love fucceed.

Cort. Fate will be- kinder then your Fears fore-tell 5
Farewel my Dear>

Cyd. -A. long and lafl: farewel:

—So eager to imploy the cruel Sword 5

Can you not one lafl: look afford !

Cort. I melt to womanifh Tears, and if I fhy$
I find my Love my Courage will betray }
Yon Tower will keep you fafe, butbe fokuid
To your own Life that none may entrance find,

Cyd. Then lead me there- [Be leads hr

For this one Minute of your Company,
1 go methinks, with fome content to Dye.

[Exeunt Cortez, Vafquez, Pizarro,Cydaria.

Aim, Farewel, O too much Lov 3 d,fincelov d in vain ! [Sola
What Difmal Fortune does for me remain !
Night and Defpair my Fatal Foot- Heps guide 5
That Chance may give the Death which he deny'd, [Exit.
[Cortez, Vafquez, Pizarvo^ and Spaniards return again.
Cort. All I hold dear, 1 truft to your defence 5 [To Pizarro.
Guard her, and on your Life, remove not hence.

[Exeunt Cortez and Vafquez.

Viz.



( S3)

Tiz. Tie venture that-



The gods are good 5 lie leave her to their care.

Steal from my Poft, and in the Plunder fhare. '(Exit.



ACT V.

SCENE, I.

The Chamber Royal , an Indian Hamock difcoverdin it.
Enter Odmar with Soldiers, Guyomar, Alibech, bound,,

QdmJT^kte is more juft then you to my defert,

JT* And in this Act you blame, Heaven takes my pas&*.

Guy, Can there be Gods, and no Revenge provide £

Odm. The gods are ever of the Conquering fide :
She's now my Queen, the Spaniardshzve agreed
I to my Fathers Empire lhallfucceed.

Alib, How much I Crowns contemn, I let thee fee,
Chufingthe younger, and refufing thee.

Guy, Were (he Ambitious, (he'd difdain to own
The Pageant Pompoffuch a fervile Throne:
A Throne which thou by Parricide doft gain,
And by a bafe fubmifiion mud retain.

Alib. I lov'd thee not before, but, Odmar know
Thatnow I hate thee and defpife thee too.

Odm. With too much violence you Crimes purfue a
Which if I Acted, 'twas for love, of you :
This, if it teach not Love, may teach you Fear:
I brought not Sin fo far, to ftop it here.
Death in a Lovers mouth, would found but ill :
But know, I either muft enjoy, or kill;

Alib. Beftow, bafe Man thy idle threats elfewhere P ,
My Mothers Daughter knows not how to Fear.
Since Guyomar, I muft not be thy Bride,
Death (hall enjoy what is to thee deny'd.

Odm. Then take thy wifhv

Guy. Hold, Odmmr^ hold :• • ■■ : *

Mm



C?4)

My right in Alibech T will refer*-*
Rather than fee her Dye, Fie fee her thine.

Alib. In vain thou wouldft refign, for I will be,,
Ev'n when thou leav'ft me, Conftant frill to thee :
That (hall not fave my Life : wilt thou appear
Fearful for her, who for her felf wants Fear?

Odm, Her Love to him (hews- me a furerway .*
I by her Love, her Vertue muft betray.- [Ajide.

Since, Alibeck^you arefo true a Wife •, [To her.

s Tis in your power to fave your Husbands Life :
The gods, by me, your Love and Vertue try :
For both willfufFer, if you let him Dye.

Alib. I never can believe you will proceed
Tofuch a Black and -Execrable Deed.

odm. I only threatn'd you 5 but could not prove
So much a Fool to murder what I Love :
But in his Death, I fome advantage fee :
Worfe than it is, I'm fure it cannot be.
If you confent, you with that gentle Breath
Preferve his Life : if not, behold his Death.

[Holds -his Sword to his Breajl.
Ahb. What (hall I do!

Guy ■ .What are your thoughts at (Irife

About a ranfom to preferve my Life>
Though to fave yours I did my Intereft give,
Think not when you were his I meant to live.

Alib* O let him be preferv'd by any way :
But name not the foul price which I miift pay. [To odmar.
Odm. You would and would not, Tie no longer ftay.

[Offers again to kill him.
Alib. I yield, I yield, but yet e're I am ill.
An innocent deftre I would fulfil :
With Guyomar I one chad: Kifs would leave,
The firft and lafl: he ever can receive.

Odm. Have what you ask : that Minute you agree
To my defires, your Husband (hall be free.

[They nnbmd her 9 fie goes to her Husband,

Guy.



Guy. No. Alibech^ we never muft imbrace r • I jWeltwm
Your guilty kindnefs why do you mifplace > , Xfrpm, bw
'Tis meant to him, he is yourprivate Choice : "' T, ,' \

I' was made yours, but by the publick voice.
And now you leave me with a poor pretence,
That your ill Aft: is for my life's defence.

AliU Since there remains no other means to try,
Think I am falfe 5 T cannot fee you dye.

Gup To give for me both Life and Honour too
Is more, perhaps then I could"give for you.
You have done much to cure my Jealoufie. ^
But cannot perfect it unlefs both Die:
For fince both cannot live, who (lays behind
Muft be thought fearful, or, what's worfe, unkind.

Alib. I never could propofe that Death you chufej
But am like you, too jealous to refufe. [Embracing him.
Together dying, we together mow
That both did pay that Faith which both did owe.

Odm. It then remains I act my own defign .*
Have you your wills, but I will firit have mine.

Affift me Souldiers. — —

[They goto bjnd heroic crks out*
Enter Vafquez, two Spaniards.

Vafq. Hold, odmar, hold, I come in happy time
To hinder my misfortune, and your Crime.

Odm. You til return the kindnefs T have mown.

Vafq. Indian^ Tfay deilft. ; V

Odm. j — Syaniard^ be gone. '

Vafq. This Lady I did for my felfdefigne:
Dare you attempt her Honour who is mine .<?

Odm. ' You 're mu6h' miftaken^ ' this ; is '(he whom I
Did with my Father's lofs, and .Coikitry'sbuy :
She whom your promife did to me convey.
When all things elte were made your common prey.

Vafq. ThatprOmife made excepted one forme 5
One whom I (till referv'd,' and this is (he.
''odm. This is not The, you cannot fee fobafe*

- I Vafq.



? ?<$#.- I love too deeply to miftake the Face :
The.Vanqu.iuYd mull receive the Victors Laws.

odm t If I am vanquifh'd I my felf am Caufe..

Vafq. Then thank your felf for what you undergo^

Odm. ThusLawlefs Might does Juftice overthrow.-

Vafq. Tray tors, like you, (houki never Juftice name,.

Odm. You owe your Triumphs to that Traitors fhame»
But to your General Tie my right refer.

Vafq. He never, will protect a Raviftier:
His Generous Heart will foon decide our ftrife 5,
Heto your Brotherwill reftore his Wife.
It refts, we two our claim in Combat try,
And that with this fair prize, the Victor flye*

odm. Makehafte,
I cannot fuffer to be long perplext :
Conqueft.is my fir ft with, and Death my next.

'Xjhey Fight, the Spaniards and Indians fights

Alib. The. gods the Wicked by themfelves o'rethrow:
All Fight againft us now and for us too \[Vnbinds her Husband.
^rhetwoSp.amzvdsandthree]nd\ansI{iM each other Va{quez
kills Odmar, Guyomar runs to his Brothers Sword,

Vafq. Now you are mine,my greateft Foe is (lain.7<? Alibech.

Guy. A greater (till to vanquifh does remain.

Vafq. Another yet!
The Wounds I make but fow new Enemies:
Which from their Blood, like Earth-born Brethren rife.

Guy. Spaniardtzke. breath : fome refpite Tie afford,
My Caufe is more advantage then your Sword.

Vafq. Thou art fo brave could it with Honour be,

i'de leek thy FriendOiip more then Victory.

Guy. Friend Chip with him whofe hand did Odmar kill !
Bafe as he was, he was my Brother ftill:
And fince his Blood has wauYd away his Guilt,
Nature asks thine for that which thou haft fpilt.

[They Fight a little and breathe > Alibech takes up a
Sword and comes on.
Mib* My weaknefs may help fomethingin the ftrife.

Guy 3 .



'(w).

Guy. Kill not my Honour to preferve my Life :\_suywghef«
Rather then by thy aid Tie Conqueft gain.
Without defence I poorly will be (lain.

[she goes bac^ they Fight again, Vafquez jfc#>*

Guy. Now Spaniard, beg thy Life, and thou (halt live.

Vafq. 'Twere vain to ask thee what thou canft not give :
My breath goes out, and lam now no more.
Yet her I lov'd, in Death I will adore. L D J eSo

Guy, Come, Alibech, let us from hence remove ;
This is a night of Horror 5 not of Love.
From every part I hear a dreadful noife :
The Vanquith'd Crying, and the Victors Joys.
Tie to my Father's aid, and Countreys flye j
And fuccor both, or in their ruine dye. [Exeunt,

SCENE, IL AFrifon.

Montezuma, Indian High Prieft bounds Pizarro,Spaniards with
Swords drawn, a. Chri ft ian Prieft.

Viz. Thou haft not yet difcover'd all thy (lore.

Mont, I neither can nor will difcover more :■
The god swill punifhyou, if they be juft;
The gods will plague your Sacrilegious Luft.

Chr, Vr. Mark how this impious Heathen juftifies
His own falfe gods, and our true God denies
How wickedly he has refus'd his wealth.
And hid his Gold, from Chriftian hands, by ftealth:
Down with him, kill him, merit Heaven thereby.

Ind. HighVr, Can Heaven be Author of fuch Cruely ?

Viz. Since neither threats nor kindnefs will prevail,
Wemuftby other means your minds afTail j
Fatten the Engines 5 ftretch 'em at their length;
And pull the ftraightned Cords with all your ftrength.

[Theyfaften them to the Kach^ and then pull them,

Mont. The gods, who made me once a King, (hall know
I ftill am worthy to continue fo :

I a Though



C?8)

Though now the fubjeft of your Tyranny, .
I'le plague you worfe then you can punifh me,
Know, I have Gold, which you (hail never find;,
No Pains, no Tortures (hall unlock my Mind.

dr. Pr. Pull harder yet *, he does not feel the Rack.

Mont. Pull till my Veins break, and my Sinews crack.

Ind. High Fr. When will you end your Barb'rous Cruelty >
I beg not to efcape, I beg to Dye.

Mont, Shame on thy Priefthood thatfuch pray'rs can bring;
Is it not brave to fuffer with thy King?
When Monarchs fuffer, gods themfelves bear part y
Then well may s ft thou, who but my Vaftal art .•
I charge thee dare riot groan, nor (hew one fign ;
Thou at thy Torments doft the leaft repine. f Crown,

Ind, HJghVr. You took an Oath when you receiv'd your
The Heavens (hould pour their ufual Bleffings down 5
The S>uu (hould (hine, the Earth it's Fruits produce,
And nought be wanting to your Subjects ufe:
Yet we with Famine were opprefr, and now
Muft to the yoke of Cruel Matters bow.

Mont. If thofe above, who made the World, could be
Forgetful of it, why then blam'ft thou me>

clr.Tr. Thofe Pains, OPrince,thoufurTereft now are light
Compar'd to thofe, which when thy Soul takes flight,
Immortal, endlefs, thou muft then endure.
Which Death begins, and Time can never cure,

Mont, Thou art deceiv'd: for whenfoe re I dye.
The Sun my Father bears my Soul on high :
He lets me down a Beam, and mounted there,
He draws it backhand pulls me through the Air:
I in the Eaftern parts> and rifing Sky,
You in Heaven's downfal, and the Weft muft lye.

Chr. Fr, Fond Man, by Heathen Ignorance mifled.
Thy Soul deftroying when thy Body's dead.*
Change yet thy Faith, and buy Eternal reft.

Ind. HighPr. Dye in your o\rn: for our Belief isbefh.

Mont. Infeekinghappinefs you both agree,
But in the fearch, the paths fo different be.,

That



(59)

That all Religions with each other* Fighf^
While only one can lead us in the Right,
But till that one hathfome more certain mark.
Poor humane kind muft wander in the dark.
And fuffer pains eternally below..
For that, which here, we cannot come to know,

Chr.Pr. That which weworfhip, and which you believe^,
From Natures common hand we both receive :
Ail under various Names, Adore and Love
One Power Immenfe, which ever rules above.
Vice to abhor, and Vertue to purfue,
Is both believ'd and taught by us and you:
But here our worfhip takes another way.— —

■Mm**.- Where. both agree. Vis there mod fafe to fray t
For what's more vain then publick light to fhun,
And fet up Tapers while we fee the Sun }

chr. Pr. Though Nature teaches whom we (hould adore,,,
By Heavenly Beams we dill difcove* more.

Mont, Or this muft be enough, or to- Mankind
One equal way to blifs is not defign'd.
For though fome more may know, and fome know leCs^
Yet all muft know enough for happinefs.

Chr. Pr. If in this middle way you (till pretend i
To flay, your Journey never will have end.

Mont. Howe*re, 'tis better in the midft toftay.
Then wander farther in uncertain way.

Chr,F. But we by Martyrdom our Faith avow..

Mont, You do no more then I for ours do now,

To prove Religion true — —

l£ either Wit or Sufferings would fuffice,
All Faiths afford the Conftant and the Wife t
And yet ev'n they, by Education fway'd.
In age defend what infancy obey d.

Chr, Pr. Since Age by erring Childhood is milled,
Refer your felf to our Unerring Head.

Mont. Man and not erre / whatreafon can you give>
• Chr.Pr. Renounce that carnal Reafon, and believe.



Mont. The light of Nature (hould'I thus betray,
Twere to wink hard that'I might fee the day.

Chr. ?r. Condemn not yet the way you do not knows
Tie make your Reafon judge what way to go.

Mont. 'Tis much too late forme new ways to take.
Who have but one (hart ftep of life to make.

mU, Increafe their Pains, the Cords are yet too flack.

chr. Tr. I muft by force convert him on the Rack.

Incl.High Vr. I faint away, and find I can no more '
Give leave, O King, 1 may reveal thy ftore,
And free my felf from pains I cannot bear.

Mont. Think'ft thou I lye on Beds of Rofes here.
Or in a wanton Bath ftretch'd at my eafe ?
Dye, Slave, and with thee, dye fuch thoughts as thefe,

QHigk Prieft turns afideand djies t

Enter Cortez attended by Spaniards, hefyeakjentring,

Cort. On painofdeatlj kill none butthofe who fight j
I much repent me of this bloody night :
Slaughter grows murder when it goes too far.
And makes aMafTacre what was a War-:
Sheath all your weapons, and in filencemove,
Tis facred here, to Beauty and to Love.
Ha [sees Montezuma.

Cort. What difrnal fight is this, which takes from me
All the delight that waits on victory I

[Runs to uke him off the Rae^,
Make hafce: how now. Religion do you frown?
Hafte holy Avarice, and help him down.
Ah Father, Father, what do I endure {Embracing Montezuma.
To fee thefe wounds my pity cannot cure !

Mont. Am I fo low that you fhould pity bring,
And give an Infants Comfort to a King?
Ask thefe if I have once unmanly groan'd j
Or ought have done deferving to be moan'd.

Cort. Did I not charge thou (houldft not ftir fromhence?[Ti?
But Martial Law (hall punifti thy offence Pizarro.

And you, [To the Chr. Triej} m

Who



* cm

Who faucily, teach Monarchs to obey,
And the wide World in narrow Cloyfters fway $j
Set up by Kings as humble aids of power,
You that which bred you, Viper-like devour,
Tou Enemies of Crowns.

Chr. Pr. —Come, let's away.

We but provoke his fury by our (lay.

Cort. If this go free, farewelthat difcipline
Which did inSpanifti Camps feverely Qiine :
Accurfed Gold, 'tis thou haftcaus'd thefe crimes 5
Thou turnft our Steel againft thy parent Climes !
And into Spain wilt fatally be brought,
Since with the price of blood thou here art bought.

[Exeunt Pried and Pizzrro
[Cortez kneels by Montezuma andweepn.
Cort. Can you forget thofe Crimes they did commit?
Mont. Tledo what for my dignity is fit:
Rife, Sir, I'm fatisfi'd the fault was theirs:
Truft me you make me weep to fee your Tears ■:;
Mufti chear you?
Cort. Ah Heavens!

Mont. —You're much to blame 5

Your grief is cruel, for it (hews my fhame,
Does my loft Crown to my remembrance bring tz
But weep not you, and Fie be ftill a Ring.
You have forgot that I your Death defign'd,
To fatisfie the Proud Almerias mind :
YoUyWhoprefervdmy Life, I doom'dto Dye.
Cort. Your Love did that, and not your Cruelty,,

Enter a Spaniard,

Sfan. Prince Guyomar the Combat ftill maintain^
Our Men retreat, and he their ground regains:
But once ineourag'd by our Generals fight.
We boldly (hould renew the doubtful Fight-

Cort. Remove not hence,you (hall not long attend".^ ^ M6n-
Fie aid my Soldiers, yet preferve my Friend, : tezuma.

Mont. Excellent Man! [ExrtCortez^&c-.



14*}

But I, by livings poorly take the way
To injure Goodnefs : which I cannot pay.

Enter Almeria,
Aim. Ruine and Death run arm'd through every Street 5
And yet that Fate I feek I cannot meet :
What Guards Misfortunes are and Mifery !
Death that ftrikes all, yet feems afraid of me.

Mont- Almeria § here : oh turn away your Face f
Mult you be witnefs too of my difgrace t

Aim. I am not that Almeriawhom you knew,
But want that pity I deny'd to you :
Your Conquerour,alas 5 hasvanquiuYdme 5
Butherefufes his own Victory:
Whifeall are Captives in your conquered State,
I find a wretched freedom in his hate.

Mont. Couldft thou thy love 00 one who fcorn'd thee lofef
He faw not with my Eyes who could refufe:
Him who could prove fo much unkind to thee,
1 ne're will fufTerto be kind to me.

Aim, lam content in death to (hare your Fate 5
And dye for him I love with him I hate.

Mont. What (hall f do in this perplexing ftreight !
My tortur'd Limbs refufe to bear my weight : ^Endeavouring
I cannot go to Death to fet me free : ttowalk^^notbe'

Deathmuftbekind^andcomehimfelfto me. ing able.

Aim. Fve thought upon't : I have affairs below,]] Aim Mujing.
Which I rauft needs difpach before I go :
Sir, I have found a place, where you maybe, [Tohiw,-

("Though not preferv'd) yet like a King dye free :
The General left your Daughter in the Tower ^
We may a while reiift the Spaniards ppwer,

\i Cuyomar prevail, -. '■ — -

Mont, Make hafte and call ^
She'l hear your Voice, and anfwer from the Wall.

Jim, My voice (lie knows and fears, but ufe your own,
And togain entrance, feign you are alone. ) A\me*h]lps
Mont. Cj/daria. I behind. '

Aim.



Aim. Louder.

Mont. Daughter!

Aim. *— Louder yet.

Mont. Thou canftnot, Cure, thy Father's voice forget.

£ He knocks at the door, at lafi Cydaria loofe
over the Balcone.

Cyd. Since my Love went, I have been frighted fo s
With difmal Groans, and Noifes from below .♦
I durft not fend my Eyes abroad, for fear
Of feeing dangers, which I yet but hear.

Mont, Cydarial

Cyd. —Sure 'tis my Father calls.

Mont. Dear Child make hafte >

All hope of fuccor, but from thee is paft :

As when upon the Sands the Traveller

Sees the high Sea come rolling from afar,

The Land grow (hort, he mends his weary pace,

While Death behind him covers all the place :

So I by fwift misfortunes am purfu'd,

Which on each other, are like Waves renew'd,

Cyd. Are you alone ?
Mont. .- I am .

Cyd. — I'le ftreight defcend •-,

Heaven did you here for both our fafeties fend.

[Cydam defcends and opens thedoor, Almeria
rttffies betwixt with Montezuma.
Cyd. Almeria here ! then I am loft again. [Both thrttfl.
Aim. Yield to my ftrength, you ftruggle but in vain :
Make hafte and fhut, our Enemies appear.

QCortez and Spaniards appear at the other end.
Cyd. Then do you enter, and let me ftay here.

[As Jhe fpeakj) Almeria over-powers her 9
thrtifis her in ■, andjhuts

Cart. Sure I both heard her voice and faw her face,
She's like a Vifion vaniuVd from the place.

K Too



e^4) ,

Too late I find my abfence was too long 5

My hopes grow fickly, and my fears grow ft'rong,

[He ktiocks a little^ then Montezuma, Cydaria, Almeria.
appear above % *.

Aim. Look up, look up, and fee if you can know
Thofe whom in vain you think to find below.

Cyd. Look up and fee Cydaria s loft eftate,

Mont. And caft one look on Montezuma's Fate.

Con. Speak not fuch difmal words as wound my Ear:
Nor name Death to me when Cydaria's ; there.
Defpair not, Sir, who. knows but Conquering Spain
May part of what you loft reftore again ? s

Mont, No Spaniard^ know, he who' to Empire born, lU
Lives to be lefs, deferves the Victors fcorn :
Kings and their Crowns have but one deftiny: . ■
Power is their life, when that expires they die.

Cyd. What dreadful words are thefe!

Mont. Name Life no more s

'Tis now a Torture worfe then all I. bore: '...V

Fie not be brib'd to fufFer Life, but dye

In fpight of your miftaken clemency.

I was your Slave, and I was us'd like one 5

The Shame continues when the Pain is gone.*

But im a King while this is in my Hand,— ...... [Bk Sword.

He wants no Subjects who can Death Command :
Youfhould havety'd him up ? t'have concjuer'd me.
But he's ftill mine, and thus he fets me free. [stabs himfelf.

Cyd. Oh my dear Father!

Curt Hafte, break ope the door.

Aim. When that is forc'd there yet remain two more.

[The Soldiers breakjopen the firji door and go in.
We (hall have time enough to take our way.
Ere any can our Fatal Journey (lay,

Mont. Already mine is paft : O powers divine
Take my laft thanks , no longer I repine :
Imighthaveliv'd my own miftiaps to mourn/
While fome would f$ity me, but more would (corn !
For Pity only on frefti Objects ftays :

But



But with the tedious fight of Woes decay? .
Still lefs andlefs my boiling Spirits flow 3
And I grow ftiff as cooling Metals do :
Farewel Almeria

Cyd. —He's gone, he's gone,

And leaves poor me defencelefs here alone.

Aim. You fhall not long befo : prepare to die,
Thatyou may bear your Father company.

Cyd. Oh name not Death to me 5 you fright mefo 3
That with the Fear I fhall prevent the blow:
I know your Mercy's more, thentodeftroy
A thing fo young, fo innocent as I.

Cort. Whence can proceed thy cruel thirft of blood.
Ah Barb'rous Woman > Woman ! that's too good.
Too mild for thee : there's pity in that name,
But thou haft loft thy pity, with thy fhame.

Aim. Your cruel words have pierc'd me to the Heart 3
But on my Rival Tie revenge my fmart.

Cort. Oh ftay your hand! and to redeem my fault,

Tie fpeak the kindeft words _

That Tongue e're utter'd'^ or that Heart e're thought.

Dear Lovely -Sweet —

Aim. This but offends me more 3 i

You adl: your kindnefs on Cydarias fcore. t
Cyd. For his dear fake let me my Life receive.
Aim. Fool for his fake alone you muft not live :
Revenge is now my Joy 5 he's not for me, 3 a :
And Tie make fure he ne'r fhall be for thee.
Cyd. But what's my Crime ?
Aim. — — -'Tis Loving where I love.
Cyd. Your own example does my ad approve.
Aim, Tisfuch a fault I never can forgive.
Cyd. HowcanI mend, unlefs you let me live>
I yet am tender, young, and full of fear.
And dare not dye, but fain would tarry here.

Cort. If blood you feek, I will my own refign :
O (pare her Life,Und in exchange, take mine.

Aim. The Love you fhew but hafts her Death the more.

K 2 ^ Cork



(66)

tort. He run, and help to force the inner door.

[is going inhajle-*

Aim, Stay, Spaniard ? 3 fray, depart not from my Eyes :
That moment that I lofe your fight, (he dyes.
To look on you Tie grant a (hort Reprieve.

tort. O make your gift more full, and let her live :
I dare not go \ and yet how dare I ftay I
Her I would fave, I murder either way.

Cyd. Can you be fo hard-hearted, to deftroy
My ripening hopes, that are fo near to joy i
I juft approach to all I would poflefs :
Death only ftands 'twixt me and happinefs.

Aim. Your Father, with his life has Joft his Thrones
Your Countreys Freedom and Renown is gone.
Honour requires your Death : you mutt obey.

Cyd, Do you dye firft } and (hew me then the way*

Aim, Should you not follow, my Revenge were loft.

Cyd. T hen rife again, and fright me with your Ghoft.

Aim. I will not truft to that, fince Death I chufe,
I*Ienot leave you that Life which I refute .*
If Death's a pain, it is not lefs to me.
And if 'tis nothing, 'tis no more to thee.
But hark/ the noife increafes from behind.
They 're near, and may prevent what I defign*d:
Take, there a Rival's gift. — . [stab s her.

Cort. Perdition feize thee for fo black a deed.

Aim. Blame not an Act which did from Love proceed .•
lie thus revenge thee with thisEatal blow ■> [stabs herfelf.
Stand fair, and let my Heart-bjlood on thee flow.

Cyd. Stay life, and keep in the chearful light ,
Death is too black, and dwells in too much night*
Thou leav'ft me. Life, but Lovefupplies thy part,
And keeps me warm by lingring in my heart:
Yet dying for him, I thy claim remove 5
How dear it cofts to conquer in my Love /
Now ftrike: that thought 1 hope, will arm my breft**

Aim* Ah with what differing pajEons am I preft !



Cyd. Death, when far off, did terrible appears
But looks lefs dreadful as he comes more near.

Aim. O Rival, f have loft the power to kill 5
Strength has forfook my Arm 3 and Rage my will :
I muft furmount that Love which thou haft fhown :
Dying for him is due to me alone.
Thy weaknefs fhall not boaft the vi£tory 3
Now thou (halt live, and dead Fie conquer thee:
Souldiers affift me down.

[Exeunt from above led by Souldiers, and enter
both led by Cortez.
Cort. Is there no danger then ? [To Cydaria.

Cyd. « You need not fear

My Wound, I cannot dye vrhen you are near.

Cort. You for my fake. Life to Cydaria give .* [To Almeria*
And I could dye for you, if you might live.

Aim. Enough, I dye content, now you are kind 3
Kill'd in my Limbs., reviving in my mind :
Come near, Cydaria^ and forgive my Crime.

Cydaria jlarts bac\*
You need not fear my rage a fecond time :
Fie bathe your Wounds in Tears for my Offence :
That Hand which made it makes this Recompence.

[Ready to joy n their hands,,
I would have joyn'dyou, but my Heart's too highi
You will, too foon, pofTefshim when I dye.
Cort. She faints, O foftly fet her do wn.

Aim. ."ITis pa ft \

In thy lov'd Bofom let me breathe my laft.
Here in this one (hort Moment that Hive,

I have what ever the longeft Life coul d give. • —[Dyes*

Cort, Farewel, thou Generous Maid : ev'n Viftory
Glad as it is, muft lend fome Tears to thee.'
Many I dare not fried, left you believe [To Cydaria*

I joy in you lefs then for her I grieve.

Cyd. But are you fure (he's dead >
I muft embrace youfaft, before I know
Whether my Life be yet fecure or no :

Some



Some other hour I will to Tears allow (
But having you, can (hew noforrow now.

•Etf/er^Guyomar and Alibech bound, withsonldiers,
Cort. Prince Guyomar in bonds ! O Friendfhip's fhanie !
tt makes me blufti to own a Victors name.

[Vnbinds him^ Cydaria, Alibech.
Cyd. See Alibech, Almeria lyes there:
But do not think 'twas I that murder'd her.

[Alibech fywk andkjffis her Dead Sifter.
Cort. Live, and enjoy more than your Conquerour : f 2> Guy-
"■Take all my Love, and (hare in all my Power. > omar.

Guy. Think me not proudly rude, if I forfake
Thofe gifts I cannot with my Honour take:
I for my Country fought, and would again,
Had I yet left a Country to maintain :
But 0nce the Gods decreed it otherwife,
I ne^er will orbits dear Ruines rife.

Alih. Of all y&ur goodnefs leaves to our difpofe,
Our liberty *s the only gift we choofe :
Abfence alone can make our forrows lefs}
And not to fee what we can ne're redrefs.

Guy. Northward, beyond the Mountains we will go s
t Where Rocks lye cover 'd with Eternal Snow,
Thin Herbage in the Plains, and fruitlefs Fields,
The Sand no Gold, the Mine no Silver yields:
There Love and Freedom we'll in Peace enjoy j
No Spaniards will that Colony deftroy.
We to ourfelves will all our wifhes grant?
And nothing coveting, can nothing want.

Cort. Firft your Great Father's Funeral Pomp provide:
That done, in Peace your generous Exiles guide.
While I loud thanks pay to the Powers abave,

Thus doubly blefr, with Conqueft, and with Love. [Exeunt.

• ■



Fl^IS.



BY A





all and ftngular in this full meetings
Ladies and Gallants , Phoebus fends me greeting.
To all his Sons by what e're Title known,
Whether of Courts ofCojfee-houfe, or Town 5
From his wo ft mighty Sons ,whofe confidence
Is placed in lofty found, and humble fence,
Fvn to his little Infants of the Time
Who write new Songs, andTrufl in Tune and Rhyme,
Bet known that Phoebus (being daily grievd
To fee good Plays condemn d, and bad receiv'd,)
Ordains your judgement upon every Caufe,
Henceforth be limited by wholefome Laws,
Hefirjl thinkj fit no Sonnettier advance
His cenfure farther than the Song or Dance.
Tour Wit Burlefque may onejlep higher climb y
Andin his fphere may judge all. Dogger el Rhyme;
All 'proves 2 and moves, and Loves, and Honours too t
All that appears high fence, and fear ce is low.
As for the Coffee-wits he fays not much,
Their proper bus* nefs is to damn the Dutch."

Tor the great Dons of Wit

Phoebus gives them full priviledge alone
lo Damn all others, and cry up their own:
Lafi,for the Ladies, 'tis A polio' s Will,
They fhouldhave power to five, but not fo hjlls
For Love and He longflnce have thought it fit,
Wit live by Beauty, Beauty Raign by Wit.



4'



RICE INSTITUTE LIBRARY
P. O. BOX 1892
Houston, Texas
