
Skip to main content

    Internet Archive Logo
    web
    books
    video
    audio
    software
    images
    search

    uploadUPLOAD
    personSIGN IN

    ABOUT
    CONTACT
    BLOG
    PROJECTS
    HELP
    DONATE
    JOBS
    VOLUNTEER
    PEOPLE

Full text of "The man of mode, or, Sr Fopling Flutter. A comedy. Acted at the Duke's theatre. By Sir George Etherege. Licensed, June 3, 1676. Roger L'Estrange"
See other formats

Digitized by the Internet Archive

in 2011 with funding from

LYRASIS IVIembers and Sloan Foundation



http://www.archive.org/details/manofmodeorsrfopOOethe



THE

Man of Mode^

OR,

S"" Fopling Flutter.

A

COMEDY

Aded at the Dul^'s Theatre.
By Sir (jeorge Ether ege.



LICENSED,

•^rJ?!* Roger UEjirange.



LONDON,

Printed by J. Macock, for Hemy Herriftgman^ and are tO"

be fold by Jof. Kj^ight, and ir. Smnders, at the Sign

of the Blue Anchor 'm. the Lower Walk of

the New-Exchangej 1684.



^i ti



AKSpiKi^



IP..



rTW/j\ ■



5'



■>w/'



.ft 47



ifc







TO HER.

Royal Highnefs

THE

DUCHESS E.

Oets, however they may be modeft o-
therwife, have always too good an
opinion of what they write. The
World when it (ees this Play Dedica?*
ted to Your ^^yal Highnefs^ will conclude, I have
more than my fliare of that Vanity. But, I hope,
the honour I have of belonging to You, will ex^
cu(e my prefiimption. 'Tis the firft thing I have
product in Your Service, and my Duty obliges
me to what my choice durftaot elfe have afpir'd.
I am very (enfible, Madam, how much it is be-
holding to Your Indulgence, for the fuccels it had
in the AAing, and Your Proteftion will be no
lefi fortunate to it in the Printing j for all are (b
ambitious of making their Court to You,that none
can be fevere to what you are pleas'd to favour*

This univerfxl dibmiflion and relpeft is due to

the greatnefs of Your Rank and Birth ; but You

have other lUuftrious Qualities, which are much

more ingaging. Thole wou'd but dazle, did not

., - t A z thefe



Ihe tipijtle Vedtcatory.

diefe really charm the Eyes and Underftandings
of all who have the Happinefe to approach You.
Authors on thefe occafions are never wanting,
to publifh a particular of their Patrons Virtues
and perfedions j but Tour ^yal Highmfss are fo t^
minently known, that did rfoUow their Exam-
ples,, I flhou'd but paint thole wonders here, of
whif h e^ery one already has the Idea in his mind.
Befides, I do not think it proper to aim at that in
Profe, which is lb glorious a (iibjedt for Verie ;$ in
which hereafter if l (Bow more zeal than skill, ft
will not grieve me much, fince I lels paffionately
defire to be efteem'd a Poet, than to be thought.



ifMadimij.






Wur Royal Highntfs^s

Mofi humble^ moftobediefi^z.

md meft faithful Strvan$^

:<>ito..

George Etheregc.






Prol6sue»



PROLOGUE.

By Sir Car Scrooge Baronet*

Like Daacers on the Rofes -poor Poets fare.
Mo fi ferijh youngs the reft in danger are \ s >

Thu (of7ewou(d thinks) Jhofi'd make OHr j4hthors wary f
Bat Game ft er like the Giddy. Fooli mfcarry,
A lucky hand or twofo tempts ''em on, ;

They cannot leave of Play till they^e undone, ''■ '■* t v
With modeft Fears a ^J^ufe does firft hegin^ '^^ ' '{^^^,--^
Lik^ a yonng Wench newly enticed to Sin : , * . V '■'. V;^

But tickfd once with praifcj by her good Will,
The Wanton Fool woH^d never more lie (iill.
^Tis an old Mrs, you^ll meet here to night, *

Whofe charms you once have lookt on with delight,
St/f now of latefiich dirty Drabs have known yee^ > .

A Mufe 0* th^ better fortes aftiam'd to ownyee. -i^ l-VrUiC::
Natwre well drawn and Wit muft now give "place. -r^ ,•>.

To gawdy Nonfence and to duU Grimace', '"

Nor is itftrange that yon ftfion'd like fo much
That kind of Wit, for moft of yours isfuch,^ ; -■,,

But Im afraid that while to VvSLUce we go, T.

To bring you home Fine Dreffes, Dance and Show ; v
The Stage like you will but more Foppifh grow-. ^■■\^\. .
Of for eign Wares why ftion'd we fetch the f cum, , . .'
When we can befo richly ferv*d at home?
Fvr Heaven be thankt ^tis not fo wife an Agt^
But your own Follies may fupply the Stage.
Tho* often plowed, there's no great Fear the foil
Should Barren grow by the too frequent toil ;
While at your "Doors are to be daily found, '■ '

Such loads of Dung-hill to manure the ground.
^Tis by your Follies that we Players thrive,
As the Phyficians by Dijeafes live.
And as each yearfqme new dtftemper Reigns^
Whofe friendly poifon helps f ' increafe their gains :
So among you, there ft arts, up every day.
Some new unheard of Fool for U6 to ^lay^
Then for your own fakes be not too fever e.
Nor what you all admire at home^ Damn here.
Since each is fond of his own ugly Face^ ..
Whyfhou'd yoHj' when wt hold it, breaktheGlafs ?



Dramatis PerfoivsB.



Mr. Medley^

Old 'BeMr,

Young ^eUairj

Sir Fo^lin^ Flutter , ^

Lady Townley^

Emiliay

Mrs. Loyeit,

Bell'mda^

Lady TfboJvi/, and I

Hornet hetDaugh-

ter, J

and Waiting Women.

Sufy, )

JShoomaher*

An Orange^woman.

Three Slovenly Sullies.

Ta^o Chair ^me^u

yir. Smirk, afarfon.

Handy, a Valet de Chamhre,

^agesy Footmen^ Sec.



Gentlemea*



^Gentlewomen.



THE



THE

MAN of M O D E,

OR,

S^ Fopling Fiutten

ACT L SCENE L

A Drejjing Raom^ aTableCoveredmth a Toilet^.
Cloaths laidreadj*

Enter Dorimant vp his Govm and Slippers^ with a Note in his handl
mtude «/>, repeating Verfes,

Mor,'%^ ^0 Wfor feme Agei had the Pride of Spain,
l^^kj Made theSm-jhine on half the World in vain,
Jy, ^l" t,Thenlook^ngonthe,Notec.

For Mrs. Loveit.
What a dull infipid thing is a Billet doux written m
Gold blood, after the heat of the bufinefs is over ?
It is a Tax upon good nature which 1 have
Here been labouring to pay, .and have done it.
But with as much regret, as ever Fanatick paid:
The Royal Aid, or Church Duties •, 'Twill
Have the fame Fate I know that all my notes
To her have had of late, 'Twill not be thought
Kind enough. Faith women are i'the riglvt
When they jealoufly examine our. Letters^ for in them
We always firft difcover our decay of paffion. ^ — —

Hay ! ^ Who waits ?

^Titer Handy.
Handf^ .S\i. m .



(J)

Dor, Call a Footman. • -

Handy. 't'^ont of /e*m are Come yet.

Dsr. Dogs ! will they e vet lie fnoring a Bed till Nson.

Handy, ^Tisall one, Sir : if they're up, you indulge *em (o^
They *re ever poaching after Whores all the Morning; ; /
' Dor. Take notice henceforward who's wanting in his daty,'-
The next Clap he gets, he fhall rpt for an example.
What Vermin are thofe Chattering without ?

Handy. Foggy Nan the Orange Woman,
And fwearing Tom the Shoemaker

Dor. Go i Call in that over-grown Jade with the Flasket of
Guts before her, fruit is refrefhing in a Morning.

It is not that I love yoH lef £ Exit Handy.

Than when he fore your feet J lay. C ^'^^^'' Or. Worn.

How now double Tripe, what news do you bring ?

Or. Worn. News / Here's the belt fruit has come to Town
T'year, Gad I was up before Four a Clock this
Morning, and bought all the Choice i'the Mar ket«
^or. The naily refufe of your Shop.

Or. Worn. You need not make mouths at it, I aflure you
'Tis all cull'd ware.

Dor. The Citizens buy better on a Holiday in their
Walk to Totnam.

Or. Worn. Good or bad ,tis all one, I never knew you
Commend any thing, Lord wou'd the Ladies had ^^ '^'^^'■'
Heard you talk of 'em as I have done : here
Bid your Man give me an Angel. ^Sets down the Frm.

Dor. Give the Bawd her Fruit again.

Or. Worn. Well, on my Confcience, there never was the
Like^of you. God'smy life, I had almofi: forgot
To tell you, there is a young Gentlewoman
Lately come to Town with her Mother, that is
So taken with you.

Dor. Isftiehandfome?

Or. Worn. Nay, Gad there are few finer Women I tell you
'But fo. and a hugeous fortune they fay. Here,
Eat this Peach, it comes from.the Stone, 'tis
Better than any Newington y*have tafted.

Dor, This fine Woman Til lay my life C f^4"^ the Pe/ich.
Is fome awkward ill faihion'd Countrey Toad, who
Not having above Four Dozen of Black hairs
On her head, has adorn'd her bald nefs with*
A large white Fruz, thatihe may look fparkilhly

In



In the Fore Front of the King's Box, atan old Pity.

Or. Worn. Gad, you'd change your note quickly if you
Did but fee her.

Dor. How came fhe to know me /

Or. Worn Shefaw youyefterdayattheG^««»^?, ihetoH
Me, you came and fool'd with the Woman
At the next Shop. ,,- / -f

Dor. I remember there was a Mask obferv'd me indeed. ,
Fool'd did fhe fay ?

Or. Worn. Ay, I VOW Ihe told me Twenty things you faid
Too, and aded with head and with her Body
So like you

Enter Medley.

Medley. Dorimant my Lifsy my Joy, my darling Sin j how
Doftthou.

Or. Worn. Lord, what a filthy trick thefe men have got of
Killing one another ! {^She ffits.

Med. Why do you fuffer this Cart-load of fcandal to
Come near you, and make your Neighbours
Think you fo improvident to need a Bawd ?

Or. Worn. Good now, we Ihall have it, you did but want
Him to help you ^ come, pay me for my Fruit.

Med. Make us thankful for it Hufwife, Bawds are
As much out of fafhion as Gentlemen Ufhers j
None but old Formal Ladies ufe the one, and
None but Foppilh old Stagers employ the other :
Go, you are an infignificant Brandy Bottle.

Dor, Nay, there you wrong her, three Quarts of Canary
Is her bufinefs.

Or. Worn What you pleafe Gentlemen.

Dor. To him, give him as good as he brings.

Or, Worn. Hang him, there's not fuch another Heathen
In the Town again, except it be the Shoomaker without.

Med. I (hall fee you hold up your hand at the Bar
Next Sedionsfor Murder, Hufwife ^ that
Shoomaker can take his Oath you are in Fee
With the DojIJors to fell green Fruit to the
Gentry, that the Crudities may breed Difeafes.

Or, Worn. Pray give me my Money.

Dor, Not a penny, when you bring the Gentlewoman
Hither you fpoke of, you fhail be paid.

Or. Worn, The Gentlewoman ! the Gentlewoman may be

B As



(4)

As bonefl: as your Sifters for ought as I know.
Pi ay pay me, Mr. Dorimam^ and do not
Abufe me fo, I have an honefter way> of living,
Vou know it.

tJ^ed, WasthereeverfuchareftyBawd?

Dor. Some Jades tricks fhe has, but fhe makes amendis.
When fhe's in good humour : Come, tell me the
t-adies namfc, and Handy Ihall pay you.

Or, wow. I mull not, (he forbid me.

Dor. That*s a fure fign Ihe wou'd have you.

^if^. Where does (he live ?■

Or. Worn. They lodge at my Houfe,

^(p<fl'. Nay, then (he's in a hopeful way.

Or. Worn. Good Mr. Medley ^ fay your pleafure of me^,but
Take heed how you affront my Houfe,,
God's my life, in a hopeful way !

Dor. Prithee, peace, what kind of Woman's the Mother ?^

Or, Wont, A goodly grave Gentlewoman, Lord how
She talks againft the wild young men o'the
Town*, as for your part fhe thinks you an
Arrant Devil, Ihou'd fhe fee yon, on my Confcience
She wou'd look if you had not a Cloven foot..

Dor. Does fhe know me ?

Or. Worn, Only by hearfay, a Thoufand horrid Stories
Have been told her of you, and fhe
Believes 'email.

Med. By the Charaifter, this (hould be the Famous
liady Woodvilj and her Daughter Harriet,

Or. Worn, The Devil's in him for gueffing I think.

Dor. Do you know 'em ?

Med. Both very well, the Mother's a great admirer of. the .
Forms and Civilities of the lafl: Age.

"Dor, An antiquated beanty may bealSow'd to
Be out of humour at the freedoms of the prefent. ,
This is a good account of the Mother, Pray
What is the Daughter?

Med. Why^ fir ft (he's an Heirefs vaftfy rich,
'Dor. Andhandfome?

Med, What an alteration a Twelv€-month may have
Bred in her I know not, but a year ago
She was the beautifulleft Creature I ever faw,
A fine, eafie, clean ihape, light brown
Hair in abundance •, her Features regular, her
Complexion clear and lively, large wanton Eyes, .



)

But above all, a mouth that has made
Me kifs it a thoufand times in imagination,
Teeth white and even, and pretty pouting
Lips, with a little moifture ever iianging on them.
That look like the Province Rofe
Fre(h on the Bu(h, 'ere the Morning Sun has quite
Drawn up the dew.
Dor. Rapture, meer Rapture !
Or. Worn, Nay, Gad he tells you true,
She*s a delicate Creature.
Dor. Has fhe Wit ?

Med. More than is ufual in her Sex, and ad much malice.
Then (he's as wild as you'd wi(h her,
And has a deraurenefs in her looks that makes
It fo furprifing.

Dor. Fiefh and blood cannot hear this
And not long to know her.

Med. I wonder what makes her Mother bring her
Up to Town, an old doating Keeper cannot
Be more jealous of his Miftrefs.

Or. Worn, She made me laugh yelterday, there was
A Judge came to vifit 'em, and the old man
She told me did fo ftare upon her, and when he
Saluted her, fmack'd fo heartily ^ who wou'd think
It of em?
Med. God a mercy Judge.

Dor, Do 'em right, the Gentlemen of the long Robe
Have not been wanting by their good Examples
To countenance the crying fin o'the Nation.

Med. Gome, on with your Trappings, 'tis later thaa ...
You imagine. . ^^^^^^!; v*«^ii^■7l.ii'rt>l J'

Dor. Call in the Shoomaker, Handy. ' ■ • ; ' cp £ r^vo' ]

Or. Wont, Good, Mr. Dormant pay me, Gad I had'' , r'^' c :
Rather give you my fruit than ftay to be
Abus'd by that foul-mouth'd Rogue •, ? . :-^:

What you Gentlemen fay it matters not ^Jujl'cdoi
Much, but fuch a dirty Fellow does one more difgrace. t;

Dor. Give her Ten (hillings, and be fure y ou tell -< ■ .
The young Gentlewoman I mull be o l:v'^

Acquainted with her.

Or. Worn. Now do you long to be tempting this pretty ^. . ; ,

Creature. Well, Heavens mend you, ;.>.ii! . ,-j'ftiyi.. A

Med. Farewel Bogg. -— t^j^it Or. Woman 4»^ Handyv ,ix }

Dormant^ when did you fee your r.. \

B 2 'Ph



?«/ rf/Z^K as yoii call her, Mrs. L(;z/«> ?
Dor. Not thefe two days.
Med. Afld how ftand affairs between you ?"
Dor, There, has been great patching of late, much

Ado we make a (hift to hang together.

Med. I wonder, how her mighty Spirit bears iti
Dor., Ill enough on all Coafcience, I never knew fo

Violent a Creature.

Med. She's the moll paffionatcrin her Love, and

The moft extravagant in her Jealoufie of

Any Woman i ever heard of. What Note is that ?
Dor. An excufe I am going to fend her for the

Negledt I am guilty of. 'nor as : . -

Med. Prithee read iti - . :\-

i)or. No, but if you'd take the pains, you may.

Medley reads.

Med. I never was aLo!Uerofybufimfs^ hnt mve.I hai^e a^^ jufi
Raefon to bate, it) (iftce it has kef t, me thefe two days .,o'i,^jq' '
From feeing yoH. I intend to wait Hf on yon in. the :,-:>"
j^fternoon, and inthe fleafure of yonr (^onverfation^
Forget all I havefnffer^d during this tediomahfence»^
This bufinefs of yours 2)mw<a«r has been ;
WithaVizardatthePlay-hoU'fe, Ihaye r.

Had an Eye on you. If forae malicious body ,::■. *. r-

ShouM betray you, this kind note wou'd hardly,^ rifioO ,V:-:^^
Make your peace with her.
^or. I defire no better.

Med. Why, wou'd her knowledge of it oblige you ? -
*Dor. Moft infinitely ^ next to the coming to a good ;
Underftanding with a new Miflrefs,
I love a quarrel with an old one, but the
Devil's in'r, there has been fuch a calm in
My affairs of late, I have not had the pleafure.
Of making a Woman fb much as break ujofwil^ ,

Her Fan, to be fullen, or forfweai:/hf r fqif ^ r a^fjn^D vov
Thefethree.daysi' . - -yS Vv^ij-'^ v--?^' K.'bjA lUsI

Med. A very great Misfortune, l6t me fee, IlOVtiQ .^,0
Mifchief well enough ; to foioWard this bufiaefs v.. ,
My felf ril about it prt:fently, and though I
Know the truthof what y'a ve done, will fn her
A raving, Til heighten it a little with Invention, .
Leave her in a Fitio'the Mother, .and be here
Ajgain before y'are ready. -,



(f7)v

Dor, Pray ftay, you may fpare your felf the Labour,
The bufinefs is undertaken already by
Onewho will manage it with as much addrefs, and
I think with a little more Malice than you can,

Me^; Who i'the Deviisname can this be I

Dor. Why the Vizard, that very Vizard you faw
Me with.

Med. Does (he love mifchief fo well, as to betray
Her felf to fpight another ?

Dor. Not fo, neither, - tJ^eMey^ I will make you comprehend
The myftery \ this Malque for a farther
Confirmation of what 1 have been thefe two days
Swearing to her, made me yefterday at the Play-houfe
Make her a promife before her face, utterly to break of!
With Loveit •, and becaufe (he tenders my reputation,
And wou'd not have me do a barbarous thing, has
Gontriv'd a way to give me a hand feme occafion, .

Med, Very good.

Dor. She intends about an hour before me, this
Afternoon, to makeiXoz/«V a vifit, aud (having -
The priviledge by reafon of a profefs'd Friendfhip -
Between 'em to talk of her concerns)

i^c<^. Is Ihe a Friend ?

Dor. Oh, an intimate Friend !

Med. Better and better, pray proceed. ~

Vor, She means inlenfibly to infiuuatca
Difcourfe of me, and artificially raife her Jealoufie
To fuch a height, that tranfported with the
Firft motions of her pafilon Ihe Ihall fly
Upon me with all the Fury imaginable;
As foon as ever I enter , the Quarrel being
Thus happily begun , I am to play my part,
Confefs and juftifie all my Roguery,
Swear her impertinence and ill humour makes
^Her intolerable, tax her with the next Fop
That comes into my head, .and in a huff
March away , flight her and leave her
To be taken by whofoever thinks it worth
His time to lie down before her.

Med.. TJiis Vizard is afpark, and has a Genius that ^
Makes her worthy of your felf, Dortmant.



£«ffr Handy, Shoemaker, <«w^ Footman,
Dar. You Rogue there, who fneaklike a Dog that



H^s



(8)

Has Rung down a Difh, ifyoudonotmeud
Your waiting, Tie uncafe you, and turn you
Loofe to the Wheel of Fortune, Handy, ~ ■
Seal this, and let hini run with it prefently.

i^Exit Handy and Footmafl. .

Med. Since y'are refolv'd on a QaarreJ, why do
You fend her this kind note ?

Dor. To keep her at home in order to the buHnefs.
How now you drunken Sot ? {To the Shoomakir^

Shoom. 'Zbud, you have no reafon to talk, I have
Not had a Bottle of Sack of yours in my Belly
This Fortnight.

Med. The(9r^«^f W3w<«« fays, yon r Neighbours take
Notice what a Heathen you are, and
Defign to inform the Bilhop, and have you burn'd
Foran Atheift.

Shoom. Damn her. Dung-hill, if her Husband does
Not remove her, ihe ftinks fo, the Parifh
Intend to indite him for a Nufauce.

Med. I advife you like a Friend, reform your
Life, you have brought the envy of the World
Upon you, by living above your felf. ......

Whoring and Swearing are Vices too gentile » i a aHlgi
For a Shoomaker. ; i - . /

Shoom, ' Zbud, I think you men of quality will growi . «■ v
As unreafonable as the Women •, you wou'd
Ingrofs the fins o'the Nation i poor Folks
Can no fooner be wicked, but th'are rail'd
At by their Betters.

SDor. Sirrah, HI have you ftand i'the Pillory
For this Libel.

Shoom. Some of you deferve it, Vm fure, there
Are fo many of 'em, that our Journey- men now idays
Inftead of harmlefs Ballads, fing nothing
But your damn'd Lampoons.

!)<??-. Our Lampoons, you Rogue ?

Shoom. Nay, Good Mafter, why fhou'd not you
Write your own Commentaries as well isCafar /

(JMed. The Raskal's read, I perceive*

Shoom. You know the old Proverb, Ale and Hiftoryo

Dor. Dr^w on my Shooes, Sirrah.

Shoom, Here's a Shooe.

Dor. Sits with more wrinkles tlian there arc
In an Angry Bullies Forehead.

Shosm,



(5»

S^oom. *Zbikl,asfniooth as your Miftrcfles skin
Does u pon her, fo^ ftrike your foot in home.
'Zbud, if e're a Monfieur of \m all
Make more fafhionable Ware, I'll beconteDt
To have my Ears whip'd ofT with my own
Paring Knife.

Med. And fervM up in a Ragouft, inftead of
Coxcombs to a Company of French Shoomakers
For a Collation.

Shoom, Hold, hold, damn 'em CatterpillarSj let 'em
Feed upon Cabbage ; Come Matter, your health
This Morning next my heart now.

Dor, Go, get you home, and govern your Family better ;
Do not let your Wife follow you to the
Ale houfe, beat your Whore, and lead you
Home in Triumph.

ShooM. 'Zbud, there's never a man i'th' Town lives more like
A Gentleman, with his Wife, than I do.
I never mind her motions,. (he never inquires
Into mine, we fpeak one to another Civilly,
Hate one another heartily, and becaufe 'tis vulgar
, To lie and foak together^ we have each of us
Our feveral Settle- bed.

'Dor. Givehimhalf a Crown.

Med. Not without he will promife to be bloody drunk.

Sheom. Tope's the word i'the Eye of the World for my
Mafters honour, Ti^hin.

Dor. Do not debauch my Servants, Sirrah,

Shoom. I only tip him the wink, he knows an
Ale houfe from a Hovel. ZExit Shoemaker ,

Dor. My Cloaths quickly.

ft,;^^^. Where fhall we dine to day? [^f wf^r Bellaix..

Dor. Where you will } here comes a good
Third man.

Bell. Your Servant, Gentlemen.

Med. Gentle Sir ; how will you anfwer this
Vifit to your honorable Miftrefs ? 'tis not
Her intereft you (hou'd keep Company
With men of fence, who will be talking reafan.

Bill. 1 do not fear her pardon^ do you but
Grant me yours, for my negleft of late. .

.<^e«^. Though y'ave made us miferable by the
Want of your good Company j to (hew you
l.am free from all refentmeot, mayjtbe.



( I»)

Beautiful caufe of our misfortune,
Give you all the Joys happy Lovers
Have fhar'd ever fince the World began.

Bell. You wiflimein Heaven, but you believe
Me on my Journey to Hell.

Med. You have a good ftrong Faith, and that may eontribute
Much toward your Salvation. 1 confefs I am
But of an outward Conftitution, apt to have
Doubts and Scruples, and in Love they are no lefs.
Diftradting than in Religion; were I fo near
Marriage, I (hould cry out by fits as I ride
In my Coach, Cuckold, Cuckold, with no lefs fury than
The mad Fanatick does glory in BethUm.

Bell. Becaufe Religion makes fome run mad,
Mufti live an Atheift?

tJMed. Is it noE great indifcretion for a man
Of Credit, who may have money enough on
His Word, to go and deal with Jews-, who for
Little fums make men enter into Bonds,
And give Judgments ?

Bell. Preach no more on this Text, lam
Determined, and there is no hope of my Converfion.

Dor. Leave your unneceflaryfidlingi a Wa%
That's buzzing about a Mans Nofe^t
Dinner is not more troublefome than thou art.

[]To Handy who isjidling about him.

Hand. You love to have your Cloaths hang juft, Sir.

Dor. I lovetobe welldrefs'djSir: and think it
No fcandal to my underftanding. ^

■Hand. Will you ufe the Eflence or Orange-Flower- Water ?

Dor. I will fmell as I do to day, no ofience
To'the Ladies Nofe?.

Hand. Your pleafure, Sir.

^Dor. That a mans excellency fhould lie in
Neatly tying of a Ribbond, or a Crevat 1 how
Careful's nature in furnifhing the World
With neceflary Coxcombs !

Bed. That's a mighty pretty Suit of yours, Dormant.

Dor. 1 am glad \ has your approbation.

BelL No man in Town has a better fancy in
His Cloaths than you have.

Dor. You will make me have an opinion of my Genius.

Med. There is a great Critick I hear in thefe matters
Lately arriv'd piping hot from Tara,

Bell.



(M)

'Sell. Sir FoplingF Inner you mean.'

%J^€d, The fame.

Bell. He thinks himfelf the Pattern of modern
Gallantry.

Dor, He is indeed the Pattern of modern Foppery.

Med. He was Yelterday at the Play, with a pair of GIov^
Up to his Elbows, and a Periwig more exadly Currd
Then a Ladies head newly drefs'd for a BalJ.

Bell. What a pretty lifp he has !

Bor. Ho, that he affefts in imitation of the people of
Quality of France.

Med. Hisheadftands, for the mofl; part, on one fide.
And his looks are more languiihing than
A Ladies, when fhe loll's at ftretch in her
Coach, or leans her head carelefly againft the
Side of a Box i'the Playhoufe.

Dor. He is a perfon indeed of great acquired Follies.
Med. He is like many others, beholding to his
Education for making him fo eminent a
Coxcomb; many a Fool had been loft
To the World, had their indulgent Parents
Wifely beftow'd neither Learning nor
Good breeding on 'em.

Bell. He has been, as thefparkifh word is. Brisk
-Upon the Ladies already^ he was yefterday
At my Aunt Tw/^^^, and gave Mrs.
Loveit a Catalogue of his good Qualities,
Under the Charader of a Compleat Gentleman,
Who according to Sir Foiling., ought to drefs well.
Dance well, Fence well, have a genius for Love Letters,
An agreeable voice for a Chamber,
Be very Amorous, fomething difcreet,
But not over Conflant.

Med. Pretty Ingredients to make an accompliflit
Perfon.

Ber. I am glad he pitcht upon Loveit.

Bell.Uowio}

Bw. I wanted a Fop to lay to hex Charge, and this
Is as pat as may be. •

Bell. I am confident Ihe loves
No man but you.

Dor. The good fortune were enough to make me vain.
But that I am in my nature modefl-.

Bell. Hark you Borimant^ with your leave Mr, Medley,

C * 'lis



'Tis ©nly a fecret concerning a fair Lady.

Med. Your good breeding Sir, gives you too much trouble
You might haYsrwhifper'd without all this
Ceremony.

£eiL How Hand your affairs with "BelUnda of late ?

E"^*? Dorimant.
- Dor. She's a little Jilting Baggage.

Bell. Nay, I believeher felfe enough, but
She's ne're the worfe for your purpofe j flie was
With you yefterday in a difguife at the Play.

Dor. There we fell out, and refolv'd never toipeak
To 9ne another more.

ML The Occafion ?

'Dor. Want of Courage to meet me at the place appointed.
Thefe young Women apprehend loving, as much
As the young Men do fighting at firft;^
But-once cnter'd., like them too they all
Turn Bullies ftraight. . £«rcr Handy f<7Bellair»

Handy. Sir, Your man without defires to fpeak with you.

Bell. Gentlemen, I'll return immediately. Exit Bellair.,

Med. A very pretty Fellow this.

Dor, He's handfome, well-bred, and by much the moll
Tolerable of all the young men that do not abound in wit,

Med. Ever well drefs'd, always complaifant, and
Seldom impertinent ; you and he are grown
Very intimate I fee.

Dor, It is our mutual interell to be fo , it
Makes the Women think the better of his
Underftanding^ and judge more favourably of my^
Reputation •, it makes him pafs upon Ibme for
A man of very good fenfe, and I upon others for a
Very civil perfon,

Med. What was that whifper >

Dor. A thing that he wou'd fain have known^.
But I did not think it fit to tell him i
It might have frighted him from his honourable
Intentions of Marrying.

Med. Smilia^ give her her due, has the befi: reputation
Of any young Woman about the Town *, who
Has beauty enough to provoke detraction ; her Carriage
Is unaffedied, her difcourfe raodefl, not at all cenforiouSj
Nor pretending like the Counterfeits of the Age.

Dor. .She's a difcreet Maid^ and I believe nothing can
Corf upt her but a Husband/

* Med



(I?)

^/e^, A Husband ?

Dor. Yes, a Hdsband ; I Iiave known many Women make
A d ifficulty of lofing a Maidenhead, who
Have afterwards made none of making a Cuckold.

Aded. This prudent confideration I am apt to think
Has made you confirm poor BelUir in the
Defperate refolution he has taken.

Dor. Indeed the little hope I found there was of her, in
The ftate flie was in , has made me by my
Advice, contribute fomething towards the
Changing of her condition. [^Snter Bellair.

Dear Bellair^ by Heavens
I thought we had loft thee *, men in love
Are never to be reckoned on when we wou'd
Form a Company.

Bell. Dormant.^ I am undone, my man has brought
The moft furprifingnews i'the World.
Med. Some ftrange misfortune is befain your love.
'Bell. My Father came to Town laft night, and
Lodges i'the very Houfe where Emilia lies.
Med. Does he know it is with her you are in love ?
Bell. He knows I love, but knows not whom, without
Some officious Sot has betray'd me.

Dor. Your Aunt Tovonley is your Confident, and favours
The bufinefs.

Bell. I do not apprehend any ill office from her.
I have received a letter, in which I am commanded
By my Father to meet him at my Aunts this Afternoon ;
He tells me farther, he has made a match for me, and bids
Me refolve to be obedient to his Will, or expe<fi to
Be difinherited.

Med. Now's your time, Bellair.^ never had Lover fuch
An opportunity of giving a generous proof of his paffion.
Bell. As how I pray ?

Med. Why, hang an Eftate, marry Emilia out of hand,
.And provoke your Father to do what he threatens ;
'Tis but defpifing a Coach, humbling your felf
To a pair of Golofhoes, being out of countenance
When you meet your Friends, pointed at and pitied
Where-ever you go, by all the Amorous Fops
That know you, and your fame will be immortal.
"Sell. I ceuM find in my heart to refolve not to marry at alL
Dor. Fie, fie, that would fpoil a good jeft, and difappoint
The well-natui'd Town of an occafion of laughing at you,

. C2 . Ser.



BelL The ftorm I have fo long expeded, hangs
O're my head^ and begins to pour down upon me j
I am on the Rack, and can have no reft tilU'm
Satisfied in what 1 fear •, where do you dine ?

Dor. At Longs y or Lockets.

Med. kX.Longs\tt\X.\)Q.

5f//. I'll run and fee £w?7«<«^. and inform ray felf
How matters ftand j if my misfortunes are not
So great as to njake me unfit for Company,
I'll be with you. ' {,Exit htMit..

Enter a FootmSin with a Letter

Footm. Here's a Letter, Sir,, [roDorimant.

t>or. The Superfcription's right ^ For Mr. Donmant.
Med. Let's fee the very fcrawl and fpelling of a
True-bred Whore.
Dor. I know the hand, the ftile is admirable I afTure you.
Med, Prethee read it.

Dor^ V. Reads,.

I told a you you dud not love me, if you dftd^'.
Ton woiid havefeen me again e're now \ I
Have nojmney and am very mallicolly -,
Fray fend me a Gnynie to fee the Operies.

YQ%t Servant to Gommand,'

(J^oUyi

Med. Pray let the Whore have a favourable
Anfwer, that ihe may fpark it in a Box^
And do honour to her profeflion.

*Dor. She fhall ^ and perk up i'the face of Quality,
Is the Coach at the Door ?

Hand. You did not bid me lend for it.

I>or. Eternal Blockhead ! lU.dLndLy offers to go out.-

Hay Sot.—..

Hand. Did you call me, Sir ?'

Dor. I hope youhavenojultexceptiou to the name, Sir?

Band. Ibavefenfe, Sir.

Dor. Not fo much as a Fly In Winter : — =— =- -.
How did you come, Medley f

Ma,



(•5) -

M^i. In a Chair.
• Footm. You may have a Hackney CoacH if you pleafe, Sir.

Dor. I may ride the Elephant if 1 pleafe, Sir ;
Gall another Chair, and let my Coach follow to Longs.

'Be calm ye great P arents., &C. \iEx. Singing,



ACT 11. SCENE I.

Enter my Lady Townly, andEmWlz.

Lady Townly. X Was afraid, Emilia, all had beeadifcover'd,
JL €mil. I tremble with the apprehenfion Ilill.

Town. That my Brother ihould take Lodgings i'the
Very Houfe where you lie.

Emit. Twas lucky, we had timely notice to warn the .%

People to be fecret, he feems to be a mighty good
Humour'd old man.

Town. He ever had a notable fmerking way with himZ

Emil. He calls me Rogue, tells me he can't abide me 5
And does fo bepat me.

Town. On my word you are much in his favour thenj

Emil. He has been very inquifitive I am told about my
Family, my Reputation, and my Fortune.

Town. I am confident he does not i'the leafl: fufped
You are the Woman his Son's in Love with.

8miL What fhou'd make him then inform himfelf io
Particularly of me ?

Town. He was always of a very loving Temper himfelf;
It may be he has a doating. Fit upon him, who knows.

Emil. It cannot be. [.Enter Young Bellairv

Town. Here comes my Nephew. Wiiere did
You leave your Father ? -^

T. Bell. Writing a Note within ; £wji/«^, this early vifit -
Looks as if fome kind Jealoufic wouM not-let you
Reft at home.

Emil. The knowledge I have of my Rival,
Gives me a little caufe to fear your Gonftancfo

r. Bell. My Conftancy ! I vow

8mil. Do not vow — Our love is frail as is our life', and
Full as little in our power, and are you fureyou fhallj
Out-live this day ? .

T. Bell-



(i6y

r. Bell. I am not, but when we are in perfed health, 'twere
An idle thing to fright our felves with the thoughts of
Sudden deaths

Town. Pray what has pafl between you and your Father
rthe Garden?

T. Bell. He's firm in his refolution,
Tells me I mull: marry bSrs. Harriet^
Or fwears he'll marry himielf,
Anddifinheritme. When I few I could not -
Prevail v/ith him co be more indulgent, I difiembled - .
An Obedience to his Wiilj which has eomposM his paffion.
And will give us time, and I hope opportunity to
Deceive him. l^Em£r Old Bdhk, with a Note m his hand.

Town. Peace, here he comes.

Old BelL Harry J tdikQ this, and let your man carry it for me
To Mr. Fonrbes Chamber, my Lawyer i'the Temple.
Neighbour, a Dod I am glad to fee thee here, [To Emilia,

Make much of her Siller, ihe's one
Of the beft of your acquaintance ; I like her .
Countenance and her Behaviour well, fhe has
A Modelly that is not common i'this Age, a Dod,
She has.

Town. I know her value, Brother, and efleem her accordingly.
;_ Old Bell. Advife her to wear a little more mirth in her
Face, a Dod (he's too ferious.

Town. The fault is very exculable in a young Woman„

Old Bell. Nay, a Dod, I like her ne're the worfe,
A Melancholy Beauty has her Charms,
I love a pretty fadnefs in a Face, which varies
Now and then^ like changeable Colours, into a fmile.

Town. Methinks you fpeak very feelingly. Brother.

Old Bell. I am but Five and Fifty, Sifter, you know, an
Age not altogether unfenfible ! chear up fweet \To Emilia.

Heart ^ I have a fecret to tell thee, may
Chance to make thee merry^ we three will make
Collation together anon, i'the mean time
Mum, I can't abide you, go, I can't

Abide you. HarryyCome., you Z^nter Young Bcllalr,

Maft afong with me to Lady Woodvills.
I am going to flip the Boy at a Miftrefs.

T. BelL At a Wife, Sir, you wou'd fay.

Old BelL You need not look fo glum, Sir,
A Wife is no Curfe when flie brings the Bkfiing
Qf a good Eftate with her, but an idle Town

¥lurt



Xi7)

Flurt, with a painted Face, a rotten Reputation,
And a crafie Fortune, a Dod is the Devil and ail.
And furh a one I liear you are in League with.
T. 'Bell, I cannot help detraction, Sir.
Old BelL Out, a pife o'their Breeches, there are
Keeping Fools enough for fuch flaunting
Baggages, and they are e'ne too good for 'em.
Remember Night, go y'are a Rogue, y'are CTi? Emilia.

A Rogue *, fare you well j come, come,
Come along, Sir. ^Ex. Old and Y. Bellair,

TowM. On my Word the old man comes on apace ;
ril lay my life he's fmitten.
Emil. This is nothing but the pleafantnefs of his humour.
Town. I know him better than yon, let it work^
It may prove lucky. Z.^nt€r a Page^ .

?age. Madam, Mr. UMedley has Cent to know
Whether a Vifit will not be troublefome ^

This Afternoon f
Town. Send him word, his vifits n^ver are fo,
£w^/i^. He's a very plea fan t man.
Town. He's a very necefFary man among us Women ^
He's not Icandalous i'the leaft, perpetually
Contriving to bring good Company together,
And always ready to flop up a gap at Ombre^
Then he knows all the little news i'the Town.

Emilia. I love to hear him talk o'the Intrigues >
Let 'em< be never fo dull in themfelveSj heHl
Make' 'em pleafant i'the relation

Town. But he improves things fo much, one can take no
Meafure of the Truth from him.
Mr. Dorimam fwears^ Flea or a Maggot is
Not made more monftruous by a magnifying
Glafs, than a (lory is by his telling it,
Emilia, Hold, here he comes.- [[ff^f^r Medley. .

Town. Mr. Medley.

Med, Your ServantjMadam. . -

Town. You have made your felf a Stranger of late.
Emilia. 1 believe you took a fur feit at Ombre
Lsft time you were here. . ' -■

Med. Indeed I had my Belly full of thatTarmagant
Lady Dealer 5 there never was fo nnfatiable
A Carder, an old Gleeker never lov'd to lit
To't like her ; I have plaid with her now at
Leaft a dozen times, till ihfi'as worn out ali

HeiT



(i8)

Her fine Complexion, and her Tour woa'd
Keep in Curl nojonger.

Tovfn. Blame her not poor Woman, Ihe loves nothifig
So well as a black Ace.

Med. The pleafure I have feen her in when ^^ has had hope
Jn drawing for a Matadore.

Emilia. 'Tis as pretty fport to her, as perfwading
Masks off is to you to make difcovcries.
Town. Pray where's your Friend, Mr. DoHmam f
Med. Sollicicing his affairs, he's a man of great
Imployment, has more Miftrefles now depending.
Than the moll eminent Lawyer in England
Has Caufes. /

Emilia. Here -has been Mrs. Loveit, fo uneafie and
•Out of humour thefe two days.

Town. How ftrangely Love and Jealoufie rage
In that poor Woman !

Med. She cou'd not have pick'd out a Devil
Upon Earth fo proper to torment her, '

Has made her break a dozen or two of
:Fans already, tare half a Icore Points in pieces.
And deftroy Hoods and Knots without number.

Town. We heard of a pleafant Serenade he gave
Her t'other Night.
Med. A Danifh Serenade with Kettle Drums, and Trumpets.
Emilia, Oh Barbarous !

Med. What, you are of the number of the Ladies, wh(^fe
\Ears are grown fo delicate fince our
Operas, you can be charm'd with nothing
But Flute doux, and French Hoboys.

Emilia. Leave your raillery, and tell us, is there a»y
New Wit come forth, Songs or Novels ?

Med. A very pretty piece of gallantry, by an
- Eminent Author, call'd the diver/ions of
JBriixells, very necelfary to be read by all
Old Ladies who are defirous to improve themfelves
At Queftions and Comraand«,BIindmans BuffJ
And the like faQiionable recreations.
Emilia, Oh Ridiculous !

Med. Then there is the Art of affedation, written
By a late Beauty of Quality, teaching you how
To draw up your Brealts, ftretch up yqar neck.
To thruft out your Breach, to play with your Head^
Xo tofs up your Nofe, to bite your Lips, to turn

Up



op).

Up your Eyes, to fpeak in a filly foft tone of
A Voice, and ufe all the Foolifli French Words,
That will infallibly make your perfon and
Converfation charming, with a Ihort apologie
At the latter end, in the behalf of young Ladies,
Who notorioufly walh, and paint, though they
Have naturally good Complexions.

Emilia. What a deal of fluff you tell us >

Med. Such as the Town affords, Madam.
The T^fians hearing the great refpedl we
Have for Foreign Dancing, have lately fent
Over Tome of their belt Balladins, who are
Now pradifing a famous Ballat, which will
Be fuddenly danc'd at the Bear-Garden.

Town. Pray forbear your idle ftories, and give us
An account of the ftate of Love, as it now ftands.

Med. Truly there has been fome revolutions in thofe
Aflairs, great chopping and changing among the
Old, and fome new Lovers, whom malice, *
Indifcretion, and misfortune, have luckily
Brought into play.

Town. What think you of walking into the next Room,
And fitting down before you engage in this bufinefs ?

Med. I wait upon yotr, and 1 hope f though Women
Are commonly unreafonable) by the plenty of
Scandal 1 fhall difcover, to give you very good
Content, Ladies.



]i€xeunt.



SCENE 11.



Enter Mrs. Loveit and Perf^

^Mrs. Loveit putting Hf a Letter^ then pulling
out her pocket CUfs.^ and looking m it,
Loveit. Pert.
Pert. Madam.

Loveit. I hate my felf, I look fo ill to day.
?ert. Hate the wicked caufe on't, that bafe man
Mr. Dorimunt^ who makes you torment and
Vex your felf continually.

Loveit. He is to blame indeed.

Pert. To blame to be two days without fending,

D Writing,



(jo)

Writing, or coming near you, conlrary to
His Oath and Covenant ^ 'Twas to much
Purpofe to make him fwear} TJf lay my
Life there's not an Article but he has broken,
Talk'd to the Vizairds i'tias Pit, waited upon the
Ladies from the Boxes tathdr Coaches i gone behind
The Scenes, and fawn'd upon thofe little infignificant
Creatures, the Players *, 'tis impoffibl:© for a man
Of his inconflant temper to forbear I'm fure^

Lov. I know he's a Devil, but he has fomething of the
Angel yet undefac'd in him, which
Makes him fo charming and agreeable^ that
I muft love him be he never fo wicked.

Pert, I little thought, Madam, to iee your fpirit
Tamed to this degree, who banifli'd poor ^' .

Mr, Lack^it but for taking up another Ladies
Fan in your prefence.

Lov. My knowing of fuch odious Fools, contributes to the
Making of me love Dormant the better*

Pert. Your knowing of Mr. Dormant ^ m my mind,
Shou'd rather make you hate all mankind.

Loveit. So it does, befides bimfelf.

Pert, Pray, whatexcufe does he make in his Letter ?

Loveit. He has had bufinefs.

Pert. Bufinefs in general terms wou'd not have
Been a currant excufe for another j
A Modifh Man is always very bufie
When he*s in purfuit of a new Miftrels. - :

Loveit. Some Fop has brib'd you to rail at him f
He had bufinefs, I will believe it, and will forgive him.

Tert. You may forgive him any thing, but I fnall never
Forgive him his turning me into Ridicule,
As i hear he does.

Loveit. I perceive you are of the number of thofe
Fools his Wit had made his Enemies*

Pert. lam of the number of thofe he's pleas'd
To railly, Madam, and if we may believe
Mr. Wagfan, and Mr. Caperwell, he fometimes
Makes merry with your felf too, among
Hi5 Laughing Companions.

Loveit. Blockheads are as malicious to witty men,
As ugly Women are to the handfome ; 'tis
Their Intereft, and they make it their bufinefs
To defame ^ena.

Pert,



(41)

Pert. I wifh Mr. *I>ormmt wou'd not make
It his bufinefs to defame you.

Loveit, Shou'd he, I had rather b€ made infamous
By him, than owe my reputation to the dull
Difcretion of thofe Fops you talk off.
Bellinda ! ^running to her.

^^ff^r Bellinda.

Bell. My Dear.

Loveit. You have been unkind of late.
Bell. Do not fay unkind, fay unhappy !
Loveit. I cou'd chide you.
Where have you been thefe two days ?

Bf //. Pity me rathei my dear, where I have been
So tired with two or three Countrey Gentlewomen,
Whofe converfation has been more
Unfuflerable than a Countrey Fiddle.
Loveit. Are they Relations ?
Bell, No, Welch acquaintance I made when I was lall
Year at St. Wimfreds^ they have asked me a thoufand
Queftions of the Modes and Intrigues of the Town,
And I have told 'em almoft as many things for news
That hardly were ib^ when their Gowns were in Falhion.
Loveit. Provoking Creatures, how cou'd you endure 'em?
Bell. Now to carry on my Plot, nothing but love
Cou'd make me capable of fo much falftiood •, L^fide.

*Tis time to begin, left Dorimant Ihou'd
Come before her Jealoulie has ftung her ^

^LaHghs^ and then ffeaks on,
I was yefterday at a Play with 'em.
Where I was fain to (hew 'em the living, as the
Man at W^<ei?ww^(fr does the dead. That is
Mrs. fuch a one, admired for her Beauty,
This is Mr. fuch a one, cry'd up for a Wit ^
Thatisfparkifh Mr. fuchaone, who ; •■;" ■ 'L, ^^ - „

Keeps reverend Mrs. fuch a one, and there -"^ .fiVysOT arii oi
Sits fine Mrs. fuch a one, who was lately < iriSv ^n i

Caftoffbymy Lord fuch a one. .iiv.?\

Loveit. Did you fee Dorimant there ?
Bell. I did, and imagine you were there with him,
And have no mind to own it.
Loveit. what fliou'd make you think fo?
'Bell. ALadymask'dinaprettydifliabilli^

D 2 Whom



(11)

Wtiom Dormant enter tain'd with more
Refpeftj than the Gallants do a common Vizard.

Loveit. Dormant at the Play entertaining a Mask,
Oh Heavens ! ^ j^fide.

Bell. Good I l^^fide.

Loveit. Did he flay all the while ?

Bell, 'Till the PJay was done, and then led her
Out, which confirms me it was you.

Loveit. Tray tor ! -

Pert. Now you may believe he had bufinefs, asd
You may forgive him too,

Loveit. Ingrateful, perjur'd man f

Bell. You feem fo much concern'd, my Dear,
I fear I have told you unawares what i _
Had better have conceal'd for your Quiet.

Loveit, What manner of fhape had fhe ?

Bell. Tall and (lender, her motions were very gentile,
Certainly ihe muft be fome perfon of condition.

Loveit, Shame and confufion be ever in her
Face when fhe ihows it.

Bell. I Ihou'd blame your difcretion for loving that
Wild man, my Dear, but they lay he has a way
So bewitching, that few can defend their hearts
Who know him.

Loveit. I will tear him from mine, or die i'the attempt.

Bell. Be more moderate.

Loveit, Wou'd I had Daggers, Darts or poyfon'd Arrows
In my Bread, fo I cou'd but remove the thoughts
Of him from thence.

. BeK. Fie, fie, your tranfports are too violent, my Dear j
This may be but an accidental Gallantry^,
And 'tis likely ended^t her Coach,

"Pert. Shou'd it proceed farther, let your comfort be.
The Condu(ft Mr. Dorimam afFeds, will
Quickly make you know your Rival, ten to one -
Let yoti fee her ruin'd, her reputation expos'd
To the Town, a happinefs aone wi'i envy her
But your felf, Madam.

Loveit. Who e're Ihe be, all the harm I wifh her, is, jnay
She love him as well as I do, and may he give her ;. ' 'v.* \.
As much caule to hate him.
Tert, Never doubt the latter end of your Curfe, Madam \
Laveit. May ail the pafiions that are raisM by negleded
Lo^e, Jealoufie, ladignation, Spight and Thirft of

' , Revenge,,



{'



Revenge, eternally rage in her Soui , as they do

Now in mine. ]yFalks up and down with a diflra^ed air.

EnteraVzge^

Vage, Madam, Mr. 'Dormant

Loveit. I will not fee him.

Tage. I told him you were within, Madam.

Loveit. Say you Jy'd, fay I'm bufie, (hut the door j
Say any thing.

Page. He's here, Madam. \iEnter Dorimant.

Dor. They tafie of death who do at Heaven arrive^
But we this Paradife approach alive.
What, dancing the Galloping Nag without a Fiddle }

[Jo Loveit

Offers to catch her by the hand,

_. jiie flings away and walks on.

I fear this refllefsnefs of the body. Madam, Zpurfning her^
Proceeds from an unquietneft of the mind .
What unlucky accident puts you out of
Humour •, a Point ill- wafiied. Knots fpoil'd i'the
Making up. Hair fliaded awry, or fome
Other little miftake in fetting you in order ?

Pert. A trifle in my opinon, Sir, more inconfiderable
Than any you mention.

Dor. Oh Mrs. Pert^ I never knew you fullen enough
To be filent, come, let me know the bulineft.

Pert. The bufinefs, Sir, is the bufiuefs that has taken you-
Up thefe two days *, how have 1 feen you
Laugh at men of bufinefs, and now to become a man
Of bufinefs your felf !

Vor. We are not Mafters of our own aftedions, our
Inclinaions daily alter •, now we love picafure, and
Anon we ftiall doaton bufinefs-, humane
Frailty will have it fo, and who can help it ?
~ Lowif. Faithlefs^ inhumane, barbarous man ^ — ■ .

Dor. Good, now the Alarm ilrikes

Loveit. Without fenfe of Love, of Honour,; or of Gratitude,,
Tell me, for I will know, what Devil mask'd
She was, you were with at the Play yefterday ?

Dor, Faith, I refolv'd as much as you, but the
Devil was obftinate, and wou'd not tell me.

Ljveit. Falfein this as in your Vows to me, you do know L

Dor. The truth is, I did all I cou'd to know,

LffViih.



(i4)

Loveit. And dare you own it to my Face ?
He 1 ! a nd Fur ies ! C Tears her Fan in pieces.

Dor. Spare your Fan, Madaaj;, you are growing hot,
And will want it to cool you.

Loveit. Horrour and diftra(n:ion feize you, Sorrow and
Remorfe gnaw your Sou! , and punifh all your
Perjuries to me ■ [Weep.

Dor. So Thnnder breaks the Clonds in Trvain^
t^nd makes a pajfage for the '^in. fuming to Bellinda.

Tellinda^ you are the Devil that have rais'd
This ftorm •, you were at the Play yefterday, (^Tc Bellinda.

And have been making difcoveries to your Dear.

5^//. Y'are the mofl: miftaken Man i'the World.

Dor. It muft be ^o^ and here I vow revenge \ refolve
To purfue, and perfecute you more impertinently
Than ever any Loving Fop did his Miftrefs, hunt
You i'the Parkjt trace you i'the aJMailj Dog
You in every Vifit you make, haunt you at
The Plays, and i'the Drawing Room, hang my
Nofe in your neck, and talk to you whether
You will or no, and ever look upon you with fuch
Dying Eyes, till your Friends grow jealous of me,
Send you out of Town, and the World lufpeft
Your reputation. U^ ^ ^^wer voice.

At my \iHe looks kindly on Bellinda*

Lady TownUy's when we go from hence.

Bellj V\\ meet you there.

^or. Enough.

Loveit, Standoff, you fha'notftare upon her fo.

CP//jl)^«^ Dorimant 4^^^.

Dor. Good! There's one made jealous already.

Loveit. Is this the conftancy you vow'd ?

Dor. Conftancy at my years ! *tis not a Vertue in
Seafon , you might as well exped the Fruit the
Antumn ripens, i'the-Spring.

Loveit. Monftrous Principle !

Dor. Youth has a long Journey to go, Madam, fhou'd
I have fet up my reft at the firft Inn I lodg'd at,
I Ihou'd never have arriv'd at the happinefs 1 now enjoy.

Loveit. Diflembler, damn'd Diffembler !

Dor, I am fo I confefs, good nature, and good manners
Corrupt me. I am honelt in my inclinations^- and
Wou'd nor, wer't not to avoid offence, make
A Lady a little in years believe I think her young, wiHuliy

Miftake



Miftake Art for Nature •, and feem as fond of a thing
I am weary of, as when I doated on't in earneft.
Loveit. Falfe Man.
Dor, True Woman.

Loveit. Now you begin to fhow your felf !
Dor. Love gilds us over, and makes us fhow fine things
To one another for a time, but foon the Gold
Wears off, and then again the native brafs appears.

Loveit, Think on your Oaths, your Vows and Protellations.
Perjur'd Man !
Dor. I made 'em when I was in love.
Loveit, And therefore ought they not to bind ?
Oh Impious !
Dor. What we fwear at fuch a time may be a certain proof
- Of a prefent paflion, but to Qy truth, in Love there is
No fecurity to be given for the future.

Z^w^>. Horrid, and ingrateful, begone,
And never fee me more.

Dor. I am not one of thofe troublefome Coxcombs,
Who, becaufe they were once well receiv'd, take the
Priviledge to plague a Woman with their Love ever
After ; I fhail obey you, Madam, though I do my felf
Some Violence. {^He ojfers togo^ and Loveit fulls him baql..

Loveit. Comeback, youfha'notgo.
Cou'd you have the ill nature to offer it ?

Dor. When love grows difeasM, the beft thing we can do
Is to put it to a violent Death •, I cannot -^
Endure the torture of a lingring and
Confumptive paffion.
Loveit. Can you think mine fickly ?
*Dor. Ob ! 'tis defperately III ! what worfe fymptoms,
Are there than your being always uneafie when
Ivifityou, your picking quarrels with me on
Slight occafions, and in my abfence kindly liftning
To the impertinences of every fafhionable Fool
That talks to you ?
-Lovsit. What fafhionable Fool can you lay to my charge ?
Dor. Why, the very Cock-fool of all thofe Fools,
Sir Fofling Flutter.
Lovett. I never faw him in ray life, but once.
Dor. Theworfe Woman you, at firft light to put on
All your charms, to entertain him with that foftnefs
In your voice, and all that wanton kindnefs in your
Eyes, you fo notorioufly afled, when you defign
A Conqueft. Loveit.



Laveit. So damnM a lie did malice never yet invent 5

Who told you this?

Dor. No matter^ that ever I fhou'd love a V»^oman that
Candoat on a fenfelefs Caper, a Tawdry French
Riband, and a Formal Cravat.

Lot/«^ You make me mad.

Dor. A guilty Confcience may do much,
Go on, be the Game Miftrefso'che Town, and
Enter ail our young Fops, as fait as they come
From travail.

Leveit. Bafe and Scurrilous !

'Dor. A fine mortifying reputation 'twill be for r

A Woman of your Pride, Wit, and Quality !

Loveit, This Jealoufie's a meer pretence, a curfed trick
Of your own devifing-, I know you.

Dor. Believe it and all the ill of me you can, I wouM
Not have a Woman have the leaft good thought
Of me, that can think well of F of ling-., farewel,
Fall to, and much good may do you with your Coxcomb.

Loveit, Stay, oh ftay, and I will tell you all.

Dor, I have been told coo much already. QEat. Dorimant.

Loveit* Call him again.

Pert, L'nelethimgo, a fair riddance.

Loveit. Run I fay, call him again, I will have him caL'J.

Pert, The Devil ihou'd carry him a way firfl:.
Were it my concern. X,Ex Pert.

Sell, H'as frighted me from the very thoughts of
Loving men •, for Heav'ns fake my dear.
Do not difcover what I told you ^ I dread his tongue
As much as vou ought to have done his Friendlhip .

Pert, Ht'^gone, Madam. {Enter V^n.

Loveit. Lightning blaftbim.

Pert, When I told him you defired him to comeback,
He fmii'J , made a mouth at me, flung into his -
Coach, and faid

Loveit, What did he fay.?

Pert, Drive away, and then repeated Verfes,

Loveit Wou'd I had made a Contrad to be a Witch
When firfl I entertain'J this greater Devil,
Monfter, Barbarian \ I could tear my (elf in pieces.
Revenge, nothing but Revenge can eafe me j Plague,
War, Famine, Fire, all that can bring univerfal ruin
And mifery on mankind, with Joy I'd perifli to
Have you in my poiver but this moment. ZEx* Loveit.

Pert,



Pert. Follow Madam, leave her not in this outragious paflion'

, L^^n gathers up the thims

Bell. H'as given me the proof which I defired of
His love, but 'tis a proof of his ill nature too ^
I wilh I had not feen him ufe her fo :
I ligh to think that Dormant may be
One day as faithlcfs, and unkind tome. *

^Exeunt,



AC T.III.

S C E N E L^iy Wood vjls Lo^/wgy.

£»f^r Harriet, and ^vSy her Woman,

S^jjr. .l^Ear Madam !

jLJ Let me fet that Curl in order.

Har. Let me alone,! will fhake 'em all out of order.

Bnfy. Will you never leave this Wildnefs ?

Har. Torment me not.

Bnfy. Look ! there's a Knot falling off.

Har. Let it drop. .

Bufy. But one pin, dear Madam.

Har. How do I dayly fuffer under thy Officious Fingers ?

Bnfy. Ah the difference that is between
You and my Lady Dapper f how uneaCe fhe is
If the leafl; thing be amifs about her ?

Har. She is indeed molt exa(ft ! nothing is ever wanting
To make her uglinefs remarkable !

'Bnfy, Jeering people fay fo !

Har\ Her powdering, painting, and her patching never fail in
Publick to draw the tongues and eyes of all the men upon her.

Bufy. She is indeed a little too pretending.

Har. That Women ihould fet up for beauty as much in fpite
Of nature, as fome men have done for Wit.

Biijy. 1 hope without offence one may endeavour
To make onesfelf agree:able.

Har. Nor, vvhen'tisimpoffible. Women then
Ought to be no more fond of drefling, than Fools
Should bs of talking ; Hoous and Modefcy,

E Mafques



Ma^ues and Silqnce, things that Ihadow and conceal r
They (hould think of nothing tlfe.

Bufy. Jefu ! Madam, what will your Mother think is
Become of you ? for Heav'ns fake go in again.

Har. I won't !

Bnfy. This is the extravagant'ft thing that ever
You did in your life, to leave her and a Gentleman
Who is to be your Husband. .

Har. My Husband !
Uaft thou fo little wit to think I fpoke what I meant
When 1 over-joy'd her in the Country, with a low Courtfy,
And what you pieafe, Madam,i|ftial) ever be obedient.

Bajy. Nay, I know not, you mwe fo many fetches.

Har. And this was one, to get her up to London !
Nothing elfe I affure thee.

Bufy. Well, the man, in my mind, is a lineman!

Har, The man indeed wears his Cloaths fafhionably, and
Has.a pretty negligent way with him, very Courtly,
And much affeded •, he bows, and talks, and frailes *
So agreeably as he thinks. . ,

ISufy. 1 never faw any thing fo gentile !

Har. Varnifh'd over with good breeding, many
A Blockhead makes a tolerable (how

Bufy. I wonder you do not like him,

Har. I think I might be brought to endure him, and that h
All areafonable Woman lliould exped in a Husband, but
There is duty i'the cafe — and like the haughty ^JMerab^ I
Find mueh aver/ion in myftubborn mind.
Which is bred by being premised and deftgr^d.

Bufy. I wilh you do not deUgn your own ruin ! 1 partly
Guefs your inclinations, Madam that Mr. Dortmant-



Har. Leave your prating, and fing fome foolifh Song or other;.
Bufy. I will, the Song you love fo well ever fince you
iaw Mr. Dqrimant^

SONG... •

When firji Amintas charm''d my hearty

My heedlef Sheep began to jiray ;
The Wolves foon fiole the greateft part ^ < -

jind all mil now be made a prey.

Ah^ let not love your thoughts pojfc^j
^is fatal to a Shepherded ^

Ths



The dan£roHt falfion yon muft Jhmj
^ ' ' ' me^ be quite undone.



'he dan^rom
Qr elfe Uke



Har, Shall I be paid down by a covetous Parent for a purchace ?
I need no Land ; no I'll lay my felf out all in love.

it is decreed —

Enter Y. BcUair.

T. Bell. What generous
Refolution are you making, Madam ? '
Har, Only to be difobedient, Sir.
T. Bell. Let me join hands with you in that-



Har. With all my heart, I never thought I fhoulS have

Given you mine fo willingly. Here I Harriet.

T. Bell. And I Harry '

Har. Do folemnly proteft

T. Bell. And vow—



Har. That I with you • •

T. Bell. And I with you

Both. Will never marry

Har, A match !
T. "Bell. And no match /
How do you like this indifference now ?
Har. You exped 1 fliould take it ill I fee !
T. Bell. 'Tis not unnatural for young Women to be a little
Angry, you mifs a Conqueft, though you wou'd flight the
Poor man were he in your power.

Har. There are fome it may be have an Eye like BartUomeWf
Big enough for the whole Fair, but I am not of the
Number, and you may keep your Ginger-bread,
'Twill be more acceptable to the Lady,
Whofe dear Image it wears. Sir. '
T. Bell. I mufl: confefs, Madam, you came a day after the Fair.

Har, You own then you are in love —

• r. Bell. I do.

. Har. The confidence is generous, and in return 1 could almofl
Find in my heart to let you know my inclinations.
T. Bell. Are you in Love >
Har. Yes, with this dear Town, to that
Degree, I can fcarce endure
The Countrey in Landskapes and in Hangings.
r. Bell. What a dreadful thing 'twould be
To be hucried back to Hampjhire 1

Har. Ah — name it not !

E 2 '. 1\ Beit



T. Bell. As for us, I find we fhall agree well enough I wou'd
We cou'd do fomething to deceive the grave people I

Har. Could we delay their quick proceeding, 'twerfi well,
, A Reprieve is a good ftep towards the getting of a Pardon.

y. Bell. If we give over the Ganie, we are undone !
What think you of playing it on booty ?

Har. What do you mean ?

T. Bell. Pretend to be in love with one another ! 'twill make
Some dilatory excufes we may feign, pafs the better. . -

Har. Letusdo't, if it be but for the dear l_

Pleafuie of diflembling.

r. Bell. Can you play your part ?

Har. I know not what it is to love, but I have made

Pretty remarks by being now and then where Lovers meet.
Where did you leave^their Gravities ?

r. Bell. Tth' next Room I your Mother was
Cenfuring our modern Gallant.

" f«ffr Old Bellair, ^;?^L^^ Woodvil. . ^

Har. Peace ! Here they come, I will lean againft this wall
And look bafhfuiiy down upon my Fan, while
You, like an Amorous Spark, modilhly entertain me.

La. Wood. Never go about to excufe 'em, come, come,
It was not io when I was a young Woman.

O.BelL A Dod, they're fomething difrefpedful.

JL. FFW. Quality was then confider'd,
And not rally'd by every fleering Fellow.

O. Bell. Youth will have its jeft, a Dcd it will,

L. Wood. 'Tis good breeding now to be civil to none but
Players, and Exchange Women, they are treated by 'em as
Much above their condition, as others are below theirs.

O. Bell. Out, a pife on 'em, talk no more, the
Rogues ha 'got an ill habit of preferring Beauty,
No matter where they find it.

L. Wood. See your Son, and my Daughter,, they have
Improv'd their acquaintaince iince they were within.

O. Bell A Dod methinks they have !
let's kr;ep back, and obferve.

T. Be'L Now for a look and gcHures that may perfwade'em
i*m faying all the pafiionate things imaginable—

Haro Your head a little more on one fide, eafe your ftlf
On your left JLeg, and play with »your right hand,

l.Telk Thus^ is it not ?

Har,



Hitr. Nov^ f;t your right kg firm on the ground, adjalt
Your Belt, then look about yoii.
' T.BetL A little exercifing will make me perfed.

Har. Smile, and turn to me again very fparkifh !

T. BelU Will you take your turri,,and be inftruded ?

Har. With all my heart.

T, Bell. At one motion play your Fan^ roul your Eyes,
And then fettle a kind look upon me.

Har. So.

T. Bell. Now fpread your Fan, look down upon it,
And tell the iticks with a Finger.

Har. Very Modifh.

T, Bell. Clap your hand up to your bofom,
Hold down your Gown \ Y . .-:

Shrug a little, draw up your Breads, and let 'em fall \ J ^^ .. j
Again, gently, with a figh or two, &c.

Har. By the good inftruiftions you give, I fufped: you for on&
Of thofe malitious Obfervers who watch peoples Eyes,
And from innocent looks, makefcandalousconclufions.

T. Bell. I know fonie indeed, who out of meer love
To mifchief, are as vigilant ss fealoufy it felF,
And will give you an account oif every Glance tt

That pafles at a Play, and i'th' Circle !

Har. 'Twill not be amifs now to feem a little pleafant.

T.Bell. Clap your Fan then in both your hands, fnatch it.
To your Mauch, fmile, and with a lively motion fling your

Body a little forwards. So now fpread it ; fall back on

The fudden, Cover your Face with it, and break out

Into a loud Laughcer— take up I look

Grave, and fall a fanning of your felf . —

Admirably well aded.

Har, I think I am pretty apt at thefe^-matters!

O. Bell, A Dod, I like this well.

L.Wood. This promifes fomet'iing.

O. 'Bell. Come 1 there is Love i*ch' cafe, a Dod there is,^
Or will be ; what f^y you, young Lady ?

Har. AH ingood time, Sir, youexpcdl: weflioiild fall to^,
And Love as Game Cocks fight, as fooa as we are fet
Together, a Dod,y'areunreaibnabler
. Q. Bell. A Dod, firrah, I like chy wit wdl \_E'2ter a Servant ,

Serv-ani. The Coach is at the Door, MadaT»

O. Bell. Go,^ get you and take the Air togcthsr.

L.Waod: Will not yougo witli US?

Q, 'Bell. Out, a pize y A Dod I ha' bufmefs, aad cannot.



We HiaD meet at night at ray Sifter Totpw/fyj.

T. Bell. He's going to Emtlia. ^Jfide].

I over heard him talk of a Collation. \_ExeHm.

SCENE II.

E^f^rL. Townley, Eoiilia, and Mr,M.^d\ty.

L. Town. I pity the young lovers, we lall talk'd of,
Though to fay truth, their conduct has been fo indifcreet,
They deferve to be unfortunate.

Med. Y*have had an exadt account, from the great Lady
Tth' Box, down to the little Orange- Wench.

Emil. Y'are a living Libel, a breathing Lampoon ;
I wonder you are not torn in pieces.

Med. What think you of fetting up an Office of Intelligence.
For thefe matters ? the projeft may get Money.

L. Town. You would have great dealings with country Ladies.

Med. More than Muddiman has {Enter Bellinda.

With their husbands.

L, Town. Bellinda, what has been become of you ! we
Have not feen you here of late
With your friend Mrs Loveit.

Bellin. Dear creature, I left her but now fo fadly afflicfted.

L. Town. With her old diftemper, Jealoufy !

Med. Dorimant has plaid her fome new prank.

BelUn\ Well, that Dorimant is certainly the word
Man breathing.

Emil. 1 once thought fo.

Bell. And do you not think fo ftill ?

Emil. No, indeed !

Bell. Ohjefui

Eml. The.Town does him a great deal of Injury, and
I will never believe what it fays of a man 1 do
Not know, again for his fake !

Bell. You make me wonder !

L Town. He's a very well-bred man.

Bell. But Ilrangely ill-natur'd.

Emil, Then he's a very witty man !

Bfll, But a man of no principles.

Med. Your man of principles is a very fine thing indeed*.

Bell To be preferr'd to men of p^arts by Women who have
Regard to theit Reputation arili Qaict. Well were I minded
To play the Fool, he (hou'd be the iaft man' fd think of.

Med.



(jV)



Med. He has been the firft in many Ladies favours, thongh
You are fo fevere, Madam .

L. Town. What he may be for a Lover I know not, but
He's a very pleafant acquaintance I am fure.
Bell. Had yon feen him ufe Mrs. Loveitas I have done,

You wou'd never endure him more .

Emil, What, he has quarrel'd with her again !
5^/. Upon the flightcftoccafion, he's jealous
Of Sir Foplwg,

L. Town. She never faw him in her life but
Yefterday, and that was here.

€mil. On my Confcience ! he's the only man in Town,
That's her averlion, how horribly out of humour • •

She was all the while he talk'd to her !

Bell. And fome body has wickedly told him

Emil. Here he comes. {^Enter Dorimant,

Med. Dormant \ you are luckily come tojuftify

Your felf -here's a Lady

Bell. Has a word or two to fay to you from
Adifconfolate psrfon.

Dor. You tender your Reputation too much I know, Madam,
To whifper with me before this good Company.
'Bell. To ferve.Mrs Loveit^ Til make a bold venture.
Dor, Here's .^(5//(f)', the very Spirit of Scandal.
Bell. No matter !

Emil. 'Tis fomething your are unw illing to
Hear, Mr. Dorimant.
L' Town. Tell him, BelUnda^ whether he will or no !
BelU Mrs. Lovett ! [jtlondc^

Dor. Softly, thefe are Laughers, you do not know 'em»
B ell. In a word, y'ave made me hate you, [To Dor. apart^
Which 1 thought you never could have done.
'Dor, In obeying your Commands.
Bell. Twas a cruel part you pla^'d ! how cou'd you ad: it f
Dor, Nothing is cruel to a man who could kill himfeif
To pleafe you ^ remember Five a Ciock to morrow Morning,
"Bell. 1 trembk when you name it.
'Dor. Be fure you come.
Bell, liha'nor.
Dor, Swear you wiin
'Bell. I dare not.
Dor^ Swear I fay.

Bell. By my life ! by all the happinefs I hope f©r-

Dor, You will, ^



, (?4)

mell. I will. ;-H ;W,:.

Dor. Kind. ': . r

'Sell. I ara glad I've fworn, I vow I think 1 fhould ha'
Faii'd youeife.

Dor. Surprifmgly kind ! in what temper did
You leave Loveki

Bed. Her raving was prettily over, and (he began to be
In a brave way of defying you, and all your works.
Where have you been fince you went from thence ?

Dor, 1 looked in at the Play.

Bell. 1 have promis'd and muft return to her agen.

Dor. Perfwade her to walk in the Mail this evening.

Bdl. She hates the place and will not come.

Dor. Do all you can to prevail with her.

Bell. For what purpofe.?

Dor, Sir Foiling will be here anon, I'll prepare him
To fet upon her there before me.

Bell. You perlecute her too much, but Til do all you'll ha'me.

Dor. Tell her plainly, 'tis grown fo dull a bullnefs [alond.
I can drudge onjio longer.

Smil. There are afHidlions in Love, Mr. Dormant.

Dor. You Women make 'em, who are commonly as
Unreafonable in that as you are at Play ; without
The Advantage he on your fide, a man can never
Quietly give over when he's weary ?

Med. If you would play without being obliged to
Complaifance, Donmant^ you ftiould play in
Publick places.

Dor. Ordinaries were a very good thing for that.
But Gentlemen do not of late frequent 'em; the
Deep play is now in private Houfes.

[_^t\\'md2iofferingtofledav(!ay.

L. Town. Bellwda^ are you leaving us {o foon ?

Bell. I am to go to the Park with Mrs. Loveit^
Madam \_Ex. Beliinda.

L. Tovon. This con6dence will go nigh to fpoil this
Young Creature. ,

^ Med. 'Twill doher good, Madam, Young men who
Are brought up under pradifing Lawyers, prove
The abler Council, when they come to be cali'd
TotheBar themfelves

Dor. The Town has been very favourable to you
This afternoon, my Lady Tomiley., you ufe to have
An Anibara'i of Chairs and Coaches at your Door,

An



(55)

An uproar of Footmen in your Hall, and a noife
Of Fools above here.

L. Tovon, Indeed my Houfe is the general Rendevou^e
And next to the PJay-houfe is the common '

Refuge of all the young idle people.

Emil. Company isavery good thing, Madam, but
I wonder you do not love it a little more chofen.

L Towrir 'Tis good to have an univerfal tafte, we
Should love Wit, but for Variety, be able to divert
Our felves with the Extravagancies of thofe who want it.

C^ed. Fools will make you laugh.

Emil. For once or twice / but the repetition of their
Folly after a vifit or two grows tedious and unfufTerable.

L. Tomj, You are a little too delicate, Emilia.

ZEmer a Ta^e^

Tage. Sir Tolling Flutter^ Madam, defires to know if
You are tobefeen.

L, Town. Here's the frefhefl Fool in Town, and one
Who has not cloy'd you yet. Page I

Page. Madam !

L. Town. Defire him to walk up.

Dor. Do not you fall on him, MeMey^ andfnubhim.
Sooth him up in his extravagance ! he will fhew the better."

Mtd. You know I have a natural indulgence for Fools,
And need not this caution, Sir !

Enter Sir Fopling Flutter, with his Page after him.

Sr. Fop. Page ! Wait without. Madam, I [To L. Townley,
Kifs your Hands, I fee Yefterday was nothing of Chance,
The belles alTembles form themfelves here every day.
Lady, your fervant ; Dorimant^ let me embrace {^To Emilia.

Thee, without lying I have not met with any of my
Acquaintance, who retain fo much of Paris as
Thou doft, the very air thou hadfl when the
Marquife miftook thee i*th' Tuilleries, and cry'd
-Hey Chevalier, and then begg'd thy pardon.

Dor. I would fain wear in Fafhion as long as I can, Sir,
'lis a thing to be valu'd in men as wells as Bawbles.

Sr. Fop. Thou art a man of Wit, and underftands
The Town : prithee let thee and I be intimate.
There is no living without making fome good
Man the confident of our pleafures.

Dot. Tistrue! but there is no man fo improper

F Far



For fueh a bufinefs as ram.

Sr. Fop. Prithee ! why hall thou f© modeft an
Opinion of thy felf?

1>or. Why firft, I cou'd never keep a fecret in my life
And then there is no charm fo infallibly makes me
Fall in love with a Woman as my knowing a
Friend loves her. I deal honeftly with you.

Sr. Fop. Thy humour's very gallant, or let m^ perifli,
I knew a French Count fo like thee.

L. Tovpn. Wit I perceive has more power over you
Than Beauty, Sir Foplmg, elfe you would not have
Let this Lady ftand fo long negleftfed.

Sr. Fop. A thoufand pardons, Madam, Ibme £Tq Smilia.

Civilitie's due of courfe upon the meeting a long abfent
Friend. The Eclat of fo much beauty I confefs ought
To have charm'd me fooner.

Emil. The brillain of fo much good language, Sir, has much
More power than the little beauty I can boaft.

Sr. Fop. I never faw any thing prettier than this high
Work on your Point D'efpaigne- —

€miL 'Tisnot fo rich as Point de Venice

Sr. Fop. Not altogether^ but looks cooler, and is more
Proper for the feafon. Dormant , is not that Medley ?

T>QY. The fame, Sir.

Sr. Fop. Forgive me, Sir, in this Ambara's of CivilitieSj
I could not come to have you in my Arms fooner.
You underfland an Equipage the bell of
Any man in Town, I hear.

Med. By my own you would not guefs it.

Sr. Fop. There are Criticks who do not write, Sir.

Med. Our peevifh Poets will fcarce allow it.

%x.Fop. Dam'em, they'll allow no Man Wit,
Who does not play the fool like themfelves and (how it ! Have
You taken notice of the Gallefli I brought over ?

Med. O yes ! 't has quite another Air, than th'Englifh makes,

Sr. Fop. 'Tis as eafily known from an Engliih Tumbril,
As an Inns of Court-man is from one of us,,

Dor. Truly there is a bell air in Galelhes as well as men.

Med. But there are few fo delicate to obferve it.

Sr. Fop. The woi Id is generally very grolfier here indeed,,

L^Town. He's very fine.

Emil. Extreara proper,

Sr. Fop. A flight fuit I made to appear in at my firft arrival,
Not worthy your confideration, Ladies.

"Dor..



(J7)

Dor. The Pantaloon is very well mounted.
Sr. Fop. The Taflels are new and pretty.
Med. I never faw a Coat better cut.
Sr. Fop. It makes me fhow long wafted, and I think flender.
Dor. That's the ihape our Ladies doat on.
Med. Your breech though is a handful too high in my
Eye, Sir FofUng.

Sr. Fop. Peace, Medley, I have wifht it lower a thouland
Times, but a Pox on't, 'twill not be.
L. Town. His Gloves are well fring'd, large and graceful.
Sr. Fop. I was always eminent for being bien gant^.
Emil. He wears nothing bat what are Originals of the
Mofl: Famous hands in Paris.
Sr. Fop. You are in the right, Madam.
X. Town, The Suit.
Sr. Fop. Barroy.
Emil. The Garniture.

Sr, Fop. LeGras— ^

Med, TheShooes!
Sr. Fop. Piccar !
. Dor. ThePerriwig!
Sr. Fop. Chedreux.
Towfi. and Smil. The Gloves !
Sr. Fop. Orangerii / You know the fmell, Ladies /
Dorimant^ I could find in my heart for an amufement
To have a Gallantry with fome of our Engliih Ladies.

Dor, 'Tis a thing no lefs neceflary to confirm the
Reputation of your Wit, than a Duel will be
To (atisfie the Town of your Courage.

Sr. Fop. Here was a Woman yefterday

Vor. M\SxtkLoveit,

Sr. Fop. You have nam'd her ! /

*Dor. You cannot pitch on a better for your purpofe.
Sr. Fop. Prithee ! what is (he ?
Dor. A perfon of Quality, and one who has a i;eft of
Reputation enough to make the Conqueft conllderable :
Befides, I hear, fhe likes you too !

Sr. Fop. Methoughts (he fcem'd though very referv'd,
And uneafie all the time I entertain'd her.

Dor, Grimace and affedation; You will fee
Her i'th' Mail to night.
St, Fop, Prithee, let thee and I take the Air t ogether.
Dor. I am engag'd to Medley, but I'll meet you at
Sumt James\ and give you fome information, upon the

F 2 Which



(38)

Which you may regulate your beoccedingsi^

Sr.Fop. All the world will in the Park tonight: Ladies,.
'Twere pity to keep fo much beauty longer within Doors,
And rob the ring of all thofe Charms

That Ihould adorn it- — Hey Page.

[iEmer Vage^, and goes out again o
See that all my People be ready.
Dorimmt a Revoir.

Med. A fine mettl'd Coxcomb.

Dor. Brisk and infipid —

Med, Pert and dull.

EmL However you defpife him, Gentlemen, Til lay my
Life he pafles for a Wit with many.

Dor. That may very well be, Nature hath her cheats, Hum's
A brain, and puts fophifticate dulnefs often on the taftlefs
Multitude for true wit and good humour. Medley^ come. ,

Med. I muft go a little way, I will meet you i'the MajL

Dor^ ril walk through the Garden thither, welhaUmeet
Anon and bow. {To the Women.

L. Town . Not to night ! we are engag'd about a bufinefs,
The knowledge of which may make you laugh hereafter..

Med. Your fervant, Ladies.

Dor. A Revoir, as Sir Fofling fays-

{Ex.Med,2in^Dor,

L, Town. The Old Man will be here immediately,

Smil. Let's expedt him i'th' Garden—

L.Tomi. Go, youareaRogueo.

Emit. I can't abide you.

{Exemt.

SCENE III. TfeMaiL

Enter Harriet, Y. Bellair, {hefulUnghim,

Hat. Come along.

r. Bell. And leave your Mother. •

Mar. Bnfie will be feat with a Hue and Cry after us ^
But that's no matter.

r. Bell. 'Twill look flrangely in me.

Bdr. She'll believe it a freak of mine, and never blame .
Your manners.

T. Bell. What reverend acquairitanceisthat fhe has met ?

Har.



(?9)

Har. A fellow-beauty of the laft King's time, though by die
Ruines you would hardly guefs it. \_exeHnt,

{Enter Dorimant md crojfes the Sta^e,
f^r^r y. Bellair^w^ Harriet.

T. Bell. By this time your Mother is in a fine taking.

Han If your Friend Mr. 'Dormant were but here now.
That fhe might find me talking with him.

r. BeiL She does not know him but dreads him, I hear, of
All mankind.

Har. She concludes if he does but fpeak to a
Woman Ihe's undone, is on her knees every day to
Pray Heav'n defend me from him.

t,.Bell. You do not^pprehend him fo much as fhe does,

Har. I never faw any thing in him that was frightful.

T. Ben. On the contrary, have you not obferved fomething
Extream delightful in his Wit and Perfon ?

Har. He's agreeable and pleafant I mull own, but he
Does fo much afFed being fo, he di(pleafes me.

T.BelU Lord, Madam, all he does and fays, isfoeafie.
And fo natural.

Har, Some mens Verfes feem fo to the unskilful^
But labour i'che one, and affecflation i'the other
To the Judicious plainly appear.

Y. Bell. I never heard him accusM of afFedation before.
Enter Dorimant and jt ares upon her.

Har. It pafles on the eafie Town, who are favourably
Pleas'd in him to call it humour. £Ex, Y. Bellair and Harriet*.

Dor. Tis Ihe 1 it mufl: be (he, that lovely hair, that
Eafie fliape, thofe wanton eyes, and all thofe melting
Charms about her mouth, which C^edley fpoke of i,
l*il fo'low the Lottery, and put in for
A Prize with my friend Bellair,

Ex* Dor. 7 In love the Vigors from the vanqmjh^dfiy ^
repeating, y They fly that Wound^ and they purfiie that dy, .
Enter Y . Bellair, and Harriet, and after them Dorimant
ftanding at a dtftance.

Y. Bell. Mofl: people prefer High Park, tothis place.

Har. It has the better Reputation I confefs : but I
Abominate the dull diverfions there, the formal bows^.
The afl'eded fmiles, the filly by-word^, and
Amorous Tvveers, inpafllng •, here one meets with.
A 1 ittle converfation now and then,

r. Bell. Thefe converfations have bsen fatal
To fome of your Sex, Madam.



\



(40)

Bar, It may be fo, becaufe fome who want temper
Have been undone by gaming, muft others who have it,
Wholly deny themfeives the pleafure of Play ?

Dor. Truft me, it were unreafonable;, Madam. .

{Coming up gently^ and bowing to her.

Har. Lord ! who's this ? {She (iarts md looks grave-

T*Be/l. Dormant.

Dor. Is this the Woman your Father would
Have you marry ?

r.BelL It is.

Dor.e Her name?

r. B IL Harriet,

Dor. I am not miftaken, Ihe*s handfome.

r. Bell. Talk to her, her Wit is better than her face •,
We were wilhing for you but now.

Dor. Overcaft with ferioufnefs o*the fudden ! {To Harriet.
A thoufand fmiles were fliining in that Face but now j
I never faw fo quick a change of Weather.

Har. I feel as great a change within \ {^^fide.

But he Ihall never know it.

Dor. You were talking of Play, Madam, Pray
What may be your flint ?

Hart A little harmlefs difcourfe in publick walks.
Or at moft an appointment in a Box bare facM
At the Play-houfe •, you are for Masks, and
Private meetings \ where Women engage
For all they are worth I hear.

Dor. I have been us'd to deep Play, but I can-make one
At fmall Game, when I like ray Gamefter well. ~^

Har. And be fo unconcern'd you'll ha' no pleafure {n't.

Dor. Where there is a confiderable fum to be won, the .
Hope of drawing pr cple in, makes every trifle confiderable.

Har. Tiie ford idnefs of mens natures 1 know makes 'em
Willing 10 3attei and comply with the Rich, though they
Are fure neve^^ ro be the better for 'em.

Dor. 'Ti£ m. tnt^ir power to do us good, and we defpair
Not but St Tome time or other they may be willing.

Har, To men who have far'd in this Town like you,
'Tiwould be a great Mortification to live on hope^
Could you keep a Lent for a Miftrefs ?

Dor. In exp2(n;ation of a happy Eafter, and though time
Be very precious, tliink forty days well loft, to gain your
Favour.

Har. Mr, BelUir I let let us walk, 'tis time to leave him :

Men



Men grow dull when they begin to be particular.

T)or. Y'arc miltaken, flattery will notenfue, though I know
Y'are greedy of the praifes of the whole Mail.
Har. You do me wrong.

Bor, I do not, as I follow'd you, 1 obferv'd how you
Were pleased when theFo/jj cry'd (he's handfome, very
Handfome, by God Ihe is, and whifper'd aloud your name, ^
The thoufand feveral forms you put your face into ■, then
To make your felf more agreeable, how wantonly you play'd
With your head, flung back your locks, and look'd frailingly
Over your Ihoulder at 'em.

Ha.r, I do not go begging the mens as you do
The Ladies Good liking with a fly foftnefs in
Your looks, and a gentle flownefs in your bows,

As you pafs by 'em as thus Sir \^A^s him.

Is not this like you ?

\_Enter Lady Woodvil and Bufy.
r. Bell. Your Mother, Madam. {^PhIIs Har. sy compofes her

ZJelf.
L. Wood. Ah my Dear Child Harriet.
Biify. Now is flie fo pleas'd with finding her agen,
She cannot chide her.
L. Wood. Come away !

Dor. 'lis now but high Mail, Madam, the moft entertaining
Time of ail the Evening.

Har. I would fain fee that 7)orimant, Mother, you fo
Cry out of, for a monfl:er, he's in the Mail
I hear.

L, Wood. Come away then ! the Plague is here, and you
Should dread the infed:ion.
T. Bell. You may be mifinform'd of the Gentleman.
L. Wood. Oh no ! I hope you do not know him.
He is the Prince of all the Devils in the Town,
Delights in nothing but in Rapes and Riots.
Dor. If you did but hear him fpeak. Madam.
L. Wood. Oh ! he has a Tongue they fay would.tempt the
Angels to a fecond fall.

Enter Sir Fopling with his Equipage, fix Foot-men^
and a Page,
Sv.Fop. Hey, Champaine, Norman, La Rofe, La Fleur,,

La Tour, La Verdure. Dorimant

L. Wood. Here, here he is among this Rout, he.
Names him*, come away /^^m^f, come away.

lEx.U Woodo. Har, Bufy ^?;^Y. Bell.

"Dor.



Dor. This fool'i coming has fpoiFd al', (he's gone,
But (he has left a pleafing Image of her felf

Behind, that wanders in my Soul—

It mufl: not fettle there.

Sr.Foj), What refverie is this ? fpeakman.

Dor. Snatch from my felf how far behind ■?
Already I behold the fhore !

Enter Medley.

Med. DorimantfZdlkoyeryl I m^t with 'Bellair.

Dor, You can tell me no news, Sir, I know alL

Med, How do you like the Daughter?

Dor. You never came fo near truth in your life,
As you did in her defcription.

Med, What think you of the Mother ?
, Dor. Whateverl think of her, fhe thinks
Very well of me, I find.

Med. Did (he know you?

Dor^ She did not, whether (he does now or no, I know not. •
Here was a pleafant Scene towards, when in came Sir
Foj)/w^, muttering up his Equipage, and at the
Latter end nam'd me, and frighted her away.

Med. Loveit and Bellinda arc not iar oS'y Ifaw'em
Alight at St. ;f^wc//.

Dor. Sr. FofUng^ hark you, a word or two, \JVhifpers,

Look you do not want aflurance.

Sr. Fop.. I never do on thefe occafions.

Dor. Walk on, we mufl; not be feen together, make your
Advantage of what I have told you, the next turn
You will meet the Lady.

Sr. Fop. Hey Follow me all. [_?x. 5r,Fop. & his Equipage,

Dor. Medley.) you (hall fee good fport anon between
Loveit and this F opting. - - -

. Med, 1 thought there was fomething toward by that whifper.:

Dor. You know a worthy pi mcipie of hers ?

Med. Not to be fo much as civil to a man who fpeaks to her
In the prefence of him (he profelTes to love.

'Dor. I have encouraged Fopling to talk to her to night

Med. Now you are here, (he will go nigh to beat him.

Dor. in the humour (he's in, her love will make her dofome
Very extravagant thing, doubtlefs.

Med. What was Bellindah bufinels with you at my
LadyToM7«/f)''s.<'

Dor. To get me to meet Loveit here in order to an
Eclercifment ^ I made fome difSculty of it; and have prepaiM

This



(4?)

This rancounter to make good my Jealoufy.

Med. Here they come ! HEnter Lov. Belf. and Pert.

Dor. rie meet her and provoke her with a deal of dumb
Civility in pafling by, then turn fhort and be behind

Her when Sir Fopling fets upon her .

See how unregarded now

That piece of Beanty fajfes- \^Ex. Dor. and Med^

Bell. How wonderful refpeiftfully he bowM !

Pert. He's always over-mannerly when
He has done a milchief .

'Bell. Methoughts indeed at the fame time he had
A ftrange defpifing Countenance.

Pert. The unlucky look he thinks becomes him.

*Se//. I was afraid you would have fpoken to him,'my Dear.

Lov. 1 would have di*d firft 5 he (hall no more find me
The loving fool he has done.

Bell. You love him ftill !

Lo'v. No.

Pert. I wifh you did not.

Lov. I do not^ and I will have you think fo : What made
You hale me to this odious place, 'BelUnda f

Bell. Ihatetobehulch'dupinaCoachi
Walking is much better.

Lov. Would we could meet Sir PopUng now.'

'Bell. Lord ! would you not avoid him ?

Lov. I would make him ail the advances that may be.

BelL That would confirm "Dorimant^s fufpicion, my Dear^

Lov. He is not jealous -, but 1 will make him Coy and be
Reveng'd a way he little thinks on.

Bell, afide. If fhe fliould make him jealous, that may make
Him fond of her again : I mull diflwade her from it. Lord !
My Dear, this will certainly make him hate you.

Lov. 'Twill make him uneafie though he does not care
For me ; I know the effefts of jealoufie on men of his
Proud temper.

Bell. 'Tis a fantaftick remedy, its operations are
Dangerous and uncertain.

Lov. 'Tis the (trongeft Cordial we can give to dying Love,
It often brings it back when ther's no fign of life remaining :
But 1 defign not fo much the reviving his, as my revenge.
Enter Sir Fopling and his Equipage,

Sir Fop. Hey / bid the Coach'-man fend home four of his
Horfes, and bring the Coach to White-Hall^ V\\ walk
Over the Park^~ Madam, the honour of kifllng your

G Fair



(44)

Fair hands is a happincis I mifs'd this afternoon at my ^ifii au .
Liiiy Tomley's I • "■

L9V,. Yon were very obliging^ SitFo^iing, the lall
Time I faw you there.

Sir Fop, The preference was due to your wit and beauty. ^
Madam, your Servant, there never was fo fwect an Evenings

B^IU Thas drawn all the rabble of the Town hither.

Sir Fop. 'Tis pity ther's not an order made, that none hvtt
The Beau Monde fhould walk here.

Lov. Twould add much to the beauty of the pUct .-
See what a fort of nafty Fellows are coming.

{Enter foHTill'fa^ion*dFell9WS.^ fnging*^
'Tis not for kijfes alone y^C.

Lov* Fo ! their Perriwigs are fcented with
Tobacco foftrong' •

SirFp/?. It overcomes our pulvilio-—- — —
Methinks I fmell the Coffee-houfe they come from.

1 Man. Dorimant^s convenient, Madam Loveit.

2 Man* I like the oylie Buttock with her.

3 .^^«* What fpruce prig is that ?

1 Man. A Caravan, lately come from P«Wi.

2 Man. Peace, they fmoak.

There's fomething elfe to be done^ &C. f* j4ll oftbem



Dor. They're ingag'd-



\CoHghing.
\JEx» Singings



Med. She entertains him as if fhe lik'd him.

Dor. Let us go forward — -feern earneft in difcourfe and
Shew our felves. Then you (hail fee how flie'il ufe himi

Bell. Yonder's Dormant.^ my Dear..

Lov. I fee him, he comes infulting -, but I will difappoint
Him in his expeflaticn. {^Ajide,

To Sir Fopling. 1 like this pretty nice humour of yours,
Sir Fopling : With what a loathing eye he look'd upon
Thofe Fellows !

Sir Fop, I fat near one of 'em at a Play 16 day, and was almofl:
Poifon'd with a pair of Cordivant Gloves he wears--— —

Ldv. Oh! filthy Cordivant
How I hate the fmell ! £ Laughs in a Imd offered way.

Sir Fop. Did you obferve, Madam, how their Crevats
Hung loofe an inch from their Neck, and what
A frightful Air it gave 'em.

Lqv, Oh, I took particiiikr noCicc of one thaiisalwaiesr

Sprue'd



(45)

Spruc'd up with a deal of dirty Sky-colur'd Ribband.

Bell. That's one of the walking Flajolets, who
Haunt the Mail o'nights

Lovi Oh ! I remember him I H*has a hollow Tooth,
Enough to (poil the fweetnefs of an Evening.

Sir Fof. I have feen the talleft walk the ftreets
With a dainty pair of Boxes, neatly bucklM on.

Lov. And a little Footboy at his Heels, Pocket-high,
With a Flat cap- — a durty Face.

Sir Fop, And a Snotty Nofe

Lov. Oh— odious, there's many of my own fex with
That Holborn Equipage trigg to Grey*s Inn-Walks \
And'now and then travail hither on a Sunday.

Med. She takes no notice of you.

Dor. Damn her ! I am jealous of a Counter.plot !

Lov. Your Liveries arc the fineft, Sir Foplmg

Oh that Page ! that Page is the prettily'ft dreft

They are all Frenchmen.

Sir Fop. There's one damn'd Englifli Blockhead
Among 'em, you may know him by his Meine.

Lov. Oh ! that's he, that's he, what do you call him ?

Sir Fop. Hey 1 know not what to call him ~-

Lov. What's your Name ?

Footm. John Tron, Madam !

Sir Fop. O unfufferable I Tron, Trotty Trott ! there's
Nothing fo barbarous as the names of our Englilh Servants.
What Countreyman are you, Sirrah ?

Footm. Hampjhire, Sir.

Sir Fop. Then, Hampjhire be your name. Hey, Hampjhire !

Lov. O That found, that found becomes the
Mouth of a man of Quality !

Med. Dorimanty you look a little bafhful on the matter !

*Dor. She diffembles better than I thought
She could have done.

Med. You have tempted her with too lufcious a bait.
She bites at the Coxcomb.

Dor. She cannot fall from loving me to that ?

Med. You begin to be jealous in earneft.

Dor. Of one I do not love

Med* You did love her. •

Dor. Tije fit has long been over

Med. But I have known men fall into dangerous relapfes
When they have found a Woman inclining to another.

Dor. He euefles the lecret of ray Heart ! I am concern'd,

^ G 2 But



U6)

But dare not fhow it, left Bdlwda fhould miftruft all I

Have done to gain ber. . [tobimfelf.

iBeiZ. t -^/^tf. ]] Ihave watchM his look, and find no
Alteration there. Did he Jove her, fome figns of
Jealoufy would have appeared ?

Dor. I hope this happy Evening, Madam, has
Reconcii'd you to the fcandalous Mail, we
Shall have you now hankering here agen — -

Lov. Sir Foiling, will you walk '

Sir Fop I am all obedience. Madam .

Lov, Come along then and let's agree to be

Malitious on all the ilUfafliion'd things we meet.

Sir Fop We'll make a Critick on the
Whole Mail, Madam.
Lov. Bellinday you Ihall engage
Bell. To the referve of our friends, my Dear.

Lov. No ! No 1 Exceptions

Sir Fof We'll facrificc all to our diverfion .

Lov. All—all" -
1 Sirfc/;. All.

Bell. AH ? Then let it be.

{Ex, Sir Fopling, Loveit, Bellinda, and Pert, langhmg..
Med. Would you had brought fome more of your
' Friends, Dorimant^ to have been Witnefles of Sir

Fo/j//»/sdifgrace, and your triumph

Dor. 'Twere uurcafonable to defire you notta
Laugh at me -, but pray do not expofe me
To the Town this day or two.
Med. By that time you hope to have regained your Credit.
Dor. I know (he hates Fo^UngyZiiA only makes ufe of
Him in hope to work me on agen ^ had it not been
For fome powerful Confiderations, which will be
Remov'd to morrow morning, 1 had made her pluck off:
This mask, and (hew the paffion that lyes
Panting under*

Enter a Footman.
M$d. Here comes a man from !Sf?/;2?Vj with news of
Your Jaft adventure.

Dor. I am glad he fent him. I long to know
The confequence of our parting.

Footm. Sir, my Mailer defires you to come to my Lady
Torv-nley^s prefently, and bring Mr. Medley with you.
My Lady W^tftf^w// and her Daughter are there.

Aled. Then all's weU, Dorimmit' ►

Footm.



U7)

Footm. They have fent for the Fiddles, and
Mean to dance! He bid iriQ tell you, Sir, the .
Old Lady does not know you, and would have
You own your felf to be Mr. Conrt\^e. They
Are all prepar'd to receive you by that name.

Dor. That foppiOi admirer of Quality, who flatters the
Very meat at honourable Tables, and never offers love
To a Woman below a Lady Grand mother.

Med. You know the Gharafter you are to adt, I fee !

Dor. This is /^-^rnVs contrivance

Wild, witty, loveforae, beautiful and young

Come along, Medley

Med. This new Woman would well fupply the lofs of Loveit.

Dor, That bufinefs mufl: not end io^ before to morrow
Sun is fet, I will revenge and clear it.

jindyou and Loveit to her coji fhallfindy

I fathom all the depths of Womankind.

\_ExeHnti



A C T IV.

The Scene opem with the Fiddles playing a
Countrey dance, .

^^^f^r Dorimant, L. Woodvill,. ro«»^ Bellair, andMrsHax:-
riet, 0/^ Bellair, 4«^ Emilia, /^r. Medley 4»^L. Town-
ley j as having jufi ended the dance.

Old Bell. C*^» ^o» fo ! a fmart bout, a very fmart bout, a Dod /
O L,Tovpno How do you like «5'?»;/?Vs.
Dancing, Brother?

O. BelU Not at all, not at all.
^ L. Town. You fpeak not what you think, I am fure.

O. 'Bell. No matter for that, go; bid her dance no more,^ it
Don't become her, it don'c become her, tell her I
Say fo-, fa Dod I love her. {_Afide6

'Dor. All people mingle now a days, [To L, Woodvill,

Madam, And in publick. places Women of Quality
Have the leaft refpcd fhow'd 'em

Lulfood. I proteft you fay the truth, Mx. Courtage,



(4«)

T^or. Forms and Ceremonies, the only things that
Uphold Quality and Greatnefs, are now fliamcfnlly
Laid alide and negleded.

L.Wood Weil ! this is not the Womens Age, let 'em
Think what they will, Lewdnefs is the bulinefs now,
Love was the bus'nefs in my Time.

Dor. The Women indeed are little beholding to the young
Men of this Age, they're generally only dull admirers
Of themfelves, and make their Court to nothing but their
Perriwigs and their Crevats, and would be more
Concern'd for the difordering of 'em, tho' on a good
Occafion, than a young Maid would be for the tumbling
Of her Head or Handkercher.

L. Wood. 1 proteft you hit 'em.

Dor. They are very affiduous to (how themfelves at Court
Well drefs't to the Women of Quality, but their bus'aels
Is with the ftale Miftrefles of the Town, who are
Prepar'd to receive their lazy addrefles by induftrious
Old Lovers, who have call 'em off, and made 'em ealy.

Har. He fits my Mothers humour fo well, a little more and
She'll dance a killing dance with him anon.
' Med. Dutifully obfervM, Madam.

Dor. They pretend to be great Critjcks in Beauty, by their
Talk you would think they lik'd no face, and yet can
Doat on an ill one, if it belong to a Landrefs or a Taylors
Daughter : they cry a Woman's paft her prime at 20,
Decay'd at four and twenty, old and unfufferable at 30.

L. Wood. Unfufferable at 30 ! That they are in the wrong,
Mr. Courtage, at five and thirty, there are living proofs
Enough to convince ^cm ,

Dor. Ay Madam ! ther's Mzs.Setlookst Mrs. Droplipy
And my Lady Lowd ! fhew me among all our opening
Buds, a face that promifes fo much Beauty as ^ ♦

The remains of theirs. . \ C

L, Wood. The deprav'd appetite of this vicious Age
Taftes nothing but green Fruit, and loaths it when
Tis kindly ripen'd.

Dor. Elfe fo many deferving Women, Madam, would
Not be fo untimely negle^ed.

L. Wood 1 proten;, Wit. Conrt^e, a dozen fuch good men
As you, would be enough to attone for that wicked
Dormant^ and all the under debauchees of the Town.
What's the matter there ? $ Har. Emil. Toung Bell. Med. Lady

\ Town, breakout into a laughter.

Med.



iW(f^. Apleafaiitmiflake, Madam, thataLady
Has made, occaHons a iittle laughter.

O, Bell. Come, come, you keep 'em idle ! they are
Impatient till the Fiddles play again.
J>or. You are not weary, Madam ?
L. Wood, One Dance more !
I cannot refufe you, M-r. Cimrtagt^ a «o / 30 {S/. {Thty dame.
Emil, You are very adtive, Sir. ^:..'- •-

r JIfter the dance^ O. Bellair, fining and
\ Aancing up to Emilia.

O. Bell. A Dod, Sirrah ; when I was a young
Fellow, I could ha'caper'd up to my
Womans Gorget.

Dor. You are willing to reft your felf, Madam— .

i» Torvxi. Wee'll walk into my Chamber and lit down,
Med. Leave us, Mr. Cdurtage^ he's a Dancer, and the
Young Ladies are not weary yet.
L. Wood. Well fend him out again,
/frfr. If you do not quickly, I know
Where to fend for Mr. 'Dmmant,

L.Wood. This Girls head, Mt. Court age<,\stvtt
Running on that wild fellow.

Dor. *Tis well you have got her a good husband,
Madam, that will fettle it.

[Ex. L. Town. Wood. ^^WDorimant.
O. Bell, to EtfiUia.2 A Dod, fweet-heart be advis'd, and do
Not throw thy felf away on a young idle fellow.
Emil. I have no fuch intention. Sir.
O. Bell. Have a little patience I Thou (halt have the mm
Ifpakeof. A Dod, he loves thee, and will make a good

Husband, but no words —

Emil. But Sir— .

O. Bell. Noanfwei — out apize ! peaee ! and think on*t»

£mer Dorimant.
Dor. Your company is defired within. Sir.

O. Bell. I go ! I go ! good Mr. Courtage fare you well !

Go! ril fee you no more. C^'u'EmlL

Smil, What have I done, Sir >
a. i?f//. You are ugly, you are ugly I
Is (he nol, Mr. CoHrti$ge ?
Emil. Better words or I fha'nt abide you.
O. Bill. Out a pize- — a l^odi^ what does fhe fay ?
Hit her a pat for me there {^Exit 0/iBeIlairj

A^d, ¥oa have charm^for the whole ii^mily.

D9r



(5°)

Dor. You'll fpoil all with fome unfeafonable Jeft, Medley.

eJ^ed. You fee I confine my Tongue, and am content to be a
Bare fpedtator, much contrary to my nature.

Emil. Methinks, Mr. Dormant^ my Lady Woodvil
Is a little fond of you.

Dor. Would her daughter were.
/ . Med. It may be you may find her fo ! try her,
You have an opportunity.

Dor. And 1 will not lofe it ! Bellair^ here's
A Lady has fomething to fay to you.

T. Bell. I wait upon her. Mr. Medley, we have both
Bufinefswith you.

Dor. Get you ail together then.
{To Harrief} That demure curt'ly is not amifs in jeft,
But do not think in earneft it becomes you.

//^r. Affe(n:ation is catching I find j from your
Grave bow I got it.

Dor. Where had you all that fcorn, and coldnefs
In your look ?

Har. From nature, Sir, pardonmy wantof art :
I have not learnt thofe foftneffes and languifliings
Which now in faces are fo much in falhion.

"Dor, You need 'em not, you have a fwgetnefs of your own,
If you would but calm your frowns and let it fettle.

Har. My eyes are wild and wandring like my paflions,
And cannot yet be ty'd to Rules of charming.

D^r. Women indeed have commonly a method of
Managing thofe meflengers of Love ! now they
Will look as if they would kiU, and anon they
Will look as if they were dying : They point and rebate
Their glances, the better to invite us.

Har. I like this variety well enough, but hate the fet face
That always looks as it would fay come love me.
A woman, who at Plays makes the Deux yeux to a
Whole Audience, and at home cannot forbear 'em
To her Monkey.

Dor. Put on a gentle fmile, and let me fee how well
It will become you.

Har. 1 am forry my face does not pleafe you as it is,
But I fhall not be complaifant and change it.

Dor. Though you are obltinate, I know 'tis capable of
Improvement, and ftialldoyou Juftlce, Madam, if 1 chance
To be at Court, when the Critiques of the Circle pals' s y rt li" .
Their judgment i for thither you mull come. > >'.

Har.



I 51)

Har\ And expeft to be taken in pieces, have all ray
Features examined, every motion cenfur'd, and on the
Whole be conderan'd to be but pretty, or a Beauty of '
The loweft rate. What think you ?

Dor. The Women ^ nay, the very lovers who belong to the
Drawing-room will malitioufly allow you more
Than that *, they always grant what is apparent.
That they may the better be believ'd, when
They name conceal'd faults they cannot
Eafily be difprovM in.

Har. Beauty runs as great a rifque expos'd at Court,
As wit does on the Stage, where the ugly and the
Foolifh, all are free to cenfure.

Dor* afide»2 I love her, and dare not let her know it,
I fear ih'as an afcendantoVeme, and may revenge the
Wrongs I have done her fex.
Think of making a party, ,Madam,Iove will engage, \lTo herl

Har. YoumakemeftartI I did not think to have
Heard of Love from you.

Dor. I never knew what 'twas to have a fettled Ague
Yet, but now and then have had irregular Fits.

Har. Take heed, ficknefs after long health is
Commonly more violent and dangerous.

Dor, I have took the infedion from her, and feel the

Difeafe now fpreading in me ^Apde,

Is the name of love fo frightful that

You dare not Hand it ? IXoher.

Har. 'Twill do little ejcecution out of your mouth
On me, lamfure.

Dor. It has been fatal

Har. Tofomeeafy Women, but we are not all
Born to one dcftiny, I was informed you ufe to
Laugh at Love, and not make it.

"Dor. The time has been, but now I muft fpeak ■ ■

Har. If it be on that idle fubjed, I will put on
My ferious look, turn my head carelefly from you,
Drop niy lip, let my eye lids fall, and hang ,

Half o're my eyes -Thus while you buz a fpeech

Of an hour long in my ear, and I anfwer
Never a word ! why do you not begin ?

Dor. That the company may take notice how paflionately I
Make advances of love ! and how difdainfully you receive 'em.

Har, When your Love's grown ftrong enough to make
You bear being laugh'd at, I'll give you leave to

H Trouble



Trouble me with it. Till when pray forbear, Sir.
Enter Sir ^O^Xm^ and other sin Mafques^
Z)<?>'.* What's here, Mafquerades?
Har, I thought that foppery had been left offj and
People might have been in private with a Fiddle.

Dor* 'Tis endeavour'd to be kept on foot ftill by
Some who find themfejves the more acceptable,
The lefs they are known.
r. 'Bett, This muft be Sir Foiling,
Afed. That extraordinary habit (hews it..
r. Beli, What are the reft ?

Med. A Company of French Rafeals, whom he pick'd
Up in Paris, and has brought over to be his dancing
Equipage, on thefe occafions ! make him own
Himfelf ^ a Fool is very troublefome, when he
Pnefumes he is Incognito.
Sir Fop. Do you know me ? ^To Harriet, .

Har. Ten to one but I guefs at you ?
Sir Fop,. Are you Women as fond of a Vizard, as we men are ?
Har. I am very fond of a Vizard that covers a
Face I do not like, Sir. '

T. Bell, Here are no Mafques you fee, Sir, but
Thole which came with you, this was intended a
Private meeting, but becaufe you look like a
Gentleman^ if you will difcover your felf, and we
Know you to be fuch, you (hall be welcome.

Sir Fop. Dear BelUir ! \_PuHing of his Mask,

Med, Sir Fopling .' how came you hither ?
Sir Fo/>. Faith, as I was coming late from W'^^V^W/,
After the King^s Couchee, one of my people told me

He had heard^Fiddles at my Lady Tovpnley\ and-

Dor. You need not fay any more, Sir,.
Sir Fop. Dorimant.^ let me kifs thee.

Dor, Hark you, Sir Fophng ? lWhi(pers,

Sir Fop. Enough, enough, Courtage.
A pretty kind of young Woman th^t.. Medley^ I obfervM
Her in the Mail more Evelie than our Englifh
Women commoly are, prithee what is flie ?
Med. The moll: noted Coquette in Town :, beware of her.
Sir Fop, Let her be what (he will, I know how to make my
Meafures, in Paris the mode is to flatter the Prude,
Laugh at the Faux-proude, make ferious love to
The Demi-proude, and only railly at the Coquette,
i^^^/^j/, what think you?

Mild,



Cy?)

Med. That for all this fmattering of the Mathematicks,
You may be out in your Judgment at Tennis.

Sir Fop. What a Ccque a Lafne is this > I talk of
Women, and thou anfwer'lt Tennis.

zJMed, Miftakes will be for want of apprehenfion.

Sir Fop. I am very glad of the acquaintance
I have with this Family.

iJJ^ed. My Lady truly is a good. Woman.

Sit Fop, Ah! Dormant f Courtage I would fay,
Would thou hadft ipent the laft Winter in Paris
With me. When thou wer't there La corneus and
Sallyes were the only habitudes we had, a Comedian
Would have been a bon^ fortune. Noftrangerever
Pafs*d his time fo well as I did fome months before
I came over. I was well received in a dozen
Families, where all the Women of quality us'd to come to
Vilit, I have intrigues to tell thee, more pleafant,
Than ever thou read'ft in a Novel.

Har. Write 'em, Sir, and oblige us Women ! our
Language wants fuch little ftories.

Sir Fop. Writing, Madam's a Mechanick part of Witt !
A Gentleman fliould never go beyond a Song or a Bill^tt

fiar. 5/<jp^ was a Gentleman.

Sk Fop. \Nho D^jimbois}

Med, Was there ever fuch a brisk blockhead ?

Har. Not lyAmhois^ Sir, but Rnbrnin, He who
Writ the Loves of France.

SkFop. That may be. Madam ! many Gentlemen do
Things that are below 'em. Damn your Authors,
Courtage, Women are the prettieft things we
Can fool away our time with.

Har. I hope you have weari*d your felf to night at Court,
Sir, and I will not think of fooling with any body here

Sir Fop, I cannot conjplain of my Fortune there, Madam—
Dormant ■

-Dor. Again/

Sir Fop, Courtage, a pox on't, I have fomething to tell thee.
When I had made my Court within, I came out
And flung my felf upon the Matt under the ftate
rth» outward room, i'th' midft of half a dozen
Beauties who were withdrawn to jeer among
Themfelves, as they call'd it.

Dor, Did you know 'em ?

Sir Fop. Not one of 'emby Heavens! not I,

H2 But



(54>

But they were all your friends.

Dor. How are you fure of that ?

Sir Faf. Why, we laugh'd^t all the Town*, fpar'd'
No body but your feif, they found me a man '
For their purpofe.

Dor, I know you are malitious to your power.

Sir Fop. And faith ! I had occafion to fliew it, for I never
Saw more gaping fools at a BaH or on a Birth-day.

*Dor, You learn'd who the women were.

Sir Fof. No matter / they frequent the Drawing-Room.

Ver. And entertain themfelves pleafantly at the expence
Of all the Fops who come there.

Sir Fof. That's their bus'nefs, faith I fifced 'em, and find
They have a fort of wit among them —
Ah filthy. {Pinches a Tallow Candle.

Dor. Look, he has been pinching the Tallow Candle.

Sir Fop. How can you breath in a Room where there's
Greafe frying ! Dorimam thou art intimate mth
My Lady, advife her^ for her own fake and the good
Company that comes hither, to burn Wax lights.

Har. What are thefe Mafquerades who ftand {o
Obfequioufly at a diftance ?

Sir Fof, A fet of Bulladins, whom I pick'd out of the beft
In France Sind brought over, with a Flutes deux or two,
My Servants •- they fhall entertain you.

Har. 1 had rather fee you dance your felf , Sir Foplin^..

Sir Fop. And I had rather do it — all the company
Knows it — bulMadam

Mecl. Come, come! noexcufes, Slip opting,.

Sir Fop. By Heav'ns

Med. Like a Woman I find you muft be flruggled with
Before one brings you what you defire.

Har. Can he dance? {Afide.

ff»?7. And fence and fing too, if you'll believe him.

Dor. He has no more excellence in his heels than in
His head. He went to Paris a plain bafhful Engliih Blockheadj
And is return'd a fine undertaking Fremh.Fopp. .

Med. I cannot prevail.

Sir Fop. Do not think it want of Complaifance, Madam. ,

Har, You are too well-bred to want that, Sir Fo/>/w^.
Ibelieveit want of power.

Sir Fop. By Heav'ns,and fo it is.
I have fat up fo damn'd late and drunk fo curs'd bard
Since I came to this lewd Town, that I am fit for,

Nothing



Nothing but low dancingnow, a Coranf, a Boree,

Or a Minnu^t : but St. Andre tells me, if I

Will but be regular, in one Month 1 (hall rife agen.

Pox on this Debauchery.. [^Endeavours a- a Caper,

Emit. I have heard your dancing much commended.

Sir Fop. It had the Fortune to pleafe in Paris,
I was judg'd to rife within an inch as high as the
Bafque in an Entry, I danc'd there,

Har.i am mightily taken with this Fool, let us fit :
Mere's a feat Sir F opting.

Sir Fop. At your feet, Madam ;
I can be no where fo much ateale : by your leave
Gown.

^^^/'^^[Ah! you'll fpoil it.

Sir Fep. No matter, my Cloaths are my Creatures.
I make 'em to make my Court to you Ladies, Hey — {JDnnce,
Qoon Commence to an Englifh Dancer Englifh Motions. I was

Forc'dto entertain this fellow, one of my ki mifcarrying .

Oh horrid ! leave your damn'd manner of dancing,
And put on the French Air : have you not a

Pattern before you

Pretty well ! imitation in time may bring him to fomething,
tAfter the Vance enter 0. Bellair, L. WoodviL
and L. Townley.

O, Bell. Hey a Dod ! what have we here, a mumming ?

L.JVood. Where's my Daughter Harriet.

Dor. Here, here. Madam !
I know not but under thefe difguifes there may be
Dangerous fparks^ I gave the young Lady warning !

L. Wood. Lord / I am fo oblig'd to you, Mv, Court age,

Har. Lord I how you admire this man !

X. Wood. What have you to except againfl: him ?

Har. He's a Fopp

L. Wood. He's not a Dorimant, a wild extravagant '
Fellow of the Times.

HJix, He's a man made up of forms and common places^
Suckt out of the remaining Lees of the Jafl: age.

L, Wood. He's fo good a man that were you notengag'd

h. Town. You'll have but little night to fleep in.

L, Wood, Lord ! 'tis per fed day

Dor, The hour is almoft come, I appointe I FeUinda,
And I am not fo^ foppilhly in love here to forget ; ZJjtde, .

Lam flefh and blood yet

L. Town,. .



Xl6)

X. Town. I am very fenfible. Madam.

L.Wood. Lord, Madam!

Har. Look, in what a ftruggle is my poor Mother yonder?

T. Bell. She has much ado to bring out the Complement ?

Dor. She {trains hard for it.

Har. See, fee ! her head tottering, her eyes ftairing,
And her under lip trembling-

2>or Now, now, (he's in the very convulfions of her
Civility. Zajtde.^ 'Sdeath, I Ihall lok Bellinda: I muft
Fright her hence 1 Ihe'il be an hour in
This fit of good manners elfe.
l^To L. Wood.'} Do you not know Sit Foplitig^ Madam ?

L. Wood. 1 have feen that Face— — Oh heav'n, - .

'Tis the fame we met in theMail, how came he here ?

Dor. A Fiddle in this Town is a kind of Fop-call -,
No fooner it ftrikes up, but the houfe is befieg'd
With an Army of Mafquerades ftraight.

L. Wood. Lord ! I tremble, Mr. Connate ! for certain
Dormant is in the company.

Dor. I cannot confidently fay he is not.
You had.befi: begon. I will wait upon you *, your
Daughter is in the hands of Mr. Bellair.

L. Wood. rU fee her before me. HaniePj come away.

r. Bell. Lights ! Lights !

L. Towj. Light down there.

D.Bell. ADod, it needs not

Dor. Call my Lady WoodviWs Coach to the Door, quickly.

O. BelL Stay, Mr. Medley^ let the young Fellows do
That duty \ we will drink a Glafs of Wine together.
'Tis good after dancing ! what mumming fpark is that ?

Med. He is not to be comprehended in few words.

Sir Fop. Hey ! La Tow^r.

Med. Whither away. Sir Fopling}

Sir Fop. I have bus'nels with Conrtage !■ -■■ . -

Med. He'll but put the Ladies into their Coach and
Comeupagen.

O. Bell. In the mean time I'll call for a Bottle. {_Bx, Old BelJ.
Enter Y. Bcllair.

Med. Where's Dormant /*

T. BelL Stoin home 1 he has had bufinefs waiting for
Him there all this night, I believe, by an
Impatience i obferv'd in him,

Med. Very likely, 'tis but diffembling Drunkennefs,
Railing at his friends, and the kind
Soul will embr ace the blefling, and forget The



( f 7 }

The tedious expe^ation.
Sir Fop, I muft fpeak with him before I fleep !
T. Bell, Emilia and I are refol vM on that bufinefs.
Me^. Peace, here's your Father.

Enter Old Bellair, and Butler with a "Bottle of Wine.
O. Bell. The Women are al! gone to bed.
Fill Boy ! Mr. Medley ^ begin a health.

Med. To Emilia. [WhifperSi

O. Bell. Out a pize ! (he's a rogue, and I'll not pledge you.
Med. I know you well.
O. Bell. A Dod, drink it then.
Sir Fop. Let us have the new Bachique.
O. BelL A Dod, that's a hard word !
What does it mean, Sir?
Med, A Catch, or drinking Song.
O. !S^//. Let us have it then.
Sir Fop. Fill the Glafles round, and
Draw up in a Body. Hey / Mufick /

They Sing.
The pleafnres of love and the joys of good Wine^
'"■ . 'To perfeB our happinefi wifely veejoyn.

We to Beauty all day _ '

Give the Soveraigfi fway.^
tAnd her favourite Nymphs devoutly obey.
j4t the Plays we are confiantly making our Courts
And when thty are ended we follow the Jport.
To the Mail and the Park^
Where we love till ^tis darkj^
Then (parkling Champaigne,
Puts an end to their reign j
It quickly recover Sy
Poor langhijhing Lovers,

Makes usfrollick and gay ^ and drowns allonr Sorrow :
But alas ! we relapfe again on the Morrow^
Let every man fh and ,
With his Glaf in his hand :
And briskly difcharge at the word 0/ Commando ■
Here's a health to all thofe.
Whom to night we depofe.
Wine and Beauty by turns great fouls fljall infpire.

Prefent all together \ and now boys give fire-

G. Bell. A Dod, a pretty bus'nefs and very merry.
Sir Fop. Hark you, Medley^ let you and I take the
Fiddles, and go sv^qr Dorimant,

Mgd.\



(58)

Med. We (hall do him a courtefy, if it be as I guefs.
For after the fatigue of this night, he'll quickly
Have his belly full •, and be glad of an occafion
To cry, takeaway. Handy.

T. Bell, ril go with you, and there we'll confolt
About affairs, ^f^/tf)'.

O, Bell, looks on his rvatch.^ A Dod, 'tis fix a Clock.

Sir Fop. Let's away then,

O. Bell. Mr. Medley., my Sifter tells me you are an
Honeftman. And a Dod I love you.
Few words and hearty, that's the way
With old Harry^ old Harry.

Sir Fop. Light your Flambeux. Hey.

O.Bell. What does the man mean?

Med. 'Tis day, Sir Foplw£,

SkFop. No matter^
Our Serenade will look the greater. {^Ex.omnes^

SCENE II.

Dorimant's Lodgings aTable^ a Candle, aToilef^Szc,
HsLudytjiifigHp Lmfjeff,

Snter Dorimant in hi^ Govpn^ and Bellinda.

'Dor. Why will you be gone fo foon ?

Bell. Why did you ftay out fo late ?

'Dor. Call la Chair, Handy ! what makes you tremble fo ?

Bell. I have a thoufand fears about me :
Have I not been feen think you ?

Vor. By no body but my felf and trully Handy.

Bell, Where are all your people ?

2)<>r. I have difperft 'em on fleevelefs Erradns.
What does that figh mean ?

Bell. Can you be fo unkind to ask me ?- — ^ well— — . £Si£hf.
Were it to do again^

Dor. We (hould do it, Ihould we not ?

Bell. I think we fhould : the wickeder man you to make
Me love fo well— will you be difcreet now ?

Dor, I will

Bell. You cannot.

Dor. Never doubt it.

Bell. I will not exped it.

Dor, You do me wrong.

Belt.



il9)

Bell. You have no more power to keep the fecret.
Than I had not to truft you with it.

Dor. By all the Joys I have had, and thofe you
Keep in flore

BelL You'll do for ray fake what you never did before-

Dor. By that truth thou haft fpoken, a wife Ihall
Sooner betray her felf to her husband —

Bell. Yet I had rather you fhould be falfe in this
Than in another thing you promisM me.

Dor. What's that?

Bell* That you would never fee Loveit more but in
Publick places, in the Park, at Court and Playes.

Dor. 'Tis not likely a man fhould be fond of feeing a
DamnM old Play when there is a new one adted.

'BelL I dare not truft your promife.

Dor. You may ~

BelL This does not fatisfy me.
You fhall fwear you never will fee her more.

Dor, I will ! a thoufand oaths by all



'Bell. Hold you fhall not, now I think on't better.

Dor. I will fwear

Bell. I fhall grow jealous of the Oath, and think
I owe your truth to that, not to your love.

Dor. Then,.by my love ! no other Oath Til fwear.
Enter Handy.

Hand. Here's a Chair.

'Bell. Let me go.

Dor. I cannot.

Bell. Too willingly I fear.

Dor. Too unkindly fear'd.
When will you promife me again .?

Bell. Not this fortnight.

Dor, You will be better than your word.

'Bell. 1 think I (hall.
Will it not make you love me lefs ? iStarting.

Heark ! what Fiddles are thefe ? twiddles without.

'Dor. Look out. Handy ! {6x. Handy, and returns.

Hand. Mr. Medley^ Mr. Sellair,2LXidi Sit Foiling,
They are coming up.

Dor. How got they in .?

Hand. The door was open for the Chair.

Bell. Lord / let me fly

Dor. Here, here, down the back ftairs.

I'll fee you into your Chair.

' I Bell,



(6o)

Bell. No, no / ftay and receive 'em : and be fure you
Keep your word, and never fee Lovek more.
L.t it be a proof of your kindnefs.

'Dor. It (hall — Handy, 6'mCt her.
Everlafting iove go along with thee. L^ifrng her hand.

lEx. Bellinda ^«^ Handy.
Enter Toung Bellair, Medley, and Sir Fopling,

r. Bell. Not a bed yet !

Med, You have had an irregular Fif, Dorimant.

Dor. I have.

r. 3^//. And is it ofTalready >

"Dor. Nature has done her part, Gentlemen,
When fhe falls kindly to work, great Cures
Are efFeded in little time, you know.

Sir Fop. We thought there was a Wench in the Cafe, bj-
The Chair that waited. Prithee make us a Confidence.

'Dor. Excufe me.
. Sir Fop. Le fage, Dormant was Ihe pretty ?

Dor. So pretty fhe may come to keep her Coach and pay
Parifn Duties if the good numour of the age continue.

A'ted. And be of the number of the Ladies kept by
Publick fpirited men for the good of the whole Town.

Sir Fop. Well faid, Medley.

{Sir Fopling dancing by himfelf.

T,.BelL See Sir Fi'/j/zV?^ dancing.

Dor, You are pradifing and have a mind to recover I fee„

Sir Fop. Prithee Dorimant ! why bafl not thou a glafs
Hung up here ? a Room is the dulleft thing without one !

T. BelL Here is Company to entertain you.

Sir Fop. But I mean in cafe of being alone, .

In a glafs a man may entertain himfelf

Dor. The fhadow of himlelf indeed.

Sir Fop. Corred the Errours of his motions and
Hisdrefs.

Med. I find Sir Fopling in your Solitude, you remember
Th^ faying of the wife man, and ftudy your felf.

Sir l^op. 'Tis the belt diverfion in ou-r retirements.
Dorimant^ thou art a pretty fellow, and wear'ft thy cloaths
Vv ell, but I never faw thee have a handforaeCrevat.
Were they made up like mine, they'd give another
Aire to thy face. Prithee let me fend my man
To drefs thee but one day. By Heav'ns an
Engiiih man cannot tye a Ribbon.

Dor, They are fomething cliimry fifted< — —

S'l^Fof.



i6i)

Sir Fop, I have brought over the prettiefl fellow that
Ever fpread a Toilet, he ferv'd fome time under
Merille the greateft Genie in the world for a
Valet d' Chambre.

Dor. What, he who formerly belong'd to the
Duke of Candde ?
Sir Fof, The fame, and got him his immortal reputation. _
Dor. Y'have a very fine Brandenburgh on Sir Foiling,
Sir Fop. It ferves to wrap me up, after the Fatigue of a Ball.
Med. I fee you often in it, with your Pcrriwig ty'd up.
Sir Fop. We fhould not always be in a fet drefs, 'tis more
En Cavalier to appear now and then in a diflabille6.
Med. Pray how goes your bufinefs with L<?v«> .^
Sir Fop. You might have anfwer'd your felf in the Mail
Lafl: night. Dormant ! did you not fee the advances
She made me? I have been endeavouring at a fong 1
Dor. Already !

S^Fop, 'Tis my CoupM Eflay in Englifti,-
I would fain have thy opinion of it.
Dor. Let's fee it.

Sir Fop. Hey Page give me my fong -Bellair^

Here, thou haft a pretty voice, fing it.
r.Bell. Sing it your felf, Sir F«'/'ft«^,
SirFtfp. Excufeme.
r. "Bell. You learnt to fing in Paris.
Sir Fop, I did of Lambert^ the greateft mafter
In the world : but I have his own fault, a weak voice,
And care not to fing out of a ru^l.
Dor, A ru^l is a pretty Cage for a finging Fop indeed.
Y.h^VidSi reads the Song,
Hovf charming Phillis ^, how fair !

Ah that (he were as willing
To eafe my wounded heart of Care,

And make her Eyes lefs killing.
Jfigh ! I (igh ! JUnguifl} now.

And Love will not let me refi,
I drive about the Parky and bow
Still as I meet my dearefi.
Sir Fop. Sing it, fing it man, it goes to a pretty new
Tune which I am confident was made by 'Baptifi.
Med. Sing it your felf, Sir FopUngy he does not know the Tune.
SirF<7/?. I'll venture. C^^V Foplingy/«g/.

Dor. Ay marry 1 now 'tis fomething. I fhall not
Flatter you, Sir ^opling^ there is not much thought in't,

I a . But



i6i)

But 'is paffionate aad well turn'd.
!^ Med, After the French way.

SirFop. That I aim'd at does it not give

You a lively Image fif the thing ?

Slap down goes the Glafs, and thus we are at it.

Dor. H does indeed, I perceive, Sir Fo/>//»^,
You'll be t he very head of the Sparks, who are lucky
In Compofitions of this nature. '

£»ffr 5/> Fopling'j Footman*.

Sir Ftfp. La Tower , is the Bath ready ?

Footm. Yes, Sir,

Sir Fof, Adieu, don Mes cheres. [Ex. Sir FofUng,

Med. When have you your revenge on Loveit, Dormant ?

Dor, I will but change my Linnen, and about it,

Med, The powerful confiderations which hinder'd
Have bin removM then.

'Dor. Moft luckily this morning, you muft along
With me, my reputation lyes at ftake there.

Med. I am engagM to Bellak.

Dor. What's your bufinefs.

iW<?^, Ma-tri-mony an't like you.

Dor. It does not, Sir. . ■ -

T, BelL It may in time. Dormant .^ what
Think you of Mrs. Harriet ?

Dor. What does (he think of me ?

T.Bell. I am confident (he loves you.

Dor. How does it appear ?

T, 'Bell. Why, Ihe's never well but when (he's talking
Of you, bat then (he finds all the faults in you Ihe can.:
She laughs at all who commend you, but
Then fee fpeaks ill of all who do not.

Dor. Women of her temper betray themfelves, by
Their over cunning. 1 had once a growing love with a.
Lady, who would always quarrel with me, when
1 came to fee her, and yet was never quiet if
I ftay'd a day from her.

T, Bell. My F«ither is in love with Emilia.

Dor. That is a good warrant for yonr proceedings,
Go on and profper, I muft to Loveit.
ty^edley, I am forry you cannot be a witnefs.

A^ed. Make her meet Sir Fopling again in the fame pkce^
i|.nd ufe him ill before me.

Dor. That may be brought about I think,
I'll be at your Aunts anon,, and give you Joy, Mr. Bellair,

T^'BeiL



(6i)

Y. Bell. You had not befl: think of Mrs. Harriet too much,
Without Church fecurity there's no taking up there.
Dor* I may fall into the Snare too. But — -
The vfife will find a difference in our Fate^
Ton wed a Woman^ 1 a good Efiate. VE^ceHnt

SCENE III.
Enter the Chair with Bellinda, the menfet it
down and open it » Bellinda/^rr???^.
Bellinda C Lord ! where am I ? in the Mail ?
Jiirfriz^d\ Whither have you brought me ?
I Chairnt. You gave us no diredions, Madam ?
Bell. The fright I was in made me forget it. ^Afide.

I Chairm, We ufe to carry a Lady from the Squires hither^
5<r//. This is Lox/«f, lam undone if {he fees me. - ^Afide,.
Quickly, carry me away

I Chairnt. Whither, an't like your Honour I
Bell. Ask no queftions— — .

Enter hov^\€s Footman.
footm. Have you feen my Lady, Madam ?
Bell. I am juft come to wait uppn her-



Footm. She will be glad to fee you, Madam,
She fent me to you this morning, to defire your Company,
And I was told you went out by five a Clock.

'Bell. More and more unlucky! [_Afide,

Footm. Will you walk in, Madam ?

BelL ril difcharge my Chair and follow, \^Ex. Footm.

Tell your Mrs. I am here, {Gives the Chairmen money.

Take this ! and if ever you fliould be examined, be fure you
Say , you took me up in the Strand., over againft the
Exchange^ as you will anfwer it to Mr, Dorimant.

Chairmen. We will an't like your Honour. {Ex.. Chairmen.

'BelU Now to come off, I muft on

I^ confidence and Lies fome hope is left '■,

'Twere hard to befannd out in the firji- Theft. ZExlt.



A C T V.

Enter Mijiref Loveit, and Pert kr Wo/nm.
Pert. TTyTEL L ! in my eyes Sir Fopling is nofuch
VV Defpicable perfon.
Lov. You are an excellent Judge..
Pert^ He's as handfeme a man as. Mr. Dorimant^^



(64)

And as great a Gallant.

Lov. Intollerable! is'tnotenoughl fubmittohis
Impertinences, butmuft 1 be plagu'd with yours too?

Pert. Indeed, Madam.

Lov.. 'Tisfalfe, mercenary malice . {_Enter her footmav^.

Footm. Mrs. Bellinda^ Madam- ■

Lov. What of her?

Footm. She's below.

Lov. How came (he?

Footm. In a Chair, ambling /i/^ry)^ brought her.

Lov, He bring her ! his Chair ftands near Dorimanth
Door^ and always brings me from thence — -run and
Ask him where he took her up ; go, there is no truth
In friendlhip neither. Women, as well as men,
AH are falfe, or all are (b to me at Icaft.

Pert. You are jealous of her too ?

Zo-y. You had beft tell her lam.
Twill become the

Liberty you take of late. This fellows bringing of her.
Her going out by five a Clock-r —
I know not wliat to think.

£»f^r Bellinda.
"Bellinda^ you are grown an early Rifer, I hear !

Bell. Do you not wonder my Dear,
What made me abroad fo foon ?

Lov. You do not ufe to be ^o.

Bell. The Countrey Gentlewomen I told you of ('Lord !
They have the oddell diverfions ! ) would never
Let me reft till I promis'd to go with them
To the Markets this morning to eat
Fruit and buy Nofegays. ••

Lov. Are they fo fond of a filthy Nofegay ?

Bell, They complain of the ftinks of the Town, and are
Never well but when they have their nofes in one.

Lov. There are Eflences and fweet waters.

^e//. O they cry out upon perfomes they are -
Un wholefome, one of 'em was falling into a fit
Withthe fnielj of thefenarolii,

Lov. Methinks in Complaifance
You (hou'd have had a Nofegay too.

Bell. Do you think, my Dear, I could be fo loathfome
To trick my ieif up with Carnations and flock- . / f
Gi'Iy-fiowers ? I begg'd their pardon and'-' -•' ', - J ¥ \
Toidt^ em I never wore any thing but Orange-
F owers awd luberofe. That which made me Willing



Willing to go, was, a ftrange defire 1 had
To eat feme frefli Ncftaren's.
Lov. And had you any?
^e//. The beiU ever tailed.
hov. Whence carae you now ?
Bell. From their lodgings, where I crowded out of a
Coach, and took a Chair to come and f^e you,my Dear.
Lov. Whither did you fend for that Chair ?
Bell 'Twas going by empty. ,
Lov, Where do thefe Country Gentlewomen
Lodge I pray ?
BelL in the Strandov^x againftthe Exchange.
Fert. That place is never without a Nell: of 'em,
They are always as one goes by flcaring in
Balconies or (lairing out of Windows.
Enter Footman.
Lov. £To the Footm.~\ Come hither. [Whifpers.

Bell,/4Jide.2 This fellow by her order has been
Queftioning the Chairmen ! I threatn'd 'em
With the name of Dorimant^ if they Ihould
Have told truth I am loft for ever.
Lov. In the Strand faid you?

Footm. Yes Madam, over againft the Exchange. XJ^x, Footm,.
Lov.' She's innocent and I am much to blame.
Bell. Afide.'X I am fo frighted, my countenance
Will betray me.
Lov. Bellinda ! what makes you look fo pale ?
Bell. Want of my ufual Reft, and jolting up and
Down fo long in an odious Hackney. CFootman returns,

Footm. Madam ! Mr. Dormant 1
Lov, What makes him hert ?
Bell. J fide.*} Then I am betray 'd indeed,
H'has broke his word, and I love a man that does
Not care for me
Lov. Lord ! you faint, Bellinda !

Belt. I think I fhall ! luch an oppreflion here on the fudden,
Tert. She has eaten too much fruit I warrant you,
Lov. Not unlikely!

Pert, 'Tis thatjyes heavy on her Stomach.
Lov. Have her into my Chamber, give her fom^
Surfeit Water, and let her ly down a little.

Pert. Come, Madam! 1 was a ftrange devourer
Of fruit when I was young,

So ravenous. LEx. Bello and?m leading her off.

Loveit, .



(66)

Lov. Oh that my Love would be but calm a while!
That 1 might receive this man with all the Scorn
And indignation he deferves.

Enter Dorimant.

"Dor, Now for a touch of Sir Foplmg to begin with.
Hey — Page — Give pofitive order that none of my

People ftir— Let the Canaile wait as they fhould do-

Since noife and nonfence have fuch powerful charms,
1 that 1 may fmce^ful proWy
Transform my [elf to what you love*

Lov. If that would do, you need not change from
What you are, you can be vain and lowd enough.

Dor. But not with fo good a grace as Sir Foplmg.
Hey, Hampfhire — ^Oh — that found, that found
Becomes the mouth of a man of Quality.

Lov. Is there a thing fo hateful as a fencclefs Mirnick ?

Dor. He's a great grievance indeed to all who like
Your felf, Madam, love to play the fool in quiet.

Lov. Aridiculous Animal, who has more of
The Ape, than the Ape has of the man in him.

Dor. I have as mean an opinion of a Sheer-
Mimick as your felf, yet were he all Ape,
1 fhould prefer him to the Gay, the Giddy,
Brisk inHpid Noify fool you doat on.

Lov. Thofe Noify fools, however you defpife 'em.
Have good qualities, which weigh more (ot ought
At kail) with us Women, than all the pernicious
Wit yoQ have to boafl of.

Dor. That I may hereafter have a juft value for their
Merit, pray do me the ftvour to name 'em.

Lov. You'J defpife 'em as the dull effedts of
Ignorance and Vanity ! yet 1 care not if I mention fome.
Firft, they really admire us, while you at beft but
Flatter us well.

Dor. Take heed ! Fools can drfTemble too

Lov. They may ! but not fo artificially as you.- —
There is no fear they fhould deceive us ! Then they
Are aifiduous, Sir, they are ever offering us their fer vice,
And always waiting on our will .

Dor. You owe tiiat to their exceffive idleneft !
They know not how to entertain themfelves at home.
And find Co little welcome abroad, they are fain to
Fly to you who countenance 'em as a refuge againft the
Solitude they would be otherwife condemn'd to.

Lov



(67)

Lov. Their converfation too diverts us better.

Dor. Playing with your Fan, fmelling to your Gloves
Commending your Hair, and taking notice how 'ds
Cut and (haded after the new way-

Lov, Were it fillier than you can make it, you mufl;
Allow 'tis pleafanter to laugh at others, than to be iaugh'd at
Our felvcs, though never fo wittily. Then, though they
Want skill to flatter us, they flatter themfelves
So well, they fave us the labour ! we need not take
That care and pains to fatisfie 'em of our Love,
Which we fo often \o^^ on you.

I>or. They commonly indeed believe too well of
Themfelves, and always better of you than you deferve.

Lov. You are in the right, they have an implicit
Faith in us, which keeps 'em from prying narrowly into
Our fecrets, and faves us the vexatious trouble of
Clearing doubts which your fubtle and caufelefs
Jealoufies every moment raife.

Dor. There is an inbred falftiood in Women, which
Inclines 'em ftill to them, whom they may mod eafily deceive.

Lov. The man who loves above his quality.
Does not fuffer more from the infolent impertinence of
His Miftrefs, than the Woman who loves above her
Underftanding, does from the arrogant prefumpcions
Of her Friend.

Dor. You miflake the ufe of fools, they are defign'd for
Properties and not for Friends, you have an indifferent
Stock of reputation left yet. Lofe it all like a frank
Gamefter on the Square, 'twill then be time enough
To turn Rook, and cheat it up again on a
Good Subftantial Bubble.

Lov. The old and the ill-favourM are only fit for
Properties indeed, but Young and Handfome
Fools have met with kinder fortunes.

Dor. They have, to the fhame of your fex be it fpoken,
'Twas this, the thought of this made me by a timely
Jealoufy, endeavour to prevent the good fortune you
Are providing for Sir Foplmg
But againfl: a Womans frailty all our care is vain.

Lov. Had I not with a dear experience bought the
Knowledge of your falftibod, you might have fool'd
Mc yet.* This is not the firft Jealoufy you have
Feign'd to makea quarrel with me, and get a week ^^ ^iJ K^^'^ ^^**'
To throw away on fomefiich unknown inconfiderable : - -^

K SH



Slut, as you have been lately lurking with at Plays.

Dor. Women, when they would break off with a man;
Ne'er want th'addrefs to turn the fault on him.

Lov. You take a pride of late in ufing of me ill, that
The Town may know the power you have over me.
Which now (as unreafonably as your felf j expedls
ThatI f do me all the injuries you can) mufl; love you ftill.

Dor, I am fo far from expecting that you fhould,
I begin to think* you never did love me.

Lov. Would the memory of it were fo wliolly worn
Out in me, that I did doubt it too ! what made you
Come to diflurb my growing quiet ?

Dor. To give you Joy of your growing infamy

Lov, Infupportable ! infulting Devil/ this from you,
The only Author oi my Ihame ! this from another
Had been but Juftice, but from you 'tis-abellifti and.
Inhumane outrage. What have I doner?

'Dor, A thing thatputs you below my fcorn, atid
Makes my anger as ridiculous as you have made my Love.

Lov. I walk'd lalt night with Sir Fofling.

Dor. You did, Madam, and you talkt and laught aloud

Ha, ha, ha Oh that laugh, that laugh becomes

The confidence of a Woman of Quality.

Lov. You who have more picafure in the ruine of a
Womans reputation, than in the indearments of her love,
Reproach me not with your felf, and I defy you to name
The man can lay a blenailh on my fame

Dor. To be feen publickly fo tranfported with the
Vain follies of that notorious Fop, to me is an infamy
Below the fin of proflitution with another man.

Lov. Rail on, I am fatisfy'd in the Jufl;ice of what
i did, you had provok'd me to't.

Dor. What I did was the effed of a paflion, whofe
Extravagancies yotPhave been willing to forgive.

Lov. And wha€ I did was the effect of a paflion ■
You may forgive if you think fit^

Dor. Are you fo indifferent grown?, Lov. lam.

Dor. Nay ! then 'tistime to-part. I'll fend you back your,
Letters you have fo often askt for .*
I have two or three of 'em about me,

Lov. Give 'em me.

Dor, You fnatch as if you thought I would Hot — -there — -
And may the Perjuf ies in 'em be mine, if e'r I fee you more.

Lov. Stay I. w/opik tPfferit9gOy fiis.catcheshm.

■ V ' .. Dor,



(6p)






Day. I will not.
Zov. Youfhall.
Dor, What have you to fay?
Lov, I cannot fpeak it yet.
Dor. Something more in Commendation of the fooJ.
Death / 1 want patience, let me go.

Lov. I cannot.
I can fooner part with the limbs that hold him. [_^(ick,

I hate that naufeous fool, you know I<lo»
Vor. Was it the fcandal you were fond of then ?
Lov. Y'had raisM my anger equal to my love, a thing

You ne're could do before, and in revenge I did

I know not what 1 did: Would you would

Not think on't any more.

Dor, Should I be willing to forget it, I fliall be daily
Minded of it, 'twill be a common place for all the
Town to laugh at me, and MedUyy when he is Rhetorically
Drunk, will ever be declaiming on it in my ears.
Lov. 'Twill be believ'd a jealous fpite ! Come, forget it."
Dor, Let me confult my reputation,yov are to carelefs of it.
JiPaHfes~\ You ihall meet Sir Foflmg in the Mail again to night.
Lov. What mean you .^

Dor, I have thought on't, and you mull. 'Tis neceflary to
Juftify my love to the world : you can handle a Coxcomb
As he deferves, when you are not out of humour. Madam !
Lov. Publick fatisfa(n:ion for the wrong I have done you !
This is fome new device to make me more ridiculous /
Dor. Hear n^ !
Lov, I will not!
Dor. You will be perfwaded.
Lov, Never.

Dor, Aie you fo obffcinate ?
Lov. Areyou fbbafe?
Dor. You will not fatisfie my love ?
Lov. I would die to fatisfy that,but I will not,to fave you from
A thpufand racks, do a Ihamelefs thing to pleafe your vanity.
Dor, Farewel falfe woman.
Lov, Do! go!

Dor, You will call me back again.
Lov. Exquifite fiend ! I knew you came but to torment me.

Enter Bellinda and Pert.
Dor. fnr prized"} Belltnda here !
Bell. Afide.'} He ftaits ! and looks pale, the fight
Of me has toucht his guilty Soul.
• . K 2 Tin.



(70)

PtrK 'Twas but a qualm as I faid, a little indi%efl:ion|
The Surfeit- Water did it, Madam,
Mixt with a little Mirabilis.

Dor. I am confounded / and cannot guefs how (he came hither !

Lov, 'Tis your fortune Bellinda ever to be here,
When I am abus'd by this prodigy of ill nature.

Bell. lamamaz'dtofindhimhere!
How has he the face to come near you >

Dor. Afide.'} Here is fine work towards !
I never was at fuch a lofs before.

Bell, One who makes a publick profeffion of breach of
Faith and Ingratitude .' I loath the fight of him^

"Dor. There is no remedy, I mufl; fubmit to their Tongues
Now, and fome other time bring my felf off as well as I can.

BelL Other men are wicked, but then they have fome
Senfe of (hame ! he is never well but when he triumphs,
Nay / glories to a Woraans face in his Villanies.

Lov. You are in the right, Bellinda^ but methinks
Your kindnefs for me makes you concern your
SeJf too much with hirff.

Bell. It does indeed, my Dear!
His barbarous carriage to you yefterday, made me hope
You ne're would fee him more, and the very next day
To find him again, provokes me ftrangely :
But becaufe I know you love hira, I have done.

T>or. You havereproachtmehandfomeiy, and I
Deferve it for coming hither, but-;^

Pert. You mull exped it, Sir I all Women will hate
You, for my Ladies fake 1 *

"Dor. Nay if fhe begins too, 'tis time to fly! Ifhall be
Scolded to death elfe. {^Jftde to Bellinda*

I am to blame in fome circumftances, I confefs ^ but as to
The Main,,I am not fo guilty as you imagine.
I Ihall feek a more convenient time to clear my felf.

Lov. Do it now! what impediments are here?

Dor. 1 want time, and you want temper.

Lov. Thefe are weak pretences !

Dor. You were never more miftaken in your life.
And fo fare wel. X.I^»rmant fiingi off.

Lov. Call a Footman! P^y^ ! quickly,
I will have hira dogg'd,

Fert. I wifli you would not for my quiet and your own.

Lov. I'll find out the infamous caufe of all
Oar quarrels, pluck her Maskoffj and expofe her

Bare-fac^d



(71)

Bare-fac'dto the world.

SeU. Let me but efcape this time, I'll never ^ /jGde.

Venture more.

Lov, Bellinda ! you (hall go with me.

'Bell. I have fuch a heavinefs hangs on me with what
I did this morning, I wouM fain go home
And fleep, my Dear.

Lov, Death ! and eternal darknels. I fhal 1 never
Sleep again. Raging Feavours feize the world, and make
Mankind as reftlefs all as I am. [^.v. Loveir.

Bell. I knew him falfe and helped to make him fo ?
Was not her ruine enough to fright me from the danger ?
It fhould have been, but love can take no warning. {Exl Bell,

SCENE 11. Lady Townteys Houfe..

Enter Medley, Young Bellair, Lady Townley,
Emilia <^/;<^ ChaplaiQ.

Med. Bear up, Bellair y and do not let us fee that
Repentance in thine, we daily do in married faces.

L. Towff, This Wedding willftrangelyfurprize
My Brother, when he knows it.

Med. Your Nephew ought to conceal it for a time,
Madam, fince Marriage has loll its good name, prudent
Men feldom expofe their own reputations till 'tis
Convenient to juftify their Wives,

Old Bell. {jvithonQ where are you all there?
Out, a Dod, will no body hear .?

L. Towt!o My Brother, quickly Mr. Smirkjt into this Clofet,
You muft not be feen yet. {jGoes mo the Clojetl .

SnterOXdi Bellair ^»^ L. Townley'^ Page.

O, Bell. Defire Mr. Fnrb to walk into the lower Parlor,

I will be with him prefently Where have you

Been, Sir, you cou'd not wait on me to day ? {To T, BelL .

T^Bell. About a bufinefs.

O, Bell. Are you fo good at bufinefs ? a Dod, I
Have a bufinefs too, you (hall difpatch out of hani, Sir.
Send for a Parfon, Sifter •, my Lady Woodvill and
Her Daughter are coming.

L. Totv». What need you huddle up things thus?

Oo Bell. Out a pife, youth is apt to play the fool,
And 'tis not good it fhould be in their power.

L, Towm You need notfear your Sou* >

O.BelL^



O. 'Bell. H'has been idling this morning, and a-Dod I do
Not like him. How doft thou do, Sweet-heart f . {To EmiUai

Smil, You are very fevere, Sir, marri'd in fuch hafle !

O. BelLGo too, thou art a rogue,and I will talk with thee anon.
Here's my Lady Woodvili come. {^Enter L. WoodviU, Harriefi
Welcome, Madame Mr. F«r&'s C^»^Bufy.

Below with the Writings.

L. Wood, Let us down and make an end then.

O, Bell. Sifter, (hew the way. {.To Y. BelL who U tdMing

Harry ^ your bufinefs lyes not there yet ! \jo Harriet.

Excufe him till we have d^nCjLady, and then, a Dod,
He (hall be for thee. Mr. Medley^ we mult
Trouble you to be a witnels.

Med. I luckily came for that purpofe. Sir.
SiEx. O. Bdl. Medley, Y. Bell. L. Townley and L. Woodvili.

Bnfy. What Will you do. Madam ?

Har. Be carried back and mew'd up in the Countrey agen.
Run away here, any thing, rather than be married to a
Man I do not care for Dear Emilia^ do thou advife me !

EmiL Mr. Bellair is engag'd you know.

Har. I do , but know noDiwhat the fear of lodng an
Eftate may fright him to.

Emil. In the defp'rate condition you are in, you(houId
Confult with fome judicious man \ what think you of
Mr. Dorimant ?

Har. I do not think of him at all.

Bufy, She thinks of nothing elfe I am fure ..

EmiL How fond your Mother was of Mr. G»«rf<i^f! - .

Har. Becaufe I contrived the miftake to make a little
Mirth, you believe I like the man.

€mil. Mr. Bellair believes you love him.

Har. Men are feldome in the right when they guefs at a
Womans mind •, would (he, whom he loves, lov'd him no better.

Bujy. Aftde ] That's e'n well enough on all confcience.

.EmiU Mr. Dormant has a great deal of wit.

Har. And takes a great deal of pains to (hew it.

Emil. He's extreamly well fafhion'd.

Har. Affededly grave, or ridiculoufly wild and apilh,

Bufy. You defend him flill againft your Mother.

Har. I would not were he juftly ralli'd, but
I cannot hear any one undefervedly raiPd at.

Emil, Has your woman learnt the Song you
Were fo taken with >

Har. I was fond of a new thing, 'tis dull at fecond hearing.

EmiU



(7?)

€mil. Mr. "Dorimant made it.
Bufy. She knows it. Madam, and has made me firg
It at leafl a dozen times this morning.
Har, Thy tongue is as impertinent as thy fingers.
Emil. You have provok'J her.
Bnfy, 'Tis but finging the Song and I ihaJI appeafe her^
* Emtl. Prithee do.

Har. She has a voice will grate your ears worfe than a
Cat call, and drefles To ill, flie's fcarce fit to tricK up a
Yeomans Daughter on a Holyday.

Bafy fings.
Song by a^^ Amoret w>/rPhillis/^/f,
Sir C, S. Qfig £>Der}ing on the Plain,

tyfndfarv the charming Strephon wait

To tell the Nym-ph his fain.
The threatning danger to remove ,

She whifper'd in her Ear-,
j^ Fhillis, if yoH xvonld not love.

This Shepherd do not hear.
None ever hadfojirange an Art

His pajfion to convey
Into a liftning Virgins heart

ty^nd fteal her SohI away. i

Fly, fly betimes^ for fear you give

Occafton for your Fate,
In vain faid jhcj in vain I firiV9,
AlafS ! ^tis now too late.

Enter Dorimant,
Dor. Mnfick,fo foftens and difarms the mind.
Har. That not one Arrow does refinance (ind. ^

"Bor. Let us make ufe of the lucky Minute then^
Har. Afide turning pom Dorimant.l My love fprings with^
My blood into my face, I dare not look upon him yet.
Dor. What have we here, the pidure of celebrated
Beauty, giving Audience in publickto a declared Lover ?

Har^ Play the dying Fopp, and make the
Piece compleat, Sir.
Dcr. What think you if the Hint were well Improv'd?

The whole myftery of making love pleafantly defign'd,.
And wrought in a Suit of Hangings ?

Har. 'Twere needlefs to execute fools in Effigie, who
Sufl^r daily in their own perfons,

1>or, To EmWi^ afide. ';\ Mrs. Bride, for fuch I know>
This happy day has made yo\»/



(74)

Ewi/. Defer the formal joy you are to give me,

And mind your bufinefs with. her—

\^JloHd'] Here are dreadful preparations, Mr. Dorimmt^
Writings fealiog, and a Paiibn fent for

Dor, To marry this Lady.

Bufy. Gondemn'd Oie is, and what will become of her
1 know nor, without you generoufly engage in a Refcue, •

Dor, In this fad condition, Madam, 1 candosolefs
Than offer you my Service.

Har. The obligation is not great, you are the common
Sanduary for all young Women who run from their Relations.

Dcr. 1 have always my arms open to receive the
Diftrefled. But I will open my heart and receive you,
Where none yet did ever enter— — You have filFd it
With a fecret, might I but let you know it-

Har, Do not fpeak it, if you would have me believe it ;
Your Tongue is fo fam'd for fallhood, 'twill do the
Truth an injury. {Turns away her head.

Dor. Turn not away then, but look on me and guefs it.

Har. Did you not tell me there ^was no credit to be given to
Faces ? that Women now adays have their paffions as
Much at will, as they have their Complexions, and
Put on joy and fadnefs, fcorn and kindneft, with the

■Same eafe they do their Paint and Patches

Are they the only counterfeits ?

Dor. You wrong your own, while you fufpeift my Eyes,
By all th^ hope I have in you, the inimitable
Colour in your cheeks is not more free from
Art, than are the fighs I offer.

Har. In men who have been long hardn'd in Sin,
We have reafon to miftruft the firfl figns of repentance.

D^y. The profped of fuch a Heav'n will make me
Perfevere, and give you marks that are infallible.

Har. What are thbfe ?

'Dor. I will renounce all the joys I have in friendfliip
And in Wine, facrifice to you all the intereft
I have in other Women .

Har. Hold — Though I wilh you devout,

I would not have you turn Fanatick. Could you

Negled thefe a while and make a journey into the Countrey ?

Dor, To be with you I could live there :
And never fejid one thought to London,

Har. What eV e you fay, 1 know all beyond
High Park'*s a defart to you, and that no Gallantry
Can draw you farther. Dor.



(75)

Dor. That has been the utmoft limit of my Love

But now my paflion knows no boundsj and
There's no meafure to be taken of what Til do
For you, from any thing I ever did before.

Har. When I hear you talk thus in Hampjhirej
I (hall begin to think there may be fome truth inlarg'd upon. .

Dor. Is this all will you not promife me —

Har. I hate to promife ! 'what we do then is expeded from
Us, and wants much of the welcome it finds, when it furprizes.
Dor, May I not hope ?

Har. That depends on you, and not on me, and
'Tis to no purpofe to forbid it. \Yurns to Bufy.

Biify, Faith, Madam, now I perceive the Gentleman
Loves you too, e'en let him know your mind, and
Torment your felves no longer.

Har. Doft think I have no fenfe of Modefty ?

'Bhfy* Think, if you lofe this, you may never
Have another opportunity.

Har. May he hate me, fa curfe that frights me
When I fpeak it ! ) if ever I do a thing againft the
Rules of decency and honour.

Dor. {To £milia.'\ I am beholding to you
For your good intentions, Madam.

Emit. 1 thought the concealing of our Marriage
From her, might have done you better Service.

1>or, TryheragaiU'

Emit. What have you refolv'd. Madam?
The time draws near.

Har. To be obftinate and protefl; againft this Marriage.
Enter L. Townley in hafie.

L, Town, [To Emilia.~\ Quickly, quickly, let Mr. Smtrh^
Out of the Clofet. QSmirk comes out of the Clofet.

Har. A Parfon ! had you laid him in here ?

Dor. I knew nothing of him, '

Har. Should it appear you did, your opinion
Of my eafinefs may coft you dear.

Enter O. Bellair, Y. Bellair, Medley, and L. Woodvill.

O. Bell. Out a pife / the Cononical hour is almolt paft^
Sifter, is the man of God come ?

L. Town. He waits your leifure

O. Bell. By your favour, Sir. A Dod, a pretty fpruce fellow !
What may we call him ?

L. Town. Mr. Smirk^l my Lady Bi^ot^s Chaplain.

O. BeS, A wife woman ! a t)od fhe is.

L The



(76)

The man will ferve for the flelfe as well as the fpirit
pleafe you, Sir, to commiirion a young Couple to go to
Bed together a Gods name ? — *— Harry.

r.Bell. Here, Sir

O. 'Bell, Out a pife, without your miftrefs in your hand t

Smirkf^ Is this the Gentleman ?

O. BelL yes, Sir /

5w;ri^ Are you not miftaken, Sir ?

O.BelL ADod, I think not, Sir.

Smirks Sure you are. Sir ? .

O. Tell. You look as if you would forbid the Bains,
Mr. Smirk. , I hope you have no pretention to the Lady 1

Smirk, Wifli him joy, Sir ! 1 have done him the good
Office to day already.

O. :S^//. Out a pife, what do I hear ?

L.Toxvn, Never ftorm, Brother, the truth is out.

O. Bell. How lay you. Sir ! is this your wedding day ?

r. BelL It is, Sir.

O. -5f//. And a Dod it Ihall be mine too,
Give me thy hand. Sweet-heart, {To Emilia.

What doft thou mean? give me thy hand, I lay.

{Emil. kneels and T, Tell*

L. Town. Come, come, give her your Bleflisg,
This is the Woman your Son lov'd, and is marry'd to.

O. Bell. Ha ! cheated ! cozenM ! and by your contrivance,Sifl:er !

L.Town. What would you do with her ?
She's a Rogue and you can't abide her.

tMedley. Shall I hit her a pat for you, Sir ?

O. Bell. A Dod , you are all Rogues,,
And I never will forgive you.

L. Tovpn. Whither ! whither ! away ?

Medley, Let him go and cool awhile!

L. Wood. Ito Dorimant.'} Here's a bufinels broke out now,
M'^. Conrtage^ I am made a fine fool of.

Dor. You fee the. old Gentleman knew nothing of it.

L. Wood. I find he did not. I (hall have fome trick put upon
Me if 1 flay in this wicked Town any longer. Harriet I dear
Child ! where art thou ? I'll into the Country ftraight.

O. "Bell: A Dod, Madam, you Ihall hear me firll—

Enter Loveit and Bcllinda,

Xi'x'. Hither my Man dog'd him! -^ — .—

Beil, Tondtr he (lands, roy Dear.

Xov. I fee hi^p.r^ — — Z^^fde,

And with him tlie Face that has undone me ! oh that I were



K77)

But where I might throw out the Anguifh of my heart,
Here it mull rage within and break it.

h.Towrt. Mrs. Loveit! are you afraid to come forward ?

Lov» 1 was amaz'd to fee fo much company here in a
Morning, the occafion fure is extraordinary^

Dor, Afide.'\ Loveit and BelUndiH ! the Devil owes me a
Shame to day, and I think never will have done paying it.

Lov, Marry'd! dQHZ Emilia! howam Irranfported
With the News ?

Har. to Dorimantr\ 1 little thought Emilia was the woman

Mr. Bellair was in love with 1*11 chide her for not trufling

Me with the fecret.

Dor, How do you like Mrs. Loveit ?

Har, She'safam'd Mrs. of yoursi hear^

Dor. She has been on occafion !

O. 'Bell. A Dod, Madam, I cannot help ic. {To L. Woodvil.

L. Wood. You need make nomor^ Apologies, Sir.

6 mil. to Loveit.'} The old Gentleman's excufing
Himfelf to my Lady Woodvil.

Lov. Ha, ha, ha I I never heard of any thing fo pleafant.

Har. She's extreamly overjoy'd at fomething. {To Dor.

Dor. At nothing, (he is one of thofe hoyting Ladies,
Who gayly fling themfelves about, and force a laugh,
When their aking hearts are full of difcontent and malice.

Losu* Oh Heav'n ! I was never fo near killing my felf with
Laughing Mr. Dorimant I are you-a Brideman?

L. Wood, Mr. Dorimant I is this Mr. Dorimant^ Madam?

Lov. If you doubt it, your daughter can refohre you, I fuppofe.

L.Wood. I am cheated too, bafely cheated.

O. 'Bell, Out a pize, what's here more Knavery yet !

L. Wood, Harriet I on my Blelfing come away I charge you.

Har, Dear Mother .' do but (lay and hear me.

L. Wood, I am betray'd, and thou art undone I fear.

Har. Do not fear it — 1 have not^ nor never will do any

Thing againft my duty believe me/ dear Mother, do.

. Dor. to Lov.'} I had trufted you with this fecret, but that
I knew the violence of your Nature would mine my fortune.
As now unluckily it has: I thank you, Madam.

Lov. She's an Heirefsi know, ard very rich.

Dor. Tofatisfy you I muft give up my intereft wholly t©
My Love, had you beena reafonable woman,
I might have fecur'd 'em both, and been happy

Lov. You might have trufted me with any thing of this kind.
You know you might. Why did you go under a wrong Name ?

L 2 Dor,



Dor. The ftory is too long to tell you now, be fatisfied^ this
Is the bufiuefs ; this is the Mafque has kept me from you. -i

'Bell. He's tender of my honor, though he's L^fi^e^

Cruel to my Love.

Lov, Wasitnoidle Miftrefsthen?

Dor. Believe me a Wife, to repair the
Ruines of my eftate that needs it,

Lov. The knowledge of this makes my Grief
Hang lighter on my foul', but I fhall never more be happy*.

Dor, Bellinda I

Bell. Do not think of clearing your felf with me, it is
Impollible Do all men break their words thus ?

Dor. Th'extravagant words they fpeak in love •,
*Tis as unreafonable to exped we fliould perform all we
Promife then, as do all we threaten when we are angry— —-

When I fee you next

^ Bell, Take no notice of me,and I fhall not hate you.
[i Dor. How came you to Mrs. Loveit f

BelL By a millake the Chairmen made for want of ;

My giving them directions. . .^

. Dior., f Twas a pleafant one. We muft meet agen.

Bell. Never." lyor. Never/

BelL When we do, may I be as infamous as you are falfeo.

L. Town. Men of Mr. 'I>orimam''s Charader, always
Suffer in the general opinion of the World.

Med. You can make no judgment of a witty man from
Common fame, confidering the prevailing Fadion , Madam- — *

0. Bell. A Dod, he's in the right.

Med. Befides 'tis a common errour among Women, to
Believe too well of them they know^and too ill of them they don't.
0..^e//. ADod, heobferveswelL

1, Town. Believe me, Madam, you will find Mr. !Z)mw^«t,
As civil a Gentleman as you thought Mc.Cmrtage.

Har: If you have mind to know him better-— —

/.. Wood. You have a mind to know him better !
Come av^7ay-- — You Pnall never lee him more— ——.

Ha\. Dear Mother^ ftay —

L.Wood. 1 wo'not be confenting to your Ruine — «-

Har. Were ray fortune in your power ^ — .

L. IVoadi Your perfon is.

Har. Could I be difobedient I might take it out of
Yours, and put it into his,

L.Wood. 'Tis that you would be at, you
Would marry this Dmw<««f.



(79)

Har, I cannot deny it / I would, and never will
Marry any other Man.

L. Wood. Is this the Duty that you promised ?

Har. But 1 will never marry him againlt your will

L. Wood. She knows the way to melt my heart. {_J{ide.

Upon your felf light yourundoing. {To Har.

Med. XJo 0. rBeU.2 Come, Sir, you Have not the heart
Any longer to refufe your blefling.

O, Bell. A Dod, I ha'not — Rife, and God blefs you both

Make much of her Harry., flie deferves thy kindnefs ,

A Dod firrah, 1 did not think it had been in thee. [^Ji? Emilia,
^'w^^y- Sir Fop] ing 4Wj Page.

Sir fo/7. 'Tisa damn'd windy day ! hey Page /
Is my Perriwig right ?

Vage. A little out of order, Sir/

Sir Fop Pox o'this apartment, it wants an Antichamber
To adjuft ones felf in. Madam I I came from {Jo LQveit.

Your houfe, and your Servants dired;ed me hither.

Lov. I will give order hereafter they fliall direct you better.

Sir Fof. The great fatisfadion I had in the Mail iaft night
Has given me much difquiet fince.

Lov, 'Tis likely to give me more than I deTre,

Sir Fop. What the Devil makes her {q referv'd ?
Ami guilty of an indifcretion, Madam >

Lov.Yon will be of a great one,if you continue your miftake^Sir.

Sir Fop. Something puts you out of humour.

Lov. The mofl fooIiOi inconfiderable thing that ever did.

SirF^p. Is it in my power?

Xo-z/. . To hang or drowm ir,do one of 'em,
And trouble me no more.

Sir Fop. So fiere Serviteur, Madam — /t/^j^/fy, Where's Dormant}

Med. Methinks the Lady has not made you thofe
Advances to day fhe did laH night. Sir Fophng

Sir Fop. Prithee do not talk of her.

Med. She would be a bone fortune.

Sir Fop. Nottomeat prefent. Med. Howfo?

Sir Fop. An intrigue now would be but a temptation to me
To throw away that Vigour on one which I mean fhal! fhortly
Make my Courtto the whole Sex in a Ballet.

Med. Wifely conlider'd, Sir Foplmg,

Sir Fop. No one woman is worth the lofs of a Cut in a Caper.

Med. Not when 'tis founiverfallydefign'd.

L. Wood. Mr. Dorimanty every one has fpoke fo much in
Your behalf, that I can no longer doubt but I was in the wrong, .

Lov..



(8o)

Lov, There's nothing but falfhood and impertinence in this
World ! all men are Villains or Fools •, take example from ray
Misfortunes. Bellinday if thou would'ft be happy, give thy
Self wholly up to goodnefs.

Har. \jo Loveit.2 Mr. Dormant has been your God
Almighty long enough, 'tis time to think of another .

Lov. Jeer'd by her ! I will lock my felf ep in my houle.
And never fee the world again.

Bar. A Nunnery is the more faihionable place for fuch a Re-
treat, and has been the fatal confequence of many a Belk j 4ffion.

L0V. Hold heart ! till I get home ! ihould I anfwer, .
Twould make her Triumph greater. [,Is£oifj^oHt.

Dor. Yom hand ^ Sir FopliJi^

Sir F/?p. Shall I wait upon you, Madam ?

Lov. Legion of Fools, as many Devils take thee. CEat.Lov.

Med. Dormant ? I pronounce thy reputation clear —and
HencefoiTvard when I would know any thing
Of woman, 1 will confult no other Oracle.

Sir Fop. Stark mad, by all that's handfome ! Dormant,
Thou hail engag'd me in a pretty bufincfs.

Dor, I have DC; kifure now to talk about it.

O. Bell. Out a prze, what does this man of mode do here agen ?

L. Town. He*d be an excellent entertainment within, Brother,
And is luckily come to raife the mirth of the Company.

L. Wood. Madam, I take my leave of you.

L.Jorvn. What do you mean, Madam?

L. Wood. To go this afternoon part of my way to Hartly—-

O. BelL A Dod you fliall ftay and dine fii ft ! come we will
All be good friends, and you (hall give M . Dormant
Leav£ to wait upon you and your Daughter in the Countrey.

L.Wood. If his occafions bring him that way, I have now
So good an opinion of him, he fliall be welcome.

Har. To a great rambling lone houfe, that looks as it were not
Inhabited, the family's fo fmall •, there you'll find my Mother, an
Old lame Aunt, and my felf, Sir,perch'd up on chairs at a diftance
|n a large parlour-, fitting mopicg hke three or four melancholy
Birds in a fpacious vollary — does not this ftagger your refolution ?

DcJr. Not at al', Madam ! the fiilltimf 1 f^w vou.
You l^k me with the pangs of love up- is

Day my Soul has qiiir.f given up hf-

Har. This is more difma' f^ r Emilia ! pity me,

Whoamgoinc rotbarf? ' ; ■ the hateful noife

Oi Rooks alreadv—^; / ' muiickinthe

Worft



(80

Worib Cry in London ! My Dill and Cowcumbers to pickle^
O. Bell. Sifter ! knowing of this matter, I hope you

Have provided us fome good Chear.

L.Town. I have, Brother, and the Fiddles too .

0. ^f//. Let 'em ftrike up then, the young Lady (hall

Have a dance before (he departs. [Dance.

Z^fter the 'Dmce,

So now we'll in, and make this an arrant wedding-day

And if thefe honefl Gentlemen rejoyce, ^To the Pitt.

A Dodthe Boy has made a happy choke. \^Ex. Omnes,



The



The E P I L O G U E by M-^ pryden^

MOST Modern WitSy fnch monftrous Fools have (how^,
Theyfeem^d not of HcAV^ns making hnt their own,

Thofe Naufeom Harlequins in Farce may faf^ —

But there goes more to a fuhfiantialj^^ ! "

Something of man mufi be expos' dta View f ! ' '

Thaty Gallant s^ they may wore refemble you:

Sir Fopling is a Foolfo nicely writ,
' The Ladies W3H*d mifiake him for a Wit,

Andvohenhe fmgs^ talks loud ^ and cocks '^Vfou^dcry^

J vow methink^he^s pretty Company-,

So brisk, fo gay y fo travailed, fo refin^dy ' .

^s he took^pains tograf upon his kind. \

True Fops help Natures worh^y and go to School^

To file and fnijh Cod almighty' sfooL

Tet none Sir Fopiing him, or him can call •

fJe''s Knight o^th^ Shire, andreprejentsye aU.

From each he meets , he calls what e'er he can-y

Legio}i*s hii name^ a People in a Man,

His bulky folly ffdthers as it goes,

j4nd, rolling o'^reyou^ like ^ Snow-ball growes.

His varioti4 anodes from various Fathers follow^

One taught the To f.^ and one the new French Wallow.

His Sword'kjiot. this 'y hisCrevat, this de/fgn'd,

<L^ndthis, the yardUng Snake he twirls behind, .

From one the f acred Perriwig he gained, r

Which Wtnd ne'er blew^ nor Tomh of Hat prophan^d,

Another s diving Bow he did adore.

Which, with a fnog^ cafts dl the hair before : ■

' Till he with full Decorum brings it back,
'■ jdndnfes with a Water Spaniel jhal^,

^s for his Songs (the Ladies dear delight)

Ihoje jure he tooh^from mofl of you who write,

Tet every man is fafefrom what he feared.

For no one Fcol is hunted from the herd. " >



S.



o: Pol*

,^^t,,,,. Texas-
