
Skip to main content

    Internet Archive Logo
    web
    books
    video
    audio
    software
    images
    search

    uploadUPLOAD
    personSIGN IN

    ABOUT
    CONTACT
    BLOG
    PROJECTS
    HELP
    DONATE
    JOBS
    VOLUNTEER
    PEOPLE

Full text of "Venice preserv'd; or, A plot discover'd. A tragedy. As it is acted at the Duke's theatr. Written by Thomas Otway"
See other formats

Digitized by the Internet Archive

in 2011 with funding from

LYRASIS Members and Sloan Foundation



http://www.archive.org/details/venicepreservdorOOotwa



Venice Preferv



O R,



A Plot Difcover



A





AG





As it is A<5ted at the
DVKE'S THEATRE.



Written by THOU A S OTWAT.



L N D ON,.

Printed for Jof. Hindmarjh at the Sign of the

Black Bull, over againft the Royal

Exchange in ComhiU. 1682.



EPISTLE

Tq Her GEL ACE the



O F



PORTS





MADAM,

ERE it pojjible for me to let the World know
how entirely your Graces Goodnefs has devoted
a poor man to your fervice 5 were there words
enough in fpeech to exprefs the mighty fenfe I
have of your great bounty towards me 5 fureiy
lfhould write and tal^ of it for ever : But your Grace has given
me Jo large a Theam , and laid fo very vaji a foundation , thai
Imagination wants jlocl^ to build upon it. I am as one dumb
when 1 would Jpeak, of it, and when I firive to write, I want
a fcale of thought fufficient to comprehend the height of it. For-
give me then, Madam, if ( as a poor Peafant once made a Pre-
fent of an Apple to an Emperour) 1 bring this fmall Tribute ,.
the humble growth of my little Garden, and lay it at your feet.
Believe it is paid yon with the utmofi gratitude, believe that fo
long as 1 have thought to remember, how very much I owe your
generous Nature, I will ever have a heart that fiall be graiefull
for it too : Your Grace, next Heaven, deferves it amply from
me 5 That gave me life, but on a hard condition, till your ex-
tended favour taught me to prize the gift, and took the heavy
burthen it was cloggd with from me : I mean hard Fortune:
When I had enemies, that with malitious power kept back^ and
fhaded me from thofe Royal Beams, whofe warmth is all 1 have,
er hope to live by \ Tour noble pity and compajjion found me,
where I was far cafi backward from my blefjing 5 down in the
rear of Fortune, calTd me up placd me in the Jhine, arid 1 have
'felt its comfort. ' Ton have in that rejiord me to my native

A 2 Right*



Epiiile Dedicatory.

Right, for a fieady Faith, and Loyalty to my Prince, was aU
the Inheritance my Father left me, and however hardly my ill
Fortune deal with me, 'tis what I prize fo well that 1 ner
pawn'd it yet, and hope I ner fiall part with it. Nature and
Fortune were certainly in league when you were born^ and as
the firji tooh^ care to give you beauty enough to enjlave the hearts
of all the Worlds fo the other refolvd to doe its' merit Jufiice,
that none but a Monarchy fit to rule that World, fiould er pof~
fefs it, and in it he had an Empire. The Toung Prince you
have given him, by his blooming Vertues , early declares the
mighty flocks he came from } and as you have takfin all th& pious
care of a dear Mother and a prudent Guardian to give him a
noble and generous education^ may it fucceed according to his
merits and your wifhes : May he grow up to be a Bulwark^ to
his illufirious Father, and a Patron to his Loyal Subje&s^ with
Wifedom and Learning to affiji him, whenever call'd to his Coun-
cils^ to defend his right again fh the encroachments of Republicans
in his Senates^ to cherifh fitch men as fhall be able to vindicate
the Royal Caufe, that good and fit fervants to the Crown, may
never %,e loji for want of a Prote&our. May He have courage
and con duff, fit to fight his Battels abroad, and terrific his
Rebeilsy%at home 5 and that all theje may be yet more Jure-,
may He\vever, during the Spring-time of his years, when thofe
growing Vertues ought with care to be cherifh' d, in order to their
ripening 5 may he never meet with vitious Natures, or the tongues
of fait hie fs, fordid, in ftpid Flatterers, to blaji 'em: To conclude $
may He be as great as the hand of Fortune (with his Honour)
fijall be able to make him : And may your Grace , who are fo
good a Miflrefs , and fo noble a Patronefs 5 never meet with
a lefi grateful/ Servant , than 5

*•■ .....

Madam,

Tour Graces entirely

Devoted Creature,

Thomas Otway.

PROLOGUE.



PROLOGUE.



}



■r



IN thefe difira&ed times , when each man dreads
The blondy ftratagems of bujie heads 5
When we have feard three years we know not what,
Till Witneffes begin to die th* rot^
What made our Poet meddle with a Plot .<?
Wast that he fanfyd, for the very fake
And name of Plot, his trifling Play might take .<?
For there's not int one Inch- board Evidence, *)
But 'tis, he fays , to reafin plain and fenfe, >
And that he thinks a plauflble defence, J

Were Truth by Senfe and Reafin to be tri'd f
Sure all our Swearers might be laid ajide :
No, of fuch Tools our Author has no need,
To make his Plot, or may his Play fucceed.$
He, of black^BiUs, has no prodigious Tales^
Or Spanifh Pilgrims cafi a-Jhore in Wales 5
Here's not one murtherd Magijirate at leafl,
Kept rank likf Venfon for a City feaft,
Grown four days ftrff^ the better to prepare
And fit his ply ant limbs to ride in Chair :
1 et here's an Army raisd, though under ground^
But no man feen, nor one Commifflon found 5
Here is a Traitour too, that's very old,
Turbulent, Jubtle, mifchievous and bold,
Bloudy, revengefull, and to crown his part,
Loves fumbling with a Wench, with all his heart 3
Till after having many changes pafs'd,
In fpight of Ago. (thanks Heaven) is hangd at laft :
Next is a Sen at our that keeps a Whore,
InVemce'none a higher office bore 5
To lewdnefs every night the Letcher ran,
Shew me, all London, fuch another man,
Match him at Mother Crefwolds if you can.
Oh Poland, Poland ! had it been thy lot,
T have heard in time of this Venetian Plot,
Thou furely chofen hadji one King from thence^
And honoured them as thou haft England (Ince.

EPI-



-



EPILOGUE,



THE Text is done, and now for Application,
And when that's ended pafs your Approbation.
Though the Confpiracy s prevented here,
Methinks I fee another hatching there ,
And there's a certain Faff ion fain would fway,
If they had flrength enough and damn this Play
But this the Author bad me boldly fay :
If any take his plainnefs in ill part,
He's glad on't from the bcttome of his heart 5
Poets in honour of the Truth fhou'd write,
With the fame Spirit brave men for it fight 5
And though again fh him caufelefs hatreds rife,
And dayly where he goes of late, hefpies
The feowles of full en and revengefull eyes 5
' Tis what he knows with much contempt to bear y
Andferves a caufe too good to let him fear ;
He fears no poifbn from an incensd Drabb t
No Ruffians five foot-fword, nor Rafial's Jiabj
Nor any other fnares of mi [chief laid,
plot a Kofi- alley Cudgel- Ambujcaae,
From any private caufe where malice reigns,
Or general Pique all Block-heads have to brains :
Nothing fljall daunt his Pen when Truth does call,
No not the * Pi&ure- mangier at Guild-hall. *The Rascal that

The Rebel-Tribe^ of which that Vermin s one, York'* pmJL

Have now fit forward and their courfe begun 5
And while that Prince's figure they deface,

As they before had maffacred his Name,
Durjl their bafe fears but look him in the face,

They'd ufe his Per Con as they've us'd his Fame v



Aface



$.f#&e., $>n >#fe# fuch iineaments -fhey wade
$ff that great M.artyfs^ whoje rich bland they fbe$
What their rebellious hate they fiill retain,
And in his Son would muriher Him again j
With .indignation i^hen, let each brave 'heart,
iRoufe and unite to take his injured part$
Till Royal Love and Goodnejs call him home r3
And Songs of Triumph meet him as he come 5
Till Heaven his Honour and our Peace rejiore,
.And Villains never wrong his Wtrtjte more.



Perfbnae Dramatis.



Duke of Venice , Mr. D. Williams,

Pr/nli, Father to Belvidera, a Mr. Boman.

Senatour,
Antonio , A fine Speaker in Mr. Leigh.

the Seiiat&g^Q^S / ,o

Pierre. -rCU^J *o Ju^-^f'




y Mr. Betterion.
Mr. Smith.
Mr. Wilfhire.
Mr. G/Zfo
Mr. Percivah



VConfpiratours,



Renault}

Bedamar,

Spinofa^

Theodore^

Eliot,

Reviflido,

Durand,

Mezzana,

Bramveil t j

Ternon,

Brabe, J

Belvidera, '"n . <i^ T t^ i /^j/O , Mrs. Barry.
AqniUna, ^*<Ay ~£i //*^A^ Mis.jOt/rrer.



Two Women, Attendants on Belvidera.

Two Women, Servants to Aquilina.

The Council of Ten.

Officer.

Guards.

Friar.

Executioner and Rabie,



VENICE







VENICE PRESERVD,

OR

A Plot Difcover d.



Act I. Scene L

Enter Priuli ^W JaffeirV !

■JNtiurj^ 'yo tnore ! Tie hear no more ; begone and leave.'
Jaff.'Hor: hear me] by my fufferings but you ihall!
My Lord, my Lord . I'm not that abjed wretch
You think me: Patience! where'sthe diftance
Me back fo far, but I may boldly fpeak (throws

In right, though proud oppreffion will not hear mee I

Prm. Have you not wrong'd me Z

Jaf. Could my Nature e're
Have brook'd Injufticeorthe doing wrongs^
I need not now thus low have bent my felf,
To gain a Hearing from a Cruel father! _ . £

Wrong'd you < J

Prist. Yes ! wrong'd me,in the niceft point :
The Honour of my Houfe • you have done me wrong •
You may remember ;V( For I now will fpeak,
And urge its bafenefa : ) When you firft came home
From TraveH, with fuch hopes,as made you lookt on
By all men's Eyes, a Youth of expectation $
Pleas'cj with your growing Virtue, I receiv'd you ;
Courted,,and fought to raife you to your Merits :
My Houfe, my Table, nay my Fortune too,
My very felf, was yours ; you might have us'd me
To your btfl fervice ; like an open friend,

£ Itrca? %



2 \emce*rrejervd,or

I treated, trufted you, and thought you mine \
When in requital of my beft Endeavours,

You treacheroufly pracus'd to undo me,
Seduc'd the weaknefsof my Age's Darling,
My only Child, and dole her from my bofome:
Oh Behidcra I

J*jf\ Tis to me you owe hor,
Childiefs you had been elfe, and in the Grave,
Y qur name Exjinctflor no more Priuli heard of.
You may remember, fcarce five years are paQ y
Since in your Brigandine you fail'd to fee
ThsAdriatick wedded by our Duke,
And I was with you : Your unskilful! Pilot
Dafh't us upon a Rock" 5 when to your Boat
You made for fafety ; entredfirft yourfelf-
The affrighted Behidera following next, <
As (he flood trembling on the VefFel fide,
Was by a Wave wafht off into the Deep,
When inftantly I plung'd into the Sea,
And Buffeting the Billows to herrefcue,
Redeem *d her Life with half the lofs of mtne 5
Like, a rich Conqueft in one hand I bore her,
And withtheother .d aflat' the fa wcy Waves,
That throng'd and preft to rob me of my prize :
I brought her, gave her to your defpai ring Arms :
Indeed you thank't ms-*, but a nobler gratitude
Rofe in her foul .-for from that hourflie lov'd me,
Till for her Life (he paid me with her felf.

Priu. You Hole her from me, like a Theif you ftole her,
At dead of night ; that curfed hour you chofe
To riHe me of all my. Heart held dear.
May all your Joys in her prove falfe like mine 5
A fleril Fortune, and a barren Bed,
Attend you both: Continual difcord make
Your Days and Nights bitter and grievous : Still
May the hard hand of a vexatious Need
Opprefs, and grind you • till at laft you find
The Curfe of Difobedience all your Portion.

Jajf. Half of your Curfe you have beftow 'din vain, .

Rcav:'n has already crown'd our faithfull Loves
, Will



AflotD'tjifiyer'd* $

With a young Boy, fweet ashis mothers Beauty :
May he live to prove more Gentle than his Grandflre,
And happier than his Father 1

Priu. Rather live
To bait thee for his bread, and din your ears
With hungry Cries : Whilft his unhappy Mother
Shs down and weeps in bitternefs of want.

Jaf. You talk as if it would pleafe you.

Priu. ' F would by Heav'n.
Once (he was dear indeed 5 the Drops that fell
From my fad heart, when (he forgot her Duty,
The fountain of my Life was not To pifetious : r
But (he is gone, and if I am a man
I will forget her.

Jaff. Would I were in my Grave.

Priu. And frte too with thee 5
For, living here, you're but my curs'd Remembrancers,
I once was happy.

Jaff.. You ufe me thus } becau(e you know my foul
Is fond of Be hider a: You perceive
My Life feeds on her, therefore thus you treat me 5
Oh ! cou!d my Soul ever have known fatiety :
Were I that Theif, thedoer of fuch wrongs
As you upbraid me with , what hinders me,
But I might fend her back to you with Contumely,
: - And court my fortune wnere (he wou'd be kinder 1

Priu. You dare not do't.

Jaff. Indeed, my Lord,! dare not.
My heart that awes me is too much my Mafter :
Three years are paft fince firff our Vows were plighted,
During which rime, the World muft bear me witnefs,
I have treated Belvidera like your Daughter,
The Daughter of a Senator of Venice ;
Diftin<5tlon, Place, Attendance and Oblervance,
Due to her Birth, (he always has commanded -
Out of my little Fortune I have done this 5
Becaufe (though hopelefs e're to win your Nature )
The World might lee, I lov'd her for her felf 3
Not as the. Heirefs of the great Priuli>- — •
"Ho more J

B 2 7^ Yes



^ Venice freftrid, or

Jaf. Yes] all, and then adieu for ever.
There's not a Wretch that lives on common Charity
But's happier than me : for I have known
The Lulcious Sweets of Plenty., every night
Have flept with (oft content about my head,
And never waked but to a joyfull morning,
Yet now muft fall like a full Ear of Corn,
Whofe bloffom fcap*d> yet's withered in the ripening."

Prm. Home and be humble, ftudy to Retrench •
Difcharge the lazy Vermin of thy. Hall,
Thofe Pageants of thy Folly,
Reduce the glittering Trappings of thy Wife
To humble Weeds, fit for thy little ftate ;
Then to fome fuburb Cottage both retire •,
Drudge, to feed loathfome life: Get Brats, and Starve-
Home, home, I fay.— [Exit Priuli*.

ypjf.. ¥es, if my heart would let me—
This proud, this fwelling heart : Home I would go ? .
But that my Dores are hatefull to my eyes,
Fiird and dkcnm'd up with gaping Creditors,
Watchfull as Fowlers when their Game will ipring ;
1 have now not 50 Ducats ki, the World>
Yet Hill I am in love, and pleas'd with Ruin.

Oh Be Ivider a \ oh (lie's my Wife

tod we will bear our way ward Fate together,,
But ne^e know Comfort more;

Enter V'loxxh*

Tierr. My Friend good morrow 1:
Mow farts the honeft Partner of my Heart f
What, melancholy I.not a word to (pare me I

Jajf. Vm thinking Eierre, how that damn'd ftarving ; QuaIkf
Call'd Honefty, got footing in the World*

Pierr. Why ; pow'rfull Villainy firft fet it up,
for its own eaieand fafety : Honed men -
.&re the foft eafy Cufhions on- which Knaves>
Repole and fatten :. Wereallmankind Villains,.
They'd ftarve eackothep ? Lawyers wou'd want practice,
Cut~Tliroats Rewards^. Each man would kill his Bret lies.
HimfdLnoiie. would be paid or hans'dfbr Murder :.

Honejrfc



'AQlotQifeoWA. %

Honefty was a Cheat invented fir ft
To bind the Hands of bald deferving Rogues,
That Fools and Cowards might fit fafe in Power,
And lord it uncontroul'd above their Betters.

faff. Then Honefty is but a Notion.

Pierx. Nothing elfe, ,
Like wit, much tatkt of, not to bedefin'd :
He that pretends to moil too, has Ieaft fhare m\ •
*Tis a ragged Virtue : Honefty ! no more on't.

Jaff. Sure thou art Honeft i

Pierr* So indeed men think me *■
But they're miftaken Jaffeir ':- 1 am a Rogue
As well as they •

A fine gay bold fae'd Villam, as thou feeft me $
Tis true, I pay my debts when they'f contracted ;
Iftealfrom noman ; would not cut a Throat
To gain admiffion to a great man's purfe,
Or.a Whores bed ; I'de not betray my Friend, 4

To get his Place or Fortune : I fcorn to flatter
A BIown-upFool above me, or Crufh the wretch beneath me],
Yet , Jaffeir, for all this, I am a Villain I

Jaff. A Villain

Pierr. Yes a moft notorious Villain :•
To fee the fuffring's of my fellow Creatures,
And own my felf a Man : To fee our Senators
Cheat the deluded people with a mew
Of Liberty, which yet they ne'f mud tafte of ;
They fay, by them our hands are free from Fetters,
Yet whom tfcey pleafe they lay in bafeft bonds > ?
Bring whom they rileafe.to Infamy and Sorrow ;
Driveus like Wracks down the rough Tideof Power,
Whilft no hold's left to fave us from Deftruclion r
All that bear this are Villains • and lone,
Not toroufe up at the great Call of Nature,
And check the Growth of thefe Domeftick /pollers,
That makes us Haves and tells us 'tis our Charter.

Jaff. Qh AqniUn.i I Friend, to lofe fuch Beauty,
The Deareft Purchafe of thy noble Labours ;
She was tiiy Right by Conqueft, as by Love.

*////•.' Qh-Jajfeirl Fde io fixt my heart upon her,

That



6 Venice TreferYd, or

That where foe're ! fram'd a Scheme of Life

For time to come,fbe was my only Joy

With which I wiuYt to fweeten future Cares 5

Ifancy'd pleafures, none but one that loves

And dotes as I did can Imagine like 'em :

When in the Extremity of all thefe Hopes,

In the mod: Charming hour of Expectation,

Then when our Eager WiOies fosr the higheft,

Ready to ftoop and gralp the lovely Game,

A Haggard Owl, a Worthlefs Kite of Prey,

With his foul wings fayl'd in and fpoyl'd my Quarry..

Jtff. I know the Wretch, and fcorn him as thou hat'ft him.

rierr. Curfe on the Common Good that's fo protected,
Where every flave that heaps up wealth enough
To do much Wrong, becomes a Lord of Right :
I, who beleiv'd no 111 could e're come near me,
Found in the Embraces of my Aqtulina
A Wretched old but itching Senator;
A wealthy Fool, that had bought out my Title,
A Rogue^ that ufes Beauty like a Lambskin,
Barely to keep him warm : That filthy. Cuckoo too
Was in my abfence crept into my Neft,
And fpoyling all my Brood of noble Pleafiire.

faff. Did ft thou not chace him thence I

Purr. I did, and drove
The rank old bearded Hirco (linking home :
The matter wascomplain'd of in the Senate,
I fummon'd to appear, andcenfur'dbafely,

For violating fomething they call privileage ■ |

This was theRecompence of my fervice :
Would Td been rather beaten by a Coward i
A Souldier's Miftrefs Jajfeir's his Religion,
W hen that's prophan'd, all other Tyes are broken,
That even duTolves all former bonds of fervice.
And from thai hour I think my felf as free

To be the Foe as e*re the Friend of Venice

Nay, Dear Revenge, when e're thou cali'ft I am ready. ,

faffl I think no fafety can be here for Virtue,
And grieve my friend as much as thou to live
In fuch a wretched State as this of Venice ;

Where



a tioc jjtjcoverd* j

Where all agree to fpoil the Publick Good,

And Villains fatten with the brave man's Labours.

Vierr. We have neither lafety, Unity, nor Peace,
For the foundation's loft of Common Good •
Juftice is lame as well as blind amongft us ;
The Laws ( corrupted to their ends that make 'em)
Serve but for Inftruments of fome new Tyranny,
That every day ftartfs up to enflave us deeper :
Now could this glorious Caufe but find out friends
To do it right ! oh f^ffeir ! then migbt'ft thou
Not wear thefe feals of Woe upon thy Face,
- The proud Priuli mould be taught humanity,
And learn to value fuch a fon as thou art.
I dare not fpeak ! But my heart bleeds this moment !

Jiff, Cur ft be the Caufe^ though I thy friend be part on't :
Let me partake the troubles of thy bofbm,
For I amus'd to mifery, and perhaps
May find a way to fweeten't to thy fpirit.

Vierr, Too foon it will reach thy kaowledg— -

Jaffi Then from thee
Let itproceed. There's Virtue in thy Friendfhip
Would make the faddeft Tale of forrow pleafing,
Strengthen my Conftancy, and welcome Ruin,

?iert. Then thou art ruin'd 1

Jajjf* That Hong fince knew,
1 and i'l Fortune have been long Acquaintance,

fierr I paft this very moment by thy dores,
And found them guarded by a Troop of Villains ;
The.fons of public Rapine were deftroying \
They told me, by the fentence of the Law
They had Commiflion to feize all thy fortune, s
Nay more, PriffliS cruel h and hath fign'd it.
Here ftooda Ruffian with a horrid face
Lording it o're a pile of mafFy Plate,
Tumbled into a heap, for publick fale :
There was another making villainous jefts
; At thy undoing ; he had ta'ne poffeflion
Of all thy antient moft domeftick Ornaments,
Rich hangings, intermixtand wrought with gold |
, The very bed , which on thy wedding night
ReceivM thee to the Amis of dslvidera, The



Thefeene of all thy Joys, was violated

By the coiirfe hands of filthy Dungeon Villains,

And thrown amongft the common Lumber.

'Jaff. Now thanks Heav'n

Purr. Thank Heav'n ! for what ?

Jajf. That I am not worth a Ducat.

Pierr> Curfe thy dull Stars, and therworfe Fate of Venice^
Where Brothers, Friends,and Fathers,all arefalfe;
Where there's no truft, no truth $ where Innocence
Stoop's under vile Oppreffion $ and Vice lords it ;
Hadft thou but feen, as I did, how at laft
Thy Beauteous Belvidera, like a Wretch
That's doom'd to Banifhment, came weeping forth,
Shining through Tears, like April Sun's in mowers
That labour to orecome the Cloud that loads 'm,
Whilft two young Virgins, on whofe Arms (he lean'd.
Kindly lookt up, and at her Grief grew fad,
As if they catch't the Sorrows that fell from her i
Even the lewd Rabble that were gather'd round
To fee the fight, flood mute when they beheld her 5
Govern'd their roaring throats and grurnbledpity :
I cou'd havehugg'd the greazy Rogues : They pleas'd meJ

Jaff. I thank thee for this ftory from my foul,
Since now I know the worfl that can befall me:
Ah Pierre I I havea Heart, that could have born
The -rougher! Wrong my Fortune could have done me:
But when 1 think what Behidera feels,
The bitternefs her tender fpirit tafts of,
I own my feifa Coward : Bear my weaknefs,
If throwing thus my Arms about thy Neck,
I play the Boy, and blubber in thy bofome.
Oh ! I fliall drown thee with my Sorrows I

Pi err. Burn I
Firft burn 5 and Level Venice to thy Ruin,
What ftarve like Beggars Brats in f roily weather,
Llnder a Hedge, and whine aurfelves to Death I
Thou , or thy Caufe,(hall never want a/Tiftance,
Whilft I have blood or Fortune fit to ferve thee 5
Command my heart : Thou art every way its mailer. '

J'f- No



Jaff. No: there's a fecret Pride in bravely dying,

pierr. Rats die in Holes and Corners , Dogs tun mad ; •
Man knows a braver Remedy for ibrrow ..: , . .. ,
Revenge ! the Attribute of Gods , they ftampt it
With their great Image on bur Natures; dye I
Confider well the Caufe that calls upon thee:
And if thou art bafe enough , dye then : Remember
Thy Beividera fuffers : Belvidera /

Dye Damn firft — — what be decently interred

In a Church-yard , and mingle thy brave duft
With ftinking Rogues that rot in dirty winding fheets %
Surfeit-flain Fools , the common Dung o'th Soyl.

Jaff. Oh !

Pierr. Wellfaid, out with't , Swear a little -—*

Jaff. Swear !
By Sea and Air ! by Earth, by Heaven and Hell ,
I will revenge my Belvidera 9 s Tears !
Heark thee my Friend - Priuli T is -* a Senator!

Pierr. A Dog!

Jaf. Agreed.

Pierr. Shoot him.

Jaf. With all my heart.
No more : Where fhall we meet at Night i

Pierr. VI tell thee ;
On the Ryalto every Night at Twelve
I take my Evening's walk of Meditation ]
There we two will meet , and talk of pretious
Mifchief

Jaff. Farewell.

Pierr. At Twelve.

Jaff. At any hour, my plagues
Will keep me waking. I Ex. Pkrr,

Tell me why, good Heav'n 3
Thou mad'ft me what I am, with all the Spirit 1 \
Afpiring thoughts and Elegant defires
That fill the happieft Man 1 Ah ! rather why
Did'ft thou not form me fordid as my Fate ,
Bafe minded, dull, and fit to carry Burdens f
Why have I fence to know the Curfe that's on me ?
Is this juft dealing, Nature ? Belvidera t [Enter Belvidera.
Poor Belvidera ! C Bel-



v* o V emce 'rrejerv a, or

Behid. Lead me 3 lead me ray Virgins!
To that kind Voice. My Lord, my Love, my Refuge I.
Happy my Eyes, when they behold thy Face :
My heavy heart will leave its doleful beating
At fight of thee , and bound with fprightful joys.
Oh fmile , as when our-Loves were in their Spring ,
And cheer, my fainting Soul.

J*jf. As when our Loves
Were in their Spring i has then my Fortune chang'd f
Art thou not Btlvidera, ftilithe fame,
Kind, good, an.drtender, as my Arms firft found thee i
If thou art aketfti, where fliail I have harbour ■<
Where eafe my loaded Heart ? Oh ! where complain i

Belv. Does this appear like Change \ or Love decaying fe
When thus I throw my (elf into thy bofom ,
With all the refolution of a ftrong Truth :
Beat's not my heart , as 'tw&u'd alarm thine
To a new Change of >bfifs* I jo-y more in thee-,
Than did thy Mother when me hugg'd thee firll \
And blefs'd the Gods for all her Travel pall.

Jaff. Can there in Woman be fuch glorious Faith £
Sure all ill ftories of thy Sex are falfe ^
Oh Woman 1 loveVWl^^8^ : ^tW€.tode'-thee/ '
To temper Man : We had been Brutes without you j
Angels are Painted fair \ to look like you ;
There's in you all that we believe of Heav'n ,
Amazing Brightnefs, Purity and Truth ,-
Eternal Joy , and everlafting Love. :
, Belv. If Love be Treafure , wee'l be wondrous rich :
I have (b much, my heart will furely break with't 5
Vow's cannot exprefs it , when I wou'd declare
How great's my Joy, I am dumb with the big thought 5-
Ifwell, and fig h, and labour with my longing.
Oh lead me to fome Defart wide and wild ,
Barren as our Misfortunes , where my Soul
May have its vent : Where I may tell aloud
To the high Heaven's, and every lift'ning Planet ," ;
With what a bouftdlefs flock my bofom's fraught 5
Where I may tfeowmy eager Arms about thee,
Give loofe to Love with kiffes, kindling jQy,
And leu^all the Fire that^n my Heart-. J d ff*



ATM DipyefL n

Jaff. Oh Belvidera / double lama Begger ]
Undone by Fortune , and in debt to thee 5
Want ! worldly Want I that hungry meager Fiend
Is at my heels , and chaces me in view 5
Can'ft thou bear Cold and Hunger t Can thefe Limbs 2
Fram'd for* the tender Offices of Love,
Endure the bitter Gripes of fmarting Poverty f
When banifht by our miferies abroad ,
(As fuddenly we (hall be) to feek out
(In fome far Climate where our Names are ftrangers )
For charitable fuccour ; . wilt thou then ,
When in a Bed of ftraw we {hrink together,
And the bleak winds fhall whittle round our heads ;
Wilt thou then talk thus to me? Wilt thou then
Hufh my CareSthus , and fhelter me with Love?

Beh. Oh I will love thee, even in Madnefs lpve thee :
Thorny diftracled Senfes fhould forfake mey

I'd find fome intervals , when my poor heart

Should fwage itfelf and be let loofe to thine.

Though the bare Earth be all our Refting -place \

It's Root's our food , fome Clift our Habitation ,

I'l make this Arm a Pillow for thy Head;

As thouflghing ly'ft, and fwelPd with forrow ,

Creep to thy Bofom, pou'r the balm of Love

Into thy Soul , and kifs thee to thy Reft ;

Then praife our Cod, and watch thee 'till the Morning.
Jaff. Hear this you Heaven's,and wonder how you made Jied

Reign, reign ye Monarchs that divide the Wojdd ,

Bufy Rebellion nere will let you know

Tranquility and Happinefs like mine •

Like gawdy -Ships, ih* obfequious Billows fall

And rife again, to lift you in your Pride ;

They wait but fqr a ftorm.and then devour you ;

I , in my private Bark* : already wrecks ,

Like a poor Merchant driven on unknown Land ,

That had by chance packt up his choicefl: Treafure

In one dear Casket , and fav'd only that :
Since I muft wander further on the fliore,
Thus hug my little, but my (precious ftore 5
Refolv'd to fcora,iindj:icuftmy Fate no more. . .[ Bxtunt.

C 2 A OX



t% Venice <PreferVd y or

ACT. II

Enter Pierre WAquilina.

Aquil. TIY all thy Wrongs; thou art dearer to my Arms
J3 Than all the Wealth of Venice : Prithee ftay.
And let us love to night.

Teirr. No: There's Fool*
There's Fool about thee : When a Woman fells
Her Flefh to Fools, her Beauty's lo'ft to me 5
They leave a Taint, a fully where th'ave paft,
There's fuch a baneful Quality about 'em,
Even fpoyls Complexions with their own Naufeoufnefs,
They infect all they touch 5 I cannot think
Of tafting any thing a Fool has pall'd.

AquiL I loath and fcorn that Fool thou mean*ft, as much
Or more than thou can'ft 3 But the Bead has Gold
That makes him necefTary : Power too,
To qualifie ray Character, and poife me
Equal with peeviih Virtue, that beholds >
My Liberty with Envy : In their Hearts
AreioofeasIam 5 But an ugly Power
Sits in their Faces, and frights Pleafures from 'em.

Pierr, Much good raay't do you. Madam, with your Senator-

AqutL My Senator] why, can'ft thou tiink that Wretch
E 3 re fill'd thy Aquilina's Arms with Pleafure i
Think'ft thou, becaufe I fometimes give him leave
To foyle himfelf at what he is unfit for $
Becaufe I force my felf to endure and fuffer him,
Think'ft thou I love him * No, by all the Joys-
Thou ever gav*$ me, his Pretence is my Pennance ;
The worft thing an old Man can be'sa Lover ,
A meei Memento Mori to pioor woman..
I never lay by his decrepit fide,
But all that night I pondered on my Grave*

Pierr. Wouldhe were well fent thither^

JqulL That's my wiffrtoor
Ids then, myVUrre^ I might have caufe with pleafure

Jto-



A not VtJcoVerd. i ?

To play the Hypocrite : Oh I ho<v I could weep
Over the dying Dotard , and kifshini too,
In hopes to fmother him quite ; then, when the time
Was come-to pay my Sorrows at his Funeral,
For he has already made me Heir to Treafures,
Would make me out-adlareal Widows whining :
How could I frame my face to fir my mourning !
With wringing hands attend him to his Grave,
Falifwooningonhis Kearfe : Take mad poffeflion,
Even of the Difmal Vault, where he lay bury'd,
There like the Ephefia* Matron dwell, till Thou,
My lovely Soldier, comeft to my Deliverance 5
Then throwing up my Veil, with open Armes
And laughing Eyes, run to new dawning Joy.

Pierr. No more I I have Friends to meet me here to nighty
And muft be private. As you prize my Friendfhip
Keep up your Coxcomb : Let him not pry nor liften,
Nor risk about the Houfe as I have feen him,
Like a tame mumpingSquirrel with a bell on ;
Currs will be abroad to bite him, if you do.

AquiL What Friends to meet i may I not be of your Council \

Pierr, How I a Woman ask Queftions out of Bed ?
Go to your Senator, ask him what panes
Amongft his Brethren, hee'l hide nothing from you ;
But pump not me for Politicks. No morel
Give order that whoever in my name
Comes here, receive Admittance : fo good night.
/ Aquil. Muft we ne're meet again I Embrace no more !
Is Love fo foon and utterly forgotten 1

Pierr. As you hence-forward treat your Fool, Pie think on't.

Aquil, Curft be all- Fools-, and doubly curft my felf,
The worftof Fools— I die if he for fakes me-
And now to keep him, Heav'n or Hell inftruft me. £Exewt,
* -> ft

5 c e n e The' Gtyalito

Enter JafFeir. '

i

faff. I am here, and thus, the Shades of Night around me,.
1 look as if all Hell were in my Hearty



vf m, Y cliltc 1 t cjcf v u t ur

And I in Hell Nay, Purely 'tis Po with me ; f^g
For every ftepT tread, methinks Pome Fiend
Knocks at ray Bread, and bids it not be quiet:
lVe heard, how defperate Wretches, like my Pelf,
Have wander'd out at this dead time of Night
To meet the Foe of Mankind in his walk :
Sure I am Po Curtt, that, tho* of Heav'n PorPakeUj
No Minifter op Darknefs cares to Tempt me.
Hell ! Hell ! why fleepefUhou i

l. Enter Pierre.

Pierr. Sure I have ftay'd too long :
The Clock has ftruck, and I may loPe my ProPelyte.
Speak, who goes there ?

Jaff. A Dog, that comesto howl
At yonder Moon : What's he that asks the Queftion J ,

Pierr. A Friend to Dogs; Porthey are honeft Creatures,
And ne're betray their Mafters ; never Fawn
On any that they love not : Weil met, Friend :
S0Wl - - . ; ~

? a ff' The Pame. Oh Peine / Thou art come in PeaPon,
I was jufl going to Pray.

Pierr. Ah that's Meehanick,
Priefts make a Trade on't, and yet ftarve by ittoo :
No Praying, it Ppoils BufinePs, and time's precious ;
Where's Belvider* ?

Jaff. For a Day or two j .
I've lodg'd her privately, %l\ I Pee farther
What Fortune will do with me ?. Prithee, Friend,
If thou would 'ft have me fit to hear good Council,-
Speak not oP Beldivera — .

Pierr. Speak not oP her.

Jaff. Oh no] - : 4

Pierr. Norname her. ' May be I wiOi her well.

Jaff. Who well?

Pierr. Thy WiPe, thy lovely Belvidera,
I hope a man may wifh his Friends WiPe well,
And no harm done I '

Jaff'. Y'are merry Pierre /

/ Pierr.



A flot Pifeoyer'd. t%

Pierr. I am fo :
Thou (halt fmile too , and Behidera fmile •
We'll all rejoyce 5 here's fomething to buy Pins \
Marriage is Chargeable.

Jaff. I but half wiftit
To fee the Devil , and he's here already.
Well i

What ranft this buy, Rebellion, Murder, Treafon i
Tell me which way Imuft be damned for this.

Pierr. When laft we parted, we had no qualms like thefe 3
Butentertain'd each others thoughts like Men ,
Whofe Souls were well acquainted. Is the World
Reformed fince our laft meetings What new miracles
Have happen' d ? Has Priulis heart relented £
Can he be honeft *

J a ff\ Kind Heav'n ! let heavy Curfes
Gall his old Age 5 Cramps, Aches, rack his Bones 5
And bittereft difquiet wring his Heart ;
Oh let him live 'till Life become his burden I
Let him groan under* t long, linger an Age
In the worft Agonies and Pangs of Death,
And find its eafe, but late.

Pierr. Nay, could'ft thou not -
As well , ray Friend , have ftretcht the Curfe to all
The Senate round , as to one (ingle Villain ?

faff. But Curfes ftick not : Could I kill with Curfing ;
By Heav'n I know notthirty Heads in Venice
Should notJbe blafted ; Senators mould rot
Like Dogs on Dunghills 5 buttheir Wives and Daughters
Dye of their own difeafes. Oh for a Curfe
To kill with !

Pierr. Daggers, Daggers, are much better J
; Jaff. Hz i "

Vierr. Daggers.

Jaff. But where are' they ?

Pierr. Oh , a Thoufand
May be difpos'd in honeft hands in Venice.

Jaff. Thou talk'ft in Glouds.
Pierr. But yet a Heart half wrong'd
k% thine has bin. would find the meaning; J*ffeir*

M



1 6 Venice TreferVd, or

Jaff. A thoufand Daggers* all in honeft hands •
And have not I a Friend will ftick one here £

Pier. Yes , if I thought thou wert not to be cherifht
To a nobler purpofe , I'd be that Friend.
But thou haft better Friends , Friends, whom thy Wrongs
Have made thy Friends 5 Friends, worthy to becali'dfo;
Fl truft thee with a fecret : There are Spirits
This hour at work. But as thou art a Man y
Whom I have pickt and chofen from the World ,
Swear, that thou wilt be true to what I utter 3
And when I have told thee, that which only Gods
And Men like Gods are privy to , then fwear ,
No Chance or Change fhall wreft it from thy Bofom.

Jaff. When thou would'fi bind me, is there need of Oaths?
( Green- ficknefs Girls lofe Maiden-heads with fuch Counters )
For thou art fo near my heart, that thou may'ftfee
Its bottom , found its ftrength , and firm nefs to thee ?
Is Coward, Fool, or Viliian, in my facef
If lfeem none of thefe, I dare believe
Thou would'ft not ufe me in a little Caufe ,
For I am fit for Honour's toughed: task ;
Nor ever yet found fooling was my Province »
And for a villainous inglorious" enterprize,
I know thy heart fo well , I dare lay mine
Before thee, fet it to what Point thou wilt.

Purr. Nay, It's a Caufe thou wilt be fond of JaffeiK
For it is founded on the noblefl: Bafis ,
Our Liberties , our natural Inheritance 5
There's no Religion , no Hypocrlfie in't \
' Wee'l dotheBufinefs, ardne'rfaft and pray for't :
Openly acl: a deed, the World fhall gaze
With wonder at, and envy when it is done.

Jaff, For Liberty !

Pierr. For Liberty my Friend :
Thou (halt be freed from bafe PriuWs Tyranny 3
And thy fequeftred Fortunes heal'd again.
I mall be freed from opprobrious Wrongs ,
That prefs me now, and bend my Spirit downward :
All Venice free, and every growing Merit
Succeed toits juft Right : Fools fhall be puli'd

From



A Plot DifcoVerd. 17

FromWifdorns Seat 5 thofe baleful unclean Birds ;
Thofe Lazy- Owls , who (perch'd near Fortunes Top)
Sit only watchful with their heavy Wings
To cuff down new fledg'd Virtues , that would rife
To nobler heights, and make the Grove harmonious.

Jaff What can I do ?

Pierr. Cans't thou not kill a Senator i

Jaff] Were there one wife or honeft , I could kill him
For herding with that neft of Fools and Knaves 5
By ail my Wrongs , thou talk'ft as if revenge
JVere to be had , and the brave Story warms me.

Pierr. Swear then 1

Jaff. I do, by all thofe glittering Stars,
And yond great Ruling Pianet of the Night I
By all good Pow'rs above , and ill below I
.By Love and Friendship, dearer than my Life I
No Pow'r or Death (hail make me falfe to thee.

Pierr, Here we embrace , and 1 Fl unlock my Heart.
A Councel's held hard by, where the deltrucVion
Of this great Empire's hatching : There II lead thee I
But be a Man , for thou art to mix with Men
Fit to difturb the Peace of all the World ,
And rule it when it's wildeft

Jaff. I give thee thanks i
For this kind warning : Yes, I will be a Man, 1
And charge thee, Pierre, when ere thou fee'ftY my fears
Betray me lefs, to rip this Heart of mine
Out of my Breaft , and fhew it for a Cowards. •
Come, let's begone, for from this hour I chafe
AH little thoughts, all tender humane Follies
Out of my bofom : Vengeance fhall have room :
Revenge J

Pierr. And Liberty ! _ ^

Jaff. Revenge ! Revenge—- [Exeunt,

. ■ -
The Scene changes to Aquilina'j huf^the Creek Curtezan.

Enter Renault. - *£

Renault. Why was my choice Ambition, the firft ground
A Wretch can build on ? it's indeed at diftance

D A



A good Profpe\fh, tempting to die TVie w .,
The Height delights! Us, andifre Mountain Top
♦Looks beautiful , becaufe it's nigh to Heavfn ,
But we ne're think how Tandy's the Foundation,
What Storm will batter, and whatiTempeftihake us !
Who's thereof

Enter Spindfa*



Spino. Renault, good (morrow i forby this timer /
I think the Scale of Night has turn'd the ballance ,
And weighs up Morning : Has the Clock ftruck Twelve t

Rena. Yes, Clocks will go as they are fet: But Man -,
Irregular Mans, ne're conftant, never certain:
I've fpent at leaft three pretious hours of darknefs
In waiting dull attendance 5 'tis the Curfe ^
Of diligent Virtue to be mixt like mine ,
^With giddy Tempers, Souls but half refolv'd. ;

Spin. Hell feize that Soul amongftuSy it can frightem

Rena. What's then the Caulethat Lam here alone f
Why are we not together ?

Enter Eliot;
Sir, welcome!

^ou are an Enghjbmm: When Treafon'si hatching
One might have thought you'd "not have been benind hand^
In what Whore's lap have you been lolling f
Qive but an Englishman his Whore and eafe ,
Beef and a Sea-coal fire , he's yours for ever*.

_Eliot. Frenchman, ,you are fawcv^

Rena, Howl

Enter Bedamore the Embaffador, Theodore, Brain veil, Dumnd fr
Brabe, Revellido, Mezzana,Ternon,;Retrofi, Confpirators.

Be dam* At difference , fy.
Is this a time for quarrels >■■ Thieves and Rogues
Fall out and brawls Should Men of your high calling J,
Men feparated by the Choree of Providence ,
3*rom the grofs heap of Mankind , and fet here
la. this g«it afTembly as in one great Jewel r .
k"y% T^dora*



T'adorii the bravefc purpsfe it er'e fmiPdoai
Should you Jike Boys wrangle fop trifles* , :

Reft. Boys! *

Beda. Renault, thy Hand!

to#. I thought I'd given my Heart
Long fince to every Man that mingles here ;
But grieve to find it trufted with fuch Tempers »
That can't forgive my frowaird Age its weakrieis.

Beda. Eliot, thou once had-ft Vertae, I have leen
Thy ltubbom Temper bend with godlike 'Gbodnefs,
Not half thus courted : Tis thy Nations Glbfly , '

To hugg the Foe chat offers brave Alliance, • 2
Once more embrace, my Friends~ — wei'l all embrace -
United thus 5 we are the mighty Engiri • m >
.Muft twift this footed Empire from its Bafis I 4
Totters it not already t

Eliot, Would it were tumbling.

Bed. Nay it fhall down : TfrisNighi weSeaHtsruine*

.

Enter Pierre.

Oh Pierre! thou art welcome!

Come to my bre ifty for by its hopes thoii look'ft -

Lo v el ilj dreadful, aiid the Fate oft Venice

Seems on thy Sword alreadyi Oh iny Mars /

The Poets that firft feign'd a God of War

Sure prophefy'd of thee. ■ '- >

Pierr. Friends! was not l Br»tris ,
(I mean that Brutus , who in epen Senate I* A

Stabb'd the firft Ctfar that ufurp'd the Worldjf
A Gallant Man * '■ - -



r



Rena. Yes 3 -and Cateline too »- ' ,x {
Tho ftory wrong bis l Fame :- ,fof!$e fcottfplfti



To prop the reeling-Glory of 'his 5 <3oi?ntry* t: ^ •
His Caufe was good.

Beda. And ours as murjlv above it,
As Renault thou ar$ Superior to Cethegm'^ :
Or Pierre to Cajfius, \A,f ,

Pierr. Then to what we aim at : £f oH •

WhendoAveftart? or'mtift we talk fore vW? *" '

D 2 B?da.



zo , Venice fPreferVd, or

Bed/. No Fierretthe Deed's near Birth : Fate feems to have fet
TheBufmefs up, and given it to our care,
I hope there's not a heart nor hand amongft us
But is firm and ready.

All. All!
Wee'l die with Bedamore*

Beda. Oh Men v ;
Matchlefs, as will your Glory be hereafter.
The Game is for a Matchlefs Prize, if won ^
If loft, difgtaceful Ruine.

Ren. What can lofe it £ j

The publick Stock's a Beggar • One Venetian
Truftsnot another: Look into their Stores
Of general fofety •, Empty Magazines , . I

A tatter'd Fleet, a murmuring unpaid Army,"
Bankrupt Nobility, a harraft Commonalty ,
A Factious, giddy, and divided Senate ,,
Is all. the ftrength of Venice: Let's deftroy it;
Let's fill their Magazines with Arms to awe them J
Man out their Fleet, and make their Trade maintain it £
Let loofcthe murmuring Army on their Mafters ,
To pay themfelves with plunder 5 . Lop their Nobles
To the bafe Roots , whence moft of 'em firft fprung $
Enflave the Rowt , whom fmarting will make humble £
Turn out their droning Senate, and pofTefs
That Seat of Empire which our Souls were fram'd for.

Tierr. Ten thoufand men are Armedat your Nod ,.
Commanded all by Leaders fit to guide
A Battle for the freedom of the. World 5
This wretched State has ftarv'd them in itsfervice J
And by your bounty quickened , they 're refolv'd
To ferve your Glory , and revenge their own !
Th* have all their different Quarters in this City ,
Watch for th* Alarm* a#d grumble 'tis fo tardy,

Beda. I doubt not Friend , but thy un weary 'd diligence
Has ftill kept waking , and it (hall have eafe;
After this Night it is refolv'd we meet
Nomore , 'till Venice own us for her Lords*

fierr. How lovely the Adriatique Whore ,
Preftinher flames, wiljftunei devouring Flames!



. \ -, A Tlot VifcoWL > % i

Sach as (hall burn her to the watery boitm
And hifs in her Foundation.

Veda. Now if any
Amongft us that owns this glorious Caufe i
Have friends or Intereft , hee'd wifh to fave I
Let it be tqld, the general Doom is Seal'd -
But Pde forgo the Hopes of a Worlds Empire ,
Rather than wound the Bowels of my Friend.

Pierr. I muft confefs you there have toucht my weaknels >
I have a Friend; hear it, fuch a Friend J
My heart was ner'e (hut to him : Nay, Tl tell you ,
He knows the very Bufinefs of this Hour ;
But he rejoyces in the Gaufe, and loves it ,

W* have chang*d a Vow to live and die together J

And He's at hand to ratify it here.
Rett. How! all betray d*
Pierr. No— I've dealt nobly with you ;
Tve brought my All into the publick Stock ;

I had but one Friend , and him PI fliare amongft you J

Receive and Cherifh him : Or if,, when (een

And fearcht, you find him worthlefs, as my Tongue

Has lodg'd this Secret in his faithful Bread ,

To eafe your fears I wear a Dagger here

Shall rip it out again, and give you reft.

Come forth , thou only Good I er'e could boaft o£

Enter Jaffeir mtb a Dagger.

Seda. His Prefence bears the (how of Manly Vertue.

Jaffl I know you'l wonder all , that thus uncalPd ,
I dare approach this place of fatal Councels ;
&ut I am amongft you, and by Heav'n it glads me ±
To fee Fo many Vermes thus united ,
To reftore Juftice and dethrown Oppredom
Command this Sword, if you. would have it quiet,
Into thisJBreaft ; but if you think it worthy
To cut the Throats of reverend Rogues in Robes-*
Send me into the curs'd anembl'd Senate y
It (brinks not, tho I meet a Father there-
Would you behold this City Flaming % Here's



■&



22 Venice TreferYd, or

A hand (hall bear a lighted Torch at nooa
To the Arfenal, and fet its Gates on fire,

Ren. You talk this well , Sir.

J of. Nay — by Heav'n jtJJ do this.
Come, come, I read diftruft in all your faces,
You fear me a Villain , and indeed it's odd
To hear a ftranger talk thus at firft meeting , ' ob

Of matters, that have been fo well debated ;
But I come ripe with Wrongs as you with Councels;
I hate this Senate, am a Foe to Venice-,
A Friend to none, but Men refolv'd like me ., v- j
To puih on Mifchief : . Oh;did you but know me 3 .
I need not talk thus !

Bcda. Pierre r I rau ft embrace him,
My heart beats to this Man as if it knew him.

Rena. I never lov'd thefe huggers :

Jaff. Still I fee
The caufe delights me not. Your Friends furvey me 3
As I were dang'rous — but I come Arm'd
Againft all doubts , and to your truft: will give
A Pledge, worth more than all the World can pay for.
My Belvidera / ' Ho >J mj Belvidera!

Bed. What wonder flext i

Jajf. Let me entreat; you 5 \ 3

As I have henceforth hopes to call ye friends,
That all but the AmbaiTador, this
Grave Guide of Couneels, with my friend that owns me, 1 -
Withdraw a while to fpare a Womans blufhes.

[Ex. all but Bed. Rena. Jaff. Pierr.

Beda. rierre, whither will this Ceremony lead us f

J off". My Belvidera I Belvidera ( ,

BeivU. Who £ {Enter Belvidera.

Who calls fo lowd at this late peacefull hour ?
That Voice was wont to come.in gentler whifpers ,
And fill my Ears with the foft breath of Love :
Thou hourly Image of my Thoughts, where art thou?

pff indeed 'tis late. •

Belv. Oh i I have flept, and dreamt ,
And dreamt again : Where haft thou been thou Loyterer ?
Tho my Eyes cios'd, my Arras have ftiil been open'd h
Suxtcht every way betwixt ray broken {lumbers, T©



JflotBifcoyer'i 2J

To fearch if thou wert come to crown my Reft .
There's no repofe without thee : Oh the day ,
Too foon will break , and Wake us to our forro w ;
Come, come to bed, and bid thy Gares good Night.

fkffi. Oh Belvidera ! we muft change the Scene
In which the paft Delights of Life were tailed :

J he poor fleep little, we muft learn to watch
ur labours late, and early every Morning,
Mid'ft winter Frofts, then clad and fed with fparing ,
Rife to our toils , and drudge away the day.

Beh. Alas I where am I ! whither is't you lead me.!
Methinks I read diftraftion in your face !
Something lefsgentle than the Fate you tell me:
Youihake and tremble too ! your blood runs cold !
Heaven's guard my Love, and blefs his heart with Patience.

Jajf, That I have Patience, let our Fate bear witnefs ,
Who has ordain'd it fo , that thou and I
(Thou the divineft Good mane're pofTeft ,
And I the wretched'it of the Race of Man)
fThis very hour, without one tear, muft part*

Beh, Part I muft we part i Oh ! am I then forfaken f
Will my Love caft me off? have my misfortunes
Offended him fo highly , that hee'l leave me <
Why dragg you from me < whither are you going <
My Dear I my Life ! my Love i

'J.af. Oh Friends !

Beh. Speak to me,

Jaff. Take her from my heart ,
Shee'lgain fuch hold elfe , I (hail ner'e get loofe.
I charge thee take her , but with tender'ft care ,
Relieve her Troubles and aflwage her forrows.

Ren. Rife, Madam ! and Command amongft your Servants I'

Jaff. To you, Sirs, and your Honours, I bequeath her,
And with her this, when I prove unworthy — [Gives a dagger,
You know the reft : — - Then ftrike it to her heart 5
And tell her, he, who-three whole happy years
Lay in her Arms , and each kind Night repeated
The paffionate r Vows" of ftill enGreafing Love,
Sent thatR^wardforaliherTruth and SuflFerings.

Mir, Nay, take my Life, finee he has fold it cheaply 5



z 4 Venice ( PrefirVd y or

Or fend me to fome diftant Clime your flave, :
But let it be far off, lead my complainings
Should reach his guilty Ears , and fhake his pease, .

Jaff. No Befoidera, I've contriv'd thy honour,
Truft to my Faith , and be but Fortune kind
To me 5 as II preferve that faith unbroken ,
When next we meet, 1*1 Jift thee, to a height ,
Shall gather all the gazing World about thee, 1
To wonder what ftrange Virtue plac*d thee there,
But if we ner'e meet more ■ ■

Belv. Oh thou unkind one ,
Never meet more 1 have I deferv'd this from you f
Look on me, tell me, tell me, fpeak thou dear deceiver,'
Why am I feparated from thy Love £
If I am falfe, accufe me-, but if true, '

Don't, prithee don't, in poverty forfake me.
But pitty the fad heart , that's torn with parting.
Yet hear me! yet recall me — VEx. Ren. Bed, and Belv, *

Jaff. Oh my Eyes! u ... , A

Look not that way, but turn your felves awhile
Into my heart, and be wean'd all together.
My Friend, where art thou !

Pierr. Here, my Honours Brother.

Jaff. Is Belviders gontf

Pierr. Renault has lead her
.Back to her own Apartment : but, byHeav'n!
Thou muft not fee her more till our word's over.

ricrr. Not for your life.

Jaff. Oh Pierre, wert thouJbut fhe ,
How I could pull thee down into my heart ]'
Gaze on thee till my Eye-ftringscrackt with Love ,
Till all my finews with its fire extended ,
Fixt me upon the Rack of ardent longing 5
Then fwelling, fighing, raging to be bleft,
Come like a panting Turtle to thy Breaft,
On thy foft Bofom ., hovering , bill and play ,
Confefs the caufe why 1 aft I fled away •

'Own 'twas a fault , but fwear to give it or'e,

And never follow falfe Ambition more. \ f £#. Ambo^

ACT



fifa ^ a. xx *•

fiito* Aquilina $$ for ^Maid.

^«//.^TpEll him I amgone to bed: Tell him I am not at
X home 3 tell him I've better Company with me , or
any thing 5 tell him infhort I will not fee him,the eternal trouble-
fame vexatious Fool ; He's worfe Company than an ignorant
Phyfitian — VI not be difturb'd at thefe unfeafonable hours.

CM.aid. But Madam I He's here already, juftenter*dth&doors.

^AquiL Turn him ouragen, youunneceffary, ufelefs,giddy-
brain'd Aflei if he will not begone, fet the houfe a fire and
burn m both : I had rather meet a Toad in my difh than that
old hideous Animal in my Chamber to Night. [Enter Antonio.

^sinto. Nacky, Nacky, Nacky • — how doll: do Nacky f Hurry
durry. I am come little Nacky- pafl: eleven a Clock , a late
hour, time in all Confcienoe to .go to bed Nacky — .Nacky did
I fay * Ay Nacky ; ^Aquilina, Una, Una, quilina, quilina, quilina^
Aquilina, Naquilina, Naquilina^cky, Acky, Nacky, Nacky, Queen
jsracky — come let's to bed — you Fubbs, you Pugg you — you
little Pufs — - Purree Tuzzey * — lama Senator. f "

<s4quil. You are Fool, lam fure.

xjfnto. May be fo too fweet-heart. Never the worle Senator
for all that.Come Nacky, Nacky, [Qts have a Game at Rump,Nacky.

i^Aquil, You would do well Signior to be trouble fome here
no longer , bdt leave me to my felf, be fober and go home, Sir.

Anto. Home LMadena f

Aquil. Ay home, Sir. Who ami?'

Anto. iJMadona , as I take it you are my ^— you are — thou
art my little Nicky Nacky— that's all i

Aquil. I find you are refolv'd to be troublefome, and fo to
make fhort of the matter in few words , I hate you , deteft
you, loath you, I am weary of you, fick of you — hang you ,
you are aji Old, filly, Impertinent, impotent, follicitous
Coxcomb, Qrazy in your head, and lazy in your Body, love to be
medling with every thing , and if you had not Money, you
are good for nothing.

i^fnto. Good for nothing 1 Hurry durry, I'l try that pre-
fently. Sixty one years Old , and good for nothing 5 that's
brave. [To the CM aid.] Come come come Miftrefs fiddle-faddle,
turn you out for a feafon^ go turn out I fay, it is our will and

E plea-



JL.\J I *»i»*w>» ;* » vy m k w, v/»



pleafure to be private fome moments — r out, out when you are
bid too-[Puts her orft and locks the dforirJGaod for nothing you fay.

AqmL Why what are you good for %

Anto. In the firft place, Madam, I am Old, and confequentJy
very wife, very wife, ^Madona, d'e mark that? in* the fecond
place take notice, if you pleafe,' that I arn a Senator , and when
I think fit can make Speeches Madona. Hurry durry, T can
make a Speech in the Senate-houfe now and then — - wou'd
make your hair ftand an end, Madona.

AftiL What care I for your Speeches in the Senate-houfe,
if you wou'd be filent here , I {Mould thank you.

'Anto. Why, I can make Speeches to thee too, my lovely
l$$lMild for Example — my cruel fair one,

[Takes out aPurfeofGold J , and at every pawfe flakes it.
Since it is my Fate, that you fliould with your Servant angry
prove-, tholateat Night — Ihope 'tis not too late with this to
gain reception for my Love — there's for thee my little Nicky
isiackr±— tike it , here take it — I fay take it , or l'i throw it
at your head — how now, rebel I

Aqiiil. Truly, my Illuftrious Senator , I muft. confefs your
Honour is at prefent moft profoundly eloquent indeed.

Anto. Very well: Come,now let's fit down and think upon't
a little — come fit 1 fay — fit down by me a little my Nicky
NackyMh — [Sits down] Hurry durry — good for nothing — >

Aqmi. No Sir,if you pleafe I can know my diftance and ftand,

Anto-. Stand : How ? Nacky, up and I down J Nay then let
me exclaim with the Poet. -

Shew me a Cafe more pitiful who can ,
\jdflanding Woman^ and a falling Man.
Hurry durry : — not fit down — fee this ye Gods —
You won't fit down i Aquil. No Sir.

Anto, Then look you now, fuppofe me a Bull, a Bafan-Bull i
the Bull of Bulls, or any Bull. Thus up I get and with my brows
thus bent —I broo, I fay I broo, I broo, I broo. You won't fit
down will you f — I broo— [Bellows like a Bull.and drives her about.

x^4quiL Well, Sir, I muft endure this. Now your [She fits
honour has been a Bull , pray what Beaft will your down*
Worfhip pleafe to be next ?

Kjinto.. Now i'l be a Senator agen , and thy Lover little
Nicky Nacky l [Be fits by her*'] Ah toad, toad, toad, toad J fpit

m



in my Face a little, Nacky — fpit in my Face prithee, fpit in my
Face, never Co little: (pit but a little bit — fpit, fpit, fpit, fpit,
when you are bid I fay; do , prithee fpit— now, now, now,
fpit: what you won't fpit, will you ? Then 1*1 be a Dog. *

^Aquil. A Dog my Lord \

<^4nto. Ay a Dog — and I'l give thee this to'ther purfe to
let me be a Dog — and to ufe me like a Dog a little. Harry
durry — I will — here 'tis.-— [Gives the Purfe.

^Aquil. Well, with all my heart. But let me befeecK your
Dogfhip to play your trick's over as faft as you can , that you
may come to ftinking the fooner , and be turn'd out of dores
as you deferve.

i^Anto. Ay, ay - no matter for that - that [Hegetsmder the Table.

(han't move me — Now, bough waugh waugh, bough
waugh [Barks like a Dog,

s^fquil. Hold, hold, hold Sir, I befeechyou: what is'c you
do < If Curs bite, they mult be kickt, Sir. Do you : fee 5 kickuhus.

K^into, Ay with all *ny heart: do kick, kick on, now I am
under the Table, kick agen — kick harder — harder yet, bough
waugh waugh, waugh, bough — 'odd, Fie have a fnap. at thy

fhins — - bough waugh wough, waugh, bough -'odd ihe

kicks bravely. —

\J2qml. Nay.then I'l go another way to work wteh you :.-. and
I think here's an Inftrument fitfor the putpofe -{Fetches a whip- m& BeQ.
What bite your Miftrefs, firrah I out, out of dores, you Dog ,
to kenneland behang'd — bite your Miftrefs by the Legs, you
rogue. - — ; : ..• ■.. X.$heMhips him.

Ann. Nay prithee Nacky,, now thou art too loving?: Hurr$
durry, 'odd l'i be a Dog no longer. .*;

Aquil. Nay none of your fawning and grinning : But be gone,
or here's thedifcipjine : What bite your Miftrefs by the Legs you
mungril i out of dores — hput hout, to kennel fir ra I go.

Anto. This is very barbarous ufage • N^cky, .very karbarous :
look you,' I will not gp ; — . I will not ftir from* the d,bre, -that I
refolve — hurry durry, what fhut me out ? [She whips htm out.

Aquil. Ay, and if you come here any more to night Fl have
my Foot- men lug you, you Curr : What biteyour poor Miftrefs
Nacky, firrah ! Enter Maid. . . ,

Maid. Heav'ns Madam ! Whats the matter * , [He howls at the

Aquil. Call my Foot-men hither prefently. 4 dore like & Dog.
I ■..■ E z Enter



28 Vetuise Prefery'd^ or

M&id. They aijehere already Madam, the houfe is ail alarm'd
with a ftrange nofe that no body knows what to make of.

Aojuil, Oo all of you and turn that troublefome Beaft in the
next room out of my houfe — If I ever fee him within thefe
wajls again, without my leave for his Admittance, you fneaking
Rogues — Tl have you poifonfd all, poifon'd, like. Rats: every
Corner of the -houfe (hall ftink of one of you: Go, and learn
hereafter to know my pleafure. So now for my Pierre:

f$ - , » Thu$\Vphen Godlike Lover rvasdtfpleas'd*

We'Smrificeom 'F col and he 7 \ apneas' di [Exeunt*

Scene The Second,
i Enter Kelvidera.
Sefaiid, |?m SaerinVd i I am fold I betray 'd to fliame t

X Inevitable Ruin has inclos'd me !
No Iboner was I to my bed repair'd ,
1o weighs and ( weeping) ponder my condition,"
But the old hoary Wretch, to whofefalfe Care
My Peace and' Honour was imrufted, came
(LikzTarqwv) gaiiely with infernal Luft.
Oh thou Roman Lmrece l thou could'ft find friends to vindicate
I never had but one, and he's prov'd falfe 5 [thy Wrongs

He that ibouldi guard my Virtue, has betray 'd it?
Left me I undone me i Oh that I could hate him J
Where fhall I go ! Oh whither whither wander?

Enter Jaffeir.
faff. ,Can Bthidera want a refting place
W htri thefe- poor Arms are open to receive her ? 4

Oh 'tis in vain to gruggle with Defires
Strong as my Love to thee- for every moment
I am from thy fight , the Heart within my Bofom
Moans- like a tender Infantum -its Cradle
Whofe Nurfe had left if : Come, and with the Songs
Of gentle Love perfwade it to its peace*

Behid. I fear the ftubborn Wanderer will not own me^
*Tis grown a Rebel to be ruPd no longer ,
Scorns the Indulgent Bofom that firftiull'd it,'.
And like a Difobedient Child difdains
The foft Authority of Befoidera,

Jaff. There was a time"

Selv, Yes, yes, there was a time J J??hen



A fht Difwerd. 29

When Behidertts tears, her crys 3 and forrows^

Were notdefpis'd; when if me chanc'd to figh,

Or look but lad $ — there was indeed a time

When ^feir would have ta'ne her in his Arms \

Eas'd her declining Head upon his Breaft ,

And never left her 'till he found the Caufe.

But let her now weep Seas,

Cry, 'tillfhe rend the Earth; figh /till fhe burft

Her heart afunder 5 ftill he bears it all-

Deaf as the Wind , and as the Rocks unfhaken.

Jaff. Have I been deaf? am I that Rock unmov'd t
Againft whofe root, Tears beat and fighes are fent 1
In vain have I beheld thy Sorrows calmly I
Witnefs againft me Heav'ns, have I done this t
Then bear me in a Whirlwind back agen ,
And let that angry dear one ne're forgive me!
Oh thou too raftily cenfur'ft of my Love I
Could'ft thou but think how I have fpent this night J
Dark and alone, no pillow to my Head ,
Reft in my Eyes , nor quiet in my Heart ,
Thou would'ft not Belvrdera, fure thou would'ft not
Talk to me thus, but like a pitying Angel
Spreading thy wings come fettle on my breaft ,
And hatch warm comfort there e ? re forrows freeze it.

Belv. Why, then poor Mourner , in what baleful Corner
Haft thou been talking with that Witch the Night?
On what cold ftone haft thou been ftretcht along ,
Gathering the grumbling Winds about thy Head ,
To mix with theirs the Accents of thy Woes 1
Oh now I find the Caufe my Love forfakes me 1
I am no longer fit to bear a fhare
In his Concernments: My weak female Virtue
Muft not be trufted •, 'Tis too frail and tender.

Jiff. Oh Portia / Portia / What a Soul was thine %<

Beh. That Porcia was a Woman^ and when Brutu*
Big with the fate of Rome , (Heav'n guard thy fafety I ,);
Gonceal'd frourher the Labours of his Mind,
She let him fee , her Blood was great as his ,
Flow'd from a Spring as noble, and a Heart
Fit, to partake his Troubles , as his Love :
Eeteh/etch that Dagger back,the dreadful dower



3 o Venice ^refety'd, or

Thou ga v'ft laft night in parting with me 5 ftrike it
Here to my heart $ and as the Bipod flows from it ,
Judge if it run not pure as C^A, Daughter^.

Jaff. Thou art too good, and I indeed unworthy ,
Unworthy fo much Virtue : Teach me how
I may deferve fuch matchlefs Love as thine ,
And fee with what attention l'l obey thee.

Belv. Do not defpife me : that's the All I ask.

Jaff. Defpife thee ! Hear me

Belv. Oh thy charming Tongue
Is but too well acquainted with my weaknefs ;
Knows, let it name but Love , my melting heart
DifTolves within my Breaft • 'till with clos'd Eyes
I reel into thy Arms, and all's forgotten.

Jaff. What fhall I do if

Belv. Tell me! be juft, and tell me
Why dwells that bufy Cloud upon thy face i q

Why am I made a ftranger? why that figh,
And I not know the Gaufe i Why wiien the World
Is wrapt in Reft , why choofes then my Love
To wander up and down in horrid darknefs ,
Loathing his bed , and thefe defiring Arms *
Why are thefe Eyes Blood mot, with tedious watching ?
Why ftarts he now i and looks as if he wilht
His Fate were finiiht i 'Tell me, eafe my fears ;
Leaft when we next time meet , I want the power
To fearch into the ficknefs of thy Mind ,
But talk as wildly then as thou look'ftnow.

Jaff Oh Belv tiera,!

Belv. Why was I laft night deliver'd to a Villain i

Jaff. Halv a Villain]

Belv. Yes i to a Villain I Why at fuch an hour
Meets that aftembly all made up of Wretches
That look as Hell had drawn 'era into League i ; v

Why, I in this hand , and in that a Dagger ,
Was I deliver'd with fuch dreadful Ceremonies?
" To you, Sirs, and to your Honour I bequeath her ,
" And, with her this : When e're J prove unworthy ,
cc Tou knsw the reft, then fir ike it to her Heart?
Ohi why's that reft conceal'd from me? mufti
Be made the hoftage of a hellifh Truft i For ;



r k *»■



For fijcb I know I am; that's all my value J
But by the Love and, Loyalty I owe thee,
Tl free thee from the Bondage of thefe Slaves -
Strait to the Senate , tell 'em all I know ,
All that I think, all that my fears inform me !

Jaffl Is this the Roman Virtue 1 this the Blood
That boails its purity with Cau 9 $ Daughter]
Would fhe have e're betray'd her Brutm I

Be lv. No:
For Brutus trufted her : Wer*t thou fo kind ,
What would not Be tvider a fufifer for thee ■{

Jaff. I (hall undo my fe'lf , and tell thee all.

Belv, Look not upon me , as I am a Woman ,
But as a Bone, thy Wife, thy Friend 5 who long
Has had admiflion to thy heart, and there
Study'd the Virtues of thy gallant Nature ;
Thy Conftancy, thy Courage- and thy Truth,
Have been my daily lefTon : I have learnt thern>
Am bold as thou , can fuffer or defpife
The worft of Fatesfdr thee ; and with thee mare them.'

Jaff. Oh you divirteft Powers ! look down and hear
My Prayers ! inftfu& me to reward this Virtue !
Yet think a little, e're thou tempt me further:
Think I have a Tale to tell , will make thy Nature I
Melt all thisboafted Conftancy thou talk'ft of
into vile tears and defpicable for rows i
Then if thou (houd'ft betray mei

Belv. Shall I fwearf

if ; - '

Jaff. No: do not fwear : I would not violate
Thy tender Nature with (b rude a Bond :
But as thou hop'ft to fee me live my days ,
And love t hee long , lock this within thy Breafl;
I've bound my felf by ail the ftri&eft Sacraments ,

Divine and humane — - Belv-.- Speak !

$*ff. To kill thy Father — - Bcfo. My Father 1
Jaff. Nay the Throats of the whole Senate-
Shall bleed a\y- Belvidera 1 He amongft us
That fpares his Father, Brother, or his Friend';.
Is Damn'd : How rich and beauteous will thefase
Of Ruin look -, when thefe wide flreets run blood ;
lane] the glorious Partner's of mf Fortune, .Sfooufe]



M. W ««|»f W ••



Shouting, and {hiding o're the proftrate Dead $
Still to new wafte ; whilft thou, far off in fafety
Smiling, fhaltfee the wonders of our daring;
And when night comes, with Praife and Love receive me,

Befo. Oh i

Jaf. Have a care, andftinink not even in thought J
For if thou do'ft —

Befo. I know it, thou wilt kill me.
Do, ftrike thy Sword into this bofom : Lay me
Dead on the Earth , and then thou wilt be fafe :
Murder my Father ! tho his Cruel Nature
Has perfecuted me to my undoing ,
Driven me to bafeft wants ; Can I behold him
With fmiles of Vengeance , butcher'dln his Age i'
The facred Fountain of my life deftroy'd i
And canft thou fhed the blood that gave me being ?
Nay, be a Traitor too, and fell thy Country ;
Gan thy great Heart defcend fo vilely low ,
Mix with hired Slaves, Bravoes, and Common ftabbers,"
Nofe- flitters, Ally-lurking Villians! joytt-
With fuch a Crew 9 and take a Ruffian's Wages ,
To cut the Throats of Wretches as they fleep %

Jaf Thou wrong'ft me, Be folder a ! I've engag'd
With Men of Souls: fit to reform the ills
Of all Mankind : There's not a Heart amongft them ,
But's as ftout as Death, yet honeft as the Nature^
Of Man firft made, e're Fraud and Vice were fafhions.

Befo. What's he, to whofe curft hands laft night thou gav'ft
Was that well done ^ Qh I I could tell a ftory ( me i

Would rowfe thy Lyon Heart out of its Den ,
And make it rage with terrifying fury.

Jaf. Speak on I charge thee i

Befo. Oh my Love ! if e're
Thy Be folder a's Peace deferv'd thy Care,
Remove me from this place : Laft night, laft night !

Jaf. Diftracl: me not, but give me all the Truth.

Befo. Isjo fooner wer'tthou gone, and I alone ,
Left in the pow'r of that old Son of Mifchief ;
No fooner was I lain on my fad Bed,
But that vile Wretch approacht me ; loofe, unbutton'd ,'
Ready for violation ; Then my Heart Throbb'd



A Tlot VtJcoVerd. jj

Throbb'd with its fears : Oh how I wept and figh'd > '
And fhrunk and trembled ; wiftYd in vain for him
That fhould protect me. Thou alas! wert gone !

Jaff. •Patience! fweet Heav'n, 'till I make vengeance fure.

Belv. He drew the hideous Dagger forth thou ga v'ft him ,
And with upbraiding fmiles he faid , behold it ;
'2 his is the fledge of a falfe Hmbwds love :
And in my Arms then preft, and wou'd have clafp'd me 5
But with my Cries I fcar'd his Coward heart,
Till he withdrew, and mutter'd vows to Hell.
Thefe are thy Friends ! with thefe thy Life, thy Honour ,
Thy Love , all's ftak't, and all will go to ruine.

Jaff. No more. : I charge thee keep this fecret clofe ;
Glear up thy forrows , look as if thy wrongs
Were all forgot, and treat him like a Friend ,
As no complaint were made. No more, retire ,
Retire my Life , and doubt not of my Honour 5
I'l heal its failings, and deferve thy Love.

Belv. Oh mould I part with thee , I fear thou wilt
In Anger leave me , and return no more :

J^ff. Return no more ! I would not live without thee
Another Night to purchafe the Creation.

Belv. When mall we meet agairr?

J*ff* Anon at Twelve !
I*] ileal my felf to thy cxpeciing Arms ,
Come like aTravell'd uove and bring thee Peace.

Belv. Indeed ! Jajf. By all our loves !

Belv. 'Tis hard to part :
But fure no falsehood eVe lookt fo fairly.
Farewell — Remember Twelve. [Ex. Belvid,

Jaff. Let Heav'n forget me -
When I remember not thy Truth, thy Love.
How curftis my Condition , tofs'd and jufti'd,
FroiMvery Corner 5 Fortune's Common Fool ,
The jeft of Rogues , an Instrumental Afs
For Villains to lay loads of Shame upon ,
And drive about juft for their eafe and fcorn.

Enter Pierre.

fierr. Jaffeir J Jaff. Who Calls] ' -

[ fierr. A Friend , that could have whin
U ¥ T'have



54 V enice [ rrejerv a, or

T have found thee otherwife imploy'd ; what, hunt
A Wife on she dull foil ! fure a Ranch Husband
Of all Hounds is the dulled £ wilt thou never,
Never be weaa'd from Caudles and Confections i
What feminine Tale haft thou been liftening, ta,
Of unayr'd fhirts; Catharrs and Tooth Aeh goe
By thin-ford (hoos? Damnation I that a Fellow
Chofen to be a Sharer in the Deftruclion
Of a whole People , Should fneak thus in Corners
To eafe his fulibm Lufts , and Fool his Mind.

Jaff. May not a Man then trifle out an hour
With a kind Woman and not wrong his calling 2

Pierr. Not in a Caufe like ours.

Jaff] Then Friend our Caufe
Is in a damn'd condition : for l'i tell thee,
That Canker-worm calTd Letchery has toucht it,
*Tis tainted vilely : would'ft thou think it, Re»Awi'fi,
(That mortify 'd old wither'd Winter Rogue)
Loves fimple Fornication like a Prieft ,
I found him out for watering at my Wife :
He viilted her laft night like a kind Guardian i
Faith (he has fome Temptations, that's the truth oa%

Pierr. He durft not wrong his Truft I

Jaff. Twas fomething late tho
To take the freedome of a Ladies Chamber.

Pierr. Was (he in bed <

Jaff. Yes faith in Virgin meets
W hite as her bofom , Pierre, difht neatly up ,.
Might tempt a weaker appetite to tafte.
Oh how the old Fox flunk I warrant thee
When the rank fit was on him.

Pierr. Patience guide me !
He us'd no violence <

Jaff. No, no! out on't, violence I < \

Played with her neck ; brufht her with his Gray-beard "„
Struggled and tow2'd, tickl'd her^tillfhefqueak'dalittle.
May be, or fo — but not a jot of violence — —

Pierr. Damn him.

Jaff. Ay > fo fay 1 1 but huih, no more on't ^
All hitherto is welt, and I believe
My felf no Monfter yet : Tho ae Man knows What



What Fate he's born to i fare 'tis near the hour
We all (hould meet for our concluding Orders;
Will the AmbafTador be here in perfon f

Fierr. No : he has fent Coramiflion to that Villain, RenmU*
To give the Executing Charge •
Fd have thee be a Man if poffible
And keep thy temper h for a brave Revenge
Ne're comes too late.

Jaffl Fear not, lam cool as Patience:
Had he compleated my difhonour, rather
Then hazard the Succefs our hopes are ripe for ,
Fd bear it all with mortifying Vertue.

Pievr. He's yonder coming this way through the Hall 5
His thoughs feem full.

Jaff. Prithee retire, and leave me
With him alone: FI put him to fome tryal,
See how his rotten part will bear the touching.

vierr. Be careful then. [Ex. Pierre,

Jaff. Nay never doubt, but truft me.
What, be a Devil ! take a Damning Oath
For flnedding native blood ! can there be a fin
In merciful repentance $ Oh this Villain.

Enter Renault.

Renault. Perverfe] andpeevifh! what a flave is Man 1
To let his itching flefh thus get the better of him !
Difpatch the Tool her Husband — that we're well.
Who's there ** J of. A Man.

Ren. My Friend , my near Ally !
The hoftage of your faith, my beauteous Charge, is very well.

*Jaff. Sir, are you fure of that <
Stands (lie in perfect health i beats her pulfe v even £
Neither too hot nor cold f

m». What means that queftion f

Jaff. Oh Women have fantaftick Conftitutions ,
Inconftant as their Wifhes, always wavering,
And ne're fixt 5 was it not boldly done
Even at firft fight to truft the Thing Ilov'd
(A tempting Treafure too I ) with Youth fo fierce
And vigorous as thine i but thou art honeft.

Ren. Who dares accufe me?

jfajfl Curft be him that doubts F 2 Thy



3 6 Venice Prefer)?' d , or

Thy virtue, I havetry'dit, and declare ,
Were I to choofe a Guardian of my Honour
I'd put it into thy keeping : for I know thee,
Ren. Know me I

Jaffl Ay know thee: There's no falfehood in thee.
Thou look'ft juft as thou art : Let us embrace.
Now would'it thou cut my Throat or I cut thine i
Ren. You dare not do't. J :i jf' You lye Sir.

Ren. How ! Jaff. No more.

'lis a bale World, and muft reform , that's all.

£#^rSpinofa, Theodore, Eliot, Revellido, Durand,
Brain veil, and the reB of the Conspirators.
Ren. Spinofa / Theodore / . Spin. The fame :

Ren. You are welcome t Spin. You are trembling, Sir,

Ren. 3 !is a cold Night indeed, I am Aged ,
Full of decay and natural infirmities. 5 [Pierre re-enters

We (hall be warm, my Friend, I hope to morrow.

Pierr. 'T was not well done, thou mou'd'ft have ftroakt him
and not have gali'd him.

Jaff. Damn him, let him chew on't.
Heav'n ! where am I? befet with curfed Fiends ,
That wait to Damn me : What a Devil's man ,
When he forgets his nature — hulh my heart.

Ren* My Friends, 'tis late : are we aflembled all i
Where y s iheodore? Theo. At hand.

Ren. Spinofi. Spin. Here.

Ren. Brainveil. Brain. I am ready,

Ren. Bur and and Brabe ,
Bttr. Command us,
We are both prepared I

Ren. U\4ezzana> Revellido,
Ternon Retrcji ; Oh you are Men I find
Fit to behold your Fate, and meet her Summons V c X
To morrow's rifing Sun muft fee you all
Deckt in your honours I are the Souldiers ready <
Omn. All, all.

Ren. You, Burand, with your thou fan d muft pofiefs
St. Marks ^ You, Captain, know your charge already ;
5 Tis to fecure the Ducal Palace : you
Brabe with a hundred more muft gain the Secgue.



J flot Difioverd.' 37

With therlike tw\X$yttBrAinveil' to the Trocuratte.
Be all this done with the ieaft tumult podible,

Till in each place you poll diffident guards :

Then (heath your Swords in every bread you meet.
Jaff. Oh reverend Cruelty: Damn'd bloody Villain!
Ren, During this Execution, DuranA, you

Muft in the mid'll keep your Battalia faft ,

And rhcodore be fu re to plant the Canon

That may Command the Greets ; whilft Revellido,

iJWezzana, Ternon and Retrofi , Guard you.

(This done ! ) weel give the General Alarm ,

Apply Petards, and force the Arsnal Gates-

Then fire the City round in feveral places.

Or with our Canon ( if it dare refill )

Batterer to Ruin. But above all I charge you

Shed blood enough , fpare neither Sex nor Age ,

Name nor Condition ; if there live a Senator

After to morrow, tho the dulleft Rogue

That er'e faid nothing , we have loft our ends j*

If poflible , lets kill the very Name

Of Senator 3 .and bury it in blood.

faff. Mercilefs, horrid flave ! — Ay, blood enough 1
Shed blood enough , old Renault : how thou charm'ft me I

Ren. But one thing more , and then farewell till Fate
Join us again 5 or (eparate us ever 1
Firft, let's embrace, Heav'n knows who next fhall thus
Wing ye together: But let's all remember
We wear no common Gaufe upon our Swords ,
Let each Man think that on his fingle Virtue
Depends the Good and Fame of all the reft ;
Eternal Honour or perpetual Infamy.
Let's remember, through what dreadful hazards
PropXious, Fortune hitherto has led us ,
How often on the brink of feme difcovery
have we flood tottering , and yet (till kept our ground
So well, the bufieft fearchers ne'r could follow
Thofe fubtle Tracks which puzzled all fufpition :
You droop Sir.

Jaff. No: with a moft profound attention
I've hard it all, and wonder at thy vertue.



1 8 Venice (PreferVi, ar

Ren. Though there be yet few hours 'twixt them and Ruin j
Are not the Senate lull'd in full fecurity ,
Quiet and fatisfy'd , as Fools are always I
Never did fo profound repofe forerun
Calamity fo great: Nay our good Fortune
Has blinded the moft piercing of Mankind :
Strengthen'd the fearfuli'ft: , eharm'd the mod: fufpecHul ,'
Confounded the moft fubtle : for we live ,
We live my Friends, and quickly (hall our Life
Prove fatal to thefe Tyrants : Let's confider
That wc deftroy Oppreflion , Avarice*,
A People nurft up equally with Vices
And loathfome Lufts , which Nature moft abhors ,
And fuch as without fhame me cannot fuffer.
faff. Oh Befoidera, take me to thy Arms
And (hew me where's my Peace, for I've loft it. {Ex. Jaff.

Ren. Without the leaft remorfe then let's refolve
With Fire and Sword ^exterminate thefe Tyrants,
And when we mall behold thofe curft Tribunals ,
Stain'd by the Tears and fuflferings of the Innocent,
Burning with flames rather from Heav'n than ours,
The raging furious and unpitying Souldier
Pulling his reeking Dagger from the bofoms
Of galping Wretches , Death in every Quarter ,
With all that fad diforder can produce ,
To make a Spectacle of horror : Then ,
Then let's call to mind , my deareft Friends,
That there's nothing pure upon the Earth.,
That the moft valu'd things have moft allays ,
And that in change of all thofe vile Enormities ,
Under whofe weight this wretched Country labours ,
The Means are only in our hands to Crown them. r v

Vierr. And may thofe Powers above that are propicioug\
^o gallant minds record this Caufe , and blefs it,

Ren. Thus happy, thus fecure of all we wifh for ,
Should there my Friends be found amongftusone
Falfe to this glorious Enterprize, what Fate,
What Vengeance were enough for fuch a Villian f

Eliot. Death here without repentance. Hell hereafter.

Ken. Let that be my lott , if as here I ftand
lifted by Fate amongft her darling Sons , Tho



Tho I had one only Brother , dear by all

The ftri&eft ties of Mature; tho one hour

Had given us birth , one Fortune fed our wants".

One only love , and that but of each other ,

Still fill'd our minds : Gould I have fuch a Friend

Joyn'd in this Caufe 3 and had but ground to fear

Meant fowl play ; may this right hand drop from me J

If I'd not hazard all my future peace,

And ftabb him to the heart before you t who

Would not do lefs i Would'ft not thou Pierre the fame i

Pierr. You have fingied me, Sir, out for this hard queflion 9
As if 'twere ftarted only for my fake 1
Am I the thing you fear i Here, here's my bdfom ,
Search it with all your Swords / am I a Traytor t

Ren, No: but I fear your late commended Friend
Is little le(s : Come Sirs, *tis now no time
To trifle with our fafety. Where's this Jaffeir ?

Spino. He left the room juft now in ftrange diforder.'

Ren. Nay, there is danger in him : I obferv'd him > y
During the time I took for Explanation ,
He was tranfported from moft deep attention
To a confufion which he could not fmother.
His looks grew full of fadnefsand furprize.
All which betrayM a wavering Spirit in him 3
That laboured with reluctancy and forrow $.
What's requifite for fafety mud be done
With fpeedy Execution: he remains ,
Yet in our power : I for my own part wear
A Dagger.

Pi err. Well.

Ren, And I could wi(h it /

Pierr. Where c

Rew Bury'd in his heart-

P/err, Away/ w'are yet all friends*
No more of this, 'twill Breed ill blood amongfi? us.

Spin. Let us all draw our Swords, and feareh the houfej,
Full him from the dark hole where he fits brooding
O're his cold fears, and each man kill his fllare of Him. .

Pierr. Who talks of killing £ who*s he'll Hied the blootf"
That's dear to me£ is*t you f or you? or you Sit t



4-o yenicc 'rrejerva , or

What not one fpeak ? how you : !;jnd gaping ail

On your grave Oracle, your woouen Cod there*

Yet not a word: Then Sir I'i teil. you a fecret ,

Sufpition's but at bed a Cowards Virtue ! [To Ren.

Ren. A Coward — [ Handles bU Sword;

Tier. Put, put up thy Sword, old Man ,.
Thy hand (hakes at it -, come let's heal this breach ,
1 am too hot: we yet may live Friends.

Spina. Till we are fafe, our Friendship cannot be Co.

Pierr, Again: who's that i

Spino. Twas I.

Xbeoi And- 1.

Revell. And I.

Eliot. And all.

Ren. Who are on my fide *

Spinof. Every honed Sword ,
Let's die like men and not be fold like Slaves.

Pierr. One fuch word more, by Heav n Fl to the Senate
And hang ye all, like Dogs in Cluders,
Why peep your Coward Swords half out their fliells t .
Why do you not all brandiih them like mine?
Vou fear to die, and yet dare talk of Killing ?

Ren. Goto the Senate and betray us, liaden,
Secure thy wretched life , we fear to die
Lefs than thou dar'ft be honed.

Pierr. That's rank falfehood,
Fear'ft not thou death * fy, there's a knavifli itch
In that fait blood , an utter foe to fmarting.
Had jAfjeirs Wife prov'd kind, he had dill been true.
Fob — . how that ftinks ?

Thou dyi thou kill my Friend! or thou, or thou ,
Or thou, with that lean wither'd wretched Face I
Away ! difperfe ail to your feveral Charges ,
And meet to morrow where your honour calls you , p , V
Pi bring that man, whofe blood you fo much third for ,
And you fhall fee him venture for you fairly —
Hence, hence, I fay. [£x, Renault angrily,

spino. I fear we have been too blame ,
And done too much.-

iheo. Twas too farr urg'd sgainfl the man you Iov'd.

Revl



A Plot Difcoverd. 41

Rev, Here, take our Swords and crufti 'em with your feet.

Spino. Forgive us, gallant Friend.

Peir. Nay, now y' have found
The way to melt and caft me as you will :
I'll fetch this Friend and give him to your merey :
Nay he fhall dye if you will take him from me s
For your repofe I'll quit my hearts Jewel $
But would not have him torn away by Villains
And ipitefull villany.

Spina. No 5 may you both
For ever live and fill the world with fame !

Peir. Now you are too kind. Whence rofe all this diicord }
Oh what a dangerous precipice have we fcap'dl
How near a fall was all we had long been building !
What an eternal blot had ftain'd our glories,
If one the braveft and the beft of men
Had fallen a Sacrifice to ra(h (ufpicion !
Butcher'd by thole whole Caufe he came to cherifh :
Oh could you know him all as I have known him,
How good he is, how juft, how true, how brave,
You wou'dnot leave this place till you had ieen him 5
Humbled yourfelves before him, kifs'd his feet.
And gain'd remiffion for the worft of follies 5
Come but to morrow all your doubts Jijail end %
And to your Loves me better recommend^
That I've prefervd your Fame, and, favd my Friend,

[Exeunt omnes*

The end of the third A&%



ACT

-.Jr > Enter JarTeir and Belvidera.

Jaffl yc "w rHere doft thou lead me ? Every ftep I move,
VV Methinks I tread upon fome mangled Limb
Of a rackd Friend : Oh my dear charming ruine !
Where are we wandring }
Bel. To eternal Honour 5

G To



42 Venice Frefervd^ or

To doe a deed fhall Chronicle thy name,
Among the glorious Legends of thofe few
That have (av'd (inking Nations : thy Renown
Shall be the future Song of all the Virgins,
Who by thy piety have been preferv'd
From horrid violation : Every Street
Shall be adorn'd with Statues to thy honour,
And at thy feet this great Infcription written,

Remember him that profd the fall of Venice.

Jaffl Rather, Remember him, who after all
The iacred Bonds of Oaths and holyer Friendfhip
In fond companion to a Womans tears
Forgot his Manhood, Vertue, truth and Honour^
To facririce the Bofom that reliev'd him.
Why wilt thou damn me?

Bel. Oh inconftant man !
How will you promife ? how will you deceive ? .
Do, return back, re-place me in my Bondage,
Tell all thy Friends how dangeroufly thou lovft me 3
And let thy Dagger doe its bloudy office.
Oh that kind Dagger, Jajfeir^ how twill look
Stuck through my hearty drench'd in my blond. to- th' hilts !
Whilft thefe poor dying eyes (hall with- their tears
No more torment thee, then thou wilt be free :
Or if thou think'ft it nobler, Let me live
Till I am a Vi&im to the hatefuil luft
Of that Infernal Devil, that old Fiend
That's Damn'd himfelf and wpu'd undoe Mankind :
Lad night, my Love !

Jafp Name, name it not again.
It Ihews a beaftly Image to my fancy 5
Will wake me into madnels. Oh the Villain I
That durft approach fuch purity as thine
On terms fo vile : Deftrucliion, fwift deftru&ion
Fallon my Coward- head, and make my Name
The common (corn of Fools if I forgive him 3
If I forgive him, if I not revenge
With utmoft rage, and moft unftaying fury,
Thy (ufferings thou dear darling of my life, Love.
Mel. Delay no longer then, but to the Senate 5

And



A Plot Difcoverd. 4-3

And tell the difmalft ftory e'r was utter'd,
Tell em what bloudfhed, rapines, defolations,
Have been prepar'd, how near's the fatal hour !
Save thy poor Country, fave the Reverend bloud
Of all its Nobles, which to morrows Dawn
Muft el(e fee died : Save the poor tender lives
Of all thofe little Infants which the Swords
Of muitherers are whetting for this moment 5
Think thou already hearft their dying (creams,
Think that thou (eeft their fad diftra&ed Mothers
Kneeling before thy feet, and begging pity
With torn difhevel'd hair and dreaming eyes,
Their naked mangled breafts befmeard with bloud,
And even the Milk with which their fondled Babes,
Softly they hulh'd, dropping in anguifh from 'em.
Think thou feeft this, and then confult thy heart.

faff. Oh !
. Bel. Think too, If thou lofe this prefent minute,
What miferiesthe next day bring upon thee.
Imagine all the horrours of that night
Murther and Rapine, Wafte and Defblation,
Confufedly ranging. Think what then may prove
My Lot ! the Raviiher may then come fafe,
And midft the terrour of the publick ruine
Doe a damn 'd deed 5 perhaps to lay a Train
May catch thy life 3 then where will be revenge,
The dear revenge that's due to fuch a wrong ?

Jaffi By all Heavens powers Prophetick truth dwells in thee 5
For every word thou fpeak'ft ftrikes through my heart
Like a new light, and (hows it how 't has wander'd 5
Juft what th' haft made me, take me, Belvidera^
And lead me to the place where I'm to (ay
This feitter LelTon, where I muft betray
My/mtrv my vertue, conftancy and friends :
Muft I betray my friends } Ah take me quickly,
Secure me well before that thought's renew cl 5
If I relapfe once more, all's loft for ever.

Bel. Haft thou a friend more dear than Belvidera .<?

Jaff. No, th' art my Soul it felfj wealth, friendiliip, honour.
All preient joys 3 and earned of all future,

G 2 Are



44 Venice Prefervd, or

Are fumm'd in thee : methinks when in thy ataies
Thus leaning on thy bread, one minute's more
Than a long thoufand years of vulgar hours.
Why was fuch happinefs not given me pure ? ^ '

Why dafh'd with cruel wrongs, and bitter wantings }
Come, lead me forward now like a tame Lamb
To Sacrifice, thus in his fatal Garlands,
Deck'd fine and pleased, The wanton skips and plays,
Trots by the enticing flittering Priefiefs (ide?
And much tranjported with his little pride,
Forgets his dear Companions of the plain
Till by Her, bound, Hees on the Altar layn
Tet then too hardly bleats, fuch pleafures in the pain. t
Enter Officer and 6 Guards
Offic. Stand who goes there ?
Bel. Friends..

Jajf. Friends, Belvidera I hide me from my Friends,
By Heaven I'd rather fee the face of Hell,
Than meet the man I love.

Offic. But what friends are you ?
Bel. Friends to the Senate and the State of Venice.
Offic My orders are to feize on all I find
.At this late hour, and bring em to the Council,
Who now are fitting-

Jaff. Sir, you (hall be obey'd.
Hold, Brutes, ftand off, none of your paws upon me.
Now the Lot's caft, and Fate doe what thou wilt.

[Exeunt guarded,

SCENE The Senate-hou[e r

Where appear fitting, the Duke of Venice , Prinli, Antonio,.
And Eight other Senators.

Duke. Antony^ Prinli, Senators of Venice^
Speak ty why are we alTemhled here this night ?
What have you to inform us of, concerns.
The State ofFenice x honour, or its fafety ? re , :

Prin* Could words exprefs the ftory I have to tell you,
Fathers 3 thefe tears were ufele% thefe fad tears



A F lot Discover d. 45

That fall from my old eyes$ bat there is caufe
We all (hould weep $ tear off chefe purple r\obes,
And wrap our (elves in Sackcloth, fitting down
On the fad Earth, and cry aloud to Heaven.
Heaven knows if yet there be an hour to come
E'r Venic§ be no more I

All Sent"- How !

Prtn. Nay we ftand \Vc

Upon the Very brink of gaping rurne,
Within this City's form'd a dark Confpiracy,
To maiTacre us all, our Wives and Children,
Kindred and Friends, our Palaces and Temples
To lay in A(hes : nay the hour too, -fixt 5
The Swords, for ought I know, drawn even this moment,
And the wild Wafte begun : from unknown hands
I had this warning : but if we are men
Let's not be tamely butcher'd, but doe fbmething
That may inform the world in after Ages,
Our Virtue was not ruin'd though we were. [A noife without.
Pvoom, room, make room for (bme Prifbners— —

2 Senat. Let's raile the City.

Enter Officer and Guard,

Prin. Speak there, what difturbance .<?

Offic Two Prifoners have the Guard feiz'd in the Streets^
Who fay they come to inform this Reverend Senate
About the prefent danger.

Enter Jaffeir and Belvidera guarded,

AH. Give 'em entrance-
Well, who are you .«?

Jaff. A Villain.

Anto. Short and pithy.
The man (peaks well.

JaJfflWonld every man that hears me
WouPfdeaj (b honeftly, and own his title.

Duke. 'Tis rumour'd that a Plot has beencontrivU
Again(t this State 5 that you have a (hare in't too..
If you are a Villain, to redeem your honour,
Unfold the truth and be reftor'd with Mercy.

Jaff. Think not that I to fave my life come hither,
I know its value better $ but in pit$

its*



46 Venice Prefervd, or

To all thole wretches whole unhappy dooms
Are fix'd and feal'd. You (ee me here before you,
The fwornand Covenanted foe of Venice.
But ule me as my dealings may delerve
And I may prove a friend.

Dnke. The Slave Capitulates,
Give him the Tortures. H ■

Jaff. That you dare not doe,
Your fears won't let you, nor the longing Itch
To hear a (lory which you dread the truth of.
Truth with the fear of frhart ihall ne'r get from me.
Cowards are (card with threatnings. Boys arewhipt
Into confeffions : but a Steady mind
Adts of its felf, ne'r asks the body Counfell.
Give him the Tortures. Name but fiich a thing
Again 5 by Heaven Til (hut thefe lips for ever,
Not all your t\acks> youE Engines, or your Wheels
Shall force a groan away — > -that you may guels at.

Anto. A bloudy minded fellow Til warrant 5
A damn'd bloudy minded fellow.

Duke. Name your Conditions.

Jaffi For my (elf full pardon,
Befides the lives of two and twenty friends [Delivers a lift.
Whole names are here inroll'd : Nay, let their Crimes
Be ne'r Co monftrous, I muft have the Oaths
And (acred promife of this Reverend Council,
That in a full Aflembly of the Senate
The thing I ask be ratifi'd. Swear this,
And I'll unfold the fecrets of your danger.

All. Wee'l (wear.

Du{e. Propole the Oath.

Jaffl By all the hopes
Ye have of Peace and Happinefs hereafter.
Swear. v

All. Weallfwear.

Jaff. To grant me what I've ask'd,
Ye fwear.

All. We (wear. j

Jaffl And as ye keep the Oath,
May you and vour posterity be bleft

Or



A Plot Dijcoverd 47

Or curft for ever.

M Elfe be curft for ever, --\ *y® -$

^^ —Then here's the lift, and with't the ttidihri Wp-
full difclofe of all that threatens you. YfhWf&per.

Now Fate thou haft caught me.

Anto. Why what a dreadful! Catalogue of Cut-throats is here !
I'll warrant you not one of thefe fellows but has ; a face like a
Lion. I dare not fo much as reade their names over.

Duke, Give orders that all diligent fearch fee made '■-■ '•■
To (eize thefe men, their characters are publkk,
The paper intimates their Rendevouz
To be at the houfe of a fam'd Grecian Curtezan
Call'd Aquilina 5 fee that place fecur'd.

Anto, What my Nicky Nacky 5 Hurry Durry> Nicky Nacky

in the Plot I'll make a Speech. Moft noble Senators,

What headlong apprehenfion drives you on,

Right noble, wife and truly folid Senators,

To violate the Eaws and right of Nations ? { &

The Lady is a Lady of renown.

Tis true, (he holds a houfe of fair Reception,

And though I fay 'c my felf, as many more

Can fay as well as I. $6imd

2 Sena. My Lord, long Speeches ' «&■•!
Are frivolous here, when dangers are fo near us* -5"
We all well know your Intereft in that Lady,
The world talks loud ont.

Anto. Verily I have done,- A

I fay no more.

DUke. But fince he has declard
Himfelf concern'd, Pray, Captain, take great caution
To treat the fair one, as becomes her Character,
And let her Bed-chamber be learch'd with decency.
You, Jifffiir^ muft with patience bear till morning, tobe©w
Priforj'^ ,

Jaffl Would the Chains of death
Had bound mefafte'rl had knownthis minute 3
I've done a deed will make my Story hereafter
Quoted in competition with all ill ones : uo 't !

The Hiftory of my wickednefs (hall run ra »' P
Down through the low traditions of the vulgar ?

And



4§ Venice Pfejervdy or

And Boys be thought to tell the tale of Jtffeir*

Du{e. Captain, withdraw your Prifoner.
- Jaff. Sir, if poffible,

Lead me where my own thoughts themfelves may lofe me,
Where I may doze out what I've left of life 3
Forget my (elf and this days guilt and faKehood.
Cruel remembrance how fhqll I appeafe thee ! ^RxrgHaxdcd.

2V?£/e_ without.
More Traitors, room, room, make room there.

Duke. How's this, Guards?
Where are our Guards ? (hut up the Gates, the Treafbn J s alrea-
dy at our Dores. mn&m ■• AuoAsfa n

Enter Officer, • 1 £ D

Offic. My-t^ords, more Traitors :

Seiz'd in the very ad: of Conmltation,

FurniuYd with Arms and InftrumeTits of mifchief,
Bring in the prifoners.;^

Enter Peirre, Kenan k^ 3?h'e$d0r& [EJHo^ ReviBido, ;oT
and other Confpirators, in fitters, guarded.

Pe/rr. You, my Lords, and Fathers, .
( As you arepleas'd to call your felves) of Venice 5
If you (it here to guide the courfe of Juftice, s ygt nsD

Why thefe difgracefull chair^^pon the limbs § c

That have fo often laboured in your- (ervice?
Are the(e the wreaths of triumphs ye bellow
On thofe that bring youConquefts home and Honours >

Duke. Goon, you (hall be heard,. Sir.

Auto, And be hang'd too, I hope.

Peirr, Are thefe the Trophies I've deferv'd forr fighting
Your Battels with confederated Powers,
When winds and Seas conlpirM to overthrow you ?
And brought the Fleets of S$ain to your own Harbours,
When you, great Ij>uke, %unk trernbling in your Palace,
And (aw your Wife 6 th'Adriatick, plough'd
Like a lew'd Whore by bolder Prows than yours
Stept not I forth, and taughtyour loofe Venetians.
The task of honour and the way togreatnefs,
Rais'd you from your capitulating fears
Toftipulate the terms of fu'd for peace,
And this my recompence? If I am a Traitor

Produce



A riot DiJCGver d. 42

Produce my charge 3 or (hew the wretch that's bafe enough
And brave enough to tell me I am a Traitor.

Duke. Know you one Jaffeir ? [Alltheconftirators murmur \

Peirr. Yes, and know his Vertue.
His Juftice, Truth, his general Worth and Sufferings
From a hard father taught me firft to love him.
Enter JafTeir guarded,

Duke. See him brought forth.

Peirr. My friend too bound ? nay then
Our Fate has conquer'd us, and we mull: fall,
Why droops the man whole welfare's fo much mine
They're but one thing? thefe Reverend Tyrants, Jaffeir^
Gall us all Traitors, art thou one, my Brother }

Jaffi To thee I am the falfeft, veryeft (lave
That e'r betray 'd a generous trailing friend.
And gave up honour to be fure of ruine.
All our fair hopes which morning was to have crown'd
Has this curft tongue o'rthrown.

Peirr. So, then all's over :
Venice has loft her freedom 3 I my life 3 ;
No more, farewell. v .

Duke. Say 3 will you make confeffion
Of your vile deeds and truft the Senates mercy ?

Peirr. Curft be your Senate : Curft your Conllitution i
The Curfe of growing factions and divifion
Still vex your Councils, (hake your publick fafety,
And make the Robes of Government, you wear,
Hatefull to you, as thefe bafe Chains to me.

Duke. Pardon or death ?

Peirr. Death, honourable death.

Renault. Death'sthe beft thing we ask or you can give.

All Con/pir. No ftiamefull bonds, but honourable death.

Duke^ Break up the Council ; Captain, guard your prifoners,
Jaffijm y'are free, but thele muft wait for judgment.

cf [Ex. all the Senators.

Peirr. Come, where's my Dungeon } lead me to my ftraw :
It will not be the firft time I've lodg'd hard
To doe your Senate iervice. > '

JaJ\ Hold one moment.

Peirr. Who's he difputes the Judgment of the Senate ?

H Pre-



50 Venice Preferv'd, or

Prefumptuous Elebel on [Strikes Jaff.

Jfffi By Heaven you ftir not.
I muft be heard ? I muft have leave to fpeak :
Thou haft difgrac'd me, Peirre^ by a vile blow :
Had not a dagger done thee nobler juftice ?
Butufeme as thou wilt, thou canft not wrong me,
For I am fallen beneath the bafeft injuries 3
Yet look upon me with an eye of mercy,
With pity and with charity behold me 3
Shut not thy heart againft a friend's repentance,
But as there dwells a God-like nature in thee
Liften with mildnefs to my fupplications.

Peirr. What whining Monk art thou } what holy cueat
That wou dft encroach upon my credulous ears
And cant'ft thus vilely ? hence. I know thee nor,
Diflemble and be nafty : leave me, Hippocrite.

Jaff. Not know me, PeirYe #

Peirr. No, know the not : what art thou?

Jaff. Jaffeir, thy friend, thy once lov'd, valu'd friend,
Though now defervedly fcorn'd, and us^d moft hardly.

Peirr. Thou Jaffeir ! Thou my once lov'd, valu'd friend !
By Heavens thou ly'ft , the man, fb call'd, my friend,
Was generous, honeft, faithful!, juft and valiant,
Noble in mind, and in his perfon lovely,
Dear to my eyes and tender to my heart :
But thou a Wretched bale, falie, worthleis Coward,
Poor even in Soul, and loathiome in thy afpeft,
All eyes muft (hun thee, and all hearts deteft thee.
Prithee avoid, nor longer cling thus round me,
Like fbmething banefull, that my nature's chill'd at.

Jaff. I have not wrong'd thee, by thele tears I have not.
But (till am honeft, true, and hope too, valiant, -
My mind ftill full of thee : therefore ftill noble, c

Let not thy eyes then fhun me , nor thy heart
Deteft me utterly : Oh look upon me
Look back and fee my fad lincere fubmiffion 1
How my heart fwells., as even 'twould bur ft my bofbm , '
Fond of its Gaol, and labouring to be at thee I
What (hall I doe? ,what fay to make thee hear me ?

Peirr. Haft thou not wrong d me? dar'ft thou call thy felf



A riot jjijcover a. % f

Jaffeir, that once lov'd, valued friend of mine,
And fwear thou haft not wrong'd me ? whence thefe chains }
Whence the vile death, which I may meet this moment >
Whence this difhonour, but from thee, thou falfe one >

Jaff. . — All's true, yet grant one thing, and I've done asking,

Peirr. What's that >

Jaff. To take thy life on fuch conditions
The Council have propos'd : Thou and thy friends
May yet live long, and to be better treated.

Peirr. Life ! ask my life ! confefs ! record my felf
A villain for the privilege to breath,
And carry up and down this curfed City
A difcontented and repining fpirit,
Burthenfbme to it felf a few years longer,
To lofe, it may be, at laft in a lewd quarrel
For lome new friend, treacherous and falfe as thou art !
No, this vile world and I have long been jangling,
And cannot part on better terms than now,
When onely men like thee are fit to live in't.

Jaff By all that's juft—

Peirr. Swear by fbme other powers,
For thou haft broke that (acred Oath too lately.

3 a ff Then by that hell I merit, I'll not leave thee,
Till to thy felf at leaft, thou rt reconcil'd,
However thy refentments deal with me.

Peirr. Not leave me 1

Jaff No., thou (halt not force me from thee,
life me reproachfully, and like a flave,
Tread on me, buffet me, heap wrongs on wrongs
On my poor head 5 I'll bear it all with patience,
Shall weary out thy moft unfriendly cruelty,
Ly at thy feet and kifs em though they fpurn me,
Till,^ wounded bymyfurTerings, thou relent,
And raife^me to thy armes with dear forgivenefs.

reirr. Art thou not .

Jaff. What?

Peirr. A Traitor }

Jaff. Yes.

Peirr. A Villain?

Jaff. Granted.

H 2 Prin*



52 Venice Prefervd, or

Peirr. A Coward, a moft fcandalous Coward,
Spiritlefs, void of honour, one who has fold
Thy everlafting Fame, for fhamelels life >

Jaffi All, all, and more,much more : my faults are Numberlefi*
Peirr. And wouldft thou have me live on terms like thine ?
Bafe as thou art falfe — —

faff* No, 'tis tome that's granted,
The fafety of thy life was all Iaim'd at,
In recompence for faith, and truft fo broken.

Peirr. I fcorn it more becaufe preferv'd by thee.
And as when firft my foolifti heart took pity
On thy misfortunes, fought thee in thy mileries,
Relieved thy wants, and £ais'd thee from thy State
Of wretchednefs in which thy fate had plung'd thee,
To rank thee in my lift of noble friends.
All I receiv'd in furety for thy truth,
Were unregarded oaths , and this, this dagger,
Given with a worthlefs pledge, thou fi nee haft ftoln,
So I reftore it back to thee again,
Swearing by all thole powers which thou haft violated,
Never from this curs'd hour to hold communion,
Friendftiip or intereft with thee, though our years
Were to exceed thofe limited the world. >

Take it — farewell — ibr now I owe thee nothing.
Jaff. Say thou wilt live then.
Peirr, For my life, difpofe it
Juft as thou wilt, becaufe tis what I'm tir'd with*
Jaff. Oh, Peirre 1
Peirr. No more.

3 a Jfi My eyes won't lofe the fight of thee,
But languifti after thine, and ake with gazing.

Peirr. Leave me— — Nay, then thus, thus, I throw thee
from me. j

And cur/es, great as is thy falsehood, catch thee. ( *

Jaffi Amen.
He's gone, my father, friend, prefer ver, _ .

And here's the portion he has left me. [Holds the dagger up'.

This dagger, wellremembred, with this dagger
I gave a folemn vow of dire importance,
Parted with this and Belvidera together 5

Have



A Plot Vifcoverd.. S3

Have&care, Mem'ry, drive that thought no farther 5
No, I'll efteem itj as a friend's laft legacy,
Treafure it up in this wretched bofbm,
Where it may grow acquainted with my heart,
That when they meet, they ftart not from each other $
So 5 now for thinking: A blow, cal I'd Traitor, Villain^
Coward^ dithonoura)ble coward, fogh I
Oh for a long found fleep, and fo forget it !
Down, bufie Devil — - — .

Enter Belvidera.

Bel. Whither (hall I fly >
Where hide me and my mileries together }
Where's now the Roman Conftancy I boafted 4
Sunk into trembling fears and defperation ! ;

Not daring now to look up to that dear face
Which us'd to (mile even oh my faults, but down
Bending thefe miferable eyes to earth,
Muft move in penance , and implore much Mercy.

Jajf. Mercy, kind Heaven has forely endlefs (lores
Hoarded for thee of bleffings yet untafted 3
Let wretches loaded hard with guilt as I am,
Bow the weight and groan beneath the burthen,
Creep with a remnant of that ftrength th' have left,
Before the footftool of that Heaven th' have injur d.
Oh Belvidera! I'm the wretched ft creature
E'r crawl'd on earth s now if thou haft V T ertue help me,
Take me into thy Armes, and fpeak the words of peace
To my 'divided Soul, that wars within me,
And raifes every Senfe to my confufion 5
By Heav'n I am tottering on the very brink
Of Peaces and thou art, all the hold I've left.

Bel. Ala(s ! I know thy forrows are moft mighty^
I knovj th'haft caufe to mourn 5 to mourn, my Jajfcir y
Withendl^ls cries, and never xeafing waitings,
Th Jl naftloft —

Jajf. Oh I have loft what can't be counted 5
My friend too, Belvidera, that dear friend,
Who, next to thee, was all my health rejoyc'd in,
Has us'd me like a (laves (hamefully us a me 5
T would break thy pitying heart to hear the ftory,

What



54 Venice Prefervd, or

What (hall I doe } refentment, indignation,
Love, pity, fear and mem'ry, how I've wrong'd him,
Diftraft my quiet with the very thought on'r,
And tear my heart to pieces in my bofome.

Bel. What has he done ?

faff. Thou'dft hate me, fhould I tell thee.

Bel. Why %

Jaff. Oh he has us'd me ! yet by Heaven I bear it $
He has us'd me, Belvidera, but firft fwear
That when I've told thee, thoult not loath me utterly,
Though vileft blots and ftains appear upon me 3
But (till at leaft with charitable goodnefs,
Be near me in the pangs of my aflli&ion,
Not (corn me, Behidera^ as he has done.

Bel. Have I then e 5 r been falfe that now I am doubted ?
Speak, whats the caufe I am grown into diftruft,
Why thought unfit to hear my Love's complainings }

fag Oh !

Bel. Tell me.

Jaffl Bear my failings, for they are many,
Oh my dear Angel ! in that friend^Fve loft
All my Soul's peace 3 for every thought of him
Strikes my Senfe hard, and deads it in my brains 5
Wouldft thou believe it ?

Bel. Speak.

Jaff, Before we parted,
E'r yet his Guards had led him to his prifon.
Full of fevereft for rows for his fufPrings,
With eyes o'rflowing and a bleeding heart,
Humbling my lelf almoft beneath my nature 5
As at his feet I kneel'd, and fu'd for mercy,
Forgetting all our friendship, all the dearnefs,
In which w' have liv'd fb many years together,
With a reproachfull hand, he dafli'd a blow,



\



\



He (truck me, Belvidera^ by Heaven, he ftruck me,
Buffeted, caird me Traitor, Villain, Coward 3
Am I a Coward } am I a Villain } tell me :
Th'art the beft Judge, and mad'ft me, if I am fa
Damnation 3 Coward !

Bel Oh 1 forgive him, Jaffeir.

And



Z\ I Wl JUlJLUUCf 11. S«j

And if his fufFerings wound thy heart already,
What will they doe to morrow >

Bel. To morrow,
When thou (halt fee him ftretch'd in all the Agonies
Of a tormenting and a (hamefull death,
His bleeding bowels, and his broken limbs,
Inluked o'r by a vile butchering villain 5
What will thy heart doe then ? Oh fure 't will dream
Like my eyes now.

Jaff. What means thy dreadfull ftory ?
Death, and to morrow ? broken limbs and bowels }
Infulted o'r by a vile butchering Villain ?
By all my fears I (hall ftart out tcf madnefs,
With barely gueffingif the truth's hid longer.

Bel. The faithlefs Senators, 'tis they've decree'd it :
They fay according to our friends requeft,
They (hall have death, and not ignoble bondage :
Declare their proffiis'd mercy all as forfeited,
Fahe to their oaths, and deaf to interceflion ^
Warrants are pals'd for publick death to morrow.

Jaff. Death ! doom'd to die ! condemn'd unheard I unpleaded !

Bel. Nay, cruel'ft racks and torments are preparing,
To force confeffions from their dying pangs 3
Oh do. not look fo terribly upon me,
How your lips {hake, and all your face diforderd !
What means my Love ?

Jaff. Leave me, I charge thee leave me— ftrong temptations
Wake in my heart.

Bel. For what }

Jaff. No more, but leave me.

Bel. Why >

Jaff Oh! by Heaven I love thee with that fondnefs
I woi^id not have thee ftay a moment longer,
NeAr thefe curft hands : are they not cold upon thee ?

Bel. No, everlafting comfort's in thy armes, C p .f s tbe fw
To lean thus on thy breaft is fofter eafe \ yjjf Zll pm &

Than downy pillows deck'd with leaves of ro(es. C baci^agen.

Jaff. Alas thou thinkeft not of the thorns 'tis fill'd with,
Fly e'r they call thee : there's a lurking. (erpent,



Ready to leap and fting thee to thy heart:
Art thou not terrifTd >„

Bel. No.

Jaff. Call to mind
What thou haft done, and whither thou haft brought me.

Bel. Hah !

'jaff. Where's my friend > my friend, thou fmiling mifchief >
Nay, (brink not, now 'tis too late, thou (houldft have fled
When thy Guilt firft had caufe, for dire revenge,
Is up and raging for my friend. He groans,
Hark how he groans, his (creams are in my ears
^Already '-, fee, th'have fixt him on the wheel,

And now they tear him Murther ! perjur'd Senate !

Murther — Oh!— hark thee, Traitrefs, thou haft done this 3
Thanks to thy tears and falfe perfwading love, J Fumbling for
How her eyes (peak ! Oh thou bewitching creature ft his Dagger.
Mad nels cannot hurt thee^ Gome, thou little trembler^
Creep, even into my heart, and there lie (ate 3

Tis thy own Cittadel hah— yet (land o£F 9

Heaven muft have Juftice, and my broken vows
Will fink me elfe beneath its reaching mercy 3
I'll wink and then 'tis done- .

Bel. What means the Lord :
Of me, my life and love, what's in thy bofom,
Thou grafpft at (b> nay, why am I thus treated ? 5 Draws the dagger,
What wilt thou doe > Ah, do not kill me, Jaffeir, 1°$ rs t0 ft ab her.
Pity thefe panting breads, and trembling limbs,
That us cl to clafp thee when thy looks were milder,
That yet hang heavy on my unpurg'd Soul, *
And plunge it not into eternal darkne(s.

Jaff. No, Belvjclera, when we parted laft
I gave this dagger with thee as in truft
To be thy portion, If I e'r prov'd falfe. r
On (uch condition was my truth believ'd : Sj '..

But now 'tis forfeited and muft be paid for. [Offers tofta\> her agvitt.

Bel. Oh, mercy ! {Kneeling.

Jaff. Nay, no ftrugling.

Bell. Now then krll me. [Leaps upon hk neckjzndkiffes him.
While thus I cling about thy cruel neck, \

Kifs thy revengefull lips and die in joys

Greater



a rwi uijcover a. $7

Greater than any I can guefs hereafter.

Jajfi I am, I am a Coward 3 witnefs't, Heaven,
Witnefsit, Earth, and every being Wit nefi 5
Tis but one blow yet: by immortal Love,
I cannot longer bear a thought to harm thee, J Htikrms away the da&

rr>f n t r 'j ' r «.l 1 i& am embraces her.

The Seal of providence is ture upon thee. t 6
And thou wert born for yet unheard of wonders :
Oh thou wert either born to fave or damn me!
By all the power that's given thee o'r my foul,
By thy refiftlefs tears and conquering fmiles,
By the vi&orious love that ftill waits on thee 3
Fly to thy cruel Father : lave ray friend,
* Or all our future Quiet's loft for ever :
Fall at his feet, cling round his reverend knees 5
Speak to him with thy Eyes, and with thy tears,
Melt thy hard heart, and wake dead nature in him,
Crufh him in th'Arms, and torture him with thy foftnefs 1
Nor, till thy Prayers are granted, Jet him free,
But conquer him, as thouhdfl vanquijftd me, [Ex, ambo.

The end of the fourth A&.





r






:


"


--







AG T V.

Enter VnvXx folus, '

Prin. X TT 7 H Y, cruel Heaven, have my unhappy days

V V ^en lengthen'd to this fad one? Oh! dishonour
And deathlefs infamy is tall'n upon me.
Was it my fault } Am I a traitour? No.
But then, my onely^child, my daughter, wedded 3
There my beft bloud runs foul, and a difeaie
Incurajhle has feiz'd upon my memory.
To make it rot and ftink to after ages.
Cur ft be trie fatal minute when I got frers
Or woud that I'd been any thing but man*
And rais'd an iflue which wou'dne'r have wrong'd me,
The milerableft Creatures (man excepted)
Are not the lefs efteem'd, though their pofterity
Degenerate from the vertues of their fathers 3

I The



5# v emce sr rejerv tf, or

The vilefl: Beafis are happy in their off-fprings,
While onely man gets traitours, whores and villains.
Curft be the names, and fbme fwift blow from Fate
Lay his head deep, where mine may be forgotten.
Enter iklvidera in a long mourning VeiL
Bel. He's there, my father, my inhumane father,.
That, for three years, has left an onely child
Expos 'd to all the outrages of Fate,
And cruel ruine — — -oh! — —

Prin. What ehild of fofrow
Art thou that com'ft thus wrapt in Weeds of fadnefr,
And mov'ft as if thy fteps were towards a graved

Bel. A wretch, who from the very top of happinefc
Am fallen into the loweft depths of miiery,
And want your pitying hand to raiie me up again.

Prin. Indeed thoutalk'ft as thou hadft tafted forrows^
Would I could help thee.

Bel. Tis greatly in your power,
TheVorld too, freaks you charitable, and J>
Who ne'r ask'd almes before, in that dear hope
Am come a begging to you, Sir.
Prin. For what }

Bel. Oh, well regard me, is this voice a ftrange one &-
Gonfider too, when beggars once pretend
A cafe like mine, no little will content 'em.
Prin. What would ft thou beg for ?

Bel. Pity and forgivenefs 5 [Throws uf her Veil.

By the kind tender names of child and rather,
Hear my complaints and takfc me to your love.
Prin, My daughter >
Bel. Yes, your daughter, by a mother
Vertuous and noble, faithfull to your honour*
Obedient to your will, kind to your wifhes,
Dear to your armes 5 by all the joys (he gave you,
When in her blooming years (he was your treafure 3
Look kindly on me $ in my face behold
The lineaments of hers y'have kifs'd fb often,
Pleading the caufe of your poor caft-oiF Child.
Prin. Thou art my daughter.

Bel. Yes And y'have oft told me

With,



A Plot Difcoverd. 5P

With fmiles of love and chafte paternal kifies*
Id much refemblance of my mother.

Prm. Oh !
Hadft thou inherited her matchlefs vertues
I'd been too blefs'd.

Bel. Nay, do not call to memory
My difobedience, but let pity enter
Into your heart, and quite deface the imprefiion y
For could you think how mine's perplext, what fadnefs
Fears and defpairs diftrad the peace within me,
Oh, you woud take me in your dear, dear Armes,
Hover with ftrong compaffian o'r your young one,
To {belter me with a protecting wing,
From the black gathered ftorm, that's juft, juft breaking.

Prm. Don't talk thus.

Bel. Yes, I muft, and you muft hear too.
I have a husband.

Prm. Damn him.

Bet. Oh, do not curfe him !
He would not fpeak fo hard a word towards you +

On any terms, + oh! e'r he deal with me. , Kaw

Prix. Hah ! what means my child }

Bel. Oh there's but this (hort moment
'Twixt me and Fate, yet (end me not with curies
Down to my grave, afford me one kind bleffing
Before we part : juft take me in your armes'
And recommend me with a prayer to Heaven,
That I may dye in peace, and when I'm dead— •— i.

Prm. How my Soul's catcht > :

Bel. Lay me, I beg you, lay me
By the dear afties of my tender mother.
She would have pitied me, had fate yet fpared her.

Prm By Heaven, my aking heart forebodes much mifchiefj
Telhne thy ftory, for I'm fttll thy father.

Bel, No, I'm contented.

Prm. Speak.

Bel. No matter.

Prm. Tell me.
By you, bleft Heaven, my heart runs o'r with fondnefs.

Bel. Oh/ '

Prm. Utter't. I 5 Bel.



60 Venice Prefervd, or

Bel. Oh my husband, my dear husband
Carries a dagger in his once kind bofome
To peirce the heart of your poor Belvidera.
Pr'm. Kill thee ?

Bel. Yes, kill me, when he pafs'd his faith
And covenant, againft your State and Senate,
He gave me up as hoftage for his truth,
With me a dagger and a dire commiffion.
When e'r he fail'd to plunge it through this bofome,
I learnt the danger, chofe the hour of love
T attempt his heart, and bring it back to honour,
Great love prevail'd and bleis'd me with fuccels,
He came, confeft, betray 'd his deareft friends*
For promis'd mercy 5 now they're doom'd to (urTer,
Gall'd with remembrance of what then was fworn,
If they are loft, he vows t'appeafe the Gods
Withthis poor life, and make my hloud th 1 attonement.

Brin. Heavens!

Bel Think you faw what pafs'd at our laft parting 5 »
Think you beheld him like a raging lion,
Pacing the earth and tearing up his fteps,
Fate in his eyes, and roaring with the pain
Of burning fury \ think you law his one hand
Fix't on my throat, while the extended other
Grafp'd a keen threatning dagger, oh 'twas thus,
We laft embrac'd, when, trembling with revenge^
He dragg'd me to the ground, and at my bofome
Prefented horrid death, cried out, my friends,
Where are my friends ? fwore, wept, rag'd, threaten'd, lov'd,
For he yet lov'd, and that dear love preferv'd me,
To this laft tryal of a father's pity.
I fear not death v but cannot bear a thought
That that dear hand fhould do th' unfriendly office \
If I was ever then your care, now hear me 5
Fly to the Senate, fave the promis'd lives
Of his dear friends, er mine be made the (acriflce*

Brin. Oh, my hearts comfort !

Bel. Will you not, my father ?
Weep not but anfwer me.

Brin. By Heaven, I will

Not



A Plot Difcwerd.- 6*

Not one of 'ernbut what (hall be immortal
Canft thou forgive me all my follies pad,
1*11 henceforth be indeed a father 3 never,
Never more thus expofe, but cherilh thee,
Dear as the vital warmth that feeds' my life,
Dear as thefe eyes that weep in fondnefs o ? r thee,
Peace to thy heart. Farewel.

Bel. Go, and remember,
Tis Belvzderas life her father pleads for. ~ {Ex./everally,

Enter Antonio.
Hum, hum, hah,

Seignior Print?, my Lord Prinli, my Lord, my Lord, my Lord :
Now, we Lords love to call one another by our Titles. My Lord,

my Lord, my Lord Pox on him, I am a Lord as well as he,

And fo let him fiddle — I'll warrant him he's gone to the Senate-
houfe, and I'll be there too, loon enough for ibmebody. Odd —
here's a tickling (peech about the Plot, I'll prove there's a Plot
with a Vengeance — would 1 had it without book 3 let me fee— ■ - 4

Molt Reverend Senatours,
That there is^ Plot, furely by this time, no man that hath eyes
or understanding in his head will prefume to doubt, 'tis as plain
as the light in the Cowcumber — no — hold there — Cowcum-
ber does not come in yet— 'tis as plain as the light in the Sun,
or as the man in the Moon , even at noon day 3 It is indeed a
Pumpkin-Plot, which, juft as it was mellow., we have gathered^ ,.
and now we have gathered it, prepar'd and drefs'd it, (hall we
throw it like a pickled Cowcumber out at the window > no :
that it is not onely a bloudy, horrid, execrable,, damnable and au-
dacious Plot, but it is, as I may fo fay, a fawcy Plot: and we all
know, molt Reverend Fathers, that what is fa wee for a Goofe is
fawce for a Gander : Therefore, I fay, as. thole bloud-thirfty
Ganders of the confpiracy would have deftroyed us Geefeof the
Senate 1 , let us make hafte to deftroy them, fo I humbly move for
hanging— »hah,, hurry durry--! think this will doe, tho 1 was fome*
thing outj at firit 3 about the Sun and the Cowcumber a
. Enter Aquiiina. .

AquiL Good morrow, Senatour. ..

Anto. Nacky, my dear Nacky, morrow, Nacky, odd I amy,
very brisk, very merry, very pert, very jovial— -haaaaa---k"us
me, Nacky^ how doft thou doe, my little Tory, rory Strum-
pet, kils me, I fay, huffy, kifs me. Aqujl I



^2 Venice Prefervd, or

Aquil Kils me 3 Nacky, hang you, Sir, Coxcomb, hang you, Sir.

Anto. Hay ty tay ty, is it (b indeed,wi?h all my heart, faith--H^
then up go wefe\th.~hey then up go we.&wm dum derum dump. [Sings,

Aquil. Seignior.

Anto. Madona.

Aquil. Do you intend to die in your bed — )

Anto. About threefcore years hence, much may be done, my

Aquil. You'll be hang'd, Seignior. (dear.

Anto. Hang'd, fweet heart, prithee be quiet, hang'd quoth-a,
that's a merry conceit, with all my heart, why thou jok'ft,Nacky,
thou art given to joking, I'll fwear 5 well, Iproteft, Nacky, nay,
I moft proteft, and will proteft that I love joking dearly, man.
And I love thee for joking, and I'll ki/s thee for joking, and
towfe thee for joking, and odd, 1 have a devililh mind to take
thee afide about that bufinefs for joking too, odd I have, and
Hey then up go we, dum dum derum dump. [Sings,

Aquil. See you this, Sir? [ Drams a dagger.

Anto. O Laud, a dagger! Oh Laud lit is naturally my averfion,
I cannot endure the fight on't, hide it, for Heavens fake, I can-
not look that way till it be gone— hide it, hide it, oh, oh, hide it !

Aquil. Yes, in your heart, I'll hide it.

Anto. My heart 5 what, hide a dagger in my heart's bloud !

Aquil. Yes , in thy heart, thy throat, thou pamper'd Devil y
Thou haft help'd toipoil my peace, and I'll have vengeance
On thy cuft life, for all the bloody Senate,
The perjur'd faithlels Senate: Where's my Lord,
My happinefe, my love, my God, my Hero,
Doom'd by thy accurled tongue, amongft the reft,
T' a fhamefull wrack ? By all the rage that's in me
I'll be whole years in murthering thee.

Anto. Why, Nacky,
Wherefore fo paffionate? what have I done > what's the matter,
my dear Nacky ? am not I thy Love, thy Happinels, thy Lord,
thy Hero, thy Senatour, and every thing in the world, Na^ky ?

Aquil. Thou ! thinkft thou, thou art fit to meet my joys 3
To bear the eager clafpsof my embraces?

Give me my Peirre, or

Anto. Why, he's to be hang'd, little Nacky,
Truftup forTreafbn, and fo forth, Child.

Aquil. Thou ly'ft, ftop down thy throat that hellifh fentence,

Or



., jTL J. l>vi L/lJLVUvr w. 2

Or Vis thy lad: fwear that my Love Chall live.
Or thou art dead.

Anto. Ahhh h.

Aquil Swear to recall his doom.
Swear at my feet, and tremble at my-fury.

Anto. I do, now if (he would but kick a little bit, one kick
now Ah h h h.

Aquil. Swear, or — -

Anto. I doe, by thefe dear-fragrant foots
And little toes, fweet as, e e e e my Nacky Nacky Nacky.

Aquil. How!

Anto. Nothing but untie thy fhoe-ftring a little faith and troth.
That's all, that's all, as I hope to live, Nacky, that's all.

Aquil. Nay, then —

Anto. Hold, hold, thy Love, thy Lord, thy Hero
Shall be preferv'd and fafe.

Aquil. Or may this Poniard
Ruft in thy heart.

Anto. With all my foul.

Aquil. Farewell ----- [ Ex. Aquil,

Anto. Adieu . W hy what a bloudy- minded in veterate,ter magant,
Strumpet have I been plagud with ! oh hh yet more ! nay then
I die, I die- 1 am dead already. [Stretches him/elf out*

Enter JafTeir.

Jaff Final deftrudtion (eize on all the world :
Bend down, ye Heavens, and (hutting round this earth 3
Crufh the Vile Globe into its firft confufion 3
Scorch it, with Elemental flames, to one curft Cindar,
And all us little creepers i n't, call'd men,
Burn, burn to nothing : but let Venice burn
Hotter than all the reft : Here kindle Hell
Ne'r to extinguish, and let fouls hereafter
Groan^here, in all thole pains which mine feels now*-

Enter Belvidera,

Bel. My Life- [Meeting him.

Jaff. My Plague - {Turning from her,

Bel. Nay then I fee my raine 9 ...
Ifl mull: die!

Jaff. No, Death s this day too bufie^
Thy Father's ill time-d Mercy came too late,.-../

I thank-



I thank thee for thy labours tha and him to®,
But all my poor betray 'd unhappy friends
Have Summons to prepare for Fate's black hour $
And yet I live.

Bel. Then be the next my doom. „^~

I fee thou haft pafs'd my fentence in thy heart,
And I'll no longer weep or plead againftit,
But with the humbleft, moft obedient patience
Meet thy dear hands, and kils 'em when they wound me 5
Indeed I am willing, but I beg thee doe it
With fbme remorfe, and where thou giv'ft the blow.
View me with eyes of a relenting love,
And (hew me pity, for 'twill fweeten Juftice.

Jaff Shew pity to thee )

Bel. Yes, and when thy hands,
Charg'd with my fate, come trembling to the deed,
As thou haft done a thoufand thoufand dear times,
To this poor breaft, when kinder rage has brought thee,
When our fting'd hearts have leap'd to meet each other,
And melting kilTes feal'd our lips together,
When joyes have left me galping in thy armes,
So let my death come now, and I'll not (hrink from't.

Jaff Nay, Belvidera^ do not fear my cruelty,
Nor let the thoughts of death perplex thy fancy,
But anfwer me to what I (hall demand
With a firm temper afid unfriaken fpirit.

Bel. I will when I've done weeping— — ■ |.

Jaff Fie, no more on't- j

How long is't fince the miferable day
We wedded firft— <

Bel. Ohhh.

Jaff. Nay, keep in thy tears,
Ceft they un man me too.

BeL Heaven knows I cannot 5
The words you utter found fb very fadly - V

Thefe ftreams will follow

Jaff Come, I'll kifs 'em dry then.

Bel. But, was't a miferable day ? ^ ,

Jaff A curs'd one.

Bel. I thought it otherwife, and you've oft fworn

In



A Plot Dijcoverd. 65

In the tranfporting hours of warmed love

When fure you fpoke the truth, you've fworn you blefs'd it.

Jajf. Twas a radi oath.

Bel. Then why am I not curfs'd too?

Jaff. No, Belvidera^ by th' eternal truth,
I doat with too much fbndnefs.

Bel. Still fo kind ?
■Still then do you you love me } • , '

Jajfi Nature, in her workings,
Inclines not with more ardour to Creation,
Than I doe now towards thee 3 man ne'r was blefs ci,
Since the fir ft pair firft met, as I have been.

Bel. Then fore you will not curfe me.

j^ No, I'll blefs thee.
I came on purpofe, Belvidera, to blefs thee.
'Tisnow, I think, three years w'have liv'd together.

Bel. And may no fatal minute ever part us,
Till, reverend grown, for age and love, we go
Down to one Grave, as our laft bed, together,
There deep in peace till an eternal morning.

Jaff When will that be? {Sighing.

Bel. I hope long Ages hence.

Jaff Have I not hitherto (I beg trree tell me
Thy very fears ) us'd thee with tender'ft love ?
Did e'r my Soul rile up in wrath againft thee ?
Did I e'r frown when Belvidera fmil'd,
Or, by the leaft unfriendly word, betray
A bating paffion ? have I ever wrong'd thee ?

Bel. No.

Jaff Has my heart, or have my eyes e'r wandred
To any other woman ?

Bel^ Never, never — I were the worft of -falfe ones (hould I
I own I've been too happy, blefs'd above (aceufethee,

My Sexes Charter.

Jaff Did I not fay I came to b(efs thee ?

Bel. Yes. i

Jaff. Then hear me, bounteous Heaven,
Pour down your bleiiings on this beauteous head,
Where everlafting fweets are always fpringing.
With a continual giving hand, let peace,
Honour and (afety always hover round her,

K Feed



66 Venice Preferv'd, or

Feed hex with plenty, let her eyes ne'r fee
A fight of forrow, nor her heart know mourning,
Crown all her days with joy, her nights with reft,
Harmlefs as her own thoughts, and prop her vertue,
To bear the lofsof one that too much lov'd,
And comfort her with patience in our parting.

BeL How 3 parting, 'parting I

Jaff. Yes, for ever parting,
I have fworn, Behidera 5 by yon Heaven,
That bed can tell how much I lofe to leave thee,
We pan this- hour for ever.

BeL Ob, call back
Your cruel bleffings, (ray with me and curie me ! ,

Jaff. No, 'Tis refblv'd.

Bel, Then hear me too, juft Heaven, .
Pour down your curies on this wretched head
With never- ceaflng Vengeance, let defpair,
Danger or infamy, nay all furround me, -
Starve me with wantings, let my eyes ne'r fee
A fight of comfort, nor my heart know peace,
But dafh my days with forrow, nights with horrours
Wild as my own thoughts now, and let loofe fury
To make me mad enough for what I lofe,
If J mud lofe him 5 iff mutt, I will not.
Oh turn and hear me .'

Jaff. Now hold, heart, or never.

BeL By all the tender days we have liv'd together,
By all our charming nights, and joyes that crown'd em,
Pity my fad condition, fpeak, but (peak.

Jaf.Ohhh.

Bel By thefe armes that now cling round thy neck,
By this dear km and by ten thoufand more,
By thefe poor dreaming eyes — (

Jaff Muither! unhold me: ^ ,.

By th'immortal deftiny that doom'dme [Draws his Dagger,

To this curs'd minute, I'll not live one longer.,
Reiblve to let me go or fee me fall



BeL Hold, Sir, be patient. <i

Jaff Hark, the difmal Bell [Pa]Jivg*hil toxvles.

Towles out for death, -1 mud attend its call too,
For my poor friend, my dying Petrre expects me,

He



n. i iQi uijtuver a, ■ 07

He Tent a meffage to require I'd fee him
BeTore he dy'd, and take his laft forgivene&
Farewell for ever.

Bel Leave thy dagger with me.
Bequeath me fomething— Not one kifs at parting } C Going otd
Oh my poor heart, when wilt thou break? < looks bacl^

Jaf. Yet ftay, : leather.

We have a Child, as yet, a tender Infant.
Be a kind mother to him when I am gone,
Breed him in vertue and the paths of Honour,
But let him never know his fathers ftory 5
I charge thee guard him from the wrongs my Fate
May doe his futuxe fortune or his name.

Now nearer yet- — [Approaching each other.

Oh that my armes were rivetted

Thus round thee ever ! But my friends, my oath !

This and no more. [Kijfes her.

Bel. Another, fare another,
For that poor little one you've ta'n care of,
I'll giVt him truly.

Jaff. So, now farewell.

Bel. For ever ?

Jaffl Heaven knows for ever 5 all good Angels guard thee.

Bel. All ill ones fure had charge of me this moment,
Curft be my days, and doubly curft my nights,
Which I muft now mourn out in widdow'd tears 3
Blaftedbe every herb and fruit and tree,
Curft be the rain that falls upon the earth,
And may the general Curfe reach man and bead 3
Oh give me daggers, fire or water,
How I could bleed, how burn^ how drown the waves
Huzzing and booming round my (inking head ,
Till I Uefcended to the peacefull bottomef
Oh there's all quiet, here all ra^ge and fury,
The Air's too thin, and pierces my weak brain,
I long for thick fubftantial deep : Hell, Hell,
Burft from the Centre, rage and roar aloud,
I f thou art half Co hot, fb mad as f am. ' ;>8

Enter Prinli md Servants.

W ho's there ? \Tkeyfeizeherl

Prin. Run, feize and bring her fafely home,

K 2 ... ~ Guard



65 Venice rrejervd, or

Guard her as you would life : Alas poor creature I ^

Bel. What ) to my husband then conducY me quickly, • t
Are all things ready ? fhall we dye moll gloriously }
Say not a word of this to my old father,
Murmuring ftreams, foft fhades, and Springing flowers,
Lutes, Laurells, Seas of Milk, and (hips of Amber. [Ex.

Scene opening difcovers a Scaffold and a Wheel prepard for the
executing of Peine, then enter Officers ^ Peirre and Guards^ a
Friar ^ executioner and a great Rabble.

Offic Room room there — ftand all by, make room for

the Prifoner.

Peir* My friend not come yet >
Father. Why are you fo obftinate }
Peirr. Why you fo troublefome, that a poor wretch
cannot dye in peace ?

But you, like Ravens will be croaking round him — —
Fath. Yet 4 Heaven — —
Peir. I tell thee Heaven and I are friends,
I ne'r broke Peace with't yet, by cruel murthers, *

Rapine, or perjury, or vile deceiving,
But liv'd in moral Juftice towards all men,
Nor am a foe to the moil: ftrong believers :
How e'r my own (hort- righted Faith confine me.
Fath. But an all-feeing Judge- — —
Peir. You (ay my conference
Muft be mine accufer : I have learch'd that Confcience,
And find no records there of crimes that fcare me.
Fath. Tis ftrange you ftiould want faith.
Peir. You want to lead
My Reafon blindfold, like a hamper'd Lion,
Check'd of its nobler vigour then, when baited,
Down to obedient tamenels, make it couch, (

And (hew (Irange tricks which you call figns of Faith*
So filly Souls are gull'd and you get money. $

Away, no more : Captain, I would hereafter
This fellow write no lyes of my conversion,
Becaule he has crept upon my troubled hours*

Enter JarTeir.
Jajfl Hold ; Eyes, be dry ,
Heart, ftrengthen me to bear



a riot vijcovera. ®?

This hideous fight, and humble me, take
The laft forgiveneis of a dying friend,
Betray 'd by my vile falfehood, to his mine.
Oh Peirre !

Peir, Yet nearer.

Jaff. Crawling on my knees ,
And proftrateon the earth, let trie approach thee,
How (hall I look up to thy injur'd face,
That always us'd to (mile, with friend (hip, on me?
It darts an air of (b much manly virtue,
Thai I, methinks, look little in thy fight,
And (tripes are fitter for me than embraces.

Peir. Dear to my Armes, though thou haft undone my fame,
I cannot forget to love thee: prithee, Jaffetr,
Forgive that filthy blow my pafiion dealt thee ,
I am now preparing for the land of peace,
And fain would have the charitable withes
Of all good men, like thee, to ble(s my journy.

Jaff Good ! I am the vileft creature, worfe than e r
Surfer d the (hamefull Fate thou art going to tafte of,
Why was I fent for to be us'd thus kindly )
Call, call me villain, as I am, defcribe
The foul complexion of my hatefull deeds,
Lead me to the J\ack, and ftretch me in thy ftead,
I've crimes enough to give it its full load,
And doe it credit : Thou wilt but fpoil the u(e on'ty
And honeft men hereafter bear its figure
About J em, as a charm from treacherous friendfriip.

Offic. The time grows (hort, your friends are dead already*

Jaff; Dead !

Peir. Yes, dead, Jaffeir, they've alldy'd like men too,.
Worthy their Character.

J&T. And what muft I doe?

Peir. Oh Jaffeir!

jaff. Speak, aloud thy burthen'd Soul,
And tell thy troubles to thy'tortur'd friend.

Peir. Friend I Could 'ft thou yet be a Friend, a generous frtend 3
I might hope Comfort from thy noble (brrows,
Heav'n knows I want a Friend.

Jaff. And I a kind one,
That would not thus (corn my repenting Vertue, ■

Or



7© Venice Prejerv d> or

Or think when he is to dye, my thoughts are idle.
Peirr. "No! live, I charge thee, Jaffeir.
Jaff. Yes, I will iive,
But it (hall be to fee thy fall reveng'd
At fuch a rate , as Venice long (hall groan for.
Peirr. Wilt thou ?
J off*. I will, by Heav'n,
Peirr. Then (till thou'rt noble,
And I forgive thee, *oh—yet— (hall I truftthee?
Jaff No : I've bee^n falfe already.
Peir. Daft thou love me ?
Jaff Pvip up my heart, and fatisfie thy doubtings.
Peir. Curie on this weaknefs. [He weeps.

Jaff Tears ! Amazement ! Tears !
I never (aw thee melted thus before 5
And know there's (bmething lab'ring in thy bofom
That rauft have vent : Though I'm a Villain, tell me.

Peir. Seeft thou that Engine ? [Pointing to the Wheel,

?#Why? ■

Peir. 1st fit a Souldier, who has liv'd with Honour,
Fought Nations Quarrels, and bin Crown'd with Conquefr,
Be expos'd a common Carcaft on a Wheel ?
Jaff Hah !

Peir. Speak! is't fitting?
Jaffl Fitting?
Peir. Yes, fs't fitting ?
J a ffi What's to be done?
Peir. I'd have thee undertake
Something that's Noble, to prelerve my Memory
From the diigrace that's ready to attaint it.
Qjfic, The day grows late, Sir.
Peir. I'll make hafte ! oh Jaffeir,
Though thou'ft betray'd me, doe me fome way Juftice. / ..

Jaff. No more of that : Thy wifhes (hall be iatisfi'^
I have a Wife, and (he fnall bleed, my Child too
Yield up his little Throat, and all t'ap- \Qoing <tway Peir.

ife thee — I ^olds him.



f-' V-la-Jl,



Peir. No — this — —no more ! [He whifpers Jaffein

Jaff. Hah! is't then fo?
Peir. Mod certainly.
Jaff. HI do r.

Peir.



A Plot Difcover d. 7 \

Pier. Remember.

Offic. Sir. •

Pier. Come , now I'm ready. ("He and Jaf-

Captain , you ftiould be a Gentleman of honour, < feir afiend
Keep off the Rabbi-, that I may have room (jhe Sciffold,

To entertain my Fare, and dye with Decency.
Come! [Takgs off hk Gown. Executioner prepares to hind htm.

Fath. Son !

Peir. Hence, Tempter.

Offic Standoff, Prieft.

P.v>, I thank you, Sir,
You'l! think' o n't. . [To Jaffeir. ;

Jaff. 'T won't grow (tale before tomorrow.

Pier. Now, Jaffeir ! now lam going. Now -? — [Executioner

Jaff. Have at thee, [having bound him.

Thou honed heart, then here — — [Stabs him.

And this is well too. [Thenffabs himfelf

Fath. Damnable Deed !

Peir. Now thou haft indeed been faithful.-
This was done Nobly — — We have deceiv'd the Senate.

Jaff. Bravely.

Peir. Ha ha ha oh oh—— [Dies.

Jaff. Now,yecurs'd Rulers,
Thus of the blood y'have (hed I make Libation,
And fprinkl 5 t mingling : May it reft upon you,
And all your Race : Be henceforth Peace a ftranger
Within your Wails 3 let Plagues and Famine wafte
Your Generations — oh poor Behidera !
Sir, I have a Wife, bear this in fafety to her.

A Token that with my dying breath I bleft her,
And the dear little Infant left behind me.
I am rick I'm quiet . [_ "Jaff. dyes.

Offic: Bear this news to the Senate,
And gua^d their Bodies till there's farther order .°

Heav'n grant I dye io well [Scene jhuts upon them.

$$fi Mufic\.. Enter Belvidera dijlracjed, led by two of her
Women, Prinli and Servants.

Pri». Strengthen her heart with Patience, pitying Heav'n.
a Belv. Come cone come come come. Nay, come to bed!
Prithee my Love. The Winds! hark how they whittle I
And the Rain beats : okhow the weather Shrinks me!

You



*j2 Venice Prefervd, &c.

You are angry now, who cares? pith, no indeed.

Choofe then, I fay you (hall not go, you fhallnot $ •

Whip youriil nature $ get you gone then*! oh, [jaffeir'sGhojirifes.

Are you return'd ? See, Father, here he's come agen,

Am I to blame to love him! oh thou dear one. [Ghofi finks.

Why do you fly me? are you angry ftili then ?

Jaffeir ! where art thou? Father, why do you doe thus ?

Stand off, don't hide him from me. He's here fomewhere.

Stand off I fay ! what gone ? remember' t, Tyrant !

I may revenge my felf for $ his trick one day. '. $Enter Officer

I'll do' t — I'll do'r. Renault $ a nafty fellow. \ and ethers.

Hang him, hang him, hanghim.

Prin. News, what news? [Offic, whijpers Vx'mW.

Offic, Moft fad, Sir.
"jaffeir upon the Scaffold, to prevent
A (hamefull death, fhb'd Peirre, and next himfelf:
Both fell together.

Prin, Daughter. (The Ghofis of Jaff. and Peir. rife

Bel. Hah, look there ! {together both bloody.

My Husband bloody, and his friend too ! Murther I
Who has done this? f peak to me thou fad Virion, [Ghofis fink.

On thefe poor trembling Knees I beg it, Vanifht

tjere they went down. Oh I'll dig, dig the Den up.

You (han't delude me thus. Hoa, Jaffeir, Jaffeir.

Peep up and give me but a look. I have him!

I've got him, Father : Oh now how I'll fmuggle Him !

My Love! my Dear! my Bleffing! help me, help me !

They have hold on me, and drag me to the bottom.

Nay — now they pull Co hard farewell — [She dyes.

Maid. She's dead.
Breathlefsand dead.

Prin. Then guard mejffom the fight on V:
Lead me intofbme place that's fit for mourning 3
Where the free Air, Light and the chearfuli Sun -
May never enter : Hang it round with black j
Set up one Taper that.may lafLaday "<&

As long as I've to live : And there all leave me.
Sparing no Tears when you this Tale relate^
But bid all Cruel Fathers dread my Fate. Curtain falls,

[Ex. omnes-,
FINIS.*









<Cs^-h \\



Bv>^%^
