
Skip to main content

    Internet Archive Logo
    web
    books
    video
    audio
    software
    images
    search

    uploadUPLOAD
    personSIGN IN

    ABOUT
    CONTACT
    BLOG
    PROJECTS
    HELP
    DONATE
    JOBS
    VOLUNTEER
    PEOPLE

Full text of "The rehearsal : as it is now acted at the Theatre-Royal"
See other formats

'-'M':



i%a ML



fi^h



■^^'^^^



:.f~Sl.



;.M^



S




4f



l^-i-r::-^ -^ C'f-^



^ 1 '2-^
^



Digitized by the Internet Archive

in 2011 with funding from

LYRASIS IVIembers and Sloan Foundation



http://www.archive.org/details/rehearsalasitisnOObuck



I ti a ^




? Ae it is nowAiSted at the

Theatre-Royal.



■^.



The third Edition with a mendments and
large Additions By the /^uthor.



LONDON,

^mtcd for ThomasDringy at thtHarrcof at the
Comer of Chancery-lane inFleet^ .
flreet. i6 j 5.



^3 a?



.M



(p'i^



PROLOGUE.

WE m?ghiv^ell caU thhP'ort Merf^jfht^'^fenrt
A Fcjit made of Weeds ivftead of F tower r 5
Tetfuclt have beenprefented to your f/ofes,
jifid there arefuch^ I fear ^ who thought 'evi Rofcf^
Wonldfome of 'em were herCy to fee ^ this flighty
IVhatJiuffit is in which they took^dclight.
Here hriskjfffpid Rogues^ for wit^ let fall
Sometimes dull fence ^ hut offner none at all :
There ^ftrutting Heroes^ with agrimfac dtrain^
shall brave the Gods ^ in King Czmbyihs vein.
For ( changing Rules^ of late ^ as if men writ
Infpjte ofReafon^ "Nature ^ Art and Wit)
Our Poets make us laugh attragtedy^
And with their Cmot dies they mak^ us cry,
Now^ Critiques, do your worji^ that here are met j
For^ like a Rook^^ I have hed^d in my "Bet,
If you approve , I pall affume thejiate
Cfthofe high-flyers wh:f me I imitate :
Aud juitly teo far I will teach you more
Than ever they would let you ki^ow before:
I will not orAyJhew i he feats they do ^

But give ycu all thetrreafons for^em tod'
Some honour may to me from hence arife.
But if:>by my endeavour s^ you grow wife
And what you oncefopraiyd.fljall now dejpife i
Then I'lUry out^fwelld with Poetic rage,
Tisl^ ]ohtjj^^^ have reform dyour Stage.



THE



1 he Actor' Names.

BAyes.
johnfon,
smith.

Two Kings of Brentford,
VnncePrettj-ntaft,
Gentleman Ufher.
Phylician.
Brawcdnfr.

General,
Lieatenant Cenerab

Cordelie. ^

torn Thimble,

Fiihermani - - -

San. J :;■■;.,- --:-:■•

Thunder,

Players.

Souldiers*

Two Heralds,

Four Cardinals T

Mayor. CMutes>

Judges. C

Serjeants at Arms^-^

ITomen^

^maiyllif, „

Chris, \ .

Varthenope^ '.^

Vallas.

Lightning*

Moon.

Earthi

Attendants of Men and Women*



Scene 'Brentford, THE



THE



Rehearfal.




ACTUS L SCyEKA h

Johnlbn ^»^ Smith.

t

Jchnf,^^ TT^^^^ Fr4«4.-' Pm glad to fee thee with all
my heart .* how long haft thou been in
Town?

Smi. Faith, not above an hour .* and, if
I had not met you here,! had gone to look
you out 5 for I long to talk with you freely, of all the ftrange
new things we have heard in the Country.

'Johnf, And, by my troth, I have long'd as much to laugh
with you, at ail the impertinent^ dull, fantafiical things, we
are tir'd out with here.

Smi, Dull, and fantaftical! that's an excellent compofitlon.
Pray, what are our men ofbufinefs doing?

Johttf. I ne'er enquire after 'em. Thou knoweft my hu*
mour lyes another way. I love to pkafe my felf as much, and
to trouble others as little as I can : and therefore do natu-
rally avoid the company of thofe fblemn Fops 5 who, beiag in-
capable of Reafon, and infenfible of Wit and Pleafure, are
always looking grave, and troubling one another^ in hopes
to be thought men of Bufineis, I

B Smi,



z TheRebearfah •

*y«?/. Indeed, I have ever obfcrvcd, that your grave lookers
are the dulleit of meo.

Johfif. I, and of Birds, and Eeafts too .* your graveft Bird is
and OVi^l, and ycur graveltBeaftisan Afs.

Smi, Well 5 but how doft thou pafs thy tinae ?

Johnf, Why, as I ufe to do ; eat and drink as well as I can,
have a (lie- friend to be private with in the afternoonj and
fometimes fee a Play ; where there are fuch things (Fra»^
fuch hideouSj monltrous things, that it has almoft made me
forfwear the Stage, and refolve to apply my felf tothefblid
nonlence of your Men of Bufinefs, as the more ingenio u&
paftime.

Sm, I have heard, indeed, you have had lately many new
Plays 5 and our Country-wits commend em.

Johnf. I,(b do fome of our City- wits toobj but they are of the
*i^w kind of Wits.

Smu New kind I what kind is that ?

Johnf. Why, your Virtuofi, your civil perfons.,your Drolls:
fellows that fcorns to imitate Nature 3 but are given altoge-
therto elevate and furprife.

Smi, Elevate, and furprife' pr'ytheemakemeunderftand
the meaning of that.

Johfif, Nayj by my troth, that's a hard matter .- I don't un-
derftand that my felf. 'Tis a phrafe they have got among
them, to exprefs their no-meaning by» Tl tcil you, as near as I
can, what it is. Let me fee:, 'tis Fighting, Loving, Sleeping,
Rhyming , Dying , Pancing , Singing, Crying j and every
thingj but thinking and Sence.

Mr.^ayespajfks o'er the Stage.

Bayes, Your mofl: obfcquious, and raoft obfervant, very fer-
vantjSir.

'johvf.God fo, this is afi Author : I'l fetch him to you.

67/?7. No, pr y thee let him alone.

'johfyf. Nay, by the Lord, I'l have him. [^Goes after him.
Here he is. I have caught him. Pray, Sir^ now tor my fake, will
you do a favour to this friend otmine>

Bajes' Sir, it is not within my fmall capacity to do favours,

but



I be Kebearjal. }

but receive 'em $ efpecially from a perfbn that does wear the
honourable Title you are pleas'd to impofe^SirjUpon this — -
Sweet Sir, your fervant,

Sff/u Your humble fervant. Sir.

Johfif, But wJIt thou do me a favour, now?

Lajes, I, Sir.* whatis't?

JoknC Whya to tell him the meaning of thy laft Play.

Baj/e'^f, H0W5 Sir, the meaning .<? do yo^-: mean the Plot?

Jo^k/, 1, 1 5 anything.

Eaj^es. Faith, Sir, the Intrigo's now quite out of my head ^
but I have a n^w one, in my pocket, that I may fay isa Vir-
gin > 't has never yet been blown upon. I muft tell you one
thing. 'Tis all new Wit, and tho I fay it, a better than
my laft .* and you know well enough how that took. In fine,
itlhall read, and write, and ad, and plot, and (hew, ay, and
pitjbox and gallery, I gad, with any Play in Europe* This
morning is its laft Rehearfal, in their habits, and all that, as it
iito be afted 5 and if you, and your friend will do it but the
honour to fee it in its Virgin attire 5 though, perhaps, it may
blu(h, I (hall not be alham'd to difcover its nakednefs unto
you.— —>I think it is in this pocket \_PHts his handin his packet ,

Johfjf' Sir, Iconfefs, I am not able to anfwer you in this new
wayv but if you plea(e to lead, I (hall be glad to follow you j
and I hope my friend will do fo too.

Smi, Sir, I have nobafinefsfo confiderable, as (houldkeep
mefrom your company.

Bayes, Yes, here it is; No, cry you mercy : this is ray
book of Drama Common f laces 5 the Mother of many other

Jofjfff, Drama Commonplaces \ pray what's that?

Bayes,^ Why, Sir, fome certain helps, that we men of Art
liave found it convenient to make ujfe of,

smi, HoWjSir^helpsfor Wit?

Bayes, I, Sir, that's my pofition. And I do h^reaverr. That
no man yet the Sun eer (hone upon, has parts fufficient to
furni(h out a Stage, except it were by the help of thefe my
Rules,

B 2 yhnj.



4 TheRebearfaL

■ Johxf, What are" thofe Rules, T pray>

Ba^es, Why, Sir, my firft Rule is the Rule of Tranfverfion,
or Regula Duplex : changing Verfe into Profe, or Profeinto
verfe, alternative ^iS-^ow pleafe.

S??n, Well . but how is this done by a Rule, Sir .«?

Bayes, Why, thus. Sir j nothing fo eafie when under-
ftood .* I take a book in my hand, either at home or elfewhere,
for that's aJJ one, ifther^ be any Wit in'tjas there is no ,book
bat Jias tome, I Tranfverfj it 5 that is, if it be Profe put it into
Verfe, f but that takes up fome time) and if it be Verie, put it
iato Profe,

Johfif. Methinks, Mr. Bayes ^ that putting Verfe into Profe
ibould be caird Tranfprofing.

Bi^es. Bf my troth. Sir, 'tfs a very good Notion, and here-
after it {hall befo.
; Smi, Well, Sir, and what d'ye do with it then?

Bayes, Make it my own. 'tis fo changed that no man can
know it. My next Rule is the Rule of Record, by w^y of
Table Book. Pray obferve.

Jobnf, We hear you Sir: goon.

Bayes, As thus, I come into a Coffee-houfe, or fome other
place where witty men refort, I make as if I minded nothings
fdo you mark?) butasfoonas any onefpcaks, pop I flap it
down, and make that, too, my own, : i;!..

'johf2f. But, Mr. Bayes ^ are you not fbmetimes in danger of
their making you reltore, by force, what you have gotten
thus by Art? •

Bayes, No, Sir 3 the World's unmindful : they never take
notice of thefe things. :

Smi, But pray, Mr. Bay^s^ amongall your Other Rples^ have
you no one Rule for invention .<? r.: // .A, ■

Bayes ^Y^s^ Sir 3 that's my third Rule that I have here m ray
pocket. ,

Smi, W hat Rule can that be, I wonder ? , ;

'-E^j'e/. Why, Sir, when I have any thing to invent,! never
trouble my head about it, as other men do 5 but prefently turn
Over this Book^ and there I have, at one view, all that Perfeus^



i kfe ixetjearjai. 5

Montaigne^ Seneca s Tragedies^ Horace^ jHvenahClaudian^Vliny^
PluParcPs lives ^SLud the reft, have ever thought upon this (kb-
^ed .* and fo, in a trice, by leaving out afewwordsj or put-
ting in others or my own, the bufinefs is done.

Johfif. Indeed, Mr. Bayes,^ this is as fure^ and compendious
a way of Wit as ever 1 heard of.

B/ijies. Sirs, if you make the leaft fcruple of the efficacy
^f thefe my Rules, do but cometothePlay-houfej and you
i'hall judge> of em by the effedts.

Smi» We'l follow you. Sir. \_Exeunt,

Enter three! Players upon the Stage,

I Play. Have you your part perfeft .<?

7 Play. Yes, I have it without book; but I don't under -
ftand how it is to be fpoken.

3 Play. And mine is fuch aone^ as Ican'tguefs for my life
what humour Tm to be in .* whether angry, melancholy, merry,
or in love. I don't know what to make on'c.

1 Play. Phoo ! the Author will be here prefently, and hel
tell us all. You rauft know, this is the new way of v/riting 5 and
the(e hard things pleafe forty times better then the old plain
way. For, look you. Sir, the grand defign upon the Stage is
to keep the Auditors infufpence , for to guefs prefently at the
plot, and the fence, tires 'em before the end of the firft Adi :
now, here, every line furprifes you, and brings in new matter.
And, then, for Scenes, Cloaths and Dances we put 'em quiet
down, all that ever went before us : and thofe are the things,
you know, that are eiiential to a Play.

2 Play, Well, 1 am not of thy mind 5 but, fo it gets us mo^
ney, 'tis no great matter.

Enter Bayes, Jchnfon and Smith.

Bayes» Come,* come in Gentlemen. Y'are very welcome
Mr. a— — Ha' you your part ready >

I Play. Yes Sir.

Bayes. But do you nnderftand the true humor of it ? ~

I Play. IjSir, pretty well..

Bayes. And Amarilhs^ how docs fhe^do ? Does not her Ar-
mor become her ?



3 ?//{;'. O5 admirably I

Bayes. PI tell you, now^ a pretty conceipt. What do you
think V\ make 'em j::alHTcr atK>n3 in this Play ?

Sm. What^lpray?

Bojies. Why, I make em call her y^rz«^r7i7//5 becaufeof her
Armor.* ha, ha^ha.

Johfjf. That will be very well, indcedj

Eajes Ay, it's a pretty little rogues I knew hei' face would
fet off Armor extreamly : and. to tell you true, I write that
Part onlyfor her. You mult know ftie is my Mifci efs.

Johnf!^^<£VL, I know another thing, little Bayes^ that thou
halt had her, I gad.

Bayes. No^Igad, not yet 5 but I'm fare I (hall .• fox I have
talkt bawdy to her already.

Johnf^ Hall thou, faith .<^ Pr'ythee how was that ?

^^/c/.. Why, Sir, there is, in the French Tongue, a certain
Criticifm, which, by the variation of the Mafculine Adjedive
inftead of theFoeminine, makes a quite different fignification
of the word: as, for exam pie. Ma vie h my life ^ but if, before
^/> yon put i^/(:?22 inftead o^Afa^ you make it bawdy.

Johfff, Very true.

Bsy^s, Now, Sir, I, having obferv'd this, fet a Trap for her,
the other day in the Tyring-Room ^ for this faid I, {Adieu hel
EJperaf/fa de ntavie \ ( which I gad is very pretty ) to which fhc
anfwer'd, I vow, almofi: as prettily, every jot , for faid fhe. Sen-
ges a mavieMeufffieur , Vv^hereupon I prefently fnapt this upon
her ^ "Non^ non^ Madam-. — Soft ges vous a moti^ by gad, aad nam'd
the thing dire&ly to her.

Smi, This is one of the richelt Stories, Mr. Bayes^ that ever I
I heard of.

Bayes, I, let me alone, I gad, when I get to *em 5 I'l nick 'em^
I warrant you ; But I'm a little nice ^ for you mull: know, at this
lime, I am kept by another woman, in the City.

Smi, How kept? for what?

Bayes, Why, for a B^au Gerfon : I am, ifackins.

S«^/. Nay, then we (hall never have done.

Bayes, And the Rogue is fo fond of me, Mr. Jok^foft^ that I
vow to gad , I know not what to do with my felf.

Johf.



IbeRebearfaL 7

'johnf. Do with thy felf ! no jl wonder how ihoiicanft make
a (hift to hold out, at this rate.

Bayes, O Devil^ I can toil like a HoiTe > onlyjfometimes, it
makes me melancholy .* and then 1 vow to gad, for a. whole day
togetherj I am not able to (ay you one good thing if it were to
fave my life. .

Smi, That we do ;^erily believej Mi Bayes.

Bayes, And that's theonly things I gad, which snadsme, in my
Amours s for Fl tell you, as a friendj Mr. Johfijo^y my acquain-
tances, I hear, begin to give it out that I am dull .• now I am the
fartheft from it in the whole World, Igid, butonly^forfooth,
they think I am fo^ becaufe I can fay nothing.

Johnf, Phoo pox. That's ill natur'dly done of 'em.

Bayss, Ay gad^ there's no trudingo'thefe Rogues . but —
a — — Come, let's (it down. Look you. Sirs, the chief
hinge of this Play^ upon which the whole Plot moves and
turns, and that caufes thevariety of all the (everal accidents,
which^ you know, ate the things in Nature that make up the
grand refinement of a-Play^is, that IfuppofetwoKingstobe
of the fame place .* as, for example, at Brentford ^ for I love to
write familiarly. Now the people having the fame relations
to 'em both, the fame afledions, the fameduty, thefameobe-
dience, and all that 5 are divided among themfelves in point
of devoir and intereft', how to behave themfelves equally be-
tween 'em; the(e Kings differing fometimcg in particular^
thoughj in the main, they agree. (I know not whether I
make my felf well underftood,^

"johnf. I did not obferve you, Sir : pray fay that again.

Bayes, Why, look you. Sir, fnay, I l3efeech you, be a little
curious in taki'ig notice of this, or ^Mt you1 never under-
hand my notion of the th?ngj the people being; embarralt by
their .equal tyes to both, and the Soveraigns concern'd in a re-
ciprocal regard, as well to their own intereft, as the good of
the people 5 may make a certain kind of a^ — — -youunder-

ftand me ■ upon which, there does ar'fe feveral difputes,

turmoils, heart-burnings,, and all that— — In fine, you [ap-
prehend it better v/hen you fee it.

[ExH^ to call the rl-^y^ff.



8 JheRehear/aL

SmL 1. find the Author will be very rnQch oblig'dtothe.
Play ersj if they cad make any fence out of this.

£;i?^^r Bayes. '-
IBaycf, Now, Gentlemenj I would fairi ask your oprnion of
one thing. 1 have made a Prologue and an Epilogue, which
may both ferve for either .-[ihat is, the Prologue for the Epi-
logue, or the Epilogue lor the Prologue] .• (do you mark>)nay3
they may both ferve tooj gad,for any other PJay'^s well as this.
Smi. Very well. That's, indeed. Artificial.
Bayes, And I would fain ask your judgements, now, which
of them would do bell: for the Prologue? For, you muft
know there is, in nature, buttwo ways of making very good
prologues. The one is by civility, by indnuation, good lan-
guage, and all that, to a in a manner, (teal your plau-
dit from the courtefic of the Auditors: the other, by making
ufe of fome certain perfonal things, which may keep a hank -
upon fuch cenfuring perfons, as cannot otherways, Agad,in
nature, be hindred from being too free with their tongues.
To which end, my firft Prologue is, that I come out in a long
black Veil, and a great Huge Hang-man behind me, with a
Furr'd-cap, and his Sword drawn, and there tell'm plainly.
That if, out of good nature, they will not like my Play,
I gad, 11 e'en kneel down, and he (hall cut my head offl

Whereupon they all clapping a - — -

Smi» I, But fuppofe they don't.

Bajies. Suppofe/ Sir, you may fuppofe what you plcafe, I
have nothing to do with your fuppofe. Sir 5 nor am Hot at all
mortifi'd at it 5 not at all, Sir ', I gad, not one jot. Sir. Suppofe

quotha! ha, ha, ha. [jValk^s away.^

Jolwf. Phoo ! pr ythee, Eajies^ don't mind what he (ays .* he
is a fellow newly come out.of the Country, he knows nothing
of what's the relifti, here, of the Town.

Bajfeir, If I writ. Sir, to plea(e the Country, Khould have

follow'd the old plain way '-> but I write for fome perfons of

Qualityj and peculiar friends of mine, that underftand what

Flame and Power in writing is; and they do m.e the right. Sir,

' toapproveof what 1 do.



/ be KebejrjaL 9

"jehfif. I, Ij they will clap, I warrant you s never fear it.

Bajes* I'm fare the defign*s good .♦ that cannot be dcnyd
Andthen, for language, 1 gad, I defie *ccn all, in nature, to
mend it* Befides, §ir, I have printed above a hundred tliect?
of papyrjtoinfinuate the Plot into the Boxes : and, withal,
have appointed two or three dozen of my fricnds» to be ready
in the Pit, who, I'm fure, will clap, and To the reft, you
know, mult follow ^ and then, pray. Sir, what becomes of
your fuppofe ? ha, ha, ha. -

.JohffJ. Nay, if the buGnefsbe fowell laid, it cannot ml{s.

Bayes. I think Co^ Sir .• and therefore would chufe this to
be the Prologue. For, if I could engage 'em to clap, before
they fee I he Play, you know 'twould be fo much the betters
becaufethen they were engag'd : for let a man write never fo
wellj there are, now-a-days, a fort of perfons , they call
Critiques, that, I gad, hdvenomorcwit in them than (b many
Hobby-horfes^ but they'll laugh you, Sir, and find fault, and
eenfure thing?} that, I gad, I'm fare, they are not able to do
themfelvcs. A fort of envious perfons, that emulate the glo"
ries of perfons of parts, and think to build their fame, by ca^-
lumniating of perfons, that, I gad, to my knowledge, of all per-
fons in the world arc, in nature, the perfons that do as much
defpife all that as a — In fine. Ml fay nomore of'cm.

Johfff. Nay, you have faid enough of *em, in all confcience:
Im fure more than they'll e'rc be able to anfwer.

Baje-f^ Why, I'il tell you^ Sir, ilncerely, and bottafde % were
it not for the fake of fome ingenious perfons, and choice fe^.
male fpirits, that have a value for me, I would fee 'em all
hang>!i, I gad, before I would e'er moie f^t pen to papyr,
but let 'em live in ignorance like ingrates.

Johftfi I marry ! that were a way to be reveng'd of cm in-
deed : and, if I were in your place, now, I would do fo.

Bayes, No, Sir ; there are certain tyes upon me, that 1 can^
not be dii^ingag'd from A otherwife, 1 would. But pray. Sir,
how do you like my hangsman >

Smi, By my troth, Sir, I fhonld like him vicry well.

Bayes. Bat how do you like it Sir > Cfor^ I fee, you can judgej

C VVouM



Would tyou ha¥eie for a Prologue J or the Epilogue?
Johnf. . Faiih, S'lr^ 'tis fo goodj let it e'en fi.rvefor both.
B:a^es, Noj no J that wont do. Befjdes 1 have made ano-
ther . -

Johf^f, What other,^ Sir >

Bayes^ Why, Sir, mf other is Thunder and Ligktm^go
'jdbnf. That's greater ; I'd rather Itick to that^
l^ayes^ Do you think fo ? I'l tell you then > tho there have
been many witty Prologues written of late, yet, I think, you'l.
fay this is a non pareilh : I'm furc no body has hit upon it
yet. For here. Sir, I make my Prologue to be Dialogue ; and.
assin my firftjyou fee 1 ftrive to oblige the Auditors by civility,
by good nature, good language, and all that 5 fb, in this, by
the other way, in Terror em^l chufe for the perfons Thu^nder and
Lightning, Do you apprehend the conceipt?

5^(?/6;!^ Phoo, Pox I thenyou haveitcock-fure. They'lbe
hang'd before they'I dare to affront an Author, that has em at
ihatlock^

^ayes' I have made, too, one cfthe moft delicate dainty
Simile's in,the whole world, I gad, if 1 knew but how to ap-
plie it.

Sfni^ Lets hear it, I pray you,
Vjoyes 'Tisanalluiion tolove.

So Boar and Sow, when any ftorm is nigh.
Snuff up, andfmellit gath'ring in the Sky ^
Boar beckons Sow to trot in Cheftnut Groves,,
And there confummate their unfiniQi'd Loves .-;
Penfive in mud they wallow all alone.
And fnore and gruntle to each others moaoo
How do you like it now, ha?

Johnf^ Faith, 'tis extraordinary fine .• and very applicable
f o Ihnnder and Lightnings methinks, becaufe it ipeaks of ^



fiorm



^ayes. T gad, and fo it does, now I think oii*t Mr. 'John*
fon^ 1 thank you^ and 11 put it in./?r^/a1;p. ' Come out^ T/;/;«-
^^.r d.nd Lightning, __

Enter



The Rehearfal ii



E»fer Thunder /rW Lightning,
Thttn. t am the bold 'ihufider^

Kiyes:, Mr. CArtwright^ pr'y thee fpcak that a little louder ,
and with a h^aife voice, I am the bold Thunder iFQiaw I fpeak
it me in a voice that thunders it out indeed; lam the bold
tlmnder,

Tkun^ I am. the bold T'^«;?6i^r.
Lights T he brisk tightvwg^ I.
Bjj^j, Nay ^y ou muft be quick- and nimble.
The brisk Lightning^ I. That's my meaning.
thiw, I am the braveft He&or of the Sky.
Light, And I fair He/e»that mide He^or die,
T^«». Iftrike men down.
I/giS^. I firetheTown,
Thun Let the Critiques take heed how they grumble.

For then begin I for to rumble,
Light^Lct the Ladies allow us their Graces,
Or ri blaft all the paint on their faces.
And dry up their Peter to Soot,
T^»^. Let the Critiques look tot*
Light* Let t he Ladies loojc to't^
Thji^. For thunder will do'r.
Light, For Ligktfiing will (boot.
2^/z«. ri give you dafh for dafh.
Light, \\ give you flaili for flafli.

Gallants H finge your Feather.
^ Thuff^Vl Thfif^der yon together ^

B&th^ Look tot, look to ti we'ldo't, we'l do't .• lookto't,
we'l do't. [ Twice or thrice repeated^

[Exennt ambe^
B4je/,There*s nomoreJTis but a flafhof a Prologue.-a DroU.
Smi^ Yes, 'Tis (hort, indeed ; but very terrible.
^ayes^ Ay, when thejlmfes in3it will do to a Miracle, I gadj,
^ Come^ come begin the Play,



Ek^.t



12. The RebearfaL

Enter fir fi Player,

I Via), Sir, Mr. Ivory is not come yetj but hee*l be here
prefently, he's but two doors off.

Bayes. Cometbcnj Centlemenj let's go out and take a pipe
of Tobacco. ^ [Exeunt,

Finif Actus Trimh



AC TuS II. SCiENA I.

:" Bayes, johiiron//«<^ Smith.

B^yes.f^Ow ^ Sir, becau(e I'll do nothing here that evecJ^

j_% was done hefore, inftead.of beginning with a Scene,
that difcoversiumethingof the Plot, I begin this Play vvitk
a whifper.'

.?*^//. Umph! very new, jndeed.

-Etfj/^i-. Come, take your feats. Begin,- Sifs.

Enter Ccntleman-Vjjier avd fhy^cian.

'Thyf^ Sir, by your habit, I ftiould ghefs you to be the Cen- ^
tlemaivUOier ofthis fiimptuous place.

Vjl. And, by your gait and fafhion^ I lliould almoft fufped
you rule the healths ofboth our noble Kings, under the noti?---
on of Phyfician. * .

F,%'." You hit my Function right,,

Zlfl.'. And yoUj mine.

Hyj. Then let's embrace,
. 1)J!j. Come.
. -.Fkyf, Gome..

' "johnf. Piay, Sir, who are thpfefo. very civil peiTons ?
::£ayes^ Why, Sir, the Gentleman- Uftier, and Phyiician o§. ^
th^two liiugsof ^/'<?/??/i?r<^. -

Johnf.' But, pray then, how comes it to paffj that they know
©i;^; alio r her no better?. ..

" ' " ' / . Uayes^



The Rebearfal. 13

\ %ayes, Phoo! that's for the better carrying on of the Plot >
Johnf, Very welJ.
i'y&^yr Sir, to conclude,
^«?/. What.^ before he begins r^

^dayes. No, Sir 5 you muft know^ they had been talking of
this a pretty while without.

%mi^ Where? in the Tyring-room?
'2}ajies. Why ay. Sir. Hes fo dull .' Gome, fpeak again.
Phyf^ Sir, to conclude, the place you fill , has more than
amply exadted the Talents of a wary Pilot, and all thele threat-
ning ftorms, which, like impregnate Clouds, hover o'er otir
heads, will Cwhen they once are grafp'd but by the eye of
reafon) melt into fruitful ftiowers of bleflings on the people.
"Bayes Pray mark that Allegory. Is not that good?
'johfif. Ycs^ thatgrafping of adorm, with the eye, is ada
mirable.

Phyf,. But yet fome rumors great are ftirring 5 and i^Lerenzo
ihould prove (alfe-which none but the greatCods can tell ) you
then perhaps v/ould find that tr7~r- [_^Whif^ers^ ■

Bdyes. •Nowhewhirpers,
rt//&. Alone, do you fay > i'jfiib^
Thyf. No ^ attended with thenoblfe ^ ; ■ ^ '- ^''''- [U'hifpers^
$>ay€s^ hgmnv • ^ ''; .

VJI). Who, he in gray?

Thyf^ Yes 5 and at the head of- — - [ IVhifpers, ■

"Bayss* Pray mark.- /j i/. . .

VJJj^ Then,Sirj^moft certaiti, 'twill in tiw&dppear.-'
Tbefeare thereafons that have mov'd himto'tTj'"

Firft,he ^Wkifpers,

Bayesi Nowtheother w^hifpers, I^'- ' ^ • '; ; ■''^■' \^ ' ■
. Z^fi,. Secondly, they-r- ; ' ^' --h fr^ow ii^r^-^[^^ar/^.
..^^^'^j:, at it ft ill,.; .b,c^;riovpi'v^^i

i)fi\ Thirdlv, and lalHy^both he^andthcy'i* ''' \^h([pers^
B<z/^j. Now'the^y both v/hifper. \_E'xenf^t Wbfjperwg,

Now^ Gentlemen, pray tell me true, and without ifiattery , is'
not this.a very odd beginning of a Play ?

-imb;. - ' ,



'14 ThehebearjaL

JohKJllnuoih^ I think it is. Sir. But why two Kings of
the fame place }

^ayes. Why? becafe it's new i and that's it I aim at. I
defpife your ']ohr?fon and Eeanmofii^ that borrow'd all they
writ from Nature ; I am for fetching it purely out of my own
fancy, I,

3^7, But what think you. Sir, of Sir 'John Suckling,

Bajes. By gads I am a better Poet than he.

S»/L Well, Sir, but pray why all this whifpering >

BajiesyVhy^Sir^ (befides that it is new, fas / told you before)
becaufe they are fuppos*d to be Politicians 3 and matters of
State ought not to be divulgd.

S;i^/j, But then. Sir, why —

Bajies. Sir, ify ou1 but refpite your curiofity till the end of
the fifth Ad, you'l find it a piece of patience not ill recom-
penc'd, \_Goestothe do0r^

'johnf^ How doft thou like this, frank) Is it not juft as I
told thee>

S«?/, Why, I did never, before this, fee any thing in Nature,
and all that, (asMr JJ^^'^j fays) fo foolifh, but 1 could give
fome ghefs at what mov'd the Fop to do it^ but this, 1 confefs,
does go beyond my reach.

'johnf^ Iti&all a like .• Mr, Winterjlmlhzs informed me of
this Play already^ Andl'l tell thee, Franck^ thou fhait not
fee one Scene here worth one farthing, or like any thing thou
canft imagine ha<, ever been the pradice of the World. And
then, when he comes to what he calls good language, it is, as
I told thee, very fantaftical, moft abominably dull, and not
one wordtoth^ purpofe,

S«?/, It doesfurprife me, I'm fure, very much,
'John^ 1 5 but it won't do fo long : by that time thou haft
feen aPlay or twOjthatH fhew thee,thon wilt be pretty well ac-
(^uaintcd with this new kind of Foppery,

Smh Pox on't but there's no Pleafure in him : he's too
grofs a fool to be laugh*d at.

Enter Bayes^

Johnf^ V\ fwear, Mv^Bayes you have done this Scene moft

admi-



TheRebearfal 15

admirably 5 tho,! mult tell you. Sir 5 it is a very difficult mat-
ter to pen a Whifper well.

Bajes. Ij Gentlemen when you come to write your lelves,
O' my word, you'l find it (b,

JoIkJ, Have a care of what you fay, Mr. B^^e/, for Mr. ^mth
there,! afliire youjhas written a great many fipe things already.

Bajies. Has he, ifackins > Why then Pray, Sir, how do you do,
when you write ?

Sm. Faith, Sir, for the moft part, I am in pretty good health.

Bayes. 1 but I mean, what doyou do, when you write ^

S«/z/ 1 1 ake PeUi Ink, and Paper, and Sit down,

Bajies, Now, 1 write (landing ^ that's one thing .* and then, a-
Hother thing is, with what do you prepare your felf ?

S,97/. Prepare eiy felf ! what, the Devil, does the fool mean }

Bajes, V^hy^Vl tell you, now, what I do. If I am to write
familiar things, as Sonnets to Armida^ and the like, 1 make ufe
of Stew'd Prunes only 5 but , when I have a grand defign in
hand, I ever take Phific, and let blood : for, when you would
have pure fwiftnefs of thought, and iiery flights of fancy , you
muit have a care of the penlive part. lo fine,you muft purge the
Belly.

^mi By my troth, Sir, this is a molt admirable Receipt^ for
writing. • ^^ . ■ '^.

Baj/es Ay, 'tis my Secret 5 and, in good earh^ft, I think^ one
of the bed I have.

Smi, In good faith. Sir, and that may very well be.

Baj/cs. May be,Sir > I gadjl'm fure oviVExperto crede Robert o»
But I mult give you this caution by the way, be fure you never :
take fnuffjwhen you write.

S«?i. Why foSir>

Bayes. Why, it fpoil'd me once, I gad, one of the fparkillieft
Playes in all England' But a friend of mine, at Grejlum Colkd^e^
has promised to help me tofomefpirit of Brains,and, f gad, that :

fhal' do mv bnfinpfs



is TheRehearfaL



5C^NA II.

Enter the iwoKings^ hi^dinhatid^



:'{-V»lV



^ajies, /^H, Thefe now are the two Ktfigs oi?jrentford\ tafe
\J notice of their ftile : 'twas never yet upon the
Stage 5 butj if you like it, I could make a (hiftj perhaps, to Qiew
you a whole Play, writ all Juftfo, ,

I. Kifjg^ Did you obferve their whifper. Brother King ?
2» King^ I did r and heard, befides, a grave bird fing*
That they intend, fweet-heart^to play us pranks.

^ajies^ This is now, familiar, becaufe they are both perfons
of the fame Quality^

.ym/Sdeachj. this would make a man fpew.
i« iC/>^, Ifthat defign appears,
ri lug 'em by the ears
Until I make em cracky
2,\R:/»f. Andfowilll, i'fack.

1. ZC/«^,, You muftbegin, /lii7«/<?^,

2 . Kiftg, Sweet, Sir, Vardomtes mey^

Bayes, Mark that ,*, I makes 'em both fpeak Frertch^ te (hew
their breeding, :

'johnjl 0,'tis extraordinary fine I
2. Kiftg^ Then, fpite of Fate, we'll thus combined ftand ,
And like true brothers, walk ftil hand in hand.

. ..; \_ExetmfRegesi

Joh/if^This is a very Majeftic Scene Indeed,
-Baj/es, Ay , 'tis a cruft, a lafting cruft for your Rogue
Critiques, I gad .• I would fain fee the proudeit of 'em all but
dare to nibble at this 5 Igad^ if they do, this ihall rub their
gums for 'em, I promife you. It was I, you muft know, that
have written a whole Play juft in this very fame ftile 3 but.
t was never Aded yet^
Joh^Jl How fo,<?



The RehearfaL 17

Wayes. I gad, I can hardly tell yoUjfor laughing fha, haj ha)
it is [o plealant a ftory .* ha, ha, ha-.

Smi. What is't >

Bajes. I gad, the Players refasM to ad it. Ha, ha, ha.

Sf;/i, That's impoffible, ,

B^yes, I gad they did it, Sir, point blank refus'4- '% I gad.
Ha, ha, ha, ^ $ ^

Johfif Fie, that was rude;

Bajies. Rude! Ay,l gad^they are the rudeitjUncivilefl: perfbn?,,
and all that, in xhe whole world, I gad : I gad, there's no liv-
ing with 'em, I have written, Mr. jfd/^^y2'«, 1 do verily believe,
a whole cart- load of things, every whit as good as this, and
yet, I vow to gad, thefe infolent Raskals have turned 'em all
back upon my hands again,

Johfif. Strange fellows indeed!

Sfffi, But pray, Mr. Bayesy how came thefe two Kings to
know of this whifper ? for, as I rememberj they were not pre-
fent at it.

Bayes. No, but that's the Adors fault, and not mine 5 for
the two Kings ftiould ( a pox take 'em ) have pop' d both their
heads in at the door, juft as the other went off.

Smi. That, indeed, would ha* done it,

Bayes. Done it / Ay, I gad, thefe fellows are able to Ipoil
the beft things in Chriftendome. 11 tell you, Mr, Johnfon^l
vow to gad I have been fo highly difbbligd by the peremptori-
nefs of thefe fellows , that I'm refblv'd hereafter , to bend
my thoughts wholly for the iervice of the Nz/y/er;', and mump
your proud Players, I gad. So 5 txow Prince Pretty- man
comes in, and falls a fleep, making love to his Miftrefs,
which, you know,was a grand Intrigue in a late Play, written
by a very honefl Gentleman ; a Knight.



D SQE^h.



i§ . TheRebearfdL

SCifiNA Ilf;

■-'v. *^ .1 ,

Enter Prince Vrctty^man -

Pret. TTOw ftrange a captive am I grown of late/
JlJ Shall 1 accufe my Love , or blame my Fate ?
My Lovie, I cannot •, that is too Divide.-
Andj> agaJnft Fate, what mortal dares repine ?
Enter Cloiis,
But here (he comes. ^ *

Sure 'tis fome blazing Comet is it not > {Lj/esdown^^

Bayes. Blazing Comet ! m?rk that, I gad, very fine !
Tret* But lam fo furpris'd with ileep, I cannot Ipeak the

reft. [A^-^*

B^yes* Does not that^ now, furprife ypu, to fall a fleep
in the nick > His fpirits exhale with the heat of 'his pallion,
and all that , and fwop falls a fleep, as you fee. Now, here,
fhe maft make ajimk,

Smi. Where's the neccffity of that Mr. ^rf^e/.
Bayes. Becaufc (he's furpris'd. J hat's a general Rule, you .
muft ever make aj^i^/Ze, whenyou arefurpris'dj 'tis the new
way of writing.

ClpriSf As fome tall Pine, which we, on Mtnd^ find

T' have ftpod the rage of many a boifc'rous wind^
Feeling without, that flames within do play.
Which would conliime his Root and Sap away 5 .
He fpreads his woorfted Arms unto the Skies^ ,
Silently grieves, all pale, repines and die^;
, So, fhrowded up, your bright eye diiappears.
Break forth, brightfcorching Sun, and dry my tears

Jdhpf. Mr. E^iycj^ M^thinks , this fmle wants a little ap*
plication too.

B4/C/. No, faith, for it alludes to paflion^ toconfuming,
to dying,- and all that 3 which, you know, are the natural
effeds of an Amour^ But I'm afraid,, this Scene has made

you



The Kehearfal. 19

yo6 fad^ for^Imuft confefs, wlien I writ it, I wept my (elf.

Smu Noj truly^Sir, my fpirits areaimoft exhal'd to, and
1 am likelier to fall a flee p.

Prince Pretty-man J?4r^/ U^ym^Qiyi^'''^

?nt, ItisrefolvM. * [Exit.

'Baps, That's all.

smi, Mr.B^/e/jmay one be fo bold as to ask youaquefti-
on, now, and you not be angry .<?

itayes* O Lord, Sir, you may ask me any thing 3 what you
pleafe, I vow to gad, you do me a great deal of honour ♦*
you do not know me, if you fay that. Sir.

Smt, Then, pray. Sir, what is it that this Prince here has rc-
folv'd in his (leep.

Bajies. Why, I muft confefs, that queftion is well enough
ask'd, for one that is not acquainted with this i^ew way of wri-
ting. But you muft know5Sir5that5to out-do all iny fellow- Wri-
ters, whereas they keep 'their Intrigo fecret, till the very laft
Scene before the Dance 5 I now. Sir, ( do you mark me ) — a —
Smi, Begin the Play, and end it, without ever opening the
Plot at all?

Bayes^ I do fo, that's the very plain troth on't 5 ha, ha, ha;
I do, I gad. If they cannot find it out themfelves, e'en let *em
alone for B^^e/, 1 warrant you. But here, now, is a Scene of
bufinefs ; pray obfervc it s for 1 dare fay you'l think it no nn-
wife dtfcourfe this, nor ill argu'd. To tell you true,'tisaDif»
ccurfe I over-heard once betwixt two grand, fober, governing
f erfoas,

SCiENAlV.

Efiter Gentleman Vfjer andPfyftciav^

Vjlh #^0me5Sir^ let's ftate the matter of Fa£i:, and lay our
V^ heads together.
Thyf, Right .* lay our heads together. 1 love to be merry
fometimes5 but when a. knotty point conies' I lay my head
clofe to it, with a fnufF box in my hand, and then I fegue it a-
Way, ifaith, D i Bayes.



\y



20 The RebearfaL

Baj/es, I do juft fo^ I gad, alwayes.

Vfi, The grand queftion is, whether they heard us whif-
per? which I divide thus.

Pfyf. Yes, it rauft be divided fo indeed.

Sm, That's very complaifant, I fwear , Mr. Bajes^ to be of
another man's opinion, before he knowes what it is,

BayesNzyy 1 bring in none, here, but wel-bred perfbns, I
afiure you.

Vp.^ I divided the queftion into when they heard , what
they heard, and whether they heard or no.

Johnf, Moft admirably divided, Ifweax- ; .

VJh. As to the when 5 you fay, jult now ; So that is anfwer'd.
Then, as for what ^ why, what anfwers it felf .* for v/hat
could they hear, but what we talk'd of? So that, naturally,
and of neceility , we come to the laft queftionj Videliceti^
whether they heard or no.

Smi, This is a very wiCe Scene, Mr^ Bajes.
' 'Bayes. Ay, you have it right .• they are both Politicians,

Vfi. Pray then to proceed in method, let meask you that
queftion //

rhjif. No, youlanfwer better, pray let meask ityou.

Vflj^ Your willmuft beaiaw.

fhyf.Corat then, Vv/ hat is it I mull ask?

Smi. This Politician, Lperceive,Mr. ^aj/esj hasfomewbat
a fiiort memory.

Bajes, Why, Sir, yoil muft know, that t'other is the main
Politician, and this is but his pupil.

V^Qo You muft ask me v/hether they heard us whifper.:

Thy' WeU, Idofo.

VJIj. Say 'it then.

Sf2ji. Hey d ay \ here's the braveft work that ever I faw,

Jl?,6///,^ This is mighty methodical!

Waves'. Ay, Six -^ thaL';j the way ; 'tisthev/ay of Arl.5 there
is no other v;^, I gad , in bufinefs.

r/)//? Did l^y here us whifper >-

VJh. Vv'ny, truly, I can't tell j there's much to be fiid up-
on" the word Whifper .-to whifper, in Latin is Sitfarrare^ which
is-aS:aiuch as to fay^to ipeak fofriy ? now, if they heard us (p^ ak

ibfrly



The RehearfaL 21

foftly, they heard us whifper ; but then comes in the ^omedo^
the how j how did they hear us whifper ? Why^ as to that, there
are two wayes> the one, by chance, or accident .• the other,
on purpofe 3 that is, with defign to hear us whifper.

■phjf Nay, if they heard us that way,ril never give *em Phy-
lie more.

VJIj, Nor I e'er more will walk abroad before 'em.
B^^e/ pray mark this i for a great deal depend upon it, to-
wards the latter end of the Play.

Smi*^ I fappofe , that's the reafon why you brought in this
Scene Mr. Ba.yes }

^ayes^ Partly, it was, Sir, but, I confefs, I was not unwil-
ling, befides, to ftiew the world a patternj here, how men
Ibould talk of bufinefs.

Johnf, You have done it exceeding well indeed-
^^^ej-. Yes, f think, this will do.

Thyfi Well, if they heard us whifper^ they'l turn us out ,
and no body elfc will take us.

Smi^ Not for Politicians, I dare anfwer for it.

fhyf. Let's then nomoreo-ur felves in vain bemoan t

. We are not fafe until we them unthrone^
tj/?j. *Tis right.*

And, linc?e occafion now feems debonair,

l\ feizeonthisj and you (hall take that Chair.

I 7hey draw their Swords^ atidfit down m
1 the Wo great Chairs jqon the Stage,
j^^/^/. There's now an odd furprize:, the whole State's turn'd
<^uite topfie-turvy^ without any puther or ftir in the whole
world, I gad,

JchTjf^ A veryfilentchangeof aGovenment, truly, 'as ever
I heard of. . .

Bayes. It is fo. And yet you fhall fee me bring '■em in again^-
byandby, in as odd a way every jot,

ihe Vfffrpcrs march cut fiouri Jinn g their Srpords,
Enter S\\\v\y^.
Shir. Hey ho,, hey ho : what a change is here i Hey day,-.
hey day ! i knew not what to do, nor what to fay. [_Exii,,.

JphmJ



iii TmRebearjaL

Johnf. y[u Bajies^ in my opinion , now , that Gentlemaa
might have (aid a little more, upon this occafian.

ha^es^ No, Sir, not at all 4 for I under writ his Part, on
purpole to fet ofFthe reft.

Johrf^ Cry you mercy. Sir, ' -

S«?/. But, pray, Sir^ howcamethey to depofe the Kings fo
eafily?

Baj/es^ Why, Sir, you mufl: know, they long had a de-
fign to do it before , but never could put it in praftice till
now; and, to tellyoutrue^ that'sone r.eafonwhy Imad^'em
whifper fo at firlt

Sk//, O very well: now I'm fully fatisfi'd,

Bajfes, And then to (hew you, Sir, it was not done fo very
eafily n'dither 5 in this next Scene you fhall (ee fome fighting,

Sm. O, ho : fo then jou make the ftrugg le to be after tfig
bufinels is done ?

Eayes. Aye.

Bmf. O, i conccJiveyou / that, I fwear^ is very natural.

Enter four mm at 0ned0or^4f2dfiHr at amfther^mith their
Swords drapff, .

I soldier, OTand. Who goes there>



STa
2,



SoL A Friend^



1 Sol What Friend ?

2 ^ol. A Friend to the Houle^

3 «y<3/. Fall on. [jhejf alij{iil one another^ Mujic firth^s*
Baps. Holdj hold, [to tk Mujfc, ft ceafetk

Now here's an odd rurpr32:e / al! thefe dead men you ihall lee
rife up prefently, at a certain Note that I have mades in Effknt
fat^ and fall a Dancing. Do you hear, dead men? remember
your note in Effantflat, Play on, £ To the Mnfic.

Now, now, now. j The mnficplayhh t^ate^ and the dead men
O t^ord, O Lord! | rife ^ but cannot get in order.
Out, outj out \ Did evcv men fpoil a good thing fo ? no figure,
W ear, no time, nothing? Ud;&ookers, you dance worfe than

the



TbeRebearfal 23

h e Angels in Han/ the Eight, or the fat Spirits mTheTem-

I. ^^4 Why, Sir, 'tis impoffible to do any thing in time , to
this Tune.

Ba/es. O Lord, C Lord ! impoffible ? why. Gentlemen, if
there be any faith in a perfon that's a Chriftian, I (ate up two
whole nights in compoiing thisAir,andaptingitforthe bufi-
nefs .' for, if youobferve, there are two.feveral Defigns in
this Tune ; it begins fwift,. and ends (low. You talk of time,
and time 5 you (ball fee me do't. Look you now. Here I
am dead, \_Lks down flat m hisface^

Now mark my Note Effmt flat. Strike up Mufic.
Now, \_As he rjfes up haiiily^ ht falls dovpn again

Ah, gadfbokers, I have broke ray Nole.

^ohnf. By my troth^ Mr. ^ayes^ this is a very unfortunate
Note of yours, in E^«r/,

Bayes, A plague of this ddmn'd Stage, with your nail?,
and your tenter-hook« J that a Gentleman catinot come to
teach you to Act, bathe muft break his nofe, and his face,
and the devil and all- Pray, Sir, can you help me to a wet
piece of brown paper?

Smi^ No ipdeed, Sir 5 Idon'tufually carry any about me^

^.Sol. Sir, I 'I go get you fome within prefentlyj^

^ayes^ Go, go then 5 1 follow you. Pray dance out the dance
and^ri bewithyouis a moment^ Remember [you dance like
Horfmen. ' [Exit Bayes,

Smi, Like Horfemen ! what, a plague, can that be }

They danee. the Dance^, hut -can ffiake nothing of it.

I Sol, A Devil /let's try this no longer: play ray Dance that
Mr.. B^e/ found fault with (b. [pance & exet/nt,

Smi^ What can this fool be doing all this while about his
Nofe> ^

Johnf^ Pr'y the lets go fee; {jxeunt^ .



FinU Atim fecmdi.

ACTUS.



%A T^^RehearfaL



jriJ 'io



AC TuS III. SCi^NA I.

Bayes with a Papjn' on his N^Je^ and the two Cmtkmen,

Bajes^^^^ "TOWj SirSjthis Idps becanfe my Fancy, in this
* i^^ 1 Play, is to end every Ad with a Dance^
I ^^ Sm. Faith, that Fancy is very good, but I
iliould hardly have broke my Nofe for it, tho.
Johfif^ ThatFancyjIfuppofe^isnew too.
Qajies\ Sir, all my Fancies are fo, I tread upon no mans heels.-
but make my flight upon my own v/ings, I afliire you. Now,
here eomes in a Scene of (beer Wit, without any mixture in
the whole World, I gad, between Prince Pretty- man and his
Taylor : it might properly enough' becall'd a prize of Wit,^
for you ihall fee 'em come in upon one another fnipfnap, hit
for hit, as faft as can be^ Firft one fpeaks, then prefently
t'othersupon him, flap, with aKepartee, then he at him a-
gain, dafh with anew conceipt : andfo eternally, eternally,
I gad, tdlthey go quite offthe Stage.

Goes to callthe flayers,
Smi^ What a plague, does this Fop mean by his fnip fnap ,
hitforhit,and dafti/

'johnf^ Mean ! why , he never meant any thing in's life .•
what doft talk of meaning for ?

Enter Bayes.
S^^ej- Why don't you come in?

Enter Prince Pretty man and Tom, Thimble.
This Scene will make you dye with laughing, if it be well
Afted \ for 'tis as full of Drollory as ever it can hold : 'tis like
an Orange ftuffd withCloves, asfor conceit^,

Frer, But pr'y thee, Tom Thimble ^' v^hy wilt thou needs

mar*



t



The Rebea^fal. ^5

marry > If nine Taylors make but Oftc man 5 and one woman
cannot befatisfied with nine men : what wqjk art thou cutting
o»t here for thy felf^ trow ?

B<ye/. Good.

Thiw^ Why, ant pkafe your Highnefsj if I can't make u^
all the work I cut out, I fhan't want Journey-men enough to
help me, I warrant you/

haye/^ Good again.

Fret, lam afraid thy Journeysmen, thOj Tem^ wont work
by the day^ but by the night.

Baj/es, Good ftill.

rhim. However if ray wife fits but crofs-Iegd, as I do,
there will be no great danger .• not half fo much as when I
trufted you. Sir, for your Coronation-fait,

Bajies. Very good, i'faith.

Fret. Why, the times then liv'd upon truft* it was the
fafhion. You would not be out of time, at fuch a time as that,
fure : a Taylor5you know,muft never be out of fafhion.

Sa^eu Ri^r.

Tl)i/^^ I'mfuresSir,! made your Cloathsjin the Court* faOiion,
for you never paid me yet.

hajtes. There's a bobfor the Court I

Pre/. Why, Ti?w,thouart a (harp rogue when thou art an''
gry, I fee.* thou pay'ft me now, methinks.

Bayes* There's pay^ upon pay ! as goodas ever was written,
I gad! ! ^i :g-a<i^-i:> M^ ot V,

J Thim^ I, Sirg in your own Goyn.:yoii give me nothing but
words. " ''''^ ■ ;^ '■. '

Bajes, Admirable, before gad ! ^^i?;

Fret^ Weil, T<7«2, 1 hope ffiortly I (hall have another coyn
for theei for now the Wars are coming on, I fhall grow to
be a man of mettal;

Bajies, O, you did not do ihat half enough.
- Johfif, Methinkshe does it admirably.

Bayes^ I, pretty well 5 but he does not hit me in't : he does
not top his part. :

2 ^/«?. That's the way to be Jtamo'd your felf. Sir. Ifball



2£ ^i^-^'Jhe ReBe^rfaL

iee you come liome, like an Angel for the Kings-Evil, with a
hole bbr'dfhrough you. ^ {_Exen»t^

^ayes. Ha, there he has Kit it up to the hilts, Igad! How-
do you like it now. Gentlemen? Is not this pure Wit>

%mi^ 'Tis fnip fiiap. Sir, as you fay^ but, methinks, not
pleafant, nor to the purpbfe, for the Play does not go on.

B^j^e/. Play dees nor goon ? I don't know what you mean^:
why, is not this part of the Play ?
:■ ^mu Yes, but the Plot ftands- [till.

V>ayes^ Plot Hand ftill ! why, what a Devilis the Plot good
for, but to bring in fine things?

5.2!!?/^ 0>' I did not know that' before^

'hayes. No, I think you did not : nor many things more., that
I am Mafter of Now, Sir, Igad, this is the bane of all us
Writers : let us foar but never (b little above the common pitch,!
g-ad, all's fpoil'd , for the vulgar never underftand if, they can
never conceive you. Sir, the excellency of thefe things,..

Johfif^ Tis a lad fate^ . I muft confefs .* but you UTite on ItilJ »
for all that? . •

Bay^s, Write on? I, Igad, I warrant you. *Tis not their
talk (hall (top me ; if they carch meat that lock, II give 'em
leave to hang me. As long as I know my things are gosd,
T'^hatcare I, what they lay s^ What^ "are they gone, wii>M')ut
finging my laft new Song ? Sbud , would it were in thcix
Bellies. , I'll, reli you j Mr.^ Johrtfon^ if I have.any jkillinthefe
matters, I vow to gadj this Song is peremtorily the very bed
that ever yet was written ; you jnuft know^, it ,Was- made
by Tom Thimbles firlt wife after file was dead^

^///?, How, Sir? after (he wasd^ad? ^

B^yes. Ay, Sir, after fhe wa^, dead. Why, what have you
to (ay ,to|:hat > : ,no ' -tjftiffiab -j^i s aie W ' uiv^wi, . •

5<?6?{/^ Saj? > Why, nothing: he werea^tHat Devil bid any.
thing to fay to thai?,; ._^ •■ ,• - -:>- ■■ L.o u... y >^ .\.;.. .

£mi, How did (lie com€ to dye, pray Sir? >iq Jr.

Bayes* Phoo ! tliat's no matter , by a fall ; but ;here's the
cQiicqir.-ihat.uppahis ka jwipg (I15 was . kill 'd;by.aiiaccident^.he
. -1 :i . ftippoles^.



ibe IxebectrjaL *57

fuppdfes, with a Sigh, that fhedy'd for loveof hlra.
Joh^j, I5 T, that*s wellicriouf^H :\tts hear it, Mt^Bixyes.
Bayes. 'Tisto theTiioe of Farewel, fair Armida^ on Sea?,,
and in battdlsj mEuiietSj.and all that. ' "

S N G,
In fwords, Pikes, and BulletSj 'tis fafer to be^
ThaninaStrong Callle, remoted from thee .*
My deaths'bruife pr^y thinltryoii gave me, tho a faU
Did give it me more;, from the top of a wall 5
For theniftUe Moat on her mud wo-uld iirtt lay.
And after before you my body convey:
. The blew on my bi eft. w.h^njyfon happen to fee,

You^l fay, with a Sigh, there's a True blew for me.
Ha^Hogues! when I am merry, I write: ithefe things as faftaii
hops, I gad ; for^you muft kn<?^>K3laiii>as|?Ieafant a Debauchtec,
as ever you law : I am ifaith,'.^.^ rr-nf^ " • 7/^^f? .gsT^s'i J T-

Smi, But Mr^ Bayes, how cdmcs this fong in here ? for^ me-
thiriks, there is no great 0:eca(H)n ior. it. i)-,

B-ayes, Alackj-Sir, ypu h'j^Qjv nothing Try on. muft ever in-
terlard your Play es .with S^ngs, Ghofts, and Dances, if you
raeanto — a— lOiJiyi :5^„r^uii

J^^»/ Pit, Box, and Gallery, Mr. F^fyexi " '•> ;.r; ,

Bayes. I gad 3 and you have nick'd ii:. Haik you, Mr.
Johffjhn, you know I don't flatter, a gad, you. have a grejj^E^

-deal ofWit. ^ ,i[r;'ti;ii ioi.'bfivyig^*^''f ^^^^•/■''^';^-^'4

Jof^ftf. O Lords Sir, you do me too' much honotirl ' :♦' " ' ^
Bayes. Nay, nay, come, come, Mr. Johnfm^ I faith this mnft
not be faid>,amongft usthat have it* 1 know you have wit by
the judgment you make ofthis Play 5 for that^s the meafurel
go by: my Play is my Touchftone. When a man tells me fueh
a oneisaperfon of-parts^ is hefOj fay I> what do I d©, but
bring him prefently to fee this Play .• tf he likes it, I know
what to think of him , if not, your moft humble Servant, Sir,
ri \m more of him upon ray word, I thank yoii. I am CUrit
t^p^rf«^5 Igad. Nowherewego.ontoourbuliiiefse



0^ I m ly^eoearjai.

SCjENA II.

Enter the two Vfirpers^ hand in handj

Vfi « 13 U^t what's become of Volfcius the great >

X3 ^Js prefence has not^,rac'd our Courts of late.
. Phj/j] Ifearfomeill, fromciftulationfprung.
Has from us that llluftrious Hero wrung.
S4^e/, Is not that Majeftieal ?
Smi, Yes, but who a Devil is that Volfcius >
B<yex» Why, that's a Print^e I make in love with Parlhe*

nope. ,.-•■,.* V'^^^i 'l-t; i^lvi'i^ -{[ijs;'-" ^ *' •"'':.•'

^2%?/. .Ithanky^OiSir-"^^-''^'^ .■■'^''^'■^-^'^^^'■' '^'■-

: 'f»/^y Cord€li6!,/^^^'
£:•^;*. MyLieges, news fromr^s^Z/ciajthePrlncc;
Z^^. Hts news is welcome^ whatfoe'er it be.
Smi, How, Sir, do you mean whether if be good or bad,
^ayes^ ^^ay, pray > Sir, have a4!ltle patience .* Codfookers

you'l fpoil all my Play. VVhy, Sii^j tis impoffible to anfwer eve-
ry impertinent queftion you ask,
Smi, Cry you mercy. Sir.

:\1Jpr^* Hts flighnefs Sirs, commanded me to tell you^ ,

T^^t th;e !&ir pqrfon whom you both do knowg

D^fpairing of forgivenefs for her fault,

Inadeepferrow, twiceflie didattemt

Upon her precious life 5 but by the eiire

Qf flandersby prevented wa% ih.it ci: '■,»^,/\ij^i\. ^ ^
%mi, 'Sheart, what ftuffs here r^-<' ojIkcboo^^ :j.i- .
,:0^ Atkft. '/ ..; .nbn;Ar 7m.ei ^r* .

VflfijHs the great this dire refol ve embraced .*

His fervants he into the Countrey fent.

And he himfelf to Per/'4i5^//7^ went.

Wher:e he's inforin'd, by Letters that fhe'^ dead.^
t;/;vDead ! is that poffibie > Dead ! ' '^' '^^^^^
^^•t^/.0,yeGods! : lExawA-

Bajes. There's a fmart expreffion of a pailion 3 O ye Gods !

That's



ThRebearfal 38

That's one of my bold ftrokes, I gadp
Smi, Yes 5 but who is the fair perfon that's dead ?
Bajcf. That you (hall know anon Sir.
Sm-. Nay; if we know it at all, 'tis well enough:
Bayef, Perhaps you may find too,, by and by, for all this

that (he's not dead neither.
S«//. Marry, that^s good news indeed -vl am glad of that

with all my heart.
B^^f/,Now here's the man brought in that isfuppos'd to have

kiird her. [^agnatfiont wnhin^ >

SG^NA III.

EnTer Amar ill is with a Bookjn her hafidy:
and Jttsndants^

AmcL. \^ That fhout triumphant'5 that ^

VV EnteraSouldier, ^

5^^/. Shie maldjUpon the River brink, near twick^nam io'^^v.^
the falfe Aflaflinate is tane.

^;!»^. Thanks to the Powers above, for this deliverance. I
hope its flow beginning will portend. • :|

A forward Ex/^ to all future end.

Bayes, Pifh, there yoa are out ^ to all Future end i No , no ^
to all future End : you muft lay the accent upon end, ore ife
you lofe theconceiptrf^

Smi* I (ee you are very perfect, in thefe matters*

"Bayes. I, Sir 5 1 have been long enough at it,one would think^
to know fome thing.'

EfJter Souldiers dragging in au old Fificr-moKj .

Ama. Villainj what Monlter did corrupt thy riiind
T'attaque the nobleft foul of humane kind? ;

Tell me who let thee on# ^

' Fifi\ Prince Prett)^man.

yf/?/<i. To kill whom? . -

Fijh. Fi'mce Pretty-njan.

Ama^ VVhatj did Prince frmy.mm hire you to kill Piince



^o TbeReheai^aU

Jma, To kill whom ?

FrJIj.PnnceFolfcms ^

Ama. What did Prince Volfcius hire you to kill Prince
Volfcius}

'FijJi.'^O'^VxmctVrettyntan.

i^«/ve. So drag him hence.

Till torture of the Rack produce his Senfe.[E;^eK»/,'

Bayes, Mark how I make the horrour of his guilt confound
his intellects , for he's out at one and t'other : and that's the
defign of this Scene.

Smi. 1 fee. Sir, you have a feveral defign for every Scene.

Bayes, I, that's my way of writing • and fo Sir, I can difpatch
vyou a whole Play^before another man, I gad^, can make an end
of his Plot,



SCiENA IV,






SO now entec Prince trettj-maKin a rage* Where the De-
vil is he? Why Pi'^//;'-«^^« .^ why when, I fay? Ofiejfie,
lie, fie! all's raarr'd, I vow to gad, quite marr'd,

E»/ey Pretty-man,
Phoo, pox! you are cometo late. Sir, now you may go out
againjifyou pleafe. Ivowtogad, Mr. — — a-^- — I would
not give a button for my rlay^ now you have done
this* '

Pret» What Sir?

B4;e/* What Sir! 'Slife, Sir, you (hould have come out in
choler, rous upon theStage, ju ft as the other went ofl^ Muft
a man be eternally telling you of thefe things ?

Johnf Sure this muft be feme very notablej matter that he's
ib angry at.

f/;27. 1 am not of your opinion.
ayes, Pifli ! come, let's hear your part. Sir,
:pret. Bring in my Father^ why dye keep him from me ?
Altho a F ifherman, he is my Father,
Was ever .Son, jet brought to this diftrefs^

To



The Rehear faL . 3f

To be, for being a Son, made fatherlefs^
Ahj you juffc Gods, rob me not of a Father .*
The being of a Son take from me rather. , [^EKit,

Smk Well, Ned^ what think you now ?
Johnf,^ Devil this is word of all. Mr. ^ayes^ pray what's
the meaning of this Scene ?

Bii^e/.O, cry you mercy. Sir; IpurteftI had forgot to tell
you. Why, Sir, you muft know, that long before the begin-
ning of this Play, this Prince was taken by a Fiiherman.
Smi, How, Sir, taken Prifbner }

hayes. Taken Prifoner ! O Lord, what a queftion's there !
did ever any man a^k fuch a queition? Godfookers, he has
put the Plot quite out of my head, with this damn'd queftia
on. What was I going to fay ? •

Jok/if, Nay, the Lord knows ; I cannot imagine,
Bjj/e/. Stayjet mefee^ taken : O 'tis true. Why, Sir, as I
was going to fay, his Highnefs here, the Prince, was taken in a
Cradle by a Fifheiman, and brought up as his Child,
^f^i. Indeed }

IBayes, Nay, pr'ythe hold thy peace. And fo, Sir 3 this
murder being committed by the River-fide, the Fiiherman,"
upon fufpition, was fcfe'd 5 and there upon the Prince grew
angry.

Swi, SOjfo 5 now 'tis very phin.

Jif^fff But Mr. B/i^^&^fj Is not this fome ditparagemenftoa -
Prince, to pafs for a Fifliermans Son? Have a care of that i-
pray. . ■■\,^ -■■''''

Bayes, No, no ^ ^ot 'ivt all > for 'tis but for a while .• 1 (hall
fetch him off again, prefently 3 yoi.l'hall fee^ -
£^^er- Pretty -man a/td Thimble.
rret. By all the Gods/I'l let the world on-fire
Blather than let em ravilh' hence my Sire.
Tkiffii Brave Pretij/maf^j it is at length, reveai'd, .

That he is noi thy Sire who thee conceal d«
B/^/j'ej-. Lo-you now^there hCijofFagain,
5^/^;//^ Admirably done i'faith.
- ^ hikjes^ Ay, now the Plot thickets very m.uch upon u^,-^^ ^ ■' ' " '



Xji TheRebearfdL

rF/*^/, What Oracle this darknefs can evince ?

/Sometimes a FiQiers Son, fometimes a Prince^
It is a fecret , great as is the world 5
In which, 1 like the Soul, am tos'dand hurl'd.
The black eft Ink of Fate^fure, was my Lotj
And, when (he writ my Name^ fhemade a blot«

{Exit.
■"^ayes^ There's abluftnng verfe for you now.
S«?/. Yes, Sir 5 but why is he fo mightily troubled to find
he ii not a FiQiermans Son.*?

- Bayes» Phoo / that is not becaufe he has a mind to be his
Son, but for fear he ihould be thought to be no bodies Son
at all ♦
S«^/, Nay, that would trouble a.man, indeed.
.Baycs, Soletmefee.

.SCiENA V". .

Enter Prince Volfcius, going out of Town, [^Reads.

Sml. T Thought he had been gone to Teccadille,

jL Bayes. Yes he gave it out fo 5: but that was only to
:co\'er his defign,

Joknf^ What defign?

Bayes, Why, to head the Army 3 that lies conceal'd for him
m Knights -bridge,

Johnf, I fee here's a great deal of Plot, Mr* ^ayes,

Bayes, Yes, now it begins to break > but we (hall have a
-world ofmorebufinefsanon*

Enter Prince Volfcius, Cloris, Amarillisj and Bsiny tfiitk
a Riding'CJoak^and^o&ts.,

Amcu Sir, you are cruel, thus to leave the Town,
And to retire to Country folitude.

C/<?. We hop'd this Summer that we (hould at leaft "^'

Have held the honour of your Company.

Bayes, Held the honour of your Company ! prettily expreftj
Held the honour of your Company ! Godfookcrs, thefe fel-
Qws.will never take notice of any thing, Johnf^



The Rebearfal. 35

Jd^f^ laflureyOuSirjIadmireit extrearoly : I don't know
what he does;

^a^es^ I^I^he's a little envious 3 but*tis no great matter.
Come.

^ma. Pray let us two this fingle boon obtain.

That yon will here, with poor us, (till remain.
Before your Horles come pronounce our fate.
For then^ alas! I fear j 'twill be too latCj
Bajies. Sad J

Volf. Harry ^ my Boots 5 for I'l go rage among
My Blades encamp'd, and quit this i)rban throng.

StHi, But pray, Mr. Bayes^ is not this a little difficult, that
yon were faying e'en now^ to keep an army thus conceal'd in
Knights- hrid^e^

Bayes, In Knightshridge ) ftay,
'johnf. No, not ifthe Inn-kcepcrs be his friends,
Bayes, His Friends/ Ay, Suyhis intimate acquaintance* or
tclfe, indeed, \ grant it could not be.

^w/. Yes, faith, (bit might be very eafie.
Bayes, NaVj If I do not make all things ealie, I gad, I'l gi v^
you leave to hang me. Now you would think that he is going
out of Town i but you Ihall fee how prettily 1 have contriv'd
to ftop him, prefently.

Smi. By my troth. Sir, you have fo amaz*d me, that 1 know
aotwhat to think.

K^^er Parthenope.
Volf. Biefs me ! how frail are all my beft refolves !
How, in a moment, is my puipole chang'd I
Too foon I thought my felfefeciire from Love,
Fair, Madam, give me leave to ask her name
:; . .- Who does fo gently rob me of my fame?
For I fliould meet the Army out of town.
And, if I fail, muft hazard my renown,
raf\ My Mother, Sir, fells Ale by the Town- walls,

And me, her dear .P4r/^e;/^;jtf {he calls.
Bjiyes^ Now that's the Purthenope^ I told you of.
"johnf, I, I .* I gad you are very right.

" - F ^Hln



34' TMKekarfal.

r<?/^ Can valgaiC veftments high- born beauty fhroud?
Thou bring'ft the Morning piftur'd in a Cloud,
B^je/. The Morning pi6tur'd in a.CIpud! A, G^diookcr.^
what a conceipt isrhere !

Far. Give you good Ev'n, Sir. -i [£^/|.

Volft, O in, aiifpicious Stars / that I was born-

To fiiddcn love, and to. more fuddenicorn ! ^
Ama. ^ How ! Prince Volfcins i^ love } Ha, ha, ha.
Clor^ ^ [ Exeufit laughing,

Smi, Sure, Mr»B^/e/y.w^ have lQft,ifome jeft here, that
tbey laugh at fo.

i^ayes* Why,didyou not obferve } He firdrefolves to go out
ofTown, andthen, as. he is pulling on his Boots falls inlove
with her» Hajhajha.

Smi^ Well, and where lye$ the jeft of that ?
'Bayes Ha ? [7Hrj?s to^hrjfofi^

jFM»/; Why.$ In the Boots ; where (ho^ld the jeft lie >
Hayes. I Gad^you are in the right ; it does [turns to Smith
Lie in the Boots- Your friend, and I know where a good jeft
lies, tho you don't. Sir.
^a?i> Much good do'tyoUjSir,

^ayes. Here, now, Mr^ /J^/j»/^», you toll Cee a combat be-
twixt Love and Honour. An ancicnt-Authoi; has made a whole
Play on t ^ but 1 have difpatch'd \t all, in this Snene.

Vo\[ciusjltsdorpfitopi£llofi hishodfs: ^ayts Stands by
andovera{istheFartashefpcaks7t,
Volf How has my pallion Made me Cup^d s fcofi I .
This hafty Boot is on, the other off, .
And fullen lies,with amorous dcfign
T J qu^'t loud, fame, and make that Beauty mine,'
Smi^ Pr ythee mark what pains. Mr..£rf^e/ takes to Adl this
fpeech himfcife !

Johnf^ Yes, ,th? fool, i ^.^. is -mightily tranrportedwith;



Volf, My Legs, theEmblem of. my various thought.
Shew to what fid din:ra^ti<>n I am brought. »
Sometimes with iiubbarii Honoiirj,.likv thisBootj



My



i be ixebear(ii(^ 55

"My mind is guarded, and, refolv'd : to dot.*
Sometimes, againj that very mindj by Love
Dilarmed, like this o^her Leg does prove.
Shall I to Honour or to Love give way >
Goon, cries HonoLir 5 tender Loyefaies, nay .•
Honour, aloud, commands., pluck both Boots onf
^"1^- foit«r Love does whifper put on none.
Vv hat fhall 1 do> what conduft (hall I find
To lead me through this twy-light of my mind >
For as bright Day with black approach of Night
Contending, makes a doubtful puzling light 5
So does my Honour and my Love together
Puzzle me io^ I can refolve for neither, [Goes out hap-
ping with om Boot on^ and the other off,
"johfif. By my troth, Sir, this is as difficult a Combat as ever
Ifaw, and as equal ■-> for 'tis determiu'd (;n neither (ide.

Buji'es. Ay, is't not now I gad, ha ? For, to go ofThip hop,hip
hop, upon this occafion, is a thouland times better than any
conclufion in the world, I gad.

Johnf Indeed, Mr. B^j'e/, that hip hop, in this place as you
fay, does a very great deal.

i,ayes. O, all in all Sir i they are thefe little things thatmar^
or fet you offa Play ; as I remember once,ia a Play of minej fet
-offa Scene I gad, beyond expectation^ only with a Petticoat,
and the Belly ake.

S»/i„ Pray, how vv as that. Sir?,'

Y)ajies. Why, Sir,I contriv d a Petticoat to be brought in
uponaChair, ( no body knew how ) into a Prince's Chamber 5
whofe Father Vv^as not to fee it, that came in by chance^

'johnf. God's my life, that was a notable Contrivance in-
deed,

Smi.lhwt^ Mr. ^djes^ how could you contrive the Belly-
ake > .

Vtaj/es. The eafielt ith' World, I Gad.- 11 teilyou how, I
made the Prince fit down upon the Petticoat, no more than fo ,
and pretended to his Father that he had juft then got the Belly-
ake : whereupon, hisFathet went out to callaPhytkian.and

, F i ' Hs



30' lmKebearjak>

his man ran away with the Petticoat.

Smi, Well and what follow'd upon that >

«^^e/. Nothing, no Earthly thing, I vow to Gad,

"johnf. O, my word, Mr. ^ajies^ there you hit it.

Bayes, Yes It gave a world of content; And then I paid 'em
away befideSj for I made 'em all talk,baudy5 ha. ha, ha.-
beaftly, downright baudry upon the Stage, IgaS > !5*f ha^ ha 3
hut with an infinite deal ofwit, that, I muft fay.

Jehfi]. That, Ithat, we know well; enough, can never faii
you.

^ajes» No, I Gadcan't it come bring in theOanceQ Exit,

to call'em^

Smi, Now, the Devil take thee for a filly, confident junnatu-
ral, fulfom Rogue.

£»^(?rBayes ^;?<^ {^layers.

B^^e/. Pray Dance well, before thefe Gentlemen ; you are
commonly {o lazy • bijt you (hoald be light ancj eafic^tah, tah
tab.

All the TX>hik they Dance^ Bayes puts, *em $Ht ■;.
Tfitfj teachivg'em. :
Well Gentlemen, you'l fee this Dance, if lam notdeceiv'd,-
take very well upon the Stage, when they are perfed in their
snotions, and all that.

SmL \ don't know how 'twill take, Sir 5 but I am fii re you
fvyeat hard for't.

Bayes, Ay, Sir, it cofts me more pains and trouble^^ to do
thefe things, than almoft the things are worth.
. Smi, By my troth, I think fo, Sir,

"Bayes f Not for the things themfelves, for 1 could write you ,
Sir, forty of 'em in a day 5 butj I gad, thefe Players are fuch
dull perfons, that, if a man be not by 'em upon every point, and
at every turn, I gad, theyl miftake you. Sir, and fpoil all. ,

Enter a Player.
What, is the Funeral ready?

TUy. Yes, Sir,

BAyss.* And is the Lance fiird with Wine .?

P/^j. Sir? 'tis juft now a doing.



The Reharfal. 37

B^ajies^ Stay then,!'] do it my felf,

Smi, Cornea ^^^'^ go with him,

Bajes. A Match, But Mr. Jolmfon^ 1 gadj am not like other
perlbns V they care not wliat becomes of their thingSj fb they
can but get mony for em ^ now, Igad, when i write^Jf it be
not juft as it fl^iould bein every circumftance, to every par-
ticular, I gad 3 larp no more able to endure it, lam not my
fejfj Tm out ofmy witSj and all that, Im the ftrangeft perfon
in the wliole world. For what care I for mony ? I write for
Reputation, {Exeunt*

Finh Atlu! tertiu



-w



ACTUS IV. SCiENA I.

^yts^ and thivfo Gentlemen,

Bi?/^/^^'*^ Entlemen^ becaufe 1 would not have any two
■ -jr things alike in this Play, the laft Adi beginning
^^-^ with a witty Scene of Mirth, I make this to be-
gin with a Funeral.

Smi, And is that all your reafon for it,Mr: '^ayesl

'Bayes^ No, Sir, I have a Precedent for it befides. A perfon
of Honour, *and a Scholar ^ brought in his Funeral juft io : and
he was one (let me tell you ) that knew as well what belong'd
to a Funeral, as any man in E^'^/zW, I gad.
' jf<?^«y! Nay if that be fo, you are faft,

hajesj gad, but I have another device , a frolick, which I
think yet better than all this, not for the Plot or Charaders,
( for in my heroic Plays, I make no difference, as to thofe mat-
ters) but for another contrivance,

Sm/^ what is that, I pray?

Bajies^ Why, I have defign'd a Conqueft, that Cannot pof-
fibly, I gad, be afted inlefs than a whole week .• and Tl fpeak a

bold



38 The RebearfdL

bold word, it (hall Drum, Trumpet, Shout^ aad Battle,! gad
with any the moft warlike Tragoedy wehavCj either ancient
or modern.

y<?^»y^J^marry, Sir, there you fay fomethJHg.

Smi, And'pray, Sir, how have you order'd this fame froilc
of yours? •

Baj/es. Faith, Sir,, by the Rule of Romance. For exam-

'pie .* they divided their things into three, four, five, fixjfeveu,

eight, or a/many Tomes as they pleafe : now, I Vv^ould very fein

know what (hould hinder me, from doing the fame with my

things, if I pleafe >

Johfff, Nay,if y ou fhould not Be Mafler of your own works,
'tis very hard.

Brf/ex, That is my fence. And then, Sir, this contrivance of
mine has fomethirig of the reafonof a Play in it too 5 for as e-
verv one makes you €ve Ads to one Play, what do me I, but
make fivePlayesto one Plot .• by which means the Auditors
have every day a new thing,

Johfif, Mod admirably good , iTaith 1 and muft certainly
take, becaufe it is not tedious.

Bayes, T3 Sir, I know that, there's the main point. And
then, upon Saturday^ to raakeaclofe of all, ( for I ever begin
upon a Monday) I make you, Sir, a fixth /'lay, that fums up the
whole matter to em, and all that, for fear they fhould have
forgot it* ,

^ohnf^ That confideration, Mr, B^/i'/, indeed, Ithinkj will
be very neceflary,

%mt. And when comes ia your fhare, pray Sir ?

^ayes. The third week.

^(7/6;?/. I vow you'l get a world of money.

^Ayes^ Why, faith, a man muft live .* andif you don t, thus,
pitch upon fome new device, I gad^ you'l never do it, for this
Age C take it o*my word ) is fomewhat hard to pleafe. But
There's one pretty odd paflage, in the lalfcof thele Plays
which may be executed two feveral ways, wherein I'd have
your opinion. Gentleman.

J^?^;?/ What is't, Sir >



TbeRebear/at 59

hayef. Why^ S\v^ I make a Male perfon to be in Love with
aFemale.

Sm^ Do you mean that, Mr. B^ye/, for a new thing >

Baj/es. YeSj Sir, as I have order'd it„ You (hall here. He
having paflionately lov'd her through my five whole Flayes,
finding at laft that (ke confents to his. love, juft after that his
Mother had appear'd to him like a Gholi, he kills himfel^
That's one way. The otheristhat fhe coming at laft toJove
him, with as violent a paflion as he lov'd her, (he kills her felf^
Now my queftion is, which of thefe two perfons thould fufJer
upon this occafion?

Jo^»f By my trothj it is a very hard cafe todecide^

^ajes. Thehardeft m the World, Igad, andhaspuzled this
pate very much. What fay you Mr. ^mith}

Smii Why truly Mr, B^^e/, ifitmight ftand with your ju-
fticenow, 1 would fpare 'em both,

Bayes, I gad, and I think ha why then, I'l make

him hinder her from killing her feife. Ay, it fball be (b. Come,
come, bring in the Funeral.

Efiter a Funeral^ with the wo Vfnrpers and AttendaKis,
Lay it down there .* no, no, here, Sir. So nowfpeak .

K^VJb:, Set down the Funeral Pile, and let our grief
Receive, from its imbraceSjfome relief;

K. Phyf. Was't notunjuft to ravifh hence her breath.

And, in life's (lead, to leave us nought but death.
The World difcovers now its emptinefs.
And, by her lof?, demonftrates we hav^ lefs

^ayes^ Is not this good language nowi* is not that elevate?
'Tis my ?26n ultra^^ I gad. You mult know they were both
in love v/nh her.

Sm, Withher> with whom? ' •

Bayes^ Why, this is I ^r^^e^^'j Funeral. ^

Smi^ Lardella 1 1, who is (he ?
- Bayex^ Why, Sir, the Sifter of Dran^caf;fr> A Lady that
was drown'd at Sea ., and had a wave for her Winding
iheet,^ .V

K.Vfi.Lardel/a^ OLardel/a^ftom-^hoYcl -

Be*



^o TbeRehearfaL

Behold the Tragic iffues of our Love, >
Pity us, finking under grief and pain,
For thy bein g call away upon the Main.
Bayes, Look you now, you fee I told you true,
Sffii, I, Sir,, and 1 thank you for it, very kindly.
Bajfes, Ay 5 I gad, but you will not have patience 3 honeft
M. — — a— — - you will not have patience.

Jokfjf, Pray, Mr. g^j-e/, who is that Dr^jo'^^^/zr ?
Bajfes. Why, Sir, a fierce Hfr<?, that frights his Miftrefs, fnubs
up Kings, bathes Armies, and does what he willj without regard
to numbers, good manners^ or juftice.
Johftf. Avery pretty Charafter.

Smi. Bur, Mv.Eayesy I thought your Heroes had ever been
men of great humanity and juftice.

ha;fes. Yes, they have been fo ^ but for my part, I prefer
that one quality of fingly beating of whole Armies above all
your moral virtues put together, I gad* You (hall fee him
come in prefently, Zookers, why don't you read the paper?

[_To the T layers^
K Vhyf. O, cry you mercy. \Coes to take the paper,

ftayes^ Pifh ! nay you are fucha fumbler. Come II read it
myfclC \Takes a pdper from off the Coffin*

Stay, it's an ill hand. I mufl: ufe my Spectacles. This, now, is
a Copy of Verfesa which I make i:<«r^e//<^ com pofe, juftas (he
is dying, with defign to have it pin'd upon her Coffinjand fb
read by one of the Dfurpers, who is her Coufin,

S///i, Avery (hrewd defign that, uponmy woi\d, Mr^B^^e/.
S/i^ej. And what do yon think now I ftncy her to make Love
like, here, in the paper >

Smi, Like a Woman.* what fhould fhe make Love like^
Bayes^ Omy vTord you are out tho,.Sir» L gad, you are.
%mi. What then } like a man >
hayes. No, Sir , like a Humble Bee,
S-^//. I confefs, that I ihould not have fancy d.
Bayes. h maybe fo^SirB But it is, tho, in order to the
opinion of fome ofyour ancient philofophers, v/ho heldth^
tranfm'gration of thefoi'.l.

Smi.



IbeRehedrfaL ifi

^mi, Very fine. ^

Bayes. f I read the Title. T& my dear Cou%y Kiffg PhyC
5»z/. That's a little too familiar with a King, tho^ Sir,, by
your favor, for a Humble Bec^

^ayes, Mr. ^^/i^^, in other things^ I grant your knowledge
may be above mei but, as for Poetry, give me leave tofay,
I uaderftand that better .• it has been longer my pra(li:ice\ it
has indeed, ^ir.

S^i, Yaur (ervant. Sir.
B<yej, Pray mark it.»

Since death my earthly part will thus remove [ Reads^
V\ cornea Humble Bee to your chafte love.
With filcnt wings Til follow you, dearCouz,
Or elfe, before you, in the Sun-beams, buz.
And when to Melancholy Groves you come.
An Airy Giio/ljyou'i icnow me by my Hum 5
For found, being Air^ aOholt does well become,
Smi. C Jfter apaufe^} Admirable!
hayes. At night, into your bofom I will creep.
And buz but foftly if you chance to fleepv
Yet* in your Dreams, I will pafsfiveepiugby,"
And then, both Hum an Buz before your eye,
'Johfff. By my troth, that's a very great promife.
Smi, Yes, and a moft extraordinary contort to boot,
Baycf, Your bed of love from dangers ! will free.
But mofl from love of any future Bee.
And when with pity your heart- firings fhall crack.
With empty arms il bear you on my back.
Smi. A pick-a-pack, a pick-a-pack,
Bayes. Ay, I gad, but is not that ?//4v7/ now, ha? is it not
tuafit ? Here's the end.

Then at your birth of immortality.
Like any winged Archer, hence i'l fly.
And teach you your firli fiutt'ring in the Sky.
Jvhf^f. Orare! This is the molt natural_j refin'd far^cy ihat
ever 1 heardj I'l fv/ear. '

Bayes^ Yes, 1 Think, for^ dead perfoOj it is a good enorJgh



4^ / mtiehearjal.

Way of making love : for being divefted of her Terreftrial
part, and all that, (he is only capable of thefe little; pretty j
amorous defigns that are innocentj and yet paflionate* Come,
draw youfwords.

Ki P/6j^ Come (wot dj come (heath thy (elf within this breaft.

Which only in L^r^e//// Tomb can re(t.
iC. tJ/7^. Comcj dagger, come, and penetrate this heart ^
Which cannot from LardeHa's Love depart,

£»^^r Pallas^

Pdl, Hold, flop your murd'ring. hands ^

At VaUaJef commands.*.
For the fuppofed dead, O Kings,
Forbear to ad foch deadly things.
jL<fr^e//rf lives 5 I did but try
If Princes for their Loves could dye«.
SuchiCeleftial confiancy

Shall, by the Gods, rewarded be : "

And from thefe Funeral Obfequies
A Nuptial Banquet (hall arife, *

[T/)e Coffin opens, and a 'Banquet is difcoverd^

Hayes. So, take away the Goffin^ Now it^s out. . This is

the very Funeral of the fair perfbn which Voljcins fent word

was dead, and P^//^/, you fee, has turn'ditinto a Banquet,

Smi, Wells but where is this Banquet ?

^rfj^j. Nay, look you, Sir, we muft firft have a Dance, for joy

that tardelta is not dead. Pray, Sir, give me leave to bring

in my things properly at lead.

Smi, Thatj indeed, I had forgot: I ask your pardon.
ha)iesi 0,d'y€fb, Sir? lam glad you will confels your
felfe once in an error, Mr. Smith,.

Dance,
K, ZJ/7j. Refplendent P^//^/, we in thee do find J

The (iercelt Beauty 5 and a fiercer mind .*
And fmce to thee ZLrfr^^Z/^V life we owe.
We'll fupple Statues in thy Temple grow^



TbeKehearfah 45

K. ?hjf. Well, fince alive LardelUs founJ,
Let, in full Boles, her Health go round.
\7he two Vfitrpers tal^ each of them 4 Bole in their hands*
K.Vfi. but Where's the Wirie?

rah Thatfhall be mine. ^

Lo, from this conquering Lance,
Doesflowthepureri WineofFr^/?re;5F//// the Boles
And, to appeafe your hunger, I c out rf her Lance,
Have, in my Helmet, brought a Pye .*
Laftly, to bear a part with thefe.
Behold a Buckler made of Cheele, [vanifh Palla?,
"Zayes, There's the Banquet. Are you fatisfid now ,
Siri?

'John/, By my troth, now, that is new, and more than I
^xpeded.

Bayes, Yes, I knew this would pleafe you .• for the chief Art
in Poetry is to elevate your expedation, and then bring you
off fome extraordinary way.

£«?^r Drawcanfir,'
K.fhyf What man is this, that dares diflurbour Fcafl:>
Bravp* He that dares drink^ and for that drink dares dye.

And, knowing this, dares yet drink on, am I,
'johnf. That is, Mr. Bayes ^ as much as to fay, that tho he
would rather die than not drink, yet he would fain drink
for all that too>

^ayes. Right s that's the conceipt on t,
"johnf, 'Tis a marvellous good one, I (wear*
itayes. Now there are fome Critics that have advis'd me to
put out the Second Dare^ and print A/*/^ in the placeon't^
butj I gad, I think 'tis better thusagfeat deal,
Johnf, Whoo ! a thoutand times.
ha)es^ Go on then r
K* VJI3. Sir, if you pleafe, we ftiould be glad to know.

How long you here will ftay, how foon you*l go }
Bayes. Is not that now.likea well bred perfon, I gad? So
mode(t,{b gent ! W^
Smi, O, very like.



e ixevearja

Draw* You (hall not know bow long I here will (lay 5
But you iVjall know 11 take your Bowles away,

X^S?iatches the Boles out of the Kr^gs
Z hctnAs-i and drivkj em offl
^ ^mi' But, Mr. Bayes, is that (too) modeft an.d gent >
^^^ej.No^ i.g;ad,Sir^but,it-s great.
K.Vfi, The, Brother, this.grum danger be a CloWn,

, He'l leave us, fure, a little to gulp down.
D/arr, Who e er to gulp one drop of this dares think
I'l flare away his very pow'r to drink.

^The tvpQ Kwgs fnegh^&ff: the Stage ^
\ with their Attendants.
' \ dr'nk I huffj I ftrut, look big and frarc 5

And all this I can do, becaufe I dare. {_Exit

Stni. I fuppofcg Mrc ^ayes^ this is the fierce Hero you fpoke
of.

Bayes^ Yes; but this is nothing X you (bxall fee him, in the
laft Adt, win above a dozen Battles, one after another , I gad^
as faft as they can poffible come upon the Stage.

Johnf. That will be a fight worth the feeing indeed, .
Smi, But pray, Mr,. Baye-s^ why do you ipakethe Kings kt
him ufe 'em ^fb fcarvily ?,.

B^j/ej. Phoo ! t?iat is to raife the chafader of Dr^^trr^^/r.
John/. O' my wprdg that was well thought on.
S'ayes' N0W3 Sirs Fl (hew you a Scene indeed 5 or rather^,
iadeedj the Sceme of Sqen^s. Tis an Heroic^cene.
£mi. And pray. Sir, what's your defigp in this Scene .\
^^^e/.. Why, Sir, my defignis guilded Truncheons, forc'd
conceipt, fmooth Verfe, and a Rant : In fine., if this Sc&ncdo,
not take, I gad, I'l writ^ no more. Come, come in, Mr.™- a — .
nay, come in as many as you. can,, Gentlemen, I mud de-
fee you to remove a little, for I mud fill the Stage,
'^^ii,,,: Why fill the. Stage >

Bayes. O, Sir , becaiife your Heroic Verfe. never founds
^'ell,^ but when the Stage is fulL .

sc^ra;



TbeRehearfal 45

s c JE N A u.

EfJter TrJn ce Fietiy n:an3 a f;d FrwceV olfclus.

N Ay,hold,hold3 pray by your kave a little. Look you,
Sirj the drift of this Scene is fomwhat more than ordina-
ry; for I make 'em both fall outbccaufe they are not in love
with the fame Woman.

sm. Not in love? you mean, Ifuppofe, becaufe they are
inlovCj ^r. 'Bayes}

Bdyes. No, Sir; I fay not in lave : there's a new conceipt
for you. Now fpeak.

Fret , Since fatCj Prince Volfcius, now has found the way
For our fo long'd for meeting here this day^
Lend thy attention to my gi and concern^
Volf* I gladly would that ftory from thee learn 5
But thou to love deft Tretty-man^ incline %
Yet love in thy breaft is not love in mine ?
%ay^Sy Antithe^s ! Thine and mine.
frei. Since love it lelf's thefame^ why (houlditbe
DifFring in you from what it is in me > ^
Yiaycs. Reafoning ! I gad, I love realbning in verfe.
VoifX^ov^ takeS) Cdmekon-\\]^^^ a various dye

From every Plant on which it felf docs lye.
'^ayes. Simile !

frst. Let not thy love the courfe of Nature fright %

Nature ioes moftin harmony delight.
Volf, How weak a Beity would nature prave

Contending with the pow'rful God of Love^
"BAyes, There's a great Verfe I
Volf, If rncenie thou wilt ofJer at the Shrine

Of mighty Love, burn it to none but mine;.
Her Rofie-iips eternal fweets exhale •>
And her bright flames make all flames elfe lookpale-
Brfje/. I gad that is right.



The RebearfaL

Pret, Perhaps dull Incenfe may thy love fufEce •
^ But mine muft be adord with Sacrifice.

All hearts turn afties which her eyes controul.;
The Body they confume as well as Soul.
Volft, My love has yet a power more Divine,
Vidims her Altars burn not, but refine .•
Amidft the flames they ne're give up theGhofl',
-''"^ Butj with her looks, revive (till as they roaft.
pr-..: j^^ ^-^g of pain and death, they're, kept alive;
Her fiery eyes makes *^eminfire furvivc,
'^ajies. That is as well, I gad, as lean do.
Volf Let ^y Parthe^ope at length prevail/
Bajes. Civil, I gad,
Pref, rifoonei' have apafliionfor a Whale :

In whole vaCt bulk, tho ftore of Oyl doth lye>
We find more (hipe, more beauty in a Fly,
Smr^ That's unciviL igad*

Bayes. Yes 3 butasfar afetch'dfancy, tho, I gad, as ere you
faw^

Fiflf, Soft, Prettf'f^^fiy^et not thy vain pretence
Of perfeift love^ defame loves excellence.
Parthenope is fure, as far a hove
All'other loves , as above all is Love. _

^ajies* Ah 1 1 gad> that llrikes me.
Pre/. To blame my C/(?mj Gods would not pretend.
Bnyes, Nowmark*

VolJ' Were all Gods joined, they could not hope to- mend
My better choice .'for fair P^r/^a«a/?«?,
Gods wouldj themfelves, UB-god themfelves to (ee;
Bajies, Now the Rant's a comings
Vret, Durd any ofthe Gods be fo uncivil,

rid make that God fubfcribe himfelf a Devil.^
^ajes* Ah, Godfookers, that's well writ!

\_Scrdtching his head^ his PerrUl{e falls off\
Volf. Could'O; thou that God from Heav n to Earth tranflate.
He coaid not fear to want a Heav'nly State
Farihe^ope.^ OH Earthy can Heav'n create*



TbeRehearfal 47

Pre/, Chris doesHeav'n itfelffo far excel.

She can tranfcend the joys of Heav*n in Hell.

^a^es. There's a bold flight for you now ! 'Sdeath, I have
loft my Perrukc. Well, Gentlemen, this is that I never yet faw
any one could write, but my felf# Here's true fpirit and flame
all through, I gad. 80,805 pray clear the Staget

\_Ee puts' em off the Stage,

Johnf I wonder how the coxcomb has got the knack of
writing (mooth Verfethus.

Smu Why there's no need of brain for this : 'tis but fcaning
the labour's in the finger 5 but where's the fence of it?

'johnf, 0\ for that, he defires to be excus'd : he is too
proud a man to creep fefvily after Senfe, laflureyoQ; But
pray, Mr* Bayes^'why is this Scene all in Verfe>

B<iy/e/.0, Sir, the fubjed is too great for Profe.

Smi, Wellfaid, i'faith^ 11 give thee a pot of Ale for that
anfwer .* 'tis well worth it,

hayes^ Come, with all my heart,
ril make that God fubfcribe himfelf aDevil.
That fingle line, I gad, is worth all that my brother Poets
ever writ. Let down the Curtain. [Exennt,

Finis A&HS Qmrth



ACT^S V. SC^NA I.

BaycSj and the two Gentlemen,



^rf/eJ.lW XO W, Gentlemen, I will be bold to fay, I'l fhcw
I ^kj you the greateft Scene that ever EvgUnd^vN r
i ^ I mean not for words, for thofe I do not value 5
but for ftate, fhew, and magnificence. In fine Ml juftifie it to
be as grand to the eye eVcry whit, 1 gad, as that great Scene
in Harry the Eight, ?nd grander too, I gad 5 for inftead

Of



The Rehear faL



of two Biftiops, I bring in here four Cardinals,

^The Curtain is drawn up^ the trvo ufurping Kings af*
c> fear in Stdte^ with the four Cardinals , Prince
^ Pretty-man, Fn^reVolfcius, Amarillis, Clorisj
y Parthenope 5 C^r. before them^ Heralds and Ser'^
{^jeants at Arms with JUaces,

' S«?/, Mr.B4/e/,pray what is thereafon that two of the Car-
dinals are in Hats, and the other in Caps?

Bayes, Why, Sir, becaule ^By gad, I won't tcllyou.

Your Country friendj Sir, grows fo troublefbme.
iCZ^. NoWaSir^tothcbufiuefsof theday. .
K^ Thyji Speak Volfcius,

VoljC Dread. Soveraign Lords, my zeal to you, naufl: not in-
vade my duty to your Son, let me intreat that great Prince
Pretty-man firfi: do (peak : whofe high preheminence, in all
things that do bear the name of good, may juftly claim that
priviledge. ; =

B/Tj/e/. Here it begins to unfold; you may perceive, now,
that he is his Son.

John/. Yes ^ Sir^ and we are very much beholdifig to you
for that difcovery.
-.Fret, Royal father, upon my knees I beg.

That the Illuftrious Foljdus firft be heard
r<?//^That prefer-enceis only due to^/^^r/////. Sir. -
Vtajes, n make herfpeak very well, by and by, youfhall
(ee^ -

Ama, Invincible Soveraigns -•*— \3^fl l^^_f^»

K Ufi. Batftay, what (bund is this invades our ears/
K^ rhyf. Sure 'tis the Mufick of the moving Spheres.
Vret, Behold, with wonder, yonder comes from far
A God like-Cloud , and a triumphant Carr ;
In which, our two right Kings (it one by one.
With VirginfeVefts, and Laurel Garlands on.
k. VJIj. Then, Brother Vhy's'm time we iliouldbegon, '

SThe tmo Vfnrpers Jieal out of the Throne^
C and go avpay^

Bayes,



Ihe Rehe^fdl. 49

BAyes Look you now, did not I tell you that this would
"bje as eafie a change as the other ?

Smi, Yes, faith, you did fo ^ tho tconfefs, I could not
believe you 3 but you have brought it about, I fee.

<CThe ir^o right Kings ^f Brentford defcejrd in the
< CloJids^ Ctnging in white garments '^ ajidtfme
C Fidkrs pting before them ^ iff green'.

B/ye/. Now, bccaufe the two right Kings defcend fl'om a-
bove, I make 'em fing to the Tune and Stile of our moderft
Spiiits.

1 King^ Hade, Brother King, we are fcnt from abovb.

2 Kang. Let us move, let us move:

Move to remove the Fate

0[ Brentfords long GryitcdSt-^te,

1 King, Tarra, tar\ tara, full Eaft and by ^outh,

2 King^ We fail with Thunder in our mouth.

In fcorching noon day, vvhil'lt the traveller 'ftayes^
Bufie, bufie, bufie, buiie, we buftle a long.
Mounted upon warm Vhxhus his Rayes,
Through the Heavenly throng.
Hailing to thofe
Who will feaft us, at night, with a Pigs Petty- toes.
I King'* And we'l fall with cur pate

In an OllJo of hate •
2'King, But now fupper's done, the Sevvitors tr)'.

Like Souldiers, to ftorm a whole half-moon-pye.
iiC7//^,They gather, they gather hot CuHard infpoons.
But AlaSj 1 mud, leave thcfe half-moons.
And repair to my trufty Dragoons.
^ King. O ftay , for } on need not as yet go adray ^

The 1 yde^like a/riend,has brought djips in our way^
And on their high ropes we will play.
Like Maggots in Filbcrds, we 1 (hug in out (hell^
We'i frifk. in our fhell
Wcl firkin our fhell,
" ~ And fare wel,

. - H -i:King,



50 TheRehear/aL

1 Kwg, But the Ladles have all inclination to dance.

And the green Frogs croak out a Coranto ofFranee,
%ijes. Is not that pretty juow ? The Fiddlers are all in green,
Smi, I, but they play no Cofyinto,
Jo^KJ, No, but they play a Tune, that's a great deal better.
Ba^cf. No Coranto, quoth a / that's a good oncj with all my
ht^ytj Came,f]ngon,

2 Kwg. Now Mortals that hear

How we Tilt and Carreer,
With wonder will fear
The event of fuch things as (hall never appea^'^.

1 Kwg. Stay you to fulfil what the Gods have^ecreed.

2 KjKg. Then call me to help you, if there (hall be need«
I Kifig* So firmly refolv'd is a true BrentfardKmg

To iaveihe diftrefled, and help to em bring.
That ere a FulUpotofgood Ale you can fwallowy.
He s here with a whoops and gone with a holla* .
[Eayes phi Hips his fi;iger^ and^»gs after 'em,
Brf)'^/. Hes here with a whoop, and gone with a holla.
Thisj Sir, you muft know, I thought once to have brought in
withaConjurer»

J$hnf^ I, that would have been better.
^ayes. No. faith, not when you consider it .' for thus 'tis
more compendiou?^ and does the thing every whit as wel!-
Smi, Thing ! what thing >

'Bayes, Why, bring em down again into theThronc, Sir j
what thing would you have?

Smi*SVt\\i, butj methinkstheSence ofthis Song is not ve-
ry plain,

' hayes. Plain? Why d\d you ever he-it any people in Clouds^
fpeak plain? They muft be all for flight of fancie, at its full
range, without the Icaft check, or controul upon it. When
onccyou tye up fprits^ and people in Clouds to fpeak pi ain^,
you fpoil alU

Smi, Bkfsnse^ what a Monger's this I '

^jhe two Kiffgs fight ofit efihe Cknds, and
I jie^ifjtathctkrQfje*.

I Kiffg*



The Rebearf.il 51

iKing. Come, now to ferious coonlel we*l advance*

2 Kiffg^ I do agree > but fii-ft, let's have q Dance.

Bayes. Right. You did that very Well^ Mr, r^^^K^r/^R But
firft, let's have a Dance. Pray remember that 5 be fure^ you do
it aivi^ays juftfo : for it muft be done as if it were the eiledb
oikthought, and premsditation. But firft, let's have a Dance.
Pray remember that,

i"//?!* Wellj Icanholdno longer^ I muft gag this. rogUe^
there's no induring of him

Jolir^f, No, pr'thee make ufc oE thy patience a little Ion*
ger : let's fee the end of him now^

[^D4?ece agratjdDuHce,

Bayes, This^noWj is an ancient Dance, of right belonging
to the Kings of Brentford ^ but (ince deriv'd, with a little al-
teration, to the Inns of Court.

j^fz Alarm. Enter iwoBerlads.

I J^i/?^. What fav^cie Groom molefts our privacies?

1 Her, The Armys at the door, and in difguife,

Defires a word with both your Majelties ;

2 H^r.Having ^^om^Kt^ightf -bridge hither march'd by ftealtb^
2 Kivg Bid 'em attend a while, and drink our health.

Smi^ HoW5Mr,2?^^e/?the Army indilguife?
Bayes. Ay, Sir, for fear the Ufurpers might difcover them
that went out but juft now.

Smt' Why, what if they had difcover'd them ?
^^^e/^ Why, then they had broke the defign-
I King, Here, take five Guineysfor thofe warlike men^
^ Kjfjg. And here s five mere, thatmakesthefum jufi: ten
I Her* We have not feen fo unuch the Lord knowes when,.

[Exeunt Heralds*
I K/>^. Speak On, hx2CVQ.Amarillis,
Ama. Invincible Soveraigns, blame not my modefty,
If at this grand conjuncture - —
^ \_prH?n beat behind the Stage,

I X/»g. What dreadful noife is thib that comes and goes j*

Enter a Souldier with his ^vj^'d drawn,
Sould, Haftehenee, great Sirs, your Royal perfonsfave,

H 2 For



5^ 1 he RehearfaL

For the event of war no mortal knowes :
The Army, wrangling for the gold you gave,
Firft fell to words and then to handy-bloW5. \_Exit',
'^ayes. h not that now a ^nretty kind of a Stanza, and a hand-
ibme come off?

2 K/^^. OdangerauseiiateofSovcraignpowV!
Obnoxious to the ciiangeof every hour.
I KfJigJ^^t us for flielter in our Cabinet Itay :

Perhaps thefe threatning fcorms may pafs away.

Johrff, But MrjB^rj/e/j did not you promife us,y*uft noWj^to
inake ^/«^r;7/ij" fpcak very well.

Y)ayes, Ay, and fo (he would have done, but that they hin-'
der'dher. •

Smi, How^Sir, whether you would or no?

"^ajtes. Ay, Sir, the Plot lay fo that, I vow to gad, it was nofe;
to be avoided.

S;;^i. Marry, that was hard;

Johfif, Butj pray, who hindfd her>'

Btiyes. Why, the battel. Sir, that's^ jufl coming in at
door ."And I'M tell you now arcrange thing, tholdon't pre-
tend to do more than other: raeUy I gad, I'l give you both a
whole week to ghefs how I'l repreient this Battel,

Sm,lh2id rather be bound to %ht your Battle, I allure
yoo. Sir.

Bayes. VVhoo/ there's it no vv.*. fight a Battle. ? there's the
comisnoiierror J knew prefently where I lllould have you. Why
-pray. Sir, do but tell me this one thing, Can you think it a de-
cent thing, in a Battle before Ladies, to have meo lua their
Swords through one a not her, anci ^H that }

5<?/;/// No, faith, 'tis not civil.

^ayes. Right on tl>e other fide ^ to have a long relation of.
Squadrons here, afid Squadrons there : what iiic but dull
p^-olixity ?

^ohfij] Excellently reafon'd bymy troth! '

hajes. Wherefore^ Sjtj to avoid both thofe fndicorum?,!
fijm up my whole Battle iu the. reprcfentaiion of two.perfons

■ only.



IbeKebeatjdL 53

onlyj no more.: and yet fo lively, that^ I vow togatl^ you would
fweartcn thoufand men v^ere at it really ergag'd. Do you
mark me?

^;9if/.Yes5Sir^butI think Ifhould hardly fvveiir tho^Cbr all that.

'Sayes^ Ey my troth. Sir, but you woiild^thOj when you fee
it .• for I make 'cm both come out in Armor C^?/?-^-ft\f3 with
their Swords drawttj and hung, with a (carlet Ribbon at their
wriihj fwhichyou know^ rcprefcnts fighting enough,)
: ^olmf^ Ijl^fo muc-hj.thatj.if Iwcre in your place I would
mak cm go out again withouteverfpeakingone svord^,

^ayes. No ^ there you are outs for I make each of 'em
hold a Lute in his hand'. "

Smi^ How Sir? inlleadofa Buckler?

Bajes^ O Lord, O Lord! inftead of a Buckler ? Pray Sir do
you ask no m.ore qucllions, Lmake'^tiij S.^r, play the battel
in Recjtativo. And here*s theconccipt^ Jufi: at the very fame
inltantrhat one fings, the other, SItj recovers you his Sword,
and puts himfcif in a warlike pofuire ;fo that you have at once
your ear entertained with Mulic and good Language • and
yciir e} e fatisiied with the garb, and acccutrements of v/ar,

Smi^ Iconfefs Sir^ you ftupifre me.-

'B.iyes. YonnullfcCo,

Jok>;f: But Kir. B^jfj'^ might not we have a little %hting>-
fori love thole playeSj where they cut and flafli one another
upon the Stage, for a whole hour together.

Eajies. VVhy^then^ to teli you true ! have contiivYi it both
Vy'ayts\ But you thai] have my Recitjtjvo' firft.

5^r?/6;7/^ Ij now } oa are right ; there is nothing then can be
obj£d:edagainftir^.

Btncs^ True : and fo, I gad , rrmakc it^ toOj a Tragedy^ in a
tr?Ge, I- EKtcr^ atjcverald0Ors.j thcGcncrai^ ^.nd

'■iii each of them a Late ni his h^iid^ a?:d his ■■
Y fword. dravc.^^andhiivg with ajcarkt lUi>
Id.. bo7i lit his rcrifl^

Lieut, Get?, V'i]iain/d'K.)u i)e[i-^

Qen hxm^:iim,CGvJ}ilvo.^:^.\in\ v/hatho?'

Thelye no iieili can brook I trow, . I/e?^/;



54 Tl)e Rebearfah

Lieut. Gen:. A cl vance, from A^on^mth the M ufquetiers.

Ge*t^ Drawdown the Cheifej Guxu^.^x^,

iL'e^^.G^^;^. The Band you boaftofjC^e//?;' Curiafiers,

Shall, in my Putney PikeSj now meet their Peers,
Gm,chifwicf^msy aged, and renown'd in fight.

Join with the Hammerfmith Brigade^
Lieut^ Gent Yg\x'\ find my Mori hh^ hoys will do them right,

Unlefs by F^//5^«? numbers over-Jaid.
Gen^ Letthe lefi:-wingoflii?/V4«^^f^ootadvaace3

And line tliat Eaftern hedge.
Lkut, Gen, The Horfe I rais'd in Fetty-Fratice
Shall try their chance.
And fcour the Meadow^s, over grown with Sedge.
Cjnt, Stand : give the word.
Liettt^ Gen^ Bright Sword.
Gent, That may be thine.

But 'tis not mine.
Xieut,Gen. Give fire, give fire, at once give fire.

And le.t thofc recreant Troops perce:ivcn>iiie irCa
Gen Furfue, purfiie 5 they fly

1 -at firft did. give the lie. ^ \_Exeum

Bayes, This , now, is not improper, I think, becaufe the
Spectators kiKJw all th^fe Towns, and mayeafily conceive
them to be within the Dominions of the two Kings ofBrentforJ^
JoJ»nf, Molt exceeding v/eli defign'd !
Bayef, How do you think 1 have contriv'd to give a flop
to this battle?
Smi. How?

l^aj/es. By an Eel ipfe.* Which, letmetellyoUj-isakindof
fancy that was yet never fo much as thought of^ but by my felf^
and one perl'on more, that fiiall be namelefs.

Enter Lieutenant General,

Lieut. Gen. Wh.^t mid-night darknefs does invade the day
And fnatch the Viiflor from his conque/d prey ?
Is the Sun weary of this bloody ligiir, .......

And winks upon us with the eye of light ? 'Tis



JkRehearfal 55

^TisanEclipfe. This was unkind^C Moon,'
To clap between me, and the Sun fofoon.
Foolilh Eclipfe .* thou this in vain haftdonci
My brighter honour hadEclips'd the Sun:
But now behold Eclipfcs two in one. \_Exit,

Jokfjf, This is an admirable reprefentation ofa Baucis as e-
ver I faw.

Bajes, IjSir. But how would you fancy now. to reprcfent
anEclipfe.<?

Sm/. Why, that's to be {uppos'd.

Bajes, Supposed ! Ay, you are ever at yonr fupp^^fe : ha,
ha, ha^. Why you may a? well i'uppofe the whole Play. No^,
itmuft come in upon the Stage, that's certain-, but in fome
odd way, that may delight^ amufe^ and all that. I have a
conceipt for't, that I am fure is new, and^.l believe to the pur-
pofe.

Johnf. How's that?

B^^'fj, Why, the truth is, I took thefirfthintorthiscutofa'
Dialogue, between Pheebusznd Aurora mthe Slighted Alaid :
which by my troth^ was very pretty , but! think, you'l confefs
this is a little better,

j^^vf. No doubt on't, Mr. B^j/ej. A great deal better.

QBayes,i)W^x ]ohn{bn^ tbcfz tuvfts to Smith;

B^j/e/. Ah dear Rogue .-but— a— Sir, you have heard Ifups
poie, that your Eclipfe of the Moon, is nothing elfe5but an
interpolition of the Earth, between the Sun and Moon .* as like*
wile your Eclipfe of the Sun iscaus'd by aninterlocation Qi--
the Moon, betwixt ^he Earth and Sun ?

S///i. I have heard fome fuch taing indeed*

^ajes. Well, Sir, then what do me I, but make the E^irth ,
Son, and Moon, come out upon the Stage, and dance the
H ey .-hura^ And, ofnecefiitysby the very nature of this Dance,
the Earth muft be fometimes between tbc Sira and the Moon^
and the Moon between the Eaith and Sdn^ and there you
have both your Eclipfes, by demonftration*

Johpjf T hat miifc needs be very fine truly.

Bajes^ 5'es, it has fancy int. And then , Sir, that there

Diay^:



5^ TbeRehearfah

maybe fomething in't too of a joqiie, T bring *em in all fing-
ing, and make the Moon fell the Earth a bargain. Come^ come
out Eclipfe to the Tune of Torn Tyler,

Enter Luna.
Lnnar Orbis^ O Or his.

Come to me thou little rogue Orhii,
Ef7ter the Earthy
Orb. Who calls Terra firm a ^ ipv^xy}
£?/^^, I^;?^ that ne'r fliines by dayv
Grb. What means I»??4 in a veil > ;'

X«/?^. /.^«^ means to (hew her tail.
Jjdjes.. There's the bargain^

'£«/€r Sol^ /tf f/j^ 7//;^^ ^/Robin Hood.
^S'*?/, Fie, Sifterg fie, thou mak'ib me mule,
Derry, derry down.
To fee the Orb abufe,
Lu^a, I hope his anger 'twill not move i
Since I fhew'd it out of love^

Hey down derry down.
OrL Where fnall I thy true love know.

Thou pretty, pretty Moon?
Lmta. To morrow fooilj ere it be noon,

0« Mount Vefiivio. \_Eif.

iW. Then I will fhine, {To the tune of Trenchmore.

€)r^. Andl will be fine*

Luna. And I will drink nothing but Lippary wine.
Omms^ AndwCjC^V.

S^AstheyD:inceikeUcy^^'^^^%f^eah^,
^ayes. Now the earth's before the Moon ^ now the Moons
before the Sun : there's the Eclipte again.
Swi^ He's mightily taken with this I fee.
Johvf. I,'tibfoextroardiniry, how can he chufe?
Bayes. So^ new, vanifn Eclipfe'. and enter t'other Battle,
and light. Here now, 'f 1 am not oiibken, you Vv'ili fee figh-
ting enough.

^I'dt,



The RehearfaL $7



A battel is fought between foot and great Ho
horfes. At M 3 Drawcanfir comei in and kj^^f
\ * email on both fide s All this while the\'2>attcl ^^
■} fighting Bayes is telling them when t&Jliout^ and
I jliOHts with em.
Draw, Others may boft a fingle man to kill 5
But Ij the bloood of thoufards daily fpill.
Let petty Kings the names of Parties know;
Where e'er I come, I flay both friend and foe.
The fwifteft Horfmen my fwift rage controuls.
And from their Bodies drives their trembling fouls.
If they had vvingS; andtotheGodscould tiie,
I would purfue and beat em through the skie ;
And moke proud jftfz;e, with all his Thunder, fee
This fingle Arm more dreadful is, than he* '[Exit.

Bayes, There's a brave fellow for you now. Sirs. You m2ij
ta]}i of y our HeS or ^uVidlAchilles^ and I know not who 5 but i
defie all your HiftorieSj and your Romances too, to (hew me
one fuch Conqueror, as this Dr<z»?f^^r-
Johnf. 1 fwear, I think you may.

Smi^ But Mr. Bajes^ how fhall all thefe dead men go off^fo; I
fe^ none alive to help 'em,

Bayes. gooff! why, as they came on? upon their legs; hew
(hould they go off ? Why do you think the people here don't
know they are not dead?He is mighty ignorant, poor man ^ 3 oil
friend here is very filly, Mr^JohnJon^ I gad, he is, ha, ha, h'a.
Come, Sir, 11 fhowyou how they (hall go off.. Rife, rife, Sirs^
and go about your bufinefs» There's go ofl for you now. Ha,
ha^ha. Mr. /z^^ry, a word. Gentlemen, 11 be with you pre-
fently. •.-. [Ex//.

5(7^;// Will you fo .<? then we'l be gone.
Sw/. I, pry thee let's go, that we may prefer veoirrhearin^^.
One Battel more will take mine Qi.;ite away,

[^Exeunt,
E?7ter'^a)xs and Players,

Baes, Where are the Gentlemen.^ '_

1 , I Pl^y



T he Rehear/aL

irlay. They are gone. Sir. ...

B^y/ej. Gone ! 'Sdeath^ this lalt Act is beft of all. 1 1 go

tcl 'em again. ^ [Exjt^

1 F/^^. What (hall wedo^now he is gone away ?

2 ?lay* Why, fo much the better 5 then let's go to dinner,

5 ?Uy, Stay, here's a foul piece of papy r of his. Let's /ee what
Vis.

3 or 4 r/<f;/,. I-, 1 5 come let's hear it^

Heads, The Argument of the Fifth AVt^
3 flay. Claris at lengthjbeing fenlibie of Prince Pretty-man's
paflion, confents to marry him ^ butj juftasthey are going to
Church, Prince Vretty^man meeting, by chance, with old Joan
the Chandlers widdow, and remembringit was (he that firft
brought him acquainted with Clorisiout of a high point of ho-
nour , brake off his match with Cloris^ and marries old "joaH. Up-
on which,C/^m, in defpair^ drovmi^ her felf : and Prince Vretty-
fuan^ difcontentedlyj walkes by the River fide. This will ne-
ver do .* 'tis juft like the relt. Conic, let's begone.

\Exennt,
Moji sf the Play, Ay, pox oat, let's go away.

EffterBzyQS,

"Sdyts^ A plague on 'em both for me, they have made roe
fweat» to run after *€m. A couple of fencelefs raskals, that
had rather go to dinner then fee this play out, with a pox
to *em» What comfort has a man ro write for fuch dull rogues?

Come Mr. . ■ a Where are you. Sir ? come a. way quick,

quick.

Unter St age- keeper.

Stage, Sir, they are gone to dinner.

^ayes. Yes, I know the Gentlemen ^re gone 5 but I ask for
the Players.

S/rf^S' Why, ant pleafe your worfhip. Sir, the Players are
gone to dinner too.

^ayes. How ! are the Players gone to Dinner ? Tis im-

poffible.*



TbeRebearfaL 59

pofiible : the Players gone to dinner I I gad, if they are, I'l
make 'em know what it is to injure a perfcn thai: does 'em
the honour to write for 'em, and all that^ A company of
proundjConceitedjhumorous, crofs-grain'd peiTons,and all that.
I gad, ri make 'em the mod contemptible, defpicable, inconfi-
derable perlbns, and all that, in the whole world for this
trick. I gad I'l be reveng'd on 'em, I'l fell this play to the
other Houfe.

Stage. Nays good. Sir, don't take a way the Book i you'l
difappoint the company that comes to fee it aded here j this
after noon#

Baj>es. That's all one. I muft referve this comfort to my
felf, my Play and I (hall go together, we will not part in-
deed. Sir.

stag, ^ut what will the Town fay, Sir?

hajfes. The Town ! why, what care 1 for the Town ? I gad,
the Town has us'd me as fcurvily, as the Players have done .•
but ri be reveng'd on them too 5 for i'l Lampoon 'em all
And Since they will not admit of my Plays, they Ihall know
what a Satyrift I am. And (b farewel to this Stage, I gad, for
ever. [Exit Baj/es^

Enter Players.

I flay. Come then , let's fet up Bills for another Play :

1 Pa). I, I i we (hall lofe nothing by this I warrant you.

1 Plajfi I am of your opinion. But before we go, lets (ee
Uaynes and Shirley praftife the lafl dance 5 for that may ferve
us another time.

2 Vlay. ri call 'em in ." I think they are but in theTirings
room.

"the Dance done,
1 flay^ Comei come 5 let's go away to dinner.
^ \Exeunt Omms,



EPL



E PILOGU E. -

THe Play is at an end, hut where s the Plot ?
That circumflance our Poet Q3,ycs forgot, \
And m can hoafl, tho 'tis a plotting Age^
SSi place is freer from it than the Stage*
The Ancients plotted^ tho^ and Uro*ve to pleaje
With fence that might be underfiood with eaje j
J hey etvery Scene with fd much wt did Jlore,
That 18? bo brought any in^ went out mth more •
*^ut this ne'^ way of '70it does fofurprife^
Men loje their wits in ^.ondri ng yohere it (yes ,
If It be truci that J^onjirous births pre f ag
The following mif chief that affliB the Jge,
And fad difajlers to the State proclaim ;
Piajs without head or taiU may do the fame,
WhercforeiforourSyandforthiKingdomespeace^^
May tips prodigioui way offvriting ceafe^
Lets ha^ve^ at leaU, once in our li^vesya time
When tr^ ma^i hear fome reafen^ npt all Rhyme :.
We, ha<ve tbeje ten years felt its lefluence ; "Kj '';■■ ?*■
Pray let thuproye a year ofProfeand Scene e. ' \-
