
Skip to main content

    Internet Archive Logo
    web
    books
    video
    audio
    software
    images
    search

    uploadUPLOAD
    personSIGN IN

    ABOUT
    CONTACT
    BLOG
    PROJECTS
    HELP
    DONATE
    JOBS
    VOLUNTEER
    PEOPLE

Full text of "The plain-dealer"
See other formats

mi



j*i*'



■7 -sjv d



fyt



m^^-^^




Digitized by the Internet Archive

in 2011 with funding from

LYRASIS IVIembers and Sloan Foundation



http://www.archive.org/details/plaindealerOOinwych



THE


















As it is Aded at the

heatre-





Written by Mr. W YC HERL E Y.



The Sixth Edition.



H O R A T.

RidicHlum acri



Fortius ^ melius niagnas plerumque ficat res.



•»-9-



Licenfed Jan. p. t6y6.



^ pmi^mmmmmm^mmmmmmmmK^m



ROGER UESTRANGE.



LONDON,

Printed for R. Bentky, at the Poft-Houfe, in Ruffel-
fireet in Covent-Garden near the Piaz^'s.



L



my LADY B-~



Madam,




Ho I never had the. Honour to receive a Favour from
yoH^ naj) or he known to you^ I take the confidence of
an Author to write to you a Biliiet doux Dedicatory ;
which is no new things for hy mofi Dedications it ap'
pears, that Authors, though they praife their Patrons from top to
tee, and feem to turn ^ern infide out^ know 'em as little as fome-
times their Patrons their Books , tho they read them cut', and if
the Poetical Dauhers did not write- the Name of the Man or Wo-
man en top of » the Pi^tire, *twere impojfthle to guefs whofe it were.
But you, Madam, without the help of a Poet, have made your f elf
known and famous in the World \ and lecaufe you do not want it ^
are therefore mofl worthy an Epiflle Dedicatory. And this flay
claims naturally your ProteSiion, Jince it has lofl its Reputation
with the Ladies of ftritler lives in the Play-houfe ; and (yon
know) when Mens Endeavours are difcountenanc d and refused,
hy the nice coy Women of Honour, they come to you, To you the
Great and Nolle Patronefs of reje^ed and hafhful Men, of which
vumher I profefs my felf to he one, though a Post, a Dedica^
ting Poet : To you I fay. Madam, who have as difcerning a
judgment, in what*s ohfcene or not, as any quick- fight ed civil
Perfon of "em all, andean make as much of a douhle meaning
faying as the hefl of 'em ; yet would not, as feme do. make no;i-'
fenfe of a Poet's Jefl^ rather _ than not tpake it haudy : hy
which they fhew they as little value Wit in a Play, as in a over,
provided they can hring t other thing about. Their fenfe indeed
lies all one way, and therefore are only for that in a Feet which
is moving, as they fay ; But what do they mean hy fhj'- • -ord
moving ? WeM. I mufi not put 'em to the hlujh^ pice I find I can
dot. In fhort. Madam, you wou d not he one <f thofe who rav^Jh
a Poet's innocent words, and make 'em guilty of their own naugh-

A 2 - iinefs.



The Epiftle

tinefs {as 'tis termd ) in fpight of his teeth ; vay^ nothing is
fecure from the power of their imagination j not not their Hus-
bands, whom they Cuckold with themfelves, hy thinking of other
men, and fo make the lawful matrimonial -, embraces Adultery ;
wrong Husbands and Poets in thought and word, to keep their
own Reputations ; but your Ladyfhips juflice^ I know^ woud think
a Woman s Arraigning and Dar/ining a Poet for her own obfcentty,
like her crying out a Rape, and hanging a Man for giving her
pleafure, only that fie might be thought not to confent tot ; and
fo to vindciate her Honour, forfeits her modefty. But you. Ma- .
dam ; have too much mode fly to pretend tot ; tho you have as
much to fay for your mode fly as many a nicer fie ; for you *never
were feen at this Play, no, not the firfl day ; and ^tis no matter
what Peoples Liv^s have been, they are umjueflionably modefl who
frequent not this Play. For^ as Mr. Bays fays of his. That it is
the only Touchflone of Mens Wit, and under flanding ; mine is,
it feems, the only Touchflone of Womens P'irtue and modefiy. But •
hold, that Touthfione is equivocal, and, by the flrength of a La-
dy^s imagination^ may become fomething that is not civile but
yo^r Ladyfl^ip, I know, fcorns to mifapply a Touchflone, And, Ma-
dam, tho you have not feen this Play, I hope {like other nice La'
dies) you will the rather read it : yet, lefl the Chamber-maid, or
Page fioud not be trufled, and their indulgences coud gain no fur-
ther admittance for ity than to their Ladies Lobbies or outward
Room, take it into your care and protetiion-, for by your recom-
mendation and procurement, it may have the honour to get into
their Clofets : for what they renounce in publick often entertains
'<fw there, with your help efpe daily. In fine. Mad am ^ for thefe
and many other reafons^ you are the fittefl Patronefs or Judge of
this play ; for you fiew no partiality to this or that Author ;
for from fome many Ladies will take a broad Jefi as chearfully
as from the Watermen, and fit at fome downright filthy Plays
{as they call 'em) as well fatisfied% and as ft ill, as a Poet coud
wifi 'em elfs where \ therefore it muji be the doubtful cbfcenity
of my Plays alone they take exceptions at, becaufe it is too bafh--
ful for "em ; and indeed mofi Women hate Men for attempting to
halves on [their Chaflity : and Baudy I find. Me Satyr, Jhoua be
home, not to have it taken notice of But, now J mention Satyr^
fome there are who fay, [Tis the Plain'dealing of the Play ;

not



# Dedicatory.

not the ohfcenityi 't/s taking off the Ladies Masks , not offering,
at their FetticoatSf which offends 'em: and generally they are
not the handfomefl^ or moft innocent^ who are the mojl angry at
heing difioverd :

*' — -* Nihil ed audacius illis

Deprehenfis ,• iram, atq ; animos a crimine fumunt

pardon, Madam^ the Quotation, for a Dedication can no more
he without ^ ends of Latine, than Flattery; and 'tis no matter
whom it is writ to • for an Author can as eafily ( / hope^ ^ttppofe
People to have more under/landing and Languages than they have,
as well as more Pertues : hut why, the Devil I fhoud any of the
few mode/} and handfome he alarmed > (for fime there are who"
as well as any deferve thofe attrihutes, yet refrain not from fee-
ing this Play, nor think it any *addition to their Vertue to fet ujy
for it in a Play-hcufe, lefi it fhoud look too much like atVmg^
But why, I fay, fhoud any at all of the truly vertuous he con^-
cernd, if thofe who are not fo are diflinguifha from 'em ? For
hy that Mask of modejly which Women wear promifcmufly in puh-
lick, they are all alike, and you can no more know a kept Wench
from a Woman of Honour hy her Looks, than hy her Drefs\for^
thofe who are of 'Quality without Honour Qif any fuch there
are ) they have their Quality to fet off their falfe mode fly, as
well as their falfe Jewels, and you mu[t no more fufpeB their
Countenances for counterfeit, than their Pendants, though as the
Plain-dealer Montaigne faySy Eles envoyent leur confdience au-
Bordel, & teinnent leur contenance en regie : But thofe vjho a^
as they look, ought not to he fcandalized at the reprehenfion of
others faults^ left they tax themfelves with 'em, and hy too-
delicate and quick an apprehenfion^ not only make fhat ohfiene
which I meant innocent^ hut that Satyr on all, which was intend-
ed only on thofe who defervd it. But ^ Madam, I heg you par'
don for this digreffton, to civil Women and Ladies of Honour^
fince you and I fhall never he the hetter for 'em ; for a Comic
Poet, and a Lady of your profejjion, make mofi of the ether fort^
and the Stage and your Houfes, like our > Plantations, are propa--
gated hy the leafi nice Women ; and, as with the Minifters of
^uftice^ tbs Fices of the Age are our hefl hufinefs. But noW'

I men*



The Epiftle

I mention Pinhlick Terfnns, I can no longer defer doin^ j^u the
Jujiice of a Dedication ^ and telling you your own; who are, of
all puhlick'fpirited People, the mofi necefaryy mofl communica-
tive^ moft generous and hcfpitahle; your houfe has leen the houfe
of the People, your Sleep Jlill dijlurFd for the Puhlick, and when
you arofe^ *twas that others might lye down, and you waked that
Mhers might refi ; the good you have done is unfpeakahle ', How
many young unexperiencd Heirs have you kept from rajh foolifh
Marriages ? and from being jilted for their lives ly the worfl
fort of Jilts^ Wives ? How many unhewitch'd iVidowers Children
have you preferved from the Tyranny of Stepmothers ? How
many old Dotards form C uc hold age j and keeping other mens Wen"
ches and Children > How many Adulteries and unnatural Sins
have you prevented ? In fne^ you hav^ keen a conflant fcourze to
the old Lecher, and often a terrour. to the young ; you have made
concupifcence its own punifJ^ment, and extinguifhed Lufl with Lufl,
like blowing up of Houfes to flop the :f re.

Nimifum propter continentiam, incontinentia
Neceilaria eft, incendium ignibus estinguitur.

There's Latin for you again, Madam; I protefl to you, as t
am an Author^ I. cannot help it ; nay, I can hardly keep my f elf
from quoting Ariftotle and Horace, and talking to you of the Rules
of Writing (like the French Authors,^ to (hew you and my Reader
I underfland 'em, in my Ep'frle^ leafi neither of you fhou d find it
out hy the PUy ; and according to the Rules of Dedications, 'tis no
matter whether you underfland or no, what I quote or fay to you, of
Writing ; ^for an Author c^n as eafily make any one a Judge or
Critick, in an Epiflle^ as an Hero in his Play ; But, Madam, that
this may prove to the end a true Epiflle Dedicatory^ fd have you
. know 'tis not without a defign upon you, which is in the hehalf of the
Fraternity of Parnaflus, that Songs and Sonnets may go at your Hou-
feSy and in your Liberties, for Guineys and half Guineys ; and
that Wit, at leafi with you, as of old, may be the price of Beauty,
and fo you will prove a true enccurager of Poetry^ for Love is a
better help to it than Wine; and Poets^ like painters, draw better
after the life, than by Fancy ; Nay, in juflice^ Madam, I think a
Poet ought to be as free of your Hcufes, as of the PlayHoufesi fince

he



Dedicatory,

be contrihutn to the fupport of hoth^ and is as necejfary tofuch as
you. as a Ballad-finger to the Pick-purfe, in convening the Cullies
at the theaters^ to he picked up^ and carry d to a Supper and Bed at
your Houfes. And^ Madam^ the reafon of this motion of mine is,
hecaufe poor Poets can get no favour in the Tyri^jg- Rooms, for they
are no Keepers, you know ; and Folly and /doney^ the old Enemies
of Wit, are even too hard for it on its own Dunghill : And for
other Ladies, a Voet can leafl go to the price of them ; lefides his
Wit, which ought to recommend him to Vw, is as much an ohJiruSli-
on to his Love, as to his Wealth or Preferment ; for moft Women
now ad ays, apprehend Wit in a Lover^ as much as in a Husband ;
they hate a Man that knows Vw, they mufl have a Mind eafie Fool,
whom they can lead ly the Nofe^ and as the Scythian Women of
old, mufl haffle a Man, and put out his Eyes, ere they will lye
with him; and then too, like thieves^ when they have plunder d
and flript a Man, leave him. But if there fioud he one of an
hundred of thofe Ladies generous enough to give her f elf to a Man
that has more Wit than Money, (^all things confiderd) he would
think it cheaper coming to you for a Miflrefs, though you made him
pay his Guiney; as a Man in a Journey, Q.out of good hushandryy
had letter pay for what he has in an Inn, than lye on free-cofl. at a
Gentlemans Houfe.

In fine, Mddam, like a faithful Dedicator, I hope I have done
my felf right in the firfl place, then you, and your prof effion, which
in the w'tfejl and moft Religious Government of the World is ho-
nour d with the puhlick allowance j and in thofe that are thought
the mofl uncivilizd and J?arharous, is prote^ed, and Jupported hy
the Mintflers of Juflice ; and of you. Madam, I ought to fay no
more here, for your Vertues deferve a Vcem rather ihan an Epifile,
or a Volume intire to give the World your Memoirs, or Life at
large, and which {upon the word of an Author that has a mind to
make an end of his Dedication) I promife to do, when I write the
Annals of our Britijh Love, which fhall he dedicated to the Ladies
concern d, if they will not think them fomething too ohfce^ie too;
when your Life, compard with many that are thought innocent, I
douht not may vindicate you and me, to the World, for the con-
fidence I have taken in this Addrefs to you; which then may he
thought nither impertinent nor immodefl ; and, whatfoever your-
Amorous misfortunes have heen, none can charge you with that

heinous,



The Epiftle



^ehous,^ an J worft ofWomens Crimes^ Hypocrifie ; my, in fpight
of misfortmes or age, you are the fame Woman fiiU; though mofi
ef your Sex grow Magdalens at fifty ^ and as a folid French Author
has iff

Apres !e Plaifir, vient la peine,
Apres la peine lavertue;

But fure an old Sinners continency is much like a Gamefiers for-
fwearimg Tlay^ when he had lofl all his Money ; and Modefly is a
kind of a youthful drefs, which as it makes a young Woman more
amiafle, makes an old one more naufeous ; a lawful old Woman is
like an hopeful old Man-, and the affe5led Ch^fiity of antiquated
Beauties, is rather a reproach than an honour to 'em, for it Jhevos
the Mens Virtue only, not theirs. But you, in fine^ Madam, are
no more an Hypocrite, than I am when I praife you j therefore I
douht not will he thought iiven hy yours and the P lay's Enemies, the
nicefi Ladys) to he the fitteft T at rone fs for.

Madam J

Your Ladyftiip's mod obedient,
faithful, humble Servant, and



the Vlak^Dealer.




spoken by the




IThe?LMN-DEALBKamtoAatoDay:
A?id my rough Part begins before the Play.
Fir ft, you who Scrible.yet hate all that Write,
And keep each other Company in fpite^
As Rivals in your common Mi/irefs, fame.
And with faint praifes, one another Damn :
'lis a good Play {me kriow) you cant forgive.
But Grudge jour felves, the Pleafure Tou receive.
Our Scribler therefore bluntly bid me fay.
He woud not have the Wits pleas' d here to Jay,
Next, you, the fine, loud Gentlemen, otb' Pit,
Who damn all Plays 3 yet, if yave any Wit,
"lis but what here you fpunge, and daily get 5
Poets, like Friends, to whom you are in Debt,
Tou hate : and fo Rooks laugh, to fee undone
Thofe pufhingGameflers, whom they live iipon.
Well, you are Sparks 3 and fi ill will be ith' fafhion :
Rail then, at Plays, to hide your Obligation.
Now, you fhrewd Judges, who the Boxes fway,
Leading the Ladies hearts, and fenje aftray.
And, for their fakeSj fee all, and hear no Play 5
Corredl your Cravats^ Foretops, Lock.behind -^
The Wrefs and breeding of the Play nere mind,

a Plain-



PROLOGUE.

flain- 'dealing is, you II fay, quite out of fajljion^

Toil 11 hate it here, as in a Dedication.

And your fair Neighbours, in a Limning Poei^

No more than in a Painter mil allow it.

Figures too like, the Ladies will not -pledfe : '

They mujl be drawn too here, like Goddejfes.

Tou^ as at Ldj'5 too, woud Truncheon wieli^

And look, like Heroes^ in a fainted Field 5

But the courfe dauber of the coming Scenes^

Zo follow Life, and Nature mly means :

Difplays you, as you are : makes his fine Wcmam

A mercenary Jilt^ and true to no Man^

His Men of Wit, andpleafure of the Age,

Are as dull Rogues as ever cumber c/ Stage :

He draws a Friend, only to Cufiom juft-j

And makes him naturally break his truji,

I, only, aSl a Part like none of you ^

And yet y ybull fay^ it is a Fools Part too:

An honeft I^an^ who, like you, never winks

At faults-^ but unlike you, fpeakj what he thinks^*

The only Fool who ne re found Patron yet -^

IBor Truth is now a fault, as well as Wit.

And where elfe, but on Stages do we fee

Truth f leafing, or rewarded Honefly ?

Which our bold Poet does this day in me.

If not to th' Honefi, be to th' profperous kind.

Some friends at Court let the PLAIN-DEALER y?«A



Somi



Some Booh Vrinted for R.Bently.



Lato'j Apologie ^f Socrates,

or Phedo, two Dialogues cott'

£ernhg the Immortality of Mans

A Natural Hiflory of the Taffions,

Country Wit.

Sophonisha.

i^ero.

Augu/lus Cisfar.

AhdeUazar,

Sir Timothy Taudery.

Mad^m Fickle.

All Miflaken.

Englijh Monfieur,

Tartuffe.

Andromache,

Califla.

Forced Marria^.

The Fool turnd Critkh

Fond Husband,

Plain- Dealer.

Jhyefies: A Tragedy.

Moral EJbySf thefecond Fart,



The Policy of the Clergy of France

to deflroy the P tot eji ants,
. Englifh Novels, blQW,
Belinda.
Count Brion.
Hap^y Slave.
7 he diforders of Love.
The fecond Tart of the Hapfy

Slave.
The Pilgrim^ in two Parts.
The Princefs of Montferrat ; in two

Parts.

French Novels.
Princejfe Montferrat.
L! Heureux Efclave^ complete tn

trois Vol.
Mercure Galand, pour t Annie*

1677^
Le Triomphe d^ Amour fur la Defli'

nee.
A French Play a^ed <Jf Whitehall,

EntituleJ, Rare-en- tout.



Manly
Mr. Heart.



Freeman
Mr. Kynailan.

Vernijh
Mr. GrifHn.



THE PERSONS.

rOf an honeft, furly, nice humour, fuppos'd
\ firft in the time of the Dutch War, to have
^ procur'd the Command of a Ship, out of
) Honour, not Intereft j and chufing a Sea-
^ life, only to avoid the World.
^Manlys Lieutenant, a Genfleman well Educa-
^ ted, but of a broken Fortune, a Complier
C with the Age.



l^ovel
Mr. Clark.
Major Oldfox
Mr. Cartwright.
My Lord Plaujihle
Mr. Hains.
Jerry Blackacre
Mr. Charkofi.



^Manlys Bofom, and only Friend.
C

{k pert railing Coxcomb, and an admirer of
Novelties, makes Love to Olivia.
C An old impertinent Fop, given to Scribling,
< makes Love to the Widow Blackacre.
t A Ceremonious, Supple, Commending Cox-
l comb, in Love with Olivia.

{A true raw Squire under Age, and his Mothers
Government, bred to the Law.

<Manlys Miftrefs. *



'In Love with Manly, and follow'd him to Sea
. In Man*s Cloaths.



Olivia

Mrs. Marihal.

Fidelia

Mrs. Boutell.

Eliza

Mrs. Kncp.

Lettice

Mrs. Knight

The Ifidoiv Blackacre? A. petulant, litigious Widow, always id Law,

Mrs. Cory. L and Mother to Squire ^^rry.



< Coufin to Olivia.
Bolivia's Woman.



Lawyers, Knights ef the Tofl, Bay tiffs, and Aldermen, a Bookfe liens
Prentice, a Poothoy, Sailors^ Waiters, and Attendants.

THESCENE



LONDON.



( I )




A C T I. S C E N E I.

Captain Manly 's Lodging.

Enter Captain Manly fi^rlily ^ and my Lord Plaufible following him
and two Sailors behind.



T'



Man. j^ ' jg" l Eil not me f my good Lord Plaufible) of your Decorums ^ fu-
percilious Forms, and flavifti Ceremonies^ your little
Tricks, which you the Spaniels of the World do daily
over and over, for, and to one another ^ not out of
love or duty, but your fervile fear.

L. TUuf. Nay, i'faith, i'faith, you are too paflionate, and I muft humbly
beg your pardon and leave to tell you, they are the Arts and Rules, the Pru-
dent of the World walk l>y.

Man. Let 'em. But I'll have no Leading-firings, 1 can walk alone; 1
hate a Harnefs, and will not tug on in a Fadion> kiffing my Leader be-
hind, that another Slave may do the like to me.

L. Plauf. What will you be lingular then, like no Body ? follow Love>
and efteem no- Body ?

Man. Rather than be general, like you ; follow every Body, Court and
kifs every Body '-, though perhaps at the fame time, you bate every Body.

L. Plauf Why, ferioully wlh your Pardon, my dear friend

Man. With your Pardon, my no Friend, I will not, as you do, whifper
my hatred, or my fcorn, call a man Fool or Knave, by figns or mouths over
his (houlder, whilll you have hira in your arms j for fuch as you, like com-
mon Whores and Pickpockets, are only dangerous to thofe you imbrace.

L. Plauf. Sach as I ! Heavens defend me upon my Honour—-

Man. Upon your Title, my Lord, if you'd have me believe you.

L. Plauf Well then, as I am a Perfon of Honour, I never attempted to
abufe, or leflln any Perfon, in my life.

Man. Whaf, you were afraid ?

L. Plauf. No j but ferioufly,- 1 hate to do a rude thing : No, faith, I fpeak
well of all Markind.

Man. I thought fo ; but know, that the fpeal^ing well of all Mankind, is the
worit kind of Detradion ^ for it takes away the Ruputatbn of the few good

B iTien



* THE PI AIN-D BALER.

men in the World, by makipg all alike : now I fpeakill of moft men, bccaufe
theydeferve k^ I that can do a rude thing, rather than an unjuft thing.

L. PUuf, Well, tell noE me, my dear Friend, what People deferve, I ne'er
qaind that; I, liks an Author in a Dedication? never fpeak well of a man for
his fake, but my own •, I will not difparage any man, to difpatage my felf \
for to fpeak ill of People behind their backs, is not like a Pcrfon of Honour :
and truly to fpeak ill of em to their faces, is not like a Comphifant psrfon :
Bui if i did fay, or do an ill Jhiag to any, ii Ihould be fure to bs behind their
backs, out of pure good manners.

Man. Very well^ but I, that an[>an unmannerly Sea- fellow, if I ever fpeak
well of People, (which is very feldom indeed) it ^)^'z\6 be fure to bt bi;hind
thsir backs •, and if 1 wou'd fay, or do ill to any, ir, fliouM bs to then Faces:
I wouM jultis a proud, ftrutting, over-icokmg Coxcomb, at hi head of- his
Sycophant?, rather than pus out my t:ongne at him, 'when b ? were pafl me j*
wou'd frown in the arrogant, big, dull f^ce of an over- grown- Knave of ba-
fmefs, rather than vent my fpieen again 0: hiim, when his bick were turn'd \
wou'd give fawning Slaves the Lye, whilft they embrace or commend me •,
Cowards, whilffcthsy brag ; call a Rafcal by no other Title, chough his Father
had left him a Dake's; laugh at fools aloud, before their Miftrefici: And
muft deiire People to leave me, when their Vifiv.s grow at lalt ss troublelbm,
as they were at: firft impertinent.

L. Plan/. I wouM not have my Vifits troubkfom.
Man. The only way to be fure not to have 'cm troubUfom, is to make
'em when People are not at home, for your Vifits, like other good turns, are
molt obliging, when made, or dene to a man, in b?s ablence. A Pox why fhou'd
any one, becaufe he has nothing to do, go and difturb another mans bufinefs?
L. Fimf. 1 beg your pardoo, my dear Friend. What, you have bufinefs ?
Man, If you have any, 1 wou'd, not detain your Lordfhip.
L. Plauf. Detain me, dear Sir, 1 can never have enough of your Company.
Man. I'm afraid 1 fhou'd be tirefom ; 1 know not what you think. "
L. Tlauf. Well, dear Sir, 1 fee you wou'd have me gone. . '

Man. But I fee you won't. l^Jfide.

L. Plmf. Your molt faishful— - — «
Man. God be w'ye, my Lord.
t. Plauf. Your moll humble. — —
Man. Farewel.

L. Plauf. And eternally

Man. And eternally Ceremony' then the Devil take ihee eternally,

L. Plauf. You fhall ufe no Ceremony, by my life.

Ma?i, 1 do not intend it.

L. Plauf. Why do you ftir then ?
V Aian. Only to fee you oui of doors, that I may fliut 'em againft more
welcomes.

L. Planf Nay, faith that fliall not pafs upon your moft faithful, humble.
Servant. >>

Man. Nor this any more upon me. ^^Jtde,



THE PLAIH-^EALRtt. 3

X» TUtif. Well> you are too ftrong for me.

Man. IMe fooner be vifited by the Plague j for that only wouM keep a
man from yifits, and his doors iSuE. .[.^fide,

{Ex. thrtifiifjg om my Lord Plaufible.
Manent Sailers.

1 SaU. Here's a finical Fellow, Jack}. Whan a brave fair-weather Captain
of a Ship he wou'd make ! -^

2 Sail. He a Captain of a Ship ! it mull be when file's in the Dock then •, for
he looks like one of thofe that gel the King's Comraiffions for Hulls, to fel! a
Kings Ship, when a brave Fellow has fought her almoft to a long-boat

1 Sail, On my Confcience then, Jacl^^^ that's the reafon our Bully T^r
funk our Ship : not only that the Bmch might not have her, but that the
Courtiers, who laugh at wooden Legs, might not make her Prize.

2 S^i/. A Pox of his linking, Tom^ we have, made a bafe, broken, Ihort
Voyage of it.

xSmL Ay, your brisk dealers ia Honour, always make quick returns
witli their Ship to the Dock, and their men to theHofpitals^ 'tis, let me fee,
juft a Month Gnce we fet out of the River, and the Wind was almoft as crofs
to us> as the Dutch.

2 Sail, Well, I forgive him finking my own poor Trunk, if he wou'd
but have given me time and leave to have fav'd black Kate of Wai^pn^%
fmall Venture.

1 SalU Faith f forgive him, fince, as thePurfer told me, he funk the value
of five or fix thoufsnd pound of his own, with which he was to fettle him-
felf fome where in the Indks^ for our merry Lieutenant was to fucceed him
irf his Commiffion for the Ship back, for he was rcflvM never to return
again for England.

2 Sail. So it feemed, by his Fighting.

1 Sail No, but he was^a wcary pf this fide of the World here, thfy fay.

2 Sail. Ay, or tX^^h?, wou'd not hav-^^bld fo fair for s paflage into t'o;b5r.

1 Sail. Jack,^ Thou Ciiink'lt thy felf in the f :<recafli% chou^-c fa waggifh •,
but I tell ycuthej?, he had a mind to go live and bask himf^ilf oo the fanny
fide of thfi Globs.

2 S^il. Wha&, oUh of af^y difcontenl? for he's always as dogged, as an
old TstpauHu, v'hen idadred of a Voyage by a young Pantaloon Captain.

1 Sail. Tis true, I never f^P him pleas'd but in the Fight, and th^n he
look'd like one of us, coming from the Pay-t^ble, with a new Lining to our
Hats ur.der our Afius.

X Sail. A Pox bs's like the B^iy of Bifcay^ rough and aegry, let the vVi^d
blow where 'twilL ' " '

1 Sdl. Nay, there's no more dealing with him, than widi the Land ia a
Storsi, No near— —

2 Smi. 'Tis 3 h?!rry flurry Blade-, doft thou remember after we hadtiiggM
hard ihe old leaky Loiig-boas, to lave his life, when I vvelcom'd him afnorej
he gave'ms a box on the ear, and ceUM me fawniag Water-dog.

Enter ¥id.n\^ and fxzim&n^ . .- '
1 Sail. Hold thy peace, Jack^ and Hand by, the fodl weather's coming.
Man. You Rafcal, Dogs, how cou'd this tame thing g€t through you ?



4 THE. PLAIN-DEALER.

1 Sail. Faith, to tell your Honour the truth, we were at Hob in the Hall,
and whilft my Brother and I were quarrelling about a Gaft, he flunk by us.

2 Sail. He's a fneaking Fellow I warrant for't.

Man. Ha vs more c ire for the future, you Slaves ^ go, and withdrawn
Cutlaces, fl:and at the Stair-foot, and keep all that ask for me fromcomiog
op i fappafe you are guarding the Scuttle to the Powder-room; let none
enter here, at your or their peril. ^

1 Sail. No, for the danger wouM be the fame ^ you wouM blow them and
us up, if ws fbou'd.

2 Sail. Maft no one come to you, Sir ?
Man. No man, Sir. —

1 Sail. No nian. Sir j but a Woman then, an't like your Honour' ^•

Man. No Woman neither, you impertinent Dog. WouM you be Pimp-
ing ? A Sea Pimp, is the ftrangeft Moniler fhe has.

2 Sail. Indeed, an't like your Honour, 'twill be hard for us to deny a
Woman any thing, fince we are fo newly come on fliore.

1 Sail. Well, let no old Woman come up, though it were our Trulling
Landlady at Wappin^.

Man. Wou'd you be witty, you Brandy Cask you? you become a jeft as ill,
as you do a Horfe. Be gone, you Dogs, I hear a noife on the Stairs. Z£x. Sailors.

Free, Faith, I am forry you wou'd let the "Fop go, I intended to have
had fome fport with him.

Man. Sport with him! A Pox then, why did you notftay? you fhou'd
have en joy'd your Coxcomb, and had him to your felf for me.

Free. No, I fliou'd not have car*d for him, without you neither ; for the
pleafure which Fops afford, is like that of Drinking, only good when 'tis
ftiar'd ', and a Fool like a Bottle, which wou'd make you merry in Company,
will make you dull alone. But how the Devil cou*d you turn a man of his
Quality down Stairs.** You ufe a Lord with very little Ceremony, it feems.

Man. A Lord! What, thou art one of thofe who efteem men only by the
marks and value Fortune has fet upon 'em, and never confider intrinlick
worth •, but counterfeit Honour will not be current with me, I weigh the man,
not his Title ^ 'tis not the Kings ftamp can make the Mettal better, or heavier :
your Lord is a Leaden fliilling, which you may bend every way ; and debafes
the ftamp he bears, inftead of being rais'd by't: Here again, you Slaves ?

Enter Sailors.

I Sail. Only to receive farther inftrudions, an't like your Honour: What
if a man fhou'd bring you Money, iliou*d we turn him back ?

Man. All men, 1 fay j mull I be pefter'd with you too? you Dogs, away.

X Sail. Nay, 1 know one man your Honour wou'd not have us hinder com-
ing to you, I'm fure.

Afan. Who's that? fpeak quickly. Slaves.

0. Sail. Why, a man that ft>ou*d bring you a Challenge ; for though you
refufe Money, I'm fure you love fighting too well to refufe that.

Man. Rogue, Rafcal, Dog. [^/Vi^' '^^ Saifors o«^

Free. Nay, let the poor Rogues have their Forecaftle jefts ; they cannot
help 'em in a Fight, fcarce when a Ship's finking.

Afan.



THE PLAIN-DEALDR, S

Man. Dam their untimely jefts j a Servant's jefl: is more faucinsfs than
his counfel.

Free. But what^ will you fee no Body ? not your Friends ?

Man* Friends— — 1 have but one, aad he, I bear, is not in Town ; nayj
can have but ons Friend, for a true heart admits but of one Friendfliipi as oi
one love J but in having that Friend, I have a thoufand, for h^ has the cou-
rage of men in defpair, yetthediffidency and caution of Cowards ^ the fecrefie
of the revengeful, and the conltancy of Martyrs : one fit to advife, to keep
a*fecret : to fight and die for his Friend. Sach I think him ^ for I have truft-
ed him with my Miilrefs in my abfence ; and the trull of Beauty, is fure
the greateft we can (hew.

Free. VVjell, but all your good. thoughts are not for him alone? (I hope^
pray what d'ye think of me for a Friend ?

Man. Of thee ! Why, thou arc a Latit Hdinarian in Friendfhipi that is no
Friend; thou doll fide with all Mankind, bat wilt fuffer for none. Thou
art indeed like your Lord Plaufible^ the Pink of Gourtefie, therefore haft
no Friendfhip \ for Ceremony and great ProfefTing, renders Friendfhip as
much fufpedted, as is does Religion.

Free. And no prof effing, no Ceremony at ali in Friend lliip, were as un-
natural and as undecent as in Religion ; and there is hardly fuch a thing as
an honeft Hypocrite, who profefTes himfelf to be worfe than he is, unlefs is
-be your felf :, for, though I cou'd never get you to fay you were my Friend,
1 know you'l prove fo.

Man. 1 muft confefs, I am fo much your Friend, I wou'd not deceive you,
therefore muft tell you (not only beeaufe my heart is taken up) but accord-
ing to your Rules of Friendfhip, I cannot be your Friend.

Free. Why, pray ?

Man.^ Beeaufe he that is (yon'l fzy) a true Friend to a man, is a Friend'
to all his Friends^ but you muft pardon me, I cannot wifli well to Pimps,
flatterers, Detradors, and Cowards, ftifFnodding Knaves, and fupple pli-
ant kifling Fools: now, all th^fe 1 have feen you ufe, like thedeareft Friends-,
in the World.

Free. Hah, hah, hah — What, you obferv'd me, I warrant, in the Galleries
ztWhitehdly doing the bufinefs of the place ! Pihaw, Court- profeflions, like
Court-promifes, go for nothing, man ! but. Faith, cou'd you think 1 was a

Friend to all thofe 1 hugg'd, kifs'd, flatter'd, bow'd to ? Hah, ha- — -

Ma?i. You told 'em fo, and fwore it too; 1 heard you.

Free. Ay, but when, their backs were lurn'd, did 1 not tell you ihey were
Rogues, Villains, Rafcals whom I defpis'd, and hated ?

Mm. Very fine? But what reafon had 1, to believe you fpoke your heart
■ to me, fince you profefs'd deceiving fo many ?

Free. Why, don't you know, good Captain, that telling truth is a quality
as prejudicial to a man that wou'd thrive in the World, as fq^iare Phy eo a
Cheat, or true Love to a whore! wou'd you have a man fpeak rrut^to his
mine? You arefeverer than the Law, which requires no man to (Wear s-
gainft himfelf j you wou'd have me fpeak truth againft my felf, ^ warrsnf,
and tell my promifing friend, the Courtier, he has a bad memory ?

Man. Yes. Fres^



^ THB PLAIN'DBALER.

free. And fo make him remember to forget my bufinefs^ and 1 fliou'd
tell the great Lawyer too, that he takes oftner fees to hold his tongue, than
to fpeak !

Man. No doubt on't.

Fne, Ay, and have him hang, or ruine me, when he Ihou'd come to be a
Judge, and I before him. And you wou'd have me tell the new Officer, who
bought his Employment lately, that he is a Coward

Man, Ay.

Free. And fo get my felf cafhier'd, not him, he having the better Friends,
though I the better Sword. And 1 Ihou'd tell the Scribler of Honour, that
Heraldry were a prettier and fitter Study, for fo fine a Gentleman, than
Poetry?

Man. Certainly.

Free. And fo find my felf mauPd in his next hir'd Lampoon. And you
wou'd have me tell the holy Lady too, (he lies with her Chaplain.

Man, No doubt on't.

^Free. And fo draw the Clergy upon my back, and want a good Table to
Dine at fometimes. And h^ the fame reafon too, I fliou'd tell you that the
World thinks you a Mad man, a Brutal, and have you cut my Throat, or
worfe, hate me ' What other good fuccefs of all my Plain-dealing cou'd 1
have, than what I've mentioned ?

Man. Why, firll your promiiing Courtier wou'd keep his word out of fear
of more reproaches *, or at kaft wou'd give you no more vain hopes : Your
Lawyer wou'd ferve you more faithfully j for he, having no Honour but his
Intereft, is trusft ftill to him he knows fufpedls him : The new Officer wou'd
provoke thee to make him a Coward, and fo be cafhier'd, that thou, or fome
other honelt Fellow, who had more courage thau money, might get his place :
the Noble Sonneteer wou'd trouble thee no more with his Madrigals : The
praying Lady wou'd leave off railing at wenching before thee, and not turn
away hsr Chamber-maid^ far her own known frailty with thee : Aud I inftead
of hating thee, fliou'd love thee, for thy Plain dealing j and in lieu of being
mortifi'd, am proud that the World and I think not well of one another.

Free. Well, Doctors differ. You are for Plain- dealing.^ I find -, but againft
your particular Noeions, 1 have the practice of the whole World. Obferve
but any Morning what people do when they get together on the Exchange ^
in Weft minfier- Hall, or the Galleries in Whitehall.

Man. I niuii: confefa, tnere they feem to rehearfe Bay^s grand Dance : -
here you fee a Bifhop bowing low to a gaudy Athtiil: j a Judge to a Door-
keeper : a great Lord, to a Filhmonger, or a Scrivener with a Jack chain
about his neck ^ a Lawyer, to a Sergeant at Arms ; a velvet Phylician, to a
thred'bare Chyoiiit: and a fupple Gentleman UfiU-r, to a furly Beef-eater •,
and fo tread round in a prepafterous huddle of Ceremony to each other,
whil'It they can hardly hold their foiemn faife Countengnces.

Fref. .Well, they underfcand the WorH*

Man. Which 1 do not, i coiifefs.

Free. But, Sir, pray believe the Friendfhip I promife you, real, what-
foever I have profeft to others : try me, at leail.

M^n.



i HE PLAIN-'BEALER: 7

Man. Why, what wou'd youdofor me ?
Free. 1 wouM fight for you.

Man, That you vvou'd do for your owa Honour, buS what elfe ?
Free. 1 wou'd knd you Money if 1 had it.

Man, To borrow more of me another time. That were but puting your
Money to interact, an Ufurer wou'd be as good a Friend. Bat whai other
piece of Friendftiip ?

Free. 1 wou'd fpsak well of you to your Enemies.

Man. Toincourage others to be your Friends, by a (hew of gratitude 5
but what elfe/*

Free. Nay, I wou'd not hear you ill fpoken of behind your back, by my
Friend.

Man. Nay, then thou'rt a Friend indeed | but it were unreafonable to
€xpeft it from thee, as the World gots now : when jiew Friends, like new
MiHrefles, are got by difparaging old ones.

Enter Fidelia. ^
But here comes another, will fay as much at leaft, dofl not thou love me,
devilifhly too, my listle Voluntier, as well as he, or any man can ?
Fid. Better than any man can love you, my dear Captain."
Man. Look you there, 1 told you fo.
Fid. As well as you do Truth or Honour, Sir ; as well.
Man. Nay, good young Gentleman, enough, for Ihame 5 thou haft been
a Page, by thy Flattering and Lying, to one of thofe praying Ladies, who love
Flattery fo well, they are jealous of it, and wert turn'd away for faying the
fame things to the old Houfe-keeper for fweet- meats, as you did to your La™,
dy : for then flattereft every thing, and every body alike.

Fid, You, dear Sir, fiiou'd not fufped the truth of what I fay of you^
though to you J Fame, theoldLyar, is believ'd when fhe fpeaks wonders of
you^ you cannoc be flattered, Sir, your Merit is unfpeakable.

Man. Hold, hold, Sir, or I fhall furped worfe of you, that you have been
a Culhion-bearer to fome State Hypocrite, and turn'd away by the Chap-
lains, for out-flattering their Probation Sermons for a Benefice.

Fid. Sufpedt me for any thing. Sir, but the want of Love, Faith, and
Duty to you, the braveft, worthieft of Mankind ^ believe me, 1 cou'd die
for you, Sir.

Man. Nay, there you lye. Sir i did I not fee thee more afraid in the Fight^
^han the Chaplain of the Ship, or the Purfer that bought his place ?
Fid. Can he be faid to be afraid, that ventures to Sea with you ?
Man. Fie, fie, no more, I Ihali hate thy Flattery worfe than thy Cowar-
dife, nay, than thy Bragging.

Fid. Well, I own then I was afraid •, mightily afraid 5 yet for you I wouM

be afraid again, an hundred times afraid : dyi«g is ceafing to be afraid, and

that 1 cou'd do fure for you, and you'll believe me one day. {Weep,

Free. Poor Youth ! believe his Eyes, if not his Tongue : he feems to/peak

truth with them.

Man. What, does he cry ? A Pox on't, a Maudlin Flatterer is as naufe-
oufly troublefom, as a Maudlin Drunkard , no more, you littk Milk-fop* do



8 THE P LAIN'DEALER.

not cry, I'll never make thee afraid again ; for of all irien> if 1 had occafion,
thou Ihoud'il not be my Second •, and, when I go to Ssa again, thou fhalE
venture thy life no more with me.

Ftii. Why, will you leave me behind then ?
Cl( you wouM preferve my life, I'm fure you Ihou'd not.) [_Afide.

Aim. Leave thee behind ! Ay, ay, thou art a hopeful Youth forthelhore
only \ here thou wilt live to be cheri(hMl)y Fortune, and the great ones 5 for
thou may'ft eafily come to oac-flatter a duUPoec, cut-lie a Coffee-houfe, or
Gazet-writer, out-fwear.a Knight of the Poll, out-watch a Pimp, out-fawn
a Rook, out-promife a Lover, out-rail a Wit, aud our-brag a Sea-Captain :
AH this thou canlt do, becaufe thou'rt a Coward, a thing 1 hate, therefore
thou'lt do better with the World than with me, and thefe are the good cour-
fes you muft take in the World. There's good advice, at kaft, at parting :
go, and be happy with't.

Fid. Parting, Sir I O let me not liear that difmal word.

Man. If my words frighten thee, be gone the fooner j for to be plain
with thee, Cowardife and 1 cannot dwell together.

Fid, And Cruelty and Courage never dwell together fure, Sir. Do not
turn me off to Ihame and mifery ^ for I am helplefs and friendlefs.

Man. Friendlefs! there are half a fcore Friends for thee then ^ [Offers her
GoW} i leave roy felf no more : they'll help thee a little. Be gone, go, I
muft be cruel to thee (if ihou calPft it fo) out of pity.

Fid, If you wouM be cruelly pitiful. Sir, Jet it be with your Sword, and
not Gold. [Extt.

Enter firfi Sailor.

I Sail. Wchave, with much ado, turn'd away two Gentlemen, who told
us forty times over, their names were Mr. Novel., and Major Oldfox.

Man. Well, to your Poft again. \_Exit Sailor.

But how come thofe Puppies coupled always together .«*

Free. O, the Coxcombs keep esch other company, to fliew each other, as
iVbz/e/ calls it j or, as 0/^oa; fays, like two Knives, to whet one another.

Man, And fet other Peoples teeth an ^^^t.

Enter fecond Sailor.

-1 Sail. Here is a Woman, an'c like your Honour, fcolds and bullies with
us, to come in, as much as a Ssamaa's Widow at the Navy Office : her name
is Mrs. Blackjcre.

Man. That Fiend too !

Free.- The Widow Blackacre^ is it not ? that Litigious S he-Petty- fogger,
who is at Law and difference with all the world ^ but I wi(h 1 cou'd make
her agree with me in the Church : they fay fhs has Fifteen hundred pounds a
Year Joynture, and the care of her Son, that is, the Dcftrudion of his Eftate.

Man. Her Lawyers, Attornies and Solicitors have Fifteen hundred pound
a Year, whil'It (he is contented to be poor, to make other People fo ^ for (he
is as vexatious as her Father was, the great Attorney, nay, as a dozen 'Nor^
/o/^ Attorneys, and as implacable an Adverfary, as a Wife fuing for Alimony,
or a Parfon for hisTiths ; and fhe loves an Eajter-Ttrm^ or any Term, not, as
otlier Country Lsdies do, to come up to be fine, . Cuckold their Husbands,

and



THE PLAIN-DEALER. 9

and take their Pieafure ^ for (he has no pleafure, but in vexing others, and
is ufually cloath'd and dagled like a Bawd in difguife, purfuM through Al-
leys by Sergeants. When (he is in Town, (he lodges in one of the Inns of
Chancery, where (he breeds her Son, and is her felf his Tutoiefs in Law-
French 5 and for her Country- abode, tho' (he has no Eflate there, (he chufes
Norfolk^ But, bid her come in, with a Pox to her | (he is. OU'via^ Kinfwo-
man, and may make me amends for her vifit, by fome difcourfe of thai
dear Woman. ^Exit Sailor.

Enur Widovp Blackacre vaith a Mantle^ and a green Bag^ and feveral Papers
in the other hand : Jerry Blackacre her Son^ in a Gown^ laden with greert
BagSy following her,

Wid. I never had fo much to do with a Judge's Door-keeper, as with
yours-, but^—
. Man. But the incomparable 0/m<f, how does (he fince I went?

Wid. Since you went, my fuit — »

Man. Olivia., I fay, is (he well ?

Wid. My Suit, if you had not return'd-

Man. Dam your Suit, how does your Cou(in Olivia ?

Wid. My Suit, I fay, had been quite loft^ but now-

Man. But now where is Olivia? in Town ? for



Wid. For to morrow we are to have a Hearing.

Man. Wou'd you'd let me have a Hearing to day.

Wid. But why won'E you hear me ?

Man. 1 am no Judge, and you talk of nothing but Suits •, but, pray tell
me, when did you fee Olivia ?

Wid. I am no Vifiier, buta Woman of bufinefsi or if I ever vifit, 'tis
only the Chancery-lane Ladies, Ladies towards the Law ; and not any of
your lazy, good-for-nothing Flirts, who cannot read Law-French, tho' a
Gallant writ it. But, as I was telling you, my Suit ■

Man. Dam thefe impertinent, vexatious People of Buflnefs, of all Sexes j
they are lliU troubling the World with the tedious recitals of their Law-
Suits : and one can no more (top their moushs, than a Wits, when he
talks of himfelf ; or an Intelligencer's, when he talks of other Psople.

Wid. And a Pox of all vexatious impertinent Lovers^ they are ftili per-
plexing the World with the tedious Narrations of their Love Suits, and
Difcourfes of their MiltreQes : you are as troublefom to a poor Widow of
Bulinefs, as a young Coxcomb Riming Lover.

Man. And thou art as troublefom to me, as a Rook to a lofing Game-
fter, or a young putter of Cafes to his Miftrefs and Sempftrefs, w(ho has
love in her head for another-

Wid. Nay, fince you talk of putting of Cafe?, and will not hear me
fpeak, hear our Jerry a little; let him put our Cafe to you, for the Try-
al's to morrow •, and fince you are ray chief Witnefs, 1 wou'd have your
memory refreOi'd, and your judgment jnform'd, that you may not give your
Evidence improperly. Speak out. Child.

C Jetc



lo THB PLAIN 'DEALER.

Jer. Yes, forfooth. Hemh! Hemh ! John-'a-Stiles^



Man. You may calk, young Lawyer, but 1 (hall no more mind you, than;
a hungry Judge does a Gaufe, after ihe Clock has ftruck One.
Free. Nay, you'll find him as peeviih too.

Wid. No matter. Jerry^ go on. Do you obferve it then. Sir, for 1 think
1 have feen you in a Gown once. , Lord, I couM hear our Jerry pus Cafes
all day long-' Mark.him, ;Sir../^ ;! ,.

Jer. John-a-Stiles no — —'There are firft, Fitz,^ Pere, and viry.'e; .

No, no ^ylcy Pers^ and Fitz. j j4yls is feized in Fee of BUckacre j John-a.-
Stiles difleifes ^yle-^ Ayle makes Glaioi, and the DilTeifor dies y then the
^^yle^ — — no theff^;::.

Wid. No, she Pere.^ Sirrah.

Jer. O, she Pere: ay, the Pere.^ Sir, and the Fitz. — — no, the Ayle:^ no,
the Pere and the Fitz.^ Sir, and— ";^
Man. Dara Pere^ Mere and Fitz^^ Sir.

PFifW. No, you are oar. Child ^ hear me, Captain, then, there are ^y^,
Tere and Fitz.^ Ayle is feifed in Fee of BUckacre ^ and being fo feifed, John- a-
Stilei diiTeifes the Jyle^ Ayle makes Clain), and the difleifor dies-, and then
the Pere re-enters, the Pere, Sirrah, the Pere — [To Jerry.] And the F/>j en-
ters upon the Pere^ and the ^yle brings his Writ of Difleizen, in the Poft ^

and the Pere brii^gs his Writ of DilTeizenj in the Pere^ and .

. Man. Canft thou here this ftuff^ Freeman ? I cou'd as foon fufFer a whole
nolfe of Flatterers at a great mans Levy in the morning ^ but thoij haft fer-
vile complacency enough to liften to a quibling Statefman, in difgrace, nay,.

and be before -hand with him, in laughing at his dull No-jeft; but I

XPff'ering to go out,
Wid: Nay, Sir, hold. Where's the 5«^-/)a?^^, Jerry? 1 muft ferve you.

Sir. You are requii'd, by this, to give your teftirnony-«

Man. Pie be forfworn, to be reveng'd on thee. t^x. Manley ^^yoip/wg'

away the Subpoena.
Wid. Get you gone, for a Lawlefs companion. Come, yerry^ 1 had al-
moft forgot we were to meet at the Mafters at three : let us mind our bufinefs
ftili. Child.

Jer, I, forfooth, e'en fo let's. •-

Free. ^Nay, Madam, now I wou'd beg you to hear me a little, a little of
my bulintfs.

Wid. 1 have bufinefs of my own calls me away, Sir.
Free. My bufinefs wou'd prove yours too, dear Madam.
IVtd. Yours v/ou'd be fome fweet bufinefs, I warrant : What, 'tis no
Weftminfier-H^Al bufinefs.'' wou'd you have my advice/

Free, No, faith, 'tis a little Wefiminfier-Ahhy bufinefs : I wou'd have your
confent.

Wid. O fy, fy, Sir *, to me fuch difcourfe, before my dear Minor there/
Jer. Ay, ^y. Mother, he wou'd be taking Livery and Seizen of your
Jointure, by digging the Turf j but I'll watch your waters. Bully, i'fac.
Gome away. Mother.

l^Ex. Jerry, haiU/jg away his Mother.

Manet



THE PLAIN-DEALER. ir

Manet Freeman : Enter to him Fidelia.

Fid. Dear Sir, you have pity j begei but fome in your Captain for me*

Free, Where is he ?

Fid. Within ^ fweariog, as much as he did in ths great Storm, and curling
you, and foraetimes finks into calms and fighs, and talks of Kiiplvvia.

Free. He wou'd never truft me to fee her: is (he handiom ?

Fid. Ho^ if you'll take my word ^ but I am not a props r Judge.

Frfe. What is fhe ?

Fid. A Gentlewoman, I fuppofe, but of as mean a Fortune as Beauty^ but
her Relations wdu'd not fufFer her to go with him to the Indies : and his aver-
lion to this fide of the World, together with the late opportunity of com-
manding the Convoy, wou'd not let him ftay here longer, the' io enjoy her.

Free. He loves her mightily then.

Fid. Yes, fo well, that the remainder of his Fortune (I hear about five
or fix thoufand pounds) he has lefe her, in cafe he had dy'd by the way, or
before fihe cou'd prevail with her Friends to follow him, which he expeded
fhe fliou'd do •, and has left behind him his great bofome-Friend to be her
Convoy to him.

Free. What Charms has (he for him, if (he be not handfom ?

Fid. He fancies her, Ifuppofe, the only Woman of Truth and Sincerity
in the World. "*

Free. No Common Beauty, I confefs.
• Fid. Or elfe fure he wou'd not have trufted her with fo great a (hare of
his Fortune, in his abfence :, I fuppofe, ^fince his late lofs^ all he has.

Free. Why, has he left it in her own cuftody ?

Fid. I am told fo.

Free. Then he has (hewed Love to her indeed, in leaving her, like an old
Husband that dies as foon as he has made his Wife a good Jointure ; but I'll
go in to him, and fpeak for you, and know more from him of his Olivia.

[Exit.
Manet f'ldtlh fola.

Fid. His Olivia indeed, his happy Olivia^
Yet (he was left behind, when I was with him ^
But (he was ne'er out of his mind or heart.
She has told him (he lov'd him-, I have (hew'd it,

And durlt not tell him fo, till I had done, j

Under this habit, fuch convincing Adts ; .

Of loving Friend(hip for him, that through it
He firffc might find out both my Sex and Love i ^

And, when IM have him from his fair Olivia.^
And this bright World of artful Beauties here,
Might then have hop'd, he wou'd have look'd on me
Amongft the footy Indians ^ ar.d 1 cou'd
To choofe there live his Wife, where Wives are forc'd
To live no longer, when their Husbands die.
Nay, what's yet worfe, to (hare 'em whil'ft they live
With many Rival WivwS. But here he comes,

C 2 ' V And



12 THB. PLAIN-DBALER.

And I muffc yet keep out of his fight, not -

To lofe it for ever. X^xk.

Enter Manly and Freeman.
Free, But what ftrange Charms has fhe that cou'd make you love ?
Man, Strange Charms indeed .' She has Beauty enough to call in queftion
her Wie or VerEue, and her Fbrmwou'd make a ftarv'd Hermit a Ravifner ^
yet her Vertas, and Condad, wou'd prelerve her frcoa the fubtil Lull of a
pamper'd Prelate. She is fo perfeft a Beauty, that Art cou'd not better it,
nor affedion deform it v yet all this is nothing. Her tongue as well as face,
ne'er knew artifice: nor ever did her words or looks contradid her heart :
She is all truth, and hates the lying, masking, daubing World, as I do •, for
which 1 love her, and for which 1 think (he dillikes not me: for fhe has often
Ihut out of her converfation for mine, the gaudy fluttering Parrots of the
Town, Apes, and Ecchoesof menonly, and refus'd their common place pen
chat, flattery, and fubraiffions, to be entertain'd with my fullen bluntnefs,
and honefl love. And, lallofalJ, fwore to me, fince her Parents wou'd noE
fuffer her to go with m-e, flie wou'd ftay behind for no other man ^ but fol-
low me, without their leave, if not to be obtaia'd. Which Oath -^*-»
Free. Did you think Or^ wou'd keep ? r, -,

.Mcin-^ Yes j for fhe is not (I ttll you) like other Women, but can keep her
promife, tho fhe has fwora to k«ep it; but, that fhe might the better keep
it, I left her the value of five or fix thoufand Pounds : for Womens wants
are generally their moft importunate Solicitors to Love or Marriage.

Free. And mone^y fummons Lovers, more -than Beauty, and augments
but their importunity, and their number-, fo makes it the harder for a
Woman to deny 'em. For my part, I am for the French Maxim, if you
wou'd have your Female Subjeds Loyai, keep 'em poor : but, in fhort, that
your Millrefs may not marry, you have given her a Portion.

Mun^ She had given me her heart firft, and I am fatisfied with the fecu-
rity: I can never doubE her truth and conftancy.

FreQ. IE feems you do, fince you are fain to bribe it with Money. But
how come you to be fo diffident of the Man that fays he loves you, and
not doubt the Woman that fays it ?

Man, I ftiou'd (Iconfefs^ doubt the love of any other Woman but her,
as 1 do the friendlhip of any other Man but iiim I have trufted ^ but I have
fuch proofs of their faith, as cannot deceive me.
Fre^. Cannot !

Man. Not, but I know, that generally, no man can be a great Enemy, but
ander the name of Friend y and if you are a Cuckold, it is your Friend only
that makes you fo •, for your Enemy is not admitted to your houfc : if you
are cheated ia your fortune, 'tis your Friend that does it j for your Enemy
is not. made your Truftee: if your Honour, or Good name be injur'd, 'tis
your Friend that does it ftill, becaufeyour Enemy is not believ'd againft you.
Therefore I rather chufe to go where honeft, down-right Barbarity is pro-
ffifl", where men devour one another like generous hungry Lions and Tygers,
not like Crocodiles ^ where they think the Devil white, of our complexion,
sad J asa already fo far an IndUm but if your weak faith doubts this

miracle



THE PLAIN-DEALDR. 13

aairade of a Woman, come along with me, and believe, and thoa wilt find her
To bandfom, thas thou who art Co much my Friend, mil have a mind to lie
with her, and fo wik not fail to difcover what her Faith and thine is to me.

When we're m Love, the great j4dverfty^
Our Friends and Miflrejfes at onee we try.



Finis Adlus Primi.



ACT II. SCENE L

Olivia's Lodging*
Enter Olivia, Eliza, Lettice.

Oliv. \ H Coufin what a World 'tis we live in ! I am Co weary of it.

jfX ^^'^' Truly, Coufin, I can find no fault with it, but that we
cannot always live in't ; for I can never be weary of it.

Oliv. O hideous ! you cannot be in earneft fure, when you fay you like
the filthy World.
£/k, You cannot be in earneft fure, when you fay you diflike if,
Oliv. You are a very cenforious Creature, 1 find.
EUz.. I muft confefs I think we Women as often difcover where w^ love
by railing •, as men when diey lye, by their fwearing ; and the World is but
a conftant keeping Gallant, whom we fail not to quarrel with, when-^ny
thing erofles us, yet cannot part with't for our hearts.

Lett. A Gailaat indeed. Madam, whom Ladies firft make jealous, and then
quarrel with ic for being fo j for if, by her dircretion,a Lady be talk'd of for
aMan,^ (he cries prefentiy, ^Tis a Cenforious World i if, by her vanity, the
Intrigue be found out, 'TfV a prying tnalicio^ts World ^ and if, by her over-fond=
nefs, the Gallant proves unconftanf, ^Tis afalfe World ; and if., by her nigard-
linefsj the Chamber-maid tslis, "^Tis a perfideoHs World: hut that, Pm fure,
your Ladvfnip cannot i^y of the World yet, as bad as 'tis.

Oliv. But I may fay, ^Tis a very impertifient World. Hold your peace.
And, Couiin, if the World be a Gallant, 'tisfuch an one as is my averfion.
Pray name it no niore.

Eliz.. But is it pofiible the World, which has fuch variety cf Charms for

other Wosien, can have none for you ? Lei's fee -Efil, what d'ye think

GrDreiTing and fine Gloaths?

Oliv. DreiBog ! Fie, fie, 'tis niy averf^oa. Bur, come hither, you Dowdy ^
meihinks you might have open'd this loure better : O hideous ! I cannot
fuffer \i ! d'ye fee how't fits ?

Elix., Weil enough, Coufin, ifDrefiing be your averfion.
Oltv. 'Tis fo : and for variety of rich Cloaths, tney are more ray averdon.
Lett. Ay, 'tis becaufe your Ladyfhip wears 'em too long ^ for indeed a
Gown, like a Gallant, grows one's averfion, by having too much of it.

- ' Oliv.



14 T HE F LAIN'D E ALER.

Olit). infatiable Creature! I'ii be fworn Ihave had this not above three
days Coufin> and within this month have made feme iix more.
Eliz,. Then your averfion to 'em is not altogether fo great.
Olivl Alas ! 'tis for my Woman only I wear 'cm, Coufin.
Let'. If it be for me only, Madam, pray do not wear 'em.

ElU. But what d'ye think of Vifics Balls •

Oliv. O, I deleft 'em.

Eliz.. Of Playes.

O/tx'. I abominate 'cm : filthy, obfcene, hideous things.

Eliz.. What fay you to M^ff^eradina m the Winter, and Hide-Parkm

the Summer ?

Oliv. InHpid pkafures Itafte not.

Eliz,. Nay, if you are for more folid Pleafures, what think you of a rich
young Husband ?

Oliv. O horrid! Marriage! what a Pleafure you have found out! I nau-
feate it of all things.

Let. But what docs your Lady (hip think then of a libera], handfome,
young Lover?

Oliv. A handfom, young Fellow, yen Impudent •' Begone, out of my
fight", name a handfom young Fellow to cne ! Fob, a hideous handfom young
Fellow I abominate. , ZSpits,

Eliz. Indeed-' But let's fee — will nothing pleafe you .^ what d'ye

think of the Court?

Oliv. How/ ths Court ! the Court, Coufin! my averfion, iby averfion,
my averfion of al! averfions.

Eliz,. How i* the Court! where-—

Oliv. Where Sincerity is a qualicy as out of fafhion, and as unprofperous,
as Bafhfulnefs ; I cou'u not laugh at a Quibble, tho' it were a fat Privy
Councelior's j nor praife a Lord's ill Verfes, tho' I were my felf the Subjed;
nor an old Lady's young looks, the' 1 were her Woman; nor fit to a vain
young Simle- maker., tho' he flatter'd me j in fliorr, I cou'd not glote upon a
man when he comes into a Room, and laugh at him when he goes out ; I
cannot rail at the abfent, to flatter the ftandersby, I- —

EIjz.. Well, but railing now is fo common, that 'tis no more Malice, bu4
the falhion ^ and the abfent think they are no more the worfe for being
rail'd at, than the prefent think they're the better for l)eing flatter'd : and
ior the Court^ — — —

Oliv. Nay, do not defend the Court •, for yi^'ll make me rail at it, like
a trufting Citizen's Widow.

Eliz. Or liks a /:/o/W»-Lady, who cou'd not get into the Isft Ball, cr was
out of countenance in the Drawing-room the lafc Sirnday of her appearance
there-, for none rail at the Court, bus thofe who cannct get into k., or elfe
who are ridiculous when they are there ^ and 1 fiiall fufpvd you were laugh'd
at, when you w;.re laft there^ or wcu'd be a Maid of Honour.

Oliv. I a' Maid of Honoiir! To be a Maid of Honour were yet of all
things my averfion.

£/'2:. 'Iq what feore. am I to underftand you! But, in fine, by the Word
Averlion, Vm Sure you diiTembic-, fori mvtt knew Woman yet thatus'd



THE PLAIN-DEALVR. 15

it, who did not. Came, our tongues bely our hearts, mors than our Pocket -
glades do our faces j but methinks v/e oiigh*; to leave ofFdifTembling, fines
'lis grosvn of no ufe to us ; for all wife obfervers underltapd us now a- days,
as they do dreams. Almanacks, and Dutch Gaz,Hies^ by the coiur.- ry : And,
a Man no more believes a Woman, when (he fays fhe has an Averfion for
him, than when (he fays fhe'll cry our.

OUv. O filthy, hideous ! Peace, Ccufin, or your difcourfo wjli be rny
Averlion ^ and you may believe me.

Eliz, Yes^ for, if any thing be a Woman's Averfion, '*i\sTlain^ dealing'
from another Woman: and perhaps that's your quarrel to the World 5
for that will talk, as- your Woman fays.

OUv. Talk, not of me fure j for what Men do I converfe with ? what
Vifits do I admit ?

Enter Boy,
Boy. Here's the Gentleman to wait upon you, Madam*.
Oli'v, On me ! you little, unthinking Fop, d'ye know what you fay ?

Boy, Yes, Madan^, 'tis the Gentleman that comes every day to you, who ■

OUv. Hold your peace, you heedlefs little Animal, and get you gone.

This Country Boy, Coufin, takes my Dancing- Matter, Taylor, or the

fpruce Millener, for Vifiters. " \_Exit Boy.

Let, No, Madam, 'tis Mr Novell I'm fure, by his talking fo loud : I

know his voice too, Madam.

OUv, You know nothing, ycu Buffle-beaded, ttupid Creature you j you
wou'd make my Coufin btlieve 1 receive Vifits : But if it be Mr.—— what
did you call him ?

Lit. Mr iVow/, Madam, he that

Ol'tv, Hold your peace, I'll hear no more of him-, but if it be your Mr.—-
(I can't think of his name again} I fuppofe he has follow'd my Coafiri hither.
EUz.. No, CoufiQ, 1 will not rob you of the Honour of the Vifit : 'tis
to you, Coufin, for I know hininos.

OUv. Nor did I ever hear of him before, upon my Honour, Coufin •, be=
fides, han't I told you, that Vifits, and the bufinefs of Vifits, Flattery, and^
Detradion, are my Averfion ? D'ye think then I wou'd admit fuch a Cox-
comb as he is/' who, rather than not rail, will rail at the dead, whom none
fpeak ill of ^ and rather than not flatter, will flatter the Poets of the Age^
whom none will flatter-, who afii'edts Noyelty as much as the Fafhion'j and
is asfanftatical as changeable^ and as well known as the Fafhion ^ who likes
nothing, but what is new, nay, wou'd chufe to have his Friend, or his
Title, a new one. In fine, he is my Averfion*
EUz.. I find you do know him, Coufin j atleaH, have heard of him.
OUv. Yes, now I remember, 1 have heard of him,
Elfz., Well}^ but finee he is fuch a Coxcomb, for Heaven's fake, let him
not come up; tell him, Mrs. Lettice, your Lady is not within.

Oliv. No, Lettice^ tell him, my Coufin is here, and that he may come up :
for notwithftanding I deleft the fight of him, you may like hisconverfationi
andtho'l wou'd ufc him fcurvily, I will not be rude to you, in my own
Lodging y fince he has foUow'd you hither^ let him come np, I fay.

'" ' ' ^ Elisi,



i^ THE PI AIN-V BALER.

EUz,, Very fine! Pray let him go to the Devil, I fay, for me: I know
him not, nor defire it. Sead hira away, Mrs. Lmice.

Oliv. Upon my word, (he fhan'6 : I roufl: difobey your Commands, to
comply with your delires, call him up, Lettice.

Eliz.. Nay, PI! fwear (lie ftiall not ftir on that Errand. [^HoU s Ltttict,
Oliv. Wei), then, Til call hira ray felf for you, fince you will have it fo.
Mr. NovcL [Calls out at the door~\ Sir, Sir.

Enter Novel.

Novel. Madam, I beg your pardon, perhaps you were bufic : I did not
think you had company with you.

£/«;?„ Yet he comes to mei Coulia ! [^Jf'de,

0//t;.^>_-Chairs there. [1 hey fit,

Nov, Well^ but. Madam, d'ye know whence I come now ?

Oliv. From fome melancholly place 1 warrant, Sir, fines they have loft
your good company.

Eliz.. So.

Nov. From a Place, where they have treated me, at .dinner, wi:h fo
much civility and kindnefs, a pox on 'em, that I cou'd hardly get away to
you, dear Madam.

O/zV. You have a' way with you fo new, and obliging. Sir.

Eliz,» You hate Flattery, Coufin ! [Jpart to Olivia.

Nov, Nay faith. Madam, d'ye think my way new ? then you are obli-
ging. Madam. I muft confefs, I hate imitation, to do any thing like other
people: all that know me, dome the Honour to fay, lam an original,
Faith ^ but as I was faying, Madam, I have been treated to day, with all
the ceremony and kindnefs imaginable, at my Lady Antums'^ but the nau-
feous old Woman at the upper end of her Table— ^

Oliv. Revives the old Grecian Guftom, of ferving in a Deaths-head with
their Banquets.

Nov. Ha! ha! fine, juft i'faith •, nay, and new: 'tis like eating with
the Ghoft in the Libertine ^ (he wou'd frighten a Man from her dinner, with
her hollow invitation, and fpoil one's ftomach.

O/i-y.. To Meat or Women. I deteft her hollow Cherry- cheeks ^ Ihe
looks like an old Coach new painted : afFeding an unfeemly fmugnefs,
whil'ft (he is ready to drop in pieces.

Eliz.. You hate Detradtion I fee, Coufin I [^j^fart to Olivia.

Nov, But the filly old Fury, whilft fhe afFeiJs to look like a Woman of
this Age, talks ^ — ' — -

Oliv. Like one of the laft ^ and as palllonately as an old Courtier, who
has out-liv'd his Office.

Nov. Yes, Madam ; but pray let me give you her Charadler. Then {he
never counts hsr age by the years, but

Oliv. By the MafqUes Ihe has liv'd to fee.

Nov. Nay then. Madam, 1 fee you think a little harmlefs railing too
jgreat a pleafure for any but your feif, and therefore I've done.

Oliv. Nay, faith, you (hall tell me who you had there at dinner.

Nov, If you wou'd hear me. Madam.

Oliv,



THE PLAIN-DEALER. rf

'Oliv. Mofb patiently : fpeak, ^Ir.

Nov, Then, we had her Daughter —

Oliv. Ay, her Dai^hter, the very difgrace to good cloath?, which (he al-
ways wears, but to nsighten her deformity, r.cc niend in ; for flie is ilili
molt fplendidly, gallantly ugly, and looks, like an ill piece of daubing in a
rich Fram.f. . - .

Nov. Sq- But have you done with her. Madam- ? and can you fpare
her to me a litile now ?

OFtv. Ay, ay. Sir.

Nov. Then, ftie is like-



Oliv, She is you'd fay, like a Ci£y Bride,, the greater Fortune, but not
the greater Beauty for her drefs.

Nov. Well : v^^ l^^ve you done. Madam ? Then fhe — —

Oliv. Then (he bellows as unfortunately on her Face, all the graces iQ
fafhion, as the langui(hing eye, the hanging or pouting Up ^ but as the
Fool is never more provoking, than when he aims at Wir, the ill-favour'd of
our Sex are never more naufet)us than when they wou'd be Beauties, adding
to their natural deformity, the artificial uglinefs of afFedation.

Eliz.. So, Coufin, 1 find one may have a colkdtion of all ones acqiiain-
tances Pidlures as well at your houfe, as at Mr. Le//s ; only the difference
is, there we find 'em much handfomer than they are, and like ^ here much
uglier, and like : and you are the firft of the profellion of Pidure-drawing
1 ever knew without flattery.

Oliv. I draw after the life ; do no body wrong, Coufin.

Eliz.. No, you hate flattery and detraction !

OUv. But, Mr. Novel, who had you belides at dinner ?

Npv» Nay, the Devil take me if I tell you, unlefs you will allow me the
priviledge of railing in my turny but, now 1 thick on't, the Women ought
to be your Province, as the men are mine: and you muit know we had him
whom -" — '^

Oliv. Him, whom"-

Nov. What, invading me already .'* And giving the character, before
you know the Man ?
-Eliz.. No, that is not fair, tho' it be ufual.

Oliv. I beg your pardon, Mr. Novel^ pray go on.

Nov. Then, I fay, we had that famjliar Coxcomb, who is at home where-
foe'er he comes.

Oliv, Ay, that Fool — —

Nov. Nay, then Madam, your Servant : I'm gone. Taking a Fool out
of ones mouth, is worfe than taking the Bread out of ones mouth. ■

Oli^. I've done, your pardon, Mr. Novel., pray proceed.

Nov. 1 fay, the Rogue, that he may ,be the only Wis in company, will
let no Body elfe talk, and -

Oliv. Ay, thofe Fops who love to talk all themfelves, are of all things
my Averfion.

Nov. Then you'll let me fpeak, Madam, fure, The Rogue, I fay, will
force his jeft upon youj and I hate a jelt that's forc'4 upon a Man, as much
a^aGlafs. D - Eliz..



i8 THE PLAIN-DEALER.

Elix,. Why, I hope, Sir, he does not exped a man of your temperance
in jeding fhouM do him reafon ?
Nov. What, interruption from this fide too ! I muft then-

{Ojfers to rijef Olivia Holds him,
OUtj. No, Sir,— You mull know, Coufin, that Fop he means, tho' he
talks only to be commended, will not give you leave to do't.

N'ov. But, Madam •

Oliv. He a Wit •' hang him, he*s only an Adopter of ftragliog Jefts,
and faiherlefs Lampoons', by the credit of which, he eats at good Tables^
and ib like the barren Beggar- Woman lives by borrow'd Children.

Nov. Madam

OUv. And never was Author of any thing, but his news ^ but that is
{till all his own.

Nov. Madam, pray

Oliv. An eternal Babler ; and makes no more ufe of his ears, than a
Man that fits ai: a Play by his Miilrefs, or in Fop-corner : he'*s, in fine, a
bafe detrading Fellow, and is my averfion. But whoelfe pry thee, Mr.iVo-
w/, was there with you ^ Nay, you (han'i: ftir.

Nov. 1 beg your pardon. Madam, 1 cannot ftay in any place, where I'm
not aliow'd a little Ghriftian liberty of railing.

Oliv. Nay, prithee, Mr. Novel.^ ftay •, and tho' you fliou'd rail at me, I
wou'd hear you with patience ; prythee who elfe was there with you ?
Nov, Your Servant, Madam* '

Oliv. Nay, prythee tell us, Mr. Novel, prythee do.
Nov. We had no body elfe.
OUv. Nay, faith 1 know you had. Come, my Lord Tlaufible was there

too, who is, Coufin, a-

EltTi, You need not cell me what he is, Coufin ; for I know, him to be a
* civil, good natur'd, harmlefs Gentleman, that/peaks well of all the World,

and is always in good humour, and

OUv. Hold, Coulin, hold, 1 hate detraction ; but Imuft tell you, Coufin
his civility is cowardife \ his good nature, want of wit; and he has neither
courage nor ftnce to rail: And for his being always in humour, 'tis becaufe
he is never diflatisfi'd withhimfeif: In fine, he is ray averfion j and 1 never
admit his Vifits beyond my Hail.

Nov. No^ he vifii you ] Dam him, cringing, grinning, Rogue; iflfhould
fee him coming up to yop, I wou'd make bold to kick him down aeaia.

Ha!- ^

Enter my, Lord Plaufible. '

My dear Lord, your moll humble Servant.

\_M[e$.^ and {dates Plaufible, and kijfes him.

Eliz.. So, I find kiding and railing fucceed each other with the angry Men,

ss well as with rhe angry Women -., and their quarrels are like Love-quarrels,

lines abfeoce is ibc only caufe. of ihem ;, for as foon as the Man appears al

" gain, thev are over. Jii^'ide,

L. PLwf. Your moH faithful, humble Servant, generous Mr. Novel -.^ and

Madam, i am your eternal Slave, andkifs your fair hands j which I had done

fooncr-



THR FLAIN-D BALER. %»

fooner, according to your commands, but ~-

Oliv. No excufes, my Lord.

EliK.. What, you Tent for him then, Con fin ? > £Jp.m.

■ Nov. Ha! invited! ^J/ide,

Oliv. I know you muR divide your felf j fcr your good company is too
general a good, to be engrofs'd^by any^ particular Friend,

L, I'lanf. O Lord, Madam, my company ! your molt obliged, faithftil,
humble Servsnt •, but I cou'd have brought you good comparfy i^ndeed, for
1 parted at your door, with two of the worchieit, braveO: Men^ —

OUv. Who were they, my Lord ?

Nov. Who do you call the worthieft? braveft msn? pray ?

L. Flauf. O the wifeil, braveft Gentlemen ! Msa of fudi Honour, and
Vertue! of fuch good qualities .' ah — - —

Eliz., This is a Coxcomb, Jhal fpeaks ill of ai! people a different way,
and libels every body with dull praife, and commonly in the wroDg place,
{o makes his Paaegyricks abufive Lampoons. {^Afids.

Oliv. But pray let me know who they were.

L. PUuf. Ah ! fach patterns of Heroick Vertue •' fuch— — ^-
> Nov. Well but who the Devil were they ?

L. TUuf. The Honour of our Nation, the glory of our Age, ah ! I
" couM dwell a Twelvemonth 00 their praife; which indeed I might fparc
by telling their Names : Sir John Current^ and Sir Richard Court-Title.

Nov. Comt'Tttle ! Ha, ha.

Oliv. And Sir John Current ! Why will you keep fuch a Wretch com-
pany, my Lord } ' ^

L. Plauf. Oh, Madam, ferfoufly you are a little too fevere, for he is a
Man of unqueftion'd reputation in every thing,

Oliv. Yes, becaufe he endeavours only with the Women, to pafs for a
Man of Courage; and with the Builits, for a Wit; with the Wits, for a
Man of bufinefs ; and with the Men of bufinefs, for a Favourite at Court:
and at Court, for good City- fecurity.

Nov. And for Sir Richard.^ he—

L' Plmf. He loves your choice, pick'd company ; perfons that

Oliv, He loves a Lordindeed ; but- •

Nov. Pray, dear Madam, let me iiave but a bold llroke or two at his
vPifture. He loves a Lord, as you fay, tho — ^

Oliv, Tho' he borrow'd his Money, and ne'er paid him again.

Nov. And wou'd befpeak a place three days before at ^he back-end of a
Lords Coach, to Htde.yark,

L. Plauf. Nay, i'faiih, i'faith, you are both too fevere.

OUv. Then, to (hew yet more his paflion for quality, he makes love to
that fulfom Coach-load of Honour, my Lady Goodly ; for he is always at
her Lodging.

L. Plan/, Becaufe it is the Conventicle-Gallant, the Meeting-houfe of all
the fair Ladies, and glorious Superfine Beauties of the Town.

Nov. Very fine Ladies ■' there's firft "

Oliv, Her Honour, as fat asan Hoftefs.



20 THE PLAIN-BEALER.

L. PUitf. She is fomelhing plump indeed,a goodly, comely^graceful perfon.

Nov. Then there's ray Lady Fr^wej^ what d'ye call'er ? ugly

OU-v. As a Citizens lawfully begotten "Daughter.

L, Flaaf. She has wit in abundance ^ and the haadfomeft heel, elbow, and
tip of an ear, you ever faw.

Nov. Heel, and elbow •' ha, ha ! And there's my Lady Betty youlcnow— •
Oliv. As flutdlh, and flatternly, as aa Irijij Woman bred in France.
L. Plaiif.Ahy all (he has hangs wiih a loofe Air indeed, and becoming
negligence.

£liz.. You fee all faults with Lovers eyes, I find, my Lord.
L. Platif. Ah, Madam, your moft obliged, ' faithful, humble Servant to com-
mand ! But you can fay nothing fure againft the Superfine Mifbrefs— —

Oliv. I know v»?ho you mean. She is as cenforious and detrading a Jade,
as a fuperannnsted Sinner.

L. P.lanf. She lias a Unarc way. of Railery, 'tis confvil.
Nov. And then, for^iMrs. Grideline,

L.^PUm/. She I'm fure is ^ ■

Oliv, One that never fpoks ill of any body, 'tis confeil ; for Ihe is as filenS
in converfation as a Country. Lover, and no better company than a Clock,, or
a.Weather-glafs^ for if fhe founds, 'tis but once an hour, to put you in mind
of the time of day, or tell you 'twill be cold or hot, rain or fnow.
X. Plaftf. Ah, poor Creature •' (he's extrearaly good and modeft.
Nov. And for Mrs. Bridlechin., /he's — —
Oliv. As proud as a Churchman's Wife.

L. Plmf. She's a Woman of great fpirit and honour, and will not make
her feif cheap, 'ds true.

Nov. Then Mrs. Hoyden^ that calls all people by their Sirnames, and is- —
Oi^x/. As familiar a Duck- — ~ .

Nov. AsandAdrefs in the Tyring; room. There I was once before-hand
with ycu, -Madam.

L^PlaiiJ. Mrs. Hoyden \ spoor, affable, good- natur'd Soul : Bui the Di- .
vine Mrs. tfiflsj comes thither too : fure her beauty, vertue, and conduft,
you can fay nothing to ?

Oliv. No/ ■ -• ' ,

-Nov, No •'■ -pray i&. me fpeak, Madam.

Oliv. Firil, can any- one be cali'd beautiful that fquintsf
L. Plmf. Her eyes languiih a little, I own. - .

Nov. Langulfn •' ha, ha. .

Oliv. Languifh ! Then, for her conduct, fhe was feen at the Country,
Wife, after the firft day. There's for you, my Lord.

L. PUuf Bar, Madam, fhe was not feen to ufe her Fan all the Play long,

turn aiide her head, or by a confcious bluih, difcover more guill tfian modefty.

Oliv. Very fine .' then ycu think a Woman modefl, that fees the hide-

.ous Conmry^Wife^ without blufhing, or publifhing her deteftation of it ?

D'ye hear him, Goufin ?

Eliz.. Yes-, and ara, I mull confefs, fomething of his opinion, and think,
that as an ever-captious Fool as a Play, by endeavouring to fhew the Au-

rhnr's



THE PLAIN-DEALE R. 21

thors want of Wit, expofes his own to more cenfure : fo may a Lady call
her own modefty In queilion, by p'jblickly cEvilling with the Poets j for
all thofe grimaces of honour, and artificial modefty, difpsrsge a Woman^s
'^ real Vertue, as much as the ufe of white arid red does the natural com-
plexion i and you niuft ufe very, very little, if you wouM have it thought
your own. _

Oliv. Then you wou'd have a Woman of Honour mih paOive looks, i:arsj
and tongue, undergo all the hideous obfcenity (he hears at nafty Plays ~<

Eliz., Truly I think a Woman bstrays her want of modefry, by fnewiog
it publickly in a Play-houfe, as much ss a Man does his want of courage by
a quarrel there^ for the truly modelt and flout fay kafc, and are kaft
excepiious, efpecJally in publick.

Oliv. O hideous! Goufin, this cannot be your opinion •, but you are ons
of thofe who have the confidence to p:irdon the filthy Play. . .

Eliz.. Why, what is there of ill iii'f, fay you ?

Oliv. O fy, fy, fy, wouM you put me to the bluni anew ? call all the
blood into my face again ? But to fatisfis you then, firfl: the clandeftine ob-
fcenity in the very name of /^/o^'wf J'.

Eliz. Truly, 'tis fo hidden, I cannot find it out, I confefs.

Oliv. O horrid ! does it not give you the rank concepiion, or image of
a Goat, or Town-Bull, or a Satyr? nay, what is yet a filthier image than
all the reft, that of an Eunuch ?

Eliz,. What then ? 1 can think of a Goat, a Bull, or Satyr, without any hurt.

Oliv. ], but, Goufin, one cannot flop there.

EJiz.. 1 can, Coulln.

Oliv, O no j for when you have thofe filthy creatures in your head once,
the next thing you think, is what they do ^ as their defiling of honeflMens
Beds and Couches, Rapes upon fleeping and waking Country- Virgins, un-
der Hedges and on Haycocks : nay, further- ^

Eliz.. Nay; no fafther, Goufin, we have enough of your Comment on
the Play, which will make you more afham'd than the Play it felf.

Oliv._ O, believe me, 'tis a filthy Play, and you may take my word for
a filthy Play, as foon ss aacthcrs ^ but the filthieft thing inihsj Play, or any
other Play, is — ■— — . , .

Eliz.. Pray keep it to your felf, if it be fo.

Oliv. No, faith, youfhall know it, I'm refolvM to make you out of love
with the Play, 1 fay, the lewdeft, fikhiell: thing, is his China -^ nay, I will
never forget the beallly Author his China : he has quite taken away the re-
putation of poor Chma it felf, and fullyM the molt innocent and pretty
Furniture of a Ladies Chamber, infomuch that I was fain to break all my de-
fil'd Velfek.' You fee I have none left^ nor you, I hope.

Eliz.. You'll pardon me, I cannot think the worfe of myCbina^ for that
of the Play-houfe.

Oliv. Why, you will not keep any now furc; ! 'tis now as unfit an orna-
ment for a Ladies Chamber, as thePidures that come from Italy^ and other
hot Countries, as appears by their nudities, which 1 always cover, or tcratch
out, wherefoe're I find 'em. But China I out upon' t, filthy Chmay nafty,
debauch'd China ! " f //&.



^s THE P LAIN^D E ALER.

£Uz.i Aill this will not pus me ont of conceit with China^ nor the Play,
which is Aded to day, or another of the fame beaflty Author's, as you call
him, which rU go fee.

Qliv. You will aos fure! nay, you (ha' r.ot venture your reputation by
going* and mine by leaving m~u aloiic with two men here : nay, you'll dif-
oblip;e me for ever, if — ^ — ■ — {^Pdls her bach

£lz.. I ftay !— ycur Servant. -' • > \^Exit Eliza.

OUv. WelJ-- "but, my Lord, tho' you jiiftiEe every body, you cannot in

earfieft uphold fobeaftly a Writer, whofs Ink isfo fmutty, as one may fay.

/.. Plauf. Faith, I dare fwear the poor man did not think to difoblige
the Ladies, by any amorous, fofc, -pairionate, iufcious faying in his Play.

OUv. Fy, my Lord^ but v^ha? thiok yon, Mr. Novel^ of the Play? tho'
I know you area Friend to all that are new. \

Nov. Faith, Madam, I mult confefs> the new Plays wou'd not be the worfe
for ray advice, but Icou'd never get the filjy Rogues, the Poets, to mind what
1 fay ^ but Til teil yon what counfel I gave the furiy Fool you fpake of.

OUv. What was't ?

Nov. Faith, to put this Play in Rithrae ^ "for Rithme, you know ofcen
makes myftical Nonfence pafs with the Criticks for Wit, and a double
meaningfaying with the Ladies, for fofr, tender, and moving PalTion. But

now I talk of pafiion, I faw your old Lover this morning Captain-

{Whif^ers,
Enter Captain Manly, Freeman and Fidelia ftandinghthivd.

OUv. Whom ?^^ nay, you need not whifpsr.

Mm. We are luckily got hither unobferv'd :— How! in a clofe conver-
fation with thefe fupple Rafcals, the Out-cafts of Seropftrelfes Ihops ?

Free. Faith, pardon her, Captaio, that fince Ihe cou'd no longer be en-
tertain'd with your manly bluntnefs, and honeft Love, fhc takes up with
the pert chat and common-place flattery of thefe fluttering Parrots of the
Town, Apes and Ecchoes of Men only.

Mm. Do not you. Sir, play the Eccho tooj mock me, dally with my own
words, and (hew your felf as impertinent as they are.

Free. Nay, Captain — --- —

Fid. Nay, Lieutenant, do not excufe her, methinks (he looks very kind-
ly upon 'cm both, and feems to^be pleas'd with what that Fool there fays to
her.

Mm. You lye, Sir, and hold your peace, that I may not be provok'd to
give you a worfe reply.

OUv. MmlyTctnTii^d^ d'ye fay ! And is he fafc?

{Whiff ers to Plaufiblc.

Man. She yet fcems concerned for my fafety, and perhaps they are ad-
mitted now here but for their news of me v far intelligence indeed is the
common Pafsport of naufeous Fools, when they go their round of good
Tables and Houfes. {Afide.

OUv. I heard of his fighting only, without particulars, and confefs I al-
ways lov'd hisB ratal Courage, bscaufe it made me hope it might rid mc of

his



THE PLAIN-VBALKR. ' 23

his moi^s Brutal Love. '

Man. What's that? ^J^pan.

Oliv. Bui is he at iall return'd, d'ye fay, unhurt /"
Nov, Ay faith,wi-thout doing bis bufinefs ; for the Rogue has been thefe two
years pretending to a v¥ood-n Leg, which he wcuM take from Fortune^ as
kindly as the Staff©!' a /Vhr^id ot F>-^?/ce, apcl rather read his Name in a Gaz,et,

Oliv. Than in she Entail of a good Eilate.

Man^ So!- \_Afide.

Nov. I have an Ambition, I miifl: coafefs, of lofing my hearty before fuch'
a fair Enemy ns your felf, Madam, but that fiUy Rogues Ihou'd be ambits-

ous of lofiiig thsir Arms, and

^ Oliv. Looking like a pair of CompalTes.

Nov. But he has no ufe of his Arms, but to fet 'era on Kimbow, for lie
never pulls off his Hat, at kail not to me, I'm fure^ for. you mult knowj
Madam, he has a fajicaltical hatred to good Company: he can's abide me.

L. Plan/. O, be not fo fevere to him, as to fay he hates good Company j
for I affure you, he has a great rcfpeft, efteem and kindnefs for me.

Mtfi- That kind, civil Rogue has fpoken yet £en thoufand times worfe of
me, than t'other.

Oliv. Well, if he be return'd, Mr. Novel., then fhsll I be pefter'd agam:
with his boifterous Sea-Love ^ have my Alcove fmell like a Cabin, my
Chamber perfumed with his Tarpaulin Brandenburgh, and hear Vollies of
Brandy fighs, enough to make a Fog in ones Room. Foh ' 1 hate a Lover
that fmells like r/7^wei-j?reef.

Man. I can bear no longer, and need hear r/o more. - {^Afide.

But, fmce you have thefe two Pulviilio Boxes, thefe Eflence Bottles, this
pair of Musk Cats here, I hope, i may venture to come yet nearer you.

Oliv. Over-heard us then .''

Nov. I hope he heard me not. \^j4fde..

L. Plauf. Molt noble and Heroick Csptgin, your moH oblig'd, faithful,
humble Servant.

iVo-y." Dear Tar, thy humble Servant.

Man. Away ^ Madam- — —

O/i-y. Nay, 1 think I have fitted ycu for liUning.

[Thrnjis Novel and PJaufible on ta(;h fide.

Man* You have fitted me, for believing you couM not be fickle, tho' you
were young j coa'd not dlfTemble Love, tho' 'twas your intereft^ nor be
vain, tho* you v.7ere handfom-, nor break your promifs, ch6' to a parting
Lover*, nor abufe your bell Friend, tho' you had Wit : but Itake not your
contempt of me worfe, than your efceem, or civility of thefe things here,
tho' you know 'em.

,Nov. Things.^ » , .

Z.. f/^w/. Let the Captain Railly a little.

Man. Yes, things ^ canft thou be angry, thou thing ?

[Coming up to Novel.

Nov. No, lince my Lord fays you fpeak in Raillery ^ for though your Sea-
raillery bs fomething rough, yet I confefs, we ufc one another to as bad every

dav*



24. T IJE P L AIN-D EALER.

da/, at Lockits^ and never qaarrel for the matter.

L^ Pimf. Nay, noble Captain, be not angry wuh him: a word with you,
I befeech vou— [V/hifp. to Manly. ,

■Qliv. Weil, ws Woman, like the reft of th: Cheatsofthe World, when
our Culiies or Creditors have found us out, and will, or can truil no longer,
pay Debt«, and Tatisfie Obligations, with a quarrel, the kindell Prefent a
Man can make to his Miilrefs, when he can make no more Prefents: for
oftentiiues in Love, as at Cards, we were forc'd to Play foul, only ta give
over the game; and ufe our Lovers like the Cards, when ws can get no more
by'eni, -throw'em up in a per, upon the lirft difpute. \iAfide.

Miin. My Lord, all EhaC you have made ras know by yoar whifpering,
which I knew not before, b, tha£ you have a ilinking breath, there's a fe-
cret, for your fecret.

L.Plauf Pfhaw ! Plhaw ! - ,

Man. Bur, Madam, tell me, pray, what was't, about this Spark, cou'd
take you ? was it the merit of his fafhionable Impudence, .the brisknefs of his
noif;:-, the wit of his laugh, his Jadgoient : or fancy in his garniture? or was
it a well-trim'd Glove, or the Scent of it that charni'd you?

Nov. Very weD, Sif, *g3d thefe Sea Captains make nothing of dreffing :
but let me tell you, Sir, a man by his dreft, as much as by any thing, fiiews
his wit and jadgmeni, nay, and his courage too.

Free. How, his courage, Mr. Novel!' '.. -

Nov. Why, for example, by red breeches, tuck'd up Hair and Perruke, a ■
_ greslie Broad-Belt, and now adays a fhott Sword.

Man. Thy courage, will appear more by thy Belt, than thy Sword, I dare
fwear. Then, Madam, for this gentle piece of courtejie, this man of tame
Honour, what cou'd yon find in him .'' was it his languifning afFedtedj tone ?
his mannerjy look .<' his fecond-hand flattery? the refufe of the Play-houfe
tiring-rooms.'' or his flavifh obrequioufnefs, in watching at the door of your
Box at the Piay-haufs, for your hand to your Chair ? or his janty way of
playing with your Fan ? or was it the Gun-powder fpot on his hand, or the
Jewel in his ear, that parchas'd your Heart ?

0U%;. Good jealous Captain, no more of your > —

L. PUuf. No, let him go on. Madam, for perhaps he may make you
laugh': and I wou'd contribute to your pleafure any way.

.^^«.' Gentle Rogue-'

Oliv. No, noble Captain, you cannot fare think any thing cou'd take me
more than that heroick Titis of yours. Captain : for you know we Women
love honour inordinsteiy.

Nov. Ha, ha, faith fhe is with thee, Bully, for thy Railery.

Man, Faith fo fhall 1 be Vv'ith you, no Bully, for your grinning.

[^Afide to Novel.

Oliv. Then that noble Lyon-like meen of your<>, that Soldier-like weather-
beaten complexion, and that manly rcughnefs of your voice ^ how can they
otherwife than charm us Women, who hate Effeminacy !

Nov. Ha, ha! Faith I can't' hold from laughing.

i4^^;?. Nor Ihalll frpmkicking.anbn. C^/^e fo Novel.



THE PLAIN-DEALS R. 25

OUv. x4nd then, that Captain-liks carelefnefs in your drefs, botefp^cirjl-
ly your Scsrf ^ 'swas juit fuch another, only a link hk,ber ty'd, made ms in
love with niy Taylor as he paft by my Window rhe laft Traiains;- dzy^ for
we Womeii adore a Martial Man, and you have nothing wanting to make
you more one, or more agreeable, but a wooden Leg. '

L. Tlauf. Nay, i'faith, thej:e your Ladyfliip was a Wag, and it was fine,
juHr and well Raillf'd.

Nov, Ay, ay. Madam, with you Ladies too Martial Men rauil nseds
[?e very killing.

M&.n. Peace, you Bartholomew' Fair Bujfocns -^ and be not yon vain tirat
thefe hugh on your fide, for they wlSl laugh at cheir own duii j»lh j but no
more of 'cm, for I will only fulFcr now this Lady to be witty and merry,
Oltv. You won'd not bsve your Panegyrick inrerrupeed. i go on then
to your humor, h there any thing more agreeable, ihs'n she pretde
fclknnefs of that? then the greatnefs of your coorage? which mbit of all-
appears in your fpidt of contradidion, for ycu dare give all Mankind the
lye-, and your opinion is your only Mifcrefs, for you renounce that too,
vvhen it becoi^es another Mans.

Nov. Hah, hah! I cannot hold, I miiil laugh at thee Tar, faith!
L. Plauf, And i'faith, dear Captain, 1 beg your pardon, and leave to laugh
at you too, tho, 1 proteit I mean you no hurt ; but> when a Lady Raiilies, a
ftander by oiuft be cotnplaifanf, and do her reafon in laughing; Hah, ha.

Man. Why, you impudent, pitiful Wretches, you prefume fure upon
your Effeminacy to urge me ^ for you are in all things fo like Women, ihafi
you may think it in me a kind of Cowardife to beai you.

Oiiv. No Hedoring, good Captain.

Man. Or, perhaps, you think this Ladies prefence fecures you j but have
a care, fhe has talk'dher felf out of all the refpe(ft I had for her ^ and by u-
fing me ill before you, has given me a priviledge of ufing you fo before her ;
bui if you vvou'd preferve your refped to her, and not bs b^ten before
her, go, be gone immediately.

Nov. Begone.' what?

i. /'/^«/. Nay, worthy, noble, generous Captain.

Man. Be gone, I fay.

Nov. Be gone again ! to us be gone !

yl/<^;?. No chattering. Baboons, inftaatly bs gone. Or- —

CManly ^ms ''em out of the Room : Novel jirats^ Piaufibie cringes.

Nov. Well, Madam, we'll go make the Cards ready in your Bed-cham-
ber -.fure you will not ftay long with him. [Eat Plauf. Nav.

Oliv. Turn hither your rage, good Captain Swsgger-huS*, znd be fancy
with your Miftt efs, I'lk'^' a true Captain ^ but be civil to your Rivals and
Betters, and do net threaten any thing but me here-, no, not lo much as
my Windows, hor. do not Ehi?ik your felf in the Lodgings of one of your
Suburb-MiitreiTcs beyjjnd ths Tower^

Man. Do-nol give me canfe to think fo, for thofe kfs infamous Womea
part with their Lovers, juftas you did from me, with unforc'd vows of
coniancy, aqd floods of willing tears; bus the fame winds awsy their*
i^v , ■ ' E ' , Lovers.



2^ Tfi^ PLAIN'BBALER.

Lovers md tb-^Jr vows : And for their grief, ii the credulous uoexpeded
Fools return, they find new Comforters, frefli Cullies, fuch as I found here.
The siicrceoary love c^f thofe Women too foffers fhipwrack, with their Gal-
lants fortunes *, now vou have heard Chance has usM me fcurvily, therefore
you do £co. Weil, perlevere in your ingratitude, falfhood, and difdaia^
have conftancy in fomethiDg, and I promife you to be as juft to your real
Rem, Tis I was to your feiga'd lo\re: And henceforward will defpife, con-
temn, hace^ loath, and deteit you, laoft faithfully.

Enter Lettice. i

Oliv. GsE the Hombre-Cards ready in the next Room; Lettice^ and

ifVhifpers to Lettice.
Free. Bravv-ly reiblv'd, Captain.

Fici. And you'll be lure to keep your word, I hope, Sir f ■
Man. \ hope fo too.

Fid, Do you but hope it, Sir.^ if you are not as good as your word,
Hvvill be the firfl: time yoa ever brsg'd, fure.
M^n. She has reftor'd tny reafoa with my heart.
Free. But now you talk of reftoring. Captain, there are other things
v^hicb, next to one's heart, one wou'd not part with j I mean your Jewels
and Money, which it feems (lie has, Sir.
Mm, What's tha£ to you. Sir ?

Free. Pardon m^, whatfo&ver is yours, I have a fliare in't, Vm fure, which
I will not lofe for asking, tho' you may be too generous, or too angry now
todo'c your felf.

FU, Nay, then I'll make bold to make claim too.

\Both going towards Olivia.
Mm. Hold, you iaipertinent ofScious Fops ^
How have I been deceiv'd ! \iJfde.

Free. Madam, there are certain Appurtenances to a Lover's heart, call'd
Jewels, which always go sloog with is.

Fid. And which, vv' it h Lovers, have no value in themielj:cs, but from the



heart they corne wieh j our Captains, Madam, It feems yoiHcorn to keep,
and much more will thclc worthlefs things without it, 1 sm confident.

Oliv. A Ger.ticman fo well made as you are, may be coofideiici^-^us ea-
lie Women couM not deny you any thing you ask, if 'twere for your ieif-
but, fiicc 'lis for another, I beg your leave to give him my anfwer. (An a-
greeable young ftllow this !— — And ^vou'd not be my Aveifion !) \^Jjide''\
Cspcain, your young Friend here has a very perfwading Face, I conftfs ; yet
you might hrfv.e ask'd nie your felf for thofe Trifles you left wi^h me, which
(heark you a littk, for I c;are truft you with the fecret: you area Man of fo
much Honour I'm fure •,j 1 fay then, not ex peding your return* or hoping

ever to fee you again, 1 have ciellver'd your Jewels tc- -[^Apde to Man.

■ Man. Whom ? ■

Oliv. My Husband. -.^ ,

M^n. Your Husband ! ^~~~~^--^

Oliv. Ay, my Husband J for fince you couM leave ine, I am lately and
privately marry'd to one, who is a Man of io much Fionour and Experience



THE PLAIN-DEALDK. 27

in the World, that I dare not ask him for your Jewels again to reltore 'em
to you 5 left he Ihould conclude you never wou'd have parted wiih'em to me,
on any other fcore, bus the exchange of my Honour : which rather than
yoriM let ma lofe, you'd iofe Vm fure your f -If, thofs Trifles of yours.

Mmi> Triujriphsnt inip'jder^ce •' but married too !

Oliv. O, fpeak not (o loud, my Servants knov^ itYiot : 1 sra marry'd |
there's no reildiDg cot's Delliny, or Love, you know.

Man. Why did you love him too .^

Olh\ Moft paffionately ; nay, love him ecwj ,tho' I have marry'd him,

and he me : which mutual love, I hope you are too good, too generous a

Man to diilurb, by sny future claim, or vifiisto tns. 'Tis true, he is new

sbfeni in the Country, but returns iliortly, therefore i beg of you, for

,your own eafe and quiet, and my Honour, you will never fee me more.

Man. I wi{h I never had feen you. ,

Oliv. Bus if you fhou'd ever have any thing to fay to roe hereafter, let
IhaE young Gentleman there be your MefTenger. ^

Man. You wou'd be kinder to him : 1 find he fhou'd be welcome.

Oliv. Alas, his youth wou'd keep ray Husband from fufpicions, and his
vifits fromTcandal ^ for we Women may have pity for fuch as he, but no
love : And 1 already think you do not well to fpiris him away to Sea, and
the Sea is already but too rich with the fpoils of Ihe fhore.

Maff* True perfed Woman! If I cou'd fay any thing more injurious

to her now, 1 wou'd ^ for I cou'd out- rail a bilk'd Whore, or a kick'd Co-
ward : but, now I think on't, that were rather to difcover my love than
hatrec] i and i mull not talk-, for fomething I mult do. {^Jfide^

Oliv. I think I have given him enough of me now, never lobz troubled

with him again-- ^^ - l^ftde,

^ ^ -^ Enter Lcttice.

Well, LemVf, are the Cards and all ready within.^ I come £hen. Cap-
tain, I beg your pardon : You will not make one at Hombrs ?

Man. No, Madam, but I'll wifhr you a little good luck before you go.

Oliv. No, if you wou'd have me thrive, Curfe me ; for that you'll do
heartily, 1 foppofe.

Man, Then if you will have it fo, May all the curfes light upon you Wo-
men ought to fear, and you defsrve ^ flrft may the Curie of loving Play .
atfend your fordid Coveloufnefs, and Fortune cheat you, by trufting to
her, ss you have cheated me ^ the Curfe of Pride, or a good Repuration,
fall on your Lulls ^ the Curf^ of Affeftstion on your Beauty j the Curfe of
j/our Husband's company on your Piesfures^ and the Curfe of your Gal-
lants difappointmenSs in his abfence •, and the Cnri^ of fcorn, jsaloufie, or
dsfpsir, on your love : and then the Curfe of loving on.

Oliv. And to requite all your Curfes, I will only return you your lali:^ may
the Curfe of loving me ftilj,fal] upon your^roud hard Heart, that cou'd befo
cruel tome in thefe horrid Curfes : but heaven forgive you. {Exit 01i\^

^^?2. Hell and the Dsvil reward thee.

,Fne. Well, you fee now, Millrefres, like Friends? are loH by letting 'ern
handle your Money 5 and moft Women are fueh kind of Witches, who can

E 2 have



28 THE PLAIN-DEALER.

have no power over a Man, unlefs you glvQ 'em Money : but when once
they have got any from you, they never leave you till they have all : there-
fore I never dare give a Woman a farthing.

Man. Well, there is yet this comfort by iofing one's Money with one's
Miflrefs, a man is oui of danger of getting another .;, of being made prize
again by Love^ who like a Pirate, takes you by fpreading faife Colours:
but when once you have run ycur Ship aground, the treacherous Picaroon
loofs, fo by your ruine ycu fave your felf from flaveryai ieail.

Enter Boy.
Soy. Mrs. Lettice^ here's Madam BUck^cre come to wait upon her Ho-
nour.

Man. D'ye hear that -^ iet us be gone, before fhe comes •, for hence for-
ward i'il avoid the whole damn'd Sex for ever, and Woman as a (inking
Ship. lEx. Man. a^id Fid.

Free: And I'il flay to revenge on her your quarrel to the Sex ; for out
of love to her Jointure, and hatred to bufmefs, I wou'd marry her, to make
aa end of her thoufand Suits, and my thoufand Engagements, to the com-
fort of two unfortunate forls of psople^ my Plaintifs, and her Defen-
dants^ my Creditors, and her Adverfaries.

Enter Widow Biackacre led in by Major Oldfox, and Jerry Blackacre
following^ lad,en with grem Bags.
Wid. 'Tis an arrant Sea- Ruffian, but I'm glad I met with him at laft, to
ferve him again. Major, for the iaft fervice was not good in Law. Boy^
DHckj Jerry^ where is my Paper of Memorandnms ? give me. Child : fo.
Where is my Goufin Olivia^ now my kind Relation .?
Free. Here is one that wou'd be your kind Relation, Madam.
Wid. What mean you, Sir ?

Free. Why, faith, Ttobe fhort) to marry you, Widow.
Wid. Is not this the wild, rude perfon, we faw at Captain Manlf^ ?
Jer. Ay, forfooth, an't pkafe.

Wid. What wou'd voti ? vehat are you ? Marry me ! .
Free. Ay faiih, for I aUi a younger Brother, and you are a Widow.
V/id. You are an impertinent perfon, and go about your bufinefs.
Free. I have none, but to marry thee. Widow.
Wid, But 1 have other bulinefs I'd have you to know.
Free. But you have no bufineTs anights, Widow ^ and I'il make ycu plsa-
fanter bufinels than any you liave: for anights I allure you, lam a man of

great buflnefsj for the bufinefs '

""Wid. Go, I'm ftjre you're an idle Fellow.

Free. Try me but, Widow, and imploy me as ycu find my abilities,
andinduflry.

Old. Pray be civil to the Lady, Mr.— fhe is a perfon of Quality, a

psrfon thsl is no perfon — _

Fne. Yes, bui lie's a perfon that is a Widow : be yoii mannerly, to
hsr, becanfe you.are to pretend only to be her Squire, to arm her to her
Lawyers Chambers j but 1 will be impudent and bawdy, for Ihemiiftlovc
and marry me.

Wid^



THE PLAIN-SEALER. 2j?

IVid. Marry come up, you faucy familiar Jack,! You think with us Wi-
dows, 'ds no more than up, and ride. Gad forgive me now adays, ever?
idle, young, hedloriog, roariag Companion, with a pair of ^urn'd fed
Breeches, and a broad Back, thinks to carry away any Widow? of the belt:
degree-, but IM have you to know. Sir, all VVidcws are noi got like places
at Court, by irapudence and importaaky only.

Old. No, no, fqft, foft, yoa are a vcuog Man, and not fit- — —
Free. For a Widow? Yes fure, old Man, ch:- titeer.
- Old. Go to, go Eo, if others had nci iaid in their claims before you— ■
Free. Nos you i hop?.

Old, Why nos f, Sir ? Sure i arts a much more proportionable match
for her, than yoo. Sir •, I who am aa elder Brother, of a coaifor table For-
fiune, and of equal Years with her.

Wid. How's that.^ You unmannerly perfon, Vd have you to knew, I
was born but in jd^fP undtc Caroli fritn*.

Old, Your pardon. Lady, your psrdon ^ be not offended wiih your very
Servant-^ — But i fay, Sir^ you are a beggarly younger Brother, twenty
years younger than her ; wiEhouG any Land or Stock, but your great ftock
of Impudence : tlierefore what prstenfion can you have tohtr ?

Free. Yoi^.have made it for me ^ firll, becaufe I am a younger Brother.

Wid. Wjiy, is that a fufficient PJea to a Rslid ?
How appears it. Sir? by what fooliih Coftom ?

Free. By cuitom, time out of mind only. Then, Sir, becaufe 1 have no-
thing to keep me after her death, i am the likelier to take care of her life.
And for my being twenty years younger than her, and having a fafficiens
ftock of Impudence, I leave it to her whether they will be valid exceptions
to me, in her Widow's Law or Equity.

Old. Well, fns has been fo long In Chancery^ that I'll ftand to hsr Equity
and Decree between us. Gomej Lady, pray foap up this young fnap at firft,
or we (hall bz troubled v?ith him ^ give him a City- Widow's Anfwer : (ihas
is with all the ill breeding imaginabk) \_Jfidetothe Wid.

Come, Madam. _ j. .

Wid, Well then, to make an end of this fooliffi Wooing, for nodiing.
interrupts buiinefs more ; firil:, for you, Major' —

Old. You declare in ray farour then? '"

Free. What, dircd the Cmnt (Come, young Lawyer, thou Oialt be a
Counfel for mz) iTo Jer.

Jer. Gad, I fhall betray your Caufe then, as well as an older Lawyer,
never ftir.

Wid. Firlt, I fay, for you, Major, my walking Hofpkal of an ancient
Foundation, thou Bag of Mummy? thas wood'lt fall afunder, if 'cw&re sios for
thy Cere-cloaths- —

Old. How, Lady?

Free. Ha, ha-



Jer. Hey, brave Mother ! ufe ail Suitors thus, for ray fake.

Wid. Thou wither'd hobling, diftor ted Cripple , nay, thou art a Cripple
all over-, wou'dil thou make m€ she Staff of thy Age, the Church of thy
Decrepidnef$ ? Me ^ ; ; Fr(§.



JO THE PLAIN-DBALER.

Fres, Wefl faid, Widow! faith, thou wou'dfl make a maa love thee
now, without diflerabling. .

IVid. Thou fenfelefs, impertinent, quibling, driveiing, feeble, paraly-
tick, impotentj fambling, frigid Nicompoop.

Jer. Hey, brave Mother, for calJing of Barnes, ifae !

U'iJ. Wou'dil thou make a Caudlsmaker, a Norfs of me? Can's, you be
Bed-rid withouE a Bed-fellow ? Wor.'si your Swan-skins, Furr«, Flanneh,
and the fcorch'd Ti encher keep you warm there ? Wou'd you have me your
Scotch Warmiiig-pan, with a pox to you ? Mel— — -

Old. O Heavens !

Free. I told you i fbou'd be thought the ficter Man, M^jor.

Jer. Ay, you old Fobus, and you Hou'd have been my Guardian, wou'd
you? to have taken care of my Eilate, ihas halt' ot't (hou*d ne'/er come
to me, by letting long Leafes ai Pepps^r corn Rents /

Wid.. if i wou'd have msrry'd aa eld Man, 'tis well known I might have
marry'd an Esrl-, nay, what's more, a Judge, and been covered the Wint=r-
nighis with the Lamb-skin?, which I prefer to the Ermins of Nobles :
And durft thou think I wou'd wrong my poor Mirier, there, for you?

Free. Your Minor isachoppiog Miucr, God blefs him.

[^Strok^s Jerry on the head.

Old. Your Minor may be a Major of Horfe or Foot, for his bignefs •,
and it feems, you will have the cheating of your Minor to your felf.

Wid. Pray, Sir, bear Witnefsj cheat my Minor/ I'll bring my Adion
of the Cafe for the flander.

Free. Nay, I wou'd bear falfe Wltnefs for thee now, Widow, fince you
have done me juftice, aad have thought me the fitter Man for you.

Wid. Fair, and foftly, Sir, 'tis my Minor's Cafe, mors than my ovtn •
And I rauft do him juftice now on you. ^^^^

Free. How -^

Old. So then.

Wid. You arefirft, (I warrant) fome Renegadofrom the Inns of Court
and the Law ; and thou'it come to fuffer for't by the Law : that is^ be hang'd!

Jer. Not about your neck) forfooth, I hope.

Free. But, Madaaj —

Old. Hear the Cotirt.

Wid. Thou ars fome dtbauch'd, drunken, lewd, hedoriog garomg Com.
panion, and" want'ft fome Widows old Gold to nick upon *, but, I thank
you. Sir, that's for my Lawyers.

Free. Faith, we fhou'd ne're quarrel about that j for Guineys wou'd ferve
my turn : but. Widow- — - —

Wid, Thou art a foul-mouth BooHer of thy Lull:, a meer Bragadochio
of thy llrength for Wine and Women, and will bely thy felf more than
thou doll: Women, and art every way a bafe deceiver of Women : And
wou'd deceive me too, wou'd you ^ .

Free. Nay, faith, Widow, this is Judging without feeing the Evidence.

Wid. I fay, you area worn-out Whoremafter, atfiveand twenty, both ia
Body and Fortune; And cannot be truiied by the Common Wenches of the

' Town*.^^



THE P LAI N -DEALER. ^ 51

Town, lefi: you fhou'd not pay 'em ; iior by the Wives of Slie Town, lelt
yon fliou'd pay 'cm •• fo you wani Women, and wou'd .have me your Baud,
to procure 'em for you.

Free. Faith} ifyouhsdany good Acquaintance, Wido'/;, 'twon'd be ci-
villy done of theej for i am juit cofne from Sea.

Wid. I mean, you wou'd ha^e me k?ep you •, thai you might torn Keeper^
for poor Widovi/s arc only nsM like Bauds by you •, you go tO' Church with
us, but to g£S othey Women to lie with. In line, *you are a cheating,
choufing Spendthrift: And having fold -^our own Annuity, wouM v?afie
my Jointure.

^fr^ And make Havock of cur Edate pi^ribnal, and all cur old gilr. Plat^ ;
I fhou'c^ foon be Picking up all our mcrig?ig'd Aipaftie-Spoons, Bowls zvA
Beakers oul of roolt of th:=; Ak^-houfcs, betwixt Hercnks Pillars and the Boa':-
fwain in IVappifjg: nay, and wou'd be fcouring aruongil niy Trees, and make
'era knock down one another, like' routed reeling Waichiiien at midnight.
Wou'd you fo, Bislly ?

Free. Nay, prishee. Widow liear me.".

Wid. No, Sir, I'd have pou £0 knov/, thou pitiful, paltry, lath-back'd Fel-
low, if 1 wou'd have marr^'d a young Man, 'dsweli known, 1 cou'd iiavehad
any young Heir in Norfolk,-^ nay, the hopefuUM; young Man this day at the
KingS'Bemh Bar \ I, that am a Rtlid and Executrix of known plentiful Af-
fi^s and parts, who uiiderftand my felf and the Law: And wou'd you have
me under Govcrt Baron again ? No, Sir, no Covert Baron for me.
Free. But, dear Widow, hear ir-e. I value you only, not your Jointure.
Wid. Nay, Sir, hold there \ I know your love to a Widow, is covetoufnefs
of her jointure : And a Widow, aliEtle ftricken in year?, with a good Join-
ture, is like an old Manfion-houfe in a good Purchafe, never vaiu'd ; bul
take one, tske t'other : And perhaps, when you are in poffeffion, you'd ne-
gkd it, let ic drop to the ground, for v/ant of neceilary repairs, cr ex-
p^nces upon't.

Free. No, V/idow, ens wou'd be for^ to keep ail right, when one is to
forfeit one's Leafs by dikpidad.on

Wid Fie, fie, 1 negkcl my bi.iiDP-fs, witlf'tbis fboliih difconrfe of Love..
"jerry Child i-;t me fee the Lift of the Jury : Pm fare my Coufin 0/w> has.
fome Relacions ainongll 'em. Bat where h ?i\'z ?

Free. Nay, Widow, but hear me one word only. ^

Wtd- Nay, Sir, bo more, pray ^ I will no more hearken again to your
fooliih love motions, than to offers of Arbitradon. \iEx-.W\i. andfzvr.
Free. Wei), Til follow thee yet •, for he that has a pretenfion at Coart,.
or to a Widow, muO: never give over for a little ill ufage.

Old. Therefore I'll get her by Affiduiey, Patience and Long-fufferingSr-
which you will not undergo •, for you idle young Fellows leave oft' LovCj,
when it comes to bq Buiinefs ^ and I nd ulVy gets more Women than Love.
Free. Ay, indafrry the Fool's and old MaQ*s merit-, bat I'll beiadullrious
too, and, make a buGnefs on't, and get her by Law, Wrangling, and Con-
tells, and not by fufFerings : xAnd, becanfe you are no dangerous ilival,
I'll give thte Coonfel, Majo-r. '^ ,



m



32 THE PLAIN-DEALER.

If %0H Litmous Widoro eVe woH^dgain^

Sigh not to her I i/Ht by the Law complain:

7V her, as to a Bama^ Defendant fne

With Statutes, and mah^ Jfiftice pimp for yon. Exeunt

Finis Adus Sicundi.



ACT III. SCENE 1.

WeftminlieY'HalL

Enter Manly and Freemap, two Sailors behind.

/l<fan,^ Hale this place, worfe than a Maa ihai has inherited a Chancery-
JL SuiEi'I wifh I were w^lou£ oa't ;?g?aa.

Free. Why you seed not be afraid of ihis place : for a Man without Mo-
ney, needs no more fsar a crowd ofLawrsrsj thanacrowM of Pick- pockets.

Man. This, the Reverend of the Law vvoii'd have thought the Palace or
Refideace of Juflice j but, if it be, flie lives here with the State of BTurkiflj
Emperour, rarely i^en •, arsd befiegM rather than defended, by her nume-
rous black Guard here.

Free, Melhinks, 'tis like one of their own Halls, in Chrifimas time, whi-
ther, frona all parts, Fools bring their Money, to try, by the Dice (not
the word Judges) whether it (hall be their own, or no : But after a tedious
fretting and wrangling, they drop away all their Money, on both fides ^
and finding neither the better, at laftj go emptily and lovingly away to-
gether, to the Tavern, joining their Curfes againft the young Lawyers
Box, that fweeps all, like the old ones.

Man. Spoken like a Revelling Chrifimas Lawyer.

Free. Yes, I was one; I confefs; buf was fain to leave the Law, out of
Confcience, and fall to making falfe Muflers : rather chufe to Cheat the
King, than his Subjsds j Plunder, rather than take Fees,

Man. Well, a Plague, and a Purfe Famine light on the Law ; and that
Female limb of it, who drag'd me hither to day : but pr'ychee go fee if
in that croud of dagled Gowns there, thou canit find her. ^

[^Pointing to a crowd of Lawyers^ fit the end tfthe Stage.

lExit Freeman.
Manet Manly.
How hard it is to be an Hypocrite!
At leafl to me, who am but newly fo.
I thought it once a kind of Knavery,
Nay, Gowardife, to hide ones faults ; but now ^j
The common frailty, Love, becomes my fiiame. \
He muO: not know I love th'ungrateful flill.
Left he contemn me, more than (he: for I, it



THR TLAIN^DEAU&IR. 33

It feems can undergo a Womans fcorn.
But not a Mans- — —•

Entsr to him JeiAtMtl *:.

Fi^. Sir, good Sir, Generous Captain.

Man, Pr'ythee, kind impertinence, leave mc; Why fhou'dft thou fol-
low me, flatter my Generofity now, fince thou knoweft I have no Money
Itf I .^ if i had it, Td give it thee, to buy my quiet.

Fid.'l never follow'd yet, Sir, Reward or Fame, but you alone j nor do
I now beg any thing, but leave to ihare your miferies : You Ihou'd not be a
Niggard of 'em, fince, raethinks, you have enough to fpare* Let mc follow
you now, becaufe you hate me, as you have often faid.

Man. I ever hated a Coward's company, I mufi: confefs.

Fid. LeE me follow you, till I am none, theuj for you, I'm fure, will
through fuch Worlds of dangers, that I ftiall be eau'rd to 'em •, nay 1 Ihall
be afraid of your anger more than danger, and fo turn valiant out of fear.
Dear Captain, do not caft me off till you have try'd me once more: do not,
do not go to Sea again without me.

Alan. Thou to Sea ! to Court, thou Fool ^ remember the advice I gave
thee : thou art a bandfome Spaniel, and canlt fawn naturally / go, busk about,
and run thy felf into the next great Man's Lobby : firit fawn upon the Slaves "
without, and. then run into the Ladies Bed-Chamber; thou may'lt be ad-
mitted at iail, to tumble her Bed : go feek, 1 fay, and lofe me ; for I am not
able to keep thee : 1 have not Bread for my felf.

Fid. Therefore 1 will not go, becaufe then I may help and ferve you. i

Man. Thou-'

Fid. I warrant you, Sir ^ for at worft, I cou'd beg or fteal for you.

Man. Nay, more bragging! dolt thou not know there's venturing your
life in flealing ? Go, pr'ythee, away : thou art as hard to £hake off, as
that flattering effeminating mifchief, Love.

' Fid. Love, did you name.^ Why, you are not fo miferable as to be yet
in Love, fure ?

Man. No, no, pr'y thee away, be gone, or .

I had almoft dilcover'd my Love and Shame; well if I had? that thing

couM not think the worfe of raet' or if I did?— — no~^ — —yes he

fhall know it ' he ftiall -but then 1 rauft never leave him, for they are

fuch fecrets, that make Parafites and Pimps Lords of their Mailers^ for any
flavery or tyranny is eafier than Love's. [^AfUe.

Come hither, fince thou art fo forward to ferve me -. hsli thou but refolution
enough to endure the torture of a fecret ? for fuch, to fome, is infupportable.

Fid. I wou'd keep it as fafe, as if your dear precious life depended on*r.

Man. Dam your dearnefs. It concerns more than my life, my honour,

Ftd. Doubt it not. Sir. ; .^

Man. And do not difcover ir, by too much fear of difcovering it^ but
have a great care you let not Freeman find it out.

Fid. I warrant you. Sir, lam already all joy, with the hopes ofyour "
commands ; and fhall be all wings in the exc.scution of 'em : ipeak quickly.

,,.;>F . . ' ; ^ ', *■:. Ma«.



34 THE PIAIK-B E A L£R.:

Man. You laid youM beg for me, oil ■$•? ;;o'V n (Mil-tiv nsiirr'v
Fid, I did. Sir.

Man. Then you (hall beg for me.
Fid. With all my heart, Sir.
Man, That is Pimp for mf.
Fid, How, Sir?

Mm, D^^^Q ftart/ thinkeft thou, thou coud*ft do me any other fervice ?
Come, no diflcmbling honour: I know you can do it handfomly, thou wert
made for't : You have loft your time with me at Sea, you mult recover it.
Fid, Do not, Sir, beget your felf more Reafons for your Averfion to me,
and make my obedience to you a fault : I am the unfitteft in the World,
to do you fuch a Service.

Man, Your Cunning arguing againft it, ftiews but how fit you are for it.
Ko more difTembling: here, (I fay; you muft go ufe it for me, to Olivia,
Fid. To her, Sir ?

Mm. Go flatter, lye, kneel, promifc, any thing to get her for mc : 1
cannot live unlefs i have her. Didft thou not fay thou wou'dft do any thing,
toiave my life i" And flie faid you had a perfwading Face.

Pid. But, did not you fay, Sir, your Honour was dearer to you, than your
Life ^ And wou'd you have me contribute to the lofs of that, and carry
love from you, to the moft infamous, moft falf«, and

Mm. And moft beautiful ! ^Sighs afide: ,

Fid, Molt ungrateful Woman, that ever liv'd ; for fare (he muft be fo,
Ihat cou'd defert you fo foon, ufe you fo bafely, andfo lately too: donoty

do not forget it, Sir, and think

Man, No, 1 will not forget it, but think of Revenge : I will lye with her
out of Revenge. Go, be gone, and prevail for me, or ntver fee me more.
Fid. You fcorn'd her laft night.

Man. I know not what I did laft night ; 1 diOembled laft night.
Fid. Heavens.'
Man. Begone, I fay, and bring me love or compliance back, or hopes

at leaft, or I'll never fee thy face'again: by

Fid. O do not fwear. Sir, firft hear me.

Man, 1 am impaticnr, away, you'll find me here till twelve. {Turns away.

Fid. Sir

Man. Not one word, no infinuating Argument more, or foothing per-
fwafion *, you'll have need of all your Rhetorick with her : go, ftrive to
alter her, not me j be gone. ^Ex. Man. at the end of the Stage,

Manet Fidelia.
Fid. Shou'd I difcover to him now my Sex,
And lay before him his ftrange cruelty,

' Fwould but incenfe it more. No, 'tis not time.

For his Love, muft 1 then betray my own ?
Were ever Love or Chance, till now, fcvere ?
• . Or ftiifting Woman pos'd with fuch a task ? ' /

ForcM to beg that which kills her, if obtain'd \

And give away her Lover not to lofe him. {J£x. Fidel.

Enter



TH& PLAIN^PSALSE 35

Mr^er Widovf Blackacre in the middle of half a dozen Lawyers^ whifier''d f©
by a Fellow in blacky Jerry Blackacre foUowin* the Croud,

Wid. Offer me a Reference, you faucy Company you ! d'ye know who
you fpeak to /" Art thou a Solicitor in Chancsry^ and offsr a Reference ? A
pretty Fellow ! Mr. Serjeant Floddon^ here's a bellow has the impudeDGe t©
offer me a Reference.

Serj. Plod. Who'^ that has the impudence to offer a Reference within
thcfc Walls?

fi^id. Nay, foraSplitter of Caufes to do*t.' '/

Serj. Plod, No, Madam, to a Lady learned in the Law, as you are, the
offer of a Reference were to ioipofe upon you.

Wid. No, no, never fear me tor a Reference, Mr. Serjeant: But come,
have you not forgot your Brief ? Are you fure you ihan'i make the miftake

of— — -Hark you JiWhifpers'} Go then, go to your Comtof CommoK-

Pleas, and fay ooe thing over and over again : You do it fo naturally, you'll
never be fufpedcd for protrafting time.

Serj. Plod. Come, I know the courfe of the Court, and your Bufinefs.

' lExit Serj. Plod.*

Wid. Let's fee, Jerry., Where are my Minutes ? Come, Mr. Qtfaint-, pra^
go talk a great deal for me in the Chancery ^ let your words be eafie and your
Senfe hard, ray Caufe requires it : Branch it bravely, and deck myCaufe
with flowers, that the Snake may lie hidden. Go, go, and be fure yoij re-
member the Decree of my Lord Chancellor Tricefimo qnm'' of the Qiieen.

Qnaint. I will, as I fee caufe, extenuate, or amplifie Matter of Fadt ^ baffle
Truth with impudence \ anfwer Exceptions with Qaeftions, tho' never £(i
impertinent ; for Reafons give 'enl words j for Law and Equisy* Tropes
and Figures : and fo relax and enervate the finews of their Argument, with
the oyl of my Eloquence. But when my Lungs can reafon no longer, and
not being able to fay any thing more for our Caufe, fay every thing of our
Adverfary *, whofe Reputation, though never fo clear and evident in the
eye of the World, yet with (harp Invedtives— — —

Wid. (Alias Billin*fgate,)

Quaint, With poinant and fower Inveftives^ I fay, I will deface, wipe
out, and obliterate his fair Reputation, even as 9 Record with the juice of
Lemons ; and tell fuch a Story, (for, the truth on'tis, all that we can d6
for our Client, in Chancery^ is telling a Story J a fine Story, a long Story,
facbaStory.

Wid. Go, favethy breath for Ibe Caufe ^ talk at the Bar, Mr, Quaitttl
You are fo copioufly fluent, you can weary any ones ears, fooner than your
own tongue* Go, weary our AdverfariesCounfel, and the Court: Go»
thou art a fine-fpokcn perfon : Adad, I ihall make thy Wife jealous of me :
if you c^n but court the Court into a Decree for us. Go, pet you gone,

remember. ^Whifpers"} . £Exit Quaint.

Come, Mr. Blunder^ pray baul ibundly for me, at the Kings-Bench j.bluiler^
fputter, qucltioQi cavil , but be fure your Argmnenc b$ iatricate enough to

, f z xoafottad



3(f THBPLAIN'BEALER.

confound the Court: And then you do my bufinefs. Talk what you will*
but be fure your tongue never ftand ftill V for your own noife will fecure
your Senfe from Cenfure : 'tis like coughing or heming when one has got
the Belly-ake, which -ftifles ths unmannerly noife. Go, dear Rogue, and
fucceed ; and I'll invite thee, e're it be long, to more fouz'd Venifon.

Blmd. I'll warrant you» after your Verdivl, your Judgmenii (hall not be
Arretted upon if's and and's.

IVid. Come, Mr. PethLwt^ let me give you fome new inftrudions, for
our Gaufe in the Exchequer : Are the Barons fate ?

Pet. Yes, no -, may be they are, may be they are not : what know I ?
what care 1 .^

WU. Hey day ! 1 wi(h you wou'd but ftap up the Gounfel on 'tother fide
anon, at the Bar, as much i and have a little more patience with me, that
I might inftrud you a little better.

Pet. You inftrudt me-' What is my brief for, Miftrefs ?
Wid. Ay,but you feidom read, your Brief,but at the Bar, if you do it then.
Pit. Perhaps I do, perhaps I don't, and perhaps 'tis time enough : pray
bold your felf contented, Miftrefs.

Wid. Nay, if you go there too, I will not be contented. Sir, tho' you, h
fee, will lofe my Caufe for want of fpeaking, I wo' not : You fhallhear me,,
and ihatt^ be inftrudted. Let's fee your Brief,

Pet. Send your Solicitor to me, inftruded by a Woman I I'de have ycu

to know, 1 do not wear a Bar- gown —

IVfd. By a Woman I And I'd have you to know, I am no common Wo-
man 5 but a Woman converfant in the Laws of the Land, as well as your
felf, tho' I havi no Bar- gown.

Pet. Go to, go to> Miftrefs, you are impertinent, and there's your
Brief for you : inftrudt me ! {_Flings her Breviate at her.

Wid, Impertinent to me, you faucy Jack you ! You return my Brtviate,
but Where's my Fee .•* You'll be fure to keep that, and fcan that fo well, that
if th«re chance to be but a brafs Half crown in' t, one's fure to hear on't
^gain : wou'd you wou'd but look on your Rreviate half fo narrowly. But
pray give me my Fee too, as well as my Brief.

Pet. Miftrefs, that's without Prefident. When did a Counfelever return
Isjs Fee, pray ? And you are impertinent, and ignorant^ to demand it.
, ^il<s?.. kii pertinent again, and ignorant to me! Gadsbodikins, yaupuny
Hpft^rE in th,e Law, to ufe me fo, you Green Bag Carrier, you Murderer of
,ii|ifoTtunate Gaufes, the Cierksink is fcarce ofFofyourFingers,youthat new-
ly come from Lamblackiug the Judges (hoes, and are not fit to wipe mine-,
you call me impertinent and ignorant •' 1 wou?d give thee a Gu(f on the ear,
J Jttiug the Courts, if 1 were ignorant Marry gep, if it had not been forme,,
"thou t^sdifc^been yetbut a hearing Counlbl at the Bar. {_Uxit Petulant.

iV' "^2 i ">{i « •^^^^ ^^' Buttongown, crQJfmg the Stage inhafie, v .

J^^'Buttmg^m^ Mr. BmtOKgowtfy whither fofeft? what,, won't yjou flay till
w&ar,e heard ?

Bat I.- 1 cannot, Mrs. MUsk^m^^ \ muft be at the CouncU^ my Lord's
Cswfe ft ays there for. me.



THR PLA IN-V'tALnn. ^j.

Wid. And mine (uffers here. ^ . y -x^k' ^U.Zu^i ]{^ ,W->

Bmt. 1 cannot help it. . ' : u ■ i -^- , u, V

Wid. I'm undone.

Butt. What's that to me ?

Wid. Confider ihe five pound Fee, if not my Caufe: that was fomefeiiing
to you.

Butt. Away, away, pray be not fo-troublefom, Miftrefs, Imufi: begone.

Wid, Nay, bur confider a little, I am your old Client, my Lord but anew
one ^ or, let him be what he will, he will hardly be a better Client to you,
than my felf ; I hope you believe I fhall be in Law as long as I live ? there-
fore am no defpicable Client, Well, but go to your Lord, 1 know you
expe<^ he (bouM make you a Judge one day : but I hope his promife to
you will prove 8 true Lord's promife : But? that he might be fure to fail
you, 1 wlfh you had his Bond for'i.

Butt. But whatrwill you be thus impertinent, Miftrefs ?

Wid. Nay, I befeech you. Sir, Hay i if it be but to tell me my Lord's
Cafe : come, in fhorr.

iS«?f. Nay, then-- ► ■' C£w Buttongown.

Wid. Well, Jerry ^ obferve Child, and lay it up for hereafter : Thefe are
thofe Lawyers, who, by being in all Caufes, are in none : therefore if yo\i
wou'd have 'em for you, let your Adverfary fee 'em ; for he may chance
to depend upon 'era : and fo in being againft thee, they'll be for thee.

Jer, Ay, Mother, they put me in mind of the unconfcionable Wooers of
Widows, who undertake briskly their Matrimonial bufinefs for their Mo^
ney^ but when they have got it once, let who's will drudge for them ^
therefore have a care of 'em, forfooth : there's Advice for your Advice.

Wid. Well faid. Boy, come, Mr. Sflitcaufe^ pray go fee when my Caufe in
Chancery comes on \ and go fpeak with Mr. Quillit in the Kings,Bench^ and
Mx.Qpiirk in the Common Fleas ^ and fee how our matters go there,
. Enter Majpr Oldfox.

0/^. Lady, a good and propitious morning to you y and may all your
Caufes go as well, as if I my felf were Judge of 'em.

Wid. Sir, excufe me, lam bufie, and cannot anfwer Complements in
Wefimififier-Hall. Go, Mr. SplitcaHfe^ and come to me sgain, to that Book^
fejlers, there I'll ftay for you, that you may be fure to find me.
lyOld' No, Sir, come to the ether Bookfellers, I'll atteiid your Ladifhip
thither.' '. [[i:^jf Spiitcaufe.

jFif^/ Why to the other ? ; -' '

Old. Becaufe he is my Bookfeller, Lady.

Wid. What, to fell you Lozenges for your Catarrh .^ or Medicines fcF
.your Corns .«' what elfe can a Major deal with a Bookfejler for I

Old. Lady, he prints for me.

Wid. Why, are you an Author.^ --

Qld. Offome few EITays ;, deign you, Lady, to perufe 'em^ (Shs* is a
^Woman of parts, and I muft win her by (hewing mine.) X^Jjjde-,-

Tke Bookfeller'*s Boy,.

Boy. Will. you fee C«/pe/'j)?r, Miftrefs? ^rijfQtle\s JPro^km i The Comfkai
. Midmfe ? : . . . _ . WirL



38 THE FLAIN-D BALRR. ..

Wid. Ho^ iQthfiQ Dalton^ Htiohs^ Shepherd, Witt£tiite.

Boy. We have no Law-books.

Wid. No? You are a pretty Bookfeller then.

Old. Come, have you c're a one of roy Eflays left ?

Boy. Yes, Sir, we have enough and ftialJ always have 'ero.

Old. How fo ?

Boy. Why they are good, Heady, lafting Ware,

Old. Nay, I hope they will live, let's fee. Be pleas'd. Madam, to perufc
the poor endeavours of my Pen^ thoM fay it, that>—

[^Gives her a Bookj

Jer. Pray let me fee St. George for Chrifiendom^ or. The Seven Champtom
of England.

md. No, no, give him. The Toun^ Clerics Guide, What, we (hall have
you read your felf into a humour of Rambling, and Fighting, and ftudying
Military Difcipline, and wearing red Breeches !

Old. Nay, if you talk of Military Difcipline, fliewhim my Trcatife of
The Art of Military.

Wid. Hold, 1 wou'd as willingly he (hou'd read a Play.

Jer. O pray, forfooth Mother, let me have a Play.

IVid. No, Sirrah, there arc young Students of the Law enough fpoil'd al-
ready by Plays •, they wou'd make you in love wish your Landrefs, or what's
worfc, feme Queen of the Stage, that was a Landrefs^ and foturn Keeper
before you are of a^e. {Several croffmg the Stage.

Butftay, Jerry ^h it not that Mr i t^hat dycaU him^ that goes there: he
that offer'd to fell mt a Suit in Chancery for five hundred Pounds, for a hun-
dred down, and only paying the Clerks Fees ?

Jer, Ay, forfooth, 'tis he.

Wid. Then ftay here, and have a care of the Bags, whilfl 1 follow him :
have a care of the Bags, T fay.

Jer. And do you have a care, forfooth, of the Statute againll Cham-
fertee, I fay. - lExit Widow.

Enter Freeman to them.

Free. So, there's a limb of my Widow, which WM wont to be infepara-
ble from her : flic can'l be far. £j4Jtde.

How now, my pretty Son- in-law that fhaij be, wher«'s my Widow?

Jer, My Mother, but not your Widow, will be forth-coming prefenily;

Free. Your Servant, Major-, what, are you buying Furniture for a little
flecping Clofet, which you mifcal a Study ? for you do only, by your
Books, as by your Wenches, bind 'em up neatly, and make 'em fine, for
other People to ufe 'em : And your Bookfeller is properly your Upholfter 5
for he furniflies your Room, rather than your Head.

Old. Well, well, good Se;i-Licutcn3nt, ftudy you your Compafs» that's
more than your head can deal with. (I will go find out the Widow, to keep
her out of his fight, or he'll board her, wblllt I am treating a peace.) l^^fde,

ll^Exit Oldfox.



THE PLAlN.t>£ALER. '39

Mamnt Freeman, Jerry.
^Jer, Nay» pr'ythee. Friend, now, lee me have bus the Se'ven Champions y,
you (h^U truft me no longer than till my Mothtrs Mr. Splptcaafe comes ^ for
i hope he'il knd me vvhere withal to pay for's.

Free. Lend thee "here. Til pay him. Do you want Money, Squire ? I'm
ferry a Man of your Eftate fliou'd want Money.

Jer. Nay, my Mother will ne're kt ms bs at Age: And till then, flic
fays——

Free. At Age ! Why, you are at Age already to have fpent an Eftatc,.
Man ; there are younger than you, have keps their Women this three years,
have had half a dozen Cigps, and loft as raanylhoufand pounds at play.

Jer, Ay, they are happy Sparks/ nay, iknow fome of my School- Fel-
lows, who when we were at School, were two years younger than me ; but
now, I know not how, are grown Men before me, and go where they will,
and look to themfelves : but my Curmudgeonly Mother won't allow mc
wherewithal to be a Man of my felf with.

Free. Why, there 'tis; 1 knew your Mother was in fault : Ask but your
School-Fellows what they did to be Men of themfelves.

Jer. Whyj I know they went to Law with their Mothers ^ for they fay,
there's no good to be done upon a Widow-Mother, till one goes to Law
with her.* but mine is as Plaguy a Lawyer as any's-of our inn. Then wou'd
flie marry too, and cut down my Trees:' Now I ihou'd hate, Man, to have
my Father's Wife kifs'd, and flapt, and t'other thing too, ( you know what
1 mean) by another Man •, and our Trees are the pureft, tall, . even, fhady

twiggs, by my fa-

Free. Come, Squire, let you Mother an^ your Trees fall as Ihe pleafes,
rather than wear this Gown, and carry green Bags all thy life, and be point-
ed at for a Tony : But you ihall be able to deal with her yet the Common
way t, thou (halt make falfeloveto fome Lawyer's Daughter, whofe Faither^
upon thy hopes of thy Marrying her, fhall lend thee Money and Law, to
prefcrve thy Eltate and Trees j and thy Mother is fougly, nobody will
have her, if flie cannos cut down thy Trees.

Jer, Nay, if I had but aay Body to Hand by me, lam as ftomachful as
another.

Free. That willl, I'll not fee any hopeful young Gentleman abus'd.
£oy. By any other but you felf.. \I^JJide,.

Jer, The truth on't is, mine's as arrant a Widow-Mother to her poor
Child, as any's in England : fhe won't as much as let one b^ve fix pence in
ones Pocket to fee a Motion, or the dancing of ths Ropes, or- — «—
Free. Gome, you (han't want Money, there's Gold for you.
Jer. O Lord, Sir, two Guineys ! d*ye^ lend me this ? is there no trick
in't ? Well, Sir, I'H give you Bond for my Security.

Free. No, no, thou haft given me thy Face for Security : And any body
wou'd fwear thoudoft not look like a Cheat. You (hail have what you will.
of me •, and if your Mother will not be kinder to you, come so msj who will.

Jer. By my fa he's a curious fine Gentleman I — — * " {afide,

Bntj will you ftaud by one-?

Free>



40 T HE P L A IN- D EA L E R.

free. If you can be refolute.

Jer, Can be refoIvM •' Gad, if (he gives me me but a cfofs word, IMI leave
her to nighc, and come to you. But, now I have got Mony, I'll go to Jack of
all Trades, at t'other end of the Hail, and bay thcneateft, pureft things—

Jer. And I'll follow the great Boy, and my blow at his mother rfteai
away the Calf, and the Cow will follow you. ^

ZBxit JiTTY^foliowU by FnQman.

Enter^ on the other fide. Manly, Widow Blackacre, and Oldfox.

Man. Dam ypur Caufe ^ can't you lofe it without me ? which you are
like enough to do, if it be as you fay, an honeft one : I will fuffer no longer
fbr'c. r

Wid. Nay, Captain, I tell you, you are my prime Witnefs, and the
Caufe is jufl: now coming on, Mr. 5/j/*Vc^«y^ tells me. Lord, methinks you.
(hou'd take a Pleafure ia walking here, ^as half you fee now do j for they
have no bufinefs here, 1 aO'ure you.

Man^ Yes, but I'll affure you then, their bufinefs is to perfecute me ♦, but
d'ye think I'll ftay any longer, to have a Rogue, be caufe he knows my name,
pluck me afide, and whifper a News-bcok-fecret to me with a ftinking
breath ?, A fecond come piping angry from the Court, and fpatter in my face
his tedious complaint againft it ? A third Law-Coxcomb, becaufehefaw
me once ata Reader's dinner, come and put me a long Law-Cafe, to make a
difcovery of his indefatigable dulnefs, and my weary'd patience? A fourth,
a moft barbarous Civil Rogue, who will keep a Man half sn hour in the
crowd with a bow'd body, anda hat off, afting the reformM Sign of the
Salfitation-Tsiverni to hear his bountiful profeffions of Service and friendlhip ;
whil'ft he cares not if I were damn'd, and 1 am wifhing hira hang'd out of
my way ^ I'd as Ibon run the Gantlet, as walk t'other turn.

Enter to them Jerry Blackacre without his Bags •, hat laden with Trinkets, which
he endeavours to hide from his Mother .* and followed at a diflance by Freeman,

Wid. O, are you come. Sir ? But where have you been, you Afs ? And
how came you thus Laden ?

Jer. Look here, forfooth. Mother, now here's a Duck, here's a Boar-
cat, and here's an Owl. [^Making a noife with Cat-calls, and

other ffich like inftrHments,

Wid. Yes, there is an Owl, Sir.

Old. He's an ungracious Bird, indeed.

V/id. But go, thou Trangame, and carry back thofe Trangames, which
thou haft ftorn or purloin'd ; for no body wou'd trull a Minor in Weftmin-
fier-Hallj fure-

Jer. Hold your felf contented, forfooth, I have thefe Commodities by
a fair Bargain and Sale ; and there ftands ray Witnefs, and Creditor.

Wid. How's that /. What, Sir, d'ye think to get the Mother, by giving
the Child a Rattle? But where are my Bags, my Writings, you Rafcal ? '



THE^F\LAIN^DEALER. 41

Jer. O Law ! Where are they indeed ? l^Afide

Wid. Howj Sirrah ? fpeak, come-

Man. Who can tell her, Freeman, I fuppofe. , ^ ^Jparttohim.

Free. 'Tis true, 1 made one of your Sak- water Shark? Real 'em, whil'it
he was eagerly chufing his Gomrpadities, as he calls 'em) in order to ray
defiga upon his Mother. . lui -is^^ ., v>\i}: • vj.i. {^Jpartto bim.

Wid- Wcfl'c you fpsqk ? ' W%ere were youy I Tay, you Son of a an un-
fortunate Woman ? O, Major, I'm undone ; they are all that concern my
Eftate, my Jointure, my Husband's Deed of Gift, my Evidences for all mf
Suits now depending ! What will become pfxhem ?

Free. I'm glad to hear this. iS/bivH \_Afids,

They'll be fafe, i warrant you, Madam.

Wid. O where? where? Gome, you Villain, along with me, and fliev?
ms wh?re. [£.ve««f Widow, Jerry? Oldfox.

yianem Manly, Freeman.

,.Man. Thou hail taken the right way to get a Widow, by roaking her

greai Boy rebel', for, when nothing will mske a Widow marry, ihe'li do'?;

xo ^crofs her Children. But canft thou in earnefl: marry this Harpy, this

Volume of ihri^^el.'dblurd Parchments and Law, this Altornies Desk.

Free. Ay, ay, I'll msrry, and li^e hon^flly: ih^i; is^iglve my Creditors,
not her, di!2 bcnoyo-kRce,'pay my debts^ ",; „'^.:': ^v.afl .;>: . ,/ •, ; ':

M^«. Thy Creditors-, you fee,.areiiot:.fo.barbarbus,:, as to putthcein Pri-
foQ, and wilt thou couiiTjit thy felf tea noifom Durigepa for thy life ? which
is the only iacisfadion thou canfl give thy Creditors by this niaich.

Free, Why^ is not (lie rich ?
j^ Man. Ay, but he that marries 2 Widow for her Monqy, will find himfelf
as much miilaken, as the Widow j^hat marries ,a .young 'fei.low for due' Be-^
nevolence, as you call it.

Free. Why, d'ye think I Ihan't deferve Wagts ? I'll drudge faii^hfully'.

Man. 1 tell thee again, he thai is the Slave in the Mice, has the lead pro-
priety in the Ore: You may d g, and dig j but if ihou wou'dit have the
Money, rather get to be her Truftee, than her Husband ; for a true Widow
will make over her ^Ilate io any body, and cheaE her -fdf, raiher than be
cheated b^ her Children, or a fccond Husband I

Enter to them Jerry rnnning in a fright:

Jer. O Law! I'm undone, I'm undone, my Mother will kill me: You
faid you'd iland by one.

Free. So I wilt, ^Y brave Squire, I warrant thee.

Jer. Ay J but I dart not ftay till (he comes : for flie's as fnriou?, now (he
has loil her Writing?, as.a Bitch when fhe has loft her Puppies.

Man. The Comparifon's handfome I . ,^

Jer. O, (he's there ?

Enter Widow Blackacre, and Old fox.

Free. [To the Sailor'} Take him Jf^c^, and mike^hsde with him, to your
Mafter's Lodging ^ and be fure you keep him up till i. come.

• ^, [E.v. jixr'j arid Sailor.

Wid. O ray dear Writings-' wlkre's thts heathen Rngucj my Minor?
Fr£i:^ Cone ia drown or hant hihiielf. G IVtd.



4a TUB PLAIN-}) BALBR.

Wid. No, I know him too well, he'll ne're be Fdo de fe that way-, but lie
may go and chufe a Guardian of his own head, ind fo be Felo defeshiens^
for he has not yet chofen one.

Fne, Say yoa fo ? And he Ihan't want one. {_Apdg.

Wid. But, now I think on't, 'tis you. Sir, have pet this Cheat upon me •,
for there is a faying, Tal^ hold of a Maid by her Smock^y and a Widow by her
Writings^ and they canmt get from you: Bui I'll play f aft and loofe with you
yt«, it there bs Law, and my Minor and Writings are not forth-coming,
I'll bring my Aftiou of Detinue or Trover. But firfl: Til try to find ou8
this Guardianiefs, gracekfs Villain. Will you jog, Major ?

Man. if you have loft your Evidence, I hope your Caufes cannot go on,
and 1 may be gone f

V/id. O fto, ftay bat a Making Water while, (as one may fay) and I'll be
with you again. t-^x Widow, andOlMox,

Manent Manly, Freeman.
Free. Well, fure I am the firft Man that ever began a Love-Intrigue, ia
Weftminjier-Hall.

Man. No, fure^ for the Love to a Widow generally begins here: And
as the Widow's Caufe goes againft the Heir or Executors, the Jointure- Ri-
vals commence their Suis to the Widow-
free. . Well, but how, pray, have you paft your time here, fincc I was
forc'd to leave you alone ? You have had a great deal of Patience.

Man. Is this a Place to be alone, or have patience in ? But 1 have had pa-
tience indeed ^ for I have drawn upon me, fince I came, but three Quarrels,
and two Law- Suits.

Free, Nay, faith, you are too curll to be let loofe in the World ^ you
ftiou'd be ty'd op again in your Sea-kennel, call'd a Ship. Bus how eouM
you quarrel here ?

Man. How cou'd I refrain ? A Lawyer talk'd peremptorily and faucily
to me, and as good as gave me the Lye.
/ Free. They do it fo often to one another at the Bar, that they make no
i Bones on'seife where.

j Man. However, 1 gave him a Cuffon the Ear-, whereupon he jogs two
! Msfl, whofe backs were iurn'd to us, (for they were reading at a BookfeK
, krs) to witncfs 1 ftruck him fitting the Court? •, which office they foreadL
) ly promised, that I cali'd 'em Rafcals, and Knights of thePoft." ons of cm
j prefently calls two other abfent WitnelTes, who were coming cowards us at
' a diitacce: vvhU'fl the other, with a whifper, defiresto knov/ my nam^, thai
he might have iatlsfaclion by ^y of Challenge, as t'other by wsyiof Wrif,
but if it were not rather to direct his Brother's Writ, than his'own Chal-
lenge : there you fee is one of my Quarrels, and two of my Law-Suits.

Free. So ; and the other two.

Man. For defiring a Poet to leave off Writzng and turn Lawyer, becaufe
he is dull, and iinpudeiit, and fays or writes nothing now, but by Prece-
dent.

Free. And the third Qparrel ?
. Man, For giving more imcere advig^*,- uo a handforae) well-drcit, young



THE PLAIN^DBALER. 43

]?efiow (who ask'd it too; not to marry a Wench, thathelov'd, and I had
iay'fl with.

Free. Nay, if you will be giving your fincere advice lo Lovers, and
Poets, you will noi fail of Quarrels.

Man. Or^ifl ftay in this place; for I fee more Quarrels crowding upon
IDC : let's be gone and avoid 'em.

Enter Novel? at a Sftance^ coming towards them.

Aplagaeon him, that Sneer is ominous to us ; he is coming upon us, and
we (hall not be rid of him.

ISfov. Dear Bully, don's look fo grum upon me, you tohl me juH: now, yoa
had forgiven me a little harmlefs Raillery upon \/^ooden legs lail night.

Man. Yes, yes, pray be gone, I am talking of bufinefs.
I'SI ■ " '



jy.



Nov. Can's I hear it ? I love thee, and will be faithful, and always-

Man. Impertinent ! 'tis bufinefs that concerns Freeman only.

Nov. Weil, I love Freeman too^ and wou'd not divulge his fecret : pr'y
thee fpeak, pr'ythee 1 muft-- —

Man. Pr'ythee let me be rid of thee, I mufl: be rid of thee.

Nov. Faith, thou can'H hardly, I love thee fo. Come, I muO: know the
bufinefs.

Man. So, I have it now. ' /' • {^j^fide.

Why, if you needs will know it, he has a quarrel, and his Adverfary bids
him bring two Friends with him : now I am one j and we are thinking who
we ihall have for a third.

Several Crojfmg the Stage, -

N&v. A Pox, there goes a Fellow owes me an Hundred pound, and goes
out of Town to morrow : I'll fpeak with him, and come to you prefently.

C^a:/> Novel.

Man. No, but you v/on'C.

Free. You are dextroufly rid of him.

Enter Old fox.

Man. To what purpofe, fince here comes another, as impertinent ? I
knowj by his grix", he is bound hither.

Old. Your Servant, worthy, noble Captain : Wei), I have left the Wi-
dow, becaufe (he carryM me from your Company; tor faith. Captain, I
mull needs tell thee, thou art the only OfHcer in England^ who was not aa
Edghill Officer, that 1 care for.

A^an. I'm forry for't.

Old. Why, wou'dft thou have me love them ?

Man. Any body, rather than me.

Old. What, you are modeft, I fee ! therefore too, I love thee.

Man. No, 1 am not modeft, but love to brag my felf,, and can'i patiently
hear you fight over the laft Civil War •, therefore go look ouc the Fellow i
faw juft now here, that walks with his Stockings and h\s Sword ous &C
heels, aad let him tell you the Hifloryof that Scar on his cheek, to give you
occafion to (hew yours) got in the field at Bloomshwy.^ not that h EdghUl -. go



44- THE P LAIN-DEALER.

to him; poor Fellow, he is fafting, and has not yet the happinefs this morning
to ftink of Brandy and Tobacco ^ go, give hicn forne to hear you, I am bufie.

Old. Well, y gad, 1 love thee now, Boy, for thy furlinefs; thou art no
tame Captain, I fee, that will fuffer — —

Man. An old Fox.

Old. k\\ that fhaa'c make me angry: I confidcr t,hou art peevifti* and
fretting at forne iilluccsfs at Law. Pr'ythce tell me what ill Luck you have
me£ with here. ;^^ v

Nian, You.

Old. Do 1 lock like tha Pidlure of ill Luck ? Gadfnouns I love thee more
and more-, and fliall \ tell thee what made me love thee firft ?

Man. Do: that i may be rid of that damn'd quality, and thee.

Old. 'Twas ihy v;earifig that broad Sword there.

Man. UtVQj Freema^^ le^'s change : Pil never wear it more.

Old. How ! Yea won't fure. Pr'y thee don't look like one of our Holy-day
Captains now a days, ??itb a Bodkin by your fide, your Martinet Rogues.

Man. (O, then there's hopes) [,Afide.

what, d'ye find fault with Martinet? let me tell you, Sir, 'tis the biftex-
ercife in the World ^ the molt ready, moil eafie, moil graceful exercife
thai ever was Ua'd, and the moft

Old. Nay, nay, Sir, so more, Sir, your Servant ^ if you praife Martinet
' once, 1 have done with you. Sir Martinet .' Martinet !

\iExit Oldfox.

Free. Nay, you have made him leave you as willingly, as ever he did an
Enemy ^ for he w?s truly for the King and Parliament: for the Parliament,
in their Lift^ and for the King, in cheating 'em of their Pay, and never
hurticg the King's party m the Field-

Enlsr a LaWytr towards thsm.- , .,

• A^a}2. A Pox! this way, here's a Lawyer 1 know thrtatning us with a-
Eolher greeting.

Larv. Sir, Sir, \our very Servant; I was afraid you had forgotten me.

Man, I was not afraid you had forgotten me.

Law. No, Sir, we Lswy.rs have pretty good memories.

Man. Yououghsto have, by your Wits. ; -

Law. O, ycu are a nicrry Ge'Ttleman^Sir^^ljr'ememkr you were merry,
when I was iail in your Company.

Man. 1 v/as never merry ia thy company, Mr. Lawyer, fure.

Law. Why, I'm fure you jok'd upon me, and (hamm'd me all night long.

Man. Shamm'd! pr'ythee what barbarous Law-term is that.^

Law. Shamming! Why, don't you know that? 'tis all our way of Wit,
.Sir.

Mafi. I am glad i do, not know it then, Shamming! What does he
ir.ean ,by't, Freeman ? „




ipon
Man. So, your Lawyers Jel^, I find, like his pra^ice, has more Knavery,



THE PLAIN-VEALER. 45

than Wi6 in't. I (hou'd make- the worft Shammer in England \ I mufl: al-
ways deal ingenuoufly, as well with you, Mr. Lawyer, aftd advife you to be
feen rather with Attornies and Solicitors, than fueh Fellows as I am ; they
will credie your Pradtice niore.^

Law. No, Sir, your company's an honour tome.

U.m. No, faith, go thy ways, there goes an Attorney, leave me for
him-, let it be never laid, a Lawyer's Civility did him hurt. '

Law. No^ worthy honour'd Sir, Til inot leave you for any Attorney, fure.

Man. Ualefs he had a Fee in his hand.

Law. Have you any bufinefs here. Sir / try me, I'd ferve you fooner
than any Attorney breathing. -- .

Man. Bufinefs !— So, I have thought of a fure way. [^AJsde,

Yes, faith, I have a little bufinefs.

Law. Have you fo. Sir? in what. Court, Sir? what is't, Sir .^ tell me
but how I may ferve you, and I'll dc'E, Sir; and tske it for as great an
honour

Man. Faith, 'cis for a poor Orphan of a Sea- Officer of mine^ that has
no Money j but if it cou'd be follcw'd in Forma Panperis, and when the Le-
gacy's recovered——— • .

Law, Forma Pauperis, Sir! ...

Man. Ay, Sir/ - r ■^'^'.

Several crojjlng the St^e^H'tfi I '..^ , .

Law. Mv. Bttmhkcafe^ Mr. Bftmblecafi^ a word with you 5 Sir, I beg your
pardon at prefent, 1 have a little bufinefs ^ ■ , ..

Man. Which is not in Forma Pauperis . '.' '; : [|£Ar/t Lawyer.

Free. So, you have now found a way to be rid of people without quart
relling. *

Enter Alderman.

Man. But htre's a City-Rogue will ftick as hard upon us, as if I ow'd
him Money,

JU. Csptain, noble Sir, I am yours heartily, d'ys fee : Why (hou'd
you avoid your old Friends ? .

Man. And why (hou'd you follow me ? Lowe you nothing.

^U. Out of ray hearty refpsdts to you ; for there is not a Man in Eng^
land^ ~

Man. Thou wou'dft'fave from hanging, with the expence of a fhiliing
only.

Jld. Nay, nay, but Captain, you are like enough to tell me— — - —

Man. Truth, which you won't cars to hear-, therefore you had better
gp talk with fome body elfe. '

j4U. No, i know iio body can inform me better, of fome young Wit, or
Spenuthrifr, that has a goc<3 dipt Seat and Eftate in Middlefex^ Hartfordjlire^
EjJeXi or Kent, any of thefe wou'd ferve my turn : now, if you knew of
fuch an one, and wou'd -but help«?-^— *

Man. Ycu to fiiiifh his ruine.

Jld. rfciith, ycu fhould have a fnip r—

Man.



THE PLAIN-DEALER.

Man. Of your Nofe j you thirty in the hundred, Rafcal •, wWd yon make
me your Squire Setter, your Bavyd for Manners f \Takes hint by the Nofe,

Ad. Oh/

Free. Hold, or here will be your third Law-Suic.

JU. Gads precious, you he(^oring psrfou you, are you wild ? I meant
you no hurt. Sir ^ I begin to thinii (as things goj Land-fecurity beft, and
have, lor a convenient Mortgage, fome ten, iirseen or twenty thoufand
pounds by me.

Man. Tfaen go lay it out upon an Hofpital, and take a Mortgage of Hea-
ven, according to your Gity-cuftom •, for you think b^ laying cut a little
Money, to hook in thai too hereafter •, do, t fay, and keep the poor you've
made by taking forfeitures, that Heaven may not take yours.

Aid. No, to keep the Cripples yoa make this War ^ this War Ipoils our
Trade.

Mm. Dsim your Trade, 'tis the better for't.

Aid. Whar, will you fpeak againft our Trade ?

Man. And dare you fpeak agiinlt the War, our Trade f .

Aid. Well, he may be a Convoy of Ships I am concern'd in. \^Afide.

Come, Captain, I will have a fair correfpondency with you, fay what you
will.

Man, Then pr'ythee be gone.

Aid. No, faith 5 pr'ythee. Captain, lei's go drink a Difh of Lac'd Cof-
fee, and talk of the times: Come, I'll treat you ; nay, you [hall go, for 1
have no bufinefs here.

Man. But I have.

Aid. To pick up a Man to give thee a Diatver : Come, I'll do thy bufinefs
for thee.

'^Man. Faith, now I think on't, fo you may, as well as any Man \ for 'tis
to pick up a Man, to be bound with me, to one who expeds City-fccurity,
for —

Aid. Nay, then .your Servant, Captain^ bufinefs muftbedone.

Miin, Pi.^.^ if it can ^ but hark you. Alderman, without you- — — -

Aid. Bufinefs, Sir, I fa'y, muil be done •, and there's an Officer of the

Treafury I have an Affair with • \SeVi:Yd eroding the Stagp.

{Exit Alderman.

Man. You fee now what the mighty friendfhip of the World is •, what all
Ceremony, Embraces, and plentiful ProfelTions come to : you are no more
to believe a profefling Friend, than a threatning Enemy \ and as no Man
hurts you, that tells you he'll do you a mifchief ; no Man, you fee, is your
Servant, who fays he is fo. Why, the Devil, then fhouM a Man bs troubled
vdth the flattery of Knaves, if he be not a Fool or Cdly j or with Xhe fond-
nefs of Fools^ if he be not a Knave or Cheat ?

Free. Only for his plfeafure j for there is fome in laughing at Fools, and
difappointing Knaves.

Man. That-s a pleafure, I think, wou'd coft you too dear, as well as mar-
rying your Widow todifappoint her ^ but, for my part, I have no pleafure by
'cm, but in defpifing 'em, whersfoe're I meet 'cm^ and then the pleafure of



THE PLAIN^DEALER 47^

hoping fo to be rid of 'em. Bu£ now my comfort is , I am notworth a fhil-
ling in the World, which all the World ftiali know, and then I'm fure 1
Ihall have none of 'em come near me.

Free, A very pretty comfort, which I think you pay loo dear for : But
is the twenty pound gone fince the morning ?

Man. To my Boats-Crew : wou'd you have the poor, honeft, brave Fel-
lows want f V
Fne. Rather than you, or I.

Man. Why, art thou without Money ? thou who art a Friend to icvery
Body ?
Free, I ventur'd my laft ftake upon the Squire, to nick him of his Mother *,

and cannot help you to a dinner, unlefs you will go dine with my Lord '- —

Man. No, no, the Ordinary is too dear forme, where flattery mull pay
for my dinner •, 1 am no Herald, or Poet.

Free. We'll go to the Biftiops

M^». There you mull (latter the old Philofophy : I cannot renounce my
Reafon for a Dinner.

Free. Why, then let's go to your Aldermans.

Man. Hang him, Rogue / that were not to diiie, for he makes us drunk
with Lees of Sack before dinner, to take away our Stomach: and there
-you mull call Ufury and Extortion, God's Blelfing, or the Honeft turning .
of the Peimy ; hear him brag of the Leather Breeches in which he trotted ■■
firit to Town \ and make a greater noife with his Money in his Parlour,
'than his Calheers do in his Counting-Houfe, without hopes of borrowing a
Ihilling.

Free. Ay, a pox on't, 'tis like dining with the great Gamefters •, and
when they fall to their common Deflert, fee the heaps of Gold drawn on all
hands, without going to twelve. Let us go to my Lady (7o^/y's.

Man. There to flatter her looks, you muft miftake her Grand-Chiidren
for her own j praifc her Cook that flie may rail at him ^ and feed her Dogs,
not your felf.

Free. What d'ye think of eating with your Lawyer then ?
^an. Eat with him/ Dam him-, to hear him employ his barbarous Elo-
quence in a Reading upon the two and ihirr/ good Bits in a Ihoulder of Veal j
and be forc'd your felf to praife the coid Bribe- Pye, that ftinks, and drink
Law French Wine, as rough and barfli as his Law French. A Pox on him,
rd rather dine in the Temple- Rounds or Walks, with the Knights with-
'Out Nofes, or the Knights of the Polt ^ who are honefter Fellows, and bet-
ter Company. Bui let us home, and try our Fortune *, for I'll ftay no lon-
ger here for your old damn'd Widow. ^

Free. Well, let us, come then *, for I muft go for my damn'd Widow,
and look after my new damn'd Charge^ three or four hundred Years ago,
a Man might have din'd in this Hall.

Man. But now., the Lawyer only here is fed :
jindfBHlly lik^^hy Qttarr els gets his Bread*



THE PLAIN-DEALE R.



ACT IV. SCENE,!.

Mdiriilfs Lo^ghigs.

Enter Manly, md Fidelia,-

Mm- \%T^^t there's faccefs in thy face; haft thou prevail'd ? fay.
__-VV Fid. As I ccuM widi, Sir.

,. Man. So, I told thee what thou werE fit for, and thou v^ouMfl not believe
me. Com^, thank me for bringing thee acqu'^iated with thy Genius. Well
thou haft mc>Ii)fi'il h-.r heart for me .^

Fid. Ho^ Sir, not fo j bu6 what^s bst-ter.

/>/."«, How ? whsi's better ! ,

Ftd. Clhall harden your heart againfl her.

Man. Have a ure, Siv, my heart is too much ia earneft to be fooled
^vvith, and my defire ai height, and needs no delays to incite ir ; what, you
are too good a Pimp already, and know how to endear pleafuie, by with-
holding it ? but leave oiF your Pages, Bawdy-houfe tricks, Sir, and tell nie,
will fhe^be kind ?

Fid. Kinder than you cou'd wifh, Sir. • \

Mm. So then: well, pr'ythee, what faid (hs ?

F*V. Shsfaid

Mm. What ? thou'rt fo tedious ; fpeak comfort to me : what ?

Fid. That, of all things, you are her averfion.

Man. How .''

Fid. That file wou'd fooner take a Bedfellow out of an Hofpjtal, and
Difeafes into her Arms, than you.

Mm. What 1

Fid. That fhe wou'd rather trufther Honour, with a dilToIute, debauch'd
Hedlor j nay worfe, with a finical baffled Coward, all over loathfora with
aflcdation of the fine Gentleman.

Mm, What's all this you fay ?

Fid. Nay, that my offers of your Love to her, were more ofFenfive, than
when Parents wooe thtir Virgin-Daughters, to the enjoyment of Riches
only •, and that you were, in all circumftances, as naufeous to her as a
Husband on compulfion.
., Man, Hold', I underftand you not.

fid. So, 'twill work I fee. !i^fidei

Man. Did you not tell me- -i-K^^^^.

Fid. She call'd you ten thoufand Ruffians. '^**fcfc-

Mm. Hold, 1 fay.

Fid. Brutes

Man, Hold.

ViA



THE PLAIN-'DEALEB.

. Fid. Sea-Moafters

Man. Dam your intelligence : hear me a little now.

Fid. ]Sfa7, furly Coward (ha call'd you too.

Man. Won'e yoa hold yet ? hold, or— ^ •

Fid. Nay, Sir, pardon me^ I cou'd not bus tell you fhe had the bafenefs,
ths injullice, to call you Coward, Sir, Coward, Coward, Sir.
Man. Not yec- — »

Fid. I've doDe, Coward, Sir. i —

Man. Did not you fay Ihe was kindet" than I ccu'd wifh her ?

Fid. Yes, Sir.

Man. How then.*' — u*-.-— 0« ■ — 1 imderftand you now. At firft fhe

appear 'd in rage*, and difdain, the trueft iign of a coming Woman-, but at
laft, youprevail'd it feems: didjou not ?

Fid. Yes, Sir.

Man. So then, let's know that only *, come pr'ythee, without delays : I'll
kifs thee for that news beforehand.

Fid. Soi thekifs I'm fure is welcome to me, whatfoe're the news will be
to you. i^-^fide.

' Man. Come, {peak.j my dear Volunlier.

FiW. How welcome were that kind word too, if it Ware not for another

Woman's fake i ' \^Afids.

. Man. What, won't you ipeak ? Youprevail'd for me, at laft, you fay ?

Fid. No, Sir.

Man. No more of your fooling, Sir, it will not agree with ray impati-
ence or temper.

Fid. Then not to fool you, Sir, Ifpake to her for you, butprevaii'd for
my felf i Ihe wou'd not hear me when I fpake in your behalf ; but bid me
fay whas 1 wouM in my own, tho' fhe gave me no occafion, Ihe was fo com-
ing, and fo was kinder. Sir, than you cou'd wifh 5 which I was only afraid
to let /you knowj without fome warning.

Vian. How's this? Young man, you are of a lying age^ but I muft hear
you out, and if-
* Fid. I wou'd not abufe you, and cannot wrong her by any report of her,
fhe is fo wicked.

yian. How, wicked ! had fhe the impudence, at the fecond fight of you
only'

Fid. Impudence, .Sir ! Oh, fhe has impudence enough to put a Court out
of countenance, and debauch a Stews. " ^

U.an. Why, what faid fhe .^

Fid^ Her tongu'e,, I confefs was filent ^ but her fpeaking Eyes gloted
fuch things, more immodeft, and lafcivious, than Raviihers can ad, or Wo-
-men undsr a confinement think.

yian. I know there are whofe Eyes refledl more Obfcenity, than the
Glafles in Alcoves-, but there are others whoufe a little Art with their
looks, to make 'em feem more beautiful, not more loving : which vain young
Fellows, like you, are apt 60 interpret in their own favour,' and to the



Lady's wrong.



H .i. Fid.



^o THE PLAJN'DBALER.

Fid. Seldom, Sir j pray have you a care of gloting Eyes^ for he that
loves to gaze upon 'em, will find at^ laft, a thoufand Fools and Cuckolds
intern, inftead ot C«p/W;.

Man. Very well. Sir : but, what, you had only Eye kindnefs from
Olivia ? ' .

Ffd. I tell you again, Sir, No Woman fticks there-, Eye-promifes of
Love they only keep •, nay, they are Contracts which make you fure of
'em. la (hort, Sir, (he feeing me, wi|h fhame and amazement dumb, lin-
a<rtive, and refiftlefs, threw her twiftrog arms about mv neck, and fmo-
ther'd me with a thoufand taltelefs Kiffes •• believe me, Sir, they were fo
to me.
Man. Why did you not avoid 'em then ?

Fid. I fenced with her eager arms, as you did with the grapples of the
Enemy's Fire-fhip-, and nothing but cutting 'em off, cou'd have freed
me.

Man. Damn'd, Damn'd Woman, that coU'dbe fo f?lfe and infamous I
And damn'd, damn'd heart of mine, that cannot yet be falfe, th^' fo infa-
mous! i^hat eafie, tame, fuffering, trampled thing does that Tittle God

of talki^ Cowards make of us ! but — .

Fid, So! It works, I find, as 1 expeded. {_Jfide,

Map. But Ihe was falfe to me before, (he told me fo her felf, and yet 1
cou'd not quite believe it ; but file was, fo that her fecond falfenefs is a fa-
vour to me, not an jn jury, in revenging me upon the Man that wrong'd me
firftofher Love. Ker Love!*- — : — a Whores, a Witches Love!— — But,

what, did flis not kifs well. Sir ? I'm fure I thought her Lips but 1 muft

not think of 'em more ^but yet they are fuch I cou'd itill kifs— grow

to- — -—and then tear off with my teeth, grind 'era into mammoks, and fpit
'em into her Cuckolds face.

Fid. Poor Man, bow uneafis is hell have hardly the heart to give him
fo much pain, the' withal I give him a cure jand to my felf new life.

\_Jfde.
Man, But, what, her Kiflss fure cou'd not but warm you into defire at
lafl, of a compliance with hers at kail ?

Fid. Nay more, I confefs^

Man. What more ? fpsak.

Fid. All you cou'd fear had pafs'd betwen us, if I cou'd have been made
to wrong you. Sir, in that nature. <•

Man. Cou'd have been made-' youlye, yx>u did.

Fid. Indeed, Sir, 'twas impoffibis for me^ befides, we were interrupted
by a vilit ^ bat, I corafefs, fhe wou'd not let me ftir, till 1 prorais'd to return
to her again within this hour, as foon as it (hou'd be dark^ by which time
flie wGu'd difpofe of her viilr, and her Servants, and her felf, for my recep-
tion: which I v^/asfainto promife to get from her;
Man, Ha !

Fid. But if ever 1 go near her again, may you. Sir, think me as falfe
to you, as Ihe is; hate, and renounce me, as you ought to do her, and I
hope will do now.

Man.



' THE PLAIN-DEALER. 5«

Man. Well, but now 1 think on'ft, you fiiall keep your word with your
Lady. What, a young Fellow, and fail the firft, nay, fo tempting an
affignation ! #

Fid. How, Sir?

Man. I fay you lliall go to her when 'tis dark, and fhall not dlfappoint
her.

Fid. I, Sir! I fhouM difappoint her more by going •, for<

Man, How fo ?

F/U Her impflldence, and injuftice to you, will make me difappoint her
Love-, loath her.

Man. Come, you have my leave •, and if you difguO: her, Pil go with you,
and ad Love, v^hilft you fhall talk it only.

Fid. You, Sir! nay, then I'll never go near her. You ad Love, Sir/ You
muft but ad it indeed, after all 1 have laid to you. Think of your Honour,
Sir, Love — „

Man. Well, call it Revenge, and that is honourable : I'll be reveng'd
on her, and thou Ihalt be ray iecond.

• Fid. Not in a bafe adion. Sir, when you are your own Enemy: O, go .
not near her, Sir, for Heavens fdke, for your ow'n, think not of it.

Man. How concernM you are-' I thought I fhouM catch you. What,
you are my Rival at laft, and are in love with her your feif; and have
fpoken ill of her out cf your love to her, not me^ and therefore wouM
not have me go to her] ' ,

Fid. Heaven witnefs for me, 'tis becaufe I love you only, I wou'd not
have you go to her.

Man. Come, come, the more 1 think-on't, the more I'm faiisfied you do
love her: thofe KifTes, young Man, I knew were irrefiftable •, 'tis certain.

Fid. There is nothing certain in the World, Sir, but my Truth, and
your Courage.

Man. Your Servant, Sir. Belides falfe, and ungrateful, as flie has' been
to me ; and tho' I may believe her hatred to me, great as you report it ^
yet I cannot think you are fo foon, and at that rate, belov'd by her, tho',
you may endeavour it.

Fid. May, if that be all, ^nd you doubt it ftill, Sir, I will condud you
to her r, and unfeen, your Ears fliall judge of her falfenefs, and my truth
to you-, if that will fatisfie you.

Man. Yes, there is forae fatisfadion iff being quite out of doubt : becaufe
'tis that alone withholds us from the pleafure of Revenge.

Fid. Revenge! What Revenge can you have, Sir? Difdain is befl re-
veng'd by Scorn •, and faithlefs Love, by the loving another, and making
her happy with the others loOngs : which, if I muft advife ^

Enter Freeman.

'■ - f

Man. Not a word more. ^

Free. What, are you talking of Love yet; Captain? I thought you had
done with't.

-— ^ _. H 2 . Man. ^



52 THE PLAIN-DEALER.

/T/^«. Why, what did you hear me fay ?

Free. Something imperfectly of Love, I think.

Man. I v«'as only wondring why Fools, Rafcals, and defertlefs Wretches,
Ihou'd itil! have the better of Men of Merit with all Women •, as much as
with their own common Miftrefs, Fortune !

Free. Becaufe moft Women, like Fortune are blind, feem to do all things
in jefb, and take pleafure in extravagant adions ^ their Love deferves nei-
ther tnanks, or blame, for they cannot help it: 'tis all fympathy ^ there-
fore the soifi^, the fiaical, the talkative^ the Cowardly, ai|^ effeminate, have
the better of the brave, the reafonables and Man of Honour ; for they have
no more reafop. in their love, or kindnefs, than Fortu/ie it felf.

Man, Yes, they have their Reafon. Firft, Honour in a Man they fear
loo rfluch to love-, and Senfe in a Lover, upbraids their want of it j arid
they hate any thing that difturbs their admiration of themfelves ; but they
are of that vaia fiumber, v;ho h?5d rather ihew their falfe generofity, in gi-
ving away profufely to worthlefs Flatterers, tlian in paying juft Debts.
And in (hort, all Womenj like Fortune, (as you fay J and Revv'ards, are
loft, by too much msritiag.

Fid. All Wcmi-n, Sir ! fure there are fome who have no other quarrel
to a Lover's merit, but that ie begets their defpair of him.

Man. Thou art young enough to be credulous j but we-—

Enter I Sailor.

I S^i/. Here are now below, thefcolding, daggled Gentlewoman, and
that Major Old — ^— old — —Fop, I think you call him.

Free. Oldfox ; pr'ythee bid 'em come up, with your leave. Captain,
for now 1 can talk with her upon the fquare , if I ihall not difturb
you.

Man. Noi for I'll begone. Coaje, Volunteer.

Free. Nay, pray (lay ^ the Scene betwixt us will not. be fo tedious to you
as you think: b:lides, you Ihall fee how I have rigg'd my^^Squire ouf, with
the remains of my Ihipwrack'd Wardrobe \ he h under your Sea-valet 4e
Chambre'^s hands, and by this time dreft, and will be worth your feeing.
Stay, and Til fetch my Fool.

Man. No ^ you know I csnnot eafiiy laugh : befides, my Volunteer and
1 have boiinsfs abroad. »• {_Ex. Manly, Fidelia on one

fide.^ Freeman on t^other^

Enter Major Oldfox and Widow Blaekacre.

IVid. What, nobody here.' Did not the Fellow fay he was within.^
Old. Yes, Lady ^ and he may be perhaps a little bufie at prefent ; but, if

you think the time long till he comes, {Vnfolding Papers^ I'll read you

here fome of the fruits, of my leifure,, the overflowings of my Fancy and Pen.

(to value me right, Ihe mull know my parts.) [^JJide.

Come— »



THE PLAIN-DEALER. . 53

Wid, No, no ^ I have reatiifig work enough of my own, in my Bag, I
thank you.

Old. I, Law, Madam 5 but here's a Poem, in Blank Verfe, which I think
^ handfome declaraiion of one^s Paffion.

Wid. O.' if you talk of Dsclaracions, I'll fhew you one of thepretdefi:
pen'd things, which i mended too my felf, you muft know.

Old. .Nay, Lady, if you have u fed your felf^fo much to the readiog of'
harlh Law, that you hate fmooih Poetry ^ here 19 a Char2<^er for you,
of ^

Wid. A Character •' Nay, then I'll /hew you my Bill in Chamery
here, that gives you facha Charaifter of my Adverfary, makes him as
black

Old. Pihsw ^ away, sway. Lady. But if you think the Ch'^rafter
too long, here is an Epigram, x^l above twenty lines, upon a cruel Lady,
who Decreed ^ her Servant /nou'd hang himfeif, to demonflrate his
Paflion.

Wid. Decreed ! if you talk of Di^creelng, I have fuch a Decree here,
drawn by the finefl Clerk —

Old. O Lady, Lady, all interruption, and no fenfe bet wen us, as if we
were Lawyers at the Bar ' But I had forgos Jpollo and Littkton never lodge
in a head together. If you hate Verfes, I'll give you a calfcof niy Poli-
- ticks in Profe : 'ds a Letter to a Friend in the Country ; which is nos^
the way of all fuch fober, folid Perfons as my felf, when they have a mind
to publifli their difgnll to the Times j tho' perhaps^ between you and I,
they have no Friend in the Country. And fure a politick, ferious perfon
may as well have a fcign'd Friend in the Country to write to, as well as an
idle Poet a feign'd Miflrefs to wrics to. And fo here's my Letter to a
Friend, or no Friend, in the Country, concerning the late Conjuncture of
Affairs, mxdziiQnX.o Coffee -honfes : ox. The Cojfec-marPs Cafe.

Wid' Nay, if your Letter have a Cafe in't, 'tis fomething^ but firfi: I'll
read you a Letter of mine, to a Friend in the Country, call'd a Letter of
jittorney.

Enter to them "^x^tmrn and Jtvx^ Blzck^cxz^ in ^n old gaudy
Siiit^ and red Breeches of FrcQmzn^s. '

Old. What, inturruption flill? O the Plague of interruption I worfe
to an Author, than the plague of Criticks-'

Wid. What's this i ft:e, Jerry Blackacrs^ my Minor, in red Breeches !
Wha;|,'hajtt thou left the mod^fl feemly Garb of Gown and Cap^ for this ?
And have i lofb ail my goo^ Inns of Chancery breeding upon thee then ?
^nd thou wilt go a breeding thy ielf from our Inn of Chancery and Weft-
minfier-HaU^ at Coffee- houfes, and Ordinaries, Piay-houfes, Tennis-court?,,
and Bawdy-houfes?

Jer. Ay, ay, what then ? perhaps Lwill ', bat what's that to you ? here's
my Guardian and Tutor now, forfootb, that I am out of your Huckflers
hands.

Wid,



■m



THE f LAIN-D &ALER.



^F«*^. Ho^/ thou haft not chofen him for thy Guardian yet .^
Jer, No, but he has chofen me for his Charge, and that's all one; and
i'li do any thing he'll have nie, and go all the World over with him ^ to
Ordinaries, and Bawdy-houfes, or any where elfe.

Wid. To Ordinaries and Bawdy-houfes .' have a care. Minor, thou wilt
infeebie there thy Eltate and Body: do not go to Ordinaries and Bawdy-
houies, good Jsrry.

Jer. Why, how come you to know any ill by Bawdy-houfes? You ne-
ver had any hurt bj 'em, had you, forfooth / Pray hold your felf content-
ed i if i do go whers Money and Wenches are to bs had^ you may thank
your felf j for you us'd me fo unnaturally, you wou'd never let me have a
Penny to go abroad with: nor fo much as come near the Garret where
your Maidens lay •, nay, you wou'd not fo much as kt me play at Ho:-
cockles with '^m, nor have any Recreatioa wiih 'em, tho» one fhou'd have
kils'd you behind, you were fo unnatural a Mother, fo you were.
Free, Ay, a very unnatural Mother, faith, Squire.
Wid. But, yerryy confider thou art yet but a Minor ; however, if thou

wilt go home with me again, and be a good Child, thou flialt fee

Free. Madam, I muft have a better care of my Heir under Age, than fo;
I wou'd foonertruft him alone with a Hals Wating woman and a Parfon,
than with his Widow-Mother, and her Lover or Lawyer.

IVid. Why, tliou Viiialn, part -Mother and Minor! Rob me of my Child
and my Writings! but thou fnali find there's Law, and as in the Cafe of
Ravilhrncnt, of Guard- — —^Wefimififier the Second.

Old. Young Gentleman, Squire, pray bs rul'^l by your Mother, and
your Friends,

Jer. Yes, I'll b^ rul'd by my Friends, therefore not my Mother, fo I
won't: I'll chufe him for my Guardian till I am of Age ^ nay, may be for
as long as I live.

Wid. Wile thou fo, thou Wretch ? And when thou'rt of Age, thou wilt
Sign, Seal, and Deliver too, wilt thou ?
Jer. Yes marry will I, if you go there too.

JVid. O<lo not fqueeze wax. Son •, raSher go to Ordinaries, and Bawdy-
houfes, than fqueeze wax : If thou doll that, farewel the goodly Mannor of
JSlack^cre^ with all its Woods, Underwoods, and appurtenances whatever-*
Oh, oh! ZlVeef^,

Free. Come, Madam, in fhort, you fee I am refolv'd to have a (hare in
the Eftste^ yours or your Son's-, if I cannot get you, I'll keep him who is
lefs coy you find •, but, if you wou'd have your Son again, you muft take me
too. Peace, or War .^ Love, or Law .^ Youfee my Hoftage is,ii^%y.*nand:
I'm inpoireflion. ^ ■ ;. ■ '_*r

IVid. Nay, if one of us mult be ruin'd, e'en let it be him. By my Body, a
good one! Did you ever know yet a Widow marry or not marry for the
fake of her Child f I'd have you to know. Sir, I fliall be hard enough for
you both yet, without m.arrying you^ if jerry won't be rul'd by me, what
fay you. Booby, will you be rul'd .<* fpeak.
Jer, Let one alone, ^'e you ?



THE plain-dealer: cc

Wid. Wilt tliou chufe him for Guardian^ whom I refufe for Husband.
Jer. Ay, to chufe, I thank you.

Wid. And are all my hopes fruftrated ? (hall I Eever hear thee put Cafes
again to John the Butler, or our Vicar.? 'Never fee thee amble the Circuit
with the judges-, and hear thee, in cur Town- Hal), louder than the
Cryer ?
Jer. No-, fori have taken my leave of Lawyeriog., and pettifogging.
iVid, Pettifoggirg.' thou prophane Viilain, haft thdu fo ? Pettifog-
ging!- — -then youfljall take your leave of me, and your Efiiate too ; thou
fhalt be an Alien to ms and it tor ever. Pettifogging 1

Jer. O, but if you be there too Mother, we have the Deed and Settle-
ment?, I thank you : Wou'd you cheat me of my Eftate, ifac ?

Wid. No, no, 1 will not cheat your little Brother Bob, for thou werS
-not born in Wedlock.
Free, How's that ?

Jer. How f What Qiierk has fiie got in her head now ^
Wid. I fay, thou canft not, (halt not inherit the Blackf.creh Eftate.
Free. Why .^ why, forfooth ? What d'ye mean, if you go there too ?
Wid. Thou art but my bafe Child ^ and according to the Law, can'ft not
inherit it : nay, thou art not fo much as Baftardeigne.
Jer. What, what .? Am I then the Son of a Whore, Mother i

Wid. The Law fays

Free. Madam» we know what the Law fay?; but have a care what yom
fay : do not let your palTion, to ruine your Son, mine your Reputation.

Wid. Hang Reputation, Sir, am not I a Widow -^ have no Husband,.
nor intend to have any .? Nor wou*d you, I fuppoie, now have me for a Wife.
So, I think now Vcn revengM on my Son and you, without marrying, as I
told you.

Free. But, eoDfider, Madam. .

y^r. What, have you no fliame left in you, Mother f
Wid, Wonder not at it. Major, 'tis often the poor preft V^idows C^Cs,^
to give up her honour to fave her Jointure *, and feems to be a light Vvo-
man, rather than marry: as fome ycuog men, they fay, pretend ta have
the filthy Difeafe, and Icfe their credit with mofl; Women, ti> avoid the:
imporsunitiss of Torse, ZJfide ro Oldfox.

Free. But one word with you, Madara.

Wid. No, no. Sir. Come, Major, let us make hafte now to the Prero-
gative Court.

Old. But, Lady, if what you fay be true, willyouftigmatlze your Repu-
tation on Record ? And, if it be not true, how will you prove it .?

Wid. Plhaw! I can prove any* things and for my Reputation, knoWy.
Major, a wife Woman will no more value her Reputation, in difinheriting
a rebellious Son of a good Eftate j than (he wou'd in getting him, to iuhe»
rit an Eftate; [^£a:. Wid. <?w^ Oldfox.

■^^■Free^ Madam ^-we muft not let her go (b, Squire.

Jer. Nay, the Devil can't ftop her 6ho' if (he has a mind to*t. But come;
BuUy-Guardian, we'll go advife with three Attornies,- two Pro(n;ors, two

Solicitors,



S^ THE PLAIN-DEALER.

Solicitors, and a (hrewd man of White-Friers^ neither Attorney, Prodtor, or
Soliciior, bat as pure a Pimp to the Law ss any of 'em ^ and fure all they
will be hard enough for her^ and I fear, Bully-Guardian, you are too good a
Jcker to have any Law in your head.

Free, Thou'rt in the rigbfi on*E Squire^ I underftand no Law: efpecially
thst againft Ballards> fioce I'm fure the Cuftom is againft that Law^ and
EDore People gets Eltates by being fo than Icfe 'cm. £Exemt.

The Scene changes to Olivia'^ Lodging,

Enter Lord PlBuHblQ^ a?jd Boy with a Ctwdle.

L. Planf. Litlle Gentleman, pur naoil obedient, faithful, humble Servant :
where, I befeech you, is that divine Perfon, yoar Noble Lady .?

£oy. Gone out, my Lord ^ bat commanded me to gi\re you this Letter.

ZGives him a Letter.

Enter to him Novel-

L.Tlaaf. Which he muft not obferve. C-^^-^^'] C^^f-^ ^"^ 'f.

Nov. Hey, Boy, where is thy Lady ?

Boy. Gone out. Sir; but I raufi: beg a word with you.

{jGives him a Letter^ and Exit,

Nov, Forme? So. [.Pms up the Letter.

' Servant, Servant, my Lord j you fee the Lady knew of yourcoming, for ihe
is gone cut.

L. FlauJ. Sir, I humbly befeech you not to cenfure the Lady's good breed-
ing : Ihe has reafon to ufe more liberty wiih me, than with any other tmn.

Nov. How, Vicount, how ?

L, Plauf, Nay, I humbly befeech you, be not in ehoier j where there is
molt love^ there may be moft freedom. . '

. Nov, Nay, then 'tis time to come to an eckrcifment with you, and to
tel] you, you raufl: think no more of this Lady's love. ^

L. Flmf. Why, under corredion, dear Sir .«'

N(rv. There are Reafbns, Reafons, Vicount. -

L. Plaiif, What, Ibgfeechyou, noble Sir .^

Nov. Pr'ythee, pr'ythse, be not imperiinent, ray Lord \ fome of you
Lords, are fuch conceited, wsll-affured, impertinent Rogues.

L, FUuf. And you noble Wits, are fo full of (hammilig and drolling, one
knows not where to have you feriouily.

Nov. V^ell, you ftali find me in Bed with this Lady, one of thefe days.

L. TIm[. Nay, I befeech you fpare the Lady's honour j for her's and
mine will be ail one fiiortly. '' . ,

Nov. Pr'ythee, my Lord, be not an Afs : dolt thou ihiflk to get her from>
me.? I have had fuch good encouragements

L, FUuf, I have not been thought unworthy of 'em.

Naii^



THE PLAIN-VEALER. 57

Nou. What, not like mine 1 Come to an eclercifment, as I faid.

L. Tlanf. Why, ferioufly then fhe has told me, Vicountefs founded pret-
tily-

Nov, And me, that Novel was a name fhe wou'd fooaer change her's for,
than for any Title inEngland,

U PUitf. She has commended the foftnefs, and refpe(n:fulnefs of my be-
haviour. "•'*- ^

Nov. She has praisM the brisknefs of my Raillery of all things, Man.

L'. Plauf. The fleepinefs of my Eyes fhe lik'd.

Nov. Sleepinefs ! dulnefs, dolnefs. But the fiercenefs of mine fhe adorM.

L. Tlauf. The brightnefs of my hair (he lik'd.

Nov. The brightnefs ! no, the greafinefs, I warrant.
But the blacknefs, and laftre of mine, fhe admires.

L. Plauf. The gentlenefs of my fmile.

iVb-y.^he fubciky of my leer.

Z.. P/<?«/*. Theclearnersofmycompkdion.

N(yv. The rednefs of my Lips.

L. Planf. The whitenefs of my teeth. •""';

Nov, My janty way of picking them.

L, PlaHf. The fweetnefs of my breath.

Nov, Ha, ha!^ -nay then fhe abus'd you, 'tis plain % for you know

What Manly faid : the fweetnefs of your Pulvillio fhe might mean -, but for
. your breath ! ha, ha, ha. Your breath is fucb, Man, that nothing but To-
bacco can perfume : and your Completion nothing cou'd mend, but the
Small Pox.

L, PUnf. Well, Sir, you may pieafe to be merry ^ but, to put you out of
all doubt. Sir, fhe has received fome Jewels from me, of value.

Nov. And prefents from me-, befides what I prefented her jantily, by
way of Ombre, of three or four hundred pound value, which I'm fureare
the tarneft Pence for our Love-bargain.

L. Pl<i»[, Nay, then. Sir, with your favour, and to make an end of all

your hopes, look you here. Sir, fhe has writ to ms

Deliver to each other their Letters^

Nov. Howl how ! well, well, and fofhe has tomej look yoii there——

X. P/^w/". What's here ! "

• Nav. How's this ?

Reads out. •

My dear Lord,

YOh^S exchfe me, foi/^breaking my word with you^ pnce ^twas to oblige^ not of-
fend you '.^ for I am only gone abroad but to dif appoint Novel, and meet yon
in the Drawing-room \ where I expe^ you, with as much impatience ■% aswhenlus^d
tofu^er Novel'^ Fijits., the mofi ifnptrtinent Fop, that ever affeUedthe name of a
V^it, therefore not capable, J hope, to give yon jealoufe \ for, for your fake alons^
you faw I renounced an old Lover, and will do all the World, Burn ths Letter
but lay up the kjndnefs of it in your hearty with your

OLIVIA.
I Very



58" THE PLAJN'DSALER.

Very fine ' bat^pray let's fee mine.
L. Plauf. I uaderftand it not ; but fure (he cannot think fo of me.

*, Reads the other Letter.

Nov. T T '^^^ ' ^'«^'-" 'i'^f^^ — ^- — ^/or yoHr fake Ufnh--^ — ijuiued

JjX <;<» oldLover « ■ World -Burn'- in your heart with your

OLIVIA.*

Jufl the fame, the naiiKs ouly alter'd.

L. Tlanf. -Purely there mult be fome miftake j or feme body has abus'd
her, and us.

Nov. Yes, you are abus'd, no doubt on't, my Lord, but I'll to White-
Bally and fee., ^

L. Tlauj, And I, where i (hail find you are abus'd.
^ Nov, Whtre, if it be fo, for our comfort, we cannot fail of meeting
with Fellow- fufferers enough-, for z% Freeman faid of another, ihe ftands in,
the Drawing room, like the Glafs, ready for all Comers, to fet their Gal-
lantry by her : and like the Glafs too, let's no man go from her, unfatisfi'd
with himfeif. lEx,Ambo^

*. Enter Olivia and Boy,

Oliv. Both here, and juft gone ?

Boy. Yes, Madam. , ^

Oliv. But are you fure neither faw you deliver the other a Letter ?

Boy. Ye^, . yes,. Madam, I am very fure.

Oliv, Go then to the Old Exchange^ to IVefiminfler^ Holboum^ and all the
other places I told you of , I ihall not reed you thefe two hours: Be gone,
and take the Candle with you, and be fure you leave word again beloW, I
am gone out*, to all that ask..
. Boy. Yes, Madam.

Oliv. And mj new Lover will not ask I'm fare-, he has his LefFon, and
cannot mifs me here, tho' in the dark : which I have purpofely delign'd, as
a remedy againit my blufhing Gallant's modefty 5 for young Lovers, likfi
Game-Cocks, are made bolder, by being kept without light. .

Enter her Hnsband Vernifli, as from a Jomney^

Ver. Where is file? Darknefs everywhere! [^Softly.

Ohv. What, come before your time .'' my Soul •' my Life / your hafte has



Ver, How ! who's that you expeded after feven ?
Oliv. Ha/ my Husband return'd! and have I been throwing away fo

Oi3Dy



THE PLAIN'DEALEn. %9

many kind Kifles on my Husband, and wrong'd my Upvcr already ? £^fide*
yer. Speak, I fay, who was-c you expedted after fevcn ?
Oliv. What fiiaU I fay f — — oh — ■ — ■ ' ' C^/^^,

Why \b but feven days, is it, deareft, fince you went out of Towd ? and I
expedsdyou not fo foon. ' '

yer. No, fore, 'u's but five days Unce I left you.
'- Oliv, Pardon my impatience, degrell, I thoughs 'em fcven a6 leaft,

Fer. Nay theO'

Oliv. But, my life, you Oia 11 never flay half fo long from mc again •, yea
(han't indeed) by this kiA, you fh'an't. ' ., ,;,..-.. ,,

Fer. No, 1.0 j but why "alone in the dark ? ' " ' ^

Oliv. Blame not my melancholy in your abfence
Bur, my foul, fince you went, I have firange News to teli yoti : l^anly h
returrj'd.

' Ftr. AfW^ refurn'd I Fortune forbid, , ./,? ...

^ Oliv. Met with the jD^^f^ in the Chanel, fought, funk his "Ship, and" ai!
hecarry'dwith him: he was here with me yefterday. ' r

Ver. And did you own our Marriage to him ?

Oliv. I told him I was marri'd, to put an end to his love, and ray trou-
ble j but to wi!om, is yet a fecret kept from him, and all the World : And
I have us'd him (o fcurvily, his great fpirit will ne're return, to reafon il
-farther with me; I have Cent him to Sea again, I warranl.

Ver. 'Twas bravtly done. And fure he will now hate the ihWe ,more
than ever, after fo grtst a difappointment Be you fure only to keep a
while our great fecrri:, till hs ba gone : in the mean time Til lead the eafie,
honeft Fool by^the Nofe, as I us'd to do j and, whil'fl he Itays, rail with
him at thee; and, when he'^ gone, laugh with Ihee at hira. But have you
his Cabinet of Jewels fafe/" Part noi with a Seed-Pearl to him, to keep
him from rtarving. #

0/fV. Nor from hanging. ^ . '>"

Ver, He cannot recover 'em j and, I think, will icorn to beg 'em again.
O/iu But, my life, have you taken the thoufand Guineys he left in my
name, out of the Goldfmith's hands ?

Fer. Ay, ay, thay are remov'd to another Goldfmith's.
Oliv. Ay But, my Soul,' you had beft have a care he find not where the
Money is : for his prefent wants (as I'm inform'd) are fach, as will make
him inqoifitive enough.

Fer, You fay true, and he knows the man too: but I'll remove it to
morrow.

Oliv. To morrow F^'^O do not ftay till to. morrow ; go to night, imme-
diately.
Fer. Now I think on't, you advlfe well, and I will go prefeqtly.
Oliv. Prefently ! inltantly : I will not let you Hay a jot.
Fer, I will then, tho' I return not home till twelve.
Oliv. Nay tho' not ti|i morning, with all my heart i go, deareft, lam

impatient till you are gone.- {jThriifts him out:

So-- I have at once now brought about thofe two gcateful bufinsITes, which

I 2 all



6o THE P LAIN -VE ALE R.

all prudent Women do together, fecured Money and pleafure ^ and now
all interruptions of thfe hll are remov'd. Go, Husband, and come upj
Friend^ jufl: ihe Buckets in the Well; the abfence of one brings the o-
ther-, but I hope, like ihem too, they will not nieet in the way, juftle,
and clafli together.

£«fffy Fidelia, and M^oly treading fofily^ and fiaywg
behind at fome diftance.

So, you are come ? (but not the Husband-bucket, I hope, again.) Who's
there ? my dearcft ? {Softly.

Fid. My life

Oliv. Right, right : where are thy lips ? here, take the dumb, and belt
W'elcomes, Kiffcs and Embraces-, 'tis not a time for idle words. In a Duel
of Love, as in, others, Parlying (hews bafely. Come we are alone? and
now the Word is only fatisfaction, iand defend not thy felf.

Man, How's this? how! fhe makes Love like a Devil in a Play; and
in this darknefs, which conceals her Angel's face-, if! were apt to be a-
fraid, I fliou'd think her a Devil. J^j^fide,

Oliv. What, you iraverfe ground, young Gentleman.

C Fidelia avoiding her;

Fid. I take breath only.

Man, GoodHeav'ns/ how was I deceived ? X^Afide.

Oliv. Nay, you are a Coward ; what, are you afraid of the fiercenefs of
sny Love ?

Fid. Yes, Madam, left its violence might prefage its change ^ and I muft
needs be afraid you wou'd leave me quickly, who cou'd defert fo brave a
Gentleman as Manly.

Oliv. O! name not his Name; for in a time of ftoln joys, as this is,'
the filthy Name of Husband were not a more allaying found.

Man. There's fome comfort yet. t,A(^de*

fiU But did you not love him ? .

Oliv. Never* How cou'd you think it ?

Fid. Becaufe he thought it, who is a Man of that fenfe, nice difcerning,
aa^ difHdency, and I fhould think it hard to deceive him.

Oliv. No -, he that diftrufts moft the World, trufts moft to himfelf, and
is but the more eafily deceived, becaufe he thinks" he can't be deceiv'd: his
cunning is like the Coward's Sword, by which he is oftner worfted, than
defended.

Fid Yet, fure, you us'd no common Art, to deceive him.

Oliv. 1 knew he loved his own lingular morofenefs fo well, as to dote
upon any Copy of it ^ wherefore I felgn'd an hatred to the World too,
that he might iove me in earneft : but, if it had been hard to deceive
him, I'm fure I'were much harder to love him. A dogged, ill-maa-
ner'd—

Fid, D'ye hear m?. Sir ? pray hear her . *

t^ftdeto Manly:
Oliv,



THE TLAin^J>EAL%E. 6i

Ollv. Surly, untradtable, fnarliog Brute ! he ! a Mafty-dog were as fig
thing to make a Gallant of.

Man. Ay, a Goat, or Monkey were fitter for thee. Z^fiJe,

. Fid. I muftconfefs, for my part, (tho'my Rival) I cannot but fay he has a
manly handfomnefs in's face and meen.

OUv, So has a Saracen in the fign.

Fid. Is proper and well made.

Oliv. As a Dray-man.

Fid. Has Wit.

Oliv. He rails at all Mankind.

F/W.* And undoubted Courage.

Oliv. Like the Hangman's, can murder a man when his hands arc ty'd.
He has Cruelty indeed ; which is no more Courage, than his railing is

yvit.

Man. Thus Women, and Men like Women, are too hafd for us, when
they think we do not hsar 'em ^ and Reputation, liks oth«r Miftreffes, is
never true to a Man in his abfence. ' ^Jlfide,

Fid. He is

Oliv. Pr'ythee no more of him ; I thought I had fatisfied you enough
before, that he cou'd never be a Rival for you to apprehend ; and you
need not be more alliirM of my averfion to him, but by the lall Teftimony
of my love to you: which I a oi ready to give you. Come, my Soul, this
way— [^Pftlls Fidelia.

Fid. But, Madam, what cou'd make you diflemble love to him, when
'twas fo hard a thing for you, and flatter his love to you s'

Oliv. That |vhieh makes all the World flatter and diflemble, 'twas his
Money : I had a real paflion for that. Yet I lov'd not that fo well, as for
it to take him , for, as foon as i had Money, I haftned his departure : like
a Wifv, who.,, >i^jen ihe has made the molt of a dying Husband's breath,
pulls av"ay the ^'uiow.

Man. binui'd Money ! its Mailer's potent Rival Hill ; and, like a faucy
pimp, '•oiTupj^ii felf the Miltrefs it procures for us. {_j4Jide,

Oliv. But I did noc thidk with you, my life, to pafs my time in talking.
Come hither, come ; yet Hay, till I have lock'd a door in the other Roc m,
that may chance to iei us in fome interruption v which reciting Poets, or
loling Gamfters fear not more than 1 at this time do.

[£a:;> Olivia.

Fid. Well, 1 hope, you are new fatibfied. Sir, and will be gone to think
of your Revenge ?
• Man. No,, I am not fatisfied, and mufl ftay to be revenged. .

Fid. How, Sir ? You'll ufe no violence to her, I hope, and forfeit your
own Life, to take away hers .*' That were no Revenge.

Man. No, no, you need not fear: my revenge fnall only be upon her
Honouj, not her Life.

JF*</.^ How, Sir? her Honour? O Heavens! Confider, Sir, (he has no
Honour. D'ye call that Reveng©.^ Can you think of fuch a thing .^ But
reflect. Sir, hpw file hates and loaths you.

Man^



6% THB, P LAIN-DEALER.

Man, Yes, fo much fhe hates rae, that it wou'd be a revenge fufBcient to
make her accefiary to my pleafure, and then let her isnow ie.

Fid. No, Sir, no-, to be reveng'd on her nov?, were co difappoint her.
Pray, Sir, let us be gone. [_PhIIs Manly.

Man. Hold off. What, you are my Rival then 5 and therefore you (hall
ftay, and keep the door for me, whiPil I go in for you ; but, when I'm
gone> if you dare to ftir off from this very Board, or breath the leaft
murmuring Accent, I'U cut hsr Throat firfl:, and if you love her, you will
not venture her iife^ nay, then Plicae your Throat too •, .and I know you
love your own life at leaf!:.

Fid. But, Sir, good Sir. *

Man. Mqi 9. word more, left I begin my Revenge oa her, by killing
you.

Fid, But are you fare 'tis Revenge, that makes you do this ? how can
i£.be.r •

Man. Whift.

Fid. 'Tis a ftrange Revenge indeed.

Man. If you make me flay, lihall keep my word, and -begin with you.
.Np more. •' :^ -^^orr-.or .

l^Exit f^i^l^^ at thr [am door QYisiz went,

Manu Fidelia.

Fid. O Heavens.' is there not punifliment enough
In loving wellr Jf you will have't a Crime *,
But you mult addfrdh Torraentsdaily to't.
And puniih us 'lik&.peevifh; Rivals ilil),
Becaufe we faia; jwould find a Heaven here .?
Bu| did there neV^er any love like me.
That untry'd Tortures you mull find me out ?
Others, at worft, you force to kill themfeives ;
But I mufc be Self-murd'refs of my love.
Yet will not grans meipow'r to end my Life,
My cruel Life}' for when a Lover^s hopes
Are dead, and gone. Life's unmerciful.



XSits dowft.^ and weeps.



Enter Manly to her.



Man. I have thought^ better on*t -, I mufl; not difcover my felf now, I
am without Witnefe: forif I barely would publifh it, fhe wou'd deny it
with as much impudence, as Ihe wou'd ad it again with this young Feltow
here. Where are you. ^

Fid. Here^ — oh — -now 1 fuppofe we may be gone. %

Man. I will, but not you ^ you muft ftay, and adl the fecond part of a
Lover: that is, talk icindneft to her.

Fid. Not I, Sir. , ^

k. Man.



THE plain-d^al'kr: &j

Man. No difputing. Sir, you mud : 'tis neceflary to my defign, qf com-
ing again to morrow night.

Fid. What, can you come 3gain then hither?

Man. Yes, and you rauft inake the appointment, and an Apology for
your leaving ber fo foon j for I have faid not a word to her, but have kept
your counfel, as I exped you fhou'd do mine : do this faithfully, and 1 pro-
miie you here you (ball tun my Fortuoe ftill, and we will never part as ion§
as we live-, bat, if you do not do it, exped not to live.

Fid. *Tis hard. Sir; h\x% fuch a coniideratioa will n?ake it ealier: you-
won't forget your promife, Sir ?

;if^«. No, by Heavens. But I hear her coming.: \_Exit.

Enter Olivia to Fidelia.

Oliv. Where is my Life? run from me already? you do no8 love me,
deareft ; nay, you are angry tvith me ; for you Wou'dcotfo much asfpeafc
a kind word to me within: What was the reafon ?

Fid. I was transported too much.

Oliv. That's kind \ but come, my Soul, what make you here ? 1st us go.'
in again, we may be furpriz'd in this Room, 'tis fo near the flairs.

Fid. No, we ftiall hear the better here, if any body fhou'd come up-

Oliv. Nay, 1 aiTure you, we fhall be fecure enough within: Come,,
come "

Fid. 1 am lick, and troubled with a fuddain dizinefs y cannot flir yetc

Oliv. Come, I have Spirits within.

Fid. Ohi don't you hear a noife. Madam ?

Oliv. No, no, there is none : Come, come. ^Tulb her.-

Fid. Indeed there is ; and I love you fo much, 1 mul| have a care of your.
Honour, if you won't, and go v but to come to you to morrow night, if -
youpleafe.

Oliv. With ail my Soul •, but "you muH not go yet : Come, pr'ytfaee*

Fid. Oh ! — — -larn now ficker* and am afraid of one of my Fits.

Oliv. What Fits?

Fid. Ofths falling (icknefs: atld I Tie generally an hour in a trance j there-
fore pray confider your honour, for the fake of my love, and kc me go,,
that 1 may return Co you often.

Oliv. Bus will you be fure then to come to morrow night ?

Fid. Yes.

Oliv. 6wear,

Fid. By our paftkindnefs.

Oliv. Well, go your ways then,, 'i^ you will, you naughty Greature-
you. ' \^£-^^t Fidel.'

Thefe young Lovers, with their fears and modelty, make themielves as brid
as old ones to us j and 1 apprehend their bsfhfulnefs, more tjj^n their tat-
ling. ' ^ .^- i

Fidelia returns.

Fid, O, Madam-, we'r^ undone i there was a Genllem'an upoa.ihe flairs,

coming



6\ r/IE PLAIN'DEALiR.

comiag up with a Candle 5 which made me retire. Look you, here ht
comes ! ,

Emer Vernilh, and his Man with a Light; .

Oliv. How .' my Husband ! Oh, undone indeed ! This way. . ^Ex,
' Fer. Ha ! You fiiall not efcape me fo, Sir. {Stop Fidelia.

Fid. O Heavens! more fears, plagues, and Torments yet in ftore !

jipde.

Ver. Come, Sir, I guefs whal your bulinefs was here •, butt this mult be

your bulinefs now. Draw. {Draws.

Fid. Sir

'Ver. No Expoftulations : 1 (hall not care to hear of*i. Draw.
Fid, Good Sir.

Fer. How, you Rafcal ! no^ courage to draw, yet durft do me the great-
eft injury in the World ? Thy Cowardife fhall not fave thy life.

IPjferstorunatTiditXxdi.
Fid, O hold. Sir, and fend but your Servant down, and Til fatisfie you,
Sir, 1 cou'd not injure you as you. Imagine.

Fer. Leave the light, and be gone. {Exit Serv.

Now, quickly. Sir, what you have to fay, or- —

Fid. I am a Woman^ Sir, a very uqfortunate Woman.

Fer. How! A very handfom Woman Tm fure then: Here are Witnef-

fes oft too, I confefs '—- {Pulls of her Feruke^ and feels her Breafts.

Well, I'm glad to find the Tables turn'd, my Wife in more danger of
Cukolding, than 1 was. {y^fide.

Fid. Now, Sir, I hope yoU are fo much a Man, of Honour, as to let me
go, now I have fatisfi'd you, Sin v
/^e^. Whiin you kave fatisfi*d me. Madam, I will.
Fid. I hope, Sir^ ycuare too much a' Gentleman, to urge thefe fecrets
from a Woman, wbich concern her Honour : Yoa may guefs my misfortune
to be- Love, by my difguife , but a pair of Breeches cou'd not wrong you.
Sir.

Fer. I may believe Love has chang'd your outfide, which cou*d not wrong
me; but why did my Wife rnri away ? •" . . • ,

Fid. I know not, Sir-, perhsps becaufe fhe wou'd not be forc'd to difco-
ver me to yon, or to. guide me from your fufpicions, that you might not dif-
cover ms your felf 5 which ucgentkraan-liks curiofity 1 hope you will ceafe
to have, and let me go. *

Fer. Wci], .Madam, if I mnf!: not know who you are, 'twill fafEce for me
only to know certainly what you are : wliich you muft not deny. me. Com?,
there is a Bed within, thd proper Racks for Lovers ^ and if you are a
Woman, there you can keep no iecrets, yoa'il teli me there ail unask'd.
Come. ^ {P**iii her.

Fid. Oh .^what d'ye mean ? Help,' oh

Fi^r. I'll (iow you ; but 'tis in vain to cry out; no oae dares help you, for
I am Lord here.

Fid.



THE PLAIN'DBALER. 6^

Fid. Tyrant here i but if you are Mafter of this H^ufe, which I have
taken for a Sanduary, do not violate it your felf.

Fer, No, I'll preferve y6u here, and nothing fhall hurt you, alid will be
as true to you, as your difguife j but you muft truft me then. Come, come.

Fid. Oh ! oh ! rather than you fhou'd drag me to a death fo horrid,
and fo fliameful, t'il die here a thoufand deaths •, but you do not look like a
Ravi(her, Sir.

Fer. Nor you like one wou'd put me to't, but if you will '^

Fid. Oh! Oh! help, help

Enter Servant,

Ver. Youfaucy Rafeal, how durft you come in, when you hea:d a Wo-
man fqueak f- that ftiou'd have been your Cue to lliuE the door.

Serv, I come, Sir, to let you know, the Alderman coming home immedi-
ately after you were at his Houfe> has fenl his Cafheer with the Money, ac-
cording to your Note.

Ver, Dam his Money ! Money never cams to any fure unfeafonably, till
now. , Bid him ftay.

Serv. He fays, he cannot a moment.

Ver. Receive it you then.

Serv, He fays, he muft have your Receipt for it : he is in haftc, for I
hear him coming up. Sir.

Ver. Dam him. Help me in here then with this diflionourer of my Fa»

mily.
Fid. Oh! oh!

Serv. You fay fhe is a Woman, Sir.
Ver. No matter, Sir i muft you prate ?

Fid. Oh Heavens! is there —

XJhey thrnft her in^ and kckjhe doer,
Ver, Slay there, my Prifoner -, you have a fliorfi reprieve.

VU fetch the Gold^ and that Jhe can't reffl ^
For with a full hand "'tis we ravijh be ft.

{jExemt,
Finis A(n:as Qpartus.



K ACT



i&/ THB PLAIN-DEALER.



ACT V. SCEl^E L

Eliza'i Lodgings,

Enter Olma, and EWzz.

OUv. A H, Coufio, nothing troubles me, but that 1 have given the mali-
xV cious World it's Revenge, and Reafon now to t^lk as freely of
me, as I usM to do of it-

£liz.: Faith, then let not that trouble you^ for, to be plain, Coulin, the
iWorld cannot talk worfe of you, than it did before.

OUv, How, Coufin? I'd have you to know, before t\m faux ^afs^ this trip
of mine, the World cou'd not talk of me.

BUtl, Only that you miiid other Peoples Actions fo much, that you take
no eare of your own, but to hide 'em •, that^ like a Thief, becaufe you know
your felf moft guilty, you impeach your Fellow-Criminals firlt, to clear your

felf.
OUv. O wicked World !

Eliz., That you pretend an averlion to all Mankind in publick, only thafe
their Wives and Miftrefles may not be'jealous, and hinder you of their con-
verfation in private.

OUv. Bafe World/

EUz,, That abroad you faften quarrels upon innocent Men, for talking of
you, only to bring 'em to ask you pardon at home, and to become dear
friends with them, who were hardly your acquaintance before.

OUv. Abominable World •'

EUz.. That you condemn the obfcenity of modern Plays, only that you
may not be cenfur'd for never miffing the moft obfcene of the old ones.

OUv. Damn'd World !

BUz.. That you deface the nudities of Pidures, and little Statues, only
becaufe they are not real.

OUv. O, fie, fie, fie j hideous, hideous, Coulin I the obfcenity of their
Cenfures makes me blufli. ^

£//^. The truth of 'em, the naughty World wou'd fay now.

Enter Lettice hafiily.

Let. Oi Madam, here is that Gentleman coming up, who now yeu fay
: Is my Matter.

• OUv. O, Coufin, whither (hall I run.^ protect me, or ^

[Olivia runs away^ and fiends at a difiance.
Enter Vernilh.
^ Fer, Nay, nay, come



THE PLAIN-DEALER. 6j

O/z-y. O, Sir, fcrgiveme.

Fer. Yes, yes, I can forgive you being alone in ths dark with a Woman
in Mans ploaths j but have a care of a Man in Womens cloaths.

Oliv. What does he mean ? he diiTerables, only to get me into his power i
Or has iny dear Friend made him believe he was a Woman i* My Husband
may be deceiv'd by him, but I'm fure I was not. l^JJidc\

Fer. Gome, come, you need not have lay'n out of your HouTe for this 5
but perhaps you were afraid, when I was warm with fufpicions^ you mul^
have difcover'd who fhe was: And pr'y thee, may I not know it?
^ Oliv. She was — -(I hope he has been, deceiv'd : and, ilnce my Lover
has play'd the Card, I rauft not renounce.^ £Jfide.

f^er. Come, what's the matter with thee ? if I muft not know who fhe isj
Vm. fatisfi'd wflhout. Come hither.

Oliv. Sure you do know her •, flie has told you her felf, I fuppofe.

yisr. No, I might have known her. better, but .that 1 was interrupted by
the Goidfmith you know, and was forc'd'to lock her into your Chamber,'
to keep her from his fight j but, when I return'd, I found fhe was got a-
way, by tying the window-curtains to the Balcony, by which (he flid dWn
into the Itreel: for, you mult know, I jefled with her, and mads her bdieve
I'd ravifh her •, which fhe apprehended, • it feems, in earnelt.

Oliv. Then fhe got from you ?

Fer. Yes.

Oliv. And is quite gone ? •

J^er. Yes.

OliV, Vm glad on'c — -ptherwife you had ravifh'd her, Str? buf; ha?y
dar'ft thou go fo far, as to make her believe you wou'd ravifh her .^ let ms
underftand that, Sir. What! there's guilt in your face, you blu(h too: nay;
then you did ravifh her, you did, you bafe Fellow. What, ravifn a Woman
in the firft month of her Marriage ! *Tis a double injury to me, thou bafe
ungrateful Man •, wrong my Bed already, Villain ! i coifd tear out Ihofe
falfe Eyes, barbarous, unworthy Wretch.

Eliz, So, ib!r— - .:-' --..^i

Fer. Pr'y thee hear, my Dear. ,

Oliv. 1 wili^ never hear you, my Plague, my Tormenl. '

Fer. I fwear- — pr'yChee hear me.

Oliv. I have heard already too many of your falfe Oaths and Vows, clpe-
cially your laft in the Church. O wicked Man! An^ wretched Woman
that I was ^ I wifh I had then funk down into a Grave, rather than to have
given you my hand, to be led 60 your lothfom Beed. Oh— "Oh ' -

£Seems to Weep^

Kf". So, very fine / jult a Marriage-quarrel! ^A^^hich tho' il generally
begins by the Wife's fault, yet, ia the concluiioii, il becomes ihe Huft
band's -, and whofoever ofFends at fir(l:, he only Is fur® to ^'ik pardon at !a§.
My Dear-



uiiv. My

r^r, Gomsj pr'ythee be appeas*d, and go .home '^ I have befpQlpn mf
for I couM BOS tat,, till I found yoa . GOi I'll gin |0'«%-



6t THE PL AIM -DEADER.

all kind of fatisfa^tions v and one, which ufes to be a reconciling one, Two .
hundred of thofe Guineys I receivM laft Night, to do what you will
with.

Oliv. What, wou'd you pay ffle for being your Bawd ?

Fer. Nay, pr'ythee no more ; go and I'll throughly fatisfie you when I
come home-, and then, too, we will have a fit of laughter at Jldanly, whom
lam going coiind at the Cock, in Bow-ftreet^ where i hear he din'd. Go,
deareft, go home.

Eliz.. A very pretty turn, indeed, this! {^jipdt.

Vcr_. Now, Coufin, finee by my Wife I have that honour, and priviledge
of calling you fo, I have foraething to beg of you too j which is, not co
take notice of our Marriage to any whatever, yet a while, for fome reafons
very important to me : and next, thai you will do my Wife the honour to
go horae with her, and nis the favour, to ufe that power you have with
her, in our reconcilement.

Eliz., That 1 dare promife, Sir, will be no hard matter.
Your Servant. \Exit Vernilh.

Well, Coufin, this I confefs was reafonable hypocrilie j you where the bet-
the for'L ^

Oliv, What hypocrifie ?

Etiz,. W^hy, this laifc deceit of your Husband was lawful, fince in your
own defence.

Oliv. What deceit? I'd have yoa to know, 1 never deceiv'd my Hus-
band.

Eliz., You do not underlland me, fure •, I fay, this was an honeft come-
offi and a good one: but 'twas a fign your Gallant had had enough of your
converfation, fince he couM fo dextroufly cheat your Husband in paffing
for a Woman.

Oliv. What dy'e mean, once more, with my Gallant, and-pafliDg for a
Woman ?

EUt^. What do you mean ? you fee your Husband took him for a Wo-
man.

Oliv. Whom ?

Elii^^ Hey-day •' why, the man he found you with, for whom laft Night
you were fo much afraid •, and who you told me—

Oliv, Lord, you rsve fure !

Eliz., Why did noE you tell me laft night — -

OUv. \ know not what 1 might tell you laft night, in a fright.*

Eliz.. Ay, what was that fright for.? for. a Woman? beiides, were you
not afraid to fee your Husband juft now ? I warrant, only for having been
found wi Ji a Woman ! nay, did you not juft now too own your falfe ftep,
or trip, as you cali'd it ? which was with a Woman too! Fy, this fooling
is fo infipid, Ms offcnfive.

Oliv. And fooling with my Honour will be more offenfive. Did you not
hear my Husband lay, he found me with a Woman, in mans cloaths ? And
d'ye think he does not know a Man from a Woman ?

Eiiz.,. Not fo well, I'm fure, as you do j therefore I'd rather take your
word ' . . OUni.



THE PLAIN-BEALER. 69

Oliv. What, you grow fcurrilous, and are I find more cenrorious than ths
World / I muft have a care of you, 1 fee.

Bliz,. No, you need not fear yet. Til keep your fecret.

Oliv. My fecret! I'd have you to know, I have no need of Confidents,
tho' you value your felf upon bsing a good one.

Eliz.. O admirable confidence! you (how more in denying your wicked-
nefs, than other people in glorying in't.

Oliv. Confidence, to me/ to me fuch language! nay, then I'll never fee
your face ag,ain. Til quarrel with, her, that people may never believe 1 was
in her power ^ but take for malice all the truth Ihe may fpeak againlt me
£Jftile.2 Lettice^ where are you ? let us be gone from this cenforious ill
Woman.

Eliz.. Nay* thou (halt ftay a little, to damn thy felf quite. ^y^/tds.

One word firft, pray Madam •, can you fwear that whom your Husband found
with you '

Oliv, Swear ! ay, that whof oever 'twas that ftole up, unknown, into my
Room, when 'twas dark, 1 know not whether Man or Woman, by Heav'ns,
by all that's good ^ or, may I never more have joys here, or in the other
World : nay, may I eternally

Eliz.. Be damn'd. So, fo, you are damn'd enough already by your Oaths i
and I enough confirm'd: and now you may pkafe to be gone. Yet take
this advice with you, in this Plain-dealing Age, to leave ofi' forfweariog
your felf ^ for when People hardly think the belter of a Woman for her real
modefty, why (hou'd you put that great conftraint upon your felf to feign it t

Oliv. O hideous! hideous advice! Let us go out of the hearing of it.
She will fpoilus, Lettice. [^Ex. Olwiafjd Lett, at one door, Eliz. at t'*Qther.

The Scene changes to the Cock in Bow-ftreet.
A Table and Bottles,

Manly and Fidelia.

Man. How ! fav'd her Honour, by making her Husband believe you were
a Woman ! 'twas well, but hard enough to do, fure.

Fid. We were interrupted before he cou'd contradidl me.

Mm. But can't you tell me, d'ye fay, what kind of Man he was/

Eid. I was fo frightned, I confefs, I can give no other account of him,
but that%e was pretty tall, round fac'd, and one I'm furelne're had feen
before.
, Man. But (he, you fay, made you fwear to return to night ?

Eid. But I have fince fworn, never to go near her again j for the Huf-
band wou'd murder me, or worfe, if he caught me again.

Man. No, I will go with you, and defend you to night, and then I'll fwsar
too, never to go near her again. .

Eid. Nay, indeed. Sir, I will not go, to be accelTary to your death too :
befides, what (hau'd you go again, Sir, for }

Man: No difputing, or advice. Sir, you have reafon to know I am un-

alterabko



fo THE F-hAIN-D BALEE. ,

alterable. Go, therefore, prefemly, and write her a Note to inquire if her
affignation with you holds •, and if nol to bs at her own Houfe, where elfe ?
and be importunate to gain admittance to her to night: let your MefTenger,
e're he deliver your Letter, inquire firft,^ if her Husband be gone out. Go,
'cis DOW almoft fix of the Clock , I exped you back here before fevePj with
leave Co fee her then. Go, do ibis dextroufly, and expedt the performance
of tBy laft nights promife, never to part with you.

tU. Ay, Sir : but will you be furs to remember that f

Man. Did I ever break my Word ? go, no more replies? ordotibts.

t^ATifV Fidelia.

Enter Freeman to Manly.

Where hail thou been ? ^

Free. In the next Room, with my Lo^d Pianpble and Novel.

Man. Ay, we came hither, betaafe'swas a priuate Houfe j but with Ihes
Indeed no Houfe can be private, for, shou halt that pretty quality of the fa-
miliar Fops of the Towo, who, in an feating-houfe, always keep compsny
with all people iu'g, bus thofe they came with.

Free. I went into their Koom, but to keep them, and my own Fool the

Squire, out of your Room ; but you Ihali be peevifii now, becaufe you have

no Money : but why Ihs Devil won't you write to Ihofe we were fpeaking

ot? fince your modefty, or your fpirit,will notfufFer you tofpeak to 'em,

to lend you Money, why won't you try 'em at laft, thaS way I

Mm. Becaufe I know 'em already, and can bear want, better than Deni-
als % nay, than Obligations.

Free. Deny you ! they cannot : all of 'em have been your intimate
Friends.

Man. No, they have been People only I have oblig'd particularly.

Free. Very well , therefore you Ought to go to 'em th'S rather, fure.

Man. No, no: shofe you have obliged mofi:, moH certainly avoid you?
when you can oblige 'em no longer ^ and they take your Vilits like fo many
Duns : Friends, like MiftrefTes, are^ avoided, for Obligations pall.

Free, POiaw ! but moll of 'em are your Rdations^ Men of great For-
tune and Honour.

Man. Yes-, but Relations have fo much Honour, as to think Poverty
taints the Blood ', and difown their wanting Kindred : believing, I fiip-
pofe, that, as Riches at firit make a Gentleman^ the wans of 'em degrades
fiim. But damn 'em, now I am poor, 1*11 anticipate their consempt, and
difown them.

Fres. Bui you have many a Femak acquaintance, whom you have been
liberal to, who may have a heari to refund loyoua little, if you wou*d
ask it." they are not all 0/iwVs,

Man. Damn thse ! how couMft thou think of fuch a thing ? I wou'd as
foon rob my Footman of his Wages j Befidesj 'twere la vain too? for a
Wench is like a Box in an Ordinary, receive all peoples Money eafily \ bug
Ibere'^ no getting, nay Chaking any ou« again j and hs thai fills It^ is miz'k
nevtr to \mp the Eey, Fm,



THE PZAIN-DEALER, ^i

Free. Well, but noble Captain, wouM you make me believe that you?
who know half the Town, have fo many Friends, and have obligM fo ma-
By, caa*£ borrow fifty or an hundred Pound ? ■

Man. Why, noble LieutenaaS, you who know all the Town, and call all
you know Friends, methinks Ihould not wonder at it ^ fince you find Ingra-
titude too ^ for how ifian^/ Lords Families (tho' defeended from Blackfrnith*
or Tinkers) haft fhou caiPd Great and liiuftrious ? how many ill Tables call'd
good eacingi' how masy noifie Coxcombs, Wiis/ how many perl-Cocking
Cowards, ftcui ? how mauy taudry afFsded Rogues, wsll dreft? how many
Perukes admi^'d ? and haw many ill Verfes . applauded \? and yet canft not
borrow a fhilliag-, doil thou exped 1, who always fpoke truth, (houM ?

Free. Nay, now you think you have paid me *, but heark you, Captain, I
have heard of a thing cali'd grinning Honour, but never of ftarving Honour,

Man. Well, but ic has been the Fate of fome brave Men: apd if they
won't give me a Ship again, I can go ftarve any where, with a Musket on
my Shoulder.

Free. Give you a Ship ! why, you will not folicit it ?

Man. If I have not folicited it by my fervices, 1 know no other way.

Free, Your Servant, Sir ; nay then I'm fatisfi'd I muft folicit my Widow
she clofer, and ruji the defperate fortune of Matrimony oa fliore. £Exit»

Enter to MmXy^ Vernifli.

Man. How .' — -Nay, here is a Friend indeed j and he that has him in his
arms can know no wants. \ \iEmbraces y^rniih'

rer. Dear Sir / and he that is in your arms. Is feeiare from all fears what-
ever ♦, nay, our Nation is fecure by your defeat at Sea, and the Dntch that
fought againftyou, have prov'd Enemies to themfelves only, in bringing
you back to us.

Man.^hf fie; this from a Friend.? and yet from any other 'twere
unfufFerable .* I thought I Ihou'd never have taken any thing ill from
you.

rier. A Friend's priviledge is to fpeak his mind, tho' it be taken ill.

Man. But your tongue need not tell me you think too well of me ; T
have found it from your heart, which fpoke in acftions, your unalterable
heart : but OUvia is falfc, my Friend, which 1 fuppofe is bo News to
you.

f^er, Hfe's in the right cn't. , Z^fide:

Man. Bui cou'dft thou not keep her true to me ?

Ver. Not for my heart, Sir.

Man. But cou'd you not perceive it al all, before I went ? ccuM (he fo
deceive us both i*

f^er. I muft confefs, flie firft time I knew it, was three days after yoijr
departure, wheafhe receiv'd the Money you had left in Lombard.ftrtef^ la
her name ^ and her tears did not hinder her it feems from counting that»
You wou'd truft her with all, like a true generous Loyer »'

Man.^ And Ihe like a mean Jilting-*— ««?-



72 THE P L AIN-V E ALER.



Ver. Trayterous-

Mayi. Bafe

Vtr, D-imn'd- —



Mm. Covetous-

Ver, Mercenary Whore-



(I can hardly hold from laughing.) - ' ylfide.

Man. Ay, a Mercenary Whore indeed, for 111 e made me pay her before I
lay with her.

Fer. How! -Why, have you layn with heri"

Man. Ay, ay.

Ver. Nay, {he deferves you fhou'd report it at leall, tho' you have not

Man. Report it ! by Heaven, 'tis true.

Ver. How ! fure not.

Man. I do tsoi ufe to lie, aor you to doubt me.

Ver. When?

Man. Laft night, about feven or eight of the Clock.

Ver^ Ha.' — Now I remember, I thought (he fpake as if flie expeded fome
other, rather than me : A confounded Whore indeed ! \Afidc.

Man. But what, thou vvondreft at it-' nay you feem to be angry too.

Ver. I cannot but be enrag'd againft her, for her ufag€ of you : damn'd,
infamous, common Jade.

Man. Nay, her Cuckold, who firfl Cuckolded me ia my Money, fhall not
laugh all himfelf ; we will do him reafon, (han't we ?

Vsr. Ay, ay.

Man. But thou doft not, for fo great a Friend, take pleafure enough in
your Friends Revenge, methinks.

Ver. Yes, yes ^ Vm glad to know it, fincg you have lay'n with her.

Man. Thou canfli not tell me who that Rafcal her Cuckold is f

Ver. No.

Man, She wou'd keep it from you, I fuppofe.

Ver. Yes, yes

/J/^«. Thou wou'd ft laugh, if thou kneweft.but all the circumftanccs of
my having her. Come, I'll tell thee.

Ver. Dam her ♦, i care liot to hear any more of her.

Man. Faith thou fiialt. You muft know- —

Enter Freeman bachvoards.^ endeavouring to k^ep out Novel, Lord PlaufiblCt
Jerry ^»^ Oldfox, "who all prejfs in upon him.

Free. I tell you, he has a Wench with him, and wou'd be private.

Man. Dam 'em •' a man can't open a Bottle in thefe Eating-houfes, but
prefently you have thefe impudent, intruding, bux^iing Flies and Infeds in

your Glafs Well, I'll tell thee all anon. In the mean time, pr'ythee go

to her, but not from me, and try if you can get her to lend me but an hun-
dred pound of my Money, to fupply my prcfent wants ^ for I fuppofe there
is no recovering any of it by Law.

Ver. Not any ^ think not of it : nor by this way neither.



^ THE. fLAlN'DEALER. f|

Man, Go try, at Icall.

Ver, I'll go •, but I can fatisfic you before-hand, it will be to no Pnrpofe:
You'll no more find a refunding Weneh

Man. Than a refunding Lawyer ^ indeed their Fees alike fcarce ever re»
turn: however, try her, put it to her.

Fer, Ay, ay, I'll try her, put it to her home, with a vengance.

{Exit, Verniih,

■ * 'iij
Aianent caieri, ^

Nov. Nay, you fhaO be our Judge, Manly. Come, Major, Vll fpeak it to

your teeth : if people provoke me to fay bitter things to their hces, they

muft take what follows j tho' like ray Lord FUufihle^ I'd rather do't civil-,

ly behind their backs.

'Man. Nay, thou art a dangerous Rogue, I've heard, behind a Man's back.

L. Plauf. You wrong him i'ure, noble Captain j he wou'd da a Man no
more harm behind his back, than to his face.

Free, I am of my Lord's mind.

Man. Yes a Fool, like a Coward, is the more to be fear'd behind a Man's
back, more than a witty Man : for, as a Coward is more bloody than a brave
Man, a Fool is more malicious than a Man of Wit. .

Nov, A Fool, Tar a F^pol! nay, thouart a brave Sea-Judge of

Wit/ a Fool / pr'ythee when did you ever find me want fomething to fay,,
as you do often ?, ,

Man. Nay, 1 confefs, thou art always talking, roaring, or making a noife j
that I'll fay for thee.

Nov. Well, and is talking a fign of a Fool?

Man. Y^^ always talking •, efpecially foo if it be loud and fail, is th^r
fign of a fool

Nov. Plhaw / Talking is like Fencing, the quicker the better •,. run 'em
down, run 'em down, no matter for parrying \ pulh on ftiil, fa, fa, fa : no
matter whether you argue in form, pu(h in guard, or no.

Man. Or hit, or no ; I think ihou always talk'H wiehout thinking.
Novel.

Nov. Ay, ay, ftudy'd Play's the worfe, to follow the Allegory, as the
old Pedant fays.

Old. A Young Fop •'

Man. lever thought the Man of moft Wit had been like him of mo.^
Money, who has no vanity in flawing ic ev^sry where-, ^hilil ths beggarly
pufher of his Fortune, has all he has about bim Hill, only to fiiow.

Nov. Well, Sir, and makes a very pretty (how in the World, let me tdl
you ; nay, a betiier than your clof; Hunks : A Pox, give n?e ready Money ia
Play •, what care I for a Man's Reputation ? what arc we thS belter for your
fabftantial thrifty Curmudgeon in Wi£, Sir ?

Old. Thou art a profufe young Rogue indeed.

Nov. So much for Talking ^ which I tbiak 1 have prov'd a mark of
Wit; and fo is Railing, Roaring, and making a noife : for Railing is Sxcyr,

' L - yo\J^



74 THE PLAIN-VE^ALRR.

you know, and Roaring, aad making a noife,. Humor.

Enter to them Fidelia, talking Manly apde^ and jhewing him a Paper.

fid. The hour is belwixt feven and eight exadly : 'tis now half 'an hour
after fix.

MAft. Well, go then to the Piazza, and wait for me ; as foon as it is quite
dark, I'll be with you : I muft ftay here yet a while for my Friend. But
is Railing Satyr, Novel? ,. C-^^. Fidel.

free. And Roaring, and making a noife. Humor ?

■Nov.. What, won't you confefs there's Humor in Roaring, and making a
noife ?

free. No.
. Nov. Nor in cutting Napkins and Hangings ?

Man. No furc,

Nov. Dull Fops !

Old. O Rogue, Rogue, infipid Rogue •' Nay, Gentlemen, allow hioj'
thofe things for Wic } for his parts lye only that way.

Nov. Peace, old Fool, I wonder not at thee v but that young Fellows
ihou'd be fo dull, as to fay, there's no Humor in making a noife, and break-
ing Windows ! I tell youi there's Wit and Humor too, in both : And a
Wit is as well khowii by his Frolick, as by his SimileV /'

Old. Pure Rogue ! there's your modern Wit for you I Wit arid Huttior,.
in breaking of Windows / There's Mifchicf, if you will j but no Wit Or
Humor.

Nov. Pr*ythec, pr'ythee peace, old Fool. 1 tell you, where there is Mif-
chief, there's Wit. Don't we ,efteem the Monkey a Wit amongft Beafts,
only beciaufe he's roifehicvous? And let me tell you, as good Nature is a
fign of a Fool, being mifchievous, is a lign of Wit.
- Old. O Rogue, Rogue ! pretend to be a Wic, by doing Mifchief and
Railing!

Nov. Why, thou old Fool, haft no other pretence to the name of a Wir^
but by railing at new Plays.

Old. Thou, by railing at that facetious, noble way of Wit, quihling-

Nov. Thou cairft thy dulnefs, gravity \ and thy dozing, thinking. \^^ '

Old. You, Sir, your dulnefs Spleen : And you talk much, and fay nothing.

Nov. Thou read'H much, and underftand'ft nothing. Sir.

Old. You laugh loud, and break no jeft. , _

Nov. You rail, and no body hangs himfelf : And thou haft nothing of the
Satyr, but in thy Face.

Old. And you have no jeft, but your Face, Sir.
Nov. Thou art an iUicerate Pedant.
Old. Thou art a Fool, with a bad Memory.

Man. Gome, a Pox on you both, you have done like Wits now j for
you Wits, when you quarrel, never give over till ye prove one another
Fools.
Nov. And you Fools have never any occafion of lauging at us Wits, but



TBB, PLAIN-*I>EALER. j?

when we quarrel : therefore let US be Friends, 0/^oa:.

Man. They arc fuch Wits as thou art, who make the name of a Wit as
fcandaious, as that of Bully j and fignifie a loud-laughing, talking, incorri-
gible Coxcomb i as Sully, a roaring, hardned Coward.

Free. And wou'd have his noife and laughter pafs for VVit^ as t'other
his huffing and bluftring, for Courage.

Enter W^rmih.

Man. Gentlemen, with your leave, here is one I wou'd fpeak with, and
I have nothing to fay to you. L^nts Um out of tk Room.

Manent Manly, Vernifh. •

Ver. I told you 'twas in vain, to think of getting Money out of h^x : Ihe
fays, if a Ihilling wou'd do't, (he wou'd not favs you from ftarvinr, ca hang-
ing, or what you wou'd think worfe, begging or flattering ^ and rails fo at
you, one wou'd not think you had lay'n with h;r.

Man. O, Freind, never iruft for that matter, a Womans railing-, for (ha
is no lefs a diffembler in her hatred, than her iove : And as her fondnefs of
her Husband is a figa he's a Cuckold, her railiDg at another Man is a fjgii
Ihe lies with him.

Fer. He's in the right on't : I know not what to truft to. l^Jfde,

Man. But you did not take any notice of it to her, I hope ?

Ver, So •'— • Sure he is afraid I fliou'd have difprovsd hiflij by an en-
quiry of her : all may be well yet. , l_Jpde.

Man. What haft thou in thy head, that makes thee f^em fo unquiet ?

Ver. Only this bafe, impudent Woman's faifgnefs : I cannot put her out
of my head.

Man. O my dear Friend, be not you too fenfible of my wrongs, for then ,
I fhall feel 'em too, with more pain, and think 'em unfufferabk. Dam her,
her Monsy, and that ill-natur'd Whore too. Fortune her felfj bui if thou
wou'dft cafe a little my prefent trouble, pr'ythee go to borrow, me fome-
where elfe, fome Money : I can trouble thee.

Fer. You trouble me indeed, moft fenfibly, when you command me any
thing 1 cannot do : 1 have lately lofta great deal of Moniy at Play, more
than I can yet pay ; fo that not only my Money, but my Credit too is gone,
and know not where to borrow^ butcou'd rob a Church for you. (Yet
wou'd rather end your wants, by cutting your throat.j ' \^Afde,

Man. Nay, then I doubly feel my poverty, fince Vm incapable of ftp-
plying thee. [^Embraces Versilh.

Ver, But, methinks, (he that granted you the laft favour, (as they call it)
fliou'd not deny you any thing-

Nav, Hey, Tarpaulin, have you done? [Hovzl lookl in^ and retires again,

Fer. I undcrftand not that point of kindnefs, I contefs.

Man. No, thou doft not underjGcand it, aad i have not time to let you
know all now, for thefe Fools, ycu fee, will interrupt us ; but anon, at Sup-



7<? THE PLAIN-DEALER.

per, we^ii laugh at leifure together, at Olivia's Cuckold; who took a Joung
FeUow, that goes betwen his Wife and me, for a Woman.

rer. Ha/

Ma,n. Senfelers, eafie Rafcal ! 'twas no wonder fhe chofehirti for a Huf-
band j but (he thought him, 1 thank her, fitter than me, for that blind,
tearing Office.

y'er. I cou'd not be deceiv'd in that long Womans hair ty'd up behind ;
nor thofe infabllible proofs, her pouting fwelling breafts: 1 have handled
too many Tjre not to know 'em. ^ [^^Jtde,

Man, What, you wonder the Fellow couM be fuch a blind Coxcomb 1

Vir. Yes, yes [^NTovcl looks in again^ and retira.

Nov. Nay, pr'ythte, come to us, Aimly , Gad, ali the fine things one
fays, in their company, are loft, without thee.

Man. Away, Fop-, l*m bufie yet.
You fee we cannot talk here at our eafe •, befides, I muft be gone immediate-
ly, in order to meeting with Olivia again to night.

Fer, To night ! it cannot be, fure '

Man. I had an appointment juft now from her.

Per. For what time ? '

Man. At half an hour after feven precifcly.

f^er. Don't you apprehend the Husband ?

Mm. H€! fnivelling Gull! he a thing tobefear'd! a Husband, the ta-^
naeft of Creatures •'

yer. Very fine ! H^ftde,

Man. But, pr'ythee, in the mean time, go try to get mefome IVloney.
Tho' thou art too modeft to borrow for thy felf, thou can'ft ^o any thing
for me, I know. Go , for I muft be gone to Olivia-, go, and meet me here
anon. Freeman^ where are you f - [^Exit Manly.

' £nter Vernifh.

Fef. Ay, I'll meet with you, I warrant ^ but it (hall be at Olivia^. Sure it
cannot be *, (he denies it fo calmly ; and with that honeft, modeft a(rurance,
it can't be true— and he does notufe to lye -.'—but belying a Woman, when
(he won't be kind, is the only lye a brave Man will leaft fcrupk; But then
the Woman in Mans cloaths, whom he calls a Man/ = — ^-well, but, by her
Breafts, 1 know her to be a Woman :- — But then, again, his appointment
from her, to meet with him to night ! I am diftracfted more with doubt, than
jealoufie. Well, I have no way to difabufe or revenge my felf, but by going
home immediately, putting on a riding Suit, and pretending to my Wife the
fame bufinefs which carry'd me out of Town laft, requires me again to go
Poft to Oxftrd to night •, then, if the appointment he boafts of be true> it's
fure to hold •, and I (hall have an opportunity either of clearing her, or re-
venging my fllf on both. Perhaps (he is his Wench, of an old date, and I
am his Cully, whilft I think him mine; and he has feem*d to make his
Wench rich, only that I might take her off his hands: or if he has but lately
lay'n with her, he muft needs difcover, by her, my treachery to him j which



THE TLAIN -DEALER. jj

I'm fure h€ will revenge wicb my death, and which I muft prevent with his,
if it were only but for fear of his too juft reproaches \ for, I muft confcfs
I never had till now any excufe, but that of int'reft, for doing ill to him.

^Exit Verailh.
Re-enter Manly and Freeman.

Man. Come hither, only, I fay, be fure you miftake not the time •, yon
know the houfe exactly where OUvia lodges : *tis juft hard by.

Free. Yes, yes.

Man, Well then, bring 'em all, I fay, thither, and all you know that may
be then in the houfe : for ihe more Witnefles I have of her infamy, ihe
greater will be my Revenge: and be fure you come ftreight up to her Cham-
ber, without more ado. Here, take the Watch : you fee 'tis above a quar-
ter pafi: feven ; bs there in half an hour exadly.

Free. You need not doubt my diligence, or dexterity •, I am an old Scow-
rer, and can naturally b^at up a VVsnches quarters that wop't be civil.
Shan*t we break hsr Windows too ?

il/<«». No, no : be pundual only. {^Rx. Ambo,

Enter Widow Blsckacrc, andtvpo Knights of the To^^ . -

rf Waiter B^/'f^ Wine. . ^ , i -

Wid. Sweet-heart, are you fure the door was {but clofe, that none of thofe
Royfters faw us come in /*

Wait. Yes, Miftrefs ; and you (hall have a privater Room above^ inftant-
ly. [^Exit Wait.

Wid. You are fafe enough. Gentlemen, for I have been private in this
houfe e're now, upon other occafions, when I was fomething younger.
Come, Gentlemen, in (hort, I leave my bulinefs to your care and fidelity :
and fo, here's to you.

1 Knight. We are ungrateful Rogues, if we fhouM no:: be honefl: to you*,
for we have had a great deal of your Money.

Wid. And you have done me many a good job for'i : and 'io, here's to you
again. ^ -

2 Knight. Why, v;€ ha"e been perjur'd but fix times for you.

I Knt7ht. Forg'd but four J>eds, with your Husband'ilalt Deed of Gift.
z Knight. And buc three Wil's.

1 kmght. And couQterfeiced Hands and Seals to fome fix Bonds , I think
that's all. Brother.

Wid.Js^^i that's all, Gentlemen ; and fo, here's to you sgain.

2 Knight. Nay, 'twou'd do ones heart good to be forfworn for you : vou
have 3 Confcience in your ways, and pay us well,

I Knight. You are in the right on't, Brother^ one wou*d be dam^'d for
her, with ail one's heart.

1 Knight. But there are Rogues, who make us forfworn for '?m; and
when we come to be paid, tjiey'l b« forfworn too, and not pay us our wa-
ges which they prorais'd with Oaths fufficient.

1 Knight. Ay, a great Lawyer, thai Ihali be Namelefs, Biikt me too.



THE PLAIN DEALER.

WM. That was hard, niethinks, tha a Lawyer IhouM yfe Gentlemen
Witfiefles no better.

i^Xnight. A Lawyer! d'ye wond r a Lawyer fhou'd do»t? 1 was bilk'd
by a Reverend Divine, that preaches iwice on Sundays, and prays half an
hour ftill before dinner.

tr*^. How .«' a Confcientious Divine,, and not pay people for damning
themfeives ! Sure then, for all hi^ talking, he docs not believe damnation.
But come, to our Bulinefs ; pray be fui j to imitate exadly the flourifli at the
end of this name. {fnlls out a Deed or two.

- I Knight. O he's the bsft in England at untangling a ^ourifh, Madam.
-'Wid And let not the Seal be a jot bigger: obfervc well the da(h too, at
the twA of this name.

2 Knight. \ warrant you, Madam.

Wi^d. WelJ, thefe, and many other fhifts, poor Widows are put to fbme-
times \ for every body wou'd be riding a Widow, as they fay, and breaking
into her Jointure : they think marrying a Widow an eafie bulinefs, like leap-
ing the Hedge, where another has gone over before-, a Widow is a meer
Gap, a Gap with them.

' Enter to them Major OldioKj with two Waiters.

[The Knights of the Fofi huddle Hp the Writings,
What, he here! go then, go, my hearcs, you have your ,inftrudiois.

- [E^if Knights of the Tofl,
Old. Come, Madam, to ba plain wich you, I'll be fob'd off no 1 nger.
I'll bind her and gag her, but flie Oiall hear me. {^Afide.

Look you. Friends, there's the Money 1 promis'd you ; and now da you
what you promis'd me : here are ray Garters, and here's a Gag : you Ihall
be acquainted wiih my parts. Lady, you fhall.

. Wid. Acqaainted v/ith your parc^ ! A Rape, a Rape — ^—What, will you
ravifh m*; .«' [Ths Waiters tye her to the Chair^ and gag her^ and Ex.

Old. Yes, Lady, I Will ravilh you ^ but it ftiall be through the Ear, Lady,
the Ear only, wich my well pen'd Acrolticks.

Enter to them Freeman, Jerry Blackacre, three Bayliffs, a Confiahle, and
, his .AjjifiantSf with the two Knights of the Pofl.

What, Ihalll never read ray things nndiftarb'd again ?

Jer. O Law ! my Mother bound hand and foot, and gaping, as if fhe
rofe before her time to day /

Free. What means this, Oldfoxf But PlI releafc yoafrom him: you fhall
be no Man's Prifoner, but mlae. BaylifFs, execute your Writ.

[^?rteman ttnties her.

Old. Nay, theft I'll be gone, for fear of being Bayl, and paying her Debts,
without being her Husband. ££^. Oldfox.

1 Bay. We arreft you in the King's name, at the fait of Mr. Freeman,
Guar^*aa to Jeremiah JBlack^wre E{q\ in an A(^ion of ten thoufand pounds.



TBE ?LAIN-T)EALEn. 7p

Wid. How, how I in a Choak-Bayle Aftion ! What, and the Pen and Ink
Gentlemen, taken too! have you confeft, you Rogues '(,

1 Knight, We needed not to confefs; for the BaylifFs dog'd us hither
to the very door, and over- heard aU that you and we faid.

Wid. Undone, undone then>no Man was ever tco hard for me till How.
^ferry. Child, wilt thou vex again the Womb that bore thee /

jern Ay, for bearing roe before Wedlock, as you fay : But I'll teach you
to call a BUckacre a Baftard, tho' you were never fo much my Mother.

Wid. Well, I'm undone: not one trick left? no Law- MeuQi imaginable ?

l^Afide'^.
Cruel Sir, a word with you, I pray.

Free, In vain. Madam-, for you have no other way to releafe your felf»
but by the Bonds of Matrimony !

Wid. How, Sir, how ! that were but to fue out an Habeas CorpHs^ for a
removal from one Prifon to another. Matrimony/

Free. Well, Bayliffs, away with her.

Wid, O ftay. Sir, can ycu be fo cruel, as to bring me under Covert-Baron
again .^ and put it out of my power to fue in my own name. Matrimony to
a Woman is worfe than Excommunication, in depriving her of the benefit
of the Law : and I won'd rather be deprived of life. But heark you. Sir, I
am contented you fliou'd hold and enjoy my perfon by Leafe or Patent , but not
by the fpiritual Patent, call'd a Licence j that is> to havethepriviledgesofa
Husband, without the dominion j that is. Durante kneplacito : in confidera--
tion of which, I will out of my Jointure, fecure you an Annuity of three
hundred pounds a Year, and pay your debts •, and that's all you younger
Brothers defire to marry a Widow for, I'm fure.

Free. Well,- Widow, if

Jer. What, I hope. Bully- Guardian, you are not making Agreements
without me ?

Free. No, no. Firft, Widow, you mull fay no more that he is the Son
of a Whore : have a care of that: And then, he muft have a fetled Ex-
hibition of forty Pounds a Year, and a Nag of Aflizes, kept by you, but
not upon the Common j and have free ingrefs, egrefs an^ regrefe to and
from your Maids Garret.

Wid. Well, 1 can grant all that too.*

Jer. Ay, ay, fair words butter no Cabbage; but Guardian make her
Sign, Sign and Seal: for otherwife, if you knew her as well as I, you wou^
not truft her word for a farthing.

Free. 1 warrant tliee. Squire. Well, Widow, fince thou art fo gene-
rous, I will be generous too •, and if you'll fecure me Four hundred pounds
a Year, but during your life, and pay my debts, not above a thoufand
pound i I'll bate you your Perfon to difpofe of as you pleafe.

Wid. Have a care. Sir, a Settlement without a confideration, is void in
the Law: you rauft dofomethiag for't.

Free. Pr'ythee then let the Settlement on me be call'd Alimony : and the
Confideration, our Separation : Come, my Lawyer, with Writings ready
drawn, is within, and in hafte. Corns.

Wid,



So THE P LAI N-V EALE R.

Wid. But what, no other kindof eonfideration, Mr. Freeman ? well, a Wi-
dow, 1 fee, is a kind of [me cnre^ by cuftora of which the unconfcionable In-
cuoibenc eojoys the profits, without any duty, bur does that itill elfewhere.

^Ex, omnes.
The Scene changes to Olivia'^ Lodging.
Enter Olivia with a Candle in her hand.
Olh. So, I am now prepar'd once roore for my timorous yojtng Lover's
Reception : niy Husband is gone'^ and go thou out too, thou next interrup-
ter of love— -[]^«^-^ o^t the Car,dle.'} Kind darknefs, that frees us Lovers
from fcandai and bafhfulnefs, from the cenfure of our Gallants, and the
World. So, are you there ?

Enter to Olivia, Fidelia, follovPd foftly by Manly.

Come, my dear pnndual Lover, there is not fuch another in the World 5 thou
haft Beauty and Youth co pleafe a Wife ^ Addrefs and Wit, to amufe and
fool a Husband ; nay, thou haft ail things to be wifh'd in a Lover, but your
Fits : 1 hope, my Dear, you won't have one to night ^ and that you may not,
ril lock the door, though there be no need of it, but to lock out your Fits ^
for my Husband is jiift gone out of Town again. Come, where are you ?

l_Goes to the door^ and locks it,

Man. Well, thou haft impudence enough to give me Fits too, and make
Revenge it fell" impvotent, hinder me from making ihec more infamous, if is
can be. [^Jfide,

Oliv. Come, ccme, my Soul, come.

Ftd Prefently, my Dear, we have time enough, fure.

Oliv. How! time enough! True Lovers can no more think they ever
have time enough, than Love enough •• You Ihall ftay with me all night ; but
that bdi a Lover's moment Come.

Fid. But won't you let me give you andmy fclfthe fatisfaclion of telling
you how I abus'd your Husband laft night .•*

. Oliv. Not when you can give me, and your felf too, the fatisfadion of
abufing him again to night. Come.

Fid. Let me but tell you how your Huiband

Oliv. O name not his, or A/^w/y's more ioathfom name, if yculcveme;
1 forbid 'era laft night: and you know I mencioa'd my Husband but oncc,
and he Come. No talking, prsy ; 'c^vas ominous to us. You make me (and
a noife at the door already, bus I'm refoiv'd not lobe interrupted. [^Anoife
At the doorr\ '^Vhere are you? Corner for, rather than Jofe my dear expeda-
tion now, tho'my Husband were at the door, and the bloody Ruffian /^^i^/jr
here in the room, with all his awful infolence, 1 wou'd give my felf 10 this
dear hand, to be led away, to Heavens of joys, which none but thoucanft
give. But what's this noife at the door } So, I told you what talking wou'd
come to. \The noife at the door increafes.J^ Ha •' — ^O Heavens, my Husband's
voice! — [OlWvd liflens at the door,

Aian Frfe;«4»iscome toofooo. £Afide,

Oliv. O, 'tis he!— Then here's the happieft mioute loft, that ever bafh-



THE fLAlN-'QEALER. 8i

ful Boy, or trifling Woman fool'd away! rm undone / my Husband's re-
concilement too was falfe, as ray joy, all delullon : but come this way, here's
a Back-door. ^ C£.^*>, ^»^ returns.

The officious Jade has lock'd us in, inftead of locking others out ^ but let
us then efcape your way, by the Balcony j and whilft you pull down the Cur-
tains, I'll' fetch from my Clofet, whatnsxt will bsft fecure our efcape : I have
left ray Key in the door, arid 'twili not fuddenly be broke open. Exit.

^A r.oife as it were people forcing the door

Man. Stir not, yet fear nothing.

Fid- Nothing, but your life, Sir.

Man. We (hail know this happy Man fhe calls Husband.

Olivia re-enters.

Oliv. Oh, where are you ? what, idle with fear .? Gome, I'll tie the Cur-
tains, if you will hold. Hers, take this Cabinet and Purfe, for it is thine, if
we efcape ; [Manly takss from her the Cabinet and Pnrfe.

therefore let us make hafte. ^ \iEx. Oiir.

Mm. 'Tis mine indeed now again, and it (hall never efcape more from
me, to you at leall.

{The dear broke open^ Enter Vernifii alone, with a dark^ Lamhorn and a Swordf
rnnning at Manly •, who draws^ puts by the thrufi^ and defends himfelf, whil^ft
Fidelia rum at Vernifh behind.

r'^r. So, there I'm right fure {_With alowvoice,

Man. Softly. Sword and dark Lanthorn, Villain, arc fome odds ; but

f^er. Odds •' I'm fare I find more odds than I expeded : what, has my

infatiable two Seconds at once ? but [With a low voice.^

^^Whiljtthsy fight Olivia re-enterSj tying two Curtains together.

Oliv. Where are you now ? what, is he entred then, and are they

fighting ! O do not kill one that can make no defence. CManly throws Ver-
nifh down^ and difarms him.^ How •' but I think he has the better on'fi : here's
hisScarff, 'tis he. So, keep him downftill- I hope thou haft no hurt, my
deareft ^ v ^Embracing Manly.

Enter to them Freeman, Lord Plaufible, Novel, Jerry Blackacre, and the
Widow Bhckzcve., lighted in by the two Sailots with Torches.

Hal— — what? Manly \ And have I been thus concern'd for him, em-
bracing him/ And has he his Jewels again too? what means this? O *tis
too fure, as well as my fliame •' which Til go hide for ever.

ZOferstogoout., and MMy ftbvs her.

Man. No, my deareft, after fo much kindnefs as has pall between 'us, I

cannot part with you yet. jFm/«<a», let no body ftir outof the Room \ for

notwithftanding your lights, we are yet in the dark, till this Gentleman

pleafe to turn his face [P«//j Vernilh by thejleeve.

How ! vermlh ! Art thou the happy man then f Thou / Thou / fpeak, 1 fay h
but thy guilty fiknce tells me all-- -well, I fliall not upbraid thee; for



82 J7/S P LATN'DEALER.

my wonder fs ftriklng me ag dumb, as thy fiiarae has made thee. But what ?
my little Volunteer hurS, and fainting/

Fid. My wound. Sir, is but a flight one, in nay Arm : 'tis only my fear of
your danger, Sir, not yet well over.

Man, But what's here i* -more ftrange things ' Iphferv'mg Fidelia'^ hair

umy*d behind, andwithoHt a Peruke^ which jlis iofi inthefcnffie.

What means this long Womans hair ^ and face .' now all of it appears too

beautiful for a Man ^ which 1 ftill thought Womanilh indeed-' what, you

have not deceivM me too, my little Volunteer ?

Oliv. Me (he has, I'm fure. [^^Jide.

Man. Speak.

Enter EWti^ <««^Lettice.

Eliz. What, Coufin, I am brought hither by your Woman, I fuppofe, to
be a witnefs of the fecond vindication of your Honour ?

Oliv. infulting is not generous : You might fpare me, I have you.

EUz.. Have a care, Coufin, you'll confcfs anon too much ; and 1 wou'd not
have your fecrets.

Man. Come, your blufhes anfwer me fuiSciedtly, and you have been my
Volunteer in love. • [To Fidelia.

fid. I mufl; confefs, I needed rocompulfion to follow you all ihe World
over^ which I attempted in this habit, partly out of (hame to^own my love
to you, and fear of a greater fhatne, your refufal of it: for I knew of your
engagement to this Lady, and che conftancy of your nature*, which nothing
cou'd have altered, but her felf.

Man. Dear Madam, I defir'd you to bring me out of confulion, and you
have given me more : I know not what to fpeak to you, or how to look upon
you ', the fenfe of my rough, hard, and ^ ufage of you^ (tho' chiefly your
own fault) gives me more pain now 'tis over, than you had, when you fuf-
fer'd it : and if my hsart, the refufal of fuch a Woman, [Pointing to Olivia J
were not a Sacrifice to prophane your love, and a greater wTong to you than
ever yet I did you ^ I wou'd beg of you to receive it, tho' you us'd it, as
flie has done ^ for iho ii defcrv'd not from her the treatment (he gave it, it
does from you- ,

Fid. Then it has had puni(hment fufficient from her already, and needs no
more from m.e ^ and, I muft confefs, 1 wou'd not be the only caufe of making
you break your lafl: night Oath to me, of never parting with me : if you
do not forget, or repent it.

Man, Then take for ever my heart, and this with it \ [Gi'ves her the O-
binet'^ for 'twas given to you before, and my heart was before your due; 1
only beg leave to difpofe of thefe few— —Here, Madaaj, 1 never yet left m/
Wench unpaid. [Takes fome of the Jewels, and offers them to Olivia; (he

firjkes ^em down .- Plaufible and Novel take ^cm Hp,

Oliv. So it fcems by giving her the Cabinet.

L. Plan/ The Pendanis appertain to your moft faithful humble Servant!

Nov. And this Locktc is mine j my earneft for love, which (he never,
paid : therefore my own again.

IVid. Bywhat Law, Sir, pray? Coufin C>/>Vm, a word : What do they



THE PIAIK-VEALEM:. ^ %

malce a Isiiljre on your Goods and GhaiSels, 'vi & armii I Maks; ^^aar dfeffi^sd^
I fay, and bring your Trover. TU follow the Law for yon.,

OUv. And 1 tny Revenge. lExtu Olir..

Man. to ^^r. But 'tis my Friend;^ myour confeieradba p30^, tbat I woa'd
liave rerurn'd part of your Wife^ portion ^ fdc *tw€re bard to take alii from;
thee^ fiflce thoa haft paid fo dear for\ m fbeiing fuck a Ralieal i yet thy
Wife is a Fortune without a Portion y and thouf mt a maa of chat extraor-
dinary merit in Villany, the World and Fortune es® Efivt i defert thee, tbo*
I do J therefore be not melancholy. Fare you weil-^ Sir.. j[£:«.. Ferniflj doggedly:
- Now, Madam, 1 beg your pardon, {THrning to Fidttb] for lefiening the
Prefent I made you? but my heart can never be k lie n'd : this I coafels
was too'fmall for yoa before^ for you deferve the Indian World'i'and £
wou'd row go thither out of eovetoufnefs for your fake only.

Fid. Your heart. Sir, is a Prefent of thdt value, I can never make any re-
turn to't ifutUng Manly from the Comfany'} but I can give you back fucb s
Prefent as this, which I got by the lofs of my Father, a Gentleman of the
North, of no mean Extradion, whofe only Child I was, therefore left me
in the prefent pofliilion of Two thoufand Pounds a Year j which I left
with multitudes of Pretenders, to follow you. Sir 5 having in feveral pub-
lick places feen yoo, and obferv'd your adions throughly, with admiration
when you were too much in love to take notice of mine, which yet was but
too vifible. The name of my Family is Grey ^ my other Fidelia : the refl
of my Story you (hall know when I have fewer Auditors.

Man, Nay, now. Madam, you have taken from me all power of making
you any complement on my part ; for I was going to tell you, that for your
fake only, I wou'd; quit the unknown plesfure of retirement j and rather
ftay in this ill World of ours ftil!, tho* odious to me, than give you more
frights again at Sea, and make again too great a venture there, in you aioneJ
But if I ihou'd tell you now all ihis, and that yowr virtue (llace greater than
I thought any was in the World) had now rceoncird me to't, my Friend
here wou'd fay, 'tis your Eftate that has made me Friends with the World.

Free. I muft confefs, I Ihou'd ^ for 1 thank moft of out quarrels to the
World, are juft fuch as we have to a handfome Women : only becaufe we
cannot enjoy her, as we wou'd do.

Man. Nay, if thou art a Plain- dealer too, give me thy hand ; for now I'll
fay, 1 am thy Friend iadeSd : And for your fakes, tho' I have been fo lately
deceiv'd in Friends of both Sexes ;

/ will believe there are now in the World
Goodnatm'^d Friends^ who are not Proftitutei^
And handfome Women worthy to be Friends •'
Tet, for my fakCi let no one e\e coffjide
In Tear s^ or Oaths, in Love., or Friend untry^d. l^Exeunt omnefi

FINIS.



EPILOGUE, Spoken by the IFic/ow Blachcre.

TO you the Judges learned in Stage-Laws,
Our Poet now, by me^ fubmits his Caufe-^
For with young Judges, fuch as m^/i of you.
The Men by Women be ft their bufinefs do :
Ancf, truth out is, if you did not fit here.
To keep for us a Term throughout the Tear,
We coud not live byr Tongues : nay, but for you,
Our Chamber-praSlice woud be little too.
And ^tis not only the Stage-praSlifer
Who, by your meeting, gets her living here 5
For, as in hlall of Wcftminfter,
Sleeks emjirefs vents^ amidfl the Courts, her Ware:
So, while we baul, aiid you in Judgment fit.
The Vifor-Mask. f^Hs Linnen too ith' Fit.
many of your Friends, befides us here.
Do live by putting off their fevral Ware,
Here^s daily done thegr^at Affair oth* Nation:
Let Love and us then, nere have Long-vacation.
But hold '^ like other F leaders, I have done
Not my poor Client's bufinefs, but my own.
Spare me a word then, now, for him. Firfl know,.
Squires of the Long Robe, he does humbly /how
He has a ju/i Right in abufing you-^
Becaufe he is a Brother-Templar too :
For at the Bar, you railly 07ie another 5
Nay Fool and Knave, is fwallowd from a Brother:
If not the Poet here, the Templar fpare -^
And maul him, when you catch him at the Bar,
From you, our common modijh Cenfurers,
Tour Favour, not your Judgment, 'tis he fears :
Of all Loves begs you then to Rail, find fault:
For Plays, like Women, by the World are thought
(When you fpeak kindly_qf ^jn) very naught.







hiy^,



It
